<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1365011-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1365011" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="29400518" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20031126"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1365011-A1" status="new" fvid="23919116"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1365011</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20031126</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03010567-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03010567</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030512</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-15244502-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>15244502</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020521</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/14        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/37        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/75        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/75        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/83        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/83        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/88        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/90        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/94        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/20        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/37        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/37        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  17/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  17/08        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   1/37</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   1/83</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   1/94</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/20C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M11D1:14B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M11D1:14D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M11D1:75</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M11D1:90</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Flüssige Handgeschirreinigungsmittel</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Liquid hand diswashing detergent</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition détergente liquide pour laver la vaisselle à la main</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-3963649-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3963649</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4797231-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4797231</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5955411-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5955411</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6251844-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6251844</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6268330-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6268330</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6444636-B1"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6444636</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CLARIANT INT LTD</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CLARIANT INTERNATIONAL LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CLARIANT INTERNATIONAL LTD.</last-name><address><street>Rothausstrasse 61</street><city>4132 Muttenz</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MANSKE SCOTT</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MANSKE, SCOTT</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MANSKE, SCOTT</last-name><address><street>2401 Grey Road</street><city>Davidson, NC 28036</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Paczkowski, Marcus, Dr.</last-name><address><street>Clariant Service GmbH Patente, Marken, Lizenzen Am Unisys-Park 1</street><city>65843 Sulzbach</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook> </agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country> <country>BG</country> <country>CH</country> <country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The invention relates to a class of detergent compositions for use in hand
dishwashing that provides excellent performance as measured by persistence of
foam in the presence of oily and fatty types of soils. Testing based on escalating
amounts of such soils to the extinction of the foam showed surprising advantage of
hand dishwashing composition comprising at least two anionic surfactants and a
polyethylene glycol and being essentially free of alkyl polyglucosides.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>FIELD OF INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a liquid detergent formulation for the hand washing
of dishes. More particularly, the present invention relates to a detergent formulation
for the hand washing of dishes where the persistence of foam in the presence of oily,
fatty types of soils is critical to the performance of the detergent.</p><heading>BACKGROUND OF INVENTION</heading><p num="0002">Liquid hand dishwashing detergent or alternatively referred to as light-duty liquid
detergent (LDL) formulations for the cleaning of kitchen surfaces are well known.
Kitchen surfaces include counter tops, stove tops, dishes and any other hard surface
commonly found in kitchen environments. The term "dishes" includes any utensils
involved in food preparation or consumption. Kitchen surfaces, particularly dishes,
must be washed free of food residues, greases, proteins, starches, gums, dyes, oils
and burnt organic residues. As the term "hand dishwashing" implies, the products
typically come into contact with both these hard surfaces to be cleaned and the skin
of the person using the product.</p><p num="0003">Most of the consumer accepted formulations for cleaning dishes with hand
dishwashing detergents include anionic surfactants as the primary cleaning
ingredients and mildness enhancing, foam stabilizing surfactants such as amine
oxides, betaines, and alkanolamides as the secondary surfactants. A significant
number of formulations will also include conventional nonionic surfactants (e.g.
alcohol ethoxylate, alkyl phenol ethoxylate) and/or specialty nonionic surfactants (i.e.
alkyl polyglucoside) to provide the benefits of a mixed active system.</p><p num="0004">The anionic surfactants in such formulations generally provide the typical high
foaming characteristics associated with dishwashing formulations. The foam
stabilizing surfactants typically provide the formulation with enhanced product 
mildness to contacted skin during hand dishwashing and enhanced performance
robustness to higher water hardness and to removed soil. This enhanced product
performance robustness is typically shown by high levels of foam over a wide range
of water hardness levels combined with extended foam persistence during the
washing process as more and more soils are deterged into the wash solution.</p><p num="0005">Foam persistence in the presence of increasing amounts of removed soils
throughout the washing session is arguably the most important cleaning efficacy
signal relied on by consumers. The hand dishwashing detergent industry uses the
laboratory Miniplate Test as the key laboratory appraisal method for assessing this
most important performance criterion and to quantify the performance quality of
liquid hand dishwashing detergent formulations.</p><p num="0006">US Patent 5,968,890 B1 discloses a liquid detergent composition for cleansing the
skin and hair and comprising a synthetic anionic surfactant, and an amphoteric
surfactant and a polyethylene glycol for improved lather.</p><p num="0007">US Patent 6,268,330 B1 discloses an acidic light duty liquid detergent which is mild
to the skin which can be in the form of a clear microemulsion and comprises a
sulfate and a sulfonate anionic surfactant and a hydroxy aliphatic acid.</p><p num="0008">US Patent 6,251,844 B1 discloses an acidic light duty detergent with desirable high
foaming and cleaning properties which kills bacteria and is mild to the skin. The light
duty liquid detergent comprises an anionic surfactant, zwitterionic surfactant,
polyethylene glycol, and a hydroxy acid. The anionic surfactant is present from
10-52 wt-% as a mixture of an alkali metal salt of an anionic sulfonate surfactant and
an alkali metal salt of a C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> ethoxylated alkyl ether sulfate or C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> alkyl ether
sulfate having a weight ratio of sulfonate surfactant to sulfate surfactant of 20 to 1:1.
The zwitterionic surfactant is a water soluble betaine. The light duty liquid detergent
further requires a magnesium salt as an essential ingredient to improve overall
product performance.</p><p num="0009">US Patent No. 6,339,057 B1 discloses a high foaming detergent formulation having
a non-ionic base. The reference points out a problem of incompatibility between 
anionic surfactants and cationic quaternary antimicrobial and the problem that non-ionic
surfactants do not normally provide significant foaming capability to liquid
formulations.</p><p num="0010">US Patent No. 5,955,411 discloses a high foaming light duty liquid detergent having
antibacterial properties containing alkyl polyglucoside and polyethylene glycol in
order to improve the viscosity of the detergent composition and to improve the flash
foam point of the composition.</p><p num="0011">US Patent Numbers 5,696,073 B1, 5,700,773 B1, 5,834,417 B1, 5,853,743 B1,
5,854,195 B1, and 5,856,293 B1 disclose a series of light duty liquid cleaning
compositions comprising anionic surfactants, specialty co-surfactants, polyethylene
glycol, inorganic salts, hydrotroping agents, and an alkyl polyglucoside surfactant,
wherein the alkyl polyglucoside is incorporated to provide mildness to human skin.</p><p num="0012">US Patent No. 5,998,355 B1 discloses a liquid dishwashing detergent that exhibits
increased viscosity, better dissolution rate, and improved cleaning performance in
hard water. The liquid dishwashing detergent comprises from about 1 to 90 percent
of an anionic surfactant and from about 1 to 30 percent of a solvent hydrotrope
selected from the group consisting of alkoxylated glycerides, alkoxylated glycerines,
esters of alkoxylated glycerines, alkoxylated fatty acids, esters of glycerine,
polyglycerol esters and combinations thereof.</p><p num="0013">It is an objective of the present invention to provide a light duty liquid detergent which
provides improved detergency in hard water and in the presence of oily and fatty
types of soils.</p><p num="0014">It is an objective to produce a light duty liquid detergent which exhibits foam
persistence in the presence of oily and fatty types of soils.</p><p num="0015">It is an objective of the present invention to provide an improved light duty liquid
detergent at a lower cost by eliminating exotic materials such as alkyl polyglucoside
(APG) surfactants. </p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0016">The invention relates to a class of compositions for use in light duty liquid, or liquid
hand dishwashing detergents which provide excellent performance as measured by
persistence of foam in the presence of oily and fatty types of soils. Testing of product
performance - based on the stability of foam in the presence of escalating amounts
of fatty or oily soils as indicated by the extinction of the foam - showed surprising
advantage of the hand dishwashing detergent composition which is essentially free
of alkyl polyglucoside , wherein the hand dishwashing detergent comprises at least
two different anionic surfactants and a polyethylene glycol.</p><p num="0017">In one embodiment, the present invention is a liquid dishwashing detergent
composition which comprises water, an anionic surfactant mixture containing at least
two different anionic surfactants, a polyethylene glycol, and a hydrotrope and/or an
inorganic magnesium salt, wherein the liquid dishwashing detergent is essentially
free of alkyl polyglucoside (APG) surfactants. The formulation includes a phase
stabilizer selected from the group consisting of a hydrotrope, an inorganic salt, and
mixtures thereof. The polyethylene glycol employed in the dishwashing detergent
formulation of the present invention comprises from 0.5 to 10 weight percent of the
dishwashing detergent and has a molecular weight ranging from 400 to 1000.</p><p num="0018">In another embodiment, the liquid dishwashing detergent consists essentially of:
water;
<sl><li>5 to 30% by weight of an anionic surfactant;</li><li>5 to 30% by weight of a co-anionic surfactant;</li><li>0.5 to 10% by weight of polyethylene glycol;</li><li>0 to 15% by weight of a foam stabilizing surfactant; and,</li><li>0 to 15% by weight of optional ingredients;</li></sl>
wherein the polyethylene glycol has a molecular weight ranging from about 400 to
1000, with the proviso that the liquid dishwashing detergent be essentially free of
alkyl polyglucosides. The optional ingredients are selected from the group consisting
of hydrotropes, perfumes, colorants, pH adjusting agents, opacifiers, biocidal agents,
preservatives, inorganic salts, viscosity modifiers, and mixtures thereof. </p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0019">Applicant discovered that the combination of at least two different anionic
surfactants, a foam stabilizing surfactant, and polyethylene glycol resulted in
surprisingly improved detergency performance, as measured by the well-known mini-plate
test in water of varying hardness, than would have been predicted by just the
addition of polyethylene glycol to liquid anionic dish washing detergent formulations
with a single anionic surfactant either with or without a foam stabilizing surfactant.
The instant invention is characterized in that the formulation of the present invention
contains essentially no alkyl polyglucosides. By the term essentially no alkyl
polyglucosides, it is meant that the dishwashing detergent contains less than 0.005
weight percent alkyl polyglucosides. By the term alkyl polyglucosides as used herein,
alkyl polyglucosides or alkyl polyglucoside surfactants include alkyl polysaccharides,
alkyl monosaccharides and admixtures thereof. Examples include: C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>17</sub> acyl-N-(C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub>-alkyl)
and -N-(C<sub>1</sub> C<sub>2</sub> hydroxyalkyl)glucamine sulfates, and sulfates of alkyl
polysaccharides, such as sulfates of alkyl polyglucoside. The characterization of
alkyl polyglucosides as disclosed in US Patents: 5,834,417 B1, 5,853,743 B1, and
5,854,195 B1.</p><heading>Anionic surfactants</heading><p num="0020">Anionic sulfonate surfactants suitable for use herein include the salts of C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> linear
alkylbenzene sulfonates, alkyl ester sulfonates, C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>22</sub> primary or secondary alkane
sulfonates, C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>24</sub> olefin sulfonates, sulfonated polycarboxylic acids, alkyl glycerol
sulfonates, fatty acyl glycerol sulfonates, fatty oleyl glycerol sulfonates, and any
mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0021">Anionic sulfate surfactants suitable for use in the compositions of the invention
include linear and branched primary and secondary alkyl sulfates, alkyl
ethoxysulfates, fatty oleoyl glycerol sulfates, and alkyl phenol ethylene oxide ether
sulfates.</p><p num="0022">Suitable anionic carboxylate surfactants include alkyl ethoxy carboxylates, alkyl
polyethoxy polycarboxylate surfactants and soaps ("alkyl carboxyls"). </p><p num="0023">An example of a preferred anionic surfactant would be the sodium salt of secondary
alkane sulfonate commercially available under the tradename of Hostapur® SAS
(Clariant Corporation, Charlotte, North Carolina).</p><heading>Polyethylene glycol</heading><p num="0024">It was discovered that the molecular weight of the polyethylene glycol had a
significant impact on the detergent performance. Polyethylene glycols having a
molecular weight ranging between 400 and 1000 provided the greatest benefit. The
polyethylene glycol used in the instant composition has a molecular weight of 200 to
1,500, wherein the polyethylene glycol has the structure
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">HO(CH2 CH2 O) <sub>n</sub> ―H</st32:che>
wherein n is 4 to 25. The concentration of the polyethylene glycol in the instant
composition is 0.5 to 10 wt. %, more preferably 0.75 wt. % to 6 wt. %. Preferably, the
molecular weight of the polyethylene glycol ranges from 400 to 1500, more
preferably, the molecular weight of the polyethylene glycol ranges between 400 and
1000, and most preferably, the molecular weight of the polyethylene glycol ranges
between 400 and 800.</p><heading>Water</heading><p num="0025">The final ingredient in the inventive compositions is water. The proportion of water in
the compositions generally is in the range of 35% to 85%, preferably 50% to 80% by
weight of the usual composition.</p><heading>Amine Oxide</heading><p num="0026">Amine oxides useful in the present invention include long-chain alkyl amine oxides,
ie., those compounds having the formula
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sup>3</sup>(OR<sup>4</sup>)<sub>x</sub>-(NO)-(R<sup>5</sup>)<sub>2</sub></st32:che>
wherein R<sup>3</sup> is selected from an alkyl, hydroxyalkyl, acylamidopropyl and alkyl phenyl
group, or mixtures thereof, containing from 8 to 26 carbon atoms, preferably 8 to 16
carbon atoms; R<sup>4</sup> is an alkylene or hydroxyalkylene group containing from 2 to 3 
carbon atoms, preferably 2 carbon atoms, or mixtures thereof; x is from 0 to 3,
preferably 0; and each R<sup>5</sup> is an alkyl or hydroxyalkyl group containing from 1 to 3,
preferably from 1 to 2 carbon atoms, or a polyethylene oxide group containing from 1
to 3, preferably 1, ethylene oxide groups. The R<sup>5</sup> groups can be attached to each
other, e.g., through an oxygen or nitrogen atom, to form a ring structure.</p><p num="0027">These amine oxide surfactants in particular include C<sub>10</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> alkyl dimethyl amine
oxides and C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>12</sub> alkoxy ethyl dihydroxyethyl amine oxides and alkyl amido propyl
amine oxide. Examples of such materials include dimethyloctylamine oxide,
diethyldecylamine oxide, bis-(2-hydroxyethyl)dodecylamine oxide,
dimethyldodecylamine oxide, dodecylamidopropyl dimethylamine oxide and
dimethyl-2-hydroxyoctadecylamine oxide. Preferred are C<sub>10</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> alkyl dimethylamine
oxide, and C<sub>10</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> acylamido alkyl dimethylamine oxide.</p><heading>Betaine</heading><p num="0028">The betaines useful in the present invention are those compounds having the
formula R(R<sup>1</sup>)<sub>2</sub> N<sup>+</sup> R<sup>2</sup> COO<sup>-</sup> wherein R is a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> hydrocarbyl group, preferably C<sub>10</sub>-C<sub>16</sub>
alkyl group, each R<sup>1</sup> is typically C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>3</sub>, alkyl, preferably methyl, and R<sup>2</sup> is a C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>5</sub>
hydrocarbyl group, preferably a C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>5</sub> alkylene group, more preferably a C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>2</sub>
alkylene group. Examples of suitable betaines include coconut
acylamidopropyldimethyl betaine; hexadecyl dimethyl betaine; C<sub>12</sub>-C<sub>14</sub>
acylamidopropylbetaine; C<sub>12</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> acylamidohexyldiethyl betaine; 4-[C<sub>14</sub>-C<sub>16</sub>
acylmethylamidodiethylammonio]-1-carboxybutane; C<sub>16</sub>-C<sub>18</sub>
acylamidodimethylbetaine; C<sub>12</sub>-C<sub>16</sub> acylamidopentanediethyl-betaine; C<sub>12</sub>-C<sub>16</sub>
acylmethyl-amidodimethylbetaine, and coco amidopropyl betaine. Preferred betaines
are C<sub>12</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> dimethylamoniohexanoate and the C<sub>10</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> acylamidopropane (or
ethane) dimethyl (or diethyl) betaines. Also included are sulfobetaines (sultaines) of
formula R(R<sub>1</sub>)<sub>2</sub> N+R<sub>2</sub> SO<sub>3</sub>-, wherein R is a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> Hydrocarbyl group, preferably a
C<sub>10</sub>-C<sub>16</sub> alkyl group, more preferably a C<sub>12</sub>-C<sub>13</sub> alkyl group; each R<sub>1</sub> is typically C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>3</sub>
alkyl, preferably methyl and R<sub>2</sub> is a C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> hydrocarbyl group, preferably a C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>3</sub>
alkylene or, preferably, hydroxyalkylene group. Examples of suitable sultaines are
C<sub>12</sub>-C<sub>14</sub> dihydroxyethylammonio propane sulfonate, and C.sub.<sub>16</sub> -C.sub.<sub>18</sub> 
dimethylammonio hexane sulfonate, with C<sub>12</sub>-C<sub>14</sub> amido propyl ammonio-2-hydroxypropyl
sultaine being preferred.</p><heading>Alkanolamide compounds</heading><p num="0029">The present formulation can include an alkanolamide compound such as an alkyl
monoalkanol amide, an alkyl dialkanol amide, and mixtures thereof.</p><heading>Hydrotrope</heading><p num="0030">The formulation of the present invention can include a hydrotrope selected from the
group consisting of ethanol, isopropanol, sodium xylene sulfonate, propylene glycol,
dipropylene glycol, sodium cumene sulfonate and mixtures thereof.</p><heading>Inorganic Salt</heading><p num="0031">The formulation of the present invention can include an inorganic or organic salt or
oxide of a multivalent cation, particularly Mg<sup>++</sup> which has phase stabilization
properties. The multivalent cation salt or oxide provides several benefits including
improved cleaning performance in dilute usage, particularly in soft water areas, and
minimized amounts of perfume required to obtain the microemulsion state.
Magnesium sulfate, either anhydrous or hydrated (e.g., heptahydrate), is especially
preferred as the magnesium salt. Good results also have been reported with
magnesium oxide, magnesium chloride, magnesium acetate, magnesium propionate
and magnesium hydroxide. These magnesium salts can be used with formulations at
neutral or acidic pH since magnesium hydroxide will not precipitate at these pH
levels.</p><p num="0032">Although magnesium is the preferred multivalent cation from which the salts
(inclusive of the oxide and hydroxide) are formed, other polyvalent metal ions also
can be used provided that their salts are nontoxic and are soluble in the aqueous
phase of the system at the desired pH level.</p><p num="0033">The liquid cleaning composition of this invention may, if desired, also contain other
optional components either to provide additional effect or to make the product more
attractive to the consumer. The following are mentioned by way of example:
Colorants or dyes in amounts up to 0.5% by weight; preservatives or antioxidizing 
agents, such as formalin, 5-bromo-5-nitro-dioxan-1,3; 5-chloro-2-methyl-4-isothaliazolin-3-one,
2,6-di-tert.butyl-p-cresol, etc., in amounts up to 2% by weight;
and pH adjusting agents, such as sulfuric acid or sodium hydroxide, as needed.
Furthermore, if opaque compositions are desired, up to 4% by weight of an opacifier
may be added. Preferably, the optional ingredients are selected from the group
consisting of hydrotropes, perfumes, colorants, pH adjusting agents, preservatives,
biocidal agents, inorganic salts, opacifiers, viscosity modifiers, and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0034">In the present formulation, it was discovered that certain parameters were required
to achieve the benefits of the invention. The total surfactant level in the detergent
formulation includes all surfactants in the detergent for example, the anionics, any
non-ionic and any amphoteric surfactants. The polyethylene glycol (PEG) is not
considered a surfactant. Preferably, the hand dishwashing composition will comprise
from 15 to 60 weight percent total surfactant, more preferably the hand dishwashing
detergent comprises from 20 to 50 weight percent total surfactant, and most
preferably, the hand dishwashing detergent comprises from 20 to 40 weight percent
total surfactant. More particularly, the ratio of the first anionic surfactant to the
second anionic surfactant comprises between 0.5 and less than 1.0. The ratio of the
foam stabilizing surfactant to the anionic surfactant mixture should comprise 1:2 or
less.</p><p num="0035">In the instant invention, detergent formulations were sought which comprised anionic
surfactants that provide persistence of foam in the presence of oily and fatty types of
soils. Testing of product performance - based on the stability of foam in the presence
of escalating amounts of fatty or oily soils as indicated by the extinction of the foam -
showed surprising advantage of liquid hand dishwashing detergent compositions
comprising at least two different anionic surfactants and a polyethylene glycol. In one
set of experiments, dishwashing detergent formulations having between 38 and 42
weight percent anionic surfactants comprising both a secondary alkane sulfonate
and an alkyl ether sulfate in approximately equal proportions, and a foam stabilizing
surfactant such as amine oxide or coco amidopropyl betaine were tested with
polyethylene glycols of increasing molecular weight. It was found that the addition of
polyethylene glycols having a molecular weight ranging between 400 to 800
exhibited significant improvement in performance as measured by the well-known 
Mini Plate test in water having a hardness of 150 ppm. At the 150 ppm level of
hardness, the performance of formulations with polyethylene glycol having a
molecular weight ranging from 400 to 800, improved between 20 and 40 percent
over formulations having no polyethylene glycol or having similar concentrations of
polyethylene glycol with a molecular weight greater than 800. At hardness levels of
300 ppm, adding polyethylene glycol resulted in a similar relative benefit over the
400 to 800 polyethylene glycol molecular weight range, but at a relatively reduced
level.</p><p num="0036">The unexpected resilient foaming properties of the formulations of the invention - as
measured by the Mini-plate test - are illustrated in the following examples. It was also
determined that flash foam production was not a reliable predictor of the Mini-plate
detergent performance.</p><p num="0037">Foam production, often called flash foaming, of the formulations in the following
examples was measured by methods well-known in the detergent art. A 100 ml
sample of each formulation at the indicated dilution level was placed in a 500 ml
graduated cylinder at ambient conditions including a room temperature of 25°C.
Samples were uniformly shaken and the resulting foam was measured according to
the volume of the foam which appeared above the 100 ml level in the graduated
cylinder.</p><p num="0038">The detergency performance effectiveness of each formulation was measured by the
well-known "Miniplate" method wherein a series of soiled miniature plates (hard
surface) are washed in a serial fashion with a brush in solutions of the hand
dishwashing samples under standard conditions until the distinguishable and
reproducible disappearance of the foam is reached. The standard conditions
included a room temperature of 25°C. The number of mini-plates washed is
compared to a commercial standard. The miniplates are soiled with a partially
hydrogenated vegetable oil, available from Procter and Gamble Coompany under
the trade name, Crisco, which was dyed red. </p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0039">The following examples illustrate liquid cleaning compositions of the described
invention. Unless otherwise specified, all percentages are by weight. The exemplified
compositions are illustrative only and do not limit the scope of the invention. Unless
otherwise specified, the proportions in the examples and elsewhere in the
specification are by weight.</p><heading>EXAMPLE I</heading><p num="0040">Formulations comprising at least two anionic surfactants were prepared and
detergency performance - as measured by the number of mini-plates washed - was
evaluated. In formulations A-F, a first anionic surfactant comprised a secondary
sodium alkane sulfonate and the co-anionic surfactant comprised an alkyl ether
sulfate. All of these blends contained 37.5 weight percent total surfactant and
contained a ratio of sulfonate to sulfate of 0.875. Formulations A-F included coco
amidopropyl betaine as a foam stabilizing surfactant, and ethanol as a hydrotrope as
shown in Table 1. Formulation B-F comprised polyethylene glycol (PEG)
components at a level of 3.8 wt-% (10 percent of total surfactant) over a molecular
weight range from 400 to 1500. Foam production as measured in a rotating cylinder
test in water hardness of 150 ppm showed improvement over the base formulation A
for the addition of polyethylene glycol over the full range of molecular weight.
However, the foam production in water having a hardness of 300 ppm indicated little
or no improvement over the molecular weight range of polyethylene glycol addition in
formulations B-F. As shown in Table 1, and according to the well-known mini-plate
test, the observed number of mini-plates washed in water having a hardness of
either 150 ppm or 300 ppm, all of the formulations which included polyethylene
glycol or PEG (See columns B-F) exhibited significantly increased detergency
performance in the presence of oily soil. The most significant increase in Miniplate
washing performance occurred in formulation C, when the molecular weight of the
polyethylene glycol was 600. This enhanced performance extended above a 600
molecular weight up to 1000 molecular weight, and then dropped off as the
molecular weight of the polyethylene glycol approached 1500. The enhanced
detergency performance also extended below the molecular weight value of 600 to
400. The detergency performance of the formulations of the present invention is
shown in comparison to the performance of a base blend A, which contains no PEG. </p><p num="0041">This trend in detergency performance with PEG addition as measured by foam
persistence was indicated by foam generation results in 150 ppm hardness water but
was not indicated by the foam production results in water with the hardness of
300 ppm.</p><heading>EXAMPLE II</heading><p num="0042">Formulation G represented a formulation that included at least two anionic
surfactants, coco amidopropyl betaine and ethanol (hydrotrope). The ratio of the
three surfactants - the two anionic surfactants and the foam stabilizing surfactant -
was maintained at the level of systems A-F while the total surfactant was increased
by 3.8 percent corresponding to the level of PEG added in systems B-F. This case
can be compared with cases B-E and clearly shows that without the PEG (400-1000
MW) component, increasing the amount of total surfactant does not achieve the
benefits of the blends containing PEG and actually reduced the detergency
performance at 150 ppm water compared to the base blend, in case A, even though
the foam forming tests indicated that there was a foam production benefit.</p><heading>EXAMPLE III</heading><p num="0043">Formulations H-J, E represented a series of formulations wherein at least two
anionic surfactants, coco amidopropyl betaine, ethanol (hydrotrope) and the content
of 600 molecular weight PEG is increased from 0.5 to 3.8 weight percent. This
series (H-J, E) can be compared with case A, which contains no PEG, and clearly
showed that the addition of 0.5 percent of PEG provides an increase in detergency
performance (Mini-plate) at the higher water hardness while at higher PEG levels (1
to 3.8 percent) there is a more substantial increase in detergency performance
shown by the Mini-plate tests- especially in the water with the greater amount of
hardness - compared to the base blend, A. Conversely, no benefits are indicated in
the foam production at the hardness of 300 ppm, and the foam production at the 150
ppm level showed a reduction in benefit with increasing addition of PEG of a 600
molecular weight.</p><heading>Example IV</heading><p num="0044">Another series of formulations (K-M) shown in Table 2 was developed wherein the
formulations included a first anionic surfactant, secondary sodium alkane sulfonate 
and a second or co-anionic surfactant, alkyl ether sulfate, with increasing amounts of
PEG. These systems did not include any additional surfactant. Formulation K
represents a revised base level without PEG and with the alkane sulfonate and
alcohol ether sulfate surfactants. From formulation K as the new base blend,
increasing amounts of a nominally 600 molecular weight PEG were added at a level
of 3.8 wt-% in formulation L and at a level of 5.0 in formulation M, with the surprising
result that the detergency performance shown by the Mini-plate test at low hardness
improved only slightly, while the detergency performance at the higher hardness
value of 300 ppm, increased significantly over the blend K containing no PEG. The
corresponding foam production tests showed no improvement for the PEG addition
in formulations L and M.</p><heading>EXAMPLE V</heading><p num="0045">Formulations N-O shown in Table 2 represented a series of comparative
formulations wherein only one anionic surfactant, alkyl ether sulfate, was employed
with ethanol, and coco amidopropyl betaine,. Formulation O represented the same
formula as N but contained 3.8 wt-% of 600 molecular weight PEG. In this series
(N-O), formulation N (no PEG) can be compared with formulation O (3.8 percent
PEG) and clearly showed that the addition of PEG at a level of 3.8 wt-% resulted in a
reduction in Mini-plate detergency performance when only a single anionic surfactant
was present. The foam production in formulation O results were mixed with the foam
production for the 150 ppm water hardness improving slightly, while the foam
production for the 300 ppm hardness decreased relative to formulation N.</p><heading>EXAMPLE VI</heading><p num="0046">Formulations P-Q and R-S shown in Table 2 represented a series of comparative
formulations wherein the total amount of surfactant was reduced to 10 weight
percent and 20 weight percent, respectively. Formulations P-Q showed that there
was no apparent advantage of adding 3.8 percent PEG to a formulation having only
10 percent total surfactant, even though the ratio of the three surfactants was the
same as case A. Foam production in formulations P and Q showed little advantage
of the PEG addition at this level of total surfactant. Formulations R-S showed that
there was a significant advantage in Mini-plate detergency performance when the
total surfactant amount was 20 weight percent in water having a hardness of 
150 ppm, while the increase in detergency performance at a hardness of 300 ppm
was only slight. Foam production in formulation R was only slightly improved over
formulation S.</p><heading>EXAMPLE VII</heading><p num="0047">Formulations T-V shown in Table 3 represented a series of comparative formulations
wherein the two anionic surfactants included secondary sodium alkane sulfonate and
alpha olefin sulfonate together with amine oxide and magnesium sulfate. PEG is
present in formulation U at 2 wt-% and in formulation V at 3 wt-%. There is no
alcohol included. In this series (T-V), the total amount of surfactant was 42 wt-%.
Both formulations U and V showed significant detergency performance improvement
over formulation T, demonstrating the unexpected performance benefit provided by
the addition of PEG to a two anionic surfactant system. Conversely, the foam
production results showed a decreased foam production for increasing PEG addition
relative to formulation T, although there was a slight improvement in foam production
in formulation V relative to formulation T, at the 300 ppm water hardness level.</p><heading>EXAMPLE VIII</heading><p num="0048">Formulations W-Z shown in Table 3 represented a series of comparative
formulations wherein only one anionic surfactant, secondary sodium alkane
sulfonate, is present together with the foam stabilizing surfactant amine oxide at a
total surfactant level of 42 wt-%. PEG is present in cases X-Z in increasing amounts
of 2, 3.8 and 5.0 wt-%. in cases X, Y and Z, respectively. In cases X-Z, detergency
performance decreased with increasing PEG in the formulation. Foam production
results did not show any significant benefit for the PEG addition. This once again
demonstrated the need for at least two anionic surfactants to achieve the
performance enhancement unexpectedly provided by the PEG.</p><heading>EXAMPLE IX</heading><p num="0049">Formulations AA-CC shown in Table 3 represented a series of comparative
formulations which are similar to formulations A, J, and C wherein the inorganic salt,
magnesium sulfate, is present at a level of 2 wt-% and ethanol is absent. PEG is
present in cases BB- and CC in increasing amounts of 2, 3.8 wt-%, in cases BB and
CC, respectively. In cases BB and CC, detergency performance showed an 
advantage with increasing PEG in the formulations. Foam production in formulations
BB and CC showed significant improvement relative to formulation AA. <img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="133" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/><img id="img-00170001" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00170001.tif" inline="no" he="229"/><img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="116" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="228"/></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A dishwashing detergent composition comprising an anionic surfactant
mixture containing at least two different anionic surfactants, a polyethylene glycol,
water, and a phase stabilizer selected from the group consisting of a hydrotrope, an
inorganic salt, and mixtures thereof, wherein said dishwashing detergent
composition is essentially free of alkyl polyglucoside surfactants and the
polyethylene glycol having a molecular weight ranging from 400 to 1000 comprises
from 0.5 to 10 weight percent of the dishwashing detergent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A liquid dishwashing detergent consisting essentially of:
water;
<claim-text><claim-text>5 to 30% by weight of an anionic surfactant;</claim-text><claim-text>5 to 30% by weight of a co-anionic surfactant;</claim-text><claim-text>0.5 to 10% by weight of polyethylene glycol;</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 15% by weight of a foam stabilizing surfactant; and,</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 15% by weight of optional ingredients;</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein the polyethylene glycol has a molecular weight ranging from 400 to 1000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method for the hand washing of a kitchen surface, comprising contacting
the kitchen surface with a detergent consisting essentially of:
water;
<claim-text><claim-text>5 to 30% by weight of an anionic surfactant;</claim-text><claim-text>5 to 30% by weight of a co-anionic surfactant;</claim-text><claim-text>0.5 to 10% by weight of polyethylene glycol;</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 15% by weight of a foam stabilizing surfactant; and,</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 15% by weight of optional ingredients;</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein the polyethylene glycol has a molecular weight ranging from 400 to 1000.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>