<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1028130-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1028130" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22930464" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000816"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1028130-A1" status="new" fvid="22904305"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1028130</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000816</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00101855-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00101855</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000131</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-24639199-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>24639199</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990209</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C   1/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C   1/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 232/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 232/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 236/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 236/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L   7/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L   7/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L   9/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L   9/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  21/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  21/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F 232/08</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F 236/20</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  21/00+B2A</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Dicyclopentadien/Limonen Polymerharz</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Polymeric dicyclopentadiene/limonene resin</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Résine polymère dicyclopentadiène/limonène</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0249904-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0249904</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4577006-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4577006</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5691432-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5691432</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 198709 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A26, AN 1987-062070 XP002136270 &amp; JP 62 018407 A (YASUHARA YUSHI KOGY), 27 January 1987 (1987-01-27)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199841 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A18, AN 1998-476848 XP002136271 &amp; JP 10 204216 A (YOKOHAMA RUBBER CO LTD), 4 August 1998 (1998-08-04)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GOODYEAR TIRE &amp; RUBBER</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>THE GOODYEAR TIRE &amp; RUBBER COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>THE GOODYEAR TIRE &amp;amp; RUBBER COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1144 East Market Street</street><city>Akron, Ohio 44316-0001</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KEITH DENISE JEANNETTE</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SEGATTA THOMAS JOSEPH</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>WIDEMAN LAWSON GIBSON</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KEITH, DENISE JEANNETTE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SEGATTA, THOMAS JOSEPH</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WIDEMAN, LAWSON GIBSON</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KEITH, DENISE JEANNETTE</last-name><address><street>1342 Krumroy</street><city>Akron, Ohio 44306</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SEGATTA, THOMAS JOSEPH</last-name><address><street>4523 Swan Lake Drive</street><city>Copley, Ohio 44321</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WIDEMAN, LAWSON GIBSON</last-name><address><street>1004 Westhaven Drive</street><city>Hudson, Ohio 44236</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Leitz, Paul</last-name><address><street>Goodyear Technical Center-Luxembourg Patent-Department</street><city>L-7750 Colmar-Berg</city><country>LU</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>This invention relates to a novel class of polymeric
resins which have a softening point ranging from 50°C to
220°C and a molecular weight ranging from 500 to 42,000
g/mol. The resins consist essentially of the polymers
which result from the polymerization reaction between
dicyclopentadiene and limonene. The polymeric resins are
particularly useful in improving traction of the rubber
when used in tire treads.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">Background of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to a polymeric resin which is
the reaction product of the polymerization reaction between
dicyclopentadiene and limonene. Use of the polymeric
resins of the present invention in a rubber tire stock
improves the traction and handling of the tire.</p><heading><u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0002">The present invention relates to a polymeric
dicyclopentadiene/limonene resin. The polymeric resins of
the present invention have softening points ranging from
50°C to 220°C, and a molecular weight of from 500 to
42,000. The present invention also includes a blend of
dicyclopentadiene/limonene resins and rubber stocks
containing the dicyclopentadiene/limonene resin.</p><heading><u style="single">Detailed Description of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0003">The present invention relates to a polymeric resin
consisting essentially of the reaction product of the
polymerization reaction between dicyclopentadiene and
limonene and having a softening point ranging from 50°C to
220°C and a molecular weight ranging from 500 to 42,000.</p><p num="0004">In addition, the present invention relates to a resin
composition comprising a blend of two or more polymeric
resins wherein each resin consists essentially of the
reaction product of the polymerization reaction between
dicyclopentadiene and limonene. Alternatively, the blend
can be formed in-situ; that is, the reaction temperature
may be raised during the polymerization to increase the
molecular weight distribution and broaden the softening
point.</p><p num="0005">In addition, there is disclosed a pneumatic tire
having a tread comprised of a rubber stock comprising (1) a
rubber selected from the group consisting of natural
rubber, rubber derived from a diene monomer or mixtures 
thereof, and (2) a polymeric resin composition consisting
essentially of the reaction product of the polymerization
reaction between dicyclopentadiene and limonene; said resin
having a softening point ranging from 50 to 220°C and a
molecular weight ranging from 500 to 42,000.</p><p num="0006">There is also disclosed a rubber stock comprising (1)
a rubber selected from the group consisting of natural
rubber, rubber derived from a diene monomer or mixtures
thereof, and (2) a polymeric resin composition consisting
essentially of the reaction product of the polymerization
reaction between dicyclopentadiene and limonene; said resin
having a softening point ranging from 50 to 220°C and a
molecular weight ranging from 500 to 42,000.</p><p num="0007">The terms "polymeric compound" and "polymer" when used
to describe the resins of the present invention are
intended to only include those molecules which contain a
monomeric unit derived from dicyclopentadiene and limonene
and where at least one of the monomeric units derived from
the dicyclopentadiene or limonene is repeated. Therefore,
the compounds formed by the reaction of a single
dicyclopentadiene molecule and a single limonene are not
polymeric as the term is used herein. The term monomeric
unit means a structure that occurs in a polymeric compound
and which differs from the structure of dicyclopentadiene
or limonene due to changes resulting from molecular
reorientation during the linking to the adjacent structure.
These changes may include addition to a double bond or the
addition or removal of a hydrogen atom from the
dicyclopentadiene or limonene.</p><p num="0008">The molar ratio of the dicyclopentadiene to limonene
in the polymerization reaction may vary, depending on the
desired properties of the final polymeric product. For
example, the molar ratio of the dicyclopentadiene to
limonene as starting material may range from 1:10 to 10:1.
The preferred molar ratio of dicyclopentadiene to limonene
may range from 5:1 to 1:5 as starting material. The most
preferred ratio ranges from 2:1 to 1:2. As to the final 
product, the molar ratio of polymeric units derived from
the dicyclopentadiene to limonene may range from 8:1 to
1:8. The preferred molar ratio of dicyclopentadiene to
limonene in the final product ranges from 1:3 to 3:1 with a
range of from 2.1:1 to 1:2.1, being particularly preferred.</p><p num="0009">The polymerization reaction between the
dicyclopentadiene may be a thermal (no catalyst)
polymerization, or catalyzed, i.e., conducted in the
presence of an acid catalyst. Examples of acid catalysts
that may be used include Bronsted acid and Lewis acid-type
catalysts. Such known acid catalysts include H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, HCl,
H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>; metal halides such as BF<sub>3</sub>, BCl<sub>3</sub>, AlCl<sub>3</sub>, AlBr<sub>3</sub>, SnCl<sub>4</sub>,
ZnCl<sub>2</sub>, SbCl<sub>3</sub> and their etherates. The choice of a
particular catalyst is dependent upon factors including the
melting or boiling points of the reactants, desired rate of
reaction, solvent, and pressure and temperature limitation
of the production equipment, etc. When higher yields are
desired, the metal halides or their etherates may be
utilized. The preferred acid catalysts are BF<sub>3</sub> and AlCl<sub>3</sub>.
The most preferred catalyst is AlCl<sub>3</sub>.</p><p num="0010">In the catalyzed polymerization process, the amount of
catalyst may range from 0.1 to 20 weight percent of
catalyst based on the total weight of reactants to be
polymerized. Preferably, a range of from 3 to 5 weight
percent of catalyst is preferred. The optimum
concentration of catalyst depends on the nature of the
solvent, if any, which effects the solubility of the
catalyst as well as on the stirring efficiency inside the
polymerization reactor. High catalyst concentration
reduces the resin molecular weight distribution and,
therefore, limits the amount of feed additive required for
controlling the resin molecular weight.</p><p num="0011">The polymerization reaction may be carried out neat
(without solvent) at or above the melting points of the
reactants, or can be carried out in the presence of a
solvent. The solvent may be an aliphatic C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>
hydrocarbon, an aromatic or haloaromatic (C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>9</sub>) 
hydrocarbon, or a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>9</sub> aliphatic halohydrocarbon.
Examples of suitable solvents include hexane, heptane,
cyclohexane, benzene, toluene, xylene, and chlorobenzene.
The preferred solvents are hexane and cyclohexane.</p><p num="0012">The polymerization reaction may be conducted under a
variety of operating conditions. The reaction pressure may
vary and range from one atmosphere to 100 atmospheres with
a pressure of from two atmospheres to ten atmospheres being
preferred. The reaction temperature may range from 0 to
100 °C with a preferred range being from 30 to 50°C.</p><p num="0013">Depending on the reactivity of the reactants, amount
of catalyst, reaction pressure and reaction temperature,
the reaction time may vary. Generally speaking, the
reaction time varies from 1 to 8 hours.</p><p num="0014">The molecular weight distribution of the polymeric
resin of the present invention may range from 500 to
42,000. In a particularly preferred embodiment of the
present invention, the resin composition comprises a blend
of two or more individual polymeric resins each one of
which is the reaction product of a polymerization reaction
between dicyclopentadiene and limonene. Each individual
polymeric resin preferably differs from the other by having
a different molecular weight range. Generally speaking,
all of the polymeric resins will exhibit some lower
molecular weight values, however, not all of the individual
resins may include the higher molecular values. In the
alternative, all of the resins may have distributions that
vary by their lower molecular values with the high
molecular weight value relatively being the same. For
example, when the resin blend comprises three individual
polymeric resins, the first resin may have a molecular
weight ranging from 700 to 24,000, the second resin may
have a molecular weight ranging from 700 to 36,000, and the
third resin may have a molecular weight ranging from 700 to
42,000.</p><p num="0015">In accordance to another embodiment of the present
invention, the resin composition may comprise a blend of 
four individual resins. In accordance with this
embodiment, the first resin may have a molecular weight
ranging from 500 to 15,000, the second resin may have a
molecular weight ranging from 700 to 15,000, the third
resin may have a molecular weight ranging from 3,000 to
15,000, and the fourth resin may have a molecular weight
ranging from 4,000 to 15,000.</p><p num="0016">The blend may be formed in-situ or mechanically
blended.</p><p num="0017">The resin composition of the present invention has a
softening point ranging from 50 to 220. For the purposes
of the present invention, the term "softening point" is
used to describe the temperature range from when wetting
occurs in a capillary melting point tube to where the resin
is completely liquid. Representative of suitable equipment
to determine the relative softening point is a Thomas-Hoover
Melting Point apparatus equipped with a silicon oil
bath. In accordance with the embodiment of the present
invention when the resin composition comprises a blend of
three individual resins, the first resin may have a
softening point ranging from 134 to 156°C, the second resin
may have a softening point ranging from 138 to 180°C, and
the third resin may have a softening point ranging from 188
to 208°C. In accordance with the embodiment of the present
invention where the blend comprises four individual resins,
the first resin may have a softening point ranging from 55
to 75°C, the second resin may have a softening point
ranging from 80 to 131°C, the third resin may have a
softening point ranging from 126 to 168°C, and the fourth
resin may have a softening point range of 168 to 195°C.</p><p num="0018">Rubber stocks containing natural rubber or rubbers
derived from a diene monomer may be modified with the resin
compositions of the present invention. Examples of rubbers
derived from a diene monomer include substituted and
unsubstituted, saturated and unsaturated, synthetic
polymers. The natural polymers include natural rubber in
its various forms, e.g., pale crepe and smoked sheet, and 
balata and gutta percha. The synthetic polymers include
those prepared from a single monomer (homopolymer) or a
mixture of two or more copolymerizable monomers (copolymer)
when the monomers are combined in the random distribution
or block form. In addition to the diene monomers, other
monomers may be used. Of all the monomers that may be
used, the monomers may be substituted or unsubstituted and
may possess one or more double bonds, for example, diene
monomers, both conjugated and nonconjugated, and
monoolefins, including cyclic and acyclic monoolefins,
especially vinyl and vinylidene monomers. Examples of
conjugated dienes are 1,3-butadiene, isoprene, chloroprene,
2-ethyl-1,3-butadiene, 2,3-dimethyl-1,3-butadiene and
piperylene. Examples of nonconjugated dienes are 1,4-pentadiene,
1,4-hexadiene, 1,5-hexadiene,
dicyclopentadiene, 1,5-cyclooctadiene and ethylidene
norbornene. Examples of acyclic monoolefins are ethylene,
propylene, 1-butene, isobutylene, 1-pentene and 1-hexene.
Examples of cyclic monoolefins are cyclopentene,
cyclohexene, cycloheptene, cyclooctene and 4-methyl-cyclooctene.
Examples of vinyl monomers are styrene,
acrylonitrile, acrylic acid, ethylacrylate, vinyl chloride,
butylacrylate, methyl vinyl ether, vinyl acetate and vinyl
pyridine. Examples of vinylidene monomers are alpha-methylstyrene,
methacrylic acid, methyl methacrylate,
itaconic acid, ethyl methacrylate, glycidyl methacrylate
and vinylidene chloride. Representative examples of the
synthetic polymers used in the practice of this invention
are polychloroprene, homopolymers of a conjugated 1,3-diene
such as isoprene and butadiene, and in particular,
polyisoprenes and polybutadienes having essentially all of
their repeat units combined in a cis-1,4-structure; and
copolymers of a conjugated 1,3-diene such as isoprene and
butadiene with up to 50 percent by weight of at least one
copolymerizable monomer, including ethylenically
unsaturated monomers such as styrene or acrylonitrile; and
butyl rubber, which is a polymerization product of a major 
proportion of a monoolefin and a minor proportion of a
diolefin such as butadiene or isoprene.</p><p num="0019">The rubber compounds which may be modified by the
resins of the present invention are preferably cis-1,4-polyisoprene
(natural or synthetic), polybutadiene,
polychloroprene and the copolymers of isoprene and
butadiene, copolymers of acrylonitrile and butadiene,
copolymers of acrylonitrile and isoprene, copolymers of
styrene, butadiene and isoprene, copolymers of styrene and
butadiene and blends thereof.</p><p num="0020">The amount of polymeric resins that may be used with
the diene containing polymers may vary and depend on the
polymer to be modified, the particular polymeric resin, the
desired degree of modification and the like. Generally
speaking, the polymeric resin is used in amounts ranging
from 5 to 50 parts per hundred (phr) of diene polymer.
Preferably, the polymeric resin is used in amounts of from
5 to 25 phr, with a range of from 10 to 25 phr being
particularly preferred.</p><p num="0021">The polymeric resins may be incorporated in the diene
containing polymer by conventional mixing procedures, for
example, by adding them in a banbury mixer or by adding
them to the rubber on a mill. Preferably, when the
polymeric resins have higher molecular weights, it is
recommended that they be ground to a fine powder to insure
adequate dispersion. Such powders may be treated to
suppress dust, for example, by the addition of oil, or they
can be mixed with a binder, for example, a polymer latex,
and granules or pellets containing up to 5 percent by
weight of a binder. They can also be formulated as pre-dispersions
or masterbatched in a diene rubber stock, which
pre-dispersions may contain, for example, from 15 to 50
percent by weight of the polymeric resin.</p><p num="0022">Similar to vulcanizing conventional rubber stocks, the
rubber stocks containing the polymeric resins need a sulfur
vulcanizing agent. Examples of suitable sulfur vulcanizing
agents include elemental sulfur (free sulfur) or sulfur 
donating vulcanizing agents, for example, an amine
disulfide, polymeric polysulfide or sulfur olefin adducts.
Preferably, the sulfur vulcanizing agent is elemental
sulfur. The amount of sulfur vulcanizing agent will vary
depending on the components of the rubber stock and the
particular type of sulfur vulcanizing agent that is used.
Generally speaking, the amount of sulfur vulcanizing agent
ranges from 0.1 to 8 phr with a range of from 1.5 to 6
being preferred.</p><p num="0023">Conventional rubber additives may be incorporated in
the rubber stock of the present invention. The presence of
a sulfur vulcanizing agent and conventional additives are
not considered to be an aspect of this invention. The
additives commonly used in rubber stocks include fillers,
plasticizers, curatives, processing oils, retarders,
antiozonants, antioxidants and the like. The total amount
of filler that may be used may range from 45 to 130 phr
being preferred. Fillers include silicas, clays, calcium
carbonate, calcium silicate, titanium dioxide and carbon
black. Preferably, at least a portion of the filler is
carbon black. Plasticizers, oils or mixtures thereof are
conventionally used in amounts ranging from 2 to 150 phr
with a range of 5 to 130 phr being preferred. The amount
of plasticizer used will depend upon the softening effect
desired. Examples of suitable plasticizers include
aromatic extract oils, petroleum softeners including
asphaltenes, saturated and unsaturated hydrocarbons and
nitrogen bases, coal tar products, cumarone-indene resins
and esters such as dibutylphthalate and tricresyl
phosphate. Examples of oils are commonly known as highly
aromatic process oil, process soybean oil and highly
paraffinic process oil. Materials used in compounding
which function as an accelerator-activator includes metal
oxides such as zinc oxide, magnesium oxide and litharge
which are used in conjunction with acidic materials such as
fatty acid, for example, stearic acid, oleic acid, murastic
acid, and the like. The amount of the metal oxide may 
range from 1 to 10 phr with a range of from 2 to 8 phr
being preferred. The amount of fatty acid which may be
used may range from 0.25 phr to 5.0 phr with a range of
from 0.5 phr to 2 phr being preferred.</p><p num="0024">Accelerators may be used to control the time and/or
temperature required for vulcanization of the rubber stock.
As known to those skilled in the art, a single accelerator
may be used which is present in amounts ranging from 0.2 to
3.0 phr. In the alternative, combinations of two or more
accelerators may be used which consist of a primary
accelerator which is generally used in a larger amount (0.3
to 3.0 phr), and a secondary accelerator which is generally
used in smaller amounts (0.05 to 1.50 phr) in order to
activate and improve the properties of the rubber stock.
Combinations of these accelerators have been known to
produce synergistic effects on the final properties and are
somewhat better than those produced by use of either
accelerator alone. Delayed action accelerators also are
known to be used which are not affected by normal
processing temperatures and produce satisfactory cures at
ordinary vulcanization temperatures. Suitable types of
accelerators include amines, disulfides, guanidines,
thioureas, thiazoles, thiurams, sulfenamides,
dithiocarbamates and the xanthates. Examples of specific
compounds which are suitable include zinc diethyldithiocarbamate,
4,4'-dithiodimorpholine, N,N-di-methyl-S-tert-butylsulfenyldithiocarbamate,
tetramethylthiuram
disulfide, 2,2'-dibenzothiazyl disulfide,
butyraldehydeaniline mercaptobenzothiazole, N-oxydiethylene-2-benzothiazolesulfenamide.
Preferably, the
accelerator is a sulfenamide.</p><p num="0025">A class of compounding materials known as scorch
retarders are commonly used. Phthalic anhydride,
salicyclic acid, sodium acetate and N-cyclohexyl
thiophthalimide are known retarders. Retarders are
generally used in an amount ranging from 0.1 to 0.5 phr.</p><p num="0026">Preformed phenol-formaldehyde type resins may be used 
in the rubber stock and are generally present in an amount
ranging from 1.0 to 5.0 phr, with a range of from 1.5 to
3.5 phr being preferred.</p><p num="0027">Conventionally, antioxidants and some times
antiozonants, hereinafter referred to as antidegradants,
are added to rubber stocks. Representative antidegradants
include monophenols, bisphenols, thiobisphenols,
polyphenols, hydroquinone derivatives, phosphites,
thioesters, naphthyl amines, diphenyl-p-phenylenediamines,
diphenylamines and other diaryl amine derivatives, paraphenylenediamines,
quinolines and mixtures thereof.
Specific examples of such antidegradants are disclosed in
The Vanderbilt Rubber Handbook (1990), pages 282-286.
Antidegradants are generally used in amounts from 0.25 to
5.0 phr with a range of from 1.0 to 3.0 phr being
preferred.</p><p num="0028">The mixing of the rubber composition can be
accomplished by methods known to those having skill in the
rubber mixing art. For example, the ingredients are
typically mixed in at least two stages; namely, at least
one non-productive stage followed by a productive mix
stage. The final curatives including sulfur vulcanizing
agents are typically mixed in the final stage which is
conventionally called the "productive" mix stage in which
the mixing typically occurs at a temperature, or ultimate
temperature, lower than the mix temperature(s) than the
preceding non-productive mix stage(s). The rubber and
polymeric resin are mixed in one or more non-productive mix
stages. The terms "non-productive" and "productive" mix
stages are well known to those having skill in the rubber
mixing art.</p><p num="0029">Vulcanization of the pneumatic tire of the present
invention is generally carried out at conventional
temperatures ranging from 100°C to 200°C. Preferably, the
vulcanization is conducted at temperatures ranging from
110°C to 180°C. Any of the usual vulcanization processes
may be used such as heating in a press or mold, heating 
with superheated steam or hot air or in a salt bath.</p><p num="0030">The following examples are presented in order to
illustrate but not limit the present invention.</p><p num="0031">Cure properties were determined using a Monsanto
oscillating disc rheometer which was operated at a
temperature of 150°C and at a frequency of 11 hertz. A
description of oscillating disc rheometers can be found in
the Vanderbilt Rubber Handbook edited by Robert O. Ohm
(Norwalk, Conn., R. T. Vanderbilt Company, Inc., 1990),
pages 554-557. The use of this cure meter and standardized
values read from the curve are specified in ASTM D-2084. A
typical cure curve obtained on an oscillating disc
rheometer is shown on page 555 of the 1990 edition of the
Vanderbilt Rubber Handbook.</p><p num="0032">In such an oscillating disc rheometer, compounded
rubber samples are subjected to an oscillating shearing
action of constant amplitude. The torque of the
oscillating disc embedded in the stock that is being tested
that is required to oscillate the rotor at the
vulcanization temperature is measured. The values obtained
using this cure test are very significant since changes in
the rubber or the compounding recipe are very readily
detected. It is obvious that it is normally advantageous
to have a fast cure rate.</p><p num="0033">In the following examples, the Flexsys Rubber Process
Analyzer (RPA) 2000 was used to determine dynamic
mechanical rheological properties. The curing conditions
were 160°C, 1.667 Hz, 15.8 minutes and 0.7 percent strain.
A description of the RPA 2000, its capability, sample
preparation, tests and subtests can be found in these
references. H A Pawlowski and J S Dick, Rubber World, June
1992; J S Dick and H A Pawlowski, Rubber World, January
1997; and J S Dick and J A Pawlowski, Rubber &amp; Plastics
News, April 26 and May 10, 1993.</p><p num="0034">The compounded rubber sample is placed on the bottom
die. When the dies are brought together, the sample is in
a pressurized cavity where it will be subjected to a 
sinusoidal oscillating shearing action of the bottom die.
A torque transducer connected to the upper die measures the
amount of torque transmitted through the sample as a result
of the oscillations. Torque is translated into the shear
modulus, G, by correcting for the die form factor and the
strain. The RPA 2000 is capable of testing uncured or
cured rubber with a high degree of repeatability and
reproducibility. The tests and subtests available include
frequency sweeps at constant temperature and strain, curing
at constant temperature and frequency, strain sweeps at
constant temperature and frequency and temperature sweeps
at constant strain and frequency. The accuracy and
precision of the instrument allows reproducible detection
of changes in the compounded sample.</p><p num="0035">The values reported for the storage modulus, (G'),
loss compliance (J'') and tan delta are obtained from a
strain sweep at 100°C and 1 Hz following the cure test.
These properties represent the viscoelastic response of a
test sample to shear deformation at a constant temperature
and frequency.</p><p num="0036">The following examples are presented for the purposes
of illustrating and not limiting the present invention.
All parts are parts by weight unless specifically
identified otherwise.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0037">A one liter stainless steel autoclave was charged with
170 grams of washed and dried dicyclopentadiene, 80 grams
of washed and dried (+)-limonene and 100 milliliters of
xylenes. The reactor was flushed with nitrogen, sealed and
heated to 270°C with stirring. The reactor pressure peaked
at 185 psig at 270°C. The reactor pressure began to drop
as the temperature was maintained at 270°C. Within 15
minutes, the pressure dropped 20 to 30 psig. After one
hour of residence time, the reactor was cooled. The
contents were transferred to a flask and heated to 170°C,
and the pressure on the surface of the contents was reduced 
to 25 inches of mercury vacuum. The stripped resin was
poured from the flask as molten material at 150°C. A
softening point from 55-75°C was determined. The molecular
weight range was determined to be 500 to 15,000.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0038">The procedures of Example 1 were repeated except the
residence time at 270°C was two hours, instead of one hour.
The softening point for this polymeric resin ranged from 80
to 131°C. The molecular weight range was determined to be
700 to 15,000.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><p num="0039">The procedures of Example 1 were repeated, except the
residence time at 270°C was 4 hours, and the polymeric
resin product had a softening point ranging from 126°C to
168°C. The molecular weight range was determined to be
3,000 to 15,000.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 4</u></heading><p num="0040">The procedures of Example 1 were repeated except the
residence time of 270°C was for 6 hours instead of one
hour, and the softening point for the resin ranged from
168°C to 195°C. The molecular weight range was determined
to be 4,000 to 15,000.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 5</u></heading><p num="0041">The dicyclopentadiene/limonene resin from Examples 1-4,
were combined by mixing 150 grams of each polymeric
resin into a 2-liter stainless steel beaker. A hot plate
was used to melt the polymeric resins and stirring gave a
homogeneous mixture. The blend was cooled to room
temperature, and chipped into small granular pieces, which
exhibited an overall softening range of from 78 to 173°C.
The product was an amber-color solid. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 6</u></heading><p num="0042">A three liter round bottom flask was fitted with a
mechanical stirrer, a constant temperature water bath, a
thermocouple and a dropping funnel. The flask was swept
with nitrogen and charged with 200 milliliters of
cyclohexane containing 10 grams of anhydrous aluminum
chloride. Stirring was started and the water bath raised
the temperature of the aluminum chloride/cyclohexane
suspension to 30°C. The dropping funnel was charged with a
170 grams of dicyclopentadiene that had been washed with 6
percent aqueous sodium hydroxide inhibitor, but not dried
after a second washing with water, 80 grams of (+)-limonene
of technical grade from Eastman Kodak and 100 milliliters
of cyclohexane. The feed stream was added as quickly as
possible with the reaction temperature maintained at 32 ±
2°C. After 25 minutes, all of the feed had been added and
the reaction temperature of 32 ± 2°C was maintained for
three hours with stirring. A solution of 200 milliliters
of isopropanol and 600 milliliters of water was added to
the reaction mixture as the heat was removed. The aqueous-organic
mixture was stirred vigorously until all of the
catalyst had been hydrolyzed. The organic layer which
contains a suspended solid was separated and washed with
two portions of 200 milliliters of water. The organic
layer which contained the suspended solid was dried in a
drying oven at 150°C and 28 inches of mercury vacuum. The
product softens or shows wetting in a capillary melting
point tube at 188 to 208°C with a molecular weight range of
700 to 40,000.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 7</u></heading><p num="0043">The reaction conditions and procedures of Example 6
were repeated at 42 ± 2°C to give a resin that softens or
shows wetting in a capillary melting tube at 138 to 180°C
with a molecular weight range of 700 to 36,000. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 8</u></heading><p num="0044">Reaction conditions and procedures of Example 6 were
repeated except the reaction was conducted at 52 ± 2°C to
give a resin that softens or shows wetting in a capillary
melting point tube at 134 to 156°C with a molecular weight
range of 700 to 24,000.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 9</u></heading><p num="0045">The dicyclopentadiene/limonene resin from Examples 6,
7, and 8 were combined by mixing 75 grams of each polymeric
resin into a 2-liter stainless steel beaker. A hot plate
was used to liquify the polymeric resins and stirring gave
a homogeneous mixture. The blend was cooled to room
temperature, and chipped into small granular pieces, which
exhibited an overall softening range of from 132°C to
191°C.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 10</u></heading> <p num="0046">Three hundred parts of cyclohexane and 50 parts of
anhydrous aluminum chloride were placed into a reactor.
While continuously stirring the mixture, 600 parts of a
hydrocarbon mixture was slowly added to the reactor over a
period of 60 minutes. The hydrocarbon mixture consisted of
30 percent inert hydrocarbons with the remaining 70 percent
by weight of the mixture comprising the following resin
forming components:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Component</entry><entry align="center">Percent</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Limonene</entry><entry align="center">67.0</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">Dicyclopentadiene</entry> <entry align="center">33.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0047">The temperature of the reaction was maintained in a
range of 25° to 30°C. After an hour of agitation from the
time of final addition, the hydrocarbon mixture was added
to approximately 4,000 parts of a 25 percent solution of
isopropyl alcohol in water to neutralize and decompose the 
aluminum chloride. The aqueous layer was removed and the
resin solution washed with an additional 4,000 parts of the
alcohol/water blend.</p><p num="0048">The resulting resin solution was steam-distilled at a
pot temperature of 235°C. The resulting residual molten
resin was cooled to room temperature to provide an 85
percent yield of a hard brittle pale yellow resin having a
softening point of 110°C to 129°C. Small molecule GPC
analysis gives a molecular weight distribution of 6.7
percent in the 9500 MW range, 69.1 percent in the 1100 MW
range, 6.5 percent in the 600 MW range, 9.0 percent in the
450 MW range and 4.6 percent in the 330 MW range.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 11</u></heading><p num="0049">A rubber stock was prepared which consisted of styrene
butadiene rubber and conventional amounts of carbon black
antioxidant, sulfur and accelerator, fatty acid and zinc
oxide. In addition, each sample contained a highly
aromatic processing oil, highly paraffinic process oil and
processed soybean oil. In Samples 1 and 3, the three oils
were partially replaced with a polymeric
dicyclopentadiene/limonene resin. In this study, each of
the four polymeric resins prepared in accordance with
Examples 1-4 was used at the 6 and 12 phr level (total
resin was 24 and 48 phr) and compared with the control
compounds. The table below provides the relative amounts
of the various oils and resins. In addition, the
properties of each of the resulting rubber stocks were
tested nd are listed in the table. The cured specimens of
each rubber stock were prepared by press curing the sample
at 150°C for 28 minutes under 280 psi pressure with the
exception of those specimens used to test for Strebler,
Zwick Rebound, Light Blow Out and DIN Abrasion. The
samples for testing for Strebler, Zwick Rebound and Light
Blow Out were cured for 38 minutes. The specimens tested
for DIN Abrasion were cured for 33 minutes. <img id="img-00170001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00170001.tif" inline="no" he="208"/><img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="202"/><img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="209"/></p><p num="0050">As one can see from the above data, the effect of
using the dicyclopentadiene/limonene resins in place of the
aromatic processing oil, paraffinic processing oil and
processed soybean oil was to increase the hysteresis
(rebound, E'', tangent delta) and low strain stiffness (E',
hardness) while reducing the cure state (300 percent
modulus), cure rate (T25, T90) and tear (Strebler). The
dicyclopentadiene/limonene resins gave better storage
modulus, loss modulus and tangent delta throughout the
temperature range of 60°C to 150°C. It is this response
with temperature that provides enhanced traction and
handling.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 12</u></heading><p num="0051">In this example, various resins were evaluated in a
rubber compound.</p><p num="0052">Rubber compositions containing the materials set out
in Tables 2 and 3 were prepared in a BR Banbury™ mixer
using two separate stages of addition (mixing); namely, one
non-productive mix stage and one productive mix stage. The
non-productive stage was mixed for 3.5 minutes or to a
rubber temperature of 160°C, whichever occurred first. The
mixing time for the productive stage was to a rubber
temperature of 120°C.</p><p num="0053">The rubber compositions are identified herein as
Samples 1-3. Samples 1 and 2 are considered herein as
controls without the use of the resin used in the present
invention being added to the rubber composition. Samples 1
and 2 each contain commercially available resins. Sample 3
is the resin prepared in Example 10.</p><p num="0054">The samples were cured at 150°C for 28 minutes.</p><p num="0055">Table 3 illustrates the behavior and physical
properties of the cured Samples 1-3.</p><p num="0056">Lab data reveals that the new DCPD/Limonene resin in
fact enhances the traction and durability properties
simultaneously without following the typical tradeoff as
previously described. Comparing the dynamic properties 
from the RPA 2000 and stress-strain data (UTS) of the
Coumarone-Indene and phenolic resins, the typical tradeoff
of sacrificing durability (lower G' at 40 percent strain,
300 percent modulus and tensile strength) for improved dry
traction (increased tan delta and loss compliance at 40
percent strain) is demonstrated. Control A (phenolic
resin) is a soft compound with high hysteresis. Control B
(Coumarone-Indene resin) is a stiff compound with low
hysteresis.</p><p num="0057">The DCPD/Limonene resin versus the Control A shows
that the durability is significantly improved (G' at 40
percent strain, 300 percent modulus and tensile strength)
and dry traction is maintained (tan delta and J'' at 40
percent). Control B represents a typical effort to
increase the durability of Control A through the use of
resins. The DCPD/Limonene resin versus the Control B shows
that the durability is only slightly reduced (G' at 40
percent strain, 300 percent modulus and tensile strength)
and the dry traction is significantly improved (tan delta
and J'' at 40 percent). <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Samples</entry><entry align="center">Ctrl 1</entry><entry align="center">Ctrl 2</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Non-Productive</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion SBR<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbon Black<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">80.0</entry><entry align="center">80.0</entry><entry align="center">80.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Aromatic Oil</entry><entry align="center">37.5</entry><entry align="center">37.5</entry><entry align="center">37.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Stearic Acid</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Microcrystalline Wax</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zinc Oxide</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Antioxidant<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Phenolic Resin<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">25.0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coumarone Indene<!--footnotes removed--> Resin</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">25.0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Resin of Example 10</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">25.0</entry></row><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Productive</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Accelerators<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Accelerator<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sulfur</entry><entry align="center">0.95</entry><entry align="center">0.95</entry><entry align="center">0.95<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Sample</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Phenolic resin</entry><entry align="center">25.0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coumarone Indene Resin</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">25.0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Resin of Example 10</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">25.0</entry></row><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">RPA 2000, 15.8 min, 160°C, 17% strain, 1.67 Hz</entry></row><row><entry align="left">T25 (min)</entry><entry align="center">1.89</entry><entry align="center">2.98</entry><entry align="center">1.92</entry></row><row><entry align="left">T90 (min)</entry><entry align="center">9.3</entry><entry align="center">9.7</entry><entry align="center">9.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Min Torque (dNm)</entry><entry align="center">0.49</entry><entry align="center">0.59</entry><entry align="center">0.66</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Max Torque (dNm)</entry><entry align="center">1.76</entry><entry align="center">2.28</entry><entry align="center">2.28</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Delta Torque (dNm)</entry><entry align="center">1.27</entry><entry align="center">1.69</entry><entry align="center">1.62</entry></row><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">RPA 2000, 1 Hz, 100°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">G' 40% (KPa)</entry><entry align="center">376</entry><entry align="center">476</entry><entry align="center">449</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tan Delta 40%</entry><entry align="center">0.254</entry><entry align="center">0.224</entry><entry align="center">0.277</entry></row><row><entry align="left">J'' 40% 1/MPa</entry><entry align="center">0.63</entry><entry align="center">0.45</entry><entry align="center">0.57</entry></row><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">UTS, cure 28 minutes @ 150°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">300% Modulus, MPa</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry><entry align="center">4.1</entry><entry align="center">3.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Strength, MPa</entry><entry align="center">13.2</entry><entry align="center">15.8</entry><entry align="center">14.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elongation, %</entry><entry align="center">719</entry><entry align="center">718</entry><entry align="center">740</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zwick Rebound, 95°C</entry><entry align="center">29.8</entry><entry align="center">35.6</entry><entry align="center">29.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rebound 120°C</entry><entry align="center">35.8</entry><entry align="center">40.6</entry><entry align="center">34</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A resin composition characterized by a polymer
which is the reaction product of the polymerization
reaction between dicyclopentadiene and limonene, said resin
having a softening point ranging from 50 to 220°C and a
molecular weight ranging from 500 to 42,000 g/mol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A resin composition characterized by comprising a
blend of two or more individual resin compositions
according to claim 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A rubber stock characterized by (1) a rubber
selected from the group consisting of natural rubber,
rubbers derived from a diene monomer or mixtures thereof,
and (2) the polymeric resin composition of claim 1 or 2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The rubber stock of claim 3 characterized in that
said rubber derived from a diene monomer or mixtures
thereof is selected from the group comprising natural
rubber, polyisoprene, polybutadiene, polychloroprene,
copolymers of isoprene and butadiene, copolymers of styrene
and butadiene, copolymers of acrylonitrile and butadiene,
copolymers of acrylonitrile and isoprene and blends
thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The rubber stock of claim 3 characterized in that
said polymeric resin composition is present in an amount
ranging from 5 to 50 parts per hundred parts of rubber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The rubber stock of claim 5 characterized in that
said polymeric resin composition is present in an amount
ranging from 10 to 25 parts per hundred parts of rubber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A pneumatic tire having a tread characterized by
(1) a rubber selected from the group consisting of natural
rubber, rubbers derived from a diene monomer or mixtures
thereof, and (2) the polymeric resin composition of claim 1
or 2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The pneumatic tire of claim 7 characterized in
that said rubber derived from a diene monomer or mixtures
thereof is selected from the group comprising natural
rubber, polyisoprene, polybutadiene, polychloroprene,
copolymers of isoprene and butadiene, copolymers of styrene
and butadiene, copolymers of acrylonitrile and butadiene,
copolymers of acrylonitrile and isoprene and blends
thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The pneumatic tire of claim 7 characterized in
that said polymeric resin composition is present in an
amount ranging from 5 to 50 parts per hundred parts of
rubber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The pneumatic tire of claim 9 characterized in
that said polymeric resin composition is present in an
amount ranging from 10 to 25 parts per hundred parts of
rubber.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="241" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="237" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>