<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1441039-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1441039" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="32594954" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040728"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1441039-A2" status="new" fvid="24095885"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1441039</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20040728</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04250314-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04250314</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040121</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-35096803-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>35096803</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030122</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22F   3/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22F   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22F   9/16        20060101CLI20060328BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22F   9/28        20060101ALI20060328BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C   1/10        20060101AFI20040422BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C   1/10        20060101CLI20040422BHEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B22F   3/00B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B22F   9/28</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22C   1/10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L22F999:00+C22C1/10+B22F9/28</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung eines Formkörpers mit dispersoidverstärkter Metallmatrix</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method for preparing an article having dispersoid distributed in a metallic matrix</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé de préparation d'un article avec matrice renforcée par dispersion</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-3152389-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3152389</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3773493-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3773493</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6264719-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6264719</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998043763-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998043763</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2001045906-A2"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2001045906</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEN ELECTRIC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1 River Road</street><city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GIGLIOTTI MICHAEL FRANCIS XAVI</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OTT ERIC ALLEN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SHAMBLEN CLIFFORD EARL</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WOODFIELD ANDREW PHILIP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GIGLIOTTI, MICHAEL FRANCIS XAVIER</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OTT, ERIC ALLEN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SHAMBLEN, CLIFFORD EARL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WOODFIELD, ANDREW PHILIP</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GIGLIOTTI, MICHAEL FRANCIS XAVIER</last-name><address><street>41 Kile Drive</street><city>Glenville, New York 12302</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OTT, ERIC ALLEN</last-name><address><street>9885 Meadow Hills Drive</street><city>Cincinnati, Ohio 45241</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SHAMBLEN, CLIFFORD EARL</last-name><address><street>9656 Lansford Drive</street><city>Cincinnati, Ohio 45242</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WOODFIELD, ANDREW PHILIP</last-name><address><street>6245 Cherokee Drive</street><city>Cincinnati, Ohio 45243</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Goode, Ian Roy</last-name><address><street>London Patent Operation General Electric International, Inc. 15 John Adam Street</street><city>London WC2N 6LU</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An article has a metallic matrix made of its constituent elements with a
dispersoid distributed therein. The article is prepared by furnishing (50) at
least one nonmetallic matrix precursor compound. All of the nonmetallic
matrix precursor compounds collectively include the constituent elements of
the metallic matrix in their respective constituent-element proportions. A
mixture of an initial metallic material and the dispersoid is produced (52). The
matrix precursor compounds are chemically reduced to produce the initial
metallic material, without melting the initial metallic material, and the
dispersoid is distributed in the initial metallic material. The mixture of the
initial metallic material and the dispersoid is consolidated (54) to produce a
consolidated article having the dispersoid distributed in the metallic matrix
comprising the initial metallic material. The initial metallic material, the
dispersoid, and the consolidated article are not melted during the
consolidation.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="83"/></p></abstract> <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention relates to the preparation of a material in which a dispersoid is
dispersed through a metallic matrix, and more particularly to the preparation
of such a material that avoids any melting of the constituents.</p><p num="0002">Materials having a dispersion of substantially inert dispersoids distributed in a
metallic matrix are known. An example is TD-nickel, in which thorium oxide
dispersoid is distributed through a nickel matrix. The dispersoids improve the
mechanical properties of the material by interfering with dislocation
movement, particularly if the dispersoids are closely spaced, and also by
inhibiting the movement of the grain boundaries of the matrix during elevated
temperature exposure.</p><p num="0003">There are two primary techniques for producing such materials, mechanical
alloying and spray forming. In mechanical alloying, the more widely used of
the two approaches, the material of the metallic matrix is melted and solidified
as a powder. One or more types of metallic powders are mixed with the
dispersoid, and the mixture is mechanically deformed in a high-energy
environment such as a ball mill. In the mechanical deformation, the largely
nondeformable dispersoid is incorporated into the deformable metallic
powder(s) by repeated fracturing and cold welding of the metallic powder
particles with the dispersion contained at the welded interfaces. After the
mechanical deformation, the mixture is consolidated. This approach requires
lengthy and/or costly ball milling operations which can be prone to the
introduction of defects into the mechanically alloyed material. Additionally,
many metallic matrix materials that are otherwise of interest cannot be used
in mechanical alloying, because they are not sufficiently malleable to cold
weld to the dispersoids in the ball milling. The use of mechanical alloying is
therefore limited primarily to lower-strength, higher-ductility metallic materials. </p><p num="0004">In spray forming, metallic material is melted and sprayed from a spray gun to
solidify or partially solidify in a suitable inert atmosphere prior to being
consolidated against a substrate. The dispersoid is added to the spray of the
metallic material as it leaves the spray gun and is thereby mixed with the
solidified metal. Spray forming can only be used in specialized
circumstances, inasmuch as the process is limited to the use of dispersoids
that do not react with or melt in the molten metal, the process is expensive,
and it is difficult to control the size and spacing of the dispersoid. The
microstructure is dominated by the solidification structure of the metallic
material produced at rapid cooling rates.</p><p num="0005">There is a need for an improved approach to the preparation of articles
having a metallic matrix with dispersoids distributed therein. The required
improvements include reducing the manufacturing time, reducing the number
of process steps, reducing the sources of contamination, and permitting the
use of higher strength matrix materials in combination with fine dispersoids.
The present invention fulfills this need, and further provides related
advantages.</p> <p num="0006">The present invention provides a technique for preparing an article having a
metallic alloy matrix with a fine dispersoid distributed therein. The article is
preferably prepared without melting of the metal alloy and without mechanical
deformation of the metal alloy, prior to final consolidation and mechanical
forming. The incidence of defects in the metallic matrix is thereby greatly
reduced, as compared with mechanical alloying. The present approach
allows the use of higher-strength metallic matrix materials than possible with
mechanical alloying, and the use of different dispersoids than are possible
with prior approaches. There is less anisotropy in the final article, and a fine
grain structure can be achieved in the final article. The cost of manufacturing
the article by the present approach is less than with prior approaches.</p> <p num="0007">An article has a metallic matrix made of its constituent elements with a
dispersoid distributed therein. The article is prepared by furnishing at least 
one nonmetallic matrix precursor compound. All of the nonmetallic matrix
precursor compounds collectively include the constituent elements of the
metallic matrix in their respective constituent-element proportions. A mixture
of an initial metallic material and the dispersoid is produced. The matrix
precursor compounds are chemically reduced to produce the initial metallic
material, without melting the initial metallic material, and the dispersoid is
distributed in the initial metallic material. The mixture of the initial metallic
material and the dispersoid is consolidated to produce a consolidated article
having the dispersoid distributed in the metallic matrix comprising the initial
metallic material. The initial metallic material, the dispersoid, and the
consolidated article are not melted during the consolidation. Preferably, there
is no mechanical deformation The initial metallic material and the matrix of
the final article may be of any operable constituents. The present approach is
operable, for example, with nickel-base, iron-base, cobalt-base, titanium-base,
magnesium-base, and aluminum-base materials.</p> <p num="0008">The dispersoids may be introduced into and mixed with the metallic
component in any operable manner. In one preferred approach, the step of
producing includes the steps of furnishing the dispersoids, and mixing the
dispersoids with the matrix precursor compounds prior to or concurrently with
the step of chemically reducing. In another preferred approach, the step of
producing includes the steps of furnishing the dispersoids, and mixing the
dispersoids with the initial metallic material after the step of chemically
reducing. In another preferred approach, the step of producing includes the
steps of furnishing a dispersoid-precursor, and mixing the dispersoid
precursor with the matrix precursor compound prior to or concurrently with the
step of chemically reducing, and wherein the dispersoid precursor chemically
reacts during the step of chemically reacting to produce the dispersoid. In
another preferred approach, an element of the dispersoid may be supplied as
a precursor compound to be reduced in a second reduction step and then
reacted to form the desired dispersoid compound. </p><p num="0009">The matrix precursor compounds may be furnished in any operable physical
form. For example, a compressed mass of the matrix precursor compounds
may be furnished. Typically, such a compressed mass is larger in dimensions
than the consolidated article. The matrix precursor compounds may instead
be furnished in an uncompressed, free-flowing form of finely divided particles,
or a liquid, or a vapor.</p><p num="0010">The chemical reduction may be performed by any operable approach, such
as solid-phase reduction or vapor-phase reduction. The chemical reduction
may produce the initial metallic material in any operable form. For example,
the step of chemically reducing may produce a sponge of the initial metallic
material, or particles of the</p><p num="0011">The consolidation may be performed by any operable approach, such as, for
example, hot isostatic pressing, forging, pressing and sintering, and
containerized extrusion. After consolidation, the consolidated article may be
formed, heat treated, or otherwise final processed.</p><p num="0012">The present approach produces an article that has a metallic matrix and
dispersoids uniformly distributed in the bulk of the metallic matrix, or with a
high concentration near the surface if desired. A wide variety of metallic
materials and dispersoid materials may be used. The dispersoids may be, for
example, oxides, carbides, nitrides, borides, or sulfides, or combinations of
the constituent elements, such as carbonitrides, formed with the elements of
the metallic matrix or with other intentionally added elements. The
dispersoids are selected to be either thermodynamically stable (non-reducible)
compared to the matrix alloy, or too chemically inert and stable to
be reduced by the process that reduces the matrix precursor compounds.
The dispersoid is introduced at a point in the processing where it is stable with
respect to all subsequent processing steps. The metallic matrix is never
melted during the preparation processing, so that there is little if any chemical
reaction between the metallic components and the dispersoid. In the
preferred approach, there is no high-energy or other deformation of the 
metallic material prior to consolidation, so that there is a greatly reduced
incidence of the mechanical and heating defects that are associated with
mechanical alloying. Additionally, because the introduction of the dispersoid
does not depend upon the mechanical deformation of the matrix material, the
present approach may be used with a broader range of useful metallic alloy
systems than possible with mechanical alloying. High-strength alloys that are
not amenable to extensive mechanical deformation may be produced with a
distribution of the dispersoid therein by the present approach but not by
mechanical alloying. New types of dispersoids may also be used. Those
dispersoids may be added as the dispersoid compound, or in some cases
may be added as elements or precursor compounds that react with the matrix
alloy to form the dispersoids. Alternatively, the precursor compound may
react with other components in a separate reaction step.</p><p num="0013">Other features and advantages of the present invention will be apparent from
the following more detailed description of the preferred embodiment, taken in
conjunction with the accompanying drawings, which illustrate, by way of
example, the principles of the invention, and in which:
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a perspective view of an article made by the present approach;</li><li>Figure 2 is an idealized microstructure of the article of Figure 1;</li><li>Figure 3 is a block flow diagram of a preferred approach for practicing the
invention;</li><li>Figure 4 is an idealized microstructure of the metallic article, after some
reaction that produces a uniform dispersion;</li><li>Figure 5 is an idealized microstructure of the metallic article, after inward
diffusion of a reactant during heat treatment or service; and</li><li>Figure 6 is an idealized microstructure of a conventional metallic article, after
inward diffusion of the reactant.</li></sl></p><p num="0014">Figure 1 depicts a component article 20 of a gas turbine engine such as a
compressor blade 22. The compressor blade 22 is preferably formed of a
titanium-base alloy having a dispersoid therein, as will be discussed in greater
detail. The compressor blade 22 includes an airfoil 24 that acts against the
incoming flow of air into the gas turbine engine and axially compresses the air
flow. The compressor blade 22 is mounted to a compressor disk (not shown)
by a dovetail 26 which extends downwardly from the airfoil 24 and engages a
slot on the compressor disk. A platform 28 extends longitudinally outwardly
from the area where the airfoil 24 is joined to the dovetail 26.</p><p num="0015">A titanium-base alloy having a dispersoid therein is one preferred application
of the present approach, and it will be used to illustrate specific embodiments.
However, the present approach is not limited to titanium-based alloys with
dispersoids therein, and is applicable to other types of metallic alloys with
dispersoids therein.</p><p num="0016">Figure 2 is an idealized depiction of the microstructure 30 of the article 20.
The microstructure 30 includes grains 32 of a metallic matrix 34 with grain
boundaries 36 separating the grains 32. The metallic matrix comprises its
alloy constituent elements. A dispersoid 38 in the form of a plurality of
dispersoid particles is distributed in the metallic matrix 34. The dispersoid 38
may include grain-boundary dispersoid particles 40 that reside along the grain
boundaries 36, and interior dispersoid particles 42 that reside within the
grains 32. The grain-boundary dispersoid particles 40 serve to limit grain
growth during elevated-temperature exposure, and the interior dispersoid
particles 42 serve to restrict dislocation movement to increase the alloy's
strength, most specifically the creep resistance. Examples of suitable
dispersoids include, for example, oxides, carbides, nitrides, borides, or
sulfides, formed with the elements of the metallic matrix or with other
intentionally added elements. The dispersoids may be simple chemical
forms. The dispersoids may instead be more complex, multicomponent
compounds such as, for example, carbonitrides or multicomponent oxides
such as Y<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-based oxides. Such dispersoids include an element (or 
elements) selected from the group consisting of oxygen, carbon, nitrogen,
boron, sulfur, and combinations thereof. The dispersoids are either
thermodynamically stable (non-reducible) compared to the matrix alloy, or too
chemically inert to be reduced by the process that reduces the matrix
precursor compounds. The dispersoid is introduced at a point in the
processing where it is stable with respect to all subsequent processing steps.
That is, if a particular type of dispersoid is unstable with respect to some
earlier processing step, it is introduced only after that processing step is</p><p num="0017">The dispersoid 38 (including both grain-boundary dispersoid particles 40 and
interior dispersoid particles 42) may be present in any amount. However, the
dispersoid 38 is preferably present in an amount sufficient to provide
increased strength to the article 20 by inhibiting dislocation movement in the
metallic matrix 34, by acting as a composite-material strengthener, and/or by
inhibiting movement of the grain boundaries 36. The volume fraction of
dispersoid 38 required to perform these functions varies depending upon the
nature of the matrix 34 and the dispersoid 38, but is typically at least about
0.5 percent by volume of the article, and more preferably at least about 1.5
percent by volume of the article. To achieve these volume fractions, the
elements that react to form the dispersoid 38 must be present in a sufficient</p><p num="0018">Figure 3 is a block flow diagram illustrating a preferred method for producing
the article 20. At least one nonmetallic matrix precursor compound is
furnished, step 50. As used herein, the term "metallic alloy" includes both
conventional metallic alloys and intermetallic compounds formed of metallic
constituents, such as approximately equiatomic TiAl. Relatively small
amounts of nonmetallic elements, such as boron, carbon, and silicon, may
also be present. All of the nonmetallic matrix precursor compounds
collectively include the constituent elements of the metallic matrix in their
respective constituent-element proportions. (The dispersoid or its precursor is
supplied separately, as will be discussed.) The metallic elements may be
supplied by the matrix precursor compounds in any operable way. In the
preferred approach, there is exactly one precursor compound for each 
alloying element, and that one precursor compound provides all of the
material for that respective metallic constituent in the alloy. For example, for
a four-element metallic matrix material that is the final result of the process, a
first precursor compound supplies all of the first element, a second precursor
compound supplies all of the second element, a third precursor compound
supplies all of the third element, and a fourth precursor compound supplies all
of the fourth element. Alternatives are within the scope of the approach,
however. For example, several of the precursor compounds may together
supply all of one particular metallic element. In another alternative, one
precursor compound may supply all or part of two or more of the metallic
elements. The latter approaches are less preferred, because they make
more difficult the precise determination of the elemental proportions in the
final metallic material.</p><p num="0019">The metallic matrix 34 and its constituent elements comprise any operable
type of alloy. Examples include a nickel-base material, an iron-base material,
a cobalt-base material, a titanium-base material, a magnesium-base material,
and an aluminum-base material. An "X-base" alloy has more of element X
than any other element.</p><p num="0020">The matrix precursor compounds are nonmetallic and are selected to be
operable in the reduction process in which they are reduced to metallic form.
In one reduction process of interest, solid-phase reduction, the precursor
compounds are preferably metal oxides. In another reduction process of
interest, vapor-phase reduction, the precursor compounds are preferably
metal halides. Mixtures of different types of matrix precursor compounds may
be used, as long as they are operable in the subsequent chemical reduction.</p><p num="0021">The nonmetallic precursor compounds are selected to provide the necessary
alloying elements in the final metallic article, and are mixed together in the
proper proportions to yield the necessary proportions of these alloying
elements in the metallic article. For example, if the final article were to have
particular proportions of titanium, aluminum, vanadium, erbium, and oxygen in 
the ratio of 86.5:6:4:3:0.5 by weight, the nonmetallic precursor compounds
are preferably titanium oxide, aluminum oxide, vanadium oxide, and erbium
oxide for solid-phase reduction. The final oxygen content is controlled by the
reduction process as discussed subsequently. Nonmetallic precursor
compounds that serve as a source of more than one of the metals in the final
metallic article may also be used. These precursor compounds are furnished
and mixed together in the correct proportions such that the ratio of
titanium:aluminum:vanadium:erbium in the mixture of precursor compounds is
that required to form the metallic alloy in the final article.</p><p num="0022">A mixture of an initial metallic material and the dispersoid is produced, step
52. As part of the producing step 52, the single nonmetallic precursor
compound or the mixture of nonmetallic precursor compounds is chemically
reduced to produce the initial metallic material, without melting the initial
metallic particles. As used herein, "without melting", "no melting", and related
concepts mean that the material is not macroscopically or grossly melted for
an extended period of time, so that it liquefies and loses its shape. There
may be, for example, some minor amount of localized melting as low-melting-point
elements melt and are diffusionally alloyed with the higher-melting-point
elements that do not melt, or very brief melting for less than about 10
seconds. Even in such cases, the gross shape of the material remains</p><p num="0023">In one preferred reduction approach, termed vapor-phase reduction because
the nonmetallic precursor compounds are furnished as vapors or gaseous
phase, the chemical reduction may be performed by reducing mixtures of
halides of the base metal and the alloying elements using a liquid alkali metal
or a liquid alkaline earth metal. For example, titanium tetrachloride and the
halides of the alloying elements are provided as gases. A mixture of these
gases in appropriate amounts is contacted to molten sodium, so that the
metallic halides are reduced to the metallic form. The metallic alloy is
separated from the sodium. This reduction is performed at temperatures
below the melting point of the metallic alloy. The approach is described more
fully in US Patents 5,779,761 and 5,958,106. </p><p num="0024">Reduction at lower temperatures rather than higher temperatures is preferred.
Desirably, the reduction is performed at temperatures of 600°C or lower, and
preferably 500°C or lower. By comparison, prior approaches for preparing
specific metallic alloys often reach temperatures of 900°C or greater. The
lower-temperature reduction is more controllable, and also is less subject to
the introduction of contamination into the metallic alloy, which contamination
in turn may lead to chemical defects. Additionally, the lower temperatures
reduce the incidence of sintering together of the particles during the reduction
step.</p><p num="0025">In this vapor-phase reduction approach, a nonmetallic modifying element or
compound presented in a gaseous form may be mixed into the gaseous
nonmetallic precursor compound prior to its reaction with the liquid alkali
metal or the liquid alkaline earth metal. In one example, oxygen or nitrogen
may be mixed with the gaseous nonmetallic matrix precursor compound(s) to
increase the level of oxygen or nitrogen, respectively, in the initial metallic
material. It is sometimes desirable, for example in a titanium-base alloy, that
the oxygen content of the initial metallic particle and the final metallic article
be about 1200-2000 parts per million by weight to strengthen the final metallic
article or to provide oxygen that is used in forming the dispersoid. Rather
than adding the oxygen in the form of solid titanium dioxide powder, as is
sometimes practiced for titanium-base alloys produced by conventional
melting techniques, the oxygen is added in a gaseous form that facilitates
mixing and minimizes the likelihood of the formation of hard alpha phase in
the final article. When the oxygen is added in the form of titanium dioxide
powder in conventional melting practice, agglomerations of the powder may
not dissolve fully, leaving fine particles in the final metallic article that
constitute chemical defects. The present approach avoids that possibility.
For other alloy systems, lower oxygen, nitrogen, etc. content may also be
beneficial. Similarly, elements such as sulfur and carbon may be added using
appropriate gaseous compounds of these elements. Complex combinations
of such gaseous elements may be provided and mixed together, such as 
gaseous compounds of oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, and/or carbon, leading to the
formation of chemically more-complex dispersoids.</p><p num="0026">In another reduction approach, termed solid-phase reduction because the
nonmetallic matrix precursor compounds are furnished as solids, the chemical
reduction may be performed by fused salt electrolysis. Fused salt electrolysis
is a known technique that is described, for example, in published patent
application WO 99/64638. Briefly, in fused salt electrolysis the mixture of
nonmetallic matrix precursor compounds, furnished in a finely divided solid
form, is immersed in an electrolysis cell in a fused salt electrolyte such as a
chloride salt at a temperature below the melting temperature of the alloy that
forms from the nonmetallic matrix precursor compounds. The mixture of
nonmetallic matrix precursor compounds is made the cathode of the
electrolysis cell, with an inert anode. The elements combined with the metals
in the nonmetallic matrix precursor compounds, such as oxygen in the
preferred case of oxide nonmetallic matrix precursor compounds, are partially
or completely removed from the mixture by chemical reduction (i.e., the
reverse of chemical oxidation). The reaction is performed at an elevated
temperature. The cathodic potential is controlled to ensure that the reduction
of the nonmetallic matrix precursor compounds will occur, rather than other
possible chemical reactions such as the decomposition of the molten salt.
The electrolyte is a salt, preferably a salt that is more stable than the
equivalent salt of the metals being refined and ideally very stable to remove
the oxygen or other gas to a desired low level. The chlorides and mixtures of
chlorides of barium, calcium, cesium, lithium, strontium, and yttrium are
preferred. The chemical reduction is preferably, but not necessarily, carried
to completion, so that the nonmetallic matrix precursor compounds are
completely reduced. Not carrying the process to completion is a method to
control the oxygen content of the metal produced.</p><p num="0027">In another reduction approach, termed "rapid plasma quench" reduction, the
precursor compound such as titanium chloride is dissociated in a plasma arc
at a temperature of over 4500°C. The precursor compound is rapidly heated, 
dissociated, and quenched in hydrogen gas. The result is fine metallic-hydride
particles. Any melting of the metallic particles is very brief, on the
order of 10 seconds or less, and is within the scope of "without melting" and
the like as used herein. The hydrogen is subsequently removed from the
metallic-hydride particles by a vacuum heat treatment. Oxygen or other gas
(e.g., nitrogen) may also be added to react with the stable-dispersoid-forming
additive elements to form the stable dispersion.</p><p num="0028">The dispersoid 38 in the form of the dispersoid particles is introduced during
the producing step 52. The dispersoid 38 may be of any operable type. The
dispersoid 38 be furnished in its final form, or it may be furnished as a
precursor that is reacted to produce the final form of the dispersoid. The
selection of the dispersoid 38 is made in conjunction with the type of matrix
alloy and the requirements of the final article. Some examples of the
dispersoids may be oxides, carbides, nitrides, borides, or sulfides, or
combinations thereof, such as carbonitrides, formed with the elements of the
metallic matrix or with other intentionally added elements.</p><p num="0029">Four approaches for introducing the dispersoid 38 are of particular interest.
In a first approach, the dispersoids are furnished in essentially their final form
and are mixed with the matrix precursor compounds prior to or concurrently
with the step of chemically reducing. That is, the mixture of matrix precursor
compounds and dispersoids is given the chemical reduction treatment, but
only the matrix precursor compounds are actually reduced. The dispersoids
are selected to be either thermodynamically stable (non-reducible) compared
to the matrix alloy, or too chemically inert to be reduced by the process that
reduces the matrix precursor compounds. The dispersoid is introduced at a
point in the processing where it is stable with respect to all subsequent
processing steps.</p><p num="0030">In a second approach, the dispersoids are furnished but not subjected to the
chemical reduction treatment. Instead, they are mixed with the initial metallic
material that results from the chemical reduction step, but after the step of 
chemically reducing is complete. This approach is particularly effective when
the step of chemically reducing is performed on a flowing powder of the
matrix precursor compounds, but it also may be performed on a precompacted
mass of the matrix precursor compounds, resulting in a spongy
mass of the initial metallic material. The dispersoids 38 are received onto the
surface of the powder or on the surface of, and into the porosity of, the
spongy mass.</p><p num="0031">In a third approach, a dispersoid-precursor is furnished, rather than the final
precursor. The dispersoid precursor is mixed with the matrix precursor
compound prior to or concurrently with the step of chemically reducing. The
dispersoid precursor chemically reacts with another element or elements
during the step of chemically reacting to produce the dispersoid. For
example, the dispersoid-precursor could be an oxide former such as
magnesium, calcium, scandium, thorium, and yttrium, and rare earths such as
lanthanum, cerium, praseodymium, neodymium, promethium, samarium,
europium, gadolinium, terbium, dysprosium, holmium, erbium, thulium,
ytterbium, and lutetium, and mixtures thereof, which react with excess oxygen
during the chemical reduction to produce oxide dispersoids.</p><p num="0032">In a fourth approach, the matrix precursor is first produced as powder
particles, or as a sponge by compacting the precursor compounds of the
metallic elements. The particles or sponge is then first chemically reduced.
The dispersoid is thereafter produced at the surfaces (external and internal, if
the particles are spongelike) of the particles, or at the external and internal
surfaces of the sponge. In one approach, the particles or sponge is dipped
into a solution of a precursor compound of the dispersoid, such as an erbium
chloride solution, to coat the surfaces of the particles or the sponge. The
precursor compound of the dispersoid is second chemically reduced to
produce the first element of the dispersoid, such as erbium, at the surfaces of
the particles or at the surfaces of the sponge. The element of the dispersoid
is then chemically reacted (for example, oxidized) to produce the dispersoid,
erbium oxide in the example, distributed over the surfaces of the particles or 
the sponge. Upon the subsequent consolidation, discrete dispersoids are
distributed throughout the consolidated and compacted article. In some
cases the oxidation may be performed during or integral with the
consolidation process. The dispersoid may also be broken into smaller
pieces in the consolidation process and distributed further through the
metallic matrix.</p><p num="0033">Whatever the reduction technique used in step 52 and however the
dispersoid is introduced, the result is a mixture of an initial metallic material
and the dispersoid. The initial metallic material may be free-flowing particles
in some circumstances, or have a sponge-like structure in other cases. The
sponge-like structure is produced in the solid-phase reduction approach if the
matrix precursor compounds have first been compacted together prior the
commencement of the actual chemical reduction. The matrix precursor
compounds may be compressed to form a compressed mass that is larger in
dimensions than a desired final metallic article.</p><p num="0034">The mixture of the initial metallic material and the dispersoid is thereafter or
concurrently consolidated to produce a consolidated article, step 54, without
melting the initial metallic material, without melting the dispersoid, and without
melting the consolidated article. The consolidation step 54 may be performed
by any operable technique, with examples being hot isostatic pressing,
forging, pressing and sintering, and containerized extrusion.</p><p num="0035">It is preferred that there be no mechanical deformation of initial metallic
material and/or the mixture of the initial metallic material and the dispersoid,
prior to the step of consolidating. Such mechanical deformation is
unnecessary with the present approach, unlike the mechanical alloying
approach.</p><p num="0036">Figure 4 illustrates the microstructure of the metallic article 70 having a
surface 72 facing the environment 74. The metallic article 70 has a
microstructure of an alloy matrix 76 with unreacted stable-dispersoid-forming 
additive element(s) and/or the dispersoids dispersed generally uniformly
therethrough. The stable-dispersoid-forming additive element(s) may be
present in solid solution, numeral 78, or as one or more unreacted discrete
phases 80. (If the dispersoids are added in their final form, there will be little
or none of the unreacted element in solid solution 78 or the unreacted
discrete phases 80.) Some of the stable-dispersoid-forming additive
element(s) initially in solid solution may have been furnished as, or reacted
with oxygen initially present in the matrix 76 to form, a dispersion of fine
stable dispersoids 82. Some of the stable-dispersoid-forming additive
element(s) initially present as unreacted discrete phase 80 may have been
furnished as, or reacted with oxygen initially present in the matrix 76 to form,
a dispersion of coarse stable dispersoids 84. (As used herein, "coarse" and
"fine" are used only in a relative sense to each other, with "coarse"
dispersoids being larger in size than "fine" dispersoids. Both the coarse
stable dispersoids and the fine stable dispersoids provide strengthening
effects.) These stable dispersoids 82 and 84 are distributed substantially
uniformly throughout the matrix 76.</p><p num="0037">The primary embodiment of the present approach is therefore directed to the
formation of a substantially uniform distribution of dispersoids 38 in the matrix
34. The uniformity is microscopically judged quantitatively at a depth of more
than about 0.003 inches from the surface, in a square field of about 0.008
inches on a side. Mean spacings of the particles are measured in this field,
and compared with values in other fields at depths of more than about 0.003
inches from the surface, measured separately but in the same manner.
Desirably, the mean spacings of the particles are within about 25 percent,
more preferably about 10 percent, of each other in the different fields.</p><p num="0038">Optionally but typically, there is further processing, step 56, of the
consolidated article. In this processing, the article is not melted. Such further
processing may include, for example, mechanically forming the consolidated
article by any operable approach, machining the consolidated article by any
operable approach, coating the consolidated article by any operable 
approach, or heat treating the consolidated article by any operable approach.
These steps are selected according to the type of matrix and dispersoid, the
shape required, and the application. Such procedures are known generally in
the art.</p><p num="0039">In addition to the bulk-alloy improvements, some near-surface modification of
the metallic alloy is possible, in some alloy systems and for some dispersoids.
The result is a non-uniform distribution of dispersoids, in the near-surface
region. In one type of further processing 56 that produces such a non-uniform
distribution of dispersoids, the consolidated metallic article is exposed
to an oxygen-containing environment at a temperature greater than room
temperature, and preferably greater than about 500°F. If there is unreacted
stable-dispersoid-forming element 78 or 80 present in the material, the
oxygen exposure, leading to the types of nonuniform microstructure shown in
Figure 5, may be either during the initial preparation of the metallic article, in a
controlled production setting, or during later service exposure at elevated
temperature. In any of these cases, the oxygen diffuses inwardly from the
surface 72 into the matrix 76. The inwardly diffused oxygen chemically reacts
with the stable-dispersoid-forming additive element(s) that are present near
the surface 72 either in solid solution 78 or in discrete phases 80. The result
is that few if any unreacted stable-dispersoid-forming additive elements in
solid solution 78 or in discrete phases 80 remain near the surface 72, and
instead are all reacted to form, respectively, additional fine stable dispersoids
82 and coarse stable dispersoids 84. Consequently, there is a higher
concentration of fine stable dispersoids 82 in a diffusion-oxidation zone 86 of
depth D1 at and just below the surface 72, as compared with the
concentration of the fine stable dispersoids 82 at greater depths. D1 is
typically in the range of from about 0.001 to about 0.003 inches for titanium
alloys, but may be smaller or larger.</p><p num="0040">In some circumstances the stable dispersoids 82 and 84 have a higher
specific volume than the stable-dispersoid-forming additive elements from
which they are produced. This higher specific volume creates a compressive 
force, indicated by arrow 90, in the matrix 76 near the surface 72. The
compressive force 90 inhibits crack formation and growth when the article is
loaded in tension or torsion during service, a highly beneficial result.
Additionally, depending upon the specific dispersoid formed by the stable-dispersoid-forming
elements, there may be formed a stable surface layer 88,
that may serve as a diffusion barrier to the diffusion of oxygen and other
elements from the environment 74 into the article 40. Although this non-uniform
dispersoid structure is discussed in terms of the most-preferred case,
inward diffusion from the free surface 72 of the dispersion-forming element
oxygen, the same principles apply to inward diffusion of other dispersoid-forming
elements such as nitrogen, carbon, silicon, sulfur, boron, and other
dispersion-forming elements that are combinable with the metallic elements in
the matrix to form the dispersoid. The dispersion-forming element is
preferably supplied from a gaseous phase that contains the dispersion-forming
element in either combined or uncombined form, but it may also be
provided in some cases from a solid or liquid contacting the free surface 72.</p><p num="0041">This structure is to be distinguished from that shown in Figure 6, a
conventional titanium alloy article 100 that is outside the scope of the present
approach. In this case, during exposure to an oxygen-containing environment
during processing and/or service, oxygen diffuses from the environment 74,
through the surface 72, and into the base metal of the article 100 to a depth
D2, which is typically from about 0.003 to about 0.005 inch in titanium alloys.
In the instance of certain titanium alloys, for example, the excess oxygen
reacts with and embrittles the alpha-phase titanum in this region to form an
alpha case 102. In the present approach as illustrated in Figure 5, on the
other hand, the gettering of the inwardly diffusing oxygen by the stable-dispersoid-forming
additive elements and the stable surface layer 88
combined to reduce and, desirably, avoid the formation of such an oxygen-stabilized
alpha case.</p><p num="0042">The presence and the nature of the distribution of the stable dispersoids 82
and 84, in either a uniform or non-uniform distribution, has several additional 
important consequences. The stable dispersoids 82 and 84 serve to stiffen
the matrix 76 by the composite-stiffening effect, strengthen the matrix 76 by
the dispersion-strengthening effect and/or the composite strengthening effect,
and also improve the elevated-temperature creep strength of the matrix 76.
The stable dispersoids 82 and 84 may also pin grain boundaries of the matrix
76 to inhibit coarsening of the grain structure</p><p num="0043">When the dispersoid precursor approach is used and the dispersoid
precursor is a preferential oxygen getter, the dispersoids 38, 82, 84 in the
metallic matrix 34, 76 also remove oxygen (or other combinable element such
as nitrogen, carbon, boron, or sulfur) from the matrix 34, 76, regardless of
how the oxygen (or other combinable element) was introduced into the matrix
34, 76. Desirably, substantially all of the oxygen (or other combinable
element) is removed from solid solution. Too much oxygen (or other element)
in solid solution in the matrix 34, 76 may have adverse effects on the
properties of the initial metallic material and/or the consolidated article in
some cases. Removal of at least a portion of, and in some cases
substantially all of, the oxygen (or other combinable element) may also allow
other desirable alloying elements to be introduced into the matrix to a degree
greater than possible when a substantial oxygen (or other combinable
element) content is present in solid solution.</p><p num="0044">The present approach may be used to prepare a wide range of dispersion-strengthened
alloys, including without limitation nickel-base, iron-base, cobalt-base,
and aluminum-base alloys. These dispersion-strengthened alloys
include alloys similar in composition to those which can be produced by other
techniques such as mechanical alloying (but having the advantages over
mechanical alloying discussed herein, and alloys that cannot be prepared in
dispersion-strengthened form by other approaches. Some specific examples
include nickel-base alloys such as MA754, dispersion-strengthened
Rene™108, dispersion-strengthened Rene™125, and dispersion-strengthened
Alloy 718; iron-base alloys such as MA956 and dispersion-strengthened
A286; titanium-base alloys such as dispersion-strengthened Ti-6242; 
cobalt-base alloys such as dispersion-strengthened L605; and
aluminum-base alloys such as Al-9052, and Al-905XL; and dispersion
strengthened 7075. The present approach is not limited to these alloys,
which are presented as examples and not by way of limitation.</p><p num="0045">For compieteness, various aspects of the invention are set out in the following
numbered clauses:
<sl><li>1. A method of preparing an article (20) comprising a metallic matrix (34)
having its constituent elements and a dispersoid (38) distributed therein,
comprising the steps of :
<sl><li>furnishing at least one nonmetallic matrix precursor compound, all of
the nonmetallic matrix precursor compounds collectively including the
constituent elements of the metallic matrix (34) in their respective constituent-element
proportions; thereafter</li><li>producing a mixture of an initial metallic material and the dispersoid
(38), the step of producing including the step of:
<sl><li>chemically reducing the matrix precursor compounds to produce the
initial metallic material, without melting the initial metallic material; and</li><li>consolidating the mixture of the initial metallic material and the
dispersoid (38) to produce a consolidated article (20) having the dispersoid
(38) distributed in the metallic matrix (34) comprising the initial metallic
material, without melting the initial metallic material, without melting the
dispersoid (38), and without melting the consolidated article (20).</li></sl></li></sl></li><li>2. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of producing includes the
steps of:
<sl><li>furnishing the dispersoid (38), and</li><li>mixing the dispersoid (38) with the matrix precursor compounds prior to
or concurrently with the step of chemically reducing.</li></sl></li><li>3. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of producing includes the
steps of: <sl><li>furnishing the dispersoid (38), and</li><li>mixing the dispersoid (38) with the initial metallic material after the step
of chemically reducing.</li></sl></li><li>4. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of producing includes the
steps of:
<sl><li>furnishing a dispersoid-precursor, and</li><li>mixing the dispersoid precursor with the matrix precursor compound
prior to or concurrently with the step of chemically reducing, and wherein the
dispersoid precursor chemically reacts during the step of chemically reacting
to produce the dispersoid (38).</li></sl></li><li>5. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of producing includes the
steps of:
<sl><li>first chemically reducing the matrix precursor compounds to produce
the initial metallic material, without melting the initial metallic material,</li><li>introducing a precursor compound of the dispersoid (38) into the initial
metallic material,</li><li>second chemically reducing the precursor compound of the dispersoid
(38) to produce a first element of the dispersoid (38), and</li><li>chemically reacting the first element of the dispersoid (38) with a
second element of the dispersoid (38).</li></sl></li><li>6. The method of clause 1, wherein there is no mechanical deformation
of the initial metallic material prior to the step of consolidating.</li><li>7. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of furnishing at least one
nonmetallic matrix precursor compound includes the step of:
<sl><li>furnishing a compressed mass of the matrix precursor compounds.</li></sl></li><li>8. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of furnishing at least one
nonmetallic matrix precursor compound includes the step of:
<sl><li>furnishing a compressed mass of nonmetallic matrix precursor
compounds larger in dimensions than those of the consolidated article (20).</li></sl></li><li>9. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of chemically reducing
includes the step of:
<sl><li>producing a sponge of the initial metallic material.</li></sl></li><li>10. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of chemically reducing
includes the step of:
<sl><li>producing particles of the initial metallic material.</li></sl></li><li>11. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of chemically reducing
includes the step of:
<sl><li>chemically reducing the mixture of nonmetallic matrix precursor
compounds by solid-phase reduction.</li></sl></li><li>12. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of chemically reducing
includes the step of:
<sl><li>chemically reducing the compound mixture by vapor-phase reduction.</li></sl></li><li>13. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of consolidating includes the
step of:
<sl><li>consolidating the initial metallic material using a technique selected
from the group consisting of hot isostatic pressing, forging, pressing and
sintering, and containerized extrusion.</li></sl></li><li>14. The method of clause 1, including an additional step, after the step of
consolidating, of:
<sl><li>forming the consolidated article (20).</li></sl></li><li>15. The method of clause 1, including an additional step, after the step of
chemically reducing, of:
<sl><li>heat treating the consolidated article (20).</li></sl></li><li>16. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of producing includes the
step of:
<sl><li>producing the initial metallic material selected from the group
consisting of a nickel-base material, an iron-base material, a cobalt-base 
material, a titanium-base material, a magnesium-base material, and an
aluminum-base material.</li></sl></li><li>17. The method of clause 1, wherein the step of producing the mixture
includes the step of:
<sl><li>producing a dispersoid (38) including an element selected from the
group consisting of oxygen, carbon, nitrogen, boron, sulfur, and combinations
thereof.</li></sl></li><li>18. The method of clause 1, including an additional step, of:
<sl><li>exposing, at a temperature greater than room temperature, the
consolidated article (20) to an environment containing a dispersion-forming
element.</li></sl></li></sl></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method of preparing an article (20) comprising a metallic matrix (34)
having its constituent elements and a dispersoid (38) distributed therein,
comprising the steps of :
<claim-text><claim-text>furnishing at least one nonmetallic matrix precursor compound, all of
the nonmetallic matrix precursor compounds collectively including the
constituent elements of the metallic matrix (34) in their respective constituent-element
proportions; thereafter</claim-text><claim-text>producing a mixture of an initial metallic material and the dispersoid
(38), the step of producing including the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>chemically reducing the matrix precursor compounds to produce the
initial metallic material, without melting the initial metallic material; and</claim-text><claim-text>consolidating the mixture of the initial metallic material and the
dispersoid (38) to produce a consolidated article (20) having the dispersoid
(38) distributed in the metallic matrix (34) comprising the initial metallic
material, without melting the initial metallic material, without melting the
dispersoid (38), and without melting the consolidated article (20).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, wherein the step of producing includes the
steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>furnishing the dispersoid (38), and</claim-text><claim-text>mixing the dispersoid (38) with the matrix precursor compounds prior to
or concurrently with the step of chemically reducing.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, wherein the step of producing includes the
steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>furnishing the dispersoid (38), and</claim-text><claim-text>mixing the dispersoid (38) with the initial metallic material after the step
of chemically reducing.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, wherein the step of producing includes the
steps of:<claim-text><claim-text>furnishing a dispersoid-precursor, and</claim-text><claim-text>mixing the dispersoid precursor with the matrix precursor compound
prior to or concurrently with the step of chemically reducing, and wherein the
dispersoid precursor chemically reacts during the step of chemically reacting
to produce the dispersoid (38).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, wherein the step of producing includes the
steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>first chemically reducing the matrix precursor compounds to produce
the initial metallic material, without melting the initial metallic material,</claim-text><claim-text>introducing a precursor compound of the dispersoid (38) into the initial
metallic material,</claim-text><claim-text>second chemically reducing the precursor compound of the dispersoid
(38) to produce a first element of the dispersoid (38), and</claim-text><claim-text>chemically reacting the first element of the dispersoid (38) with a
second element of the dispersoid (38).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, wherein the step of furnishing at least one
nonmetallic matrix precursor compound includes the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>furnishing a compressed mass of the matrix precursor compounds.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, wherein the step of chemically reducing
includes the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>producing particles of the initial metallic material.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, wherein the step of chemically reducing
includes the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>chemically reducing the mixture of nonmetallic matrix precursor
compounds by solid-phase reduction.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, wherein the step of chemically reducing
includes the step of:
<claim-text><claim-text>chemically reducing the compound mixture by vapor-phase reduction.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, including an additional step, after the step of
chemically reducing, of:
<claim-text><claim-text>heat treating the consolidated article (20).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>