<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1136534-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1136534" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="24120451" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010926"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1136534-A1" status="new" fvid="23237715"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1136534</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010926</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01106832-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01106832</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010319</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-53212200-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>53212200</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000321</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B24B  37/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B24B  37/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09G   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09G   1/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09G   1/02</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Hybrid-Polieraufschlämmung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Hybrid polishing slurry</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new"  lang="FR">Boue de polissage hybride</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0842997-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0842997</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5997620-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5997620</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998023697-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998023697</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PRAXAIR TECHNOLOGY INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PRAXAIR S.T. TECHNOLOGY, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Praxair S.T. Technology, Inc.</last-name><address><street>441 Sackett Point Road</street><city>North Haven, CT 06473</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KNAPP JAMES KENT</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KWOK DORIS</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KNAPP, JAMES KENT</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KWOK, DORIS</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KNAPP, JAMES KENT</last-name><address><street>6251 N. County Road 250E</street><city>Pittsboro, Indiana 46167</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KWOK, DORIS</last-name><address><street>8931 Bradwell Place 205</street><city>Fischers, Indiana 46038</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Schwan - Schwan - Schorer</last-name><address><street>Patentanwälte European Patent Attorneys Elfenstrasse 32</street><city>81739 München</city><country>DE</country></address> </addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country> <country>FR</country> <country>GB</country> <country>IE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A hybrid slurry mixture that polishes substrates'
surfaces. The hybrid slurry includes, by weight
percent, 1 to 30 primary polishing particles, 1 to 50
dispersed colloidal particles, 1 to 40 oxidizer and
balance water. The primary polishing particles are
metal compounds selected from the group consisting of
oxides, nitrides, carbides and borides. The primary
polishing particles have a particle size from about 0.1
to 2 µm mean diameter. The dispersed colloidal
particles are at least one oxide selected from the
group consisting of alumina and silica. The dispersed
colloidal particles have a particle size from about 2
to 500nm mean diameter.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">Technical Field</u></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to the field of polishing
slurries. In particular, this invention relates to the
field of polishing slurries for producing smooth
surfaces for computer hard disks.</p><heading><u style="single">Background Art</u></heading><p num="0002">The typical manufacturing process for memory hard
disk media involves plating an aluminum disk substrate
with a layer of nickel phosphorus and polishing the
nickel alloy to obtain a smooth and flat surface. This
polished nickel alloy's surface is suitable for the
application of a hard disk's magnetic storage layer.
The computer industry's requirements for increased
storage capacity on hard disk drives has necessitated a
substantial increase in areal density, i.e., data
storage capacity per unit surface area, on the disk
media. This demand for hard disks with higher areal
densities has required several manufacturing
improvements that include enhanced plating uniformity,
reduced surface roughness after polishing and enhanced
texturing characteristics. The polishing process is an
important factor that influences many of these new
requirements.</p><p num="0003">In addition to these new manufacturing
requirements, significant improvements in surface
inspection methodology have allowed disk manufacturers
to inspect for smaller surface defects. This advanced
inspection technology has led to optimization of
polishing parameters such as polishing time, pressure
and revolution rate of a polishing machine's upper and
lower tables. Optimizing these parameters typically 
reduces surface defects that can occur during
polishing. This technique however requires a high
degree of expertise; and it is quite time consuming.
Other advances have been made in the area of
consumables: polishing pads, abrasive slurry, and
cleaning materials.</p><p num="0004">Although these techniques all reduce surface
defects, surfaces with various types of defects do
result in uneven plating of the magnetic layer. For
example, surface defects on the magnetic layer such as
nodules that reduce the clearance between the magnetic
head and the magnetic layer to less than 0.2 µm may
damage or even crush the magnetic head. Other defects
such as scratches and pits may result in errors in
reading or writing information on hard disks.</p><p num="0005">Manufacturers have experienced limited success
with eliminating errors that arise from conventional
aluminum oxide slurries. These high-tech slurries use
aluminum oxide of various surface area (5 to 50m<sup>2</sup>/g)
and size distribution (0.1 to 10 µm) as the polishing
agent. Unfortunately, these slurries' large particle
sizes cause micro-scratches, micro-pits and nodules on
nickel-plated substrates' surface. There are several
possible causes for these defects including: 1) the
grinding action of aluminum oxide on substrate surfaces
introduces polish scratches; 2) the accumulation of
unwanted wastes from the oxidized substrate and nickel
debris mixed with the water to reduce the effectiveness
of the injected polishing slurry; and 3) agglomeration
of the abraded debris in the pores of the polishing
pads scratches and pits the substrate's surface. In
view of all these factors, it is difficult for disk
manufacturers to achieve their required smooth surface, 
i.e., a roughness (peak-to-valley height) of less than
3Å or even 6Å with conventional alumina-based slurries.</p><p num="0006">Manufacturers have suggested that surface defects
form primarily during the nickel plating process. In
an attempt to correct these plating defects, most
proposed solutions have increased the polishing rate to
reduce or eliminate surface irregularities. For
example, chemical additives such as chelating agents
and oxidizers promote oxidation and accelerate the
polishing rate of slurries. Others have used smaller
or softer alumina-based abrasive particles to minimize
polish scratches on substrate surfaces.</p><p num="0007">These attempts for eliminating surface
irregularities have primarily focused on increasing the
rate of chemical etching and mechanical abrasion of the
nickel plated on the aluminum substrate, for example,
by applying a high polishing rate. It is however
necessary to increase the particle size of aluminum
oxide in order to provide sufficient mechanical
abrasion. Unfortunately, the use of large particles
also tends to roughen the polished surfaces. Thus, it
is often difficult, if not impossible, to achieve a
high polishing rate and low roughness simultaneously.
Other slurry manufacturers have used strong oxidizers
or accelerators in slurries to increase the oxidizing
rate of nickel plated on aluminum substrates. These
chemically aggressive slurries may, however, cause
pitting on the substrate surfaces and result in an
undesirable buildup of slurry and nickel debris in the
polishing pads. An excessive build up of unwanted
waste in polishing pads leads to: defects on substrate
surfaces; longer pad scraping between polishing cycles;
and reduced pad life. </p><p num="0008">Wang et al., in U.S. Pat. No. 5,693,239 disclose
the use of submicron alumina for chemical-mechanical
polishing. Okajima et al., in U.S. Pat. No. 4,956,015
combine α-alumina with boemite for improved polishing
removal rates. As far as known, these slurries lack
the combination of removal rate and performance
demanded by current disk manufacturers.</p><p num="0009">Furthermore, there have been other unsuccessful
attempts to prevent the formation of surface defects by
using smaller and softer conventional abrasives
powders; these slurries however, often form pits and
nodules due to their slow polishing rates. In
addition, prior attempts to polish nickel-plated
aluminum substrates include using a silica-only slurry.
For example, PCT Pat. Pub. No. 98/23697 discloses
polishing with slurries that contain 5 weight percent
silica. Similarly, U.S. Pat. No. 5,733,819 to Kodama
et al. discloses the use of fumed silica with malic
acid. Finally, Kodama et al., in U.S. Pat. No.
5,575,837, disclose a silica gel with a relatively
strong persulfate accelerator for increasing polishing
removal rates. Although these fumed silica processes
obtain a smooth surface, their polishing rate are too
slow for many commercial applications--even when adding
a large amount of oxidizers or accelerators to the
slurry. Furthermore, these slurries can become too
acidic for safe handling by operators on a daily basis.</p><p num="0010">It is an object of this invention to provide a
polishing slurry for producing flat-smooth surfaces.</p><p num="0011">It is a further object of this invention to
provide a polishing slurry for disk manufacturers to
achieve a surface roughness of less than 6Å. </p><p num="0012">It is a further object of this invention to
produce a smooth surface with removal rates analogous
to alumina-based slurries.</p><heading><u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0013">A hybrid slurry mixture that polishes substrates'
surfaces. The hybrid slurry includes, by weight
percent, 1 to 30 primary polishing particles, 1 to 50
dispersed colloidal particles, 1 to 40 oxidizer and
balance water. The primary polishing particles are
metal compounds selected from the group consisting of
oxides, nitrides, carbides and borides. The primary
polishing particles have a particle size from about 0.1
to 2 µm mean diameter. The dispersed colloidal
particles are at least one oxide selected from the
group consisting of alumina and silica. The dispersed
colloidal particles have a particle size from about 2
to 500nm mean diameter.</p><heading><u style="single">Detailed Description</u></heading><p num="0014">The present invention includes a hybrid polishing
composition containing a metal compound as the primary
polishing agent and a sol or gel of alumina or silica
as the secondary-polishing agent. Polishing with this
combination of primary polishing particles and
dispersed colloidal particles improves substrates'
surface characteristics and minimizes or eliminates all
surface defects. This hybrid polishing composition's
bimodal size distribution is most advantageous for
polishing rigid hard disks plated with nickel and
nickel alloys such as, nickel-phosphorus alloys. It
achieves a surface roughness of less than 3Å with
commercially acceptable nickel removal rates. This
hybrid slurry reduces the number of defective products 
and the cost of production. When using colloidal
silica, the nickel debris produced from the chemical
etching and the mechanical abrasion of the substrate
surface react or adsorb onto silica particles' surface.
Thus, since polishers continuously remove the silica as
a wash product, it also removes adsorbed nickel debris.
Therefore, this process unexpectedly reduces pad
scraping between polishing cycles and increases
production capacity.</p><p num="0015">Effective primary polishing particles include at
least one metal compound selected from the group of
oxides, nitrides, carbides and borides. In particular,
at least one metal oxides of silica, alumina, ceria,
zirconia, titania provide excellent polishing
performance. Most advantageously, the primary
polishing particles are alumina particles. In
particular, alumina particles predominately in the form
of an alpha crystal structure form the most effective
primary particles.</p><p num="0016">The primary particle concentration in the
polishing composition advantageously is in the range of
about 1 to 30 percent by weight, most advantageously,
about 5 to 25 percent by weight. The primary particles
have a particle diameter in the range of about 0.1 to
2.0 µm mean diameter. Advantageously, the primary
polishing particles have a particle diameter of about
0.1 to 1 µm mean diameter and most advantageously,
about 0.1 to 0.3 µm mean diameter. The surface area of
the primary polishing particles typically have a
surface area of about 4 to 100m<sup>2</sup>/g. Advantageously,
this has a surface area of about 5 to 60m<sup>2</sup>/g and most
advantageously, about 30 to 40m<sup>2</sup>/g for effective
polishing. </p><p num="0017">The dispersed colloidal particles advantageously
originate from a stable dispersion or sol of discrete
particles of at least one oxide selected from the group
consisting of alumina and silica. Most advantageously,
the dispersed particles are silica. Amorphous silica
forms a particularly effective colloidal dispersion.
These silica dispersions may originate from hydrolysis
of silicon compounds, neutralizing soluble silicates
with acids, electrodialysis, ion exchange, etc.</p><p num="0018">The colloidal dispersion typically has a particle
diameter in the range of about 2 to 500nm mean
diameter. Advantageously, it has a particle diameter
of about 10 to 200nm mean diameter. Most
advantageously, about 20 to 60nm mean diameter for
smooth polishing with acceptable removal rates. The
dispersed colloidal particle's surface area
advantageously falls within the range of about 60 to
about 250m<sup>2</sup>/g, most advantageously, about 65 to 90m<sup>2</sup>/g.
The sol or gel of alumina or silica has a solid
concentration in the range of about 1 to 50 percent by
weight-it's possible to add this component directly to
a polishing slurry under agitation. Advantageously,
the colloidal alumina or silica is in the range of
about 2 to 50 percent by weight and most advantageously
about 10 to 40 percent by weight.</p><p num="0019">The resulting slurry also contains a chemical
oxidizer, which accelerates the polishing removal rate.
Acceptable chemical accelerators include: nitric acid,
nickel nitrate, aluminum nitrate and magnesium nitrate.
Advantageously, the slurry contains about 1 to 40
weight percent oxidizer. Most advantageously, it
contains about 1 to 10 weight percent oxidizer.</p><p num="0020">The advantageous blending ratio of primary alumina
particles to colloidal silica particles is about 1-to-1 
to 1-to-5 by weight. Furthermore, a dilution ratio of
about three parts water to one part slurry
advantageously dilutes the slurry at the point-of-use.
Final solids content at the point-of-use most
advantageously ranges between about 5 and 15 percent by
weight, depending on the application.</p><p num="0021">Polishing with softer and smaller particle size
alumina-based slurries obtains smoother substrate
surfaces. Experimental data show that very fine
alumina slurries (0.05 to 0.3 µm mean diameter) achieve
a surface roughness of less than or equal to about
3.5Å.</p><heading>Example</heading><p num="0022">Nickel-phosphorus plated aluminum substrates of 95
mm outer diameters were polished with a slurry
consisting of three samples. Comparative Sample A
(alumina only) contained: 100g aluminum oxide, 33g
aluminum nitrate, 0.77g aluminum sulfate and 365g de-ionized
water. Comparative Sample B (silica only)
contained 100g silica, 62g aluminum nitrate and 108g
de-ionized water.</p><p num="0023">Sample 1 contained 100g aluminum oxide, 100g
silica, 33g aluminum nitrate, 0.77g aluminum sulfate
and 465g de-ionized water. Sample 2 contained: 100g
alumina, 450g silica, 33g aluminum nitrate, 0.77g
aluminum sulfate and 820g de-ionized water. The
alumina of Samples A, 1 and 2 had a particle size of
0.2 µm (mean diameter) and a surface area of 40m<sup>2</sup>/g.
The silica of Samples B, 1 and 2 had a particle size of
0.04 um (mean diameter) and a surface area of 70m<sup>2</sup>/g.
The polisher used was a Strasbaugh 6EE--an automatic
polisher that laps on both sides. The polisher had a
polyurethane-based polishing pad mounting on the upper 
and lower tables of the polishing machine. The
duration of the polishing cycle was 10 minutes by
mutually sliding the disks and the two polishing pads
under a net downforce of 80 g/cm<sup>2</sup> and by injecting
350ml/min of the above-mentioned slurry between the
disks and the polishing pads. Upon completion of the
polishing cycle, the disks were removed from the
polisher and cleaned in a Vtech disk cleaner to remove
any residual particles attached onto the surfaces of
the disk. The weight of the disk was measured, and the
average polishing rate was determined from the
reduction in weight. The roughness of the disk was
measured using a Veeco TMS 2000 laser scattering device
in which the surface measurements of 6000 points on the
disk were taken to compute the average disk roughness.
The surface of the disk was also inspected visually by
microscope for various types of surface defects. The
test results are shown in Table 1.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Table 1. Polishing Test Results</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Sample</entry><entry align="center">Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>: SiO<sub>2</sub> Weight</entry><entry align="center">Polishing rate µm/min/side</entry><entry align="center">Roughness Å</entry><entry align="center">Surface Defects</entry></row><row><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">1:0</entry><entry align="center">8.64</entry><entry align="center">3.4</entry><entry align="left">Micro-pits and micro scratches</entry></row><row><entry align="center">B</entry><entry align="center">0:1</entry><entry align="center">1.88</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="left">Orange-peel defects</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1:1</entry><entry align="center">8.64</entry><entry align="center">3.2</entry><entry align="left">Very few micro-pits, no scratches</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">1:5</entry><entry align="center">4.83</entry><entry align="center">2.4</entry><entry align="left">No pits or scratches</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0024">Hybrid Samples 1 and 2 had different water
dilution ratio at point-of-use. The dilution ratio of
Sample 2 was reduced to match the polishing rate of
Sample 1 in order to compare surface quality of disks
polished with these two samples. </p><p num="0025">The hybrid slurries readily produce flat-smooth
surfaces having a surface roughness of less than about
4Å. Furthermore, the hybrid slurries produce smooth
surfaces with removal rates analogous to alumina-based
slurries. For example, primary alumina/colloidal
silica slurries remove electrodeposited nickel-phosphorus
coatings at a rate of at least about 7.5
µm/min/side.</p><p num="0026">Although the invention has been described in
detail with reference to a certain preferred
embodiment, those skilled in the art will recognize
that there are other embodiments of the invention
within the spirit and the scope of the claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A hybrid slurry mixture for polishing
surfaces comprising by weight percent about 1 to 30
primary polishing particles, said primary polishing
particles being at least one metal compound selected
from the group consisting of oxides, nitrides, carbides
and borides and said primary polishing particles having
a particle size from about 0.1 to 2 µm mean diameter,
about 1 to 50 dispersed colloidal particles being at
least one oxide selected from the group consisting of
alumina and silica, said dispersed colloidal particles
having a particle size from about 2 to 500nm mean
diameter, about 1 to 40 oxidizer and balance water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The hybrid slurry mixture of claim 1 wherein
said primary polishing particles are alumina and said
dispersed colloidal particles are silica.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A hybrid slurry mixture for polishing
surfaces comprising by weight percent about 5 to 25
primary polishing particles, said primary polishing
particles being at least one oxide selected from the
group consisting of silica, alumina, ceria, zirconia
and titania, said primary polishing particles having a
particle size from about 0.1 to 1 µm mean diameter and
a surface area from about 4 to 100m2/g, about 2 to 50
dispersed colloidal particles, said dispersed colloidal
particles being at least one oxide selected from the
group consisting of alumina and silica, said dispersed
colloidal silica having a particle size from about 10
to 200nm mean diameter and a surface area from about 60
to 250m2/g, about 1 to 40 oxidizer and balance water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The hybrid slurry mixture of claim 3 wherein
said primary polishing particles are alumina.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The hybrid slurry mixture of claim 3 wherein
said dispersed colloidal particles are silica.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A hybrid slurry mixture for polishing
surfaces comprising by weight percent about 5 to 20
alumina polishing particles, said alumina polishing
particles having a particle size from about 0.1 to 0.3
µm mean diameter and a surface area from about 5 to
60m2/g, about 10 to 40 silica, said silica having a
particle size from about 20 to 60nm mean diameter and a
surface area from about 65 to 90m2/g, about 1 to 10
oxidizer and balance water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The hybrid slurry mixture of claim 6 wherein
said oxidizer is selected from the group consisting of
nitric acid, nickel nitrate, aluminum nitrate and
magnesium nitrate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The hybrid slurry mixture of claim 6 wherein
said alumina polishing particles have a surface area
from about 30 to 40m2/g.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The hybrid slurry mixture of claim 6 having a
ratio of said alumina to said silica of about 1 to 1 to
1 to 5 by weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The hybrid slurry mixture of claim 6 wherein the
slurry mixture removes electrodeposited nickel-phosphorus
coatings at a rate of at least about 7.5
µm/min/side and produces a finished surface roughness
of less than about 4Å.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>