<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1541218-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1541218" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34523015" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050615"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1541218-A1" status="new" fvid="24359293"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1541218</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050615</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04028959-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04028959</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20041207</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-73050503-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>73050503</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031208</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  53/28        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  53/28        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J   8/00        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J   8/00        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  19/00        20060101AFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  19/00        20060101CFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  19/02        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  19/02        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  20/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  20/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  20/30        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  20/32        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B  21/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B  21/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B  23/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B  23/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01C   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01C   1/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01D  53/28</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  20/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  20/32</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C01B  21/04D4D2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C01B  23/00D4D2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C01C   1/02P</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01B210:00T</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01B210:00W14</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Abtrennung von Wasser aus Ammoniak</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Process for removing water from ammonia</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Méthode pour l'élimination de l'eau dans l'amoniac</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-20020100366-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20020100366</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-20030094098-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20030094098</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4075306-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4075306</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000020330-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000020330</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199746 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class E37, AN 1997-501255 XP002257682 "Production of air-drying agent - comprises two stage impregnation of sorbent granules with solution of alkali or alkaline earth metal chlorides" &amp; RU 2 077 944 C (DZERZ ZARYA STOCK CO) 27 April 1997 (1997-04-27)</text><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>AIR PROD &amp; CHEM</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AIR PRODUCTS AND CHEMICALS, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>AIR PRODUCTS AND CHEMICALS, INC.</last-name><address><street>7201 Hamilton Boulevard</street><city>Allentown, PA 18195-1501</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHIANG ROBERT LING</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DONG CHUN CHRISTINE</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>RAO MADHUKAR BHASKARA</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WHITLEY ROGER DEAN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WU DING JUN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHIANG, ROBERT LING</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DONG, CHUN CHRISTINE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>RAO, MADHUKAR BHASKARA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WHITLEY, ROGER DEAN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WU, DING JUN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CHIANG, ROBERT LING</last-name><address><street>11 Governor Drive</street><city>Baskin Ridge, NJ 07920</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DONG, CHUN CHRISTINE</last-name><address><street>2288 Boulder Circle</street><city>Macungie, PA 18062</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>RAO, MADHUKAR BHASKARA</last-name><address><street>8782 Summit Circle</street><city>Fogelsville, PA 18051</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WHITLEY, ROGER DEAN</last-name><address><street>311 Hopewell Drive</street><city>Allentown, PA 18104-8501</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WU, DING JUN</last-name><address><street>5754 Fresh Meadow Drive</street><city>Macungie, PA 18062</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kador &amp;amp; Partner</last-name><address><street>Corneliusstrasse 15</street><city>80469 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IS</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LT</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>This invention relates to an improvement in a process for removing water from a
hydride gas, and particularly ammonia, by contacting the hydride gas with a drying agent
under conditions for effecting removal of the water. The improvement for significantly
reducing the water content to trace levels in said hydride gas resides in the use of at least
Group 1 metal oxide and at least one Group 2 metal oxide as a drying agent.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">Ultra-high purity ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>) is used in the electronics industry for integrated
circuit (IC) and light emitting diodes (LED) manufacturing. Water is one of the major
contaminants that must be removed to a concentration of 40 parts per billion (ppb) or
less. Even though such low concentrations of water can be achieved in the ammonia
manufacturing process, contamination is possible during subsequent shipping, handling,
or at the point of use. There is a need for a point-of-use purifier (for bulk streams) or
built-in purifier (for cylinders) including a drying agent to insure that water concentration
is at 40 ppb and generally less before being used.</p><p num="0002">There are a number of physical and chemical adsorption methods in the prior
art for removing water and other oxygen-containing impurities from hydride gases such
as ammonia and inert gases. The following patents and articles are representative of the
prior art.</p><p num="0003">US 5,536,302 teaches a process for removing trace levels of oxygen from an
inert gas, e.g., nitrogen and oxygen, via an adsorbent comprised of a porous reducing
support impregnated with an alkali metal oxide or alkaline earth metal oxide of about 10
to 90% by weight. The oxides are formed from metal salts, such as, nitrates, acetates,
benzoates, lactates, etc., the metals including cesium, sodium, potassium, and barium.</p><p num="0004">WO 97/06104 discloses a process for removing oxygen from ammonia via a
getter material comprised of metallic iron and manganese present in a weight ratio of 7:1
and 1:1. Moisture is removed downstream of the oxygen removal process, by contact
with a drying material. Examples of drying materials include barium oxide, calcium
oxide, strontium oxide, or 3A zeolites.</p><p num="0005">US 6,461,411 discloses a process for removing trace impurities, e.g., carbon
dioxide and water to ppb and ppt levels from matrix hydrides, inert gases, and non-reaction
gases including ammonia, phosphine, and arsine, etc., by contact with an
activated gas purifier comprised of thermally activated unmodified organic aluminas and 
thermally activated modified inorganic aluminas under an inert gas. Modified aluminas
are formed by treating the organic and inorganic aluminas with a basic salt such as
oxides, hydroxides, carbonates, acetates, or oxalates of Group IA or IIA metals.</p><p num="0006">US 6,241,955 discloses a method of removing gaseous contaminant, e.g.,
oxygen and water, from a hydride gas by contacting the gas stream with a quantity of
high surface area reduced metal oxide, which is in an oxidation state which is less than
its maximum and but not lower than its lowest oxidation state. Oxides such as
manganese or molybdenum oxides are preferred although oxides of barium, calcium,
iron, lithium, potassium, rhenium, sodium, strontium, titanium, tungsten, and vanadium
can also be used.</p><p num="0007">Japanese Patent 9-142833 discloses removal of water from ammonia by
contacting the gas with an adsorbent comprising BaO, or a mixture containing BaO and
CaO with BaO as the major compound, whereby water is removed through a chemical
reaction with the metal oxide.</p><p num="0008">EP 1,176,120 discloses a process for removing water and other impurities to a
level of less than 0.1 ppm from ammonia by contacting the ammonia with an adsorbent
having manganese oxide and/or nickel oxide as an active ingredient on a porous support
and thereafter with a zeolite. The adsorbent is prepared by reducing the metal oxide in
hydrogen at temperatures greater than 500°C for manganese and up to 350°C for nickel.
The ammonia may further be passed through a bed of synthetic zeolite with a pore
diameter between 4 to 10 angstroms to remove oxygen, carbon dioxide, and moisture.</p><p num="0009">EP 0 484,301 B1 and 0 470,936 B1 describe processes for removing oxygen
and other impurity gases from ammonia by the use of hydrogenated getter metal alloys
comprised of varying amounts of zirconium (Zr), vanadium (V) and iron (Fe) with a
preferred composition of 70% Zr, 24.6% V, and 5.4% Fe.</p><p num="0010">US 6,110,258 and US 6,395,070 disclose a method for removing water from a
gas, particularly acid gases by contacting the gas with a zeolite that has a silica to
alumina ratio above about 10. Prior to contact, the zeolite is heated to a temperature
above 650°C prior to contacting it with the gas.</p><p num="0011">US 4,983,363 describes an apparatus for removing water, oxygen and other
impurities from various gases such as arsine, phosphine, and ammonia by contact with a 
scavenger including a high surface area support with anions that are reactive towards
the impurities.</p><p num="0012">U.S. Patent 5,531,971 discloses a process for purifying gas streams such as
hydrogen, hydride gases, and nitrogen by contact with a pyrolyzed metal scavenger
deposited on a polymeric or macroreticulate polymer support. The pyrolyzed metals are
selected from Group IA of the Periodic Table.</p><p num="0013">Physical adsorption by zeolites such as A and X has also been widely used as a
means for removing water. These physical adsorbents are effective and have good
capacity for inert gas purification. However, their efficiency and capacity for water
removal from ammonia and other hydride gases are not sufficient. Accordingly, new
adsorbents for effecting the removal of water are desired.</p><heading>BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0014">This invention relates to an improvement in a process for removing water from a
hydride gases, particularly ammonia, and inert gas, and by contacting the hydride gas or
inert gas with a drying agent under conditions for effecting removal of the water. The
improvement for significantly reducing the water content to trace levels in said hydride or
inert gas resides in the use of at least one Group 1 metal oxide and at least one Group 2
metal oxide in their maximum oxidation state as a drying agent.</p><p num="0015">There are significant advantages which can be achieved by the practice of the
invention and representative advantages include:
<sl><li>an ability to scavenge water and carbon dioxide from ammonia and other hydride
gases to essentially nondetectable limits, e.g, down to 40 ppb and less; and,</li><li>an ability to use a scavenger having a very high affinity for water, high capacity,
and good water uptake kinetics at very low water partial pressures.</li></sl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0016">The basis for this invention is that it has been found that water can be removed
from hydride and inert gases, particularly ammonia, to trace levels by passing a gaseous
hydride or inert stream over a drying adsorbent comprising a mixture of at least one alkali
metal oxide and at least one alkaline earth metal oxide. As used herein, the term "trace"
levels of water refers to approximately 40 ppb or less of water. In cases where residual 
or trace levels of carbon dioxide are present, such carbon dioxide may also be removed
by the drying agent. These adsorbents often are incorporated into point-of-use purifiers
and built-in-purifiers to remove contaminant water as desired.</p><p num="0017">Typically, hydride gases and inert gases are delivered to adsorbent systems
having a water content of 500 parts per million (ppm), generally 100 ppm and less. In
the initial process for preparing the gases for delivery, the water content is reduced by
cryogenic means or by use of zeolites adsorbents. Many applications, particularly in the
electronics industry, require water levels in hydride gases in the range of ppb level, e.g.,
below 40 ppb (detection limit), and the lower the better. Although a number of drying
adsorbents can reduce the water content of a hydride gas to levels of 40 ppb and below,
they often do not have sufficient capacity at these low water partial pressures to be
suitable for applications such as in-line and bulk purification.</p><p num="0018">The drying adsorbent employed in the practice of this invention is comprised of
a mixture of an alkali metal oxide and an alkaline earth metal oxide. The alkali metal
oxide can be comprised of lithium oxide, sodium oxide, potassium oxide, cesium oxide,
and the alkaline earth metal oxide can be comprised of magnesium oxide, calcium oxide,
barium oxide, and strontium oxide. Other metal oxides can be included in combination
with the drying agent as desired and these include manganese oxide, nickel oxide, and
iron oxide.</p><p num="0019">The mixed metal oxides comprised of a Group 1 and Group 2 metal oxide, as
the drying adsorbent, are carried on an inert support by first impregnating the support
with a combination of an aqueous or non-aqueous solution of the corresponding metal
salts. Examples of appropriate salts of the metals are nitrates, oxalates, benzoates,
lactates, tartrates, acetates, succinates, and formates. Although water is preferred, other
solvents can be used for dissolution of the metal salt and these include methanol,
ethanol, acetone, or ether. Impregnation of the support with aqueous salts can be
accomplished using methods well known in the art, for example, incipient wetness, spray
impregnation, and thermal spontaneous dispersion.</p><p num="0020">The impregnation of the support is effected in a manner to achieve a weight
loading of the mixed metal oxides based upon the combined weight of the support and
mixed metal oxides is about 10 to about 90% by weight and from 30 to 40% by weight is
preferred. The use of a support allows for an increased surface area for the drying agent
and affords better contact with trace levels of water present in the gas. </p><p num="0021">Following impregnation, the support-salt combination is dried at approximately
50°C to 120°C. for approximately 2 to 16 hours. Then, the dried impregnated support is
activated by heating it under flowing gas, e.g., air to a temperature of about 200°C to
600°C, typically 400 to 550 °C, which decomposes the salt to the corresponding oxide.
Residence time of the flowing oxidizing gas during activation, depending upon the
activation temperature, is approximately 0.5 to 30 seconds; preferably 10 seconds.
Successful decomposition of the metal salt to the oxide is ensured by holding the
composite material at or above the decomposition temperature of the metal salt for at
least about 1 hour. If complete oxidation of the respective metal is not effected, the
metal, in its reduced state, may react with trace levels of oxygen which may be present in
the hydride or inert gas and generate contaminant water.</p><p num="0022">The mixed metal oxides are employed in ratios to provide from 0.1 to 10 moles
Group 1 alkali metal oxide per mole of Group 2 alkaline earth metal oxide. Preferably,
the moles ratio of alkali metal per mole of alkaline earth metal oxide is from about 0.3 to
5. Specific alkali/alkaline earth metal oxide combinations are as follows; K<sub>2</sub>O/MgO
K<sub>2</sub>O/BaO Na<sub>2</sub>O/MgO Na<sub>2</sub>O/BaO, Cs<sub>2</sub>O/MgO, Cs<sub>2</sub>O/BaO, Li<sub>2</sub>O/MgO and Li<sub>2</sub>O/BaO.</p><p num="0023">The support for carrying the mixed metal oxides is a substrate having a plurality
of pores and a surface area that ranges from about 100 to about 1500 m<sup>2</sup>/g. Examples of
supports are titania, alumina, zeolites. The preferred support is alumina.</p><p num="0024">Drying of the hydride or inert gas is effected by passing the gas over the oxide
impregnated support, preferably at ambient temperature (approximately 20°C). The
pressure can range from about 1 to about 10 atmospheres; preferably 5 atmospheres.
When the drying adsorbent becomes saturated, the drying adsorbent is replaced and the
process continued.</p><p num="0025">The following examples are provided to illustrate various embodiments of the
invention and are not intended to restrict the scope thereof.</p><heading>General Procedure:</heading> <p num="0026">Two methods were used to evaluate the effectiveness of the test adsorbents. In
the parallel method, a bed was packed with a test adsorbent and another bed filled with
a commercial adsorbent. The bed filled with commercial adsorbent was sized such that
it was not capacity limited. Flow of gas was fed to either bed at identical flow rates. The
trace water content of the test bed was measured against the trace water content of the 
bed filled with commercial adsorbent. The difference in measured water content was
indicative of the effectiveness of the test adsorbent in removing water.</p><p num="0027">The second method is characterized as the series method wherein the test gas
was passed through the test bed first, and then, the treated gas from the test bed passed
through the bed filled with commercial adsorbent and the trace water content measured.
The series method, although similar to the first in principle, allows for some water
absorption/desorption in pipes and is not a direct comparison to the first method.
However, it is deemed quite suitable for comparison. This method was used to compare
water removal with BaO alone as a single metal oxide.</p><heading><i>Specific Breakthrough Test Process and Operating Condition</i></heading><p num="0028"><u style="single">Process configuration:</u> The test runs were generally carried out to breakthrough
in an effort to gain information as to capacity, adsorption kinetics, and so forth. The test
bed had a dimension of 0.85 cm inner diameter and 5 cm length. The empty space
inside the vessel was filled with glass beads. The amount of media packed into the
vessel for each adsorbent is listed in Table 1. The bed filled with the commercial
adsorbent had a dimension of 1.5" diameter and 4.5" long.</p> <p num="0029"><u style="single">Feed:</u> A mixture of N<sub>2</sub> (7.5 vol%) and high-purity NH<sub>3</sub> with a H<sub>2</sub>O content of 200
ppb (92.5 vol%) was used as the feed for the breakthrough tests. The N<sub>2</sub> was from a
moisture generator and the H<sub>2</sub>O concentration in the mixture was relatively stable at 1.8
ppm.</p> <p num="0030"><u style="single">Operating condition:</u> The water/ammonia mixture was passed through the test
bed at a flow rate of 250 sccm. In the parallel method, the mixture was periodically
shifted through the bed filled with the commercial adsorbent to obtain a reference H<sub>2</sub>O
reading. The experiments were conducted under 84 psig and at ambient temperature
(about 25°C).</p> <p num="0031"><u style="single">Analytical instrumentation:</u> A MKS FTIR was used for H<sub>2</sub>O analysis. It has a
method detection limit (MDL) of 40 ppb. Due to continuous downstream system drying
and ambient temperature fluctuations, the H<sub>2</sub>O reading from FTIR can shift by
approximately 50 ppb. To mitigate the temperature dependence, the H<sub>2</sub>O reading from
the bed filled with the commercial adsorbent was used as the reference. </p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0032">Preparation of Adsorbent Samples</p><p num="0033">Several adsorbents were synthesized and tested for their effectiveness in
removing water from NH<sub>3</sub> per the general procedure. The following adsorbents were
prepared in accordance with described procedure.</p><p num="0034"><u style="single">4A Molecular Sieve (comparative):</u> The as-received commercial 4A molecular
sieve had a particle size of about 2 mm in diameter and 5 mm in length. Prior to
breakthrough test, the molecular sieve was ground to 16-20 mesh inside a glove box.
TGA analysis indicated the ground adsorbent had 0.3% residual water.</p><p num="0035"><u style="single">5A Molecular Sieve (comparative):</u> A 5A molecular sieve sample was prepared
in conventional manner by activating it at 400°C. TGA analysis indicates that it had
1.12% residual water. The material was ground to 16-20 mesh inside a glove box after
activation.</p><p num="0036"><u style="single">BaO/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></u> (comparative): A sample of BaO/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> was prepared by dissolving
76.4 g (~100 cc) AA300 (Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> from Alcan) into a 50 cc Ba(NO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub> solution (0.3 g
Ba(NO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O per cc H<sub>2</sub>O). The solution was mixed well, then, the extra solution was
decanted, and the adsorbent was dried at room temperature in a hood for overnight.
The test sample then was ground to 16-20 mesh. 1.050 g sample of the ground
Ba(NO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> was loaded into the test bed. The test bed was purged with nitrogen at a
flow rate of 1 slpm. The test bed was heated at 100°C for 24 hrs and at 300°C for
another 24 hrs. The BaO loading was estimated to be about 0.5 mmole/g of test
adsorbent or 7 wt%.</p><p num="0037"><u style="single">M<sub>g</sub>O-K<sub>2</sub>O/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>:</u> A sample of MgO-K<sub>2</sub>O/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> was prepared by depositing an
aqueous solution of magnesium acetate tetrahydrate (Mg(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>3</sub>O<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>, ACS grade) and
potassium acetate (KC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>3</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, ACS grade) on Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>. The sample was dried and the
dried, impregnated Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> was ground to 16-20 mesh. The ground material was calcined
at 550°C for 4 hours in zero air (substantially free of water and carbon dioxide). The
sample had a MgO loading of 0.4 mmole/g or 1.6 wt% and a K<sub>2</sub>O loading of 1.0 mmole/g
or 9.1 wt% of the adsorbent. </p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0038">Evaluation of Test Adsorbents</p><p num="0039">The test samples were evaluated for their effectiveness in the removal of water
from ammonia per the general procedure as indicated. The results of the evaluation are
reported in Tables 1-5.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Water Removal Capacity and Efficiency for Test Adsorbents</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Adsorbent</entry><entry align="center">Amount of adsorbent packed (g)</entry><entry align="center">H<sub>2</sub>O capacity (mmole/g)</entry><entry align="center">H<sub>2</sub>O efficiency (ppb)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4A</entry><entry align="center">0.519</entry><entry align="center">0.21</entry><entry align="center">&lt;MDL</entry></row><row><entry align="left">5A</entry><entry align="center">0.539</entry><entry align="center">0.18</entry><entry align="center">&lt;MDL</entry></row><row><entry align="left">BaO/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.712</entry><entry align="center">0.35</entry><entry align="center">&lt;MDL</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MgO-K<sub>2</sub>O/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.514</entry><entry align="center">&gt;0.36</entry><entry align="center">&lt;MDL</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Water Concentrations during 4A Adsorbent Breakthrough Test</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Accumulated time (hrs)</entry><entry align="center">H<sub>2</sub>O (ppb) when passing thru test bed</entry><entry align="center">H<sub>2</sub>O (ppb) when passing thru commercial adsorbent</entry><entry align="center">Difference in H<sub>2</sub>O concentration (ppb)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">15.2</entry><entry align="center">14</entry><entry align="center">-1</entry><entry align="center">15</entry></row><row><entry align="center">63.2</entry><entry align="center">31</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">86.7</entry><entry align="center">41</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">36</entry></row><row><entry align="center">94.6</entry><entry align="center">67</entry><entry align="center">-2</entry><entry align="center">69<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Water Concentrations For During 5A Adsorbent Breakthrough Test</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Accumulated time (hrs)</entry><entry align="center">H<sub>2</sub>O (ppb) when passing thru test bed</entry><entry align="center">H<sub>2</sub>O (ppb) when passing thru commercial adsorbent</entry><entry align="center">Difference in H<sub>2</sub>O concentration (ppb)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">64.6</entry><entry align="center">51</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">16</entry></row><row><entry align="center">88</entry><entry align="center">56</entry><entry align="center">-5</entry><entry align="center">61<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Water Concentrations For BaO/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> Adsorbent Breakthrough Test</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Accumulated time (hrs)</entry><entry align="center">H2O (ppb) when passing thru test bed</entry><entry align="center">H2O (ppb) when thru commercial adsorbent</entry><entry align="center">Difference in H2O concentration (ppb)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">50.5</entry><entry align="center">22</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">20</entry></row><row><entry align="center">87.5</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">-2</entry><entry align="center">14</entry></row><row><entry align="center">95.2</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">19</entry><entry align="center">16</entry></row><row><entry align="center">111.7</entry><entry align="center">51</entry><entry align="center">37</entry><entry align="center">14</entry></row><row><entry align="center">135.5</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">159.6</entry><entry align="center">-15</entry><entry align="center">-23</entry><entry align="center">8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">231.7</entry><entry align="center">157</entry><entry align="center">-24</entry><entry align="center">181</entry></row><row><entry>* start breakthrough</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Water Concentrations during MgO-K<sub>2</sub>O/ Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> Adsorbent Breakthrough Test</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Accumulated time (hrs)</entry><entry align="center">H<sub>2</sub>O (ppb) when passing thru test bed</entry><entry align="center">H<sub>2</sub>O (ppb) when passing thru commercial adsorbent</entry><entry align="center">Difference in H<sub>2</sub>O concentration (ppb)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">14.8</entry><entry align="center">-30</entry><entry align="center">-35</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">22.8</entry><entry align="center">-29</entry><entry align="center">-33</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="center">38.8</entry><entry align="center">-31</entry><entry align="center">-32</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">62.9</entry><entry align="center">-28</entry><entry align="center">-30</entry><entry align="center">2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">71.1</entry><entry align="center">-12</entry><entry align="center">-6</entry><entry align="center">-6</entry></row><row><entry align="center">97.4</entry><entry align="center">-20</entry><entry align="center">-20</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">134.3</entry><entry align="center">-37</entry><entry align="center">-34</entry><entry align="center">-3</entry></row><row><entry align="center">158.6</entry><entry align="center">-31</entry><entry align="center">-29</entry><entry align="center">-2</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0040">The results in the above tables show that all the adsorbents could remove H<sub>2</sub>O
to a level approaching or below the detection limit of the FTIR (40 ppb). The following
comments are relative to the tables.</p><p num="0041">Table 1 shows a summary of the capacity for the test adsorbents at a threshold
level 40 ppb water. The results indicate that the adsorbent employing the mixed oxides,
i.e., K<sub>2</sub>O/MgO, had the highest capacity in millimoles water removed per gram adsorbent
of all tested adsorbents. Given the same residence time for all tests, the reaction
kinetics are equally as good as the prior art comparative adsorbents.</p><p num="0042">Table 2 shows the H<sub>2</sub>O breakthrough and H<sub>2</sub>O removal efficiency data for a 4A
adsorbent. It was able to remove H<sub>2</sub>O to a level similar to that of the commercial 
adsorbent. But, its capacity at the 40 ppb threshold level was the lowest among the
tested adsorbents.</p><p num="0043">Table 3 shows the H<sub>2</sub>O breakthrough and H<sub>2</sub>O removal efficiency data for the
5A adsorbent. Since the stream was not passed through the commercial adsorbent
during the first 65 hrs of the breakthrough test, it cannot be concluded whether the
adsorbent could remove H<sub>2</sub>O to a level lower than that of the commercial adsorbent.
However, because the difference was only 16 ppb at the 65<sup>th</sup> hr of the breakthrough test,
it is highly likely that the 5A adsorbent should be able to remove H<sub>2</sub>O to a level below the
FTIR detection limit.</p><p num="0044">Table 4 shows the H<sub>2</sub>O breakthrough and H<sub>2</sub>O removal efficiency for the
BaO/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> adsorbent. The BaO/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> adsorbent was able to achieve water levels
comparable to that of the commercial adsorbent and it had a capacity higher than that 4A
and 5A molecular sieves.</p><p num="0045">Table 5 shows the H<sub>2</sub>O breakthrough and H<sub>2</sub>O removal efficiency data
respectively for MgO-K<sub>2</sub>O/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>. Over the course of the runs, as shown in Table 1, the
MgO-K<sub>2</sub>O/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> had adsorbed 0.36 mmole/g and the experiment had not reached
breakthrough. Comparing against all adsorbents tested, the drying agent comprised of
the mixed metal oxides achieved water levels similar, and possibly below to the
commercial adsorbent, and it had a capacity higher than either molecular sieve, i.e., 4A
and 5A.</p><p num="0046">Summarizing the data and results from the tables, traditional water removal has
been conducted by numerous methods, as evidenced by the adsorbents reported in
Tables 2-3, including distillation and adsorption. Removal of water where the feed
concentration oftne is in the 100 ppb range to levels below 40 ppb is difficult. To achieve
meaningful capacity at these low partial pressures of water has been a major obstacle in
drying by use of adsorbents. The breakthrough experiments as illustrated in Table 5 has
shown that a combination of mixed Group 1 and 2 metal oxides have a much higher
capacity for water than these other systems at these low partil pressures of water. In
addition, they have the capability to reduce the water level in ammonia to levels below
the limits of detection, i.e., 40 ppb.</p><p num="0047">Although not intending to be bound by theory, it is believed the combination of
an adsorbent with a relatively strong chemical reactivity and another adsorbent with a
relatively strong physical adsorption force can improve the drying efficiency and capacity 
of the adsorbent in hydride gases and inert gases. Comparing the two groups of metal
oxides, the belief is that Group 1 metal oxides are stronger in chemical reaction with
water due to the low valance of the metal ions, which allows forming a tight chemical
bond between water and metal oxides especially at a very low water partial pressure;
while the Group 2 metal oxides have a stronger attraction force to water molecules due
to a relatively high ionic charge of the metal ion, which provides a higher chance of
achieving contact of the water molecules with adsorbent surface. When a Group 1 metal
oxide is used alone as an adsorbent, at the water partial pressure range of our interest,
the limiting step of water removal is in effecting contact of the gas phase water
molecules with the metal oxide. On the other hand, if only a Group 2 metal oxide is
present in the adsorbent, the water removal at an extremely low water partial pressure is
limited by the relatively low chemical reactivity of the metal oxide. Without form ing a tight
chemical bond, the physically adsorbed water can desorb automatically, resulting in a
low equilibrium adsorption capacity. Therefore, it is our observation that the combination
of Group 1 with Group 2 metal oxides increases the drying efficiency and capacity for
hydride gases at the water partial pressure range of interest.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>In a process for removing water from a hydride or inert gas which
comprises contacting said hydride or inert gas stream with an effective quantity of a
drying agent under conditions for effecting adsorption of said water, the improvement
which comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>utilizing a mixture of metal oxides comprised of at least one Group 1 metal oxide
and at least one Group 2 metal oxide as a drying agent.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method of Claim 1 where the mixture of metal oxides are dispersed on
a porous support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method of Claim 2 wherein the Group 1 alkali metal oxide is selected
from the group consisting of sodium, potassium, lithium and cesium oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method of Claim 3 wherein the Group 2 metal oxide is selected from
the group consisting of calcium, magnesium, strontium, and barium oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method of claim 4 wherein the porous support has a surface area of at
least 100 meters squared/gram.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method Claim 5 wherein the support is alumina.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method of Claim 4 wherein the activation temperature for forming the
metal oxides is from 200 to 600 °C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method of Claim 4 wherein the drying agent is selected from the group
consisting of K2O/MgO and Cs2O/MgO.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method of Claim 4 wherein the mole ratio is from 0.1 to 10 moles of
Group 1 alkali metal oxide to Group 2 alkaline earth metal oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method of Claim 9 wherein the mole ratio is from 0.3 to 5 moles of
Group 1 alkali metal oxide to Group 2 alkaline earth metal oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The method of Claim 10 wherein the loading of mixed metal oxides is from
10 to 90 % by weight of the combined support and metal oxide</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The method of Claim 10 wherein the loading of mixed metal oxides is from
30 to 40 % by weight of the combined support and metal oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>In a process for removing water from ammonia which comprises
contacting said hydride or inert gas stream with an effective quantity of a drying agent
under conditions for effecting adsorption of said water, the improvement for removing
water from said ammonia, said water content of not greater than 500 ppm which
comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>utilizing a mixture of metal oxides comprised of at least one Group 1 metal oxide
and at least one Group 2 metal oxide as a drying agent.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The method of Claim 13 where the mixture of metal oxides are dispersed
on a porous support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The method of Claim 14 wherein the Group 1 alkali metal oxide is selected
from the group consisting of sodium, potassium, lithium and cesium oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The method of Claim 15 wherein the Group 2 metal oxide is selected from
the group consisting of calcium, magnesium, strontium, and barium oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The method of Claim 16 wherein the mole ratio is from 0.1 to 10 moles of
Group 1 alkali metal oxide to Group 2 alkaline earth metal oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The method of Claim 17 wherein the mixed metal oxides are selected from
the group consisting of K2O/MgO K2O/BaO Na2O/MgO, Na2O/BaO, Cs2O/MgO,
Cs2O/BaO, Li2O/MgO and Li2O/BaO.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The method of Claim 18 wherein the drying agent is selected from the
group consisting of K2O/MgO and Cs2O/MgO.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>