<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2000000634-A2" country="WO" doc-number="2000000634" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="22316366" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20000106"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2000000634-A2" status="new" fvid="77360850"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000000634</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20000106</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-9904490-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>9904490</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>19990629</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-10738398-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>10738398</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19980630</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>C12Q   1/00</main-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  39/106       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  39/106       20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  45/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  45/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  31/00        20060101C I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  31/04        20060101A I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  14/195       20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  14/205       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  16/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  16/12        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  16/40        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  16/40        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   1/21        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   1/21        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   9/78        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   9/80        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12P  21/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12P  21/08        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/18        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/58        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/58        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12R   1/01        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07K  16/12A12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C12Q   1/18</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C12Q   1/58</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">S01N333:205</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">METHODS OF INHIBITING HELICOBACTER PYLORI</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">PROCEDES SERVANT A INHIBER HELICOBACTER PYLORI</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-5942409-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5942409</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="E" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1993007273-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1993007273</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1994026901-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1994026901</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>D R SCOTT, D WEEKS, C HONG, S POSTIUS, K MELCHERS, G SACHS: "The role of internal urease in acid resistance of Helicobacter pylori" GASTROENTEROLOGY, vol. 114, January 1998 (1998-01), pages 58-70, XP000863566 cited in the application</text><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>J K AKADA, M SHIRAI, H TAKEUCHI, M TSUDA, T NAKAZAWA: "Transcriptional analysis of urease structural gene and the ureI gene in Helicobacter pylori" GUT, vol. 41, 1997, page A9 XP000863597 cited in the application</text><sources><source category="AD"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>M CLYNE, A LABIGNE, B DRUMM: "Helicobacter pylori Requires an Acidic Environment To Survive in the Presence of Urea" INFECTION AND IMMUNITY, vol. 63, no. 5, May 1995 (1995-05), pages 1669-1673, XP002125711 cited in the application</text><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>S SKOULOUBRIS, J-M THIBERGE, A LABIGNE, H DE REUSE: "The Helicobacter pylori UreI Protein Is Not Involved in Urease Activity but Is Essential for Bacterial Survival In Vivo" INFECTION AND IMMUNITY, vol. 66, no. 9, September 1998 (1998-09), pages 4517-4521, XP002125710 cited in the application</text><sources><source category="XPD" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>CUSSAC VALERIE</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>LABIGNE AGNES</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PASTEUR INSTITUT</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>REUSE HILDE DE</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SKOULOUBRIS STEPHANE</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CUSSAC, VALERIE</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DE REUSE, HILDE</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>INSTITUT PASTEUR</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LABIGNE, AGNES</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SKOULOUBRIS, STEPHANE</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CUSSAC VALERIE</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DE REUSE HILDE</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LABIGNE AGNES</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SKOULOUBRIS STEPHANE</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CUSSAC, VALERIE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DE REUSE, HILDE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LABIGNE, AGNES</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SKOULOUBRIS, STEPHANE</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data> <abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>This invention relates to methods of screening molecules capable of inhibiting the survival of Helicobacter pylori in vivo by specifically inhibiting the activity of UreI, to the molecules identified by these methods, and to the use of these molecules to treat or prevent H. pylori infection.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>L'invention concerne des procédés servant à cribler des molécules capables d'inhiber la survie d'Helicobacter pylori in vivo par inhibition spécifique de l'activité d'UreI, les molécules identifiées au moyen de ces procédés, ainsi que l'utilisation de ces molécules afin de traiter ou de prévenir l'infection par H. pylori.</p></abstract><description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>--><p num="p0001"> METHODS OF LNHIBITLNG HELICOBACTER PYLORI</p> <p num="p0002">This invention relates to methods of screening molecules capable of inhibiting the survival of Helicobacier. particularly Helicobacter pylori, in vivo by specifically inhibiting the activity of Urel, to the molecules identified by these methods, and to the use of these molecules to treat or prevent Helicobacter infection.</p> <p num="p0003">BACKGROUND OF INVENTION</p> <p num="p0004">Helicobacter pylori is a microaerophilic Gram-negative bacterium, which colonizes the gastric mucosa of humans (10). H. pylori is associated with gastritis and peptic ulcer disease and has been shown to increase the risk of gastric cancers. Urease is a major virulence factor of H. pylori. It is involved in neutralizing the acidic microenvironment of the bacterium and also plays a role in H. pylori metabolism (11, 26).</p><p num="p0005">The urease region of the H. pylori genome is composed of two gene clusters common to all strains (9 and Figure 1), one comprising the ureAB genes encoding the structural urease subunits and the other containing the ureEFGH genes encoding the accessory proteins required for nickel incorporation into the urease active site. The urel gene lies immediately upstream from this latter gene cluster and is transcribed in the same direction (Figure 1). The ureA, ureB, ureE. ureF, ureG. ureH, and urel genes and gene products have been described and claimed in United States Patent 5,695,931 and allowed patent application Serial No. 08/472,285. both of which are specifically incorporated herein by reference.</p><p num="p0006">The distances separating urel from ureE (one base pair, bp) and ureE from ureF (11 bp) suggest that urel-ureE-ureF constitute an operon. Cotranscription of urel and ureE has been demonstrated by northern blot analysis (1). An H. pylori N6 mutant with a urel gene disrupted by a MiniTn -Km transposon was previously described by Ferrero et al. (1994) (13). This strain (N6-z/re/::TnKm-8) presented a urease negative phenotype, so it was concluded that urel was an accessory gene required for full urease activity.</p><p num="p0007">The sequences of Urel from H. pylori and the AmiS proteins, encoded by the aliphatic amidase operons of Pseudomonαs αeruginosα and Rhodococcus sp. R312, are similar (5, 27). Aliphatic amidases catalyze the intracellular hydrolysis of short-chain aliphatic amides to produce the corresponding organic acid and ammonia. It has been shown</p><p num="p0008">C0NRR ATI0N COPY 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
that H. pylori also has such an aliphatic amidase, which hydrolyzes acetamide and propionamide in vitro (23).</p><p num="p0009">In view of the sequence similarity between Urel and AmiS together with the very similar structures of the urease and amidase substrates (urea: NH2-CO-NH2 and acetamide: CH<sub>3</sub>-CO-NH<sub>2</sub>) and the production of ammonia by both enzymes, a better understanding of the function of the H. pylori Urel protein is required. This understanding will open new opportunities for the prevention and treatment of H. pylori infections.</p><p num="p0010">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</p><p num="p0011">This invention provides methods for identifying molecules capable of inhibiting the growth and/or survival oϊ Helicobacter species, particularly, H. pylori, in vivo. In particular, the methods of this invention involve screening molecules that specifically inhibit Urel protein function.</p><p num="p0012">The invention encompasses the molecules identified by the methods of this invention and the use of the molecules by the methods of this invention to treat or prevent Helicobacter, and particularly H. pylori, infection in humans and animals.</p><p num="p0013">Another aspect of this invention is a method of preventing or treating Helicobacter species infection by administration to a human or animal in need of such treatment a molecule capable of inhibiting the growth and/or survival oϊ Helicobacter species in vivo. One such molecule according to the invention is characterized by a high affinity for Urel, which allows it (i) to be transported inside the Helicobacter cell, or (ii) to inhibit transport properties of Urel, or (iii) to inhibit Urel function by inhibiting Urel interaction with urease or other Helicobacter proteins. By inhibiting Urel, such molecule renders the bacteria more sensitive to acidity.</p><p num="p0014">Yet another aspect of this invention is the production of immunogenic Urel antigens and their use as vaccines to prevent Helicobacter species infection and/or colonization of the stomach or the gut. Antibodies to these Urel antigens are also encompassed within the scope of this invention.</p><p num="p0015">This invention further relates to recombinant strains of H. pylori comprising a modified urel gene, such that the products of the modified gene contribute to the attenuation of the bacteria's ability to survive in vivo, and thus, its pathogenic effects. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
 BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE FIGURES</p><p num="p0016">Figure 1 depicts the urease gene cluster of H. pylori parental strains N6 and SSI and of the derived mutants deficient in Urel, strains N6-823, N6-834, and SS1-834. The genes are indicated by boxes with an arrow showing the direction of their transcription. The distances between the ure genes are given in base pairs, bp. The site hybridizing to the primers used to confirm correct allelic exchange in strains N6-823, N6-834, and SSI -834 is shown. Blank boxes represent the cassettes containing the genes conferring resistance to Cm (cat) or to Km (aphA-3). The urease activity of these strains is given on the right-hand side of the figure. Urease activity was measured as the release of ammonia on crude extracts of bacteria grown 48 hours on blood agar plates as described previously (9). One unit corresponds to the amount of enzyme required to hydrolyze 1 μmol of urea min<sup>"1</sup> mg<sup>"1</sup> total protein. The data are means ± standard deviation calculated from 3 to 5 determinations.</p><p num="p0017">Figure 2A depicts a restriction map of pILL823, pILL824, pILL833 and pILL834. Small boxes mark the vector of each plasmid, and large boxes correspond to genes. On indicates the position of the ColEl origin of replication. Sp and Ap are the genes conferring resistance to spectinomycin and ampicillin, respectively. Cassettes inserted into urel and conferring resistance to chloramphenicol {cat) or kanamycin {aphA-3) are also shown. The sequence of the DNA region comprising the urel stop codon and the ureE start codon, including the Bell site where adaptor HI 9 was inserted, is given. Insertion of HI 9 into the Bell site of pILL824 produced pILL825, the resulting urel-ureE intergenic region is also shown. The stop codon oϊurel and the start codon of ureE are boxed and the ribosome binding site (RBS) is underlined. Brackets indicate the position of restriction sites removed by ligation.</p><p num="p0018">Figure 2B depicts a restriction map of two H. pylorilE. coli shuttle plasmids: pILL845 and pILL850. Small boxes mark the vector of each plasmid, and large boxes correspond to genes. On indicates the position of the E. coli ColEl origin of replication and rep A the gene coding for the Rep A protein necessary for autonomous replication of the pHel2 in H. pylori. Cm<sup>p</sup> marks the gene conferring resistance to chloramphenicol. The urel promoter is represented by a "P" with an arrow indicating the direction of the transcription. The other symbols are as in Figure 1. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
 Figure 3 shows the alignment of the amino acid sequence of Urel from H. pylori with those of similar proteins and prediction of the two-dimensional structure of members of the Urel/ AmiS protein family. Residues identical at one position in, at least, four sequences are boxed, and dashes indicate gaps inserted to optimize alignment. The organisms from which the sequences originated and the degree of identity with the H. pylori Urel protein are: Urel-Hp, Helicobacter pylori (195 residues, accession No. M84338); Urel-Hf, Helicobacter felis (74% identity over 196 residues, accession No. A41012); Urel-Lacto, Lactobacillus fermentum (55% identity over the 46 residues-long partial sequence, accession No. D10605); Urel-Strepto, Streptococcus salivarius (54% identity over the 129 residues-long partial sequence, accession No. U35248); AmiS-Myco, Mycobacterium smegmatis (39% identity over 172 residues, accession No. X57175); AmiS-Rhod, Rhodococcus sp. R312 (37% identity over 172 residues accession No. Z46523) and AmiS-Pseudo, Pseudomonas aeruginosa (37% identity over 171 residues, accession No. X77161). Predicted transmembrane V-helices are shown as shaded boxes. The regions separating these boxes are hydrophilic loops labeled "IN" when predicted to be intracellular and "OUT" when predicted to be extracellular.</p><p num="p0019">Figure 4 depicts the kinetics of ammonium release by the N6 parental strain (panel A) and the Urel-deficient strain N6-834 (panel B). Bacteria (2X10<sup>8</sup>/ml) were harvested and washed (as described in Skouloubris et al. (30)) resuspended in 10 ml of phosphate saline buffer (PBS) at pH 7, 5 or 2.2 in the presence of lOmM urea. After 0, 3, 5 and 30 minutes, 0.5ml were withdrawn and centrifuged to eliminate bacteria. The supernatant was kept on ice until ammonium concentration was measured using the assay commercialized by Sigma (kit reference #171).</p><p num="p0020">Table 2 shows the results obtained with the in vitro viability tests and the pH measurements.</p><p num="p0021">Table 3 gives the values of ammonium production by strain N6 and N6-834 presented on the graphs of Figure 4.</p><p num="p0022">DETAILED DESCRIPTION The urease cluster of Helicobacter species is unique among the many urease operons of Gram-negative bacteπa that have been sequenced (20) in that it has an extra gene, urel. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
The function of Urel has therefore been the subject of much speculation. It has mostly been attributed the function of an accessory protein required for nickel incorporation at the urease active site or a nickel transporter. A H. pylori strain carrying a deletion of urel replaced by a non-polar cassette (Kanamycin resistance cassette) has been constructed and was named N6- 834 (30). The strain has been deposited at C.N.C.M. (Collection Nationale de Culture de Microorganismes, 25 rue du Docteur Roux, 75724 Paris Cέdex 15, France) on June 28, 1999. This is the first time that a non-polar cassette (19) has been shown to be functional in H. pvlori. These results provide a valuable tool for genetic analysis of complex H. pylori operons, such as Cag, a multigenic pathogenicity island.</p><p num="p0023">Studies with this strain demonstrated that Urel is not required for full activity of H. pylori urease as measured after in vitro growth at neutral pH. This result argues against Urel being involved in nickel transport since such a protein, NixA (3) already identified in H pylori, is necessary for full urease activity. Comparing ureases expressed from a Urel- deficient strain and the corresponding parental strain show that (i) they present the same activity optimum pH (pH 8); (ii) the urease structural subunits, UreA-B, are produced in equal amounts; and (iii) the urease cellular location is identical.</p><p num="p0024">It is demonstrated here that (i) Urel is essential for colonization of mice by H. pylori; (ii) Urel is important for survival of H pylori at acidic pH; and (iii) Urel is necessary for urease "activation" at low pH.</p><p num="p0025">H. pylori during the colonization process of the stomach has to deal with important pH variations and especially has to adapt rapidly to extremely acidic pH (as acidic as pH 1.4). We have shown that Urel is required for H. pylori adaptation to acidity, consistently with the absence of colonization of the mouse stomach. As an essential protein for the H. pylori resistance to acidity, Urel certainly plays a key role in the infection, establishment, and persistence of H. pylori. Urel has a sequence similar to those of the AmiS proteins, proposed to be involved in the transport of short-chain amides (27), molecules structurally similar to urea. The Urel/ AmiS proteins have the characteristics of integral membrane proteins, probably of the cytoplasmic membrane.</p><p num="p0026">Different roles for Urel can be proposed. For instance, Urel might be involved in transport (import or export) of urea or short chain amides specifically active at low pH. However, an essential role for Urel as an amide transporter is less likely because a SSI 
<!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>-->
mutant, deficient in aliphatic amidase, colonizes as efficiently as the parental strain in mouse colonization experiments. In addition, amidase activity is not significantly modified by the deletion of urel in the N6-834 mutant strain (C.N.C.M. filed on June 28,1999). Import or export of urea could be consistent with the existence of a urea cycle, which is one of the characteristics of H. priori (28).</p><p num="p0027">Alternatively. Urel might be involved in an active ammonium export system. Finally, Urel might be involved in a mechanism of coupling urease activity to the periplasmic pH, allowing urease to become more active when extracellular pH is acidic.</p><p num="p0028">Our results are compatible with the first hypothesis of Urel being an urea transporter active at acidic pH values and the third hypothesis of Urel being a kind of sensor protein between the periplasmic pH and urease activity. We think that these two hypothesis are not exclusive. Whatever the role of Urel, as a membrane protein essential for the survival of H pylori in vivo, it now provides a powerful target for a new eradication therapy and for vaccines against H. pylori.</p><p num="p0029">Molecules capable of inhibiting the growth and/or survival of Helicobacter in vivo may be identified by contacting a parental Helicobacter strain with said molecule in a biological sample; testing and comparing, in the presence or absence of urea, the sensitivity to the extracellular pH of the parental strain to a strain deficient in Urel and to a Urel deficient strain complemented with urel; selecting said molecules displaying a differential effect on the parental or complemented strain as compared to the Urel deficient strain; and collecting said active molecule.</p><p num="p0030">A molecule active specifically on Urel will be the one rendering H. pylori sensitive to acidic pH (pH 2.2) in the presence of urea without affecting the strain behavior at neutral pH. Sensitivity to acidity in the presence of urea can be tested on whole H. pylori cells following a protocol described in the examples and adapted from Clyne et al. (8). We are now trying to transpose this test in E. coli whole cells carrying the complete urease gene cluster on a plasmid {ureAB-urelEFGH). Screening for a molecule rendering this recombinant E. coli more sensitive to acidity in the presence of urea will be performed as described for H. pylori m the examples. To distinguish between inhibitory molecules acting on Urel and those acting on urease, the medium pH after whole cell incubation at pH 7 in the presence of urea will be measured. Interesting molecules are those affecting response to 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>-->
acidity without inhibiting the alkalization of the medium observed after incubation at neutral pH.</p><p num="p0031">These methods may be used to identify molecules that inhibit any Helicobacter species carrying a Urel-nomolog This includes the gastric Helicobacter species- Helicobacter pylori, Helicobacter fehs, Helicobacter mustelae, Helicobacter muridarum, and also Helicobacter heiimannu, Helicobacter cams, Helicobacter bilis, Helicobacter hepaticus, and Helicobacter troguntum</p><p num="p0032">The molecules identified by the methods of this invention will be capable of inhibiting Urel activity b&gt; (i) inhibiting transport of urea or short chain amides, (ii) inhibiting ammonium export, or (in ) inhibiting urease "activation" at low pH. The molecules according to point (1) and (ii) should be able to diffuse throughout the outer membrane and should be active even at low concentration Suitable candidate molecules are structural analogs of urea or short chain amides, ammonium derivatives or urease inhibitors. For example, molecules deπved from AHA (acetohydroxamic acid), hydroxyurea, hippuπc acid, flurofamide, hydroxylamme, methylurea, thiourea (29), or methylammonium. The molecules according to point (iii) should inhibit the contact between Urel (probably inserted in the cytoplasmic membrane) and periplasmic, membrane, or cytoplasmic H. pylori proteins, which are necessary for urease "activation" at low pH These proteins could be the structural subumts of urease itself, the accessory proteins, or other proteins. Molecules obtained according to this invention should not be urease competitive inhibitors, should not be toxic or mutagenic in vivo and could potenuahze the action of antibiotics or bacteπcidal molecules. Validation of the action of such molecules could be performed in vivo in the mouse animal model with the pair of lsogenic strains SSI and SSI -834 as described in the examples.</p><p num="p0033">One example of a molecule according to this invention is a monoclonal or polyclonal antibody specific for Urel. Preferably, the antibody is capable of specifically inhibiting Urel activity</p><p num="p0034">The molecules of this invention may be administered m combination with a pharmaceutically acceptable earner to a patient suffenng from a Helicobacter infection. Alternatively, immunogεmc compositions compnsmg one or more molecules according to this invention may be administered m a vaccine composition to prevent infection by Helicobacter species 
<!-- EPO <DP n="10"/>-->
 Immunogenic compositions according to this invention may also comprise all or part of the Urel protein. Preferably, the Urel fragments comprise at least 10 consecutive amino acids of the native Urel sequence and more preferably, the fragments comprise at least 18, 20, or 25 consecutive amino acids of the native Urel sequence. Other suitable Urel fragments may contain at least 40 or at least 100 consecutive amino acids of the native Urel sequence. Suitable fragments of Helicobacter pylori include, for example, fragments selected from the group consisting of amino acid residues 22 to 31, 49 to 74, 94 to 104, and 123 to 142 of H. pylori (GenBank accession No. M84338)</p><p num="p0035">Reference will now be made to the following Examples. The Examples are purely exemplary of the invention and are not to be construed as limiting of the invention.</p><p num="p0036">EXAMPLES Construction of defined mutations of the H. pylori urel gene</p><p num="p0037">H. pylori strains with defined mutations in urel were generated by allelic exchange to determine whether the Urel protein was necessary for production of active urease. For this purpose, two plasmids (pILL823 and pILL834) with cassettes carrying antibiotic resistance genes inserted in urel were constructed in E. coli.</p><p num="p0038">In one plasmid. pILL823 (Figure 2A), the urel gene was inactivated by insertion of a promoterless cat gene, conferring resistance to chloramphenicol (Cm). A 780 bp blunt- ended BamHl restriction fragment containing the "cat cartridge" from pCM4 (Pharmacia, Sweden) was introduced into a unique Hpal site, between codons 21 and 22 of urel, in pILL753 (9). In the resulting plasmid, pILL823 (Figure 2A), cat is in the same orientation as urel and is expressed under the control of the urel promoter.</p><p num="p0039">The second plasmid, pILL834, carried a urel gene in which all but the first 21 codons were deleted and replaced with a non-polar cassette composed of the aphA-3 kanamycin (Km) resistance gene (25), which has been deleted from its own promoter and terminator regions (19). In Shigella βexneri (19) and other organisms (such as Yersinia enterocolitica, 2) this cassette has been shown not to affect the transcription of the genes downstream within an operon as long as these distal genes have intact translation signals. There is only one base pair separating urel from ureE (Figure 1) and ureE does not have an RBS (ribosome binding site) of its own, so the expression of urel and ureE is 
<!-- EPO <DP n="11"/>-->
transcriptionally and translationally coupled. Therefore, a urel deletion was accompanied by the addition of an RBS immediately upstream from ureE. Three intermediates, pILL824, pILL825 and pILL833 (Figure 2 A), were constructed in order to produce the final plasmid, pILL834 (Figure 2A). A 1.8 Kb Hpal-Hindlll restriction fragment from pILL753 (9) was inserted between the EcoRW and H dIII sites of pBR322, to give pILL824. Insertion of the HI 9 adaptor (carrying an RBS and ATG in frame with ureE, Table 1) into a Bell site overlapping the two first codons of ureE in pILL824 produced pILL825 (Figure 2A). The BamΗl fragment of pILL825 was then replaced by a 1.3 Kb blunt-ended vwII- BamHl fragment from pILL753. This resulted in the reconstitution of a complete urel gene, and this plasmid was called pILL833. Finally, pILL834 was obtained by replacement of the Hpal-Bglϊl fragment of pILL833 (thereby deleting all but the first 21 codons of urel) with an 850 bp blunt-ended EcoK -BamΗI fragment of pUC18K2 containing the non-polar Km cassette (19).</p><p num="p0040">TABLE l:Name and nucieotide sequence of oligonucleotides</p><p num="p0041">Pπmer Oligodeoxynucleotide sequence</p><p num="p0042">(5' to 3')</p><p num="p0043">HΪ7 TTTGACTTACTGGGGATCAAGCCTG (SEQ ID NO: 1 )</p><p num="p0044">H19* GATCATTTATTCCTCCAGATCTGGAGGAATAAAT (SEQ ID NO:2)</p><p num="p0045">H28 GAAGATCTCTAGGACTTGTATTGTTATAT (SEQ ID NO:3)</p><p num="p0046">H34 TATCAACGGTGGTATATCCAGTG (SEQ ID NO:4)</p><p num="p0047">H35 GCAGTTATTGGTGCCCTTAAACG (SEQ ID NO:5)</p><p num="p0048">H50 CCGGTGATATTCTCATTTTAGCC (SEQ ID NO:6)</p><p num="p0049">8A GCGAGTATGTAGGTTCAGTA (SEQ ID NO:7)</p><p num="p0050">9B GTGATACTTGAGCAATATCTTCAGC (SEQ ID NO: 8)</p><p num="p0051">12B CAAATCCACATAATCCACGCTGAAATC (SEQ ID NO:9)</p><p num="p0052">*H19 was used as adaptor and the others were used as primers for PCR amplification.</p><p num="p0053">Introduction of urel mutations into H. pylori</p><p num="p0054">H. pylori urel mutants were produced by allelic exchange following electroporation with a concentrated preparation of pILL823 and pILL834 as previously described by 
<!-- EPO <DP n="12"/>-->
Skouloubris et al. (23) from H. pylori strain N6 (12) and from the mouse-adapted H. pylori strain, SSI (Sydney Strain, 17). Bacteria with chromosomal allelic exchange with pILL823 were selected on Cm (4 μg ml) and those with chromosomal allelic exchange with pILL834 on Km (20 μg/ml). It was determined that the desired allelic exchange had taken place in strains N6-823, N6-834. and SS1-834 (Figure 1) by performing PCR with the appropriate oligonucleotides (Table 1). The PCR products obtained with genomic DNA of these strains were as expected (i) for strain N6-823: 140 bp with primers Η28-Η34, 220 bp with H35-9B, and 1.2 Kb with H28-9B. and (ii) for strains N6-834 and SS1-834, 150 bp with primers H28-H50, 180 bp with H17-12B, and 1 Kb with H28-12B.</p><p num="p0055">The growth rate of strain N6-834 carrying a non-polar deletion of urel was compared to that of the parental strain N6. No difference in the colony size was observed on blood agar medium plates. Identical doubling times and stationary phase OD were measured for both strains grown in BHI (Oxoid) liquid medium containing 0.2% 3-cyclodextrin (Sigma). Thus, Urel is not essential for H. pylori growth in vitro.</p><p num="p0056">Urease activity of H. pylori urel mutants</p><p num="p0057">The urease activity of strains N6-823, N6-834, and SSI -834 was measured in vitro as described previously by Cussac et al. (9) and compared to the activity of the parental strains, N6 and SSI (Figure 1). Urease activity was almost completely abolished in strain N6-823 (0.3±0.1 units). Strains 6-834 and SSI -834, with non-polar urel mutations had wild-type levels of activity (N6-S34 and SS1-834: 12±2 units; parental strains, N6: lO±l and SSI : 12±0.4 units).</p><p num="p0058">The pH optimum of urease produced either from the N6 parental strain or from the Urel deficient strain N6-S34 was measured and compared. For both strains, urease has a pH optimum of 8 which is consistent with the published data.</p><p num="p0059">These results strongly suggest that the urease-negative phenotype of the N6- ure/::TnKm-8 (13) and the very weak urease activity of N6-823 strains were due to a polar effect of the inserted cassettes on the expression of the downstream genes ureE and ureF (Figure 1). This hypothesis was tested by measuring urease activity of strain N6-823 complemented in trans with an E. colilH. pylori shuttle plasmid expressing the ureE-F genes. This plasmid, pELL845 (Figure 2B), was obtained by insertion of a 2.8 Kb Clal- 
<!-- EPO <DP n="13"/>-->
BamEl fragment of pILL834 (comprising the 3'-end of ureB, the non-polar deletion of urel and intact ureE and ureF genes) into the corresponding sites of the shuttle vector pHel2 constructed by Heuermann and Haas (15). Strain N6-823 was electroporated with a DNA preparation of pILL845 as described by Skouloubris et al. ( 23), and transformants were selected on kanamycin (20μg/ml) and chloramphenicol (4μg/ml). In strain N6-823 harboring pILL845, wild type urease activity was recovered confirming that the very low urease activity of strain N6-823 was due to a polar effect on the expression of the accessory genes ureE-F. In Klebsiella aerogenes, the absence of UreE has little effect on urease activity (4). In contrast. UreF, as part of the accessory protein complex (UreDFG), is absolutely required for the production of active urease (21). Thus, by analogy, it is likely that the phenotype of the H. pylori polar urel mutants was due to the absence of ureF expression.</p><p num="p0060">The urease structural subunits, UreA and UreB, produced by strain N6 or strain N6- 834 were compared with the Western blot technique using a mixture of antisera directed against each urease subunit. It was observed that the amount of each subunit produced by the two strains is identical. The possibility that urease cellular localization could be affected in the absence of Urel was examined after cellular fractionation (separating the soluble from the membrane associated proteins and from the supernatant) of strains N6 and N6-834. These experiments revealed no difference between the urease cellular localization in the wild type strain or in the Urel-deficient mutant. These results demonstrate that, at neutral pH, Urel is neither implicated in the stabilization of the urease structural subunits nor in a targeting process of urease to a specific cellular compartment. Colonization test for the H. pylori SS1-834 mutant in the mouse animal model</p><p num="p0061">The mouse model for infection by the H. pylori SSI strain (Sydney Strain, 17), validated by Chevalier et al. (7) and Ferrero et al. (14), was used to test the function of Urel in vivo. Mice were infected with the non-polar urel mutant, SSI -834, and with the parental strain, SSI, (which had gone through an equivalent number of in vitro subcultures) as a positive control. This experiment was repeated three times and produced identical results (30). Two independently constructed SSI -834 mutants were used. The first mutant strain had gone through 30 in vitro subcultures, the second only 20. Under the same experimental 
<!-- EPO <DP n="14"/>-->
conditions, strain SSI can undergo more than 80 in vitro subcultures without losing its colonization capacity.</p><p num="p0062">In each experiment, aliquots (100 μl) containing 10<sup>6</sup> H. pylori strain SSI or SSI -834 bacteria prepared in peptone broth were administered orogastrically to 10 mice each (six to eight -weeks old Swiss specific-pathogen- free mice) as described by Ferrero et al. (14). Mice were killed four weeks after inoculation. The presence of H. pylori was tested with a direct urease test on biopsies performed on half the stomach (14). The remaining gastric tissues were used for quantitative culture of H. pylori as described by Ferrero et al. (14). In each experiment, the stomachs of the ten SSI -infected mice all tested positive for urease. The bacterial load was between 5xl0<sup>4</sup> and 5xl0<sup>5</sup> colony forming units (CFU) per g of stomach. None of the stomachs of the mice infected with strain SSI -834 tested positive for urease and no H. pylori cells were cultured from them. Thus, the Urel protein is essential for the H. pylori in vivo survival and/or colonization of the mouse stomach. Urel is essential for H. pylori resistance to acidity</p><p num="p0063">Survival to acidic conditions in the presence or absence of 1 OmM urea was tested with strains N6 and N6-834. The experimental procedures detailed in Skouloubris et al. (30) were based on those described in Clyne et al. (8). Exponentially grown bacteria were harvested, washed in PBS (phosphate buffer saline), and approximately 2 XlO<sup>8</sup> CFU/ml were resuspended in PBS of pH 2.2 or pH 7 in the presence or the absence of 1 OmM urea and incubated at 37EC. After one hour incubation (i) quantitative cultures of the H. pylori strains were performed to evaluate bacterial survival, and (ii) the bacteria were centrifuged and the pH of the medium was measured. The results obtained are presented in Table 2. In the absence of urea, both strains N6 and N6-834 presented identical phenotype, i.e., they were killed at pH 2.2, and survived at pH 7 without modifying the final pH of the medium (Table 2). After incubation at pH 7 in the presence of urea, both strains were killed because the final pH rose to pH 9. At pH 2.2 in the presence of urea, the parental strain survived well since it was able to raise the pH to neutrality. In contrast, a completely different phenotype was obtained with the Urel-deficient strain N6-834 which was unable to raise the pH and whose viability was seriously affected (Table 2). 
<!-- EPO <DP n="15"/>-->
Complementation of the Urel-deficient strain N6-834 with plasmid pILL850</p><p num="p0064">Direct implication of the Urel protein in the H. pylori capacity to resist to acidity has been confirmed by trans-complementation with plasmid pLLL850 (Figure 2B restriction map and details of construction). This plasmid [CNCM 1-2245 filed on June 28,1999] is derived from the H. pylori/E. coli shuttle vector pHel2 (15). Plasmid pILL850 carries the urel gene under the control of its own promoter and was constructed as follows: a 1.2 kb BcR restriction fragment of plasmid pILL753 (9) was introduced between the BamΑl and BcR. restriction sites of pHe!2 (Figure 2B). Strains N6 and N6-834 were transformed by this plasmid and the phenotype of the complemented strains in the acidity sensitivity test experiments described above was examined. As shown in Table 2, the phenotype of strain N6-834 complemented by pILL850 is identical to that of the parental strain N6. Interestingly, the urease activity of the complemented strains (measured on sonicated extracts as described in Skouloubris et al. (30)) has been found to be significantly higher as compared to that of the corresponding strains without pILL850. For the purpose of the deposit at the CNCM pLLL850 is placed into an E. coli strain, MCI 061 (Wertman KF. et al, 1986, Gene 49: 253-262). Measurements of ammonium production</p><p num="p0065">The amount of ammonium produced in the extracellular medium of H. pylori whole cells was measured by an enzymatic assay commercialized by Sigma following the supplier's instructions. These experiments were performed after incubation of the cells in PBS at different pH values and after different incubation times. Such experiments gave an accurate evaluation of ammonium production and excretion in different strains as well as a measure of the kinetics of this reaction. A control experiment showed that ammonium production was very low (10-20μM) in the absence of urea.</p><p num="p0066">Figure 4 depicts the kinetics (0, 3, 5, and 30 min. incubation time) of extracellular ammonium released by the N6 parental strain (panel A) and the Urel-deficient strain N6-834 (panel B) incubated in PBS at pH 2.2, pH 5, or pH 7 in the presence of lOmM urea. The results obtained indicate that (i) ammonium is largely produced and rapidly released in the extracellular medium: and (ii) in the N6 wild type strain (Figure 4, panel A and Table 3) ammonium production is significantly enhanced when the extracellular pH is acidic. This effect is already visible at pH 5 and is even stronger at pH 2.2. This last observation is 
<!-- EPO <DP n="16"/>-->
consistent with the results of Scott et al. (31) who suggested urease activation at low pH. In our experiments, the rapidity of the response to acidity argues against urease activation depending on transcriptional regulation or on de novo protein synthesis.</p><p num="p0067">Ammonium production was then measured in the Urel-deficient strain N6-834 (Figure 4, panel B and Table 3). At neutral pH, kinetics of ammonium production were similar to those of the wild type strain. In contrast, at pH 5 ammonium production was reduced and delayed as compared to the wild type strain. A dramatic effect of the absence of Urel was observed at pH 2.2, where the amount of ammonium was very low, which is consistent with our results showing that Urel is necessary for adaptation to acidity.</p><p num="p0068">Our results demonstrate that Urel is essential for the resistance of H. pylori to acidity. In the absence of Urel. urease, although present in huge amounts, is not able to protect the bacteria against the aggression of acidity. This is consistent with the essential role of Urel in vivo. During its passage in the acidic stomach lumen, the viability of the Urel-deficient strain is affected. As a consequence, the bacterial load becomes too low to permit colonization. The different roles proposed for Urel are presented in the "detailed description" section.</p><p num="p0069">Alignment of the Urel and AmiS protein sequences and two dimensional structure prediction</p><p num="p0070">A systematic search for Urel homologs in the protein data banks was carried out. It was determined that H. pylori is not the only ureolytic bacterium with a urel gene. Two phylogenetically related Gram-positive organisms, Streptococcus salivarius, a dental plaque bacterium (6), and Lactobacillus fermentum, a lactic acid bacterium (16), carry genes for Urel-homologs (Figure 3) located immediately upstream from the urease structural genes. The urel gene has been detected in various Helicobacter species; the H. felis urel gene has been entirely sequenced (Figure 3 and allowed United Stated Patent application Serial No. 08/467,822, the entire contents of which are incorporated herein by reference). PCR experiments have suggested that there is a urel gene in H. heilmannii (24) and in H. mustelae.</p><p num="p0071">Sequence similarities between the Urel protein of H. pylori and the AmiS proteins expressed by the aliphatic amidase operons from P. aeruginosa (27) and Rhodococcus sp. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="17"/>-->
R312 (5) have been reported. In Mycobacterium smegmatis, there is an additional AmiS- homolog encoded by a gene, ORF P3, located immediately upstream from an amidase gene (18).</p><p num="p0072">Alignment of these Urel AmiS proteins [using the Clustal W(l . 60) program] defined strongly conserved stretches of amino acids (Figure 3). All but one of these conserved blocks are in highly hydrophobic segments. These regions, each 17 to 22 residues long, are probably folded into transmembrane V-helices (Figure 3). Six transmembrane regions were predicted for the proteins from H. pylori, H. felis, and P. aeruginosa and seven for those from Rhodococcus sp. R312 and M. smegmatis (highly reliable predictions, performed with pHD, a profile fed neural network system as described by Rost et al. (22)). The orientation of the Urel/ AmiS protems in the membrane was deduced from the charges of the intercalated hydrophilic regions, which are short in these proteins (Figure 3). The first five such regions are poorly conserved and of various length. The last interhelical segment common to these proteins is significantly more conserved than the others. This region predicted to be intracellular may be the active site of Urel or a site of multimerization or interaction with an intracellular partner. These results strongly suggest that the members of the Urel/ AmiS family, found in both Gram-positive and -negative bacteria, are integral membrane proteins. These proteins have no signal sequence and should therefore be inserted into the cytoplasmic membrane in Gram-negative bacteria.</p><p num="p0073">Two peptides. selected from the Urel sequence, were synthesized and injected into two rabbits to obtain serum containing polyclonal antibodies directed against Urel. One peptide corresponds to the first predicted intracellular loop of Urel (from residue nB 15 to 31, see Figure 3) and the second one to the second predicted extracellular loop of Urel (from residue nB 118 to 134. see Figure 3. These sera are presently being tested and if proven to recognize the Urel protεm will allow us to precisely define the localization of this protein and to verify the predicted Urel two-dimensional structure presented in Figure 3.</p><p num="p0074">The references cited herein are specifically incorporated by reference in their entirety. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="18"/>--></p><p num="p0075"><img id="imgf000018_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="166" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000018_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="97"/></p><p num="p0076">Table 2 : Effect of the presence of urea at pH 7, 5 or 2.2 on (i) the viability o f different H. pylori strains and (ii) the extracellular pH (indicated as final pH). The experimental procedures are described in reference 30 and in the examples. Strain N6 is the parental strain and strain N6-834 the Urel-deficient mutant. Plasmid plLL850 is derived from a £ colilH. pylori shuttle vector, it carries the urel gene and complements the urel mutation of strain N6-834. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="19"/>-->
Table 3</p><p num="p0077">medium [NH4]</p><p num="p0078">Strain PH minutes mM</p><p num="p0079">N6 7,0 0 3.5</p><p num="p0080">N6 7,0 3 4.4</p><p num="p0081">N6 7,0 5 3.1</p><p num="p0082">N6 7,0 30 5.6</p><p num="p0083">N6 5,0 0 12.8</p><p num="p0084">N6 5,0 3 9.3</p><p num="p0085">N6 5,0 5 11.8</p><p num="p0086">N6 5,0 30 16,0</p><p num="p0087">N6 2,2 0 6.7</p><p num="p0088">N6 2,2 3 9,0</p><p num="p0089">N6 2,2 5 11,0</p><p num="p0090">N6 2,2 30 20,0</p><p num="p0091">N6-834 7,0 0 2, .7</p><p num="p0092">N6-834 7,0 3 2.8</p><p num="p0093">N6-834 7,0 5 3.8</p><p num="p0094">N6-834 7,0 30 5.8</p><p num="p0095">N6-834 5,0 0 1.4</p><p num="p0096">N6-834 5,0 3 1.7</p><p num="p0097">N6-834 5,0 5 2.9</p><p num="p0098">N6-834 5,0 30 4.6</p><p num="p0099">N6-834 2,2 0 0.9</p><p num="p0100">N6-834 2,2 3 0.6</p><p num="p0101">N6-834 2,2 5 0.7</p><p num="p0102">N6-834 2,2 30 1.3 
<!-- EPO <DP n="20"/>-->
 REFERENCES</p><p num="p0103">1. Akada, J. K., M. Shirai, H. Takeuchi, M. Tsuda, and T. Nakazawa. 1997. Transcriptional analysis of urease structural gene and the urel gene in Helicobacter pylori. Gut. 41 :A9.</p><p num="p0104">2. Allaoui, A., Schulte, R. and G. R. Cornelis. 1995. Mutational analysis of the Yersinia enterocolitica virC operon: characterization of yscE, F, G, H, I, J, K required for Yop secretion and ysch encoding YopR. Mol. Microbiol. 18:343-355.</p><p num="p0105">3. Bauerfeind, P.. R. M. Garner, and H. L. T. Mobley. 1996. Allelic exchange mutagenesis of nixA in Helicobacter pylori results in reduced nickel transport and urease activity. Infect. Immun. 64:2877-2880.</p><p num="p0106">4. Brayman, T. G.. and R. T. Hausinger. 1996. Purification, characterization, and functional analysis of a truncated Klebsiella aerogenes UreE urease accessory protein lacking the Histidine-Rich carboxyl terminus. J. Bacteriol. 178:5410-5416.</p><p num="p0107">5. Chebrou, H., F. Bigey, A. Arnaud, and P. Galzy. 1996. Amide metabolism: a putative ABC transporter in Rhodococcus sp. R312. Gene. 182:215-218.</p><p num="p0108">6. Chen, Y.-Y. M.. K. A. Clancy, and R. A. Burne. 1996. Streptococcus salivarius urease: genetic and biochemical characterization and expression in a dental plaque Streptococcus. Infect. Immun. 64:585-592.</p><p num="p0109">7. Chevalier, C, J.-M. Thiberge, R. L. Ferrero, and A. Labigne. 1999. Essential role of Helicobacter pylori g-Glutamyltranspeptidase (GGT) for the colonization of the gastric mucosa in mice. Mol. Microbiol. 31:1359-1372.</p><p num="p0110">8. Clyne, M., A. Labigne, and B. Drumm. 1995. Helicobacter pylori requires an acidic environment to survive in the presence of urea. Infect. Immun. 63:1669-1673. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="21"/>-->
9. Cussac, V., R. L. Ferrero, and A. Labigne. 1992. Expression of Helicobacter pylori urease genes in Escherichia coli grown under nitrogen-limiting conditions. J. Bacteriol. 174:2466-2473.</p><p num="p0111">10. Dunn, B. E., H. Cohen, and M. Blaser. 1997. Helicobacter pylori. Clin. Microbiol.</p><p num="p0112">Rev. 10:720-741.</p><p num="p0113">11. Eaton, K. A., and S. Krakowka. 1994. Effect of gastric pH on urease-dependent colonization of gnotobiotic piglets by Helicobacter pylori. Infect. Immun. 62:3604-</p><p num="p0114">3607.</p><p num="p0115">12. Ferrero, R. L.. V. Cussac, P. Courcoux, and A. Labigne. 1992. Construction of isogenic urease-negative mutants of Helicobacter pylori by allelic exchange. J. Bacteriol. 174:4212-4217.</p><p num="p0116">13. Ferrero, R. L.. V. Cussac, P. Courcoux, and A. Labigne. 1994. Construction of isogenic mutants of Helicobacter pylori deficient in urease activity, pp 179- 182. In Basic and Clinical Aspects of H. pylori infection. Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg.</p><p num="p0117">14. Ferrero, R. L.. J.-M. Thiberge, M. Huerre, and A. Labigne. 1998. Immune responses of specific-pathogen- free mice to chronic Helicobacter pylori (strain SSI) infection. Infect. Immun. 66:1349-1355.</p><p num="p0118">15. Heuermann, D.. and R. Haas. 1998. A stable shuttle vector system for efficient genetic complementation of Helicobacter pylori strains by complementation and conjugation. Mol. Gen. Genet. 257:519-528.</p><p num="p0119">16. Kakimoto, S.. Y. Sumino, K. Kawahara, E. Yamazaki, and I. Nakatsui. 1990. Purification and characterization of acid urease from Lactobacillus fermentum. Appl. Microbiol. &amp; Biotechnol. 32:538-543. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="22"/>-->
17. Lee, A., J. O'Rourke, M. Corazon De Ungria, B. Robertson, G. Daskalopoulos, and M. F. Dixon. 1997. A standardized mouse model of Helicobacter pylori infection: introducing the Sydney Strain. Gastroenterology. 112:1386-1397.</p><p num="p0120">18. Mahenthiralingam, E., P. Draper, E. O. Davis, and M. J. Colston. 1993. Cloning and sequencing of the gene which encodes the highly inducible acetamidase of Mycobacterium smegmatis. J. Gen. Microbiol. 139:575-583.</p><p num="p0121">19. Menard, R., P. J. Sansonetti, and C. Parsot. 1993. Nonpolar mutagenesis of the ipa genes defines IpaB, IpaC, and IpaD as effectors of Shigella flexneri entry into epithelial cells. J. Bacteriol. 175:5899-5906.</p><p num="p0122">20. Mobley, H. L. T., M. D. Island, and R. P. Hausinger. 1995. Molecular biology of ureases. Microbiol. Rev. 59:451-480.</p><p num="p0123">21. Moncrief, M. B. C, and R. P. Hausinger. 1997. Characterization of UreG, identification of a UreD-UreF-UreG complex, and evidence suggesting that a nucleotide-binding site in UreG is required for in vivo metallocenter assembly of Klebsiella aerogenes urease. J. Bacteriol. 179:4081-4086.</p><p num="p0124">22. Rost, B., R. Casadio, P. Fariselli, and C. Sander. 1995. Prediction of helical transmembrane segments at 95% accuracy. Prot. Science. 4:521-533.</p><p num="p0125">23. Skouloubris, S.. A. Labigne, and H. De Reuse. 1997. Identification and characterization of an aliphatic amidase in Helicobacter pylori. Mol. Microbiol. 25:989-998.</p><p num="p0126">24. Solnick, J. V.. J. O'Rourke, A. Lee, and L. S. Tompkins. 1994. Molecular analysis of urease genes from a newly identified uncultured species of Helicobacter. Infect. Immun. 62: 1631-1638. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="23"/>-->
25. Trieu-Cuot, P.. G. Gerbaud, T. Lambert, and P. Courvalin. 1985. In vivo transfer of genetic information between Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria. EMBO J.</p><p num="p0127">4:3583-3587.</p><p num="p0128">26. Williams, C. L„ T. Preston, M. Hossack, C. Slater, and K. E. L. McColl. 1996. Helicobacter pylori utilizes urea for amino acid synthesis. FEMS Immunol. Med. Microbiol. 13:87-94.</p><p num="p0129">27. Wilson, S. A., R. J. Williams, L. H. Pearl, and R. E. Drew. 1995. Identification of two new genes in the Pseudomonas aeruginosa amidase operon, encoding an ATPase (AmiB) and a putative integral membrane protein (AmiS). J. Biol. Chem. 270:18818-</p><p num="p0130">18824.</p><p num="p0131">28. Mendz, G.L. and S.L. Mazell. 1996. The Urea Cycle of Helicobacter pylori. Microbiology 142:2959-2967.</p><p num="p0132">29. Nicholson, E.B., E.A. Concaugh and H.L.T. Mobley. 1991. Proteus mirabilis urease: use of ureA-lacZ fusion demonstrates that induction is highly specific for urea. Infection and Immunity. 59(10):3360-3365.</p><p num="p0133">30. Skouloubris, S.. J.-M. Thiberge, A. Labigne and H. De Reuse (1998) The Helicobacter pylori Urel protein is not involved in urease activity but is essential for bacterial survival in vivo. Infect. Immun. 66: 4517-4521.</p><p num="p0134">31. Scott, D. R., D. Weeks, C. Hong, S. Postius, K. Melchers and G. Sachs (1998) The role of internal urease in acid resistance of Helicobacter pylori. Gastroenterology. 114: 58-70. 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="24"/>--><claim-text>We claim:</claim-text><claim-text>1. An in vitro method for identifying a molecule capable of inhibiting the growth or survival of Helicobacter in vivo, comprising the steps of:</claim-text><claim-text>(a) contacting a parental Helicobacter with said molecule in a biological sample;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) testing and comparing the response to extracellular pH and the sensitivity to acidity of the parental strain to a strain deficient in Urel and/or of a Urel deficient strain complemented with a plasmid carrying urel in the presence or absence of said active molecule: and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) selecting said molecule displaying a differential effect on the parental strain as compared to the Urel deficient strain.</claim-text><claim-text>2. The method according to claim 1, wherein the degree of acidity sensitivity is measured in step (b).</claim-text><claim-text>3. The method according to claim 1 , wherein the molecules are specific to Urel.</claim-text><claim-text>4. The method according to claim 1, wherein the Helicobacter strain is selected from the group consisting of Helicobacter pylori, helicobacter felis, Helicobacter heilmannii, Helicobacter mustelae, Helicobacter canis, Helicobacter bilis, Helicobacter hepaticus, Helicobacter muridarum, and Helicobacter troguntum.</claim-text><claim-text>5. A molecule capable of inhibiting the growth or survival of H pylori in vivo identified by the method according to claim 1.</claim-text><claim-text>6. A method of treating or preventing H. pylori infection in humans or animals comprising the step of administering a molecule according to claim 5 together with a pharmaceutically acceptable carrier to a human or animal in need of such treatment.</claim-text><claim-text>7. A method of preventing or treating H. pylori infection comprising the step of administering a molecule capable of inhibiting the growth or survival of H. pylori in vivo to a human or animal in need of such treatment.</claim-text><claim-text>8. The method according to claim 7, wherein the molecule is transported inside the H. pylori cell due to a high affinity for Urel.</claim-text><claim-text>9. The method according to claim 7, wherein the molecule inactivates Urel by inhibiting its properties in H. pylori resistance to acidity.</claim-text><claim-text>10. The method according to claim 7, wherein the molecule inactivates Urel by inhibiting its properties as a transporter. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="25"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>11. The method according to claim 7, wherein the molecule inactivates Urel by inhibiting an interaction between Urel and other H. pylori proteins.</claim-text><claim-text>12. The method according to claim 7, wherein the molecule is capable of intracellular inhibition of urease in H. pylori.</claim-text><claim-text>13. A molecule capable of inhibiting the growth or survival of Helicobacter pylori in vivo said molecule being capable of interacting directly or indirectly with Urel protein or Urel activity or with the corresponding urel gene.</claim-text><claim-text>14. A molecule according to claim 13, wherein the molecule is transported inside the H. pylori cell due to a high affinity for urel.</claim-text><claim-text>15. A molecule according to claims 9 and 13, wherein the molecule inactivates Urel protein by directly binding to urel.</claim-text><claim-text>16. A molecule according to claims 10 and 13, wherein the molecule is specifically inhibiting Urel transporter properties either in ammonia export or in urea transport (export or import).</claim-text><claim-text>17. A molecule according to claims 11 and 13 wherein the molecule is capable of specifically inhibiting an interaction between Urel and other H. pylori proteins.</claim-text><claim-text>18. A molecule according to claims 12 and 13 wherein the molecule is capable of intracellular inhibition of H. pylori urease.</claim-text><claim-text>19. An immunogenic composition comprising all or part of H. pylori Urel and a pharmaceutically acceptable carrier.</claim-text><claim-text>20. A method of preventing Helicobacter pylori infection comprising the step of administering an immunogenic composition according to claim 19.</claim-text><claim-text>21. Monoclonal or polyclonal antibodies that specifically recognize all or part of H. pylori Urel.</claim-text><claim-text>22. A recombinant strain of H. pylori comprising a modified urel gene, wherein the product of the gene contributes to the attenuation of the bacteria's ability to survive in vivo.</claim-text><claim-text>23. A recombinant strain according to claim 22 named H. pylori N6-834 mutant deposited at C.N.C.M. on June 28,1999. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="26"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>24. A plasmid pILL 850, deposited at the C.N.C.M. on June 28,1999 under Accession Number 1-2245, able to stably replicate in H. pylori, carrying the urel gene and complementing the H. pylori N6-834 mutant. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>