<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1241141-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1241141" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="25199527" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020918"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1241141-A2" status="new" fvid="23570842"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1241141</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20020918</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02005568-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02005568</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020312</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-80871901-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>80871901</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010315</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B  19/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B  19/09        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B  20/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03B  20/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C30B  15/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C30B  15/10        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C30B  29/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C30B  29/06        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C03B  19/09B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C30B  15/10</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren und Zwischenprodukt zur Herstellung eines Tiegels aus Quarzglas</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">A method and an intermediate product for making a silica crucible</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé et produit intermédiaire pour la fabrication d'un creuset en silice vitreuse</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0737653-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0737653</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-63166791-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>63166791</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5885071-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5885071</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 012, no. 444 (C-545), 22 November 1988 (1988-11-22) -&amp; JP 63 166791 A (TOSHIBA CERAMICS CO LTD), 9 July 1988 (1988-07-09)</text><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HERAEUS QUARZGLAS</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HERAEUS SHIN ETSU AMERICA INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HERAEUS QUARZGLAS GMBH &amp; CO. KG</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HERAEUS SHIN-ETSU AMERICA, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Heraeus Quarzglas GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG</last-name><address><street>Quarzstrasse 8</street><city>63450 Hanau</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Heraeus Shin-Etsu America, Inc.</last-name><address><street>4600 N.W. Pacific Rim Blvd.</street><city>Camas, WA 98607</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KEMMOCHI KATSUHIKO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MOSIER ROBERT</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SPENCER PAUL</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TOGAWA TAKAYUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KEMMOCHI, KATSUHIKO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MOSIER, ROBERT</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SPENCER, PAUL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TOGAWA, TAKAYUKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KEMMOCHI, KATSUHIKO</last-name><address><street>520 SE Columbia River Drive, Apt 332</street><city>Vancouver, WA 98661</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MOSIER, ROBERT</last-name><address><street>15903 NE 9th Circle</street><city>Vancouver, WA 98684</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SPENCER, PAUL</last-name><address><street>250 NE Vista Drive</street><city>Stevenson, WA 98684</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TOGAWA, TAKAYUKI</last-name><address><street>Porosupero Meson CO201, 2-20-73 Hiraide</street><city>Takefu-shi, Fukul-ken, 915-0803</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Staudt, Armin</last-name><address><street>Edith-Stein-Strasse 22</street><city>63075 Offenbach am Main</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Silica crucibles containing an inner layer which is substantially pure and substantially
bubble-free and methods for making such crucibles. The inner layer is also
substantially stable against roughening and spot devitrification. The inner layer is
formed by making a web structure which is then converted to a continuous layer,
thereby minimizing or eliminating bubble formation. The inner layer is also formed
using a gettering agent which getters alkaline and alkaline-earth elements while the
inner layer is formed. The alkaline and alkaline-earth elements are gettered on an
innermost portion of the inner layer which is later removed, leaving an inner layer with
relatively few impurities. When used in a CZ-crystal growing process, the inner
surface of the crucible remains smooth and substantially no bubbles grow in the inner
layer.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention generally relates to crucible fabrication. Specifically, the
present invention relates to methods and apparatus for making quartz glass crucibles
that are suitable for use in pulling silicon single crystals for semiconductor
applications.</p><p num="0002">There are several methods for making single crystal silicon materials. One such
method―the "Czochralski" (CZ) method―has been widely adopted for producing
single crystal silicon materials for semiconductor applications. In this method,
polycrystalline silicon is melted in a vessel and a single-crystal seed crystal is dipped
at its tip end portion into the molten silicon. The seed crystal is then "pulled" while
being rotated so that a single crystal from the melt is grown on the seed crystal with
the same crystallographic orientation.</p><p num="0003">A crucible is one vessel commonly employed in this pulling operation for making
ingots of silicon single crystals. Crucibles are typically configured in a bowl shape,
with walls and a bottom, to contain the molten silicon during the pulling operation.
Crucibles may be made of any material which adequately contains the molten silicon
without contaminating it, yet introduces a desired amount of oxygen into the molten
silicon. One of the most widely used materials for such crucibles is silica or quartz
glass.</p><p num="0004">These walls of the crucibles normally have double layer structures, with an inner layer
and an outer layer. Normally, the outer layers of the crucibles are translucent―for
increased scattering of the radiation from heater elements―and therefore contain
numerous tiny bubbles. When the bubbles open during the crystal-pulling operation,
however, they can damage the silicon ingots because any generated particle can
travel from the bubble to melt-ingot interface and damage the crystal structure of the 
pulled ingot. To reduce this impact of bubbles in the outer layer, as well as for other
reasons, the bubble-free inner layer is often formed between the outer layer and the
melt.</p><p num="0005">The inner layer of the crucible wall should also as pure as possible to minimize the
possibility of contamination of the ingot during the crystal-pulling operation. During
the crystal-pulling process, portions of the inner layer can dissolve into the silicon
melt. Silicon and oxygen, which are the main components of the inner layer, are not
harmful to the silicon melt. Indeed, the dissolved oxygen―a main source of oxygen in
the wafers cut from the ingot―acts as a mechanical strengthening element and as a
gettering agent in the wafers. Other components such as impurities, however, are
also transferred to the melt during the crystal-pulling operation.</p><p num="0006">One of the numerous methods known for preparing crucibles with inner layers which
are substantially bubble-free is described in U.S. Patent Nos. 4,416,680, 4,956,208,
and 4,935,046, the disclosures of which are incorporated herein by reference. Other
methods include those described in Japanese Patents JP1-197381 and JP1-197382
(which are modifications of the method described in U.S. Patent No. 4,416,680), the
disclosures of which are incorporated herein by reference. There are also numerous
methods known for purifying the quartz grain used to make crucibles as well as
electrolyzing finished crucibles, thereby making crucible walls with a "pure" inner
layer. See, for example, respectively U.S. Patent Nos. 5,637,284 and 4,874,417, the
disclosures of which are incorporated herein by reference.</p><p num="0007">Despite the above efforts, currently available crucibles still have many problems. One
important problem, as mentioned above, is the purity. Another important problem is
that after running a long period, such as more than 100 hours, the inner surface of
the crucible becomes rough. It is believed that the inner surface becomes rough
either through merging of cristobalite rings formed on the inner surface during crystal
pulling or through spot devitrification. When the inner surface becomes rough, the
crystal structure of the ingot can suffer. </p><p num="0008">The semiconductor industry is moving towards larger wafer sizes. Consequently, the
diameter of the ingots from which the wafers are cut must also be larger. But both of
the problems mentioned immediately above become more pronounced as the size of
the ingots becomes larger. To obtain larger diameter ingots, the CZ process must be
run longer, increasing the possibility of the inner surface become rougher and more
impurities dissolving into the melt from the inner layer of the crucible wall.</p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0009">The present invention provides silica or quartz glass crucibles containing inner layers
that are substantially pure and substantially bubble-free. When used in a CZ-crystal
growing process, the inner layers of such crucibles are substantially stable against
roughening and spot devitrification. The present invention also provides methods for
making crucibles with these characteristics.</p><p num="0010">The inner layer is formed by a method which first forms a web structure using quick
and high fusion power at the initial stage of fusing quartz grain to a silica glass
crucible. The web structure is then converted to a continuous layer, thereby
minimizing or eliminating bubble formation, bubble growth, surface roughening, and
spot devitrification. The inner layer is also formed using a gettering agent which
getters alkaline and alkaline-earth elements while the inner layer is formed. The
alkaline and alkaline-earth elements are gettered on an innermost surface of the
inner layer which is later removed, leaving an inner layer with relatively few impurities.</p><heading><u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u> </heading><p num="0011">One aspect of the present invention will be described in conjunction with Figures 1-10,
where:
<dl tsize="9"><dt><b>Figure 1</b></dt><dd>is view of an apparatus and associated process for making silica crucibles
according to the present invention;</dd><dt><b>Figure 2</b> </dt> <dd>is a view of a web structure formed during the process according to the
present invention; </dd> <dt><b>Figure 3</b></dt><dd>is partial view of a silica crucible according to the present invention;</dd><dt><b>Figure 4</b></dt><dd>is a photograph of a web structure formed during the process according to
the present invention;</dd><dt><b>Figure 5</b></dt><dd>is photograph of a crucible having web structure formed during the process
according to the present invention;</dd><dt><b>Figure 6</b></dt><dd>is a view of an inner surface of a used crucible made according to the
present invention;</dd><dt><b>Figure 7</b></dt><dd>is a view of an inner surface of a used crucible made according to a
conventional process;</dd><dt><b>Figure 8</b></dt><dd>is a partial view of a preferred silica crucible of the present invention;</dd><dt><b>Figure 9</b></dt><dd>is a detailed view of a portion of a crucible wall of the present invention; and</dd><dt><b>Figure 10</b></dt><dd>is a view showing an example of the aluminum and calcium concentration
in a portion of a crucible wall of the present invention.</dd></dl></p><p num="0012">Figures 1-10 presented in conjunction with this description are views of only particular
portions―rather than complete portions―of a silica crucible and an apparatus (and
associated method) for making the same.</p><heading><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0013">The following description provides specific details in order to provide a thorough
understanding of the present invention. The skilled artisan would understand,
however, that the present invention can be practiced without employing these specific
details. Indeed, the present invention can be practiced by modifying the illustrated
crucibles and methods and can be used in conjunction with techniques conventionally
used in the industry. </p><p num="0014">The crucibles of the present invention can be made using any suitable apparatus
known in the art. One suitable apparatus employs an electrical arc, such as described
in U.S. Patent No. 4,416,680, the disclosure of which is incorporated herein by
reference. Another suitable apparatus is illustrated in Figure 1. In Figure 1, gas
permeable mold 104 is installed in a vacuum-tight casing 105. The mold and casing
rotate around a shaft 21 connected to an evacuation system through a rotary union.
The grain 110 is supplied using any suitable means to the mold 104 and is fused by
an electrical arc 106 created between electrodes 107.</p><p num="0015">The configuration and the size of mold 104 depends on the desired configuration and
size of crucible 108 to be produced. Mold 104 may be made of any suitable material
having a satisfactory heat resistance and mechanical strength, yet which may be
formed into any desired configuration. Examples of suitable materials include
stainless steel or graphite.</p><p num="0016">Crucible 108 is formed on the inner surface of mold 104 by any suitable process. One
suitable process is described in U.S. Patent No. 4,528,163, the disclosure of which is
incorporated herein by reference. In this process, mold 104 is rotated about rotating
shaft 21. High-purity silicon dioxide grain 110 is then supplied and directed toward the
inner surface of mold 104. The grain is then heated to form the crucible 108, leaving
unfused grain 109 between the crucible and the mold. Any suitable means known in
the art for heating the grain can be used in the present invention, including the
electrical arc discussed above.</p><p num="0017">The silica grain 110 supplied in the process of the present invention may be of any
suitable size which will melt and form a crucible under the operating conditions. The
grain may be crystalline, amorphous, or a mixture thereof and preferably is of a high
purity so impurities in the crucible can be minimized. If desired, the grain can be
purified before being supplied to the crucible-making operation by any suitable
process known in the art. See, for example, U.S. Patent No. 5,637,284, the
disclosure of which is incorporated herein by reference. </p><p num="0018">In one aspect of the invention, the supplied grain 110 contains at least one gettering
agent. The gettering agent, as described below, combines with other impurities in the
inner layer during the process of making the inner layer of the crucible walls. The
combined gettering agent and the impurities are later removed, thus increasing the
purity of the inner layer. Any suitable gettering agent which accomplishes this
function can be used in the present invention. Examples of suitable getting agents
include aluminum-containing materials such as aluminum or aluminum oxide.</p><p num="0019">The concentration of the gettering agent in the supplied grain 110 depends on the
amount needed to getter the desired impurities. In one aspect of the invention, such
as when aluminum is used, the concentration of the gettering agent is greater than
about 10 ppm, and preferably ranges from about 10 to about 15 ppm. The gettering
agent can be automatically contained in the silica grain or can be added to the grain
to obtain the desired concentration.</p><p num="0020">It is known in the art to obtain a low concentration of Al on the inner surface of the
crucible by normal fusion of silica grain by an electrical arc, followed by etching the
inner surface with HF acid. See, for example, Japanese Patent JP 63-166791, the
disclosure of which is incorporated herein by reference. The crucibles formed by this
method, however, are defective as they exhibit quick bubble evolution and growth in
the inner layer.</p><p num="0021">To overcome this defect, the present invention makes an inner layer which exhibits
little to no bubble growth. This advantage is achieved using the process of the
present invention, which employs a large electrical power in a short time period
during the fusion process. This electrical "burst" contributes to a high concentration of
aluminum on an innermost portion of the inner layer. Thus, it is important to use
aluminum-containing silica grain, preferably with an aluminum concentration higher
than about 12 ppm.</p><p num="0022">After the grain is supplied to the rotating mold, a quartz glass or silica web (or similar
structure) is formed from the grain. An exemplary silica web 6 is illustrated in Figure 
2, where each string or strand of the web is connected to another strand. The silica
web can be formed by any process which converts the quartz grain from a powder
form to any partially continuous layer such as a web, lacework, lattice, mesh, or the
like. In a preferred aspect of the invention, the silica web is formed by heating the
grain quickly at a high power.</p><p num="0023">The quick heating process and high power fuses the grain into a silica web of low
viscosity. Because of the surface tension of the fused silica, a substantially complete
continuous layer is not formed at this stage. Rather, a web structure similar to that
shown in Figure 2 is formed provided that the power is quick enough and high
enough. The web structure has a high surface to bulk ratio and a low viscosity,
allowing the bubbles created during this stage to escape to the surface of the
individual strings or strands of the web.</p><p num="0024">The speed and temperature of the heating and the power required in this conversion
stage can be any combination which produces the desired web structure. In one
aspect of the invention, the quartz grain is heated by an electric arc starting at a low
power, e.g., a power of about 150 KVA. The power is then ramped to a higher power,
e.g., a power ranging from about 500 KVA to about 900 KVA, depending on the
diameter of the crucible. The ramping period can range from about 8 to about 30
seconds depending on the crucible size and the peak power value.</p><p num="0025">A higher power (i.e., more than about 900 KVA) or shorter ramping period (i.e., less
than 8 seconds) may be acceptable depending on the size of the crucible. For
example, the above ranges for the power and the ramping period are employed for
crucibles with diameters ranging from about 14 to about 24 inches. If larger crucibles
are made (i.e., a 40-inch crucible), the power needed may need to be higher (i.e.,
1500 KVA) and ramp may be slower. Slower ramping, however, such as more than
30 seconds may not work to obtain the necessary silica web structure.</p><p num="0026">The amount of grain in mold 104 that is formed into the web structure is important. If
too much of the grain 8 is formed into the web structure (which, as described below, 
is later converted into the inner layer), not enough grain will be left to sinter and form
the outer layer of the crucible (as described below). Thus, only a selected inner
portion of grain is converted to the web structure and the outer portion of grain is left
in an unfused state. In one aspect of the invention, the web structure is formed on a
substantially unfused grain bed.</p><p num="0027">Next, as shown in Figure 3, the web structure is then converted to a substantially
bubble-free, substantially continuous inner layer 2 depending on the mass of the
silica web. The thickness of the inner layer 2 can be any suitable thickness known in
the art, and is preferably about 2 mm.</p><p num="0028">The silica web can be converted to the substantially continuous layer through any
suitable process which "fills in" the voids present between the strands in the web
structure, e.g., through merging of the strands of the silica web. Since each individual
strand is bubble-free and continues to remain bubble-free as the strands merge, the
resulting inner layer also becomes essentially bubble-free. In one aspect of the
invention, one suitable process for this conversion includes continuously heating the
silica web. The continuous heating causes the merging of the individual strands in the
web, thereby creating the substantially continuous layer. This continuous heating is
usually carried out at a temperature ranging from about 2000°C to about 2600°C for
about 10 to about 120 seconds.</p><p num="0029">Next, the outer quartz grain which has not been converted to the silica web (and then
to the inner layer) is then fused into silica glass to form the outer layer 4 of the
crucible as illustrated in Figure 3. The outer quartz grain can be fused through any
suitable process, such as a sintering process, which causes the individual grains to
fuse together and form a continuous layer. This process is substantially similar to any
of the known techniques to make bubble-containing crucibles. See, for example, U.S.
Patent No. 4,528,163, the disclosure of which is incorporated herein by reference.</p><p num="0030">Optionally, the above process can be modified slightly to obtain a three-layer crucible
as illustrated in Figure 8. In this process, the inner layer (converted from the silica 
web) is made on a known double-layer crucible. The double-layer crucible can be
prepared by a controlled vacuum fusion process, which is described in JP1-197381.
This controlled vacuum fusion process is a modification of the process for making a
transparent crucible described in U.S. Patent No. 4,416,680. As the crucible is made
by fusing the grain, layer by layer from the inside to the outside, a transparent-translucent
double-layer crucible can be made by stopping the vacuum intermediate
of the total fusion cycle.</p><p num="0031">In one aspect of the method of the present invention, a very high and quick heating is
used to make the web structure. Because the web structure is open to gas flow, a
vacuum is not applied to the fused silica glass. After obtaining the continuous inner
layer 101, which is a no bubble growth layer, from the web structure, a vacuum is
applied to make a transparent layer 102 beneath the inner layer 101. The transparent
layer 102 fused under the vacuum exhibits bubble growth. Thus; a bubble-growth
transparent layer 102 is covered by a no-bubble-growth transparent layer 101. Then,
stopping the vacuum and continuing the heating yields the translucent outer layer
103.</p><p num="0032">As described above, high temperatures are used during the heating stages used to
form the inner layer 2 or 101. At these high temperatures, silica sublimates from the
surface of the inner layer of the crucible. Aluminum in the form or aluminum oxide
(alumina), however, is very stable at such high temperatures and does not sublimate
as quick as silica, thus remaining in the inner layer. As the silica sublimates near the
bulk surface, the concentration of aluminum near the surface increases while the
concentration of silica decreases.</p><p num="0033">This sublimation results in two layers (or regions) in inner layer 2: an aluminum-rich
innermost layer 111 and a bulk inner layer 112 as illustrated in Figure 9. In one
aspect of the present invention, the concentration of the aluminum ranges from about
40 ppm to about 200 ppm, on average, when the innermost layer 111 is about 100
micrometers in thickness. The concentration of Al, of course, varies over the distance
of the crucible wall and is higher the closer to the innermost surface of the inner layer. </p><p num="0034">A representative profile of the Al concentration in the crucible wall is depicted in
Figure 10.</p><p num="0035">As known in the industry, Al atoms in silica glass attract atoms of alkaline elements,
e.g., Li, Na, K, Rb, Cs, and Fr. Al atoms are relatively immobile in silica while atoms
of alkaline elements are relatively mobile at high temperatures. The atoms of the
alkaline elements are trapped by the Al atoms to form a complex. In this manner, the
atoms of the alkaline elements can be gettered by the Al atoms. It is believed that the
aluminum atoms also combine with atoms of the alkaline-earth elements, including
Ca and Mg, to form additional complexes. These alkaline and alkaline-earth elements
are often detrimental because they can accelerate degradation of the crucible.</p><p num="0036">By combining with the alkaline and alkaline-earth elements, the aluminum (as a
gettering agent) getters these impurities from the inner layer. Thus, this gettering
process modifies the impurity concentration of the inner layer 2. As described above,
the concentration of the aluminum is higher in the innermost layer 111 because of the
silica sublimation. Some of the alkaline and alkaline-earth elements in the bulk layer
112 migrate to the innermost layer 111 to combine with Al to form complexes. Thus,
the alkaline and alkaline-earth elements are partially removed from the bulk layer 112
and trapped in the Al-rich innermost layer 111. Consequently, the relative
concentration of the alkaline and alkaline-earth elements in the innermost layer 111
becomes higher and correspondingly lower in bulk layer 112. Representing alkaline
and alkaline-earth group impurities, the calcium concentration profile is schematically
depicted in Figure 10.</p><p num="0037">Next, the crucible is cooled by any suitable process known in the art. Then, the
crucible is measured for the desired size and cut by any suitable process known in
the art.</p><p num="0038">Finally, the aluminum-rich and impurity-rich innermost layer of the inner layer is
removed, leaving an inner layer with a relatively low concentration of impurities. Any
desired thickness of the innermost layer can be removed by the process, but should 
be limited to that portion of the inner layer containing the higher concentration of Al
and alkaline and alkaline-earth elements. In one aspect of the invention, about 60
micrometers of the inner surface is removed. But a larger and/or smaller thickness
can be removed, if desired.</p><p num="0039">This inner surface can be removed by any suitable process which removes the Al-rich
innermost layer leaving the remaining portion of the inner layer. Suitable processes
include mechanical processes like sand-blasting or chemical processes like etching
processes. In a preferred aspect of the invention, the Al-rich innermost layer is
removed by an etching process, such as a chemical etch with an acid. For example,
for a Al-rich innermost layer with a thickness of about 60 micrometers, the etch can
be performed with about 50% HF for more than 15 minutes or at about 25% HF for
more than 300 minutes. Other concentrations and durations, of course, can be used
depending on the thickness desired to be removed. Optionally, other additives or
agents can be used in the etching process to aid in the etching process. For example,
an inorganic acid such as nitric acid may be added to remove other metallic
impurities.</p><p num="0040">After the removal process, the crucible is rinsed, dried, and packaged by any suitable
process known in the art.</p><p num="0041">The process described above yields silica crucible having a substantially pure,
substantially bubble-free inner layer which remains substantially bubble-free during
use. This inner layer maintains a substantially smooth surface during prolonged time
of reaction with molten silicon, such as the increased time needed to make larger size
wafers. Further, the resulting inner layer from the above process has fewer
devitrification spots because―it is believed―the inner layer contains fewer
devitrification agents, such as alkaline and alkaline-earth elements.</p><p num="0042">The following non-limiting examples illustrate the present invention. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0043">Natural quartz grain was obtained and then purified by hydrochloric gas at 1100
degree C in a rotary kiln. The purity of the processed grain is reported in Table 1. The
grain was poured in a vertically rotating mold as illustrated in Figure 1. Starting with
150 KVA, the power was then ramped to 900 KVA in 12 seconds.</p><p num="0044">The heating was then continued at 750 KVA under a vacuum of about 350 torr until
the silica web structure was converted to a transparent, inner layer with a thickness of
about 2 mm shown as 101 in Figure 8. Then, the inner part of the outer layer was
sintered under a vacuum to make another bubble-free layer 102 (see Figure 8). The
vacuum was stopped while the heating was continued at 450 KVA for 240 seconds to
form a bubble-containing outer layer 103 (see Figure 8) on the outside of the
transparent layer. When the fusion cycle was complete, a three-layer crucible was
present with unfused quartz grain left between the crucible and the mold.</p><p num="0045">The inner surface of the inner layer of the crucible was then etched with 50% HF
solution for 15 minutes. The metallic impurities and Si concentration in the etching
solution after etching were analyzed. By normalization procedures using the Si
concentration, it was determined that the etched off layer had an Al concentration of
90 ppm, as well as the concentrations of Li, Na, Ca, and Mg reported in Table 1.</p><p num="0046">The crucible thus obtained was used in a CZ-pulling process for 120 hours, and the
inner surface which had contacted the silicon melt was then observed. The amount of
cristobalite rings 12 and devitrification spots 10 present are illustrated in Figure 6.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0047">Natural quartz grain was obtained and then purified by hydrochloric gas at 1100
degree C in a rotary kiln. The purity of the processed grain is reported in Table 1. The
grain was poured in a vertically rotating mold similar to the one illustrated in Figure 1, 
except for the connection to the vacuum system. Starting with 150 KVA, the power
was then ramped to 900 KVA in 12 seconds.</p><p num="0048">The heating was then continued at 750 KVA until the silica web structure was
converted to a transparent, inner layer with a thickness of about 2 mm. The heating
was continued at 450 KVA for 240 seconds to form a bubble-containing outer layer.
When the fusion cycle was complete, a two-layer crucible was present with unfused
quartz grain left between the crucible and the mold.</p><p num="0049">The inner surface of the inner layer crucible was then etched with 50% HF solution
for 15 minutes. The metallic impurities and Si concentration in the etching solution
after etching were analyzed. By normalization procedures using the Si concentration,
it was determined that the etched off layer had an Al concentration of 90 ppm, as well
as the concentrations of Li, Na, Ca, and Mg reported in Table 1.</p><p num="0050">The crucible thus obtained was used in a CZ-pulling process for 120 hours, and the
inner surface which had contacted the silicon melt was then observed. The amount of
cristobalite rings 12 and devitrification spots 10 present are similar to that illustrated
in Figure 6.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><p num="0051">Natural quartz grain was obtained and then purified by hydrochloric gas at 1100
degree C in a rotary kiln. The purity of the processed grain is reported in Table 1. The
grain was poured in a vertically rotating mold as illustrated in Figure 1.</p><p num="0052">Starting with 100 KVA, the power was then ramped to 450 KVA and maintained for
180 seconds to fuse the grain and make a bubble-containing layer. Then, 2 kg of
grain was supplied at the rate of 200 gram per minute into the arc to deposit the grain
and form a 1.3 mm bubble-free inner layer on the bubble-containing layer. </p><p num="0053">The inner surface of the crucible was then etched with 10% HF solution for 15
minutes. The metallic impurities and Si concentration in the etching solution after
etching were analyzed. By normalization procedures using the Si concentration, it
was determined that there was a small decrease in the Li concentration, but
otherwise the purity has not substantially changed from that in the starting material.</p><p num="0054">The crucible thus obtained was used in a CZ-pulling process for 90 hours, and the
inner surface contacted with the melt was then observed. The inner surface was
almost covered by merged cristobalite rings 12 and many devitrification spots 10, as
shown in Figure 7. The inner surface was also rough with small wavy irregularities.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">Al (wtppm)</entry><entry align="left">Li (wtppm)</entry><entry align="left">Na (wtppm)</entry><entry align="left">Ca (wtppm)</entry><entry align="left">Mg (wtppm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Quartz Grain</entry><entry align="right">10</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="left">&lt;0.1</entry><entry align="right">1.5</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Innermost Layer</entry><entry align="right">90</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="left">0.5</entry><entry align="right">2.4</entry><entry align="left">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Inner Layer: Ex. 1, 2</entry><entry align="right">10</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="left">&lt;0.1</entry><entry align="right">0.6</entry><entry align="left">&lt;0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Inner Layer: Ex. 3</entry><entry align="right">10</entry><entry align="center">0.7</entry><entry align="left">&lt;0.1</entry><entry align="right">1.5</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0055">Having thus described in detail the preferred embodiments of the present invention, it
is to be understood that the invention defined by the appended claims is not to be
limited by particular details set forth in the above description, as many apparent
variations thereof are possible without departing from the spirit or scope thereof.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for making a silica crucible, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing a silica web structure containing a gettering agent;</claim-text><claim-text>converting the web structure to a substantially continuous inner layer so an
innermost portion of the inner layer contains a portion of the gettering agent;</claim-text><claim-text>providing an outer layer; and</claim-text><claim-text>removing the innermost portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, wherein the gettering agent comprises aluminum.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method of claim 2, wherein the concentration of aluminum is greater than
about 10 ppm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, wherein the gettering agent getters alkaline and alkaline
earth group impurities.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, including providing the inner layer by forming a silica web
structure and then converting the structure to a substantially continuous layer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method of claim 5, including forming the silica web structure by providing
quartz grain containing the gettering agent in a rotating mold and quickly heating
an inner portion of the grain at a high power.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method of claim 6, where the heating is performed for about 8 to about 30
seconds at a power ranging from about 500 KVA to about 900 KVA.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method of claim 5, including converting the web structure by heating until the
strands of the web structure are substantially merged.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method of claim 6, including providing the outer layer by sintering the outer
portion of the grain in the rotating mold.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, including removing the inner portion of the inner layer by
an etching process.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The method of claim 10, wherein the etching process uses HF acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A method for making a silica crucible, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing an inner layer with an innermost portion thereof containing a
gettering agent;</claim-text><claim-text>providing an outer layer; and</claim-text><claim-text>removing the innermost portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A method for making a silica crucible, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing an inner layer with an innermost portion thereof containing a
gettering agent, the gettering agent comprising aluminum with a concentration
greater than about 10 ppm;</claim-text><claim-text>providing an outer layer; and</claim-text><claim-text>removing the innermost portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A silica crucible made by the method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing a silica web structure containing a gettering agent;</claim-text><claim-text>converting the web structure to a substantially continuous inner layer so an
innermost portion of the inner layer contains a portion of the gettering agent;</claim-text><claim-text>providing an outer layer; and</claim-text><claim-text>removing the innermost portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A silica crucible made by the method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing an inner layer with an innermost portion thereof containing a
gettering agent;</claim-text><claim-text>providing an outer layer; and</claim-text><claim-text>removing the innermost portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A silica crucible made by the method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing an inner layer with an innermost portion thereof containing a
gettering agent, the gettering agent comprising aluminum with a concentration
greater than about 10 ppm;</claim-text><claim-text>providing an outer layer; and</claim-text><claim-text>removing the innermost portion.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>An intermediate silica body for making a silica crucible, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an inner layer with an innermost portion containing a gettering agent, the
gettering agent comprising aluminum with a concentration greater than about
60 ppm; and</claim-text><claim-text>an outer layer.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>An intermediate structure used to make a silica crucible with a substantially
bubble-free inner layer, the structure comprising a partially continuous layer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The structure of claim 18, wherein the partially continuous layer is a web-like
structure.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>