<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1538154-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1538154" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34442835" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050608"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1538154-A1" status="new" fvid="24363326"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1538154</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050608</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04078170-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04078170</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20041119</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="DK-200301723-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DK</country><doc-number>200301723</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031120</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 225/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 225/34        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07H  21/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07H  21/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/68        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/68        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07H  21/00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Löscher-Zusammensetzung mit Anthraquinon</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Quencher composition comprising anthraquinone moieties</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition avec agent d'étouffement d'antraquinone</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-20030096254-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20030096254</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2004026804-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2004026804</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>D. BARASCH ET AL.:  "Novel anthraquinone derivatives with redox-active functional groups capable of producing free radicals by metabolism: are free radicals essential for cytotoxicity?" EUR. J. MED. CHEM., vol. 34, 1999, pages 597-615, XP008045540</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>MIYASHITA T ET AL:  "Novel dinucleoside phosphotriester unit conjugated with an intercalative moiety in a stereospecific manner enhances thermal stability of an alternate-stranded triple helix" TETRAHEDRON LETTERS, ELSEVIER SCIENCE PUBLISHERS, AMSTERDAM, NL, vol. 44, no. 40, 29 September 2003 (2003-09-29), pages 7399-7402, XP004453432 ISSN: 0040-4039</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>V. GIBSON ET AL.:  "Molecular modelling of anthraquinone-oligonucleotide conjugates" PHARMACEUTICAL SCIENCES, vol. 2, 1996, pages 545-548, XP008045524</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>EXIQON AS</name><address><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>EXIQON A/S</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Exiqon A/S</last-name><address><street>Bygstubben 9</street><city>2950 Vedbaek</city><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LOMHOLT CHRISTIAN</name><address><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MELDGAARD MICHAEL</name><address><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PFUNDHELLER HENRIK</name><address><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LOMHOLT,CHRISTIAN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MELDGAARD, MICHAEL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PFUNDHELLER, HENRIK</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>LOMHOLT,CHRISTIAN</last-name><address><street>Bille Brahes Vej 12, 2. th</street><city>1963 Frederiksberg C</city><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MELDGAARD, MICHAEL</last-name><address><street>Avang 35</street><city>3400 Hillerod</city><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PFUNDHELLER, HENRIK</last-name><address><street>Orbaekgards Allé 806</street><city>2970 Horsholm</city><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Inspicos A/S</last-name><address><street>Böge Allé 5 P.O. Box 45</street><city>2970 Hörsholm</city><country>DK</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IS</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention provides novel quencher composition comprising anthraquinone
quencher moieties. The anthraquinone quencher moieties are useful as quencher labels when
attached to biomolecules such as natural or modified polynucleotides, oligonucleotides,
nucleosides, nucleotides, carbohydrates and peptides. For example, polynucleotides can be
labeled at the 3' terminus with fluorescence quencher solid support compositions, and
polynucleotides can be labeled at internally or at the 5' terminus. The detectable probes may
have a format like molecular beacons, scorpion probes, sunrise probes, conformationally
assisted probes and TaqMan probes.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="87"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">The present invention provides new quencher compositions, including anthraquinone
quencher moieties that are useful as quencher labels when attached to biomolecules such as
natural or modified polynucleotides, nucleosides, nucleotides, carbohydrates and peptides.</p><p num="0002">Also provided are methods of using the quencher compositions as probes and methods of
using the probes.</p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0003">The intensity of fluorescence can be decreased by a wide variety of processes overall called
quenching. For probes with a stem structure, e.g. molecular beacons and scorpion probes, or
other pair of probes, e.g. kissing probes and competitive hybridisation probes, where the
reporter dye and quencher are brought into close proximity, the main mechanism of
quenching is static or contact quenching where the energy from the fluorophore reporter dye
is transferred to the quencher which then dissipates the energy as heat without fluorescence
(J.R. Lakowicz, Principles of fluorescence spectroscopy, 1999, Kluwer Academic/Plenum
Publishers, New York). Static quenching occurs through the formation of a ground state
complex where the reporter dye and quencher moieties bind together to form a ground state
complex - an intramolecular dimer. Förster resonance energy transfer (FRET or RET) is the
mechanism which commonly is cited as controlling fluorescence quenching in probes without
a stem structure, e.g. TaqMan probes (Marras et. al., Nucleic Acid Res., 2002, 30, e122).
FRET is a process that occurs whenever the emission spectrum of a fluorophore overlaps with
the absorption spectrum of the acceptor molecule e.g. the quencher (J.R. Lakowicz, ibid.).
For optimal FRET quenching the reporter and quencher moieties should be chosen so the
spectral overlap between the emission fluorescence and the quencher absorption is optimal.
The efficiency of the process is dependent on 1/r<sup>6</sup> (Förster distance) where r is the
fluorophore - quencher distance (T. Förster, Ann. Phys., 1948, 2, 55). In another collisional
quenching mechanism (Dexter quenching) the excited state fluorophore is deactivated during
a diffusive encounter with the quencher. Traditionally, dual-labelled probes have been
designed focusing on choosing a matched fluorophore - quencher pair for optimal FRET
quenching. It has recently been proposed that fluorophore - quencher pairs in non-stem dual
labelled probes also should be chosen for increasing static quenching through the formation
of the ground-state complex - the intramolecular dimer - as this was found to be an
extremely effective quenching method (Johansson et al, J. Am. Chem. Soc., 2002, 124, 
6950-6956; Johansson and Cook, Chem. Eur. J., 2003, 9, 3466-3471). Thus, fluorophore -
quencher pairs with an inherent affinity of each other are suited for ground-state complex
formation resulting potentially in increased quenching. Quenchers can be fluorescent e.g.
TAMRA (tetramethylrhodamine) or non-fluorescent e.g. derivatives of 4-(dimethylamino)azobenzene
(Dabcyl). Non-fluorescent quenchers are also referred to as dark
quenchers. Fluorescent quenchers have 2 significant limitations: The presence of background
fluorescence and the preclusion of detection of reporter fluorescence at the acceptor
fluorescence emission. Thus, preferred quenchers are dark quenchers.</p><p num="0004">1,4-Diaminoanthraquinones have earlier been incorporated into oligodeoxynucleotides using
phosphoramidite chemistry. The 1,4-diaminoanthraquinone dark quencher LQ1 ("LQ1") was
incorporated into the 5'-end of DNA molecular beacons (May et. al., Chem. Commun., 2003,
970-971) with either FAM or Cy5 as a fluorophore. The LQ1 quencher has an absorption
range of 500-700 nm and is thus better suited as a quencher for long wavelength dyes like
Cy5 compared to other non-anthraquinone quenchers as e.g. dabcyl which on the contrary is
more suited for shorter wavelength dyes like e.g. FAM. A structurally related 1,4-diaminoanthraquinone
dark quencher called IOWA Black-3.1™ ("IOWA Black") is available
from Integrated DNA Technologies (www.idtdna.com). IOWA Black contains an α-aminoaryl
group compared to an α-aminoalkyl group in LQ1 thus having a higher extinction cooefficient
at higher wavelength compared to LQ1. The LQ1 and IOWA Black phosphoramidite quenchers
can only be incorporated at the 5'-end of oligonucleotides when using standard
phosphoramidite chemistry on DNA synthesizers and thus cannot be incorporated in the
preferred 3'-end of or internally in oligonucleotide molecules. May et al. (Chem. Commun.,
2003, 970-971) has prepared the 1,4-diaminoanthraquinone dark quencher molecule LQ2
which was attached to controlled pore glass (CPG) via an amide containing linker and a
deoxyribose sugar. With this approach the 1,4-diaminoanthraquinone dark quencher
molecule LQ2 can be incorporated into the 3'-end but not internally nor in the 5'-end of the
oligonucleotide molecule. When LQ2 modified oligonucleotides are deprotected after
oligonucleotide synthesis using standard deprotection conditions (concentrated aqueous
ammonia) the LQ2 molecule is cleaved from the oligonucleotide due to the labile amide bonds
in the linker. Alternatively, LQ2 modified oligonucleotides can be deprotected using
water:methanol:tert-butylamine (2:1:1) or ammonium hydroxide: concentrated aqueous
methylamine (1:1) mixtures where the use of the latter mixture results in the cleanest
product. However, these procedures require either the use of N-DMF protected G
phosphoramidites or N-acetyl protected C phosphoramidites, respectively, e.g. nucleoside
phosphoramidites containing non-standard protecting groups. </p><p num="0005">In summary, there is a need for α-amino substituted anthraquinone dark quenchers that can
be easily synthesized, are inexpensive and are capable of being incorporated internally as
well as in the 3'- end and 5'-end of oligonucleotide molecules.</p><p num="0006">Furthermore, a series of quenchers having similar physical properties for e.g. increased static
quenching through ground-state complex formation, but distinct spectral properties would be
particular advantageous.</p><p num="0007">WO 2004/026804 A1 was filed before, but was published after, the priority date of the
present application. WO 2004/026804 A1 discloses various anthraquinone quencher dyes,
their preparation and use.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0008">The present invention provides quencher compositions of the formula (II), cf. claim 2.</p><p num="0009">The present invention further provides quencher compositions of the formula (III), cf. claims
1 and 5.</p><p num="0010">The present invention also provides novel, α-amino substituted anthraquinone compounds, in
particular mono-, di-, tri- and tetra-α-amino substituted anthraquinone compounds.</p><p num="0011">The anthraquinone compounds are useful as quencher labels when attached to biomolecules
such as natural or modified polynucleotides, nucleosides, nucleotides, carbohydrates and
peptides. The anthraquinone compounds are useful for labelling when attached to
biomolecules, in particular for the use as quencher labels.</p><p num="0012">The present invention further provides microarrays, methods for probing a microarray,
labelled nucleosides and nucleotides, methods for labelling polynucleotides, methods for
primer extension, methods for oligonucleotide ligation, methods for hybridization detection, a
kit for primer extension.</p><p num="0013">The quencher labeled biomolecules may further contain fluorescent reporter moieties, which
form energy transfer pairs.</p><p num="0014">Other aspects of the invention include methods of labeling polynucleotides and polypeptides
with the di, tri or tetra-a-amino anthraquinone quencher moieties of the invention. For
example, polynucleotides can be labeled at the 3' terminus with fluorescence quencher solid 
support compositions. Polynucleotides can be labeled at internally or at the 5' terminus with a
di, tri or tetra-α-amino anthraquinone quencher phosphoramidite.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0015"><sl><li>Figures 1-9 illustrate the synthetic routes for various quenchers as described in more detail in
the Examples section.</li><li>Figure 10 illustrates the result from performing real time PCR with probes carrying either the
<b>Q1</b> (<b>3</b>) or the <b>Q2</b> (<b>6</b>) quencher together with the fluorecein dye.</li><li>Figure 11 illustrates the result from performing real time PCR with probes carrying the <b>Q1
(3)</b> as an internal quencher incorporated in a LNA/DNA oligonucleotide.</li><li>Figures 12-20 illustrate UV spectra for the quencers <b>(1), (4), (7), (11), (15), (18), (20),
(23)</b> and <b>(26)</b>.</li></sl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0016">The present invention relates to a quencher composition of the formula (II):
<img id="img-00040001" orientation="unknown" wi="52" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
wherein Y is nitrogen or
<img id="img-00040002" orientation="unknown" wi="20" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040002.tif" inline="no" he="16"/>
wherein R<sup>9</sup> is hydrogen, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>-alkyl, or aryl;

L<sup>1</sup>, L<sup>2</sup> and L<sup>3</sup> are each, independently, a bond or a linker;

X is a biomolecule or a protected form thereof, or an acid-labile or base-labile protecting
group;
 
wherein the biomolecule is selected from an amino acid, a polypeptide, a nucleoside, a
nucleotide, and a polynucleotide, and optionally further comprises a fluorophore;

Z is a bond or selected from -H, -CO<sub>2</sub>H -OH, -NH<sub>2</sub>, -NHR<sup>10</sup>, -N(R<sup>10</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, -SH, a phosphate, a
nucleotide, a substituted nucleotide, a polynucleotide, a substituted polynucleotide, an ester,
a cleavable linker, a solid support, a reactive linking group, and a label;

all of which are optionally substituted with a label or a solid support;

and wherein R<sup>10</sup> is selected from C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl, and aryl,

Q is a compound of the formula (I)
<img id="img-00050001" orientation="unknown" wi="83" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050001.tif" inline="no" he="39"/>
wherein at least one, two, three or four of R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>4</sup>, R<sup>5</sup> or R<sup>8</sup> are each, independently selected
from substituted or non-substituted amino-alkyl, amino-aryl and amino-alkylaryl, and the
remaining R<sup>1</sup> to R<sup>8</sup> groups are each, independently hydrogen or substituted or non-substituted
hydroxy, amino, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl or alkoxy;

and wherein Q is attached to the linker L<sup>1</sup> either through one of the α-amino groups or
through one of the aryl carbons of the quencher moiety.</p><p num="0017">The invention also relates to a quencher composition of the formula (III):
<img id="img-00050002" orientation="unknown" wi="55" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050002.tif" inline="no" he="17"/>
wherein L<sup>1</sup> and L<sup>2</sup> are each, independently a bond or a linker;

X is a biomolecule or a protected form thereof, or an acid-labile or base labile protecting
group;
 
wherein the biomolecule is selected from an amino acid, a polypeptide, a nucleoside, a
nucleotide and a polynucleotide, and optionally further comprises a fluorophore;

Z is a bond or selected from -H, -CO<sub>2</sub>H, -OH, -NH<sub>2</sub>, -NHR<sup>10</sup>, -N(R<sup>10</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, -SH, a phosphate, a
nucleotide, a substituted nucleotide, a polynucleotide, a substituted polynucleotide, an ester,
a cleavable linker, a solid support, a reactive linking group, and a label;

all of which are optionally substituted with a label or a solid support;

and wherein R<sup>10</sup> is selected from C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl, and aryl,

Q is a compound of the formula (I)
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="88" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="44"/>
wherein at least one, two, three or four of R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>4</sup>, R<sup>5</sup> or R<sup>8</sup> are each, independently selected
from substituted or non-substituted amino-alkyl, amino-aryl and amino-alkylaryl, and the
remaining R<sup>1</sup> to R<sup>8</sup> groups are each, independently hydrogen or substituted or non-substituted
hydroxy, amino, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl or alkoxy; and wherein Q is attached to the
linkers L<sup>1</sup> and L<sup>2</sup> at two different positions, either through one of the α-aminogroups or
through the aryl carbons of the quencher moiety.</p><p num="0018">In view of the publications of WO 2004/026804 A1, quencher compositions represented by
the whole content of European patent application No. 20030759288 are preferably explicitly
disclaimed from the quencher compositions of the formulae (II) and (III).</p><p num="0019">In the quencher compositions of the formula (II), L<sup>1</sup>, L<sup>2</sup> and L<sup>3</sup> are preferably each,
independently selected from C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkyldiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkoxydiyl, alkylaryl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylaminodiyl,
C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylamidediyl, aryldiyl and 1-20 ethyleneoxy units.</p><p num="0020">In the quencher composition of the formula (III), L<sup>1</sup> and L<sup>2</sup> are preferably each,
independently a bond or a linker, said linker being selected from alkylaryl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkyldiyl, 
C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkoxydiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylaminodiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylamidediyl, aryldiyl and 1-20 ethyleneoxy
units.</p><p num="0021">In preferred embodiments, the group X in the quencher compositions of the formulae (II) and
(III) is a biomolecule comprising a fluorophore and Z is a nucleotide or a polynucleotide both
of which are optionally substituted with a label or a solid support.</p><p num="0022">In other embodiments, e.g. where the quencher compositions of the formulae (II) and (III)
are prepared for further extension with nucleotides and polynucleotides, X is an acid labile
protecting group and Z is a reactive linking group of the formula (IV):
<img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="72" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/>
wherein R<sup>11</sup> and R<sup>12</sup> are individually selected from isopropyl, methyl, ethyl, and C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>14</sub> aryl, or
R<sup>11</sup> and R<sup>12</sup> are, when taken together, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>11</sub> cycloalkyl or morpholine; and R<sup>13</sup> is C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl,
substituted C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl, C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>14</sub> aryl or a protecting group; in particular R<sup>11</sup> and R<sup>12</sup> are both
isopropyl and R<sup>13</sup> is cyanoethyl. X as the protecting group is typically selected from the group
consisting of DMT, MMT, trityl, substituted trityl, pixyl and trialkylsilyl.</p><p num="0023">In still further embodiments, the quencher composition is immobilized on a solid support in a
manner so that the quencher composition can be cleaved from said solid support. In such
embodiments, Z may have a structure of the formula (V):
<img id="img-00070002" orientation="unknown" wi="70" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070002.tif" inline="no" he="14"/>
wherein A is a cleavable linker selected from the structures (Va-Vf): <img id="img-00080001" orientation="unknown" wi="58" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080001.tif" inline="no" he="20"/><img id="img-00080002" orientation="unknown" wi="126" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080002.tif" inline="no" he="21"/><img id="img-00080003" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080003.tif" inline="no" he="26"/><img id="img-00080004" orientation="unknown" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080004.tif" inline="no" he="27"/>
wherein R<sup>14</sup> is C<sub>1-12</sub> alkyl or C<sub>1-12</sub> alkoxy; R<sup>15</sup> is alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl or alkoxy; L<sup>4</sup> and L<sup>5</sup> are
independently selected from a bond and a linker, said linker being selected from C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkyldiyl,
C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkoxydiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylaminodiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylamidediyl, aryldiyl and 1-20
ethyleneoxy units; G is a bond, a nucleotide, a substituted nucleotide, a polynucleotide, a
substituted polynucleotide or a hybridization-stabilizing moiety; and B is a solid support.</p><p num="0024">In one variant of the above, G is a hybridization-stabilizing moiety, e.g. comprising the
structure:
<img id="img-00080005" orientation="unknown" wi="87" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080005.tif" inline="no" he="55"/>
wherein L designates the sites of attachment to L<sup>2</sup> and L<sup>5</sup>. </p><p num="0025">In the above embodiment, the solid support is typically selected from polystyrene, controlled-pore-glass
(CPG), silica gel, silica, polyacrylamide, a magnetic material, polyacrylate,
hydroxyethylmethacrylate, polyamide, polyethylene, and polyethyleneoxy, and copolymers
and grafts of such.</p><p num="0026">The form of the solid support is typically selected from a particle, a bead (e.g. a magnetic
bead), a membrane, a frit, a fiber, a tube, a capillary, a slide, a plate, a micromachined chip,
an alkanethiol-gold layer, a non-porous surface, an addressable array, and polynucleotide-immobilizing
medium.</p><p num="0027">In one important embodiment which is further described below and illustrated in the
examples section, X is a polynucleotide comprising a fluorescent dye.</p><p num="0028">In some variants hereof, the polynucleotide comprises one or more N-[2-(aminoethyl)]-glycine
units having a nucleobase attached to nitrogen through a methylene carbonyl linkage.
Such units are normally known as units of a PNA molecule.</p><p num="0029">In other variants hereof, which are particularly preferred, the polynucleotide comprises one
or more of 2'-4' or 3'-4' bicyclic sugar modifications. Such sugar modifications are normally
known as LNA.</p><p num="0030">Particularly interesting variants of the quencher composition (III) are those wherein L<sup>1</sup> and L<sup>2</sup>
are each, independently a bond or a linker; X is a polynucleotide comprising a fluorescent
dye; Z is a nucleotide or a polynucleotide both of which are optionally substituted with a label
or a solid support; and Q is as described above.</p><p num="0031">In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the α-amino substituted anthraquinone
compounds of the formula (I) are di-α-amino substituted.</p><p num="0032">With respect to the particular quencher compound, Q, it is believed that those selected from
1,4-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone <b>(1),</b> 1-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-4-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(2),</b> 1,5-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(4),</b> 1-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-5-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(5),</b> 1,4-bis-(4-(2-hydroxyethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone <b>(7),</b> 1-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-4-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(8),</b> and 1,8-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone, are particularly
useful for the quencher compositions of the formula (II), and that those selected from 1,4-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(1)</b>, 1,5-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(4),</b> 1,4-bis-(4-(2-hydroxyethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone <b>(7),</b> and 1,8-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone, 
are particularly useful for the quencher
compositions of the formula (III).</p><p num="0033">As alternatives, quencher compounds, Q, selected from 1,4-bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-6-methylanthraquinone
<b>(11),</b> 1-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-4-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-6(7)-methyl-anthraquinone
<b>(12),</b> 1,4-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-6-methyl-anthraquinone
<b>(15),</b> 1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-carboxy-anthraquinone <b>(17),</b>
1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(6,7-dihydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(7-dimethoxytrityloxy-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone
<b>(18)</b>, 1,4-bis(propylamino)-6-carboxy-anthraquinone,
1,4-bis(propylamino)-6-(N-(6,7-dihydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,4-bis(propylamino)-6-(N-(7-dimethoxytrityloxy-6-hydroxy-4-oxoheptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,5-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(20),</b> 1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-5-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(21),</b> 1,8-bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(23),</b> 1-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-8-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(24),</b> 1,8-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(26),</b> and 1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-8-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(27),</b> are believed to be useful for the quencher
compositions of the formula (II), and quencher compounds, Q, selected from 1,4-bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-6-methylanthraquinone
<b>(11),</b> 1,4-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-6-methyl-anthraquinone
<b>(15),</b> 1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(6,7-dihydroxy-4-oxoheptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(7-dimethoxytrityloxy-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone
<b>(18),</b> 1,4-bis(propylamino)-6-(N-(6,7-dihydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,5-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone <b>(20),</b> 1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-5-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(21),</b> 1,8-bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(23),</b> 1-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-8-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(24),</b> 1,8-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(26),</b> and 1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-8-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(27),</b> are believed to be useful for quencher
compositions of the formula (III).</p><p num="0034">It should be understood that although the quencher compounds, Q, are mentioned as the
discrete molecules, Q is attached to the linker(s) L<sup>1</sup> (and L<sup>2</sup>) at one or two different positions,
either through one of the α-aminogroups or through the aryl carbons of the quencher moiety.
Preferably, however, Q is attached to the linker(s) L<sup>1</sup> (and L<sup>2</sup>) via the O-atom of the hydroxy
groups. </p><p num="0035">It is believed that some of the quencher compounds are novel as such, thus, it should be
understood that the present invention also relates to quencher compounds selected from 1,4-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(1),</b> 1-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-4-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(2),</b> 1-(3-(2-cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)propylamino)-4-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(3),</b> 1,5-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(4)</b>, 1-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-5-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(5),</b> 1-(3-(cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)propylamino)-5-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(6),</b> 1,4-bis-(4-(2-hydroxyethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(7),</b> 1-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-4-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(8),</b> 1-(4-(2-(2-cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)-phosphinoxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-4-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(9)</b>, and 1,8-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone; or alternatively
selected from 6-methyl-Quinizarin <b>(10),</b> 1,4-bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-6-methyl-anthraquinone
<b>(11),</b> 1-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-4-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-6(7)-methyl-anthraquinone
<b>(12),</b> 1-(3-(2-cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)-phosphinoxy)propylamino)-4-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-6(7)-methyl-anthraquinone
<b>(13),</b> 1,4-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-6-methyl-anthraquinone <b>(15),</b>
1,4-Dihydroxy-2,3-dihydro-6-carboxy-anthraquinone <b>(16),</b> 1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-carboxy-anthraquinone
<b>(17),</b> 1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(6,7-dihydroxy-4-oxoheptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(7-dimethoxytrityloxy-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone
<b>(18),</b> 1,4-Bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(7-(2-cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone
<b>(19),</b> 1,4-bis(propylamino)-6-carboxy-anthraquinone,
1,4-bis(propylamino)-6-(N-(6,7-dihydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,4-bis(propylamino)-6-(N-(7-dimethoxytrityloxy-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,5-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)-phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(20),</b> 1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-5-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(21),</b> 1-(4-(2-(cyanoethoxy-(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-5-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(22),</b> 1,8-bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(23),</b> 1-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-8-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)-propylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(24),</b> 1,8-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(26),</b> and 1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-8-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
<b>(27).</b></p><p num="0036">Another aspect of the present invention relates to a polynucleotide probe containing at least
one quencher composition as described above. In addition to the quencher moiety, the probe
preferably further comprises at least one quenchable label. Typically, the quenchable label is 
separated from the quencher by a nuclease susceptible site. In this case, the polynucleotide
probe is typically blocked for extension by the polymerase in the 3'end.</p><p num="0037">The probe described above, can typically adopt at least 1 conformation when not bound to
the target where the label is quenched by the quencher, and at least one other conformation
when the probe is bound to the target where the label is at least partially unquenched by the
quencher. In one variant, a 3' part and a 5' part of the polynucleotide are perfectly
complementary such as to form a hairpin structure when not bound to the target.</p><p num="0038">More generally, it is preferred that the polynucleotide probe comprises at least one target
recognition region complementary to a target gene.</p><p num="0039">The polynucleotide probe, including the variants described above, typically has a length of 5
to 50 nucleotides.</p><p num="0040">A further aspect of the invention relates to a method of primer extension comprising:
<sl><li>annealing a polynucleotide primer to a target polynucleotide; and extending the primer by
polymerase-mediated incorporation of a nucleotide 5'-triphosphate; wherein the primer or
the nucleotide 5'-triphosphate is attached to a quencher moiety of the formula (I) (preferably
as defined as for quencher composition (II) and (III)); whereby a labelled polynucleotide is
formed. Typically, the method further comprises the step of amplifying the target
polynucleotide with nucleotide 5'-triphosphates, a polymerase, and two or more primers
(typically by the polymerase chain reaction, or another nucleic acid amplification method);
wherein the primers are complementary to the target polynucleotide sequence and at least
one primer is attached to a quencher moiety of the formula (I).</li></sl></p><p num="0041">A still further aspect of the invention relates to a method of amplifying a target
polynucleotide comprising nucleotide 5'-triphosphates, a polymerase, two or more primers;
wherein the primers are complementary to the target polynucleotide sequence, and a
detectably labelled probe; wherein at least a part of the detectably labelled probe is
complementary to the target polynucleotide and comprises at least a fluorescent dye and a
quencher moiety of the formula (I) (preferably as defined as for quencher composition (II)
and (III)). Preferably, the method further comprises detecting a signal from the fluorescent
dye of said detectable probe. Typically, the signal is detected at each thermal cycle during
amplification.</p><p num="0042">In a further variant of the method, the polymerase cleaves the detectable probe during
amplification; whereby the fluorescent dye and the quencher moiety are separated. Like
before, the method preferably further comprises detecting a signal from the fluorescent dye 
of said cleaved, detectable probe. Typically, the signal is detected at each thermal cycle
during amplification.</p><p num="0043">Hybridization to the target polynucleotide may be monitored by FRET and used to detect the
target sequence. The probe may be cleaved by nuclease activity of an enzyme during nucleic
acid amplification. Cleavage may generate a detectable signal and used to monitor and detect
nucleic acid hybridization and amplification. The primers and probes may be further labeled
with hybridization-stabilizing moieties, such as minor groove binders.</p><p num="0044">In a still further variant of the method, the fluorescent dye is attached to the 5' terminus or
3' terminus of the detectable probe. Still further, the quencher moiety is attached to the 5'
terminus or 3' terminus of or internally in the detectable probe.</p><p num="0045">In a particular variant of the method, the detectable probe is further labelled with a
hybridization-stabilizing moiety, e.g. a hybridization-stabilizing moiety comprising the
structure:
<img id="img-00130001" orientation="unknown" wi="81" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/>
where L is an attachment site to the detectable probe.</p><p num="0046">In other variants of the method, the detectable probe has a format selected from molecular
beacons, scorpion probes, sunrise probes, conformationally assisted probes and TaqMan
probes.</p><p num="0047">In still other variants of the method, the detectable probe comprises one or more one or
more N-[2-(aminoethyl)]glycine units having a nucleobase attached to nitrogen through a
methylene carbonyl linkage, or the detectable probe comprises one or more of 2'-4' or 3'-4'
bicyclic sugar modifications.</p><p num="0048">A still further aspect of the invention relates to a method of hybridization detection
comprising annealing a probe to a target polynucleotide sequence, wherein the probe is 
covalently attached to a fluorescent dye and a quencher moiety of the formula (I) (preferably
as defined as for quencher composition (II) and (III)); and detecting a signal from the
fluorescent dye.</p><p num="0049">The invention further includes kits or reagents for performing the methods and uses detailed
herein. The kits may contain the fluorescence quencher compositions, biomolecules labeled
with the quencher moieties, and/or other reagents.</p><p num="0050">A still further aspect of the invention relates to a kit for nucleic acid amplification comprising
two or more primers, and a probe with a detectable label and a quencher moiety of the
formula (I) (preferably as defined as for quencher composition (II) and (III)).</p><p num="0051">Another aspect of the invention relates to a kit for primer extension comprising one or more
nucleotide 5'-triphosphates and one or more primers wherein at least one primer is
covalently attached by a linkage to an aryl carbon of a quencher moiety of the formula (I)
(preferably as defined as for quencher composition (II) and (III)).</p><p num="0052">A further aspect of the invention relates to a microarray comprising a quencher moiety of the
formula (I) (preferably as defined as for quencher composition (II) and (III)), said quencher
being conjugated directly to a solid support or to a carrier molecule attached to said solid
support.</p><p num="0053">A still further aspect of the invention relates to a method of probing a microarray for the
presence of a compound, said method comprising: (a) contacting said microarray with a
probe interacting with said compound, said probe comprising a quencher moiety of the
formula (I) (preferably as defined as for quencher composition (II) and (III)); (b) detecting a
difference in a fluorescence property of a member selected from said probe, said compound
and combinations thereof, thereby ascertaining the presence of said compound.</p><p num="0054">A even further aspect of the invention relates to detection systems, for example
<sl><li>(A) a detection system comprising: (a) a target binding entity, (b) a quenchable detectable
label and (c) a quencher composition of the formulae (II) or (III), wherein the quenchable
label and the quencher each are positioned on the target binding entity and/or the target
such that the label is quenched by the quencher when the target binding entity is unbound to
its target, and such that binding of the binding entity to its target will remove the quencher
from the label such that the label is at least partially unquenched; and </li><li>(B) a detection system comprising: (a) a target binding entity, (b) a quenchable detectable
label and (c) a quencher composition of the formulae (II) or (III), wherein the quenchable
label and the quencher each are positioned on the target binding entity and/or the target
such that the label is at least partially unquenched by the quencher when the target binding
entity is unbound to its target, and such that binding of the binding entity to its target will
bring the quencher in vicinity of the label such that the label is at least partially quenched.</li></sl></p><p num="0055">In such detection systems, the target binding entity preferably comprises a polynucleotide,
an antibody, an aptamer, or a ligand.</p><heading><i>Definitions</i></heading><p num="0056">Unless defined otherwise, all technical and scientific terms used herein generally have the
same meaning as commonly understood by one of ordinary skill in the art to which this
invention belongs. Generally, the nomenclature used herein and the laboratory procedures in
cell culture, molecular genetics, organic chemistry and nucleic acid chemistry and
hybridization described below are those well known and commonly employed in the art.
Standard techniques are used for nucleic acid and peptide synthesis.

Generally, enzymatic reactions and purification steps are performed according to the
manufacturer's specifications. The techniques and procedures are generally performed
according to conventional methods in the art and various general references (see generally,
Sambrook et al. MOLECULAR CLONING : A LABORATORY MANUAL, 2d ed. (1989) Cold Spring
Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold Spring Harbor, N. Y., which is incorporated herein by
reference), which are provided throughout this document. The nomenclature used herein and
the laboratory procedures in analytical chemistry, and organic synthetic described below are
those well known and commonly employed in the art. Standard techniques, or modifications
thereof, are used for chemical syntheses and chemical analyses.</p><p num="0057">In the above structural formulae and throughout the present specification, the following
terms have the indicated meaning:</p><p num="0058">The term "alkyl" is used herein to refer to a branched or unbranched, saturated or
unsaturated, monovalent hydrocarbon radical, generally having from about 1-30 carbons and
preferably, from 1-6 carbons. Suitable alkyl radicals include, for example, structures
containing one or more methylene, methine and/or methyne groups. Branched structures
have a branching motif similar to iso-propyl, t-butyl, i-butyl, 2-ethylpropyl, etc. As used
herein, the term encompasses "substituted alkyls" and "cyclic alkyl". "Substituted alkyl"
refers to alkyl as just described including one or more substituents such as, for example, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>-alkyl, 
aryl, acyl, halogen (i.e. alkylhalos, e.g., CF<sub>3</sub>), hydroxy, amino, alkoxy, alkylamino,
acylamino, thioamido, acyloxy, aryloxy, aryloxyalkyl, mercapto, thia, aza, oxo, both
saturated and unsaturated cyclic hydrocarbons, heterocycles and the like. These groups may
be attached to any carbon or substituent of the alkyl moiety. Additionally, these groups may
be pendent from, or integral to, the alkyl chain.</p><p num="0059">The term "alkylaryl" means a radical obtained by combining an alkyl and an aryl group.
Typical alkylaryl groups include phenethyl, ethyl phenyl and the like.</p><p num="0060">The term "amino-alkyl" means amino substituted with alkyl. In a preferred embodiment, the
amino group is attached to the anthraquinone structure.</p><p num="0061">The term "amino-alkylaryl" means amino substituted with alkylaryl. In a preferred
embodiment, the amino group is attached to the anthraquinone structure.</p><p num="0062">The term "amino-aryl" means amino substituted with aryl. In a preferred embodiment, the
amino group is attached to the anthraquinone structure.</p><p num="0063">The terms "annealing" and "hybridization" are used interchangeably and mean the base-pairing
interaction of one nucleic acid with another nucleic acid that results in formation of a
duplex or other higher-ordered structure. The primary interaction is base specific, i.e. A/T
and G/C, by Watson/Crick and Hoogsteen-type hydrogen bonding.</p><p num="0064">The term "aryl" means a monovalent aromatic hydrocarbon radical of 5-14 carbon atoms
derived by the removal of one hydrogen atom from a single carbon atom of a parent
aromatic ring system. Typical aryl groups include, but are not limited to, radicals derived
from benzene, substituted benzene, naphthalene, anthracene, biphenyl, and the like,
including substituted aryl groups. "Substituted aryl" refers to aryl as just described including
one or more substituents such as, for example, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>-alkyl, aryl, acyl, halogen (i.e.
alkylhalos, e.g., CF<sub>3</sub>), hydroxy, amino, alkoxy, alkylamino, acylamino, thioamido, acyloxy,
aryloxy, aryloxyalkyl, mercapto, thia, aza, oxo, both saturated and unsaturated cyclic
hydrocarbons, heterocycles and the like. These groups may be attached to any carbon or
substituent of the aryl moiety.</p><p num="0065">The term "aryldiyl" means an unsaturated cyclic or polycyclic hydrocarbon radical of 5-14
carbon atoms having a conjugated resonance electron system and at least two monovalent
radical centers derived by the removal of two hydrogen atoms from two different carbon
atoms of a parent aryl compound, including substituted aryldiyl groups. </p><p num="0066">The term "biomolecule" encompasses an amino acid, a polypeptide, a nucleoside, a
nucleotide, a polynucleotide, a carbohydrate, a vitamin, a hormone, and any other compound
produced by an organism.</p><p num="0067">The term "alkoxydiyl" as in "C<sub>1</sub>-C <sub>12</sub>-alkoxydiyl" means an alkoxyl group having two
monovalent radical centers derived by the removal of a hydrogen atom from the oxygen and
a second radical derived by the removal of a hydrogen atom from a carbon atom. Typical
alkoxydiyl radicals include, but are not limited to, methoxydiyl (-OCH<sub>2</sub>-) and 1,2-ethoxydiyl or
ethyleneoxy (-OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-).</p><p num="0068">The term "alkylamidediyl" as in "C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylamidediyl" means an alkylamide group having
two monovalent radical centers derived by the removal of a hydrogen atom from the nitrogen
and a second radical derived by the removal of a hydrogen atom from a carbon atom. Typical
alkylamidediyl radicals include, but are not limited to -NHC(O)CH<sub>2</sub>-, -NHC(O)CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-, and
-NHC(O)CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-.</p><p num="0069">The term "alkylaminodiyl" as in "C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylaminodiyl" means an alkylamino group having
two monovalent radical centers derived by the removal of a hydrogen atom from the nitrogen
and a second radical derived by the removal of a hydrogen atom from a carbon atom. Typical
alkylaminodiyl radicals include, but are not limited to -NHCH<sub>2</sub>-, -NHCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-, and -NHCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-.</p><p num="0070">The term "alkyldiyl" as in "C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkyldiyl" means a saturated or unsaturated, branched,
straight chain, cyclic, or substituted hydrocarbon radical of 1-12 carbon atoms, and having
two monovalent radical centers derived by the removal of two hydrogen atoms from the
same or two different carbon atoms of a parent alkane, alkene or alkyne. Typical alkyldiyl
radicals include, but are not limited to, 1,2-ethyldiyl (-CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-), 1,3-propyldiyl
(-CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-), 1,4-butyldiyl (-CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-), and the like.</p><p num="0071">The term "cleavable linker" is a linker which has one or more covalent bonds which may be
broken by the result of a reaction or condition. For example, an ester in a molecule is a linker
that may be cleaved by a reagent, e.g. sodium hydroxide, resulting in a carboxylate-containing
fragment and a hydroxyl-containing product.</p><p num="0072">The term "end-point analysis" refers to a method where data collection occurs only when a
reaction is substantially complete.</p><p num="0073">The term "label" refers to any moiety which can be attached to a molecule and: (i) provides a
detectable signal; (ii) interacts with a second label to modify the detectable signal provided 
by the second label, e.g. FRET; (iii) stabilizes hybridization, i.e. duplex formation; or (iv)
provides a capture moiety, i.e. affinity, antibody/antigen, ionic complexation. Labelling can
be accomplished using any one of a large number of known techniques employing known
labels, linkages, linking groups, reagents, reaction conditions, and analysis and purification
methods. Labels include light-emitting or light-absorbing compounds which generate or
quench a detectable fluorescent, chemiluminescent, or bioluminescent signal (Kricka, L. in
Nonisotopic DNA Probe Techniques (1992), Academic Press, San Diego, pp. 3-28).
Fluorescent reporter dyes useful for labelling biomolecules include fluoresceins (U.S. Pat.
Nos. 5,188,934; 6,008,379; 6,020,481), rhodamines (U.S. Pat. Nos. 5,366,860; 5,847,162;
5,936,087; 6,051,719; 6,191,278), benzophenoxazines (U.S. Pat. No. 6,140,500), energy-transfer
dye pairs of donors and acceptors (U.S. Pat. Nos. 5,863,727; 5,800,996;
5,945,526), and cyanines (Kubista, WO 97/45539), as well as any other fluorescent label
capable of generating a detectable signal. Examples of fluorescein dyes include 6-carboxyfluorescein;
2',4',1,4,-tetrachlorofluorescein; and 2',4',5',7',1,4-hexachlorofluorescein.
See Example 50 and Menchen, U.S. Pat. No. 5,118,934. Another class of labels
are hybridization-stabilizing moieties which serve to enhance, stabilize, or influence
hybridization of duplexes, e.g. interchalators, minor-groove binders, and cross-linking
functional groups (Blackburn, G. and Gait, M. Eds. "DNA and RNA structure" in Nucleic Acids
in Chemistry and Biology, 2Edition, (1996) Oxford University Press, pp. 15-81). Yet another
class of labels ("affinity ligands") effect the separation or immobilization of a molecule by
specific or non-specific capture, for example biotin, digoxigenin, and other haptens (Andrus,
A. "Chemical methods for 5' non-isotopic labelling of PCR probes and primers" (1995) in PCR
2: A Practical Approach, Oxford University Press, Oxford, pp. 39-54). Non-radioactive
labelling methods, techniques, and reagents are reviewed in: Non-Radioactive Labelling, A
Practical Introduction, Garman, A. J. (1997) Academic Press, San Diego.</p><p num="0074">The term "nucleobase" means any nitrogen-containing heterocyclic moiety capable of forming
Watson-Crick hydrogen bonds in pairing with a complementary nucleobase or nucleobase
analogue, e.g. a purine, a 7-deazapurine, or a pyrimidine. Typical nucleobases are the
naturally occurring nucleobases adenine, guanine, cytosine, uracil, thymine, and analogs of
the naturally occurring nucleobases, e.g. 7-deazaadenine, 7-deazaguanine, 7-deaza-8-azaguanine,
7-deaza-8-azaadenine, inosine, nebularine, nitropyrrole, nitroindole, 2-aminopurine,
2-amino-6-chloropurine, 2,6-diaminopurine, hypoxanthine, pseudouridine, pseudocytosine,
pseudoisocytosine, 5-propynylcytosine, isocytosine, isoguanine, 7-deazaguanine, 2-thiopyrimidine,
6-thioguanine, 4-thiothymine, 4-thiouracil, O-methylguanine, N-methyladenine,
O-methylthymine, 5,6-dihydrothymine, 5,6-dihydrouracil, 4-methylindole,
pyrazolo[3,4-D]pyrimidines (U.S. Pat. Nos. 6,143,877 and 6,127,121; WO 01/38584), and
ethenoadenine (Fasman (1989) in Practical Handbook of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology,
pp. 385-394, CRC Press, Boca Raton, Fla.). </p><p num="0075">The term "nucleoside" refers to a compound consisting of a nucleobase linked to the C-1'
carbon of a sugar, such as ribose, arabinose, xylose, and pyranose. The sugar may be
substituted or unsubstituted. Substituted ribose sugars include, but are not limited to, those
riboses in which one or more of the carbon atoms, for example the 2'-carbon atom, is
substituted with one or more of the same or different Cl, F, -R, -OR, -NR<sub>2</sub> or halogen groups,
where each R is independently H, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>-alkyl or C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>14</sub>-aryl. Ribose examples include ribose,
2'-deoxyribose, 2',3'-dideoxyribose, 2'-haloribose, 2'-fluororibose, 2'-chlororibose, and 2'-alkylribose,
e.g. 2'-O-methyl, 4'-[alpha]-anomeric nucleotides, 1'-[alpha]-anomeric
nucleotides, 2'-4'- and 3'-4'-linked and other "locked" or "LNA", bicyclic sugar modifications
(WO 98/22489; WO 98/39352; WO 99/14226). Modifications at the 2'- or 3'-position of
ribose include hydrogen, hydroxy, methoxy, ethoxy, allyloxy, isopropoxy, butoxy, isobutoxy,
methoxyethyl, alkoxy, phenoxy, azido, amino, alkylamino, fluoro, chloro and bromo.
Nucleosides and nucleotides include the natural D optical isomer, as well as the L optical
isomer forms (Garbesi (1993) Nucl. Acids Res. 21:4159-65; Fujimori (1990) J. Amer. Chem.
Soc. 112:7435; Urata, (1993) Nucleic Acids Symposium Ser. No. 29:69-70). When the
nucleobase is purine, e.g. A or G, the ribose sugar is attached to the N-position of the
nucleobase. When the nucleobase is pyrimidine, e.g. C, T or U, the pentose sugar is attached
to the N-position of the nucleobase (Komberg and Baker, (1992) DNA Replication, 2Ed.,
Freeman, San Francisco, Calif.).</p><p num="0076">The term "nucleotide" refers to a phosphate ester of a nucleoside, as a monomer unit or
within a nucleic acid. "Nucleotide 5'-triphosphate" refers to a nucleotide with a triphosphate
ester group at the 5' position, and are sometimes denoted as "NTP", or "dNTP" and "ddNTP"
to particularly point out the structural features of the ribose sugar. The triphosphate ester
group may include sulfur substitutions for the various oxygens, e.g. [alpha]-thio-nucleotide
5'-triphosphates. For a review of nucleic acid chemistry, see: Shabarova, Z. and Bogdanov,
A. Advanced Organic Chemistry of Nucleic Acids, VCH, New York, 1994.</p><p num="0077">As used herein, the terms "polynucleotide" and "oligonucleotide" are used interchangeably
and mean single-stranded and double-stranded polymers of nucleotide monomers, including
2'-deoxyribonucleotides (DNA) and ribonucleotides (RNA) linked by internucleotide
phosphodiester bond linkages, or internucleotide analogs, and associated counter ions, e.g.,
H, NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>, trialkylammonium, Mg<sup>+2</sup>, Na<sup>+</sup> and the like. A polynucleotide may be composed
entirely of deoxyribonucleotides, entirely of ribonucleotides, or chimeric mixtures thereof.
Polynucleotides may be comprised of nucleobase and sugar analogs. Polynucleotides typically
range in size from a few monomeric units, e.g. 5-40 when they are more commonly
frequently referred to in the art as oligonucleotides, to several thousands of monomeric
nucleotide units. Unless denoted otherwise, whenever a polynucleotide sequence is
represented, it will be understood that the nucleotides are in 5' to 3' order from left to right 
and that "A" denotes deoxyadenosine, "C" denotes deoxycytidine, "G" denotes
deoxyguanosine, and "T" denotes thymidine, unless otherwise noted. The polynucleotides or
oligonucleotides are not restricted to naturally occurring nucleotide and may comprise one or
more nucleotide analogues in the sequence. The polynucleotides can be substituted as
disclosed in "Current Protocols In Nucleic Acid Chemistry", edit by S. L. Beaucage et. al., John
Wiley Sons, Inc. 1999, Chapter 4.</p><p num="0078">The term "polypeptide" refers to a polymer including proteins, synthetic peptides, antibodies,
peptide analogs, and peptidomimetics in which the monomers are amino acids and are joined
together through amide bonds. When the amino acids are [alpha]-amino acids, either the L-optical
isomer or the D-optical isomer can be used. Additionally, unnatural amino acids, for
example, valanine, phenylglycine and homoarginine are also included. Commonly
encountered amino acids that are not gene-encoded may also be used in the present
invention. All of the amino acids used in the present invention may be either the D- or L-optical
isomer. In addition, other peptidomimetics are also useful in the present invention.
For a general review, see Spatola, A. F., in Chemistry and Biochemistry of Amino Acids,
Peptides and Proteins, B. Weinstein, eds., Marcel Dekker, New York, p. 267 (1983). The term
"amino acid" refers to naturally occurring and synthetic amino acids, as well as amino acid
analogs and amino acid mimetics that function in a manner choices can be found in many art
recognized references.</p><p num="0079">The expression "enzymatically extendable" in connection with "primer extension" refers to a
nucleotide which is: (i) capable of being enzymatically incorporated onto the terminus of a
polynucleotide chain through the action of a polymerase enzyme, and (ii) capable of
supporting further primer extension. Enzymatically extendable nucleotides include nucleotide
5'-triphosphates, i.e. dNTP and NTP.</p><p num="0080">The term "probe" means a polynucleotide that is capable of forming a duplex structure by
complementary base pairing with a sequence of a target nucleic acid. For example, probes
may be labelled, e.g. with a quencher moiety, or an energy transfer pair comprised of a
fluorescent reporter and quencher.</p><p num="0081">A "protecting group" is a functionality that is removed either through a chemically or
physically interaction whereby a new functional group is formed. An "acid labile protecting
group" is a functionality that is removed when subjected to acidic conditions. Suitable acid
labile protecting groups include trityl (triphenylmethyl), MMT (4-momomethoxytrityl), DMT
(4,4'-dimethoxytrityl), substituted trityl and pixyl (9-phenyl-xanthene-9-yl). A "base labile
protecting group" is a functionality that is removed when subjected to basic conditions.
Suitable base labile protecting groups include acetyl, benzoyl, 2-cyanoethyl, 4-cyano-2-butenyl, 
4-oxo-pentyl and 3-(N-tert-butylcarboxamido)-1-propyl. A "photo-cleavable
protecting group" is a functionality that is removed when irradiated with light of a specific
wavelength.</p><p num="0082">The term "quenching" refers to a decrease in fluorescence of a fluorescent reporter ran
moiety caused by a quencher moiety by energy transfer, regardless of the mechanism.
Hence, illumination of the fluorescent reporter in the presence of the quencher leads to an
emission signal that is less intense than expected, or even completely absent.</p><p num="0083">The term "reactive linking group" refers to a chemically reactive substituent or moiety, e.g. a
nucleophile or electrophile, on a molecule which is capable of reacting with another molecule
to form a covalent bond. Reactive linking groups include active esters, which are commonly
used for coupling with amine groups. For example, N-hydroxysuccinimide (NHS) esters have
selectivity toward aliphatic amines to form aliphatic amide products which are very stable.
Their reaction rate with aromatic amines, alcohols, phenols (tyrosine), and histidine is
relatively low. Reaction of NHS esters with amines under nonaqueous conditions is facile, so
they are useful for derivatization of small peptides and other low molecular weight
biomolecules. Virtually any molecule that contains a carboxylic acid or that can be chemically
modified to contain a carboxylic acid can be converted into its NHS ester. NHS esters are
available with sulfonate groups that have improved water solubility. Reactive linking groups
also include active phosphor compounds normally referred to as phosphoramidites as
described in S.L. Beaucage and M.H. Caruthers, Chapter 3.3 in "Curent Protocols In Nucleic
Acid Chemistry", edit by S. L. Beaucage et. al., John Wiley Sons, Inc. 1999.</p><p num="0084">The term "real-time analysis" refers to periodic monitoring during PCR. Certain systems such
as the ABI 7700 and 7900HT Sequence Detection Systems (Applied Biosystems, Foster City,
Calif.) conduct monitoring during each thermal cycle at a pre-determined or user-defined
point. Real-time analysis of PCR with FRET probes measures fluorescent dye signal changes
from cycle-to-cycle, preferably minus any internal control signals.</p><p num="0085">The term "solid support" refers to any solid phase material upon which a nucleic acid or
polypeptide is synthesized, attached or immobilized. Solid support encompasses terms such
as "resin", "solid phase", and "support". A solid support may be composed of organic
polymers such as polystyrene, polyethylene, polypropylene, polyfluoroethylene,
polyethyleneoxy, and polyacrylamide, as well as co-polymers and grafts thereof. A solid
support may also be inorganic, such as glass, silica, controlled-pore-glass (CPG), or reverse-phase
silica. The configuration of a solid support may be in the form of beads, spheres,
particles, granules, or a surface. Surfaces may be planar, substantially planar, or non-planar.
Solid supports may be porous or non-porous, and may have swelling or non-swelling 
characteristics. A solid support may be configured in the form of a well, depression or other
vessel. A plurality of solid supports may be configured in an array, addressable for robotic
delivery of reagents, or by detection means including scanning by laser illumination and
confocal or deflective light gathering.</p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0086">Processes for preparing compounds for use in the novel quencher compositions are further
illustrated in the following examples, which however, are not to be construed as limiting.</p><p num="0087">The structures of the compounds are confirmed by either elemental analysis (MA) nuclear
magnetic resonance (NMR) or mass spectrometry (MS). NMR shifts (δ) are given in parts per
million (ppm) and only selected peaks are given. "mp" is melting point and is given in °C.
Column chromatography was carried out using the technique described by W.C. Still et al, J.
Org. Chem. 1978, 43, 2923-2925 on Merck silica gel 60 (Art 9385). Compounds used as
starting materials are either known compounds or compounds which can readily be prepared
by methods known per se. UV-Spectra (Figures 12-19) were acquired on a Shimadzu UV-1601(PC)
in a ~10<sup>-6</sup>M concentration of the quencher dissolved in methanol. The synthetic
routes are illustrated in Figures 1-9.</p><heading><i>Example 1: Preparation of 1-(3-(2-cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)-propylamino)-4-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone</i><b>(3)</b></heading><heading><u style="single">1,4-Bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(1)</u></b></heading><p num="0088">Leucoquinizarin (9.9 g; 0.04 mol) is mixed with 3-amino-1-propanol (10 mL) and Ethanol
(200 mL) and heated to reflux for 6 hours. The mixture is cooled to room temperature and
stirred overnight under atmospheric conditions. The mixture is poured into water (500 mL)
and the precipitate is filtered off washed with water (200 mL) and dried. The solid is boiled in
ethylacetate (300 mL), cooled to room temperature and the solid is collected by filtration.
Yield: 8.2 g (56%).</p><heading><u style="single">1-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-4-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraguinone (</u><b><u style="single">2</u></b><u style="single">)</u></heading><p num="0089">1,4-Bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone (7.08 g; 0.02 mol) is dissolved in a mixture of
dry N,N-dimethylformamide (150 mL) and dry pyridine (50 mL). Dimethoxytritylchloride (3.4 
g; 0.01 mol) is added and the mixture is stirred for 2 hours. Additional dimethoxytritylchloride
(3.4 g; 0.01 mol) is added and the mixture is stirred for 3 hours. The mixture is
concentrated under vacuum and the residue is redissolved in dichloromethane (400 mL)
washed with water (2 x 200 ml) and dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). The solution is filtered through a silica
gel pad (Ø 10 cm; h 10 cm) and eluted with dichloromethane until mono-DMT-anthraquinone
product begins to elude where after the solvent is the changed to 2% methanol in
dichloromethane. The pure fractions are combined and concentrated resulting in a blue foam.
Yield: 7.1 g (54%). <sup>1</sup>H-NMR(CDCl<sub>3</sub>): 10.8 (2H, 2xt, J = 5.3 Hz, NH), 8.31 (2H, m, AqH), 7.67
(2H, dt, J = 3.8 and 9.4, AqH), 7.4-7.1 (9H, m, ArH + AqH), 6.76 (4H, m, ArH) 3.86 (2H, q,
J = 5.5Hz, CH<sub>2</sub>OH), 3.71 (6H, s, CH<sub>3</sub>), 3.54 (4H, m, NCH<sub>2</sub>), 3.26 (2H, t, J = 5.7 Hz,
CH<sub>2</sub>ODMT), 2.05 (4H, m, CCH<sub>2</sub>C), 1.74 (1H, t, J = 5 Hz, OH).</p><heading><u style="single">1-(3-(2-cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)propylamino)-4-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(3)</u></b></heading><p num="0090">1-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-4-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone (0.66
g; 1.0 mmol) is dissolved in dry dichloromethane (100 mL) and added 3Å molecular sieves.
The mixture is stirred for 3 hours and then added 2-cyanoethyl-N,N,N',N'-tetraisopropylphosphordiamidite
(335 mg; 1.1 mmol) and 4,5-dicyanoimidazole (105 mg; 0.9 mmol). The
mixture is stirred for 5 hours and then added sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (50 mL) and stirred for 10
minutes. The phases are separated and the organic phase is washed with sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (50
mL), brine (50 mL) and dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). After concentration the phosphoramidite is obtained
as a blue foam and is used in oligonucleotide synthesis without further purification. Yield: 705
mg (82 %). <sup>31</sup>P-NMR (CDCl<sub>3</sub>): 150.0. <sup>1</sup>H-NMR(CDCl<sub>3</sub>): 10.8 (2H, 2xt, J = 5.3 Hz, NH), 8.32
(2H, m, AqH), 7.67 (2H, m, AqH), 7.5-7.1 (9H, m, ArH + AqH), 6.77 (4H, m, ArH) 3.9-3.75
(4H, m), 3.71 (6H, s, OCH<sub>3</sub>), 3.64-3.52 ( 3.54 (6H, m), 3.26 (2H, t, J = 5.8 Hz, CH<sub>2</sub>ODMT),
2.63 (2H, t, J = 6.4 Hz, CH<sub>2</sub>CN) 2.05 (4H, m, CCH<sub>2</sub>C), 1.18 (12H, dd, J = 3.1 Hz, CCH<sub>3</sub>).</p><heading><i>Example 2.: Preparation of 1-(3-(cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy) propylamino)-5-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone</i><b><i>(6)</i></b></heading><heading><u style="single">1,5- Bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(4)</u></b></heading><p num="0091">1,5-Dichloroanthraquinone (2.8 g; 10 mmol) is mixed with 3-amino-1-propanol (10 mL) in
DMSO (50 mL) and heated to 130°C for 4 hours. The mixture is cooled to ~ 80° and added
water (150 mL). When the mixture has reached RT the formed precipitate is isolated by 
filtration, washed with water (2 x 50 mL), boiled in toluene (200 mL) and the un-dissolved
product is isolated by filtration and dried. Yield: 3.2 g (90%).</p><heading><u style="single">1-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-5-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone (</u><b><u style="single">5</u></b><u style="single">)</u></heading><p num="0092">1,5-Bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone (1.4 g; 4 mmol) is co-evapourated with
pyridine (50 mL) and then resuspended in pyridine (50 mL) added dimethoxytritylchloride
(1.4 g; 4.1 mmol) and stirred overnight. The mixture is concentrated and the residue
redissolved in dichloromethane (150 mL), washed with sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (2 x 50 mL), brine (50
mL), dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) and concentrated. Purify on silica gel column (MeOH/dichloromethane
2/98). After concentration of the appropriate fractions the mono-DMT compound is obtained
as a red foam. Yield: 0.9g (34%). <sup>1</sup>H-NMR(CDCl<sub>3</sub>): 9.7 (2H, 2xt, NH), 7.6-6.7 (19H, m, ArH),
3.86 (2H, q, J = 5.5Hz, CH<sub>2</sub>), 3.74 (6H, s, CH<sub>3</sub>), 3.48 (4H, m, NCH<sub>2</sub>), 3.26 (2H, t, J = 5,9
Hz), 2.05 (4H, m, CH<sub>2</sub>), 1.45 (1H, t, J = 5 Hz).</p><heading><u style="single">1-(3-(cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)propylamino)-5-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(6)</u></b></heading><p num="0093">1-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-5-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone (0.4
g; 0.61 mmol) is dissolved in dry dichloromethane (50 mL) and added 3Å molecular sieves.
The mixture is stirred for 3 hours and then added 2-cyanoethyl-N,N,N',N'-tetraisopropylphosphordiamidite
(200 mg; 0.66 mmol) and 4,5-dicyanoimidazole (71 mg; 0.6
mmol). The mixture is stirred for 2 hours and then added sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (50 mL) and stirred
for 10 minutes. The phases are separated and the organic phase is washed with sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub>
(50 mL), brine (50 mL) and dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). After concentration the phosphoramidite is
obtained as a red foam and is used in oligonucleotide synthesis without further purification.
Yield: 490 mg (93%). <sup>31</sup>P-NMR (CDCl<sub>3</sub>): 148.3.</p><heading><i>Example 3.: Preparation of 1-(4-(2-(2-cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)
phosphinoxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-4-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</i><b><i>(9)</i></b></heading><heading><u style="single">1,4-Bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(7)</u></b></heading><p num="0094">Leucoquinizarin (2.5 g; 0.01 mol) is mixed with boric acid (1.9 g; 0.03 mol) and ethanol (100
mL) and heated to reflux for 1 hour. The mixture is cooled to room temperature and added 
4-aminophenethyl alcohol (4.1 g; 0.03 mol) where after the mixture is heated to reflux for 3
days. The mixture concentrated redissolved in dichloromethane (300 mL) washed with water
(3 x 100 mL), dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) and concentrated. The residue is purified on silica gel column
with MeOH/dichloromethane (1/19). After concentration of the appropriate fractions the
compound is obtained as a blue solid. Yield: 1.5 g (31%). <sup>1</sup>H-NMR(DMSO-<i>d<sub>6</sub></i>): 12.2 (2H, s,
NH), 8.31 (2H, dd, J = 3.1 and 6.0 Hz, AqH), 7.88 (2H, dd, J = 3.1 and 6.0 Hz, AqH), 7.59
(2H, s, AqH), 7.27 (2H, d, J = 2.7 Hz, ArH), 4.67 (2H, t, J = 5.2 Hz, OH), 3.63 (4H, dt, J =
5.2 and 7.1 Hz, CH<sub>2</sub>O), 2.74 (4H, t, J = 7.1 Hz, ArCH<sub>2</sub>).</p><heading><u style="single">1-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-4-(4-(2-hydroethy)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(8)</u></b></heading><p num="0095">1,4-Bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone (0.950 g; 2 mmol) is dissolved in a
mixture of dry N,N-dimethylformamide (25 mL) and dry pyridine (5 mL). Dimethoxytritylchloride
(0.34g; 1 mmol) is added and the mixture is stirred for 2 hours. Additional
dimethoxytritylchloride (0.34g; 1 mmol) is added and the mixture is stirred for 4 hours. The
mixture is concentrated under vacuum and the residue is redissolved in dichloromethane
(200 mL) washed with water (2 x 100 ml) and dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). The solution is filtered through
a silica gel pad (Ø 10 cm; h 10 cm) and eluted with dichloromethane until mono-DMT-anthraquinone
product begins to elude where after the solvent is the changed to 1%
methanol in dichloromethane. The pure fractions are combined and concentrated resulting in
a blue solid. Yield: 0.81 g (52%). <sup>1</sup>H-NMR(CDCl<sub>3</sub>): 12.2 (2H, s, NH), 8.38 (2H, dd, J = 3.4
and 6.0 Hz, AqH), 7.75 (2H, dd, J = 3.4 and 6.0 Hz, AqH), 7.46 (2H, s, AqH), 7.4-7.1 (17H,
m, ArH), 6.8 (4H, m, ArH), 3.63 (2H, dt, J = 5.8 and 6.6 Hz, CH<sub>2</sub>O), 3.75 (2H, s, CH<sub>3</sub>), 3.33
(2H, t, J = 6.6 Hz, CH<sub>2</sub>ODMT) 2.88 (4H, t, J = 6.6 Hz, ArCH<sub>2</sub>), 1.42 (1H, t, J = 5.8 Hz, OH).</p><heading><u style="single">1-(4-(2-(2-cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-4-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(9)</u></b></heading><p num="0096">1-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy-)ethyl)phenylamino)-4-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
(0.50 g; 0.64 mmol) is dissolved in dry dichloromethane (50 mL) and added
3Å molecular sieves. The mixture is stirred for 3 hours and then added 2-cyanoethyl-N,N,N',N'-tetraisopropylphosphordiamidite
(215 mg; 0.72 mmol) and 4,5-dicyanoimidazole
(64 mg; 0.55 mmol). The mixture is stirred for 4 hours and then added sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (25 mL)
and stirred for 10 minutes. The phases are separated and the organic phase is washed with
sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (25 mL), brine (25 mL) and dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). After concentration the
phosphoramidite is obtained as a blue foam and is used in oligonucleotide synthesis without
further purification. Yield: 0.59g (94%). </p><heading><i>Example</i> 4: <i>Preparation</i> of <i>1-(3-(2-Cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)-propylamino)-4-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-6(7)-methyl-anthraquinone
<b>(13)</b></i></heading><heading><u style="single">6-methyl-Quinizarin</u><b><u style="single">(10)</u></b> </heading><p num="0097">4-methyl-phthalic anhydride (10 g, 62 mmol), p-chlorophenol (3.6 g, 28 mmol) and Boric
acid (1.6 g) were dissolved in concentrated H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> (34 ml) and the mixture was stirred at
200°C for 6 hours in a flask covered with a glass plate. After completion of the reaction, the
mixture was allowed to cool and then poured into water (160 ml) and the precipitate
collected by filtration. The solid was suspended in boiling water (320 ml) and boiled for 5
min, whereupon the solid was collected by filtration. The product was obtained as a dark red
solid (5 g, 19.7 mmol) after drying. MALDI-MS: m/z 255.7 (M+H).</p><heading><u style="single">1,4-Bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-6-methylanthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(11)</u></b> </heading> <p num="0098">6-methyl-quinizarin was dissolved in ethanol (35 ml) and 3-aminopropanol (15 ml) was
added and the mixture was refluxed for 6 hours. After completion, the reaction mixture was
cooled to room temperature and poured into water (300 ml) and extracted with
dichloromethane. The organic phase was evaporated to dryness and subsequently purified by
column chromatography affording the diol as a blue oil (~1 g, ~ 2.7 mmol) Rf: 0.12 (5%
MeOH/DCM) MALDI-MS: 369.5 (M+H).</p> <heading><u style="single">1-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-4-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-6(7)-methyl-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(12)</u></b></heading><p num="0099">To a solution of 1,4-Bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-6-methylanthraquinone (0.5 g, 1.36 mmol)
in anhydrous pyridine (30 ml) was added 4,4'-dimethoxytritylchloride (500 mg, 1.48 mmol)
and the reaction mixture was stirred under inert atmosphere for ½h, whereupon the reaction
was quenched by addition of NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (30 ml) and diluted with dichloromethane (100 ml). The
phases were separated and the organic phase was washed with brine (30 ml), dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>)
and evaporated to dryness. The residue was coevaporated with toluene to remove pyridine.
The mono-DMT protected anthraquinone was purified by column chromatography (0-1%
MeOH/dichloromethane containing 0.1% triethylamine) affording the compound as a blue
solid (100 mg, 0.15 mmol). MALDI-MS: 670 (M<sup>+</sup>) </p><heading><u style="single">1-(3-(2-cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)propylamino)-4-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)propylamino)-6(7)-methyl-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(13)</u></b></heading><p num="0100">The mono-DMT protected compound (100 mg, 0,15mmol) was dissolved in anhydrous
dichloromethane (30 ml), 3Å molecular sieves were added and the mixture was stirred
overnight under inert atmosphere. 4,5-Dicyanoimidazole (38 mg, 32 mmol) was suspended
in anhydrous dichloromethane (6 ml) and 2-cyanoethyl-N,N,N',N'-tetraisopropylphosphoramidite
(11 mg, 0.36 mmol) was added and the mixture was stirred for 10 min at
room temperature. Thereafter, this mixture was transferred to the flask containing the
anthraquinone derivative and the mixture was allowed to stir for 30 min at room
temperature. After completion of the reaction, NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (saturated solution, 50 ml) was added
and the phases were separated. The organic phase was subsequently washed with NaHCO<sub>3</sub>
(50 ml) and brine (50 ml). The organic phase was dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> evaporated to dryness and
finally co-evaporated with anhydrous acetonitrile affording the amidite as a blue oil (80 mg,
0.09mmol), which was used for oligonucleotide synthesis without any further purification.
MALDI-MS: m/z = 869 (M+).</p><heading><i>Example 5: Preparation of 1,4-Bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-6-methyl-anthraquinone</i><b><i>(15)</i></b></heading><p num="0101">6-Methyl-quinizarin (1 g, mmol) was mixed with Zn-dust (2 g) in acetic acid (150 ml) and
stirred for 2½h at 90°C where after the reaction was filtered through a thin layer of celite.
The product precipitated by addition of water and was subsequently collected by filtration and
washed with water (300 ml). The reduced anthraquinone derivative was subsequently
dissolved in n-pentanol (50 ml). Boric acid (2 g), phenetylamine (2 g) and Na<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>S<sub>2</sub> (2 g) was
added and the mixture was stirred at 120°C for 4 days where after the mixture was pored
into water and the mixture was extracted with dichloromethane (100 ml). The organic phase
was washed with brine, dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) and evaporated to dryness. The product was purified
by column chromatography (0-2% MeOH/dichloromethane) affording the 1,4-amino-substituted
anthraquinone derivative as a blue/green solid (0.1 g). MALDI-MS: 493.4 (M+H) </p><heading><i>Example</i> 6: <i>Preparation of 1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(7-(2-cyanoethoxy-(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone</i><b><i>(19)</i></b></heading><heading><u style="single">1,4-Dihydroxy-2,3-dihydro-6-carboxy-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(16</u>)</b></heading><p num="0102">1,4-Dihydroxy-anthraquinone-6-carboxylic acid (1.5 g) is mixed with Zn dust (3 g) in 300 mL
glacial Acetic acid. The mixture is heated to 100°C for 2 hours, filtered through Celite
concentrated to half volume and added 250 mL water and placed at 5°C overnight. The
precipitate is collected by filtration. Yield: 1.1 g.</p><heading><u style="single">1,4-Bis(4-methyl-phenylaminol-6-carboxy-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(17)</u></b></heading><p num="0103">1,4-Dihydroxy-2,3-dihydro-6-carboxy-anthraquinone (300 mg) Boric acid (300 mg) and p-Toluidine
(1.8 g) is mixed in n-pentanol (5 mL) and heated to 110°C for 4 hours, the mixture
is co-evaporated with 2x50 ml of water. The residue is redissolved in dichloromethane/THF
(1/1) 200 ml washed with water (3x100 mL) dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>), filtered and concentrated. The
residue is purified on a silicagel column (CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> / MeOH / NEt<sub>3</sub>; 90/9/1) resulting in 350 mg
of pure material. MALDI-MS: m/z 463.2 (M+H)</p><heading><u style="single">1,4-Bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(7-dimethoxytrityloxy-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(18)</u></b></heading><p num="0104">1,4-Bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-carboxy-anthraquinone (155 mg) is dissolved in mixed
CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> (10 mL) added NEt<sub>3</sub> (0.5 mL) and benzotriazol-1-yloxy-tris(dimethylamino)-phosohonium
hexafluorophosphate (200 mg) and stirred for 15 minutes. 7-(Dimethoxytrityloxy)-6-hydroxy-4-oxa-heptylamine
(220 mg) is added and the mixture is
stirred for 2 hours. The mixture is purified on a silicagel column (CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> / EtOAc / NEt<sub>3</sub>;
89/10/1) resulting in 210 mg of a green foam. MALDI-MS: m/z 895.6 (M+H)</p><heading><u style="single">1,4-Bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6(N-(7-(2-cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(19)</u></b></heading><p num="0105">1,4-Bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(7-dimethoxytrityloxy-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone
(150 mg) is dissolved in dry dichloromethane (15 mL) and
added 3Å molecular sieves. The mixture is stirred for 3 hours and then added 2-cyanoethyl-N,N,N',N'-tetraisopropylphosphordiamidite 
(55 mg) and 4,5-dicyanoimidazole (15 mg; 0.55
mmol). The mixture is stirred for 4 hours and then added sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (10 mL) and stirred
for 10 minutes. The phases are separated and the organic phase is washed with sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub>
(10 mL), brine (10 mL) and dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> After concentration the phosphoramidite is
obtained as a blue/green foam and is used in oligonucleotide synthesis without further
purification.</p><heading><i>Example 7: Prepare</i>/<i>on of 1-(4-(2-(cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)ethyl)-phenylamino)-5-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</i><b>(22)</b></heading><heading><u style="single">1,5-Bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(20)</u></b></heading><p num="0106">1,5-Dinitroanthraquinone (3.0 g; 10 mmol) is mixed with 4-aminophenethyl alcohol (6 g) in
DMSO (50 mL) and heated to 130°C for 4 hours. The mixture is cooled and added water (150
mL). The precipitate is isolated by filtration, washed with water (2 x 50 mL), dried and
purified on silicagel column (CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> 0-10% MeOH). Yield: 1.2 g (25 %). MALDI-MS: m/z
479.4 (M+H).</p><heading><u style="single">1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-5-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(21)</u></b></heading><p num="0107">1,5-Bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone (960 mg; 2 mmol) is co-evaporated
with pyridine (25 mL) and then resuspended in pyridine (25 mL) added dimethoxytritylchloride
(680 mg; 2 mmol) and stirred overnight. The mixture is concentrated and the
residue redissolved in dichloromethane (150 mL), washed with sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (2 x 50 mL),
brine (50 mL), dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) and concentrated. Purify on silica gel column
(MeOH/dichloromethane 2/98). Yield: 395 mg (24%) MALDI-MS: m/z 780.9 (M+H)</p><heading><u style="single">1-(4-(2-(cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-5-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(22</u></b><u style="single">)</u></heading><p num="0108">1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-5-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
(0.350 mg; 0.44 mmol) is dissolved in dry dichloromethane (15 mL) and
added 3Å molecular sieves. The mixture is stirred for 3 hours and then added 2-cyanoethyl-N,N,N',N'-tetraisopropylphosphordiamidite
(150 mg; 0.5 mmol) and 4,5-dicyanoimidazole (50
mg; 0.4 mmol). The mixture is stirred for 3 hours and then added sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (25 mL) and 
stirred for 10 minutes. The phases are separated and the organic phase is washed with sat.
NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (25 mL), brine (25 mL) and dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). After concentration the phosphoramidite
is obtained as a dark red foam and is used in oligonucleotide synthesis without further
purification. Yield: 410 mg.</p><heading><i>Example 8: Preparation of 1-(3-(cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)propylamino)-8-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone
(25)</i></heading><heading><u style="single">1,8-Bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(23)</u></b></heading><p num="0109">1,8-Dinitrochloroanthraquinone (3 g; 10 mmol) is mixed with 3-amino-1-propanol (10 mL) in
DMSO (50 mL) and heated to 130°C for 4 hours. The mixture is cooled and added water (150
mL), the formed precipitate is isolated by filtration, washed with water (2 x 50 mL) dried and
purified on silicagel column (CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> 0-10% MeOH). Yield: 2.8 g (78 %) of a purple solid.
MALDI-MS: m/z 355.4 (M+H).</p><heading><u style="single">1-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-8-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(24)</u></b></heading><p num="0110">1,8-Bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone (1.4 g; 4 mmol) is co-evapourated with
pyridine (50 mL) and then resuspended in pyridine (50 mL) added dimethoxytritylchloride
(1.4 g; 4 mmol) and stirred overnight. The mixture is concentrated and the residue
redissolved in dichloromethane (100 mL), washed with sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (2 x 50 mL), brine (50
mL), dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) and concentrated.</p><p num="0111">Purify on silica gel column (MeOH/dichloromethane 2/98). After concentration of the
appropriate fractions the mono-DMT compound is obtained as purple foam. Yield: 1.1 (42%)
MALDI-MS: m/z 657 (M+H).</p><heading><u style="single">1-(3-(cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)propylamino)-8-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(25)</u></b></heading><p num="0112">1-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-8-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone (0.4
g; 0.61 mmol) is dissolved in dry dichloromethane (50 mL) and added 3Å molecular sieves.
The mixture is stirred for 3 hours and then added 2-cyanoethyl-N,N,N',N'-tetraisopropylphosphordiamidite
(200 mg; 0.66 mmol) and 4,5-dicyanoimidazole (70 mg; 0.6 mmol). The
mixture is stirred for 2 hours and then added sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (50 mL) and stirred for 10 
minutes. The phases are separated and the organic phase is washed with sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (50
mL), brine (50 mL) and dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). After concentration the phosphoramidite is obtained
as purple foam and is used in oligonucleotide synthesis without further purification. Yield:
440 mg (85%).</p><heading><i>Example 9: Preparation of 1-(4-(2-(cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)ethyl)-phenylamino)-8-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</i><b><i>(28)</i></b></heading><heading><u style="single">1,8-Bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(26)</u></b></heading><p num="0113">1,8-Dinitroanthraquinone (3.0 g; 10 mmol) is mixed with 4-aminophenethyl alcohol (6 g) in
DMSO (50 mL) and heated to 130°C for 4 hours. The mixture is cooled and added water (150
mL). The precipitate is isolated by filtration, washed with water (2 x 50 mL), dried and
purified on silicagel column (CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> 0-10% MeOH). Yield: 1.2 g (20 %). MALDI-MS: m/z
479.2 (M+H).</p><heading><u style="single">1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-8-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(27)</u></b></heading><p num="0114">1,8-Bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone (480 mg; 1 mmol) is co-evapourated
with pyridine (25 mL) and then resuspended in pyridine (25 mL) added dimethoxytritylchloride
(340 mg; 1 mmol) and stirred overnight. The mixture is concentrated and the
residue redissolved in dichloromethane (150 mL), washed with sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (2 x 50 mL),
brine (50 mL), dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) and concentrated. Purify on silica gel column
(MeOH/dichloromethane 2/98). Yield: 220 mg (28%) of a dark purple foam. MALDI-MS: m/z
780.7 (M+H).</p><heading>1-(4-(2-(cyanoethoxy(diisopropylamino)phosphinoxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-8-(4-(2-(4,4'-<u style="single">dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone</u><b><u style="single">(28)</u></b></heading><p num="0115">1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-8-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
(0.200 mg; 0.25 mmol) is dissolved in dry dichloromethane (10 mL) and
added 3Å molecular sieves. The mixture is stirred for 3 hours and then added 2-cyanoethyl-N,N,N',N'-tetraisopropylphosphordiamidite
(90 mg; 0.3 mmol) and 4,5-dicyanoimidazole (25
mg; 0.2 mmol). The mixture is stirred for 3 hours and then added sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (25 mL) and
stirred for 10 minutes. The phases are separated and the organic phase is washed with sat. 
NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (25 mL), brine (25 mL) and dried (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). After concentration the phosphoramidite
is obtained as a dark red/purple foam and is used in oligonucleotide synthesis without further
purification. Yield: 220 mg.</p><heading><i>Example 10: Synthesis, deprotection and purification of dual labelled oligonucleotides</i></heading><p num="0116">The dual labelled oligonucleotides were prepared on an automated DNA synthesizer (Expedite
8909 DNA synthesizer, PerSeptive Biosystems, 0.2 µmol scale) using the phosphoramidite
approach (Beaucage and Caruthers, <i>Tetrahedron Lett. 22:</i> 1859-1862, 1981) with 2-cyanoethyl
protected LNA and DNA phosphoramidites, (Sinha, et al., <i>Tetrahedron Lett. 24:</i>
5843-5846, 1983), CPG-Phosphate solid supports and 5'-fluorescein phosphoramidite (GLEN
Research, Sterling, Virginia, USA). The synthesis cycle was modified for LNA
phosphoramidites and quencher phosphoramidites (250 s coupling time) compared to DNA
phosphoramidites. 1<i>H-</i>tetrazole or 4,5-dicyanoimidazole (Proligo, Hamburg, Germany) was
used as activator in the coupling step.</p><p num="0117">The oligonucleotides were deprotected using 32% aqueous ammonia (1 h at room
temperature, then 2 hours at 60°C) and purified by HPLC (Shimadzu-SpectraChrom series;
Xterra™ RP18 column, 10 µm 7.8 x 150 mm (Waters). Buffers: A: 0.05 M Triethylammonium
acetate pH 7.4. B. 50% acetonitrile in water. Eluent: 0-25 min: 10-80% B; 25-30 min: 80%
B). The composition and purity of the oligonucleotides were verified by MALDI-MS
(PerSeptive Biosystem, Voyager DE-PRO) analysis.</p><heading><i>Example 11: Real Time PCR with probes synthesized with quenchers prepared as described in
Example 1 (Compound</i><b><i>(3), Q1)</i></b><i>or Example 2 (Compound</i><b><i>(6), Q2)</i></b></heading><p num="0118">Reagents for the Real Time dual label probe PCRs were mixed according to the following
scheme (Table 1): <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">PCR Setup</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Reagents</entry><entry align="left">Final Concentration</entry></row><row><entry align="left">H<sub>2</sub>O</entry></row><row><entry align="left">GeneAmp 10x PCR buffer II</entry><entry align="left">1x</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mg<sup>2+</sup></entry><entry align="left">3.5 mM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">dNTP</entry><entry align="left">0.2 mM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dual Label Probe</entry><entry align="left">0.1 µM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Template</entry><entry align="left">1 µL<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Forward primer</entry><entry align="left">0.2 µM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Reverse primer</entry><entry align="left">0.2 µM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">AmpliTaq Gold</entry><entry align="left">2.5 U</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="left">50 µL<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0119">The following primers and probes were included in the above mentioned PCR mix (Table 2).
<img id="img-00330001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00330001.tif" inline="no" he="86"/></p><p num="0120">Assays were performed in a DNA Engine Opticon® (MJ Research) using the following PCR
cycle protocol (see Table 3). <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">PCR-termocycling protocol</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">95°C for 7 minutes</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="2">40 cycles of:</entry><entry align="left">94°C for 20 seconds</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="2">60°C for 1 minute</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="2">Fluorescence detection</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0121">Results from the two Real Time PCRs are illustrated in Figure 10, which shows that dual
labelled probes with either of the two quenchers <b>Q1 (3)</b> and <b>Q2 (6)</b> are fully functional as
real time PCR probes.</p><heading><u style="single">Production of of SSA4 cDNA for detection with dual labelled probes</u></heading><p num="0122">The functionality of the constructed probes were analysed in PCR assays where the probes
ability to detect different SSA4 PCR amplicons were questioned. Template for the PCR
reaction was cDNA obtained from reverse transcription of cRNA produced from in vitro
transcription of a downstream region of the SSA4 gene in the expression vector pTRIamp18
(Ambion). The downstream region of the SSA4 gene was cloned as follows:</p><heading><u style="single">PCR amplification</u></heading><p num="0123">Amplification of the partial yeast gene was done by standard PCR using yeast genomic DNA
as template. Genomic DNA was prepared from a wild type standard laboratory strain of
<i>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</i> using the Nucleon MiY DNA extraction kit (Amersham Biosciences)
according to supplier's instructions. In the first step of PCR amplification, a forward primer
containing a restriction enzyme site and a reverse primer containing a universal linker
sequence were used. In this step 20 bp was added to the 3'-end of the amplicon, next to the
stop codon. In the second step of amplification, the reverse primer was exchanged with a
nested primer containing a poly-T<sub>20</sub> tail and a restriction enzyme site. The SSA4 amplicon
contains 729 bp of the <i>SSA4</i> ORF plus a 20 bp universal linker sequence and a poly-A<sub>20</sub> tail.</p><heading><u style="single">The PCR primers used were:</u></heading><p num="0124"><img id="img-00340001" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00340001.tif" inline="no" he="7"/><img id="img-00340002" orientation="unknown" wi="144"  img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00340002.tif" inline="no" he="6"/><img id="img-00340003"  orientation="unknown"  wi="146"  img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00340003.tif" inline="no" he="7"/></p><heading><u style="single">Plasmid DNA constructs</u></heading><p num="0125">The PCR amplicon was cut with the restriction enzymes, <i>Eco</i>RI + <i>Bam</i>HI<i>.</i> The DNA fragment
was ligated into the pTRIamp18 vector (Ambion) using the Quick Ligation Kit (New England
Biolabs) according to the supplier's instructions and transformed into <i>E</i>. <i>coli</i> DH-5 by
standard methods.</p><heading><u style="single">DNA sequencing</u></heading><p num="0126">To verify the cloning of the PCR amplicon, plasmid DNA was sequenced using M13 forward
and M13 reverse primers and analysed on an ABI 377.</p><heading><u style="single">In vitro transcription</u></heading><p num="0127">SSA4 cRNA was obtained by performing in vitro transcription with the Megascript T7 kit
(Ambion) according to the supplier's instructions.</p><heading><u style="single">Reverse transcription</u></heading><p num="0128">Reverse transcription was performed with 1 µg of cRNA and 0.2 U of the reverse
transcriptase Superscript II RT (Invitrogen) according to the suppliers instructions except
that 20 U Superase-In (RNAse inhibitor - Ambion) was added. The produced cDNA was
purified on a QiaQuick PCR purification column (Qiagen) according to the supplier's
instructions using the supplied EB-buffer for elution. The DNA concentration of the eluted
cDNA was measured and diluted to a concentration of SSA4 cDNA copies corresponding to 2
x 10<sup>7</sup> copies pr µL.</p><heading><i>Example 12: Real time PCR with probes carrying the quencher (Compound</i><b><i>(3), Q1)</i></b><i>as an
internal quencher incorporated in a LNA</i>/<i>DNA oligonucleotide</i></heading><p num="0129">The experiments were conducted essentially as in Example 11. <img id="img-00360001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00360001.tif" inline="no" he="93"/><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">PCR setup</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Reagents</entry><entry align="left">Final Conc.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">For Primer EQ-15910</entry><entry align="left">0.9 µM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rev Primer EQ-15911</entry><entry align="left">0.9 µM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Probe (EQ-16234)</entry><entry align="left">0.2 µM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Qiagen Taq</entry><entry align="left">0.05 U/µL</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MgCl<sub>2</sub> (additional)</entry><entry align="left">1.5 mM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">dUTP</entry><entry align="left">200 µM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">ROX (Invitrogen)</entry><entry align="left">0.1 X</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PCR-buffer (Qiagen, incl. 1.5 mM Mg<sup>++</sup>)</entry><entry align="left">1 X</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Template</entry><entry align="left">4 pM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">H<sub>2</sub>O</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Final Volume (incl. Template)</entry><entry align="left">350 µL</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">PCR-termocycling protocol</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">95°C for 10 minutes</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="2">40 cycles of:</entry><entry align="left">94°C for 20 seconds</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="2">60°C for 1 minute</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="2">Fluorescence detection</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0130">Results are shown in Figure 11.</p><heading><i>Embodiments</i></heading><p num="0131">The invention can also be defined by means of the following embodiments, wherein the term
"item" refers to a preceding item with the specified number.
<sl><li>1. A quencher composition of the formula (II):
<img id="img-00370001" orientation="unknown" wi="54" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00370001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/>
wherein Y is nitrogen or

wherein R<sup>9</sup> is hydrogen, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>-alkyl, aryl, aryldiyl or aryltriyl; L<sup>1</sup>, L<sup>2</sup> and L<sup>3</sup> are each,
independently, a bond or a linker; X is a biomolecule, a protected form thereof or an acid-labile
or base labile protecting group; wherein the biomolecule is selected from an amino
acid, a polypeptide, a nucleoside, a nucleotide or a polynucleotide and optionally further
comprises a fluorophore; Z is a bond or selected from -H, -CO<sub>2</sub>H -OH, -NH<sub>2</sub>, -NHR<sup>10</sup>, or
-N(R<sup>10</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, -SH, a phosphate, a nucleotide, a substituted nucleotide, a polynucleotide, a
substituted polynucleotide, an ester, a cleavable linker, a solid support, a reactive linking
group or a label; all of which are optionally substituted with a label or a solid support; and
wherein R<sup>10</sup> is hydrogen, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl, aryl, aryldiyl, aryltriyl; Q is a compound of the formula
(I) <img id="img-00380001" orientation="unknown" wi="88" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00380001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/>
wherein at least one, two, three or four of R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>4</sup>, R<sup>5</sup> or R<sup>8</sup> are each and independently
selected from substituted or non-substituted amino-alkyl, amino-aryl or amino-alkylaryl and
the remaining R<sup>1</sup> to R<sup>8</sup> groups are each and independently hydrogen or substituted or non-substituted
hydroxy, amino, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl or alkoxy; and wherein Q is attached to the
linker L<sup>1</sup> either through one of the α-amino groups or through one of the aryl carbons of the
quencher moiety.</li><li>2. A compound of item 1 wherein L<sup>1</sup>, L<sup>2</sup> and L<sup>3</sup> are each, independently selected from C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkyldiyl,
C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkoxydiyl, alkylaryl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylaminodiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylamidediyl, aryldiyl or
1-20 ethyleneoxy units.</li><li>3. A compound of item 1 or 2 wherein X is a biomolecule comprising a fluorophore and Z is a
nucleotide or a polynucleotide both of which are optionally substituted with a label or a solid
support.</li><li>4. A compound of item 1 to 3 wherein X is an acid labile protecting group and Z is a reactive
linking group of the formula (IV):
<img id="img-00380002" orientation="unknown" wi="71" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00380002.tif" inline="no" he="30"/>
wherein R<sup>11</sup> and R<sup>12</sup> are individually selected from isopropyl, methyl, ethyl and C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>14</sub> aryl or
R<sup>11</sup> and R<sup>12</sup> are, when taken together C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>11</sub> cycloalkyl or morpholino; R<sup>13</sup> is C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl,
substituted C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl, C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>14</sub> aryl or a protecting group.</li><li>5. A compound of item 4 wherein R<sup>11</sup> and R<sup>12</sup> are both isopropyl and R<sup>13</sup> is cyanoethyl.</li><li>6. A compound of item 4 or 5 wherein X is a protecting group selected from the group
consisting of DMT, MMT, trityl, substituted trityl, pixyl and trialkylsilyl. </li><li>7. A compound of items 1-6 wherein Z is a structure of the formula (V):
<img id="img-00390001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390001.tif" inline="no" he="11"/>
wherein A is a cleavable linker selected from the structures (Va-Vf):
<img id="img-00390002" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390002.tif" inline="no" he="22"/><img id="img-00390003" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390003.tif" inline="no" he="28"/><img id="img-00390004" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390004.tif" inline="no" he="24"/><img id="img-00390005" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390005.tif" inline="no" he="32"/>
wherein R<sup>14</sup> is C<sub>1-12</sub> alkyl or C<sub>1-12</sub> alkoxy; R<sup>15</sup> is alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl or alkoxy; L<sup>4</sup> and L<sup>5</sup> are
independently selected from a bond or a linker selected from C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkyldiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkoxydiyl,
C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylaminodiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylamidediyl, aryldiyl or 1-20 ethyleneoxy units; G
is a bond, a nucleotide, a substituted nucleotide, a polynucleotide, a substituted
polynucleotide or a hybridization-stabilizing moiety; and B is a solid support.</li><li>8. A compound of item 7 wherein G comprises: <img id="img-00400001" orientation="unknown" wi="84" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400001.tif" inline="no" he="57"/>
wherein L designates the sites of attachment to L<sup>2</sup> and L<sup>5</sup>.</li><li>9. A compound of item 7 or 8 wherein the solid support is selected from polystyrene,
controlled-pore-glass, silica gel, silica, polyacrylamide, magnetic beads, polyacrylate,
hydroxyethylmethacrylate, polyamide, polyethylene, polyethyleneoxy, and copolymers and
grafts of such.</li><li>10. A compound of item 7 or 8 wherein the form of the solid support is selected from a
particle, a bead, a membrane, a frit, a fiber, a tube, a capillary, a slide, a plate, a
micromachined chip, an alkanethiol-gold layer, a magnetic bead, a non-porous surface, an
addressable array, and polynucleotide-immobilizing medium.</li><li>11. A compound of items 1-10 wherein X is a polynucleotide comprising a fluorescent dye.</li><li>12. A compound of item 11 wherein the polynucleotide comprises one or more N-[2-(aminoethyl)]glycine
units having a nucleobase attached to nitrogen through a methylene
carbonyl linkage.</li><li>13. A compound of item 11 wherein the polynucleotide comprises one or more of 2'-4' or 3'-4'
bicyclic sugar modifications.</li><li>14. A quencher compositions of the formula (III):
<img id="img-00400002" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400002.tif" inline="no" he="19"/>
wherein L<sup>1</sup> and L<sup>2</sup> are each, independently, a bond or a linker; X is a biomolecule, a protected
form thereof or an acid-labile or base labile protecting group; wherein the biomolecule is
selected from an amino acid, a polypeptide, a nucleoside, a nucleotide or a polynucleotide 
and optionally further comprises a fluorophore; Z is a bond or selected from -H, -CO<sub>2</sub>H -OH,
-NH<sub>2</sub>, -NHR<sup>10</sup>, or -N(R<sup>10</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, -SH, a phosphate, a nucleotide, a substituted nucleotide, a
polynucleotide, a substituted polynucleotide, an ester, a cleavable linker, a solid support, a
reactive linking group or a label; all of which are optionally substituted with a label or a solid
support; and wherein R<sup>10</sup> is hydrogen, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl, aryl, aryldiyl, aryltriyl; Q is a compound of
the formula (I)
<img id="img-00410001" orientation="unknown" wi="88" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410001.tif" inline="no" he="38"/>
wherein at least one, two, three or four of R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>4</sup>, R<sup>5</sup> or R<sup>8</sup> are each and independently
selected from substituted or non-substituted amino-alkyl, amino-aryl or amino-alkylaryl and
the remaining R<sup>1</sup> to R<sup>8</sup> groups are each and independently hydrogen or substituted or non-substituted
hydroxy, amino, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl or alkoxy;and wherein Q is attached to the
linkers L<sup>1</sup> and L<sup>2</sup> at two different positions, either through one of the α-aminogroups or
through the aryl carbons of the quencher moiety.</li><li>15. A compound of item 14 wherein L<sup>1</sup> and L<sup>2</sup> are each, independently, a bond or a linker
selected from alkylaryl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkyldiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkoxydiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylaminodiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylamidediyl,
aryldiyl or 1-20 ethyleneoxy units.</li><li>16: A compound of item 14 or 15 wherein X is a biomolecule comprising a fluorophore and Z
is a nucleotide or a polynucleotide both of which are optionally substituted with a label or a
solid support.</li><li>17. A compound of items 14 to 16 wherein X is an acid labile protecting group and Z is a
reactive linking group of the formula (IV):
<img id="img-00410002" orientation="unknown" wi="69" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410002.tif" inline="no" he="27"/> 
wherein R<sup>11</sup> and R<sup>12</sup> are individually selected from isopropyl, methyl, ethyl and C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>14</sub> aryl or
R<sup>11</sup> and R<sup>12</sup> are, when taken together C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>11</sub> cycloalkyl or morpholino; R<sup>13</sup> is C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl,
substituted C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl, C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>14</sub> aryl or a protecting group.</li><li>18. A compound of item 17 wherein R<sup>11</sup> and R<sup>12</sup> are both isopropyl and R<sup>13</sup> is cyanoethyl.</li><li>19. A compound of item 17 or 18 wherein X is a protecting group selected from the group
consisting of DMT, MMT, trityl, substituted trityl, pixyl and trialkylsilyl.</li><li>20. A compound of items 14 to 19 wherein Z is a structure of the formula (V):
<img id="img-00420001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420001.tif" inline="no" he="12"/>
wherein A is a cleavable linker selected from the structures (Va-Vf):
<img id="img-00420002" orientation="unknown" wi="62" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420002.tif" inline="no" he="14"/><img id="img-00420003" orientation="unknown" wi="131" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420003.tif" inline="no" he="22"/><img id="img-00420004" orientation="unknown" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420004.tif" inline="no" he="24"/><img id="img-00420005" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420005.tif" inline="no" he="22"/>
wherein R<sup>14</sup> is C<sub>1-12</sub> alkyl or C<sub>1-12</sub> alkoxy; R<sup>15</sup> is alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl or alkoxy; L<sup>4</sup> and L<sup>5</sup> are
independently selected from a bond or a linker selected from C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkyldiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkoxydiyl,
C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylaminodiyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>-alkylamidediyl, aryldiyl or 1-20 ethyleneoxy units; G
is a bond, a nucleotide, a substituted nucleotide, a polynucleotide, a substituted
polynucleotide or a hybridization-stabilizing moiety; and B is a solid support. </li><li>21. A compound of item 20 wherein G comprises:
<img id="img-00430001" orientation="unknown" wi="87" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430001.tif" inline="no" he="55"/>
wherein L designates the sites of attachment to L<sup>2</sup> and L<sup>5</sup>.</li><li>22. A compound of item 20 or 21 wherein the solid support is selected from polystyrene,
controlled-pore-glass, silica gel, silica, polyacrylamide, magnetic beads, polyacrylate,
hydroxyethylmethacrylate, polyamide, polyethylene, polyethyleneoxy, and copolymers and
grafts of such.</li><li>23. A compound of item 20 or 21 wherein the form of the solid support is selected from a
particle, a bead, a membrane, a frit, a fiber, a tube, a capillary, a slide, a plate, a
micromachined chip, an alkanethiol-gold layer, a magnetic bead, a non-porous surface, an
addressable array, and polynucleotide-immobilizing medium.</li><li>24. A compound of items 14 to 23 wherein X is a polynucleotide comprising a fluorescent
dye.</li><li>25. A compound of item 24 wherein the polynucleotide comprises one or more N-[2-(aminoethyl)]glycine
units having a nucleobase attached to nitrogen through a methylene
carbonyl linkage.</li><li>26. A compound of item 24 wherein the polynucleotide comprises one or more of 2'-4' or 3'-4'
bicyclic sugar modifications.</li><li>27. A compound of items 1 to 26 wherein Q is 1,8-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone
or 1,5-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone.</li><li>28. A compound selected from 1,8-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone or 1,5-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone. </li><li>29. A polynucleotide probe containing at least one quencher composition according to any of
the items 1-27.</li><li>30. A polynucleotide probe according to item 29 further comprising at least one quenchable
label.</li><li>31. A polynucleotide probe according to item 30 wherein the quenchable label is separated
from the quencher by a nuclease susceptible site.</li><li>32. A polynucleotide probe according to item 30 where the probe can adopt at least 1
conformation when not bound to the target where the label is quenched by the quencher, and
at least one other conformation when the probe is bound to the target where the label is at
least partially unquenched by the quencher.</li><li>33. A polynucleotide according to item 32, where a 3' part and a 5' part of the polynucleotide
are perfectly complementary such as to form a hairpin structure when not bound to the
target.</li><li>34. A polynucleotide probe according to any of the items 29 to 33, comprising at least one
target recognition region complementary to a target gene.</li><li>35. A polynucleotide of any of the items 29 to 34 having a length of 5 to 50 nucleotides.</li><li>36. A polynucleotide probe according to item 31 where the probe is blocked for extension by
the polymerase in the 3'end.</li><li>37. A method of primer extension comprising: annealing a polynucleotide primer to a target
polynucleotide; and extending the primer by polymerase-mediated incorporation of a
nucleotide 5'-triphosphate; wherein the primer or the nucleotide 5'-triphosphate is attached
to a quencher moiety of the formula (I); whereby a labelled polynucleotide is formed.</li><li>38. The method of item 37 further comprising amplifying the target polynucleotide with
nucleotide 5'-triphosphates, a polymerase, and two or more primers; wherein the primers are
complementary to the target polynucleotide sequence and at least one primer is attached to
a quencher moiety of the formula (I).</li><li>39. A method of amplifying a target polynucleotide comprising nucleotide 5'-triphosphates, a
polymerase, two or more primers; wherein the primers are complementary to the target 
polynucleotide sequence, and a detectably labelled probe; wherein at least a part of the
detectably labelled probe is complementary to the target polynucleotide and comprise at
least a fluorescent dye and a quencher moiety of the formula (I).</li><li>40. The method of item 39 further comprising detecting a signal from the fluorescent dye of
said detectable probe.</li><li>41. The method of item 40 wherein the signal is detected at each thermal cycle during
amplification.</li><li>42. The method of item 39 wherein said polymerase cleaves the detectable probe during
amplification; whereby the fluorescent dye and the quencher moiety are separated.</li><li>43. The method of item 42 further comprising detecting a signal from the fluorescent dye of
said cleaved, detectable probe.</li><li>44. The method of item 43 wherein the signal is detected at each thermal cycle during
amplification.</li><li>45. The method of item 39 wherein said fluorescent dye is attached to the 5' terminus or 3'
terminus of the detectable probe.</li><li>46. The method of item 39 wherein said quencher moiety is attached to the 5' terminus or 3'
terminus of or internally in the detectable probe.</li><li>47. The method of item 39 wherein the detectable probe is further labelled with a
hybridization-stabilizing moiety.</li><li>48. The method of item 47 wherein the hybridization-stabilizing moiety comprises the
structure: <img id="img-00460001" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00460001.tif" inline="no" he="53"/>
where L is an attachment site to the detectable probe.</li><li>49. A method of item 39 where the detectable probe has a format selected from molecular
beacons, scorpion probes, sunrise probes, conformationally assisted probes and TaqMan
probes.</li><li>50. A method of item 39 where the detectable probe comprises one or more one or more N-[2-(aminoethyl)]glycine
units having a nucleobase attached to nitrogen through a methylene
carbonyl linkage.</li><li>51. A method of item 39 wherein the detectable probe comprises one or more of 2'-4' or 3'-4'
bicyclic sugar modifications.</li><li>52. A kit for nucleic acid amplification comprising two or more primers, and a probe with a
detectable label and a quencher moiety of the formula (I).</li><li>53. A method of hybridization detection comprising annealing a probe to a target
polynucleotide sequence, wherein the probe is covalently attached to a fluorescent dye and a
quencher moiety of the formula (I); and detecting a signal from the fluorescent dye.</li><li>54. A kit for primer extension comprising one or more nucleotide 5'-triphosphates and one or
more primers wherein at least one primer is covalently attached by a linkage to an aryl
carbon of a quencher moiety of the formula (I).</li><li>55. A microarray comprising a quencher moiety of the formula (I) said quencher being
conjugated directly to a solid support or to a carrier molecule attached to said solid support.</li><li>56. A method of probing a microarray for the presence of a compound, said method
comprising: (a) contacting said microarray with a probe interacting with said compound, said
probe comprising a quencher moiety of the formula (I); (b) detecting a difference in a 
fluorescence property of a member selected from said probe, said compound and
combinations thereof, thereby ascertaining the presence of said compound.</li><li>57. A detection system comprising: (a) a target binding entity, (b) a quenchable detectable
label and (c) a quencher according to any of items 1-27 wherein the quenchable label and
the quencher each are positioned on the target binding entity and/or the target such that the
label is quenched by the quencher when the target binding entity is unbound to its target,
and such that binding of the binding entity to its target will remove the quencher from the
label such that the label is at least partially unquenched.</li><li>58. A detection system comprising: (a) a target binding entity, (b) a quenchable detectable
label and (c) a quencher according to any of items 1-27 wherein the quenchable label and
the quencher each are positioned on the target binding entity and/or the target such that the
label is at least partially unquenched by the quencher when the target binding entity is
unbound to its target, and such that binding of the binding entity to its target will bring the
quencher in vicinity of the label such that the label is at least partially quenched.</li><li>59. A detection system according to item 57 and 58 wherein the target binding entity
comprises a polynucleotide, an antibody, an aptamer, or a ligand. <img id="img-00480001" orientation="unknown" wi="154" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00480001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/><img id="img-00490001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00490001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/><img id="img-00500001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00500001.tif" inline="no" he="92"/></li></sl></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A quencher compositions of the formula (III):

wherein L1 and L2 are each, independently a bond or a linker;
X is a polynucleotide comprising a fluorescent dye;
Z is a nucleotide or a polynucleotide both of which are optionally substituted with a label or a
solid support;
Q is a compound of the formula (I)

wherein at least one, two, three or four of R1, R4, R5 or R8 are each, independently selected
from substituted or non-substituted amino-alkyl, amino-aryl and amino-alkylaryl, and the
remaining R1 to R8 groups are each, independently hydrogen or substituted or non-substituted
hydroxy, amino, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl or alkoxy; and wherein Q is attached to the
linkers L1 and L2 at two different positions, either through one of the α-aminogroups or
through the aryl carbons of the quencher moiety.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A quencher composition of the formula (II):

wherein Y is nitrogen or
wherein R9 is hydrogen, C1-C6-alkyl, or aryl;
L1, L2 and L3 are each, independently, a bond or a linker;
X is a biomolecule or a protected form thereof. or an acid-labile or base-labile protecting
group;
wherein the biomolecule is selected from an amino acid, a polypeptide, a nucleoside, a
nucleotide, and a polynucleotide, and optionally further comprises a fluorophore;
Z is a bond or selected from -H, -CO2H -OH, -NH2, -NHR10, -N(R10)2, -SH, a phosphate, a
nucleotide, a substituted nucleotide, a polynucleotide, a substituted polynucleotide, an ester,
a cleavable linker, a solid support, a reactive linking group, and a label;
all of which are optionally substituted with a label or a solid support;
and wherein R10 is selected from C1-C6 alkyl, and aryl,
Q is a compound of the formula (I)

wherein at least one, two, three or four of R1, R4, R5 or R8 are each, independently selected
from substituted or non-substituted amino-alkyl, amino-aryl and amino-alkylaryl, and the
remaining R1 to R8 groups are each, independently hydrogen or substituted or non-substituted
hydroxy, amino, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl or alkoxy;
and wherein Q is attached to the linker L1 either through one of the α-amino groups or
through one of the aryl carbons of the quencher moiety;
with the proviso that quencher compositions represented by the whole content of European
patent application No. 20030759288 are not included.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The quencher composition according to claim 2, wherein Q is selected from 1,4-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone
(1), 1-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-4-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone
(2), 1,5-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone
(4), 1-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-5-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone
(5), 1,4-bis-(4-(2-hydroxyethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone (7), 1-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-4-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
(8), and 1,8-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The quencher composition according to claim 2, wherein Q is selected from 1,4-bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-6-methylanthraquinone
(11), 1-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)-propylamino)-4-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-6(7)-methyl-anthraquinone
(12), 1,4-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-6-methyl-anthraquinone
(15), 1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-carboxy-anthraquinone
(17), 1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(6,7-dihydroxy-4-oxoheptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(7-dimethoxytrityloxy-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone
(18), 1,4-bis(propylamino)-6-carboxy-anthraquinone,
1,4-bis(propylamino)-6-(N-(6,7-dihydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,4-bis(propylamino)-6-(N-(7-dimethoxytrityloxy-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,5-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
(20), 1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-5-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxy-trityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
(21), 1,8-bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone
(23), 1-(3-hydroxypropylamino)-8-(3-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)propylamino)-anthraquinone
(24), 1,8-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
(26), and 1-(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-8-(4-(2-(4,4'-dimethoxytrityloxy)ethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
(27).</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A quencher compositions of the formula (III):

wherein L1 and L2 are each, independently a bond or a linker;
X is a biomolecule or a protected form thereof, or an acid-labile or base labile protecting
group;
wherein the biomolecule is selected from an amino acid, a polypeptide, a nucleoside, a
nucleotide and a polynucleotide, and optionally further comprises a fluorophore;
Z is a bond or selected from -H, -CO2H, -OH, -NH2, -NHR10, -N(R10)2, -SH, a phosphate, a
nucleotide, a substituted nucleotide, a polynucleotide, a substituted polynucleotide, an ester,
a cleavable linker, a solid support, a reactive linking group, and a label;
all of which are optionally substituted with a label or a solid support;
and wherein R10 is selected from C1-C6 alkyl, and aryl,
Q is a compound of the formula (I)

wherein at least one, two, three or four of R1, R4, R5 or R8 are each, independently selected
from substituted or non-substituted amino-alkyl, amino-aryl and amino-alkylaryl, and the
remaining R1 to R8 groups are each, independently hydrogen or substituted or non-substituted
hydroxy, amino, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl or alkoxy; and wherein Q is attached to the
linkers L1 and L2 at two different positions, either through one of the α-aminogroups or
through the aryl carbons of the quencher moiety;
with the proviso that quencher compositions represented by the whole content of European
patent application No. 20030759288 are not included.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The quencher composition according to any one of claims 1 and 5, wherein Q is selected
from 1,4-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone (1), 1,5-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone
(4), 1,4-bis-(4-(2-hydroxyethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone (7), and 1,8-bis-(3-hydroxy-propylamino)-anthraquinone.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The quencher composition according to any one of claims 1 and 5, wherein Q is selected
from 1,4-bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-6-methylanthraquinone (11), 1,4-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-6-methyl-anthraquinone
(15), 1,4-bis(4-methyl-phenylamino)-6-(N-(6,7-dihydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,4-bis(4-methylphenylamino)-6-(N-(7-dimethoxytrityloxy-6-hydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone
(18), 1,4-bis(propylamino)-6-(N-(6,7-dihydroxy-4-oxo-heptane-1-yl))carboxamido-anthraquinone,
1,5-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone (20),
1,8-bis(3-hydroxypropylamino)-anthraquinone (23), and 1,8-bis(4-(2-hydroethyl)phenylamino)-anthraquinone
(26).</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A quencher composition according to any one of claims 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 and 7, wherein X is
a polynucleotide comprising a fluorescent dye, wherein the polynucleotide comprises one or
more of 2'-4' or 3'-4' bicyclic sugar modifications.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A quencher composition according to any one of claims 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 and 8, wherein
Z is a structure of the formula (V):

wherein A is a cleavable linker selected from the structures (Va-Vf):

wherein R14 is C1-12 alkyl or C1-12 alkoxy; R15 is alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl or alkoxy;
L4 and L5 are independently selected from a bond and a linker, said linker being selected from
C1-C12-alkyldiyl, C1-C12-alkoxydiyl, C1-C12-alkylaminodiyl, C1-C12-alkylamidediyl, aryldiyl and
1-20 ethyleneoxy units;
G is a bond, a nucleotide, a substituted nucleotide, a polynucleotide, a substituted
polynucleotide or a hybridization-stabilizing moiety; and B is a solid support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A quencher composition according to any of claims 1-10, wherein X is a 4,4'-dimethoxytrityl,
and Z is a phosphoramidite.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>