<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1306370-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1306370" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22040596" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030502"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1306370-A1" status="new" fvid="23754666"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1306370</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030502</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02257421-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02257421</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021025</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-6216101-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6216101</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011026</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 333/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 333/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 135/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 135/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 135/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 135/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  30/06        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  30/10        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  40/25        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C 333/20</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 135/18</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 135/22</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 135/24</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Dithiocarbamate mit Alkylthio- und Hydroxysubstituenten</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Dithiocarbamates containing alkylthio and hydroxy substituents</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Dithiocarbamates contenants des substituents alkylthio et hydroxy</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0349131-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0349131</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="FR-2735130-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>FR</country><doc-number>2735130</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE  CAPLUS [Online] CHEMICAL ABSTRACTS SERVICE, COLUMBUS, OHIO, US; Database accession no. 137:127291 XP002228722 &amp; LATYUK, I ET AL: "1-Alkylthiopropanol-2-derivatives as multifunctional additives to lubricating oils" NEFTEKHIMIYA, vol. 42, no. 2, 2002, pages 145-149,</text><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE  CAPLUS [Online] CHEMICAL ABSTRACTS SERVICE, COLUMBUS, OHIO, US; Database accession no. 88:74354 XP002228723 &amp; KUBOTA, S. ET AL:  "Synthesis and biological activity of 1,3-dithiol, 1,2-dithiolane and 1,3-dithiane-2-thione" JOURNAL OF THE FACULTY OF AGRICULTURE, KYUSHU UNIVERSITY, vol. 22, no. 1-2, 1977, pages 1-13,</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>LEN, CHRISTOPHE ET AL:  "Synthesis and Antifungal Activity of Novel Bis(dithiocarbamate) Derivatives of Glycerol" J.AGRIC.FOOD CHEM., vol. 44, 1996, pages 2856-2858, XP002228721</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ETHYL CORP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ETHYL CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ETHYL CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>330 South Fourth Street, P.O. Box 2189</street><city>Richmond, Virginia 23218-2189</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GATTO VINCENT JAMES</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GATTO, VINCENT JAMES</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GATTO, VINCENT JAMES</last-name><address><street>13709 West Bay Drive</street><city>Midlothian, Virginia 23112</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Cresswell, Thomas Anthony</last-name><address><street>J.A. KEMP &amp;amp; CO. 14 South Square Gray's Inn</street><city>LONDON WC1R 5JJ</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>BE</country><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A compound of formula
<img id="img-80000001" orientation="unknown" wi="72" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="80000001.tif" inline="no" he="26"/>
wherein R and R<sup>1</sup> may be the same or different and each is hydrogen or alkyl
provided that at least one of R or R<sup>1</sup> is alkyl and R<sup>2</sup> is alkyl, R<sup>3</sup>OCOCH<sub>2</sub> or
R<sup>3</sup>OCOCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub> where R<sup>3</sup> is alkyl, or
<img id="img-80000002" orientation="unknown" wi="39" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="80000002.tif" inline="no" he="27"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to a low cost wear inhibitor that can be used to formulate
low phosphorus lubricants. In addition to wear inhibition, the new inhibitors provide
substantial oxidation protection and are not detrimental to fuel economy.</p><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0002">Studies have suggested that emissions systems can be deactivated as a result of
contamination from compounds derived from the engine oil. Other studies have
suggested that emissions system durability may be improved by using lubricants
containing high metal/phosphorus ratios. Reducing the level of phosphorus in the engine
oils has also been suggested as a means of prolonging the efficiency of the catalytic
converter. The phosphorus in engine oils originates primarily from zinc
dialkyldithiophosphates (ZDDP's), which are used to prevent wear and control oxidation.
Over the years ZDDP's have demonstrated reliable anti-wear and antioxidant
effectiveness. Most engine builders would not recommend engine oils which contain
substantial reductions from today's ZDDP levels without extensive proof in the
laboratory and the field that wear protection is acceptable. Commercial engine oils
meeting API SJ requirements usually contain approximately 0.10 wt. % phosphorus
derived from ZDDP. A substantial reduction in ZDDP's, which may be required for 
catalytic converter durability, would result in significantly higher engine wear and oil
oxidation. To compensate for the use of less ZDDP in engine oils, supplemental wear
and oxidation inhibitors are required.</p><p num="0003">Dithiocarbamates have been known in the art for some time. Examples of various
structurally different dithiocarbamates are disclosed in the following patents:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="right">3,407,222</entry><entry align="right">5,693,598</entry><entry align="right">4,885,365</entry><entry align="right">4,125,479</entry><entry align="right">5.902,776</entry></row><row><entry align="right">3,867,359</entry><entry align="right">5,686,397</entry><entry align="right">4,836,942</entry><entry align="right">4,758,362</entry><entry align="right">3,509,051</entry></row><row><entry align="right">2,710,872</entry><entry align="right">5,789,357</entry><entry align="right">4,927,552</entry><entry align="right">5,629,272</entry><entry align="right">3,356,702</entry></row><row><entry align="right">5,840,664</entry><entry align="right">4,957,643</entry><entry align="right">4,876,375</entry><entry align="right">5,759,965</entry><entry align="right">4,098,705</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables>
All patents, patent applications, and articles or publications are incorporated herein by
reference for their full disclosure.</p><p num="0004">Examples of alkoxy- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates are known in the
art and examples are disclosed in the following references: Zh. Org. Khim. (1991), 27(1),
161-170; Zh. Org. Khim. (1988), 24(2), 286-291; Z. Chem. (1987), 27(1), 24-25; Zh.
Org. Khim. (1985), 21(6), 1173-1176; Neftekhim (1983), 23(3), 409-412; and
Neftepererab. Neftekhim. (Moscow) (1983), (1), 20-22.</p><p num="0005">Methods of producing alkylglycidyl thioethers are reported in U. S. patents
4,931,576 and 5,618,778.</p><p num="0006">Examples of commercially available dithiocarbamates include Vanlube 7723, a
methylenebis(dibutyldithiocarbamate), Molyvan A, a molybdenum oxysulfide
dithiocarbamate, Molyvan 822, an organo molybdenum dithiocarbamate, Vanlube AZ, a
zinc diamyldithiocarbamate, Vanlube 71, a lead diamyldithiocarbamate, Vanlube 73, an 
antimony dialkyldithiocarbamate, and Vanlube 732, a dithiocarbamate derivative, all
obtained from R. T. Vanderbilt Company, Inc.</p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0007">According to an embodiment of the present invention, novel dithiocarbamate
compositions are prepared by reacting alkyl glycidyl thioethers with primary and/or
secondary amines and carbon disulfide. These new dithiocarbamates are effective
antioxidants and wear inhibitors and can be used in low phosphorus lubricants as a partial
replacement for ZDDP. An additional benefit of the dithiocarbamates of the present
invention is that they are not detrimental to the friction modification properties of
lubricants.</p><p num="0008">The compounds described in this invention act to improve wear and oxidation
performance in engine oils containing reduced levels of ZDDP's, i.e. engine oils
containing reduced levels of phosphorus.</p><p num="0009">A further benefit which these low cost wear inhibitors of the present invention
provide is to reduce friction in fully formulated crankcase engine oils containing low
levels of ZDDP's, thereby, providing improved fuel economy to the engine.</p><p num="0010">This invention describes a new class of alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted
dithiocarbamate compounds that have utility as anti-wear and oxidation inhibitors in, for
example, crankcase oils. The dithiocarbamates of the present invention may be used in a
wide variety of crankcase oils including passenger car engine oils, heavy duty diesel
engine oils, railroad oils, and natural gas engine oils. They may be used as the main anti-wear 
component to deliver wear and oxidation protection in lubricants that contain no
additional anti-wear additives. In this case they would be considered the principle anti-wear
component. Used as such they can be applied towards the development of zero
phosphorus crankcase oils. They may also be used as a supplemental anti-wear
component in lubricants containing one or more additional anti-wear additives. An
example of this would be their use as supplemental anti-wear components in passenger
car engine oils containing reduced levels of phosphorus.</p><p num="0011">A reduced level of phosphorus for SJ oils is defined as any phosphorus level less
than the maximum currently allowable level of 1000 ppm. Typical reduced phosphorus
levels may range from about 900 ppm phosphorus to levels as low as about 500 ppm
phosphorus or lower. In such cases, the dithiocarbamates of the present invention can be
used in combination with ZDDP's to deliver both wear and oxidation performance.</p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0012">The chemical structure of the alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted
dithiocarbamates according to an embodiment of the present invention is shown below,
where R and R' may be hydrogen or alkyl with the requirement that at least one of R
and/or R' is alkyl, R" is alkyl or R'''OCOCH<sub>2</sub> or R'''OCOCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub> where R"' is alkyl,
and X is S. In a preferred embodiment, R" is alkyl with a chain length of C<sub>4</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>, more
preferably C<sub>9</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>. <img id="img-00050001" orientation="unknown" wi="65" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050001.tif" inline="no" he="26"/></p><p num="0013">In an embodiment of the present invention, it is preferred that the total sum of
carbon atoms in R, R' and R" be greater than ten so that the additive is of low volatility
and remains in the formulated crankcase oil at elevated operating temperatures.
Additives with ten or less carbons are too volatile for use in the high temperature
crankcase environment. In use, such volatile components would evaporate out of the
crankcase before they could perform their anti-wear and anti-oxidant functions.
According to the present invention, alkyl groups for R, R', R", and R''' may vary from 1
to about 22 carbon atoms and can include all possible linear, or <i>n</i>-, and branched, or <i>iso-</i>,
alkyl isomers. Examples of typical alkyl groups include methyl, ethyl, propyl, butyl,
pentyl, hexyl, heptyl, octyl, nonyl, decyl, undecyl, dodecyl, tridecyl, tetradecyl,
pentadecyl, hexadecyl, heptadecyl, and octadecyl and include all possible isomers of each
alkyl type. For example, the 2-ethylhexyl alkyl group is considered an isomer of the
octyl group. R and R' can be independently selected from alkyl groups having three to
eight carbon atoms, and preferably having four to six carbon atoms.</p><p num="0014">The alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates of the present invention
may be prepared in one embodiment by combining at approximately equal molar
concentrations an epoxide, a primary or secondary amine, and carbon disulfide. The
reactions are carried out at low temperatures, such as 0° to 30°C, but temperatures as high 
as, for example, 80°C are operative herein.</p><p num="0015">Thus, in another embodiment, the present invention is directed to a method of
preparing a composition comprising reacting an alkyl glycidyl thioether with a primary
and/or secondary amine, and carbon disulfide.
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="23"/>
It is preferred that equal molar concentrations of the three components (epoxide, amine,
and carbon disulfide) be used. However, a small excess of any one or two components
may be used, especially if the excess can be removed once the reaction is complete. For
example, a typical molar ratio of epoxide to amine to carbon disulfide may be about
1:1:1.2.</p><p num="0016">Examples of epoxides that may be used in preparing the additives of the present
invention can include methylglycidyl thioether, ethylglycidyl thioether. <i>n</i>-propylglycidyl
thioether, <i>n</i>-butylglycidyl thioether, <i>sec</i>-butylglycidyl thioether, <i>n</i>-hexylglycidyl
thioether, cyclohexylglycidyl thioether, <i>n</i>-octylglycidyl thioether, <i>tert</i>-nonylglycidyl
thioether, <i>n</i>-dodecylglycidyl thioether, <i>tert</i>-dodecylglycidyl thioether, and mixtures of
these. Additional epoxides that may be used in the present invention include carboxylic
acid ester-substituted alkyl glycidyl thioethers, such as those with the following chemical
structures: <img id="img-00070001"  orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif"  inline="no"  he="24"/>
where the alkyl group can vary from methyl to dodecyl and can include both linear and
branched alkyl groups.</p><p num="0017">Methods of producing alkylglycidyl thioethers are reported in U. S. patents
4,931,576 and 5,618,778.</p><p num="0018">A diluent may be used in the reaction but such diluents are not necessary. In fact,
it is preferred that a diluent not be used in order to keep manufacturing costs low and
production cycle times short. Examples of diluents include water, alcohols, hydrocarbon
solvents, aromatic solvents, chlorinated solvents, polar aprotic solvents, diluent oils,
process oils, and base oils. Diluents may be carried over from the preparation of the
epoxides and used in the subsequent preparation of the alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted
dithiocarbamates. For example, in one embodiment of the present invention,
the dithiocarbamates may be prepared in two steps by first preparing the epoxide from the
mercaptan and epichlorohydrin, without isolation or purification of the epoxide, followed
by reaction of the epoxide with the amine and carbon disulfide. In such a case, the water
from the preparation of the epoxide is retained and carried over into the reaction to assist
in the preparation of the alkylthio- and hydroxyl- substituted dithiocarbamates of the
present invention. This reaction, as shown below, allows the preparation of the new
dithiocarbamates from readily available raw materials in two reaction steps using only 
one reactor.
<img id="img-00080001"  orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/></p><p num="0019">Thus, in another embodiment, the present invention is directed to a method
including the steps: providing an epoxide by reacting a mercaptan and epichlorohydrin;
and reacting the epoxide with the amine and carbon disulfide. In one embodiment of this
method, the epoxide is not isolated or purified before reacting with said amine and carbon
disulfide.</p><p num="0020">A catalyst may be used in the reaction but such catalysts are not necessary. In
fact, it is preferred that a catalyst not be used in order to keep manufacturing costs low
and production cycle times short.</p><p num="0021">However, catalysts may be required to improve yields of the alkylthio- and
hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates. Examples of catalysts that may be used include
the alkali and alkaline earth metal hydroxides such as lithium hydroxide, sodium
hydroxide, potassium hydroxide, magnesium hydroxide, and calcium hydroxide. The
catalyst may be used as a true catalyst, were the concentration is less than stoichiometric
relative to the amine, or it may be used as a reagent, where the concentration is
stoichiometric or greater relative to the amine. </p><p num="0022">The reaction between amines, carbon disulfide and epoxides are exothermic and
as such do not require heating. In fact, the combination of the three components will
generate substantial heat and usually requires cooling for control and to prevent loss of
the volatile carbon disulfide. Reaction temperatures can vary from 0°C to 30°C during the
combination of the components, and from 20°C to 80°C after the component addition.</p><p num="0023">A typical reaction involves adding, over 1 hour, the amine to a stirred solution
containing carbon disulfide and epoxide at a temperature controlled between 0° and 5°C
by the addition rate. After the addition the reaction mixture is heated at 60° to 80°C for 1
to 2 hours. A vacuum strip may be used to remove excess or residual carbon disulfide or
unreacted amine. The vacuum strip is generally performed for 1 to 2 hours at 60° to 80°C.
Solvents, if used, may be removed by vacuum distillation. Catalysts, if used, may be
removed by carrying out a series of aqueous washes and/or filtrations. Again, it is
preferred to carry out these reactions in the absence of solvent and catalysts.</p><p num="0024">Modifications to the reactions may be made without substantially changing the
product produced. For example, trace quantities of hydrogen peroxide may be added to
reduce the odor of certain products.</p><p num="0025">When the alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates of the present
invention are prepared in two steps from the mercaptan, it is possible that small quantities
of by-products may form. For example, unreacted epichlorohydrin in the first step may
react with two equivalents of amine and two equivalents of carbon disulfide to form a
novel product of the type shown below where R and R' are as defined above, and
preferably are C<sub>3</sub> or greater. For the present invention, this novel by-product is referred 
to herein as 2-hydroxypropyl-1,3-bis-dialkylcarbamodithioate.
<img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="80" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="32"/></p><p num="0026">The presence of this compound in small quantities in the product is not
detrimental and may in fact be beneficial since it possesses structural features similar to
the alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates. This compound can be
eliminated, if desired, by purification of the intermediate epoxide.</p><p num="0027">A small amount of epichlorohydrin in the first step may react with two
equivalents of mercaptan to form a product of the type shown below where R" is as
defined above. The presence of this compound in small quantities in the product is not
detrimental and may in fact be beneficial since it possesses structural features similar to
the alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates of the present invention. The
presence of this compound can be eliminated by purification of the intermediate epoxide.
<img id="img-00100002" orientation="unknown" wi="60" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00100002.tif" inline="no" he="27"/></p><p num="0028">The principle difference between the dithiocarbamates of the prior art and the
alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates of the present invention lies in the
presence of two types of sulfur within the same molecule. The prior art dithiocarbamates 
contain sulfur in the form of the dithiocarbamate functional group. The new
dithiocarbamates of this invention contain sulfur in two forms, i.e., as the dithiocarbamate
functional group, and as a sulfide functional group. The combination of two forms of
sulfur, in which one form is a sulfide and the other form is a dithiocarbamate, combined
with the presence of the bridging hydroxyl groups, gives these new dithiocarbamates
unique properties as antioxidants and anti-wear inhibitors, while at the same time
showing no harm to finished lubricant frictional properties.</p><p num="0029">Further advantages of the new alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted
dithiocarbamates are as follows:</p><p num="0030">They are ashless. This is an advantage in formulating low ash lubricants such as
low ash heavy duty diesel engine oils and natural gas engine oils.</p><p num="0031">They do not contain phosphorus. This is primarily an advantage when formulating
low or zero phosphorus lubricants for passenger car engine oils. The use of phosphorus-free
additives improves catalytic converter performance, which results in reduced NOx
emissions over the life of the passenger car.</p><p num="0032">They have low thermal stabilities. This improves the performance of the new
dithiocarbamates as anti-wear additives. Some commercial dithiocarbamates have very
high thermal stabilities and as such are used primarily as antioxidants in high temperature
applications. An example of such a commercial dithiocarbamate with high thermal
stability is methylenebis (dibutyldithiocarbamate).</p><p num="0033">It has also been found that when X is equal to a group other than S, the
performance of lubricating oils containing the resulting dithiocarbamate is significantly 
diminished. In order to maximize performance of the lubricating oils it is critical to have
X = S. This will be demonstrated in the performance bench tests provided in the
examples below.</p><p num="0034">The alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates of the present invention
may be used as antioxidants and anti-wear additives in a wide variety of lubricants.
Examples of typical applications include passenger car engine oils, heavy duty diesel
engine oils, railroad oils, natural gas engine oils, industrial and automotive gear oils,
automatic and manual transmission fluids, hydraulic oils, rust and oxidation oils, turbine
oils, and greases. They may also be used in a wide variety of viscosity grade oils and
basestock types.</p><p num="0035">These alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates can be used to
formulate low phosphorus passenger car engine oils by replacing all or part of the
ZDDP's currently used. One advantage of these new dithiocarbamates over ZDDP's is
that the additives of the present invention are not detrimental to the friction modification
properties of the lubricant. This can translate to improved fuel economy performance in
certain types of passenger car engines. Another advantage is that they do not contain
phosphorus, so there is currently no mandated upper limit on the quantities of such
compounds that may be used in passenger car oils.</p><p num="0036">Thus, the present invention also provides a lubricant additive comprising a novel
dialkyl dithiocarbamate of the present invention, as well as lubricating oil containing such
a lubricant additive. Lubricating oils of the present invention can further contain at least
one of a detergent, a dispersant, an antiwear agent, a friction modifier, a pour point 
depressant, a foam inhibitor, a corrosion inhibitor, a rust inhibitor, and a viscosity index
improver. In addition, the lubricating oils of the present invention can further contain at
least one antioxidant selected from diphenylamines. phenothiazines, hindered phenols,
alkyl phenols, sulfurized hindered phenols, sulfurized alkyl phenols, methylene-bridged
hindered phenols, sulfides and polysulfides, sulfurized olefins, sulturized fats and
sulfurized oils.</p><p num="0037">The compositions of the present invention are effective for reducing the oxidation
of lubricating oils in which the compositions are incorporated. In addition, the
compositions of the present invention reduce deposit formation in an engine lubricated
with a lubricating oil containing the compositions, relative to the deposits formed in an
engine lubricated with an oil which does not contain a composition of the present
invention. Also, engine wear and engine friction are reduced by lubricating the engine
with an oil containing a dialkyl dithiocarbamate composition of the present invention.
Fuel economy, color retention, and odor reduction are also benefits derived from the use
of the compositions of the present invention in oils used to lubricate engines, relative to
engines lubricated with oils which do not contain the compositions of the present
invention. Finally, improved engines, automatic transmissions, turbines, gears, and
hydraulics are provided by the present invention when such equipment is lubricated with
the compositions and oils of the present invention. </p><heading><b>Examples</b></heading><heading><b>Comparative Example 1</b></heading><p num="0038">A 250 mL four neck round bottom flask is equipped with a magnetic stirrer, an
addition funnel, a thermometer, and a nitrogen inlet. A slight positive pressure of
nitrogen atmosphere is maintained in the reaction flask. The reactor is charged with 2-ethylhexyl
glycidyl ether (28.0 g, 0.150 mol) and carbon disulfide (13.0 g, 0.171 mol).
The mixture is stirred with cooling to approximately room temperature (tap water bath).
Bis(2-ethylhexyl)amine (35.8 g, 0.148 mol) is slowly added to the reaction over a 1 hour
period. An exotherm is observed and the addition is controlled to keep the reaction
temperature under 30°C. After 4 hours at ambient temperature the mixture is gently
heated for 1 hour at 50°C. The reaction mixture is cooled below 30° C and an additional
charge of carbon disulfide (1.2 g, 0.016 mol) is added. Stirring at ambient temperature is
continued overnight. The next morning the reaction is heated to 50°C and held at that
temperature, under vacuum, for 1.5 hours. A yellow viscous liquid (74.7 g, 98.7 %) is
isolated. Sulfur content = 12.41 wt % (theory = 12.72 wt %), Nitrogen content = 2.94 wt
% (theory = 2.78 wt %). Low molecular weight GPC analysis of the liquid shows the
presence of a single peak (100 %, r. t. = 22.3 min). FT-IR, <sup>13</sup>C-NMR and H-NMR
analysis confirms that the main component of the mixture is 3-(2-ethylhexyloxy)-2-hydroxypropyl
bis(2-ethylhexyl)carbamodithioate having the following chemical
structure:
<img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="39"/></p><heading><b>Comparative Example 2</b></heading><p num="0039">A 250 mL four neck round bottom flask is equipped with a magnetic stirrer, an
addition funnel, a thermometer, and a nitrogen inlet. A slight positive pressure of
nitrogen atmosphere is maintained in the reaction flask. The reactor is charged with 2-ethylhexyl
glycidyl ether (28.0 g, 0.150 m) and carbon disulfide (14.3 g, 0.188 m). The
mixture is stirred with cooling to approximately room temperature (tap water bath).
Dibutylamine (19.2 g, 0.149 m) is slowly added to the reaction over a 30-minute period.
An exotherm is observed and the addition is controlled to keep the reaction temperature
under 30°C. After 2 hours at ambient temperature the mixture is gently heated for 2 hours
at 35°C followed by 1 hour at 50°C. Volatile components are removed under vacuum at
50°C for 1.5 hours. A yellow viscous liquid (57.8 g, 95.7 %) is isolated. Sulfur content =
16.07 wt % (theory = 16.37 wt %), Nitrogen content = 3.86 wt % (theory = 3.58 wt %).
Low molecular weight GPC analysis of the liquid shows the presence of predominantly
one peak (99 %, r. t. = 23.0 min). FT-IR, <sup>13</sup>C-NMR and H-NMR analysis confirms that
the main component of the mixture is 3-(2-ethylhexyloxy)-2-hydroxypropyl
dibutylcarbamodithioate having the following chemical structure:
<img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="39"/></p><heading><b>Inventive Example 1</b></heading><p num="0040">A 1000 mL four neck round bottom flask is equipped with a mechanical stirrer, an
addition funnel, a thermometer, and a reflux condenser cooled to approximately 5°C. Dry
nitrogen is passed into the reactor through the addition funnel and out of the reactor
through the reflux condenser. The reactor is chilled with an ice water bath and charged
with epichlorohydrin (46.3 g, 0.50 mol) and <i>tert</i>-dodecylmercaptan (101.1 g, 0.50 mol).
The mixture is stirred with cooling to approximately 5°-10°C. Sodium hydroxide (21.2 g,
0.53 mol), water (230 g) and tetrabutylammonium hydroxide (40% in water, 6.0 g, 6
mmol) are combined with mixing and slowly added to the epichlorohydrin and <i>tert</i>-dodecylmercaptan
over a 1 hour period. An exotherm is observed and cooling is
continued maintaining the reaction temperature between 5°-10°C during the addition.
After the addition the reaction is heated for 2 hours at 50°C and cooled to 5°C. Carbon
disulfide (40.0 g, 0.53 mol) is then added rapidly to the reaction mixture. Next,
dibutylamine (65.0 g, 0.50 mol) is slowly added over 1 hour while maintaining the
reaction temperature between 5°-15°C. The reaction is warmed to ambient temperature
overnight. The following morning the reaction is heated at 80°C for 1 hour and then 0.60
g of 30% hydrogen peroxide is added at 70°C. The reaction is heated at 70°C for an
additional 15 minutes, cooled to 50°C, and the phases separated. The organic portion is
washed with 2 x 100 mL of water. The organic solution is returned to a 500 mL three
neck round bottom flask and residual water is removed under vacuum at 60°C for 3 hours.
The product is filtered through a coarse fritted glass funnel yielding 220.0 g (94.5 %) of
a clear yellow viscous liquid with the following physical and chemical properties: <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Nitrogen Content</entry><entry align="left">3.14 wt %</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sulfur Content</entry><entry align="left">19.68 wt %</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity @ 40°C</entry><entry align="left">295 cSt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Low Molecular Weight GPC Analysis</entry><entry align="left">97.1 % dialkylated product (r.t. = 22.7 min)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">TGA Weight Loss</entry><entry align="left">10% loss @ 212°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">25% loss @ 241°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">50% loss @ 268°C</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables>
FT-IR, <sup>13</sup>C-NMR and H-NMR analysis confirms that the main component of the mixture
is 3-(<i>tert</i>-dodecylthio)-2-hydroxypropyl dibutylcarbamodithioate having the following
chemical structure:
<img id="img-00170001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/></p><heading><b>Inventive Example 2</b></heading><p num="0041">A 2000 mL four neck round bottom flask is equipped with a mechanical stirrer, an
addition funnel, a thermometer, and a reflux condenser cooled to approximately 5°C. Dry
nitrogen is passed into the reactor through the addition funnel and out of the reactor
through the reflux condenser. The reactor is chilled with an ice water bath and charged
with epichlorohydrin (138.9 g, 1.50 mol) and 2-ethylhexyl 3-mercaptopropionate (327.6
g, 1.50 mol). The mixture is stirred with cooling to approximately 5°-10°C. Sodium
hydroxide (63.0 g, 1.58 mol), water (700 g) and tetrabutylammonium hydroxide (40% in
water, 18.8 g, 19 mmol) are combined with mixing and slowly added to the 
epichlorohydrin and 2-ethylhexyl 3-mercaptopropionate over a 1 hour period. An
exotherm is observed at the beginning of the addition that causes the temperature to reach
80°C. The temperature is returned to 5°C and cooling is continued maintaining the
reaction temperature between 5°-10°C for the remainder of the addition. After the
addition the reaction is heated for 2 hours at 50°C and cooled overnight. The following
morning the reaction is cooled to 5°C and carbon disulfide (120.0 g. 1.58 mol) is added.
Next, dibutylamine (193.8.0 g, 1.50 mol) is slowly added over 1 hour while maintaining
the reaction temperature between 5°-15°C. The reaction is heated at 80"C for 1 hour and
then 5.0 g of 30% hydrogen peroxide is added at 70°C. The reaction is heated at 70°C for
an additional 15 minutes, cooled to 50°C, and the phases separated. The organic portion
is washed with 400 mL of 10% aqueous sodium bicarbonate. Toluene (300 mL) is added
to improve phase separation and the organic solution is washed with 2 x 300 mL of water.
Toluene is removed on a rotary evaporator under a water aspirator vacuum. The organic
product is then returned to a 1000 mL three neck round bottom flask and residual water is
removed under vacuum at 60°C for 3 hours. The product is filtered through a coarse
fritted glass funnel yielding 692.0 g (95.2 %) of a clear yellow viscous liquid with the
following physical and chemical properties:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Nitrogen Content</entry><entry align="left">3.00 wt %</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sulfur Content</entry><entry align="left">19.28 wt %</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity @ 40°C</entry><entry align="left">116 cSt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Low Molecular Weight GPC Analysis</entry><entry align="left">91.3 % dialkylated product (r.t. = 22.6 min)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">TGA Weight Loss</entry><entry align="left">10% loss @ 236°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">25% loss @ 269°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">50% loss @ 288°C</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables> 
FT-IR, <sup>13</sup>C-NMR and H-NMR analysis confirms that the main component of the mixture
is 2-ethylhexyl 3-[[3-[[(dibutylamino)thioxomethyl]thio]-2-hydroxypropyl]thio]propanoate
having the following chemical structure:
<img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="158" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="38"/></p><heading><b>Inventive Example 3</b></heading><p num="0042">A 1000 mL four neck round bottom flask is equipped with a mechanical stirrer, an
addition funnel, a thermometer, and a reflux condenser cooled to approximately 5°C. Dry
nitrogen is passed into the reactor through the addition funnel and out of the reactor
through the reflux condenser. The reactor is chilled with an ice water bath and charged
with epichlorohydrin (46.3 g, 0.50 mol) and <i>n</i>-dodecylmercaptan (101.2 g, 0.50 mol).
The mixture is stirred with cooling to approximately 5°-10°C. Sodium hydroxide (21.0 g,
0.52 mol), water (240 g) and tetrabutylammonium hydroxide (40% in water, 7.0 g, 7
mmol) are combined with mixing and slowly added to the epichlorohydrin and <i>n</i>-dodecylmercaptan
over a 1 hour period. An exotherm is observed and cooling is
continued maintaining the reaction temperature between 5°-10°C during the addition.
After the addition the reaction is heated for 2 hours at 50°C and cooled to 5°C. Carbon
disulfide (40.0 g, 0.53 mol) is then added rapidly to the reaction mixture. Next,
dibutylamine (64.6 g, 0.50 mol) is slowly added over 1 hour while maintaining the 
reaction temperature between 5°-15°C. After the addition the reaction is heated at 80°C
for 1 hour and then 1.0 g of 30% hydrogen peroxide is added at 80"C. The reaction is
heated at 80°C for an additional 30 minutes, cooled to 50°C, and the phases separated.
The organic portion is washed with 2 x 100 mL of water. The organic solution is
returned to a 500 mL three neck round bottom flask and residual water is removed under
vacuum at 60°C for 2 hours. The product is filtered through a coarse fritted glass funnel
yielding 226.6 g (97.7 %) of a clear yellow viscous liquid with the following physical and
chemical properties:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Nitrogen Content</entry><entry align="left">3.10 wt %</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sulfur Content</entry><entry align="left">19.21 wt %</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity @ 40°C</entry><entry align="left">85 cSt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Low Molecular Weight GPC Analysis</entry><entry align="left">96.8 % dialkylated product (r.t. = 22.3 min)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">TGA Weight Loss</entry><entry align="left">10% loss @ 228°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">25% loss @ 267°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">50% loss @ 287°C</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables>
FT-IR, <sup>13</sup>C-NMR and H-NMR analysis confirms that the main component of the mixture
is the 3-(<i>n</i>-dodecylthio)-2-hydroxypropyl dibutylcarbamodithioate having the following
chemical structure:
<img id="img-00200001" orientation="unknown" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00200001.tif" inline="no" he="38"/></p><heading><b>Inventive Example 4</b></heading><p num="0043">A 250 mL four neck round bottom flask is equipped with a mechanical stirrer, an
addition funnel, a thermometer, and a reflux condenser cooled to approximately 5°C. Dry
nitrogen is passed into the reactor through the addition funnel and out of the reactor
through the reflux condenser. The reactor is chilled with an ice water bath and charged
with epichlorohydrin (11.6 g, 0.125 mol) and <i>tert</i>-dodecylmercaptan (25.3 g, 0.125 mol).
The mixture is stirred with cooling to approximately 5°-10°C. Sodium hydroxide (5.2 g,
0.13 mol), water (60 mL) and tetrabutylammonium hydroxide (40% in water, 1.75 g, 1.7
mmol) are combined with mixing and slowly added to the epichlorohydrin and <i>tert</i>-dodecylmercaptan
over a 1 hour period. An exotherm is observed and cooling is
continued maintaining the reaction temperature between 5°-10°C during the addition.
After the addition the reaction mixture is slowly warmed to room temperature over 1-1/2
hours. The reaction is heated for an additional 1 hour at 50°C and then cooled to 5°C.
Carbon disulfide (10.0 g, 0.131 mol) is added rapidly to the reaction mixture. Then bis(2-ethylhexyl)amine
(30.3 g, 0.125 mol) is slowly added over 1 hour while maintaining the
reaction temperature between 5°-15°C. The reaction is heated at 80°C for 1 hour and
diluted with 60 mL of toluene. The phases are separated and the organic portion is
washed with 50 mL of water. The organic solution is dried with MgSO<sub>4</sub> and concentrated
on a rotary evaporator for 2 hours. A yellow viscous liquid (69.9 g, 96.7 %) is isolated.
Sulfur content = 15.26 wt %, Nitrogen content = 2.66 wt %. Low molecular weight GPC
analysis of the liquid shows the presence of a main peak (90.7 %, r. t. = 22.1 min)
corresponding to a product formed by dialkylating epichlorohydrin. FT-IR, <sup>13</sup>C-NMR 
and H-NMR analysis confirms that the main component of the mixture is 3-(<i>tert</i>-dodecylthio)-2-hydroxypropyl
bis(2-ethylhexyl)carbamodithioate having the following
chemical structure.
<img id="img-00220001" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00220001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/></p><heading><b>Inventive Example 5</b></heading><p num="0044">In a procedure analogous to that followed in Inventive Example 4, 2-ethylhexylamine
is reacted with <i>tert</i>-dodecylmercaptan, epichlorohydrin, and carbon
disulfide. A yellow viscous liquid (56.2 g, 96.6 %) is isolated. Sulfur content = 19.43 wt
%, Nitrogen content = 3.37 wt %. Low molecular weight GPC analysis of the liquid
shows the presence of a main peak (79.9 %, r. t. = 22.5 min) corresponding to a product
formed by dialkylating epichlorohydrin. FT-IR, <sup>13</sup>C-NMR and H-NMR analysis confirms
that the main component of the mixture is 3-(<i>tert</i>-dodecylthio)-2-hydroxypropyl 2-ethylhexylcarbamodithioate
having the following chemical structure:
<img id="img-00220002" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00220002.tif" inline="no" he="28"/></p><p num="0045">The advantages of the new alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates
are shown in the following examples where their effectiveness as antioxidants, friction
modifiers and anti-wear additives is demonstrated. In Example 6, the benefits as
antioxidants over alkoxy- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates is demonstrated. In
Example 7, the benefits as friction modifiers over a commercial dithiocarbamate Vanlube
7723 (DTC) and zinc dialkyldithiophosphates (ZDDP) are demonstrated. In Example 8,
the benefits as wear inhibitors over DTC are demonstrated. In Example 9, the benefits as
wear inhibitors in the presence of a wear promoter are demonstrated. In Example 10,
TGA is used to explain the observed performance properties.</p><heading><b>Example 6</b></heading><p num="0046">A variety of alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates and alkoxy- and
hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates were blended into an SAE Grade 5W-30 type
motor oil as shown in Table 1. These oils contained a typical dispersant inhibitor
package and were formulated with a low sulfur and low aromatic hydrocracked and
isodewaxed basestock that meets the API Group II category. The oils contained 500 ppm
phosphorus derived from secondary zinc dialkyldithiophosphate (ZDDP). For
comparison, a commercial dithiocarbamate antioxidant (DTC), Vanlube 7723, available
from R. T. Vanderbilt company, Inc., a commercial sulfurized olefin antioxidant (SO),
HiTEC 7188, available from Ethyl Corporation, and a commercial zinc
dialkyldithiophosphate (ZDDP), HiTEC 7169 available from Ethyl Corporation, were
included in the study. All additive treat rates for the dithiocarbamates, sulfurized olefin 
and the zinc dialkyldithiophosphate were based on delivering equal sulfur to the oil (1500
ppm sulfur). Therefore, the higher the sulfur content is of the additive, the lower the
additive treat rate to the finished oil is. It is desirable to have low additive treat rates.
Some oils also contained an alkylated diphenylamine antioxidant (DPA), HiTEC 4793,
available from Ethyl Corporation. The oxidation stability of these oils was measured by
pressurized differential scanning calorimetry (PDSC) as described by J. A. Walker and
W. Tsang in "Characterization of Lubrication Oils By Differential Scanning
Calorimetry", SAE Technical Paper Series. 801383 (Oct. 20-23, 1980). Oil samples were
treated with an iron (III) naphthenate catalyst (55 ppm Fe) and 2.0 milligrams were
analyzed in an open aluminum hermetic pan. The DSC cell was pressurized with 500 psi
air and programmed with the following heating sequence: (1) jump from ambient to
155°C, (2) ramp from 155°C to 175°C at 10°C/minute, (3) ramp from 1.75°C to 185°C at
5°C/minute, (4) iso-track at 185°C. The oil samples were held at 185°C until an
exothermic release of heat was observed. The exothermic release of heat marks the
oxidation reaction. The time from the start of the experiment to the exothermic release of
heat is called the oxidation induction time and is a measure of the oxidative stability of
the oil (i.e. the longer the oxidation induction time, the greater the oxidative stability of
the oil). All oils are evaluated in duplicate and the results averaged. As shown in Table
1, at an equal sulfur comparison the new alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted
dithiocarbamates are more effective than alkoxy- and hydroxyl-substituted
dithiocarbamates. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Oil ID</entry><entry align="left">5W-30 Motor Oil (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">DPA (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">Additive</entry><entry align="left">Additive Treat (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">100 N Diluent (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">Induction Time (min)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">1</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="left">None</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">2.494</entry><entry align="center">14.4</entry></row><row><entry align="right">2</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">None</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">1.994</entry><entry align="center">43.8</entry></row><row><entry align="right">3</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">SO</entry><entry align="center">1.20</entry><entry align="center">0.794</entry><entry align="center">77.9</entry></row><row><entry align="right">4</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">1.21</entry><entry align="center">0.784</entry><entry align="center">49.6</entry></row><row><entry align="right">5</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">0.93</entry><entry align="center">1.064</entry><entry align="center">66.6</entry></row><row><entry align="right">6</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry> <entry align="left">Inventive Example 1</entry><entry align="center">0.74</entry><entry align="center">1.254</entry><entry align="center">80.3</entry></row> <row><entry align="right">7</entry> <entry align="center">97.506</entry> <entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">Inventive Example 2</entry><entry align="center">0.77</entry><entry align="center">1.224</entry><entry align="center">89.4</entry></row><row><entry align="right">8</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">Inventive Example 3</entry><entry align="center">0.75</entry><entry align="center">1.244</entry><entry align="center">86.8</entry></row><row><entry align="right">9</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">ZDDP</entry><entry align="center">0.60</entry><entry align="center">1.894</entry><entry align="center">83.7</entry></row><row><entry align="right">10</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">DTC</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="center">1.494</entry><entry align="center">98.3</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b>Example 7</b></heading><p num="0047">The same oils evaluated for oxidation performance in Example 6 were also
evaluated for boundary friction properties using the High Frequency Reciprocating Rig
(HFRR). In this instrument 1-2 milliliters of the test motor oil are placed in a temperature
controlled steel pan. A steel ball attached to a moveable arm is lowered into the pan. A
load of 400 grams is applied to the steel ball/arm assembly. The steel/ball arm assembly
is oscillated at 20 Hz over a 1 millimeter path length. As the arm is oscillated a friction
coefficient is determined every 5 seconds. The test lasts 3 minutes so approximately 30
data points are averaged to determine the friction coefficient of an oil. A reduction in the
friction coefficient corresponds to improved friction properties of the oil. Duplicate tests
were performed on each oil at 130°C. The average friction coefficient for each sample is
shown in Table 2. The results show that the addition of zinc dialkyldithiophosphate 
(ZDDP), or methylenebis(dibutyldithiocarbamate) (DTC) is detrimental to the friction
properties of the oil. However, the alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates
and the alkoxy- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates show no harm to the friction
properties of the oil.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Oil ID</entry><entry align="left">5W-30 Motor Oil (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">DPA (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">Additive</entry><entry align="left">Additive Treat (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">100 N Diluent (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">Friction Coefficient</entry></row><row><entry align="right">1</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="left">None</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">2.494</entry><entry align="center">0.083</entry></row><row><entry align="right">2</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">None</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">1.994</entry><entry align="center">0.075</entry></row><row><entry align="right">3</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">SO</entry><entry align="center">1.20</entry><entry align="center">0.794</entry><entry align="center">0.081</entry></row><row><entry align="right">4</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">1.21</entry><entry align="center">0.784</entry><entry align="center">0.077</entry></row><row><entry align="right">5</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">0.93</entry><entry align="center">1.064</entry><entry align="center">0.075</entry></row><row><entry align="right">6</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">Inventive Example 1</entry><entry align="center">0.74</entry><entry align="center">1.254</entry><entry align="center">0.074</entry></row><row><entry align="right">7</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">Inventive Example 2</entry><entry align="center">0.77</entry><entry align="center">1.224</entry><entry align="center">0.076</entry></row><row><entry align="right">8</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">Inventive Example 3</entry><entry align="center">0.75</entry><entry align="center">1.244</entry><entry align="center">0.075</entry></row><row><entry align="right">9</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">ZDDP</entry><entry align="center">0.60</entry><entry align="center">1.894</entry><entry align="center">0.086</entry></row><row><entry align="right">10</entry><entry align="center">97.506</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="left">DTC</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="center">1.494</entry><entry align="center">0.085</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b>Example 8</b></heading><p num="0048">The anti-wear properties of the alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted
dithiocarbamates were demonstrated using the Four Ball Wear Test as defined in ASTM
D-4172. The additives being evaluated were blended into a SAE Grade 5W-30 type
motor oil as shown in Table 3. The motor oils contained a typical dispersant inhibitor
package and were formulated with a low sulfur and low aromatic hydrocracked and
isodewaxed basestock that meets the API Group II category. The oils also contained 500 
ppm phosphorus derived from secondary zinc dialkyldithiophosphate (ZDDP) and 0.3 wt.
% HiTEC 4793 alkylated diphenylamine antioxidant. For comparison, a commercial
dithiocarbamate antioxidant (DTC), Vanlube 7723, was included in the study. All
additive treat rates for the dithiocarbamates were based on delivering equal sulfur to the
oil (750 ppm sulfur). Therefore, the higher the sulfur content of the additive, the lower
the additive treat rate to the finished oil. All oils were treated with 1.0 wt. % cumene
hydroperoxide as a wear promoter prior to testing. Results in the Four Ball Wear Test are
reported as a wear scar in millimeters. Low values for wear scar indicate effective wear
protection while high values indicate poor wear protection. The results in Table 3 clearly
show that the addition of the alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates
reduces the wear scar in the Four Ball Wear Test. The results also show that the new
alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates are more effective than the
commercial dithiocarbamate Vanlube 7723 at reducing the wear scar.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Oil ID</entry><entry align="left">5W-30 Motor Oil (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">Additive</entry><entry align="left">Additive Treat (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">100 N Diluent (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">Wear Scar (mm)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">11</entry><entry align="center">98.1</entry><entry align="left">None</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">1.90</entry><entry align="center">0.73</entry></row><row><entry align="right">12</entry><entry align="center">98.1</entry><entry align="left">Inventive Example 1</entry><entry align="center">0.37</entry><entry align="center">1.53</entry><entry align="center">0.54</entry></row><row><entry align="right">13</entry><entry align="center">98.1</entry><entry align="left">Inventive Example 2</entry><entry align="center">0.38</entry><entry align="center">1.52</entry><entry align="center">0.60</entry></row><row><entry align="right">14</entry><entry align="center">98.1</entry><entry align="left">Inventive Example 3</entry><entry align="center">0.38</entry><entry align="center">1.52</entry><entry align="center">0.52</entry></row><row><entry align="right">15</entry><entry align="center">98.1</entry><entry align="left">DTC</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry><entry align="center">1.65</entry><entry align="center">0.63</entry></row><row><entry align="right">16</entry><entry align="center">98.1</entry><entry align="left">Sulfurized Olefin</entry><entry align="center">0.38</entry><entry align="center">1.53</entry><entry align="center">0.63</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b>Example 9</b></heading><p num="0049">Four Ball Wear Tests, as defined above, were performed in a slightly different
motor oil. The additives being evaluated were blended into an SAE Grade 5W-30 type
motor oil as shown in Table 4. The motor oils contained a typical dispersant inhibitor
package and were formulated with a low sulfur and low aromatic hydrocracked and
isodewaxed basestock that meets the API Group II category. The oils also contained 500
ppm phosphorus derived from secondary zinc dialkyldithiophosphate (ZDDP) and 0.4 wt.
% HiTEC 4793 alkylated diphenylamine antioxidant. In these evaluations varying levels
of cumene hydroperoxide (peroxide) were used. The dithiocarbamate treat rates were
based on delivering approximately 1500 ppm sulfur to the finished motor oil. The results
in Table 4 clearly show that in the presence of the wear promoter, the addition of the
alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates of the present invention reduces the
wear scar in the Four Ball Wear Test.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Oil ID</entry><entry align="left">5W-30 Motor Oil (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">Additive</entry><entry align="left">Additive Treat (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">100 N Diluent (wt.%)</entry><entry align="left">Wear Scar No Peroxide (mm)</entry><entry align="left">Wear Scar 0.50% Peroxide (mm)</entry><entry align="left">Wear Scar 1% Peroxide (mm)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">17</entry><entry align="center">99.2</entry><entry align="left">None</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">0.80</entry><entry align="center">0.427</entry><entry align="center">0.607</entry><entry align="center">0.740</entry></row><row><entry align="right">18</entry><entry align="center">99.2</entry><entry align="left">Inventive Example 1</entry><entry align="center">0.80</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">0.434</entry><entry align="center">0.526</entry><entry align="center">0.600</entry></row><row><entry align="right">19</entry><entry align="center">99.2</entry><entry align="left">Inventive Example 2</entry><entry align="center">0.80</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">0.453</entry><entry align="center">0.539</entry><entry align="center">0.600</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b>Example 10</b></heading><p num="0050">Thermal Gravimetric Analysis (TGA) can be used as a tool to qualitatively
estimate the thermal stability of additives. This test involves heating a small sample of
additive following a specific temperature ramping sequence. The TGA instrument
monitors sample weight loss as a function of temperature. For materials with
approximately the same molecular weight, a more rapid weight loss rate corresponds
roughly to reduced thermal stability. TGAs were performed on the new alkylthio- and
hydroxyl-substituted dithiocarbamates of the present invention and a commercial
dithiocarbamate Vanlube 7723 (DTC). The following heating sequence was used:
equilibrate at 30°C, ramp at 20°C/min to 900°C. The experiments were performed under a
nitrogen atmosphere. The temperatures at which specific weight losses were observed are
reported in Table 5. The results show that the alkylthio- and hydroxyl-substituted
dithiocarbamates of the present invention are more volatile than the commercial
dithiocarbamate DTC. Since the molecular weights of the new dithiocarbamates are
slightly higher than DTC, the more rapid weight loss is due to reduced thermal stability.
This data illustrates that the dithiocarbamates of the present invention are decomposing at
lower temperatures than the conventional DTC, and such a property explains the
improved anti-wear and friction performance of the new dithiocarbamates relative to
conventional DTC. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Dithiocarbamate Sample</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Inventive Example 1</entry><entry align="center">Inventive Example 2</entry><entry align="center">Inventive Example 3</entry><entry align="center">DTC</entry></row><row><entry nameend="5" align="left" namest="1">Additive Molecular Weight</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Calcd.</entry><entry align="right">464</entry><entry align="right">480</entry><entry align="right">464</entry><entry align="right">423</entry></row><row><entry nameend="5" align="left" namest="1">TGA Weight Loss Temperature (C)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">10% @</entry><entry align="right">212</entry><entry align="right">236</entry><entry align="right">228</entry><entry align="right">302</entry></row><row><entry align="left">25% @</entry><entry align="right">241</entry><entry align="right">269</entry><entry align="right">267</entry><entry align="right">316</entry></row><row><entry align="left">50% @</entry><entry align="right">268</entry><entry align="right">288</entry><entry align="right">287</entry><entry align="right">329</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0051">This invention is susceptible to considerable variation in its practice.
Accordingly, this invention is not limited to the specific exemplifications set forth
hereinabove. Rather, this invention is within the spirit and scope of the appended claims,
including the equivalents thereof available as a matter of law.</p><p num="0052">The patentee does not intend to dedicate any disclosed embodiments to the public,
and to the extent any disclosed modifications or alterations may not literally fall within
the scope of the claims, they are considered to be part of the invention under the doctrine
of equivalents.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A compound of formula

wherein R and R1 may be the same or different and each is hydrogen or alkyl
provided that at least one of R or R1 is alkyl and R2 is alkyl, R3OCOCH2 or
R3OCOCH2CH2 where R3 is alkyl, or
</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A compound according to claim 1, wherein R and R1 are the same or different
and each is C3-8 alkyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A compound according to claim 1 or claim 2 wherein R2 is C4 to C12 alkyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A compound according to any preceding claim wherein R2 is alkyl and the
total number of carbon atoms in R, R1 and R2 is greater than 10.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A compound according to claim 1 wherein R2 is

and R and R1 are the same or different and each is alkyl of C3 or greater.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A compound according to claim 1 selected from:<claim-text><claim-text>2-propanol-1,3-bis-dialkylcarbamodithioate;</claim-text><claim-text>3-(tert-dodecylthio)-2-hydroxypropyl 2-ethylhexylcarbamodithioate;</claim-text><claim-text>3-(tert-dodecylthio)-2-hydroxypropyl dibutylcarbamodithioate;</claim-text><claim-text>2-ethylhexyl 3-[[3-[[(dibutylamino)thioxomethyl]thio]-2-hydroxypropyl]thio]
propanoate;</claim-text><claim-text>3-(n-dodecylthio)-2-hydroxypropyl dibutylcarbamodithioate; and</claim-text><claim-text>3-(tert-dodecylthio)-2-hydroxypropyl bis(2-ethylhexy)carbamodithioate.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A composition comprising two or more compounds according to any
preceding claim.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A process of preparing a composition comprising reacting an alkyl glycidyl
thioether with a primary and/or secondary amine, and carbon disulfide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A process according to claim 8 wherein the alkyl glycidyl thioether, primary
and/or secondary amine, and carbon disulfide are combined at approximately
equal molar concentrations.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A process according to claim 8 or claim 9 comprising the steps of reacting a
mercaptan and epichlorohydrin so as to provide an alkylglycidyl thioether and
reacting the alkylglycidyl thioether with the amine and carbon disulfide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A process according to claim 10 wherein the alkylglycidyl thioether is not
isolated or purified before reacting with the amine and carbon disulfide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A process according to any one of claims 8 to 11 wherein the alkylglycidyl
thioether is reacted with a primary amine and carbon disulfide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A process according to claim 12 wherein the alkyl glycidyl thioether is
selected from methylglycidyl thioether, ethylglycidyl thioether, n-propylglycidyl
thioether, n-butylglycidyl thioether, sec-butylglycidyl
thioether, n-hexylglycidyl thioether, cyclohexylglycidyl thioether, n-octylglycidyl
thioether, tert-nonylglycidyl thioether, n-dodecyglycidyl
thioether, tert-dodecylglycidyl thioether, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A process according to claim 12, wherein the alkyl glycidyl thioether is a
carboxylic acid ester-substituted alkyl glycidyl thioether.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A process according to any one of claims 8 to 14 for producing a lubricant
additive.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A lubricating oil or functional fluid comprising a base oil of lubricating
viscosity and a compound according to any one of claims 1 to 6, a
composition according to claim 7, a composition produced by a process
according to any one of claims 8 to 14 or a lubricant additive produced by a
process according to claim 15.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A lubricating oil or functional fluid according to claim 16 further comprising
at least one detergent, dispersant, antiwear agent, friction modifier, pour point
depressant, foam inhibitor, corrosion inhibitor, rust inhibitor or viscosity
index improver.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A lubricating oil or functional fluid according to claim 16 or claim 17 further
comprising at least one antioxidant selected from diphenylamines,
phenothiazine, hindered phenols, sulfurized hindered phenols, alkyl phenols,
sulfurized alkyl phenols, methylene-bridged hindered phenols, sulfides and
polysulfides, sulfurized olefins, and sulfurized fats and oils.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A lubricating oil or functional fluid according any one of claims 16 to 18
formulated as:<claim-text><claim-text>a passenger car crankcase engine oil; a heavy duty diesel engine oil; a railroad
oil; a natural gas engine oil; a hydraulic oil; a turbine oil; a rust and oxidation
oil or an automatic transmission fluid.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>Use of a lubricating oil or functional fluid according to one of claims 16 to 18
as a passenger car crankcase engine oil; a heavy duty diesel engine oil; a
railroad oil; a natural gas engine oil; a hydraulic oil; a turbine oil; a rust and
oxidation oil or an automatic transmission fluid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>A method of reducing the oxidation of a lubricating oil or functional fluid
comprising adding to an oil of lubricating viscosity a compound according to
any one of claims 1 to 6, a composition according to claim 7, a composition
produced by a process according to any one of claims 8 to 14 or a lubricant
additive produced by a process according to claim 15 for reducing engine
wear in an engine, or improving fuel economy in an engine, comprising
lubricating the engine with a lubricating oil according to any one of claims 16
to 18.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>