<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1518906-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1518906" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34194805" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050330"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1518906-A1" status="new" fvid="24312947"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1518906</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050330</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04020732-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04020732</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040901</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-66895603-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>66895603</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030923</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   5/44        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   5/44        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D   5/44K2</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung von Beschichtungen auf elektrisch leitfähigen Substraten mit Kathodischen Elektrotauchlacken</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Process for producing coating on electrically conductive substrates by cathodic electrodeposition coating</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Méthode de production de revêtements sur des substrats électroconducteurs par électrodéposition cathodique</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1384760-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1384760</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="EXA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-2368302-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2368302</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-20030082368-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20030082368</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5670441-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5670441</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6436201-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6436201</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2004000955-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2004000955</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="EXA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DU PONT</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>E.I. DU PONT DE NEMOURS AND COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>E.I. DU PONT DE NEMOURS AND COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1007 Market Street</street><city>Wilmington, Delaware 19898</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KLEIN KLAUSJOERG</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LEHMANN HORST</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SCHIPFER RUDOLF</name><address><country>AT</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KLEIN, KLAUSJOERG</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LEHMANN, HORST</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SCHIPFER, RUDOLF</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KLEIN, KLAUSJOERG</last-name><address><street>Richard-Strauss-Allee 33</street><city>42289 Wuppertal</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>LEHMANN, HORST</last-name><address><street>Graefratherstrasse 13</street><city>42329 Wuppertal</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SCHIPFER, RUDOLF</last-name><address><street>Ernst-Haeckelstrasse 53</street><city>8010 Graz</city><country>AT</country> </address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DuPont Performance Coatings Biering/Blum/Kimpel</last-name> <address><street>DuPont Performance Coatings GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG, Patent &amp;amp; licence Dep., Christbusch 25</street> <city>42285 Wuppertal</city> <country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A process for the production of a CED (cathodic electrodeposition)
coating with improved adhesion towards subsequent layers by cathodic
electrodeposition of a coating layer of a CED coating composition onto an
electrically conductive substrate and thermal curing by baking in an
indirectly heated circulating air oven operated with a proportion of fresh air
in the circulating air of the oven of 0 to 20 vol.%, wherein the CED coating
composition used contains at least one water-soluble metal nitrate
corresponding to a quantity of 1 to 10 mmol of nitrate per 100 g of resin
solids content, wherein the metal is selected from the group consisting of
metals of atomic numbers 20 to 83, with the exception of chromium,
arsenic, rubidium, ruthenium, rhodium, palladium, cadmium, antimony,
caesium, osmium, iridium, platinum, mercury, thallium and lead, and
wherein at most 50 area-% of the CED-coated substrate surface are
rinsed with water prior to thermal curing.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b><u style="single">Field of the Invention</u></b></heading><p num="0001">The invention relates to a process for the production of coating
layers on electrically conductive substrates by cathodic electrodeposition
(CED) coating.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Background of the Invention</u></b></heading><p num="0002">CED coating is a well-known process for coating electrically
conductive, in particular, metallic substrates, in particular, for the
production of corrosion-protective primer layers on metallic substrates,
such as, for example, automotive bodies.</p><p num="0003">In CED coating, the substrates are coated in a conventional CED
coating bath (CED coating composition, CED coating agent, CED coating
paint), and excess, inadequately adhering CED coating composition is
then rinsed from the substrates back into the CED coating tank. To avoid
an increase in the volume of the CED coating bath, the substrates are
conventionally rinsed with ultrafiltrate obtained from the CED coating bath.</p><p num="0004">The ultrafiltrate is obtained by known methods and, in addition to
water, contains, for example, low molecular constituents, neutralizing
agents, solvents and dissolved salts from the CED coating bath.</p><p num="0005">Finally, the substrates can be rinsed with water.</p><p num="0006">After rinsing, the CED coating layers are thermally cured (cross-linked)
by baking in large, directly or indirectly heated circulating air ovens.
Directly heated circulating air ovens are heated by combustion of, for
example, natural gas, the combustion waste gases entering the circulating
air of the oven. In circulating air ovens indirectly heated by means of heat
exchangers, no combustion waste gases enter the circulating air of the
oven.</p><p num="0007">It has been observed in industrial practice that the adhesion of
subsequent coating layers, in particular underbody sealant layers, applied 
onto baked CED coating layers is often inadequate if the CED precoating
has been baked in indirectly heated circulating air ovens.</p><p num="0008">WO 01/40550 solves the problem of inadequate adhesion of
subsequent coating layers by a process for the production of an
electrodeposition coating layer with improved adhesion towards
subsequent coating layers by electrodeposition of a coating layer of an
electrodeposition coating composition onto an electrically conductive
substrate and baking, wherein the electrodeposition coating composition
used contains one or more water-insoluble organic nitrites and/or nitrates
and baking proceeds in an indirectly heated circulating air oven.</p><p num="0009">Metal compounds, for example, specific metal salts, are used in
CED coating compositions, in particular, as cross-linking catalysts and/or
anti-corrosion additives. In particular, lead compounds, such as lead
silicate, often also in combination with tin compounds, such as dibutyl tin
oxide, have been used. More recently, lead-free CED coating
compositions have become known. CED coating compositions containing
bismuth compounds have acquired particular significance, as described,
for example, in US 5,936,013, US 5,554,700, US 5,908,912, US
6,174,422, US 5,670,441, WO 96/10057, US 5,972,189, WO 00/50522,
US 6,265,079, EP 1 041 125, WO 00/47642, WO 01/51570, US 5,702,581
and US 5,330,839.</p><p num="0010">Surprisingly, the solution to the problem disclosed in WO 01/40550
can equally well be achieved if, instead of the water-insoluble organic
nitrites and/or nitrates disclosed therein, certain water-soluble metal
nitrates are used as an additive in CED coating compositions and if a
minimum proportion of the area of the substrate surface coated with a
CED coating layer from the CED coating compositions is not rinsed with
water prior to thermal curing.</p><p num="0011">Nitrate in anionic form cannot be deposited on the cathode; it is in
particular also consequently surprising that the same effect as described
in WO 01/40550 can be achieved.</p><p num="0012">Advantages are achieved not only in terms of the simpler handling
of water-soluble metal nitrates in comparison with the handling of the
water-insoluble organic nitrites and/or nitrates, but also in that a metal
required as a formulation constituent can also be introduced into the CED 
coating composition by means of a single chemical compound, namely, a
metal nitrate.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u></b></heading><p num="0013">The present invention provides a process for the production of a
CED coating with improved adhesion towards subsequent layers by
cathodic electrodeposition of a coating layer of a CED coating composition
onto an electrically conductive substrate and thermal curing by baking in
an indirectly heated circulating air oven operated with a proportion of fresh
air in the circulating air of the oven of 0 to 20 vol.%, wherein the CED
coating composition used contains at least one water-soluble metal nitrate
corresponding to a quantity of 1 to 10 mmol of nitrate per 100 g of resin
solids content, wherein the metal is selected from metals having atomic
numbers 20 to 83, with the exception of chromium, arsenic, rubidium,
ruthenium, rhodium, palladium, cadmium, antimony, caesium, osmium,
iridium, platinum, mercury, thallium and lead, and wherein at most 50
area-% of the CED-coated substrate surface is rinsed with water prior to
thermal curing.</p><p num="0014">The present invention also provides a process in which a
subsequent layer, in particular a conventional underbody sealant layer, is
applied onto the thermally cured CED coating layer produced according to
the invention.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Detailed Description of the Embodiments</u></b></heading><p num="0015">The CED coating compositions according to the invention comprise
known aqueous cathodically depositable electrodeposition coating agents.
The CED coating compositions are aqueous coating compositions with a
solids content of, for example, 10 to 30 wt.%. The solids content, in
addition to the metal nitrate(s), consists of the resin solids content,
optionally present pigments and/or fillers and further non-volatile additives.
The resin solids are composed of conventional self- or externally cross-linking
CED binder(s) having cationic substituents or substituents which
can be converted to cationic groups; optionally, present are cross-linking
agent(s) and optionally, present are other resin(s) contained in the CED
coating agent, such as, paste resin(s). The cationic groups may be
cationic groups or basic groups which can be converted to cationic groups, 
e.g., amino, ammonium, quaternary ammonium, phosphonium and/or
sulfonium groups. Binders having basic groups are preferred. Nitrogen-containing
basic groups, such as, amino groups are particularly preferred.
These groups may be present in the quaternized form or they are
converted to cationic groups with a conventional neutralizing agent, such
as, amidosulfuric acid or methanesulfonic acid, lactic acid, formic acid,
acetic acid.</p><p num="0016">The cationic or basic binders may be resins containing, for
example, primary, secondary and/or tertiary amino groups, the amine
values of which are, e.g., 20 to 250 mg KOH/g. The weight-average
molecular mass (Mw) of the CED binders is preferably 300 to 10,000.
There are no restrictions on the CED binders that can be used. The
various CED binders or CED binder/cross-linking agent combinations
known, for example, from the extensive patent literature may be used.
Examples of such CED binders include amino(meth)acrylate resins, amino
epoxy resins, amino epoxy resins with terminal double bonds, amino
epoxy resins with primary OH groups, amino polyurethane resins, amino
group-containing polybutadiene resins or modified epoxy resin/carbon
dioxide/amine reaction products. As self-crosslinking or externally cross-linking
binders, these CED binders have functional groups capable of
crosslinking, in particular hydroxyl groups, for example, corresponding to a
hydroxyl number of 30 to 300 mg KOH/g, preferably 50 to 250 mg KOH/g.</p><p num="0017">These binders may be self-crosslinking or they may be used in
combination with cross-linking agents known to the skilled person.
Examples of such cross-linking agents include aminoplast resins, blocked
polyisocyanates, cross-linking agents with terminal double bonds,
polyepoxide compounds, cross-linking agents with cyclic carbonate groups
or cross-linking agents that contain groups capable of transesterification
and/or transamidization. Preferred systems are those which self-crosslink
or externally crosslink by reaction of groups comprising active hydrogen
with blocked isocyanate groups, in particular those which crosslink by
reaction of hydroxyl and/or primary and/or secondary amino groups with
blocked isocyanate groups to form urethane and/or urea groups.</p><p num="0018">The CED binders may be converted to CED binder dispersions and
used as such for the preparation of CED coating agents. The preparation
of CED binder dispersions is known to the skilled person. For example,
CED binder dispersions may be prepared by converting CED binders to an 
aqueous dispersion by neutralization with acid and dilution with water.
The CED binders may also be present in mixture with cross-linking agents
and converted together with these to an aqueous CED binder dispersion.
If present, organic solvent(s) may be removed to the desired content
before or after conversion to the aqueous dispersion, for example, by
vacuum distillation.</p><p num="0019">The CED coating compositions used according to the invention
contain at least one metal nitrate amounting to a proportion of 1 to 10
mmol, preferably 2 to 6 mmol, of nitrate per 100 g of resin solids content of
the CED coating composition.</p><p num="0020">The metal nitrates are selected from among the water-soluble
nitrates of metals from the group consisting of metals of atomic numbers
20 to 83, wherein chromium, arsenic, rubidium, ruthenium, rhodium,
palladium, cadmium, antimony, caesium, osmium, iridium, platinum,
mercury, thallium and lead are excepted. The term "metal nitrate" used in
the present description and in the claims should not be understood
exclusively to denote a simple metal nitrate salt comprising metal cations
and nitrate anions, but also includes compounds such as, for example,
metal oxynitrates or nitrate compounds with counter-cations containing the
relevant metal. Preferred nitrates are those of titanium, vanadium, iron,
zinc, yttrium, zirconium, tin, cerium, neodymium or bismuth, in particular of
yttrium, neodymium or bismuth, especially of bismuth. Examples of
bismuth nitrates are Bi(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> and Bi<sub>5</sub>O(OH)<sub>9</sub>(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>.</p><p num="0021">As described in greater detail below, the metal nitrates may be
added to the CED coating compositions in various manners, for example,
from the outset during production of the CED coating compositions or
subsequently, for example, immediately before or during use for cathodic
electrodeposition coating.</p><p num="0022">It may be expedient if, in addition to the metal nitrate(s), the CED
coating compositions also contain one or more further metal compounds
other than the metal nitrate(s), for example, as additives serving to
catalyse cross-linking and/or to provide corrosion protection. In such
metal compounds, the metals are present in an oxidation number of +2 or
above and not as a constituent of anions. The further metal compounds
other than the metal nitrates are preferably not lead compounds or
compounds of other toxic metals such as, for example, chromium,
arsenic, cadmium, antimony, mercury or thallium. </p><p num="0023">In the event that the CED coating compositions contain one or more
further metal compounds other than the metal nitrate(s), they may
comprise compounds of the same metal(s) present in the metal nitrate(s)
or compounds of metals differing there-from. Preferred examples are
compounds of vanadium, iron, zinc, yttrium, zirconium, tin, cerium,
neodymium or bismuth, in particular of yttrium, neodymium or bismuth,
especially of bismuth.</p><p num="0024">In particular, the further metal compounds other than the metal
nitrate(s) may, for example, comprise corresponding metal complex
compounds, for example, metal chelate complexes or preferably
corresponding metal salts of an inorganic or organic acid, wherein the
term "metal salt" includes not only salts consisting of appropriate doubly or
multiply positively charged metal cations and acid anions, but also, for
example, salts consisting of cations containing the metal and acid anions,
and metalloxy salts. Examples of inorganic or organic acids from which
the metal salts can be derived are inorganic or organic sulphonic acids,
carboxylic acids, for example, formic acid or acetic acid, amino carboxylic
acids and hydroxy carboxylic acids, such as lactic acid or
dimethylolpropionic acid.</p><p num="0025">Preferred metal compounds are acetic acid salts, formic acid salts
and hydrocarbyl sulphonic acid salts, such as alkylsulphonic acid salts of
yttrium or neodymium and, in particular, acetic acid salts, methoxy acetic
acid salts, aminocarboxylic acid salts or especially hydroxycarboxylic acid
salts and sulphonic acid salts of bismuth. Preferred examples of the last
bismuth salts are aliphatic hydroxycarboxylic acid salts of bismuth, such
as lactic acid salts or dimethylolpropionic acid salts of bismuth, for
example, bismuth lactate or bismuth dimethylolpropionate; amidosulphonic
acid salts of bismuth; hydrocarbylsulphonic acid salts of bismuth, in
particular alkyl sulphonic acid salts, especially methane sulphonic acid
salts of bismuth, for example, bismuth methane sulphonate.</p><p num="0026">The total metal content arising from the contributions from metal
nitrate and further metal compounds other than metal nitrate amounts, for
example, to 0.1 to 2 wt.%, wherein the sum of the contributions calculated
as metal is in each case relative to the resin solids content of the CED
coating composition.</p><p num="0027">In addition to the binder(s), optionally present cross-linking
agent(s), the metal nitrate(s) and water, the CED coating agents may also 
contain pigments, fillers, organic solvents and/or conventional coating
additives.</p><p num="0028">Examples of pigments and fillers include the conventional inorganic
and/or organic colored pigments and/or special-effect pigments and/or
fillers such as, e.g., titanium dioxide, iron oxide pigments, carbon black,
phthalocyanine pigments, quinacridone pigments, metallic pigments,
interference pigments, kaolin, talc, silica. The pigment plus filler/resin
solids weight ratio of the CED coating agents is, for example, from 0 : 1 to
0.8 : 1, and for pigmented coating agents it is preferably from 0.05 : 1 to
0.4 : 1.</p><p num="0029">Examples of organic solvents which may be used in the ready-to-apply
CED coating bath in amounts of, for example, up to 5 wt.% include
polar aprotic water-miscible solvents such as, N-methylpyrrolidone,
dimethyl sulfoxide, dimethyl formamide, sulfolane; alcohols, such as,
cyclohexanol, 2-ethylhexanol, butanol; glycol ethers, such as,
methoxypropanol, ethoxypropanol, butoxyethanol, diethylene glycol diethyl
ether; ketones, such as, methyl isobutyl ketone, methyl ethyl ketone,
cyclohexanone; hydrocarbons.</p><p num="0030">Examples of conventional coating additives which may be used in
the CED coating agents in amounts of, for example, up to 5 wt.%, based
on the resin solids, include wetting agents, neutralizing agents, anti-crater
agents, leveling agents, antifoaming agents, light stabilizers and
antioxidants.</p><p num="0031">The CED coating compositions may be prepared in accordance
with known processes for the production of CED coating baths, i.e. in
principle both by means of the single-component method and by means of
the two-component method.</p><p num="0032">The CED coating compositions may, for example, be produced in
such a manner that the metal nitrate(s) is (are) mixed as such or as an
aqueous solution with the other constituents of the CED coating
compositions. The metal nitrate(s) may here be added to the CED coating
compositions in various manners, for example, from the outset during
production of the CED coating compositions or subsequently.</p><p num="0033">When producing the CED coating compositions by the single-component
method it is, for example, possible to proceed by dispersing
pigments and/or extenders in a proportion of the binder and/or cross-linking 
agent and then performing grinding in a suitable unit, for example,
a bead mill, whereupon final formulation proceeds by mixing with the
outstanding proportion of binder and/or cross-linking agent. The material
obtained in this manner may then (unless already performed, after addition
of neutralizing agent) be converted into the virtually ready CED coating
composition by dilution with water, to which metal nitrate is yet to be
added, in particular in the form of an aqueous solution.</p><p num="0034">When producing the CED coating compositions by the two-component
method it is, for example, also possible to proceed by
converting the cationic binders present in non-aqueous phase into the
aqueous phase by dilution with water. Metal nitrate, in particular in the
form of an aqueous solution, may then be added to the aqueous phase.
The CED binder dispersion obtained in this manner may then be
converted into a pigmented CED coating composition by mixing with a
separate pigment paste. Alternatively, when using the two-component
method, it is also possible to proceed by adding an aqueous pigment
paste containing metal nitrate to a CED binder dispersion.</p><p num="0035">The metal nitrate(s) may also be added to the CED coating
compositions separately, in particular in the form of an aqueous solution.
It is, for example, also possible to carry out the separate addition
subsequently to ready-to-apply CED coating baths.</p><p num="0036">According to the invention, CED coating layers are produced, for
example to a dry film thickness of 10 to 30 µm, on electrically conductive,
in particular, metallic substrates such as, for example, automotive bodies,
from the CED coating compositions containing the metal nitrate(s).</p><p num="0037">After cathodic electrodeposition, the CED-coated substrate surface
is rinsed generally at least in the area visible to the observer with
ultrafiltrate obtained from the CED coating bath in a conventional manner
known to the person skilled in the art in order to remove excess, not firmly
adhering CED coating composition. This may proceed in the conventional
manner by the dip and/or spray rinsing process, wherein the removed
CED coating composition is returned to the CED coating tank in the
conventional manner. Rinsing may then be performed with water,
wherein, however, only at most 50 area-% of the CED-coated surface may
be rinsed with water. Rinsing with water may here proceed on the CED-coated
surface which has already been rinsed with ultrafiltrate and/or has
not been rinsed. Complying with the limitation of rinsing with water to at 
most 50 area-% of the CED-coated surface is no problem in particular with
three-dimensional substrates of a complicated geometry, such as, for
example, automotive bodies, since internal surfaces, such as, for example,
of cavities or surfaces located on the underside of the substrate, for
example, of the automotive underbody, are not reached by the water used
to spray down (shower down) the surfaces visible to the observer. In the
case of automotive bodies, a sufficiently large proportion of the area can
be excluded from rinsing with water simply on this basis.</p><p num="0038">After rinsing, the CED coating layer is thermally cross-linked by
baking in indirectly heated circulating air ovens at object temperatures of,
for example, 150 to 190°C. The phrase "indirectly heated circulating air
ovens" means those circulating air ovens in which no combustion waste
gases enter the circulating air of the oven and which are operated with no
or only a small proportion of fresh air, as is the case for indirectly heated
circulating air ovens operated in industrial practice. The proportion by
volume of fresh air, relative to the circulated volume of air per unit time, is
0 to 20%, preferably no more than 10%. In the process according to the
invention, there preferably prevails during baking, a ratio of oven volume
to CED coating area to be baked of up to 2, for example of 0.2 to 2 cubic
meters per square meter. The dimensions can be clarified by an example
from automotive OEM coating: for example in an industrially operated
circulating air oven with a volume of 1000 cubic meters, there are
simultaneously present 25 vehicle bodies each comprising 80 square
meters of CED coating layer to be baked, the circulating air throughput is
150,000 cubic meters per hour at a throughput of exhaust and fresh air of
12,000 cubic meters per hour in each case. In order to simulate the
baking process in an industrially operated, indirectly heated circulating air
oven, it is possible to use a laboratory circulating air oven, the fresh air
proportion of which can be limited to up to 20%, preferably to below 10%
and in which a ratio of 0.2 to 2 cubic meters of oven volume per square
meter of CED coating layer to be baked is preferably maintained.</p><p num="0039">The process according to the invention is in particular suitable for
the automotive sector, for example, for the production of a corrosion-protective
CED primer layer on automotive bodies or body parts, which are
then provided with further coating layers, in particular for example
underbody sealant layers. </p><p num="0040">The underbody sealant layers conventional in automotive coating
can be applied. These are, for example, coating compositions based on
polyvinyl chloride (PVC) plastisols. These are in particular applied onto
the areas of automotive underbodies which are at risk of stone impact.
Thick layers, for example of 0.5 to 3 mm, are generally applied.</p><p num="0041">Without providing a binding explanation, the theoretical assumption
is that, at the air temperatures prevailing during baking of, for example,
180 to 220°C, any nitrate remaining on areas of the surface which have
not been rinsed or have been rinsed only with ultrafiltrate but not with
water decomposes to eliminate nitrogen oxides, hereinafter designated
NO<sub>x</sub>, and the NO<sub>x</sub> released into the circulating air of the oven brings about
improved or adequate adhesion of subsequently applied coating layers.</p><p num="0042">The process according to the invention ensures good adhesion of
subsequent coating layers, such as in particular underbody sealant layers,
applied onto CED coating layers baked in indirectly heated circulating air
ovens.</p><p num="0043">The following examples illustrate the invention. All parts and
percentages are on a weight basis unless otherwise indicated.</p><heading><b><u style="single">EXAMPLES</u></b></heading><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u> (Production of bismuth lactate):</heading><p num="0044">901 parts by weight of 70 % by weight aqueous lactic acid were
introduced and heated to 70°C. 466 parts bismuth oxide (Bi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) were
added batchwise while stirring. After stirring for an additional 6 hours at
70°C the mixture was cooled to about 20°C and left for 12 hours without
stirring. Finally, the precipitate was filtered off, washed with a little water
and ethanol and dried at a temperature of 40 to 60°C.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u> (Preparation of a CED dispersion)</heading><p num="0045"><sl><li>a) 832 parts of the monocarbonate of an epoxy resin based on
bisphenol A (commercial product Epikote® 828) were mixed with 830
parts of a commercial polycaprolactone polyol (commercial product CAPA
205) and 712 parts of diglycol dimethylether and reacted at 70°C to 140°C
with 0.3% BF<sub>3</sub>-etherate as catalyst until an epoxy value of 0 was obtained.
In the presence of 0.3% Zn acetyl acetonate as catalyst, 307 parts of a 
reaction product of 174 parts of toluene diisocyanate and 137 parts of
2-ethyl hexanol were added to this product at 40°C to 80°C with the
addition of 0.3% benzyl trimethylammonium hydroxide. The reaction was
continued until an NCO (isocyanate) value of about 0 was obtained and
the mixture then adjusted to a solids content of 70 wt.% with diglycol
dimethyl ether.</li><li>b) 618 parts of a reaction product of 348 parts of toluene
diisocyanate and 274 parts of 2-ethyl hexanol were added slowly to 1759
parts of a biscarbonate of an epoxy resin based on bisphenol A
(commercial product Epikote® 1001) at 60°C to 80°C with the addition of
0.3% benzyl trimethylammonium hydroxide. The reaction was continued
to an NCO value of about 0.</li><li>c) At a temperature of 20°C to 40°C, 622 parts of the reaction
product of 137 parts of 2-ethylhexanol with 174 parts of toluene
diisocyanate with benzyltrimethylammonium hydroxide catalysis (0.3%)
were added to 860 parts of bishexamethylene triamine dissolved in 2315
parts of methoxy propanol and the reaction was continued until an NCO
content of about 0 was obtained. Then 4737 parts of the reaction product
b) and 3246 parts of the reaction product a) (in each case 70% in diglycol
dimethyl ether) were added and reacted at 60°C to 90°C. The reaction
was ended at an amine value of about 32 mg KOH/g. The product
obtained was distilled under vacuum to a solids content of about 85%.</li><li>d1) Neutralization was carried out with 30 mmole of formic acid/100
g of resin. The mixture was then heated to 70°C and bismuth lactate (from
Example 1) was added in portions, with stirring, over a period of two
hours, in an amount such that 0.7 wt.% of bismuth, based on resin solids
content, were present in the mix. Stirring was then continued for another 6
hours at 60°C. After cooling, the mixture was converted with deionized
water to a dispersion with a solids content of 40 wt.%.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u> (production of a pigment paste)</heading><p num="0046">15 parts of acetic acid (50%), 30 parts of a conventional
commercial wetting agent (50%), 100 parts of a 5 wt.% aqueous solution
of Bi(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> and 250 parts of deionized water were added in a stirrer
running at high speed to 223 parts of the paste resin according to EP-A-0
469 497 A1, Example 1 (55 wt.%). 12.3 parts of carbon black and 430 
parts of titanium dioxide were added thereto. A solids content of 53 wt.%
was established with deionized water and the mixture was ground in a
bead mill. A stable pigment paste was obtained.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 4</u> (production of a pigment paste)</heading><p num="0047">Example 3 was repeated, but, instead of the 100 parts of the
aqueous solution of Bi(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>, 100 parts of an aqueous solution of bismuth
lactate with the same bismuth content were used.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 5a</u> (production of a CED coating, according to the invention)</heading><p num="0048">A CED coating bath with a solids content of 20 wt.% and a
pigment/binder ratio by weight of 0.5:1 was produced in the conventional
manner by mixing the CED dispersion from Example 2, deionized water
and adding the pigment paste from Example 3 with thorough stirring. The
CED coating bath contained 1 wt.% of bismuth, relative to resin solids
content, and 4.3 mmol of nitrate per 100 g of resin solids content.</p><p num="0049">Once the CED coating bath had been adjusted with formic acid to
an acid content of 35 milliequivalents/100 g of solids content, 10 panels
(10 cm x 20 cm in size) of conventional, phosphated bodywork steel were
each coated therewith to a dry film thickness of 20 µm by cathodic
electrodeposition, the panels were rinsed on both sides with ultrafiltrate
obtained from the CED coating bath in order to remove excess, not firmly
adhering CED coating bath material and were baked for 30 minutes at
160°C (object temperature) in an electrically heated laboratory circulating
air oven with a volume of 0.5 cubic meters (air temperature 220°C, fresh
air proportion limited to less than 8%).</p><heading><u style="single">Example 5b</u> (production of a CED coating, according to the invention)</heading><p num="0050">Example 5a was repeated, with the exception that one side of the
sheet was additionally rinsed with water before baking.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 5c</u> (production of a CED coating, comparison)</heading><p num="0051">Example 5a was repeated, with the exception that both sides were
additionally rinsed with water before baking. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 6</u> (production of a CED coating, comparison)</heading><p num="0052">Example 5a was repeated, with the exception that the pigment
paste from Example 4 was used instead of the pigment paste from
Example 3. The CED coating bath contained 1 wt.% bismuth, relative to
resin solids content.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 7</u> (production of a CED coating, comparison)</heading><p num="0053">Example 5a was repeated, with the exception that the laboratory
circulating air oven was operated with the fresh air supply at maximum.</p><p num="0054">The CED-coated sheets obtained in Examples 5-7 were knife
coated with a conventional commercial, PVC plastisol-based underbody
sealant to a film thickness of 2 mm and baked for 20 minutes at 140°C
(object temperature) in order to gel the plastisol. Parallel scores at a
spacing of 1.5 cm were made in the gelled plastisol layer. Using a knife,
the gelled plastisol was carefully detached from the CED coating layer at
the edge between two scores in order to create a tab to grip. The attempt
was then made to pull the plastisol layer off manually. Adhesion was
adequate only in Examples 5a and 5b, both according to the invention. In
Comparative Examples 5c (100 area-% of the CED-coating layer rinsed
with water prior to thermal curing), 6 (CED coating bath containing no
nitrate) and 7 (huge proportion of fresh air in the circulating air of the
oven), the gelled plastisol layer could be pulled off the CED-coated
substrate.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process for the production of a CED (cathodic electrodeposition)
coating with improved adhesion towards subsequent layers comprising the
steps of
<claim-text><claim-text>a) cathodic electrodepositing a coating layer of a CED coating
composition onto an electrically conductive substrate and</claim-text><claim-text>b) thermal curing by baking in an indirectly heated circulating
air oven operated with a proportion of fresh air in the circulating air of
the oven of 0 to 20 vol.%,</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein the CED coating composition used contains at least one water-soluble
metal nitrate corresponding to a quantity of 1 to 10 mmol of nitrate
per 100 g of resin solids content, wherein the metal is selected from the
group consisting of metals of atomic numbers 20 to 83, with the exception
of chromium, arsenic, rubidium, ruthenium, rhodium, palladium, cadmium,
antimony, caesium, osmium, iridium, platinum, mercury, thallium and lead,
and wherein at most 50 area-% of the CED-coated substrate surface are
rinsed with water prior to thermal curing.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, wherein the metal nitrate is present in a
proportion of 2 to 6 mmol of nitrate per 100 g of resin solids content of the
CED coating composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The process of claim 1 or 2, wherein the at least one metal nitrate is
selected from the group consisting of the nitrates of titanium, vanadium,
iron, zinc, yttrium, zirconium, tin, cerium, neodymium and bismuth.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The process of any one of the preceding claims, wherein, in
addition to the at least one metal nitrate, the CED coating compositions
contain at least one further metal compound other than the at least one
metal nitrate, wherein the metals are present in these metal compounds
with an oxidation number of +2 or above and not as a constituent of
anions.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The process of claim 4, wherein the at least one further metal
compound comprises a compound selected from the group consisting of
compounds of vanadium, iron, zinc, yttrium, zirconium, tin, cerium,
neodymium or bismuth.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The process of claim 4 or 5, wherein the total metal content arising
from the contributions from metal nitrate and the at least one further metal
compound amounts to 0.1 to 2 wt.% and wherein the sum of the
contributions calculated as metal is in each case relative to the resin solids
content of the CED coating composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The process of any one of the preceding claims, wherein the
substrates comprise automotive bodies or automotive body parts.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The process of any one of the preceding claims, wherein the CED-coated
substrate surface is rinsed at least in the area visible to the
observer with ultrafiltrate obtained from the CED coating bath.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The process of claim 8, wherein, after rinsing with ultrafiltrate,
rinsing is performed with water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The process of any one of the preceding claims, wherein at least
one further coating layer is applied onto the baked CED coating layer.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>