<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="US-20060231476-A1" country="US" doc-number="20060231476" kind="A1" lang="EN" date="20061019" family-id="37107476" date-produced="20090604" status="new"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="76911646" ucid="US-20060231476-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>US</country><doc-number>20060231476</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20061019</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-16316005-A" us-series-code="11" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>16316005</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20051007</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-16316005-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>16316005</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20051007</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-72677903-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>72677903</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031203</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   1/28        20060101AFI20061019BHUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   1/28        20060101CFI20061019BHUS        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-national country="US" status="new"><main-classification>210266</main-classification><further-classification>210282</further-classification></classification-national><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C02F   1/00D4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M02F1:28D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M02F1:32</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M02F1:42</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M02F201:00P</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M02F201:326</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="EN" load-source="us" status="new">PORTABLE, REFILLABLE WATER DISPENSER SERVING BATCHES OF WATER PURIFIED OF ORGANIC AND INORGANIC POLLUTANTS</invention-title></technical-data><related-documents status="new"><relation type="continuation"><child-doc ucid="US-16316005"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>US</country><doc-number>16316005</doc-number><date>20051007</date></document-id></child-doc><parent-doc ucid="US-72677903" psta="unknown"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>US</country><doc-number>72677903</doc-number><date>20031203</date></document-id></parent-doc></relation></related-documents><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>HEADWATERS R &amp; D INC</name><address><country>CA</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>HEADWATERS R &amp; D, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>ANDERSON TROY C</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>HAMILTON JEREMY</name><address><country>CA</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>LANNING CHARLES R</name><address><country>CA</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>VANDENBELT RUDY A</name><address><country>CA</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>ANDERSON TROY C.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>HAMILTON JEREMY</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>LANNING CHARLES R.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>VANDENBELT RUDY A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Anderson</last-name> <first-name>Troy</first-name><address><city>Marblehead</city><state>MA</state><country>US</country></address> </addressbook> </inventor> <inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Hamilton</last-name><first-name>Jeremy</first-name><address><city>Celemis</city><country>CA</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Lanning</last-name><first-name>Charles</first-name><address><city>Ottawa</city><country>CA</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Vandenbelt</last-name><first-name>Rudy</first-name><address><address-1>308 Billings Ave.</address-1><city>Ottawa</city><postcode>K1H 5L3</postcode><country>CA</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><correspondence-address sequence="1" format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Law Office of A.P. Durigon</last-name><address><address-1>20 Eustis Street</address-1><city>Cambridge</city><state>MA</state><postcode>02140</postcode><country>US</country></address></addressbook></correspondence-address></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" load-source="us" status="new"><p num="p-0001">A portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants includes a portable, refillable and hand-holdable vessel for holding and pouring water having a spout and, inside the portable, refillable and hand-holdable vessel, moving water and still water processing module cooperative to remove inorganic and organic pollutants from water received batchwise by the vessel. </p></abstract><description lang="EN" load-source="us" status="new"><?cross-reference-to-related-applications description="Cross Reference To Related Applications" end="lead"?><heading>CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS </heading><p num="p-0002"> This application is a continuation application of U.S. Non-provisional application Ser. No. 10/726,779, filed Dec. 3, 2003, of the same inventive entity as herein, incorporated herein by reference.</p><?cross-reference-to-related-applications description="Cross Reference To Related Applications" end="tail"?><?summary-of-invention description="Summary of Invention" end="lead"?><heading>FIELD OF THE INVENTION </heading><p num="p-0003"> This invention is drawn to the field of water purification, more particularly, to point of use water purifiers, and more particularly, to a novel portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants. </p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION </heading><p num="p-0004"> Systems that treat water for regional consumption such as municipal waterworks and systems that treat water for point of use consumption are the two basic types of systems by which water may be treated to remove impurities. The municipal systems, of course, afford no purification of other than “city” water, such as well water, and organic and inorganic impurities often remain in “city” water notwithstanding filtration, UV treatment, ozone treatment or treatment by any of the other water purification techniques well-known to those of skill in the art. The point of use systems for their part may be locally installed or portable. However, point of use systems installed into existing plumbing are typically line-powered, requiring line voltage and current for the treatment of water, and often involve an expense beyond the budget of many consumers for equipment acquisition, installation services and periodic maintenance. The portable point of use systems on the other hand are often cumbersome, suitcase-sized units that are difficult to use, involving multiple manual treatment steps, or do not remove both inorganic and organic impurities, and sometimes are no less expensive to acquire and maintain than their installed counterparts. </p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION </heading><p num="p-0005"> It accordingly is the general object of the present invention to provide a novel point of use water purifier, and more particularly, to provide a portable, refillable water dispenser that itself serves batches of water purified of both organic and inorganic pollutants. As used herein, the term “organic” in the phrase “organic pollutants” refers to “living organisms” such as bacteria, and the term “inorganic” in the phrase “inorganic pollutants” refers to “non-living, organic (carbon) or inorganic compounds.”</p><p num="p-0006"> In general terms, the present invention contemplates a portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants that includes a portable, refillable and hand-holdable vessel for holding and pouring water having a spout and, inside the portable, refillable and hand-holdable vessel, moving water and still water processing modules cooperative to remove inorganic and organic pollutants from water received batchwise by said vessel. The module processing moving water disposed inside the vessel is adapted to receive water to be processed batchwise, and is further adapted to cause the water to be processed received batchwise to move through a flow-through filter to remove inorganic impurities and then out of said module. The module processing still water disposed inside the vessel is adapted to receive the water that flows out said module processing moving water and to contain it batchwise as a body of still water in fluid communication with said spout of said vessel, and is further adapted to provide UV radiation that is omnipresent to every region of each said body of still water contained batchwise therein with an intensity and a duration to neutralize organic impurities at every region of said body of still water contained batchwise therein. In this manner, water from which inorganic impurities have been removed and in which organic impurities have been neutralized may be dispensed through said spout of said portable, refillable and hand-holdable vessel. </p><p num="p-0007"> Preferably, the portable, refillable and hand-holdable vessel includes a pitcher with an open mouth and side and bottom walls that provide a basin for containing and pouring still water, a handle to one side of the pitcher, and a lid removably mounted to said open mouth of said pitcher. The module processing moving water preferably includes a bucket mounted inside said pitcher with its mouth in fluid communication with said mouth of said pitcher having an ion exchange and activated carbon flow-through filter bed that is fed by gravity action with water to be processed that is poured batchwise into said bucket all at once. The module processing still water preferably includes a single UV line radiator upstanding in, and centrally disposed within, said basin of said pitcher and a battery-powered controller carried by the pitcher that includes a control panel and user interface, preferably located on its handle, operatively coupled to the single UV line radiator. </p><p num="p-0008"> Preferably, the removable lid includes a fill opening, and a louvered disc valve cooperative therewith to allow water to be poured through the fill opening batchwise into the bucket of the moving water processing module while blocking direct viewing of the UV line radiator. </p><p num="p-0009"> Operation of the presently preferred portable, refillable and hand-holdable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants is elegantly straightforward. All that is needed is to pour water to be processed batchwise into the bucket of the moving water processing module either directly, when the lid is removed, or through the fill opening, when the lid is attached to the pitcher, and to start the processing sequence by actuation of the control panel and user interface. The controller of the still water processing module waits for a first time to allow the water to be processed that has been poured batchwise into the bucket to move through the moving water processing module flow-through filter to remove inorganic impurities therefrom, then actuates the UV line radiator for a second time to neutralize organic impurities in the body of still water contained batchwise in the basin of the still water processing module, after which time it provides an indication at the control panel that a batch of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants is ready to be dispensed through the spout of the pitcher. </p><?summary-of-invention description="Summary of Invention" end="tail"?><?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS </heading><p num="p-0010"> These and other objects, inventive aspects and advantageous features of the present invention will become apparent as the invention becomes better understood by referring to the following, solely exemplary, detailed description of the presently preferred embodiments thereof, and to the drawings, wherein: </p><p num="p-0011"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of a portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic impurities in accord with the present invention; </p><p num="p-0012"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a longitudinal sectional view through the midsection thereof; </p><p num="p-0013"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a longitudinal sectional view through the midsection of the removable lid of the portable, refillable water dispenser of <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>; </p><p num="p-0014"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a bottom plan view of the removable lid; and </p><p num="p-0015"><figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a block circuit diagram of the portable, refillable and hand-holdable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic impurities in accord with the present invention.</p><?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?><?detailed-description description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PRESENTLY PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS </heading><p num="p-0016"> Referring now to <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, generally designated at <b>10</b> is a portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic impurities in accord with the present invention. The portable, refillable water dispenser <b>10</b> includes a portable, refillable and hand-holdable pitcher <b>12</b> for containing, receiving and pouring water having a handle <b>14</b> to one side thereof, a pour spout <b>16</b> and a removable lid <b>18</b>. Any portable, refillable water dispenser for receiving, containing and dispensing water such as a standalone, countertop water purifier, may be employed without departing from the inventive concepts. A control panel and user-interface <b>20</b> to be described is mounted on the handle <b>14</b>. A flip lid <b>22</b>, cooperative with the spout <b>16</b> of the pitcher <b>12</b>, and a fill opening generally designated <b>24</b> and cooperative louvered disc valve to be described having actuation handle <b>26</b>, are carried by the removable lid <b>18</b>. </p><p num="p-0017"> As best seen in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a bucket generally designated <b>28</b> is mounted inside the pitcher <b>12</b> having side and bottom walls <b>30</b>, <b>32</b> that bound a volume whose capacity, when filled, accepts water to be purified poured batchwise all at once thereinto. A flow-through filter generally designated <b>34</b> is removably mounted in an opening provided therefor in the bottom wall <b>32</b> of the bucket <b>28</b> that is fed with water to be processed received batchwise in the bucket <b>28</b> by action of gravity. Water to be processed received batchwise by the bucket <b>28</b> flows into inlet ports generally designated <b>36</b> of flow-through filter <b>34</b>, though ion exchange and activated carbon filter media, not shown, contained inside the walls of inner and outer cups <b>38</b>, <b>40</b> to remove inorganic impurities, and out outlet port generally designated <b>42</b> at the top and to the side of flow-through filter <b>34</b> away from the spout <b>16</b> of the pitcher <b>12</b>. Reference in this connection may be had to commonly assigned, co-pending United States utility patent application entitled “Filter Cartridge for a Standalone Point of Use Water Purification Device,” filed on even date herewith, incorporated herein by reference. Any suitable moving water processing module adapted to receive water to be processed batchwise and further adapted to cause the water be processed received batchwise to move through a flow-through filter to remove inorganic impurities may be employed without departing from the inventive concepts, </p><p num="h-0007"> and a flow-through filter having other than an ion exchange and activated carbon flow-through filter media such as activated carbon block media, ceramic media, or semipermeable membranes, may be employed. </p><p num="p-0018"> The pitcher <b>12</b> has side walls <b>44</b> and a contained bottom wall <b>46</b> that provide a basin in fluid communication with the spout <b>16</b> for receiving, holding and pouring water. The side walls <b>44</b> of the pitcher <b>12</b> are fashioned of a material that is transparent to ambient light and opaque to UV light, such as plastic. The capacity of the basin is at least as great as the capacity of the bucket <b>28</b>. </p><p num="p-0019"> A single UV line radiator generally designated <b>48</b> is upstanding in, and centrally positioned within, the basin of the pitcher <b>12</b>. The UV line radiator <b>48</b> includes a two hundred fifty-four (254) nm cold cathode fluorescent lamp (CCFL) <b>50</b> and protective, UV transparent quartz sheath <b>52</b> mounted in water-tight sealing relation to the bottom wall <b>46</b> of the pitcher <b>12</b>. The UV lamp <b>50</b> of the UV line radiator <b>48</b> is operatively connected to a controller to be described supplied by power from batteries <b>52</b> carried in an electronics pack generally designated <b>54</b> attached to the bottom wall <b>46</b> of the pitcher <b>12</b>. The electronics pack <b>54</b> is connected to the control panel and user interface <b>20</b> via cable <b>56</b> that is threaded through the handle <b>14</b> of the pitcher <b>12</b>. </p><p num="p-0020"> Water to be processed received batchwise by the bucket <b>28</b> of the moving water processing module is received in the basin of the pitcher <b>12</b> as it flows streamwise through the flow-through filter <b>34</b> thereof, which, after all the water of a batch has flowed therethrough, is contained batchwise as a body of still water in the basin of the pitcher <b>12</b> in fluid communication with the spout <b>16</b>. The body of still water contained batchwise in the basin completely submerges the UV line radiator <b>48</b>. The CCFL <b>50</b>, actuated by the controller in response to user control input to the control panel and user interface <b>20</b> in a manner to be described, provides UV radiation that is omnipresent to every region of the basin containing the body of still water received batchwise with an intensity and a duration to neutralize inorganic impurities at every region of the body of still water contained batchwise in the basin of the pitcher <b>12</b>. The controller thereafter provides a signal indication at the control panel and user-interface <b>20</b> that a batch of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants is ready for dispensation through spout <b>16</b>. Any still water processing module adapted to receive water from the moving water processing module and contain it batchwise as a body of still water other than the basin of the pitcher <b>12</b> and further adapted to provide UV radiation that is omnipresent to every region of the body of still water received batchwise with an intensity and a duration to neutralize inorganic impurities at every region of the body of still water contained batchwise other than the battery-powered, single UV line radiator upstanding in, and centrally disposed within, the basin of the pitcher may be employed without departing from the inventive concepts. </p><p num="p-0021"> Referring now to <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, generally designated at <b>60</b> is a longitudinal view through the midsection of the removable lid <b>18</b> of the portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants in accord with the present invention. The flip lid <b>22</b> is pivotally mounted on an axle <b>62</b> best seen in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The flip lid <b>22</b> covers the pour spout <b>16</b> of the pitcher <b>12</b> while allowing water contained in the basin thereof to be dispensed therethrough. The bucket <b>28</b> includes a front wall <b>56</b> that intercepts the line of sight from the pour spout <b>16</b> to prevent direct viewing of the UV line radiator <b>48</b> in the basin of the pitcher <b>12</b> as schematically illustrated by arrow <b>58</b> in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. A lid seat sensing switch <b>64</b>, such as a magnetic reed switch, is mounted to the removable lid <b>18</b> to disable the UV line radiator <b>48</b> in the basin of the pitcher <b>12</b> when the removable lid <b>18</b> is off of the pitcher <b>12</b>. </p><p num="p-0022"> A louvered disc valve generally designated <b>66</b> retained by cap <b>68</b> on rotary bearing <b>70</b> is mounted for rotation to the underside of the removable lid <b>18</b> adjacent the fill opening <b>24</b> thereof. The louvered disc valve <b>66</b> includes the actuation handle <b>26</b>, and as best seen in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a disc valve <b>72</b> and a louver generally designated <b>74</b>, whose opening generally designated <b>76</b> is provided with a series of slanted, radially spaced fins <b>78</b>. Water received through fill opening <b>24</b> of the removable lid <b>18</b> with the louvered disc valve <b>66</b> rotated to its fully opened position illustrated in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> by handle <b>26</b> flows through the louver opening <b>76</b> into the bucket <b>28</b> while the slanted fins <b>78</b> thereof block direct viewing of the UV line radiator <b>48</b> within the pitcher <b>12</b> as schematically illustrated by dashed arrow <b>80</b> in <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. As will be appreciated, the slanted fins <b>78</b> of the louvered disc valve <b>66</b> block direct viewing of the UV line radiator <b>48</b> inside the pitcher <b>12</b> when it is not in any of its non-fully-closed positions, not shown, which are not further described herein for the sake of brevity of exposition. Another mechanism that allows water to be processed to be received batchwise through the removable lid while blocking direct view of the UV radiator other than the louvered disc valve <b>66</b> may be employed without departing from the inventive concepts. </p><p num="p-0023"> Referring now to <figref idrefs="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, generally designated at <b>90</b> is a block circuit diagram of the portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants in accord with the present invention. Controller <b>92</b>, supplied with DC power from battery <b>94</b>, is operatively coupled to UV line radiator <b>96</b>. A lid seat sensor <b>98</b> is electrically connected to the controller <b>92</b>. A control panel and user interface <b>100</b> is electrically connected to the controller <b>92</b>. The controller <b>92</b> may be powered by AC line power or a combination of AC and rechargeable DC without departing from the inventive concepts. </p><p num="p-0024"> In operation, the controller <b>92</b> in response to sequence initiation input via the control panel and user interface <b>100</b> waits a first time to allow water to be processed received batchwise in the bucket to move through the moving water processing module and into the basin of the pitcher where it is contained as a body of still water. For an exemplary thirty-two (32) ounce capacity bucket, water received batchwise takes about takes about ten (10) minutes to drip through its flow-through filter. After the first time lapses, the controller <b>92</b> actuates the UV line radiator <b>96</b> to provide UV radiation that is omnipresent to every region of the body of still water contained in the basin of the still water processing module with an intensity and a second time duration to neutralize inorganic impurities at every region of the body of still water contained in the basin of the still water processing module. Different second time durations may be selected for “city” versus water from wells or other sources. For an exemplary thirty-two (32) ounce capacity basin, five (5) minutes of irradiation neutralizes organic impurities in “city” water and ten (10) minutes neutralizes organic impurities in well water. If at any time during the processing sequence (or at any other time) a signal is detected from the lid seat sensor <b>98</b>, the controller disables the UV line radiator <b>96</b> and resets its water treatment sequence. Otherwise, after the second time has elapsed, the controller <b>92</b> provides a signal indication at the control panel and user interface <b>100</b>, such as by illuminating a light or causing an audio signal to sound, that a batch of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants is ready to be served through the spout of the pitcher. The controller monitors the time since it was last actuated, and if a predetermined third time elapses, such as twenty-four (24) hours, since it was last actuated, it provides a signal indication at the control panel and user interface to retreat the batch of water. </p><p num="p-0025"> Many modifications of the presently disclosed invention will become apparent to those of skill in the art without departing from the inventive concepts. </p><?detailed-description description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?></description><claims lang="EN" load-source="us" status="new"><claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001"><claim-text><b>1</b>. A portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic impurities, comprising: 
<claim-text>a water pitcher having an open top, side and bottom walls enclosing a basin for holding still water, a spout in fluid communication with the basin for pouring water, and a removable lid mounted to the open top of the pitcher; </claim-text><claim-text>a moving water processing module including a bucket mounted inside the water pitcher having an open top in fluid communication with the open mouth of the pitcher and having side and bottom walls that enclose a volume whose capacity, when filled, accepts a batch of water to be treated that is poured all at once thereinto, a flow-through filter removably mounted to said bucket bottom wall that is fed with the water of each batch of water by action of gravity, said flow-through filter including filter media that acts to remove non-living organic (carbon) and inorganic impurities as said water flows therethrough and to streamwise discharge that water into said basin; and </claim-text><claim-text>a still water processing module including a UV line radiator disposed within the basin of the pitcher operative after the water of a batch of water has been discharged streamwise from the moving water processing module and received by the basin of the pitcher which contains it batchwise as a body of still water to provide UV radiation that is omnipresent to every region of the body of still water contained batchwise by the basin with an intensity and a duration to neutralize living organism organic impurities at every region of the body of still water contained batchwise by the basin, and, thereafter, to provide a signal indication that a batch of water purified of living and nonliving organic and inorganic pollutants is ready to be served through the spout of the pitcher. </claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002"><claim-text><b>2</b>. The portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the removable lid includes a fill opening therethrough, and a mechanism cooperative therewith to allow water to be received through said fill opening but to block direct viewing of UV radiation within said pitcher. </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00003"  num="00003"><claim-text><b>3</b>. The portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said mechanism includes a louvered disc valve. </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004"><claim-text><b>4</b>. The portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said flow-through filter media is an ion exchange and activated carbon flow-through filter. </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005"><claim-text><b>5</b>. The portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further including a lid seat sensing switch mounted to the removable lid to disable the UV line radiator in the basin of the pitcher when the removable lid is off of the pitcher. </claim-text></claim><claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006"><claim-text><b>6</b>. The portable, refillable water dispenser serving batches of water purified of organic and inorganic pollutants of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said UV line radiator of said still water processing module is upstanding in, and centrally disposed within, said basin.</claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure id="figure-D00000" num="00000"><img id="EMI-D00000"  he="129.03mm"  wi="127.32mm"  file="US20060231476A1-20061019-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" orientation="portrait" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00001" num="00001"><img id="EMI-D00001" he="200.24mm" wi="177.46mm" file="US20060231476A1-20061019-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" orientation="portrait" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00002" num="00002"><img id="EMI-D00002" he="192.19mm" wi="176.36mm" file="US20060231476A1-20061019-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" orientation="portrait" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00003" num="00003"><img id="EMI-D00003" he="91.52mm" wi="172.38mm" file="US20060231476A1-20061019-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" orientation="portrait" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00004" num="00004"><img id="EMI-D00004" he="185.50mm" wi="168.74mm" file="US20060231476A1-20061019-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" orientation="portrait" inline="no"/></figure><figure id="figure-D00005" num="00005"><img id="EMI-D00005" he="118.62mm" wi="147.83mm" file="US20060231476A1-20061019-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif" orientation="portrait" inline="no"/></figure></drawings><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>