<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1418000-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1418000" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="32105485" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040512"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1418000-A2" status="new" fvid="24056938"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1418000</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20040512</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03023893-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03023893</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031021</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002324361-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002324361</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021107</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  14/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  14/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  19/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  19/24        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   2/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   2/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   2/04        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   2/10        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  14/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  19/24</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren und Vorrichtung zur Herstellung von Wasser absorbierendem Harz</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Process and apparatus for production of water-absorbent resin</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé et appareil de production de résine absorbante d'eau</invention-title></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NIPPON CATALYTIC CHEM IND</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NIPPON SHOKUBAI CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Nippon Shokubai Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>1-1, Koraibashi 4-chome, Chuo-ku</street><city>Osaka-shi, Osaka 541-0043</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DAIROKU YORIMICHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>FUJINO SHINICHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>FUJITA YASUHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>IRIE YOSHIO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SHIBATA HIROFUMI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TADA KENJI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DAIROKU, YORIMICHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>FUJINO, SHINICHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>FUJITA, YASUHIRO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>IRIE, YOSHIO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SHIBATA, HIROFUMI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TADA, KENJI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DAIROKU, YORIMICHI</last-name><address><street>25, Nakahamacho 2-chome Shikama-ku</street><city>Himeji-shi Hyogo 672-8085</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>FUJINO, SHINICHI</last-name><address><street>550-4, Hamada Aboshi-ku</street><city>Himeji-shi Hyogo 671-1242</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>FUJITA, YASUHIRO</last-name><address><street>63-11-107, Komatsu-cho 1-chome Hirohata-ku</street><city>Himeji-shi Hyogo 671-1152</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>IRIE, YOSHIO</last-name><address><street>3253-3, Funatsu-cho</street><city>Himeji-shi Hyogo 679-2101</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SHIBATA, HIROFUMI</last-name><address><street>Hamada-ryo 931-11, Hamada Aboshi-ku</street><city>Himeji-shi Hyogo 671-1242</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TADA, KENJI</last-name><address><street>Hamada-ryo 931-11, amada Aboshi-ku</street><city>Himeji-shi Hyogo 671-1242</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Glawe, Delfs, Moll</last-name><address><street>Patentanwälte Postfach 26 01 62</street><city>80058 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country> <country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country> <country>MC</country> <country>NL</country> <country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>There is disclosed a process to uniformly and rapidly carry out the mixing of a
monomer liquid and a polymerization initiator and thus for the resulting polymer not
to adhere to the inner surface of the piping or the inside of the apparatus in an art of
producing a water-absorbent resin by continuously mixing the monomer liquid and
the polymerization initiator together and thereby carrying out polymerization. This
process comprises the steps of: (a) continuously supplying a monomer liquid 20 to
such as a supply pipe 10 to continuously stir the monomer liquid 20 in the supply
pipe 10 with such as a stirring apparatus 12; (b) causing a polymerization initiator 30
to join into a flow of the monomer liquid 20 being in a stirred state, thereby obtaining
a mixed liquid 40 of the monomer liquid 20 and the polymerization initiator 30; and
(c) continuously supplying the mixed liquid 40 from the supply pipe line 10 to a
polymerization apparatus to cause the mixed liquid 40 to run a polymerization
reaction.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="59" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="120"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><heading><u style="single">A. TECHNICAL FIELD</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a process and an apparatus for production of a
water-absorbent resin.</p><heading><u style="single">B. BACKGROUND ART</u></heading><p num="0002">Water-absorbent resins are widely utilized for various uses such as sanitary
articles (e.g. disposable diapers, sanitary napkins, adults' incontinent products) and
water-retaining agents and are produced and consumed in large quantities.</p><p num="0003">As prior processes for production of these water-absorbent resins, there are
known arts such as aqueous solution polymerization. For example, there can be
cited such as: a process comprising the step of polymerizing an aqueous solution
containing a hydrophilic monomer while fracturing the resulting polymer gel by
stirring (refer to JP-A-034101/1982); and a process comprising the step of statically
polymerizing an aqueous solution containing a monomer (refer to JP-A-156102/1987,
JP-A-126310/1989, JP-A-174414/1991, JP-A-175319/1992, JP-A-236203/1992).
Particularly, in the case where the static polymerization is continuously carried out
for the production, for example, there can be adopted a process comprising the step
of continuously supplying the aqueous monomer solution onto an endless belt to
cause the aqueous monomer solution to run a polymerization reaction.</p><p num="0004">In such a process for production of a water-absorbent resin, it is actually
impossible to mix the aqueous monomer solution, as supplied onto the belt, and a
polymerization initiator together, and it is therefore necessary to mix the aqueous
monomer solution with the polymerization initiator before supplying the aqueous
monomer solution onto the belt. However, if, when the aqueous monomer solution
and the polymerization initiator are beforehand mixed together, the mixing or 
supplying takes time, or a portion of the resulting mixed liquid stagnates in the
piping, then there may occur problems such that a polymer adheres to the inside of
the piping or apparatus (through which the mixed liquid is passed) and grows there
before the mixed liquid is supplied onto the belt, so that the piping is clogged up.
Accordingly, it is necessary to rapidly carry out the mixing of the aqueous monomer
solution and the polymerization initiator and the supply of their mixture onto the belt,
and further it is necessary that the mixing is carried out sufficiently and uniformly.
Particularly in the case where a high-concentration or high-temperature aqueous
monomer solution and the polymerization initiator is mixed together, extreme
difficulties are involved, because the induction period of the polymerization is short
and also because the polymerization is fast.</p><p num="0005">For example, in cases of such as inline mixing and spray mixing which are
used as common arts to mix liquids together, a comparatively good mixed state may
be obtained, but a dead space is produced in a mixer so easily that a portion of the
resulting mixed liquid stagnates in this dead space. Therefore, a polymer forms and
grows to thus clog up the mixer.</p><p num="0006">Thus, there have been proposed some arts which specify the method for the
mixing of the aqueous monomer solution and the polymerization initiator in the
continuous polymerization, thereby aiming at inhibiting the clogging of the piping
caused by the polymerization and at improving the workability.</p><p num="0007">For example, there have been proposed such as: (a) an art in which the
polymerization initiator is supplied at a flow rate of a specific ratio to a flow rate of
the aqueous monomer solution into a supply pipe through which the aqueous
monomer solution is flowing (refer to Japanese Patent No. 2679280); (b) a method in
which the aqueous monomer solution and the polymerization initiator are mixed
together by the force of a jet of a fluid using a mixing head having at least two jet
nozzles without any driving part (refer to JP-A-032514/1981); and (c) an art in which
the aqueous monomer solution and the polymerization initiator are supplied through 
their respective different supply pipes and then caused to flow into each other to
thereby be mixed together in a position of just before being discharged into a
polymerization machine (refer to JP-A-240903/1999).</p><p num="0008">However, none of the aforementioned prior arts can be said to be sufficient, but
all the aforementioned prior arts still have problems.</p><p num="0009">For example, in the case where the flow rates of the aqueous monomer solution
and the polymerization initiator are merely adjusted like in the art (a) of Japanese
Patent No. 2679280, a uniformly mixed state cannot be obtained immediately after
the supply of the polymerization initiator (in more detail, because the flow rates are
adjusted in the range near an equal rate). Therefore, the properties of the final
product are inferior. It takes such a long time to make the mixed state uniform by
this method as to need a long distance, namely, long piping, from the mixing to the
supply to the polymerization machine. As a result, a polymer forms and then
adheres to the inner surface of the piping and grows there to thus clog up the inside
of the piping.</p><p num="0010">As to the mixing head used in the art (b) of JP-A-032514/1981, there is a
possibility that: the monomer may polymerize near the jet nozzle to thus clog it up;
or a portion of the mixed liquid may stagnate in the inner space of the mixing head,
so that a polymer may adhere and grow to thus hinder the mixing or clog up the jet
nozzle.</p><p num="0011">As to arts involving the confluence in the position of just before the supply into
the polymerization machine such as the art (c) of JP-A-240903/1999, the mixing
makes progress almost on the polymerization machine. Therefore, almost no
polymer forms in the piping. However, there is a long way from the achievement of
the uniformly mixed state.</p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><heading><u style="single">A. OBJECT OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0012">Accordingly, an object of the present invention is to provide a production 
process and a production apparatus such that: when a water-absorbent resin is
continuously produced, the mixing of the polymerization initiator can be carried out
well without causing the clogging of the monomer-supplying pipe, and the properties
of the final product are good.</p><heading><u style="single">B. DISCLOSURE OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0013">A process for production of a water-absorbent resin, according to the present
invention, comprises the steps of mixing a monomer liquid with a polymerization
initiator and then polymerizing the resultant mixture, thereby producing the
water-absorbent resin; with the process further comprising the steps of: (a)
continuously supplying the monomer liquid to a supply pipe line to continuously stir
the monomer liquid in the supply pipe line; (b) causing the polymerization initiator to
flow into a flow of the monomer liquid being in a stirred state, thereby obtaining a
mixed liquid of the monomer liquid and the polymerization initiator; and (c)
continuously supplying the mixed liquid from the supply pipe line to a
polymerization apparatus to cause the mixed liquid to run a polymerization reaction.</p><p num="0014">Hereupon, the "monomer liquid" is a technical conception including a case
where it is a liquid monomer itself and a case where it is a monomer solution as
formed by dissolving a monomer into water or another solvent.</p><p num="0015">These and other objects and the advantages of the present invention will be
more fully apparent from the following detailed disclosure.</p><heading><b>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</b></heading><p num="0016"><sl><li>Fig. 1 is a schematic sectional view of the production process, which illustrates
a mode for carrying out the present invention.</li><li>Fig. 2 is a block diagram of the production process.</li><li>Fig. 3 is an entire structural view which illustrates an apparatus for production
of a water-absorbent resin.</li></sl></p><p num="0017">An explanation of the symbols is as follows.
<sl><li>10: Supply pipe </li><li>12: Stirring apparatus</li><li>14: Confluent pipe</li><li>20: Monomer liquid</li><li>30: Polymerization initiator</li><li>40: Mixed liquid</li></sl></p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0018">Hereinafter, detailed descriptions are given about modes for carrying out the
present invention.</p><p num="0019">There is no especial limitation on the monomer as used in the present invention
if it can form a water-absorbent resin by polymerization. However, examples
thereof include the following. Hereupon, as the monomer component, there can be
cited such as: anionic unsaturated monomers (e.g. (meth)acrylic acid, maleic acid
(anhydride), itaconic acid, succinic acid, vinylsulfonic acid, allyltoluenesulfonic acid,
vinyltoluenesulfonic acid, styrenesulfonic acid,
2-(meth)acrylamido-2-methylpropanesulfonic acid, 2-(meth)acryloylethanesulfonic
acid, 2-(meth)acryloylpropanesulfonic acid, 2-hydroxyethyl (meth)acryloyl
phosphate) and their salts; mercapto-group-containing unsaturated monomers;
phenolic-hydroxyl-group-containing unsaturated monomers; amido-group-containing
unsaturated monomers (e.g. (meth)acrylamide, N-ethyl(meth)acrylamide,
N,N-dimethyl(meth)acrylamide); and amino-group-containing unsaturated
monomers (e.g. N,N-dimethylaminoethyl (meth)acrylate, N,N-dimethylaminopropyl
(meth)acrylate, N,N-dimethylaminopropyl(meth)acrylamide). These monomers
may be used either alone respectively or in appropriate combinations with each other.
However, from the viewpoint of the performances of the resulting water-absorbent
resin and from the viewpoint of costs, it is favorable to use acrylic acid and/or its salt
(e.g. salt of such as sodium, lithium, potassium, ammonium, or an amine; above all,
the sodium salt is preferable from the viewpoint of costs) as the main component.
The amount of the acrylic acid and/or its salt as used is favorably not smaller than 70 
mol %, more favorably not smaller than 80 mol %, still more favorably not smaller
than 90 mol %, particularly favorably not smaller than 95 mol %, of the entire
monomer components.</p><p num="0020">The monomer concentration during the polymerization is not especially limited.
However, it is favorably in the range of 20 to 100 weight %, more favorably 25 to 80
weight %, still more favorably 30 to 70 weight %. In the case where the monomer
concentration is less than 20 weight %, the productivity is poor. The superiority of
the present invention will be apparent particularly under monomer concentration
conditions of not less than 40 weight %, and further not less than 45 weight %, where
the concentration is so high that the polymerization easily occurs.</p><p num="0021">In the case where the monomer is an acid-group-containing monomer, its
neutralization degree is not especially limited. However, for uses possible to
involve contact with human bodies such as sanitary articles, the neutralization degree
is favorably in the range of 40 to 90 mol %, more favorably 50 to 80 mol %, also for
a purpose such that the neutralization will not be needed after the polymerization.</p><p num="0022">An internal-crosslinking agent is used when the above polymerization is
carried out. As such an internal-crosslinking agent, there can be used those which
are conventional and publicly known. Specific examples thereof include
N,N'-methylenebis(meth)acrylamide, (poly)ethylene glycol di(meth)acrylate,
(poly)propylene glycol di(meth)acrylate, trimethylolpropane tri(meth)acrylate,
glycerol tri(meth)acrylate, glycerol acrylate methacrylate, ethylene-oxide-modified
trimethylolpropane tri(meth)acrylate, pentaerythritol hexa(meth)acrylate, triallyl
cyanurate, triallyl isocyanurate, triallyl phosphate, triallylamine,
poly(meth)allyloxyalkanes, (poly)ethylene glycol diglycidyl ether, glycerol
diglycidyl ether, ethylene glycol, polyethylene glycol, propylene glycol, glycerol,
1,4-butanediol, pentaerythritol, ethylenediamine, ethylene carbonate, propylene
carbonate, polyethylenimine, and glycidyl (meth)acrylate. One or two or more of
them are usable in consideration of the reactivity. Above all, it is preferable to 
essentially use a compound having at least two polymerizable unsaturated groups.
The amount of the internal-crosslinking agent as used can be determined
appropriately for desired properties of the resulting water-absorbent resin. However,
this amount is usually in the range of 0.001 to 5 mol % relative to the aforementioned
monomer components. In the case where the amount of the internal-crosslinking
agent as used is too small, the gel strength tends to be low, and the extractable
content tends to increase. On the other hand, in the case where the amount of the
internal-crosslinking agent as used is too large, the absorption capacity tends to be
low.</p><p num="0023">When the polymerization is carried out, to the reaction system there can be
added the following: hydrophilic polymers such as starch, starch derivatives,
cellulose, cellulose derivatives, poly(vinyl alcohol), poly(acrylic acid) (salts), and
crosslinked poly(acrylic acid) (salts); chain transfer agents such as hypophosphorous
acid (salts); and chelating agents.</p><p num="0024">The viscosity of the monomer liquid, as used in the present invention, is
favorably in the range of 0.1 to 500 mPa·s (but not including 500 mPa·s), more
favorably 0.1 to 100 mPa·s (but not including 100 mPa·s), still more favorably 0.1 to
50 mPa·s (but not including 50 mPa·s). In the case where the viscosity is too large,
the stirring operation is so difficult as to result in bad mixability of the
polymerization initiator.</p><p num="0025">The polymerization is carried out usually under ordinary pressure from the
viewpoint of such as ease of the apparatus and operation. It is also a favorable
mode to carry out the polymerization under reduced pressure in order to lower the
boiling temperature of the polymerization system.</p><p num="0026">The polymerization initiator, as used in the present invention, is not especially
limited. One or two or more selected from among those which are utilized for
conventional water-absorbent resin production can be used appropriately for such as
the kind of the monomer to be polymerized and the polymerization conditions. 
Examples thereof include: thermal initiators (e.g. persulfates such as sodium
persulfate, potassium persulfate, and ammonium persulfate; peroxides such as
hydrogen peroxide, t-butyl peroxide, and methyl ethyl ketone peroxide; azo
compounds such as azonitrile compounds, azoamidine compounds, cyclic
azoamidine compounds, azoamide compounds, alkylazo compounds,
2,2'-azobis(2-amidinopropane) dihydrochloride, and
2,2'-azobis[2-(2-imidazolin-2-yl)propane] dihydrochloride); and photoinitiators (e.g.
benzoin derivatives, benzyl derivatives, acetophenone derivatives, benzophenone
derivatives, azo compounds). The persulfates are favorable from the viewpoint of
costs and from the viewpoint of the ability to reduce the residual monomer content.
Furthermore, a redox initiator is also available by using the above polymerization
initiator jointly with a reducing agent which promotes the decomposition of the
above polymerization initiator and thus combining both with each other. Examples
of the above reducing agent include: (bi)sulfurous acid (salts) such as sodium sulfite
and sodium hydrogensulfite; L-ascorbic acid (salts); reducible metals (salts) such as
ferrous salts; and amines. However, there is no especial limitation thereto. In the
case where the oxidizable polymerization initiator and the reducing agent are used
like the redox initiator, each of them may be caused to join into a flow of the
monomer liquid by the process according to the present invention, or the reducing
agent may beforehand be mixed into the monomer liquid. More favorably, the
photoinitiator and the thermal initiator are used together.</p><p num="0027">It is usually in a state of a solution or dispersion that the polymerization
initiator is mixed with the monomer liquid. However, if the polymerization initiator
is liquid, it is also possible to mix the polymerization initiator, as it is, with the
monomer liquid. The amount of the polymerization initiator as used is usually in
the range of 0.001 to 2 weight %, favorably 0.01 to 0.5 weight %, relative to the
monomer components in the monomer liquid.</p><p num="0028">The temperature of the monomer liquid is usually in the range of 10 to 110 °C. 
In the case where the polymerization initiation temperature is lower than 10 °C, not
only is the productivity poor due to the extension of the induction period and the
polymerization time, but also the properties of the resulting water-absorbent resin are
inferior. In the process according to the present invention, even if the temperature
of the monomer liquid is a comparatively high temperature of not lower than 50 °C,
the polymerization initiator can stably be mixed.</p><p num="0029">The monomer liquid is continuously supplied by being fed from its production
apparatus directly to the supply piping or by being once stored in a tank or reservoir
and then fed to the supply piping.</p><p num="0030">The supply amount of the monomer liquid is adjusted so as to match the
desired yield. On this occasion, the diameter of the pipe to supply the monomer
liquid and the flow rate of the monomer liquid will do if they are selected in their
respective ranges appropriate for the kind of the fluid and the purpose and further if
the pipe diameter is adjusted so as to be an economical one. For details, it is
possible to refer to publicly known references (e.g. "Piping Engineering (author:
Yoshio SHOKOCHI, published by Engineering Books K.K.)").</p><p num="0031">As an apparatus for applying the stirring operation to the monomer liquid being
continuously supplied in the present invention, there can be used a stirrer for
ordinary liquids. Particularly preferable is a stirrer having an inline structure of
carrying out the stirring on the way of a pipe through which a flow of the monomer
liquid continuously passed. Examples of the stirrer having the inline structure
include: a small-sized stirrer which has stirring blades that are fixed to the inside of a
cylindrical pipe or are able to revolve; and a static mixer such that the stirring can be
carried out during the transportation of a liquid flow by an element (mixing element)
of the shape of a 180°-twisted rectangular plate wherein the element is inserted in a
pipe. In addition, it is also possible to apply the stirring operation to the monomer
liquid by such a jet nozzle, a throat, an orifice, a baffle, a branch pipe, or a confluent
pipe as is put in a pipe. </p><p num="0032">When the stirring operation is applied to the monomer liquid which is
continuously flowing in a pipe, the flowing state of the liquid can be evaluated by
schematically adapting the stirring Reynolds number which is used to represent the
flowing state of a fluid as stirred by a stirring apparatus as equipped with a container
for placing the fluid therein (stirring vessel) and with stirring blades. This
evaluation is favorably carried out in such a manner that the stirring Reynolds
number Re of the monomer liquid to which the stirring operation is applied will
reach not smaller than 50. In general, Re &lt; 50 is judged a laminar flow state, and
Re &gt; 1,000 is judged a turbulent flow state. In addition, the range of 50 &lt; Re &lt;
1,000 is judged a transition state where the laminar flow state and the turbulent flow
state intermingle (refer to "Handbook of Chemical Engineering", 6th revised edition,
p.424, edited by Chemical Engineering Society, published by Maruzen).</p><p num="0033">The polymerization initiator can also be supplied either directly from its
preparation apparatus or, if necessary, from a tank or reservoir in which the
polymerization initiator is beforehand stored.</p><p num="0034">The polymerization initiator may be caused to join into a flow of the monomer
liquid after having been stirred similarly to the monomer liquid, but will do if the
polymerization initiator is caused to join into the flow of the monomer liquid without
especially carrying out the stirring operation. The polymerization initiator may be
caused to join into the flow of the monomer liquid either from one place or
simultaneously from at least two places. Similarly to the monomer liquid, the flow
rate and pipe diameter of the polymerization initiator will also do if they are selected
so as to be appropriate for such as the supply amount and the kind of the fluid.</p><p num="0035">If the polymerization initiator joins into a flow of the monomer liquid being
stirred, then a good mixed state can be obtained in a shorter time than the case where
the monomer liquid is merely flowing through an ordinary pipe without being stirred.
Accordingly, even if, in a short time after the monomer liquid has been mixed with
the polymerization initiator, the resultant mixture is discharged from a supply pipe to 
thus be supplied to a polymerization machine, then a uniformly mixed state can be
obtained. Therefore, the properties of the resulting water-absorbent resin are good,
and also the clogging of the inside of the pipe can be inhibited. In addition, it is
also possible to consider a reason that if, even though the mixed liquid is not
completely uniformly mixed in the supply pipe, the mixed liquid is still in a stirred
state, then the mixing can easily be carried out even in the polymerization machine
after the mixed liquid has been discharged from the supply pipe. The pipe line
length of from the confluence to the discharge is usually not less than 1 cm,
favorably not less than 5 cm, more favorably not less than 10 cm, though depending
also on conditions such as the stirred state of the monomer liquid, the behavior and
state of the polymerization initiator, the temperature of the monomer liquid, the
decomposition rate of the polymerization initiator, and the induction period. In the
case where the induction period is comparatively long, the above pipe line length can
be made longer.</p><p num="0036">As to the supply piping of from the mixing of the monomer liquid and the
polymerization initiator to a supply opening to the polymerization machine, it is
better not to use such as a screw joint or a union on the way of the supply piping, if
possible. In the case where they exist, there is a possibility that a dead space may
be produced at the joint part so easily that a polymer grows in this dead space. In
addition, as to the above piping, a conventional stainless steel pipe may be used, but
it is favorable to use: a steel pipe of which the inner surface is coated with a
fluororesin; or a fluororesin-made pipe.</p><p num="0037">Furthermore, in the case where the polymerization is suspended, it is favorable
to wash the piping with water in order that the monomer liquid stagnating in the
piping can be caused to flow out by the washing. If, even though the
polymerization is once stopped and then resumed, the above washing is carried out,
then there occurs no problem such that the piping or apparatus is clogged up with the
polymer. </p><p num="0038">The polymerization method, as used in the present invention, is not especially
limited. However, aqueous solution polymerization is favorable. Specific
examples thereof include: a static polymerization method in which an aqueous
monomer solution is polymerized in a static state; and a stirring polymerization
method in which the aqueous monomer solution is polymerized in a stirring
apparatus. There is no especial limitation on the production apparatus, as used in
the present invention, if it is such an apparatus as can continuously polymerize a
mixed liquid of the monomer liquid and the polymerization initiator wherein the
mixed liquid is obtained in the above way and continuously supplied. There can be
adopted such a continuous belt polymerization machine or continuous stirring
polymerization machine as is used for conventional water-absorbent resin production.
In the case of the stirring polymerization machine, even a single-shaft stirrer is
available. However, there is favorably used a stirrer having at least two stirring
shafts such as a continuous kneader.</p><p num="0039">To the continuous belt polymerization apparatus, there can be applied such arts
as are disclosed in such as JP-A-034305-2000, JP-A-228604-1999,
JP-A-156102-1987.</p><p num="0040">The production process according to the present invention can realize a good
mixed state without clogging the piping when mixing the polymerization initiator,
even if there is used a high-temperature or high-concentration monomer liquid which
easily polymerizes. Therefore, the production process according to the present
invention is useful particularly for application under such polymerization conditions.
For example, the production process according to the present invention is applicable
to the enablement of the continuation of such a high-temperature or
high-concentration polymerization art as is disclosed in JP-A-212204-2002. A
polymerization apparatus which is favorable for this case is an endless belt type
continuous polymerization apparatus to which the mixed liquid, as obtained in the
aforementioned way, of the monomer liquid and the polymerization initiator is 
supplied, wherein the endless belt type continuous polymerization apparatus has the
following: a belt which is made of a fluororesin or of which the surface is coated
with the fluororesin; a belt unit which is heated or heat-insulated; and a system to
recover and recycle vaporized water or a vaporized monomer liquid. In addition, as
to the belt, it is desirable that: either the belt is laid horizontal or a
monomer-mixed-liquid-supplying part is put in a low position so that the monomer
liquid can be inhibited from flowing backward; and a belt-washing step is set on the
way of from the discharge of a polymer gel off the surface of the belt to a
monomer-mixed-liquid-supplying orifice.</p><p num="0041">The aforementioned continuous belt polymerization gives a polymer gel of a
water-absorbent resin which continues in the shape of a band. The polymer gel may
be used either as it is or after having been finely pulverized. Usually, the polymer
gel is further dried and pulverized to form a particulate water-absorbent resin, and
the resultant water-absorbent resin particles are further treated by
surface-crosslinking or granulated to thus be used as a water-absorbent resin product.
For the pulverization, drying, and surface-crosslinking treatment of the polymer gel,
it is enough to adopt publicly known arts.</p><p num="0042">Fig. 1 schematically illustrates a structure of an apparatus involved in the step
of mixing the monomer liquid and the polymerization initiator together. On the
way of a supply pipe 10 through which the monomer liquid 20 flows, there is set a
stirring apparatus 12. A supply pipe 14 of the polymerization initiator 30 joins into
the supply pipe 10 downstream of the stirring apparatus 12. The supply pipe 14 of
the polymerization initiator 30 enters the inside of the supply pipe 10 of the
monomer liquid 20 from the outer periphery of the supply pipe 10 and then bends in
the shape of an elbow toward the downstream side and then opens into the
downstream direction. The position of the opening part in the pipe may be
anywhere within the range of from the central part to the outer peripheral part, but is
preferably near the outer peripheral part. For example, the supply pipe 14, having a 
pipe diameter of 0.5 mm, of the polymerization initiator joins into the supply pipe 10,
having a pipe diameter of 8 mm, of the monomer liquid.</p><p num="0043">Upstream of the stirring apparatus 12, the monomer liquid 20 can be regarded
as being in what is called a laminar flow state. A portion (a) of Fig. 1 illustrates a
flow rate distribution over a diameter section of the supply pipe 10. In the laminar
flow state, there occurs a smooth incline from the central axis toward the inner
surface of the pipe.</p><p num="0044">As the stirring apparatus 12, there can be used a Static Mixer (produced by
Noritake Company) having a spiral element. The monomer liquid passing through
the stirring apparatus 12 forms a vortical flow by the stirring blade or element to thus
be brought into what is called a turbulent flow state. It can be considered that, as is
illustrated in (b) of Fig. 1, the flow rate distribution of the monomer liquid 20 on this
occasion is made almost uniform in the pipe diameter direction except portions near
the inner surface of the pipe and therefore does not show such a non-uniform flow
rate distribution as in the laminar flow state. Incidentally, the monomer liquid 20,
which has formed the vortical flow by being stirred, returns to the laminar flow state
gradually along with the movement of the monomer liquid 20 toward the
downstream side in the supply pipe 10. Thus, it is also effective to bring the
polymerization initiator 30 into confluence in a position near the stirring apparatus
12 as much as possible, because, at least at the confluence of the supply pipe 14 of
the polymerization initiator 30, the monomer liquid 20 needs to keep the vortical
flow necessary for the mixing.</p><p num="0045">In addition, the tendency for the monomer liquid 20, which has formed the
vortical flow by being stirred, to return to the laminar flow state gradually along with
the movement of the monomer liquid 20 toward the downstream side in the supply
pipe 10 is strong if the viscosity of the monomer liquid is high. Therefore, it is
preferable that the monomer liquid is a low-viscosity fluid.</p><p num="0046">Fig. 2 illustrates a block process diagram relating to the production apparatus 
according to the present invention. Fig. 3 schematically illustrates an example of
the constitution of the apparatus according to the present invention for production of
a water-absorbent resin including the mixing step of Fig. 1.</p><p num="0047">As is illustrated in Fig. 3, this apparatus comprises a supply mechanism of the
monomer liquid 20 upstream of the supply pipe 10 illustrated in Fig. 1. First, there
are equipped: a tank 50 in which an aqueous NaOH (sodium hydroxide) solution is
reserved; and a tank 60 in which AA (acrylic acid) is reserved. These tanks 50 and
60 are connected through pumps 54 and 64 respectively to a dispersing machine 56.
Between the pump 64 and the dispersing machine 56, there are supplied such as a
crosslinking agent liquid (e.g. PEGDA (polyethylene glycol diacrylate), water, and
other additives (e.g. chelating agents, photoinitiators). The water may be used in
the form of an aqueous acrylic acid solution by being beforehand placed in a
predetermined amount in the tank 60, or may be supplied between the pump 64 and
the dispersing machine 56. A favorable state is that the acrylic acid is supplied to
the dispersing machine 56 in such a degree of aqueous solution concentration as to
have no flash point, specifically, in the form of an aqueous acrylic acid solution
having a concentration of not more than about 60 weight %. Thereby, the danger of
a fire and explosion becomes so low that special measures against the danger to
apparatuses and structures can be reduced, thus getting an advantage also in point of
costs. In addition, air in a part or all of the aqueous NaOH solution, the AA, and
the water may be displaced with such as nitrogen, if necessary.</p><p num="0048">In the dispersing machine 56, such as the aqueous NaOH solution, the AA, and
the PEGDA are uniformly neutralized or mixed to form the monomer liquid 20. At
this stage, there is almost no possibility that the monomer liquid may polymerize to
become a gel. Therefore, the mixing can sufficiently be carried out with the
conventional dispersing machine 56 to thereby obtain the monomer liquid 20 having
a uniform composition. Next, the monomer liquid 20 is adjusted to a predetermined
temperature with a condenser or heater on the way of from the dispersing machine 56 
to the stirring apparatus 12. Or, if the dispersing machine 56 is fitted with such as a
jacket for the temperature adjustment, then it becomes unnecessary to set the
condenser or heater downstream of the dispersing machine. In addition, if the
temperature of such as the aqueous NaOH solution or the AA, which is supplied to
the dispersing machine 56, is beforehand adjusted, then the temperature adjustment
of the monomer liquid 20 is also achieved to a certain extent.</p><p num="0049">After having been made vortical by the stirring apparatus 12, the flow of the
monomer liquid 20 is joined with the polymerization initiator 30 (e.g. aqueous
sodium persulfate solution) as supplied from the pipe 14. The detailed structure of
the confluent part is as illustrated in Fig. 1. In the present invention, it is not
necessary to equip any special stirring apparatus to the supply pipe 10 downstream of
where the polymerization initiator 30 is mixed. There is a case where the monomer
liquid 20 having come out of the dispersing machine 56 is in the form of a vortical
flow as formed by the stir-mixing with the dispersing machine 56. In such a case,
the dispersing machine 56 can be used also as the stirring apparatus 12 by causing
the polymerization initiator 30 to join into the above vortical flow.</p><p num="0050">The supply opening (discharging outlet) downstream of the supply pipe 10 is
set above a belt conveyor 70 constituting the polymerization apparatus. The mixed
liquid 40 is discharged onto the belt conveyor, and the polymerization runs on the
belt conveyor to form a band-shaped polymer gel 42 of a water-absorbent resin.
Incidentally, the mixed liquid 40, which is discharged from the supply pipe 10, may
either keep in the vortical flow state or be back to the laminar flow state, if the
mixing of the polymerization initiator 30 is uniform. Even if the mixed state of the
mixed liquid 40 is a little bad, it is enough that the vortical flow is kept to such a
degree that the mixing immediately becomes uniform on the belt.</p><p num="0051">In the case where the polymerization is once stopped, water can be supplied to
the supply pipe so that the entire course through which acrylic acid passes can be
washed with the water. </p><p num="0052">The band-shaped polymer gel 42 may be used either as it is or in the form of
water-absorbent resin particles as formed by the pulverization and/or drying.</p><heading>(Effects and Advantages of the Invention):</heading><p num="0053">In the process according to the present invention for production of a
water-absorbent resin, because the polymerization initiator is supplied in a state
where a flow of the monomer liquid which is flowing through the pipe is stirred, the
mixing runs rapidly at a stage when the polymerization initiator has joined into the
flow of the monomer liquid. It is not necessary to run the mixing with a long
distance and a long time spent after the confluence like in the case where the
polymerization initiator is uniformly mixed without stirring. It is possible to inhibit
such formation of a polymer during the stir-mixing operation and such fixation of the
formed polymer to the insides of the piping and apparatus as are caused in the case
where the mixing is carried out with a stirring apparatus after the confluence of the
polymerization initiator. Therefore, even if the supply to a polymerization
apparatus is carried out immediately after the polymerization initiator has joined into
the flow of the monomer liquid, the mixing does not result in being non-uniform.</p><p num="0054">As a result, the production of the water-absorbent resin can be carried out
stably and efficiently, and also the quality of the resultant water-absorbent resin can
be made good.</p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</b></heading><p num="0055">Hereinafter, the present invention is more specifically illustrated by the
following Examples of some preferred embodiments in comparison with
Comparative Examples not according to the present invention. However, the
present invention is not limited to them. Incidentally, in these examples, unless
otherwise noted, the unit "part(s)" denotes "weight part(s)", and the temperature for
measurement is in the range of about 23±2 °C.</p><p num="0056">Incidentally, the water absorption performances of the water-absorbent resin
were measured and the flowing state of the stirred monomer was calculated, in the 
following ways.</p><heading>[Measurement of absorption capacity without load (GV)]:</heading><p num="0057">About 0.2 g of water-absorbent resin was weighed out and then uniformly
placed into a nonwoven-fabric-made bag (60 mm x 60 mm) and then into a 0.9
weight % aqueous sodium chloride solution (physiological saline (solution)). After
30 minutes, the bag was pulled up and then drained of water at 250 × 9.81 m/s<sup>2</sup> (250
G) with a centrifugal separator for 3 minutes and then weighed as W1 (g). The
same procedure as the above was carried out without the water-absorbent resin, and
the resultant weight W0 (g) was measured. Then, the GV (absorption capacity
without load) was calculated from these weights W1 and W0 in accordance with the
following equation:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">GV (g/g) = [(W1- W0)/weight of water-absorbent resin] -1</st32:df></p><heading>[Measurement of extractable content]:</heading><p num="0058">An amount of 184.3 g of a 0.9 weight % aqueous NaCl solution (physiological
saline (solution)) was weighed out into a plastic container of 250 mL in capacity
having a lid. Thereafter, 1.00 g of water-absorbent resin was added into the above
aqueous solution, and then the resultant mixture was stirred for 16 hours, whereby
extractable components were extracted from the resin. The resultant extract was
filtrated with filter paper, and then 50.0 g of the resultant filtrate was weighed out as
a solution for measurement. Next, to begin with, only the physiological saline
(solution) was titrated first with a 0.1N aqueous NaOH solution until pH became 10
and thereafter with a 0.1N aqueous HCl solution until pH became 2.7, thus obtaining
blank titration amounts ([bNaOH] mL, [bHCl] mL). The same titration procedure
as the above was carried out also as to the above solution for measurement, thereby
determining titration amounts ([NaOH] mL, [HCl] mL). For example, in the case
of a water-absorbent resin comprising acrylic acid and its sodium salt, the extractable
content in this water-absorbent resin was calculated from the following calculation
equation based on the weight-average molecular weight Mw of the water-absorbent 
resin comprising the above monomers and on the titration amounts as obtained by the
above procedures.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Extractable content (weight %) =<st32:break type="required"/>
0.1 × Mw × 184.3 × 100 ×<st32:break type="required"/>
([HCl] - [bHCl])/1000/1.0/50.0</st32:df>
wherein:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Mw=<st32:break type="required"/>
72.06 × (1 - neutralization degree/100) + 94..04 × neutralization degree/100</st32:df><st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Neutralization degree (mol %) =<st32:break type="required"/>
[1 - ([NaOH] - [bNaOH])/<st32:break type="required"/>
([HCl] - [bHCl])] × 100</st32:df></p><heading>[Measurement of residual monomer content]:</heading><p num="0059">An amount of 0.5 g of water-absorbent resin was added to 1,000 g of deionized
water to carry out extraction under stirring for 2 hours. Thereafter, the
water-absorbent resin having formed into a swollen gel was filtered off with filter
paper to analyze the residual monomer content in the filtrate by liquid
chromatography. On the other hand, a calibration curve, as obtained by analyzing a
standard monomer solution of an already known concentration in the same way as
the above, was used as the external standard to determine the residual monomer
content in the water-absorbent resin considering the dilution degree of the filtrate.</p><heading>[Calculation of stirring Reynolds number Re]:</heading><p num="0060">When the stirring operation is applied to the monomer liquid which is
continuously flowing in a pipe, the flowing state of the liquid is evaluated by
schematically adapting and thus calculating the stirring Reynolds number which is
used to represent the flowing state of a fluid as stirred by a stirring apparatus as
equipped with a container for placing the fluid therein (stirring vessel) and with 
stirring blades.</p><heading>Calculation Example 1):</heading><p num="0061">The stirring Reynolds number is calculated from the following calculation
equation in the case where the monomer liquid having a density ρ (kg/m<sup>3</sup>) and a
viscosity µ (Pa·s), which is flowing at an average flow rate u (m/s), is stirred with a
static mixer including an element having a length L (m) and a diameter (pipe
diameter) d (m) wherein the element is formed by twisting a rectangular plate right
or left n times (revolution of 180 degrees per one-time twisting).
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Re = u × 0.5 × n/L × d<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup> × ρ/µ</st32:df></p><heading>Calculation Example 2):</heading><p num="0062">The stirring Reynolds number is calculated from the following calculation
equation in the case where the monomer liquid having a viscosity µ (Pa·s) and a
density ρ (kg/m<sup>3</sup>) is stirred at a rate of n revolutions per second with a small-sized
stirrer which has stirring blades of d m in blade diameter and is placed on the way of
the pipe.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Re = n × d<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup> × ρ/µ</st32:df></p><heading>[Example 1]:</heading><p num="0063">A water-absorbent resin is produced with the apparatus of Fig. 3 as follows.</p><p num="0064">A monomer liquid 20 was prepared with the apparatus of Fig. 3 by setting the
following flow rates of: a 48.5 weight % aqueous sodium hydroxide solution at 5.83
g/s; acrylic acid at 7.24 g/s; a 30 weight % aqueous polyethylene glycol diacrylate
(average molecular weight: 487) solution (I) at 0.0287 g/s; a solution (II), as prepared
by dissolving 0.989 weight parts of 2-hydroxymethyl-2-methylpropiophenone and
1.08 weight parts of a 45 weight % aqueous pentasodium
diethylenetriaminepentaacetate solution into 97.4 weight parts of a 20 weight %
aqueous acrylic acid solution, at 0.0893 g/s; and water at 3.32 g/s. The temperature
of this monomer liquid 20 was stable at about 95 °C.</p><p num="0065">The monomer liquid 20 was stirred with a stirring apparatus having been 
prepared as a static mixer by inserting a 1.5-revolution-twisted element of 18.6 mm
in length and 6 mm in diameter into a pipe of 6 mm in pipe diameter. Thereafter, a
2 weight % aqueous sodium persulfate (polymerization initiator) solution was caused
at a flow rate of 0.151 g/s to join into a flow of the monomer liquid 20 in a position
of about 3 cm downstream from the rear of the element, thus preparing a mixed
liquid 40. The stirring Reynolds number at that time was calculated as 2,280 (p=
1,160, µ = 0.001). The mixed liquid 40 was supplied onto a belt polymerization
apparatus 70 comprising: an endless belt of 3.8 m in length and 60 cm in width of
which the surface was coated with a fluororesin; a UV lamp as set above the belt; the
bottom and the periphery as heated and heat-insulated at about 100 °C; and an
aspirating pipe to recover vaporized water, which was set at the central part.
Thereby, polymerization was continuously carried out to obtain a band-shaped
polymer gel. Incidentally, the pipe line length of from the confluence of the
polymerization initiator to the outlet for discharge to the polymerization machine was
30 cm. Furthermore, the band-shaped polymer gel having a surface temperature of
about 70 °C was continuously pulverized with a meat chopper and then dried with
hot air of 180 °C to form a dried material. Thereafter, this dried material was
pulverized with a roll mill to obtain a particulate water-absorbent resin (1). The
resultant water-absorbent resin particles (1) were sieved to classify them into
particles being in the range of 300 to 600 µm. The properties of the classified
particles were measured. The results are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>[Comparative Example 1]:</heading><p num="0066">Water-absorbent resin particles (2) were obtained by the same process as of
Example 1 except that the polymerization initiator 30 was caused to join into a
unstirred flow of the monomer liquid 20 using a supply pipe 10 as not equipped with
the static mixer as a stirring apparatus. The resultant water-absorbent resin particles
(2) were classified into particles being in the range of 300 to 600 µm. The
properties of the classified particles were measured. The results are shown in Table 
1.</p><heading>[Comparative Example 2]:</heading><p num="0067">An experiment was carried out by the same process as of Example 1 except
that, in the same way as of Comparative Example 1, the monomer liquid 20 and the
polymerization initiator 30 were caused to flow into each other without equipping the
stirring apparatus 12, but that the mixing treatment was carried out using a supply
pipe 10 as equipped with the static mixer downstream of the confluent part.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">GV

g/g</entry><entry align="center">Extractable content

weight %</entry><entry align="center">Residual monomer content

ppm</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-absorbent resin (1)</entry><entry align="left">34</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">780</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-absorbent resin (2)</entry><entry align="left">40</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">5,410</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>[Evaluation] :</heading><p num="0068"><sl><li>(1) As can be understood from Table 1, in Example 1 in which the stirring
treatment was carried out, the water-absorbent resin having good quality and
performance was obtained. In addition, there occurred no problem even if the
operation was carried out continuously for a long time.</li><li>(2) In Comparative Example 1 in which the stirring treatment was not carried
out, there occurred no problem even if the operation was carried out continuously for
a long time. However, as is clear from Table 1, the quality of the resultant
water-absorbent resin was so inferior that the relation between the GV and the
extractable content was bad, and further that the residual monomer content was high.</li><li>(3) In Comparative Example 2, the pressure in the supply pipe rose gradually
from just after the beginning of the experiment and, about 25 minutes later, it became
impossible to supply the mixed liquid 40 to the polymerization apparatus. The
apparatus was decomposed and then inspected. As a result, it was found that the
inside of the static mixer and the piping parts upstream and downstream of the static
mixer were clogged up with the polymer.</li></sl></p><p num="0069">Various details of the invention may be changed without departing from its
spirit not its scope. Furthermore, the foregoing description of the preferred
embodiments according to the present invention is provided for the purpose of
illustration only, and not for the purpose of limiting the invention as defined by the
appended claims and their equivalents.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process for production of a water-absorbent resin, which comprises the
steps of mixing a monomer liquid with a polymerization initiator and then
polymerizing the resultant mixture, thereby producing the water-absorbent resin;
   with the process further comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) continuously supplying the monomer liquid to a supply pipe line to
continuously stir the monomer liquid in the supply pipe line;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) causing the polymerization initiator to join into a flow of the monomer
liquid being in a stirred state, thereby obtaining a mixed liquid of the monomer liquid
and the polymerization initiator; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) continuously supplying the mixed liquid from the supply pipe line to a
polymerization apparatus to cause the mixed liquid to run a polymerization reaction.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A process for production of a water-absorbent resin according to claim 1,
wherein, in the step (a), a monomer liquid having a concentration of not less than 40
weight % is used as the monomer liquid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A process for production of a water-absorbent resin according to claim 1
or 2, wherein, in the step (a), a monomer liquid having a liquid temperature of not
lower than 50 °C is used as the monomer liquid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A process for production of a water-absorbent resin according to any one
of claims 1 to 3, wherein, in the step (a), the monomer liquid is stirred until its
stirring Reynolds number reaches not smaller than 50.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An apparatus for production of a water-absorbent resin, which is an
apparatus used for the production process as recited in any one of claims 1 to 4;
   with the apparatus comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a supply pipe line to which the monomer liquid is continuously supplied;</claim-text><claim-text>a stirring treatment part which is placed on the way of the supply pipe line to
continuously stir the monomer liquid;</claim-text><claim-text>a mixing part which is placed on the supply pipe line downstream of the
stirring treatment part to supply the polymerization initiator to mix it with the
monomer liquid; and</claim-text><claim-text>a polymerization apparatus which is placed downstream of the supply pipe line
to cause a mixed liquid of the monomer liquid and the polymerization initiator to run
a polymerization reaction.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>