<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1006143-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1006143" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18336750" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000607"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1006143-A1" status="new" fvid="22834657"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1006143</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000607</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99119083-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99119083</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991001</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-34041698-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>34041698</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981130</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B09B   3/00        20060101AFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B09B   3/00        20060101CFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J  11/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J  11/28        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08J  11/14+L75/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08J  11/28+L75/04</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Vorrichtung zur Zersetzung und Rückgewinnung von Polyurethanharz</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Apparatus for decomposition and recovery of polyurethane resin</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Installation pour la décomposition et la récupération de résine de polyuréthane</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-4128588-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>4128588</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0854165-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0854165</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3117940-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3117940</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998034904-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998034904</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KOBE STEEL LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TAKEDA CHEMICAL INDUSTRIES LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KABUSHIKI KAISHA KOBE SEIKO SHO</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TAKEDA CHEMICAL INDUSTRIES, LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kabushiki Kaisha Kobe Seiko Sho</last-name><address><street>3-18, Wakinohama-cho 1-Chome, Chuo-ku, Kobe-shi</street><city>Hyogo 651-0072</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TAKEDA CHEMICAL INDUSTRIES, Ltd.</last-name><address><street>1-1, Doshomachi 4-chome, Chuo-ku</street><city>Osaka-shi, Osaka-fu</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KASUYA FUMIHIKO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KODAMA KATSUHISA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KUMAKI TAKASHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MURAYAMA KOUICHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NAGASE YOSHIYUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>NAKATA MASAAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NISHIDA SATOSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KASUYA, FUMIHIKO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KODAMA, KATSUHISA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KUMAKI, TAKASHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MURAYAMA, KOUICHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NAGASE, YOSHIYUKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NAKATA, MASAAKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NISHIDA, SATOSHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KASUYA, FUMIHIKO</last-name><address><street>Osaka Branch Kobe Steel, Ltd., 4-1-3, Bingomachi</street><city>Chuo-ku, Osaka-shi, Osaka-fu</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KODAMA, KATSUHISA</last-name><address><street>Takeda Chem.Ind., Ltd., 17-85 Jusohonmachi 2-chome</street><city>Yodogawa-ku, Osaka-shi, Osaka-fu</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KUMAKI, TAKASHI</last-name><address><street>Takeda Chem.Ind., Ltd., 17-85 Jusohonmachi 2-chome</street><city>Yodogawa-ku, Osaka-shi, Osaka-fu</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MURAYAMA, KOUICHI</last-name><address><street>Takeda Chem.Ind., Ltd., 17-85 Jusohonmachi 2-chome</street><city>Yodogawa-ku, Osaka-shi, Osaka-fu</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Nagase, Yoshiyuki, Kobe Corp. Res. Lab.</last-name><address><street>Kobe Steel, Ltd., 5-5, Takatsukadai 1-chome</street><city>Nishi-ku, Kobe-shi, Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NAKATA, MASAAKI</last-name><address><street>Osaka Branch Kobe Steel, Ltd., 4-1-3, Bingomachi</street><city>Chuo-ku, Osaka-shi, Osaka-fu</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NISHIDA, SATOSHI</last-name><address><street>Osaka Branch Kobe Steel, Ltd., 4-1-3, Bingomachi</street><city>Chuo-ku, Osaka-shi, Osaka-fu</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Müller-Boré &amp;amp; Partner Patentanwälte</last-name><address><street>Grafinger Strasse 2</street><city>81671 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country> <country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country> <country>PT</country> <country>SE</country> </ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Disclosed is an apparatus for decomposing a polyurethane
resin and recovering the decomposed polyurethane resin as a
polyamine compound and a polyol compound, said apparatus
including: a fluidizer that fluidizes the polyurethane resin as a
target compound of hydrolysis decomposition; a reactor that
hydrolyzes the fluidized target compound of decomposition with
either one of supercritical water and high-temperature high-pressure
water to a decomposition product mixture; a water
supplier that feeds either one of supercritical water and high-temperature
high-pressure water to the reactor; and a post-processor
that causes the decomposition product mixture
discharged from the reactor to be subjected to a post treatment
procedure, such as dehydration, addition, distillation, separation,
and liquid separation to recover the polyamine compound and/or
the polyol compound.</p><p>According to the present invention, there can be provided
an apparatus of decomposition and recovery that continuously
decomposes and recovers polyurethane resin with high-temperature
high-pressure water or supercritical water, which
advantageously reduces the required energy cost, reduces the size of
the whole apparatus, removes foreign substances from the
shredder dust, and decreases the required quantities of substances
for decomposition.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="54"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to an industrially
advantageous apparatus that chemically decomposes cut piece
wastes of polyurethane resin in the molding and working process
and product wastes thereof after their use, and recovers the
decomposed polyurethane resin as a polyamine compound and/or a
polyol compound that are the materials of the polyurethane resin.</p><p num="0002">Polyurethane resin is massively used in the form of soft,
semi-rigid, and rigid urethane foams in a variety of fields as the
cushioning materials, for example, for sofas, beds, other furniture,
and seats in vehicles and the thermal insulating materials, for
example, for the refrigerators. The polyurethane resin is also
used in the form of elastomers, for example, for shoe bottoms, tires,
and belts. As the greater importance is placed on protection of
the resources and preservation of the environment, a variety of
techniques have been proposed and studied to attain the recycle
and the reuse of various plastics including polyurethane resin.</p><p num="0003">Known recycling procedures of polyurethane resin are
roughly classified into three; that is, the material recycling
technique, the chemical recycling technique, and the energy 
recycling technique. One example of the material recycling
technique reclaims the used polyurethane foams as the cushioning
materials by means of re-bonding or compression molding.
Another example crushes the used polyurethane foams and
elastomers and mixes the crushed resin as a filler with a new
material. The chemical recycling technique decomposes the
polyurethane resin to its raw materials or to compounds which can be
used as the raw materials, and reuses the raw materials and the
compounds. The chemical recycling may be attained, for example,
through glycol decomposition, amine decomposition, or hydrolysis.
The energy recycling technique utilizes the used polyurethane
resin directly as a fuel or as an energy resource to give steam or a
gaseous fuel.</p><p num="0004">The material recycling technique, however, possibly causes
problems of the poor quality of resulting products and thus limits
the range of application. The energy recycling technique possibly
leads to environmental problems, such as generation of harmful
substances through the combustion. The chemical recycling
technique is, on the other hand, applicable to a wide variety of
compounds to be recovered. By taking into account these merits
and demerits, it has highly been demanded to develop an improved
apparatus to attain the chemical recycling technique economically
on the industrial base.</p><p num="0005">The glycol decomposition process or the amine
decomposition process applied for the chemical recycling technique 
cuts the urethane bond, the biuret bond, the allophanate bond,
which are relatively easily decomposable among all the bonds,
such as the urethane bond, the urea bond, the biuret bond, and the
allophanate bond, that are present in the polyurethane resin, by
means of the glycol compound or the amine compound, thereby
decomposing the polyurethane resin to low molecular-weight
substances and generating a liquid decomposition product. The
glycol compound or the amine compound used as the decomposer,
however, newly generates urethane bonds and urea bonds and is
linked to the decomposition product by these bond. Such
decomposition processes can thus not decompose the polyurethane
resin to a polyol compound as a starting material of the
polyurethane resin, and a polyamine as an intermediate compound
of polyisocyanate. The recovered substances are accordingly
usable for only the limited applications.</p><p num="0006">The applicant of the present invention has proposed a
method of hydrolyzing polyurethane resin using high-temperature
high-pressure liquid water as the decomposer (WO98/34909).
This proposed technique heats polyurethane foam to decrease its
volume and supplies the solid polyurethane foam of the reduced
volume to hydrolysis means. A further improvement in material
supply means is required to provide an efficient continuous flow
apparatus for carrying out the hydrolysis of polyurethane resin on
the industrial base. Problems of contaminating the reaction
passage with foreign matters and blocking the reaction passage 
may arise, for example, in the process of recycling shredder dust of
the seats in the vehicles, which is generally a mixture of fibers and
resin.</p><p num="0007">An object of the present invention is thus to provide an
apparatus of decomposition and recovery that continuously
decomposes and recovers polyurethane resin with high-temperature
high-pressure water or supercritical water, which
advantageously reduces the required energy cost, reduces the size
of the whole apparatus, removes foreign substances from the
shredder dust, and decreases the required quantities of substances
for decomposition, and the like.</p><p num="0008">At least part of the above and the other related objects is
realized by an apparatus for decomposing a polyurethane resin and
recovering the decomposed polyurethane resin as a polyamine
compound and/or a polyol compound. The apparatus includes: a
fluidizer that fluidizes the polyurethane resin as a target
compound of hydrolysis decomposition; a reactor that hydrolyzes
the fluidized target compound with either one of supercritical
water and high-temperature high-pressure water to a
decomposition product mixture; a water supplier that feeds of
either one of supercritical water and high-temperature high-pressure
water to the reactor; and a post-processor that causes the
decomposition product mixture discharged from the reactor to be 
subjected to a post process, such as dehydration, addition,
distillation, separation, and liquid separation, to recover the
polyamine compound and/or the polyol compound.</p><p num="0009">The apparatus of the present invention fluidizes
polyurethane resin and feeds the fluidized polyurethane resin to
the reactor. This arrangement enables continuous decomposition.
Compared with the prior art apparatus that hydrolyzes solid
polyurethane resin in a reactor, this arrangement relieves the
conditions of the hydrolysis. This advantageously decreases the
water addition ratio and reduces the reaction time, thereby
reducing the volume of the reactor, lowering the required level of
the performance of the water supply unit, and eventually reducing
the recycling cost.</p><p num="0010">These and other objects, features, aspects, and advantages
of the present invention will become more apparent from the
following detailed description of the preferred embodiments / examples
with the accompanying drawings.
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is a diagram showing an apparatus for decomposition
and recovery in one embodiment according to the present
invention;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a diagram showing another apparatus for
decomposition and recovery in another embodiment according to
the present invention; and </li><li>Fig. 3 is a diagram showing stilt another apparatus for
decomposition and recovery in still another embodiment according
to the present invention.</li></sl></p><p num="0011">The apparatus of the present invention includes: a fluidizer
that fluidizes the polyurethane resin as a target compound of
hydrolysis decomposition; a reactor that hydrolyzes the fluidized
target compound with either one of supercritical water and high-temperature
high-pressure water to a decomposition product
mixture; a water supplier that feeds either one of supercritical
water and high-temperature high-pressure water to the reactor;
and a post-processor that causes the decomposition product
mixture discharged from the reactor to be subjected to a post
process, such as dehydration, addition, distillation, separation,
and liquid separation, and recovers the polyamine compound
and/or the polyol compound.</p><p num="0012">In accordance with one preferable application, the fluidizer
includes a decomposition tank, in which combining a polyamine
compound and the polyurethane resin causes aminolysis to thereby
decompose the polyurethane resin and to produce the resulting
fluidized target compound of hydrolysis decomposition. This
arrangement enables the polyurethane resin to be readily fluidized
by means of a polyamine compound and ensures the continuous
processing. The polyamine compound obtained by the hydrolysis 
of the polyurethane resin may be refluxed and used for the
fluidization process. This effectively saves the limited resources.
Instead of taking advantage of the aminolysis, the fluidization
process may use a medium like a polyol compound to make the
polyurethane resin slurry or use an adequate solvent to make the
polyurethane resin dissolved.</p><p num="0013">In accordance with another preferable application, the
apparatus further includes a filter disposed in a pathway between
the fluidizer and the reactor to continuously feed the fluidized
target compound of hydrolysis decomposition to the reactor. In
the event that the fluidized target compound contains some foreign
matters, the filter removes the foreign matters and effectively
prevents the foreign matters from causing troubles, such as
blocking, in the downstream portion of the apparatus including the
reactor.</p><p num="0014">In accordance with still another preferable application, the
apparatus further includes a reflux system that refluxes part of
the decomposition product mixture from an arbitrary position
downstream from the reactor with respect to the mixture feeding
direction to the fluidizer. The decomposition product mixture
includes a polyamine compound and a polyol compound, and is
refluxed to the fluidizer by the reflux system, so as to be used in
the aminolysis process or a medium of the process of making the
slurry.</p><p num="0015">In one preferable embodiment, the post-processor has a 
dehydrator that removes water from the decomposition product
mixture, and a separating/recovering unit that separately recovers
the polyamine compound and the polyol compound from the
dehydrated decomposition product mixture. The dehydrator
disposed before the separating/recovering unit favorably assures
the size reduction of the separating/recovering unit.</p><p num="0016">In the above structure, the reflux system may be disposed
between the dehydrator and the separating/recovering unit. The
liquid decomposition product mixture after the dehydration or
removal of water non-required for the fluidization is refluxed to
the fluidizer. This configuration enables only the decomposition
product mixture required for the fluidization to be fed to the
fluidizer, thereby assuring the size reduction of the whole
apparatus and enabling the fluidization with a high efficiency.</p><p num="0017">In the above structure, it is preferable that the post-processor
further includes a rough separation unit disposed
between the dehydrator and the separating/recovering unit to
roughly divide the dehydrated decomposition product mixture into
a first portion mainly composed of the polyamine compound and a
second portion mainly composed of the polyol compound. The
reflux system refluxes the first portion mainly composed of the
polyamine compound. This arrangement causes the polyamine
compound required for the fluidization to be roughly separated and
refluxed to the fluidizer. This also assures the size reduction of
the whole apparatus and enables the fluidization with a high 
efficiency.</p><p num="0018">In the above configuration, the reflux system refluxes the
second portion mainly composed of the polyol compound, instead of
the first portion mainly composed of the polyamine compound.
This arrangement is useful when the fluidizer adopts the process
of making the slurry.</p><p num="0019">In accordance with one preferable embodiment of the above
structure, the reflux system refluxes the polyamine compound
separately recovered by the separating/recovering unit. This
arrangement enables the polyamine compound of the higher purity
to be refluxed to the fluidizer for the aminolysis with a higher
efficiency, thereby enabling further size reduction of the whole
apparatus.</p><p num="0020">In accordance with another preferable embodiment of the
above structure, the reflux system refluxes the polyol compound
separately recovered by the separating/recovering unit. This
arrangement enables the polyol compound of the higher purity to
be refluxed to the fluidizer to make the slurry with a higher
efficiency.</p><p num="0021">In accordance with still another preferable embodiment of
the above structure, it is preferable that the apparatus further
includes a water reflux system that refluxes water discharged from
the dehydrator to the water supplier. This arrangement enables
water indispensable for the hydrolysis to be recycled and thereby
decreases the quantity of exhaust discharged out of the apparatus. </p><p num="0022">In accordance with still another preferable embodiment of
the above structure, the fluidizer includes: a decomposition tank,
in which combining a polyamine compound and the polyurethane
resin causes aminolysis to thereby decompose the polyurethane
resin and to produce the resulting fluidized product; and an
intermediate separation tank that separates the fluidized product
into a target compound of hydrolysis decomposition and a non-hydrolysis
compound. The apparatus further may have a feeder
that feeds the non-hydrolysis compound discharged from the
intermediate separation tank to the separating/recovering unit.
As the result of aminolysis in the fluidizer, the fluidized product
includes an urea bond-containing compound and a polyol compound.
The polyol compound is, however, a target of recovery and does not
require any hydrolysis. The arrangement of bypassing the
reactor and passing the polyol compound directly to the
separating/recovering unit favorably reduces the size of the
reactor and the post-processor.</p><p num="0023">The apparatus for decomposition and recovery according to
the present invention hydrolyzes polyurethane resin to useful
substances for recycling. The polyurethane resin, which is the
object to be decomposed, is obtained in the form of cut piece wastes
and defectives in the molding and working process of the
polyurethane resin products, as well as in the form of article
wastes after the use in a variety of fields. The polyurethane resin
includes foams, such as flexible urethane foam, semi-rigid 
urethane foam, and rigid urethane foam, elastomers (cast, kneaded,
and thermoplastic elastomers), RIM products, and ISF (integral-skin
foams). The apparatus of the present invention can
decompose any of these polyurethane resins. The apparatus can
also decompose shredder dust without any problems since foreign
matters included in the fluidized shredder dust are filtered out by
the filter.</p><p num="0024">The apparatus of the present invention decomposes the
polyurethane resin to a polyol compound and a polyamine
compound, which are the raw materials of the polyurethane resin.
The polyol compound and the polyamine compound are then
recycled and reused as the raw materials for producing the
polyurethane resin.</p><p num="0025">The apparatus for decomposition and recovery according to
the present invention is described more in detail with referring to
the drawings.</p><p num="0026">Fig. 1 schematically illustrates an apparatus for
decomposition and recovery in one embodiment according to the
present invention. The apparatus includes a fluidizer 1, a
supplier 2 for feeding a fluidized target compound of hydrolysis
decomposition to a reactor 3, the reactor 3 for causing the fluidized
target compound of decomposition to be brought into contact with
supercritical water or high-temperature high-pressure water for
hydrolysis, a water supplier 4 for feeding a supercritical water or
high-temperature high-pressure water to the reactor 3, a post-processor 
5, a reflux system 6, an introduction unit 10 for
introducing polyurethane resin into the fluidizer 1, and a pressure
control valve 31.</p><p num="0027">The polyurethane resin is fed from the introduction unit 10
to the fluidizer 1 by a batch process or by a flow process. The
introduction unit 10 may be a hopper or a reservoir. In the event
that the polyurethane resin to be decomposed is not sufficiently
small pieces like shredder dust, it is preferable to cut the
polyurethane resin into sufficiently small pieces with a milling
machine, such as a cutter mill, a roll mill, or a hammer mill, before
the polyurethane resin is stored in the introduction unit 10. A
powder feeder like a rotary feeder or a belt feeder may be used to
pass the small pieces of polyurethane resin to the introduction
unit 10.</p><p num="0028">The fluidizer 1 fluidizes the polyurethane resin. There are
mainly three processes applicable for the fluidization. The first
process causes the polyurethane resin to react with a polyamine
compound and decomposes the polyurethane resin to a polyol
compound and a urea bond-containing compound through the
aminolysis. The second process uses a polyol compound or
another liquid medium and physically stirs the polyurethane resin
to a slurry. The third process dissolves the polyurethane resin in
a solvent having ability to dissolve the polyurethane resin.</p><p num="0029">The fluidizer 1 corresponding to one of these three processes
includes a vessel for decomposing, making a slurry, or dissolving 
and an agitating mechanism. Concrete examples of the fluidizer 1
include a tank reactor with an agitator, a horizontal reactor, a
vessel rotating mixer such as a V-shaped rotating mixer or a
conical mixer, and mechanical agitation blenders with ribbon-shaped
or cone-shaped screws. In the case of continuous
decomposition and recovery process, vessel rotating mixers,
mechanical agitation blenders, and a horizontal reactor are
preferably used. For example, a horizontal reactor for agitating a
high viscous substance described in JAPANESE PATENT LAID-OPEN
GAZETTE No. 10-342 enables fluidization with a high
efficiency.</p><p num="0030">Among the three applicable processes for fluidization
described above, the aminolysis is the most favorable method.
The aminolysis gives a polyol compound, which is a target of
recovery, prior to the hydrolysis process. The configuration of
passing the polyol compound obtained by the aminolysis to the
post-processor 5 enables size reduction of the units after the
reactor in the apparatus. The polyamine compound produced by
the hydrolysis process may be used for the aminolysis. This saves
the limited resources. The presence of a little amount of a polyol
compound decreases the viscosity of the reaction mixture in the
fluidizer. This enables the reaction to proceed homogeneously.
When the aminolysis is applied for the fluidization process, the
vessel of the fluidizer 1 is a decomposition tank.</p><p num="0031">The polyamine compound, which is the raw material of the 
polyurethane resin, may be used for the aminolysis. Typical
examples of the polyamine compound include tolylenediamine
(TDA), diaminodiphenylmethane, polymethylpolyphenyl polyamine.
The aminolysis is generally carried out at temperatures of 120 to
220°C.</p><p num="0032">The target compound of hydrolysis decomposition fluidized
by the fluidizer 1 is fed into the reactor 3 by means of the supplier
2, such as a pump or a screw extruder. A filter may be disposed
integrally with the fluidizer 1 or in the vicinity of an exit of the
fluidizer 1. When the polyurethane resin to be decomposed
includes foreign matters like shredder dust, it is preferable to
remove the foreign matters before passing the fluidized target
compound to the reactor 3, in order to prevent possible troubles
like blocking. The filter may be arranged at any arbitrary
position between the fluidizer 1 and the reactor 3. Examples of
the filter include a filter, a disc filter, and a centrifuge.</p><p num="0033">The hydrolysis is performed in the reactor 3. In the case
where the target compound of hydrolysis decomposition fluidized
through the aminolysis is fed into the reactor 3, the hydrolysis
reaction mainly hydrolyzes the urea bond included in the urea
bond-containing compound. In the case where the fluidizer 1
adopts the process other than the aminolysis, on the other hand,
the hydrolysis reaction hydrolyzes a variety of bonds included in
the polyurethane resin.</p><p num="0034">Either supercritical water or high-temperature high-pressure 
water is required for the hydrolysis. The reactor 3 used
should maintain water in the supercritical state or in the high-temperature
high-pressure state. The water supplier 4 feeds
water kept in the supercritical state or in the high-temperature
high-pressure state to the reactor 3. The respective states of
water are described below. In the embodiment shown in Fig. 1,
the water supplier 4 comprises a water tank 41, a pump 42, and a
heater 43. A heat exchanger may be used for the heater and heats
water by taking advantage of a hot medium discharged after the
separating/recovering process or a hot medium heated in another
heater.</p><p num="0035">In another possible configuration, only the pump 42 may use
as the water supplier 4 and pressurized water is introduced into a
reactor with a heater by means of the pump 42. In still another
possible configuration, water is introduced into a reactor with a
heater and subsequently pressurized by decreasing the volume of
the reactor kept in a sealed state by means of a cylinder.</p><p num="0036">The hydrolysis is carried out at temperatures of 200 to
400°C in a specific pressure range of 3 to 30 MPa, in which water is
kept in the liquid state in this temperature range. The water is
preferably supplied to the reactor 3 at a temperature and pressure
sufficient to ensure that the hydrolysis is carried out in the
reactor 3 in the above temperature range and pressure without a
heating of the reactor. Water at the temperature of 374°C or
more under 22.1 MPa or more is referred to as supercritical water. 
Water at the temperature in the range of 200-400°C under the
pressure in the range of 3-30 MPa other than the region of
supercritical water is referred to as high-temperature high-pressure
water. It is preferable to regulate the amount of water
in such a manner that the fluidized target compound of hydrolysis
decomposition and water are fed to the reactor at the ratio of 1:0.3
to 1:10.0(weight ratio, hereinafter referred to as the water
addition ratio). The more preferable water addition ratio (the
weight of water to the weight of hydrolysis target compound)
ranges from 1.0 to 5.0.</p><p num="0037">A decomposition product mixture discharged from the
reactor 3 is passed to the post-processor 5 via a passage with the
pressure control valve 31. In the embodiment shown in Fig. 1, the
post-processor 5 has a dehydrator 51, and a separating/recovering
unit 52. The dehydrator 51 is a simple distillation apparatus ,
and the separating/recovering unit 52 is a distillation column.
The decomposition product mixture contains water, carbon dioxide,
a polyol compound, and a polyamine compound. The dehydrator
51 removes water and carbon dioxide, and the
separating/recovering unit 52 separately recovers the polyol
compound and the polyamine compound. This completes the
separating recovery process of the polyurethane resin in the
apparatus of the present invention.</p><p num="0038">Examples of the dehydrator 51 include a simple distillation
apparatus, a flash vaporization apparatus like a flash drum, a 
vacuum distillation apparatus like a distillation column, an
adsorption apparatus like an adsorption column, and a dryer. In
the case of using the flash vaporization apparatus, the reactor 3
has a high internal pressure, so that only a pressure decreasing
operation, for example, an operation of passing the decomposition
product mixture to the atmospheric pressure in the flash
vaporization apparatus with the pressure control valve 31,
implements dehydration of the decomposition product mixture.</p><p num="0039">Examples of the separating/recovering unit 52 include a
simple distillation apparatus, a vacuum distillation apparatus like
a distillation column, a thin-film evaporator, and apparatuses for
degasification, extraction, centrifugation, filtration, squeeze, and
fractionation. The post-processor 5 may further include an
addition unit, such as a reactor for a chemical reaction, (a reactor
for adding alkylene oxide to the polyamine compound and
recovering a polyol compound) and a liquid separation unit, which
may be used alone or in combination with the dehydrator 51 and
the separating/recovering unit 52. The respective treatment may
be performed under reduced pressure or under pressure. Any of
the post-processor 5 may include a plurality of apparatuses and
units. In the case of using a distillation column as the
separating/recovering unit 52, the polyamine compound is
recovered as a light weight fraction from the top of the column,
while the polyol compound is recovered as a heavy weight fraction
from the bottom of the column. </p><p num="0040">In the embodiment shown in Fig. 1, the reflux system 6 is
disposed between the dehydrator 51 and the separating/recovering
unit 52 to reflux the dehydrated decomposition product mixture to
the fluidizer 1. The reflux system 6 is, for example, a reflux
conduit with a valve. The reflux system 6 is not necessarily
located between the dehydrator 51 and the separating/recovering
unit 52, but may be disposed at any arbitrary position downstream
from the reactor 3 with respect to the decomposition product
mixture feeding direction. In the case where the aminolysis is
applied for fluidization of the polyurethane resin, it is necessary
to contain the polyamine compound in the refluxed fluid, and the
reflux fluid may or may not contain water and the polyol compound.
In order to attain the high efficiency of aminolysis, however, it is
not desirable to dilute the reaction mixture excessively.
Refluxing the non-required medium in the apparatus makes the
whole apparatus undesirably bulky, so that the reflux system 6 is
preferably arranged downstream the dehydrator 51.</p><p num="0041">Fig. 2 illustrates another apparatus for decomposition and
recovery in another embodiment according to the present invention.
The same constituents as those in Fig. 1 are shown by the same
numerals. In this embodiment of Fig. 2, the post-processor 5 has
a rough separation unit 53, which is a centrifuge and is disposed
between the dehydrator 51 and the separating/recovering unit 52.
The rough separation unit 53 roughly divides the dehydrated
decomposition product mixture into a polyamine compound-rich 
first portion and a polyol compound-rich second portion. For the
reduced running cost of the whole apparatus, the rough separation
unit 53 preferably has a low energy cost and does not require
heating. Preferable examples of the rough separation unit 53
include a tubular or decanter-type centrifugal settling classifier, a
liquid cyclone, a film separator, and a tank for still standing
separation. Especially preferable is the technique of utilizing the
fact that the polyamine compound has a greater specific gravity
than the polyol compound for separation, that is, the centrifugal
settling classifier, the liquid cyclone, and the tank for still
standing separation. The polyamine compound-rich first portion
is discharged from the lower part of such rough separation unit 53.
In the event that a distillation column is used for the
separating/recovering unit 52, it is preferable to feed the
polyamine compound-rich first portion to an upper half of the
distillation column. This reduces the required size of the
distillation column and the energy cost.</p><p num="0042">In the embodiment shown in Fig. 2, a reflux system 61
refluxes the polyamine compound-rich first portion discharged
from the rough separation unit 53 to the fluidizer 1. Another
reflux system 62 may be disposed in place of or in addition to the
reflux system 61. The reflux system 62 refluxes part of the
polyamine compound discharged from the separating/recovering
unit 52 to the fluidizer 1. In the event that a distillation column
is used for the separating/recovering unit 52, the polyamine 
compound recovered from the top of the distillation column and the
polyamine compound-rich substance taken out of the upper half of
the distillation column may be refluxed through the reflux system
62.</p><p num="0043">Refluxing the polyamine compound purified by the
separating/recovering unit 52 with a certain energy cost to the
fluidizer 1 for the aminolysis wastes the energy. Refluxing the
polyamine compound of the higher purity is preferable, on the
other hand, in order to attain the high efficiency of the aminolysis.
Either one of or both of the reflux systems 61 and 62 may thus be
applied according to the requirements. Either of the reflux
systems 61 and 62 refluxes the polyamine compound-rich
substance obtained by the removal of water and the polyol
compound, which are not required for the aminolysis, with a low
energy cost. This arrangement favorably reduces the quantities
of water and the polyol compound from the reflux fluid, thereby
reducing the size of the whole apparatus and the running cost. In
the event that the process of making the slurry with the polyol
compound is applied for the fluidization, the reflux system 61 may
be disposed at an upper outlet of the rough separation unit 53 or
alternatively at the bottom of the separating/recovering unit 52, in
order to reflux the polyol compound-rich substance.</p><p num="0044">In the embodiment of Fig. 2, a water reflux system 7
includes a condenser 71 and a feeding device like a pump 72.
Water discharged from the dehydrator 51 is condensed by the 
condenser 71 and refluxed to a water tank 41 by the feeding pump
72. Water used for the hydrolysis may contain the polyamine
compound and the polyol compound, since water containing the
polyamine compound and the polyol compound dose not adversely
affect the hydrolysis. Recycling the water discharged from the
dehydrator 51 decreases the quantity of water discharged out of
the apparatus and thus advantageously reduces the consumption
of water.</p><p num="0045">Fig. 3 illustrates still another apparatus for decomposition
and recovery in still another embodiment according to the present
invention. In the embodiment of Fig. 3, the fluidizer 1 is a
decomposition tank 11 and an intermediate separation tank 12
that separates the fluidized product discharged from the
decomposition tank 11 into a target compound of hydrolysis
decomposition and a non-hydrolysis compound. In the case where
the aminolysis is applied for the fluidization process, the fluidized
product(the discharge from the decomposition tank 11) mainly
contains a polyol compound and an urea bond-containing compound.
The polyol compound is a target of recovery and does not require
the hydrolysis. The intermediate separation tank 12 separates
the polyol compound as the non-hydrolysis compound from the urea
bond-containing compound as the target compound of hydrolysis
decomposition. This arrangement advantageously reduces the
size of the whole apparatus including the reactor and the energy
cost. </p><p num="0046">The intermediate separation tank 12 may be a tubular or
decanter-type centrifugal settling classifier, a liquid cyclone, or a
tank for still standing separation, which are exemplified as the
rough separation unit 53, since the strict separation is not
required here. A filter may be disposed at an inlet of the
intermediate separation tank 12. The non-hydrolysis compound
discharged from the intermediate separation tank 12 is directly
fed to the separating/recovering unit 52 by a feeder 13 like a pump
for the separation and purification. The hydrolysis target
compound mainly composed of the urea bond-containing compound
is passed to the reactor 3 via the supplier 2.</p><p num="0047">The apparatus for decomposition and recovery according to
the present invention has been described with reference to Figs. 1
to 3. The apparatus of the present invention is, however, not
restricted to the configurations of these embodiments, but may be
modified without departing from the scope and the spirit of the
present invention.</p><p num="0048">The present invention is further described with some
examples.</p><heading>Examples 1 to 3</heading><p num="0049">A mixture of polypropylene triol ("Actcol 79-56"
manufactured by Takeda Chemical Industries, Ltd., molecular
weight 3000, hereinafter abbreviated to PPG) and tolylene
diisocyanate ("Takenate 80" manufactured by Takeda Chemical 
Industries, Ltd., hereinafter abbreviated to TDI) was polymerized
and foamed to a soft polyurethane foam. The soft polyurethane
foam thus obtained had the density of 25 kg/m<sup>3</sup>.</p><p num="0050">A decomposition and recovery experiment was carried out
for the soft polyurethane foam with the apparatus for
decomposition and recovery shown in Fig. 1. In the experiment,
the soft polyurethane foam was cut into small pieces, and the small
pieces of the foam were charged into a hopper (the introduction
unit 10), and introduced in a fixed quantity of the polyurethane foam
into a tank reactor with an agitator (the fluidizer 1). An equal-volume
solution mixture of tolylenediamine (TDA) and PPG (for
decreasing the viscosity of the reaction mixture) was added six
times by weight to the fixed quantity of the polyurethane foam and
stirred for one hour at 170°C. The polyurethane foam was then
completely liquefied and fluidized, the progress of the aminolysis
was conformed.</p><p num="0051">The fluidized product was then fed to the reactor 3 by means
of a pump (the supplier 2), while high-temperature high pressure
water, which was passed from the water tank 41, pressurized by
the pressure pump 42, and heated by the heater 43, was fed to the
reactor 3. The fluidized product was brought into contact with
the high-temperature high-pressure water in the reactor 3 for
hydrolysis. The conditions of the hydrolysis are shown in Table 1.
The water addition ratio denotes the weight ratio of the high-temperature
high-pressure water to the hydrolysis target 
compound included in the fluidized product.</p><p num="0052">The decomposition product after hydrolysis was discharged
from the reactor 3, and the pressure thereof was decreased to the
atmospheric pressure with the pressure control valve 31. The
product under the atmospheric pressure was passed to a simple
distillation column (the dehydrator 51), and removed water and
carbon dioxide. The dehydrated substance (TDA and the polyol)
was recovered from the bottom of the simple distillation column.
The experiment did not use a distillation column (the
separating/recovering unit 52) but determined the quantity of TDA
included in the recovered substance by gas chromatography. The
quantity of TDA recovered from the polyurethane foam was
calculated by subtracting the quantity of TDA used for the
fluidization from the quantity of TDA thus determined. The
recovery rate was calculated according to an equation given below.
The results of the calculation are shown in Table 1.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Recovery rate of TDA [%] = 100 x (recovered quantity of TDA
[mole] / quantity of TDI for synthesis of polyurethane foam [mole])</st32:df><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Temperature (°C)</entry><entry align="center">Pressure (MPa)</entry><entry align="center">Water addition ratio (wt/wt)</entry><entry align="center">Recovery rate of TDA (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex.1</entry><entry align="right">250</entry><entry align="right">12</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="right">90</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex.2</entry><entry align="right">250</entry><entry align="right">12</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="right">99</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex.3</entry><entry align="right">250</entry><entry align="right">12</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="right">98</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0053">A decomposition and recovery experiment was carried out
for the polyurethane foam produced in Example 1 with the
apparatus used in Example 1. In the experiment, the soft
polyurethane foam was cut into small pieces, and the small pieces
of the foam were charged into a hopper (the introduction unit 10),
and introduced in a fixed quantity of the polyurethane foam into a
tank reactor with an agitator (the fluidizer 1). The decomposed
and recovered substance obtained in Example 2 was added ten
times by weight to the fixed quantity of the polyurethane foam and
stirred for one hour at 170°C. The polyurethane foam was then
completely liquefied and fluidized, the progress of the aminolysis
was conformed.</p><p num="0054">The fluidized product was hydrolyzed in the same manner as
Example 1, except two conditions shown in Table 2 were applied for
the hydrolysis. The decomposed and recovered substance was
obtained through the dehydration (simple distillation) process.
The recovery rate of TDA [%] is shown in Table 2.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Temperature (°C)</entry><entry align="center">Pressure (MPa)</entry><entry align="center">Water addition ratio (wt/wt)</entry><entry align="center">Recovery rate of TDA (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">250</entry><entry align="right">12</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="right">97</entry></row><row><entry align="right">270</entry><entry align="right">15</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="right">99</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="0055">A decomposition and recovery experiment was carried out
for the polyurethane foam produced in Example 1 with the
apparatus used in Example 1. In the experiment, the soft
polyurethane foam was cut into small pieces, and the small pieces
of the foam were charged into a hopper (the introduction unit 10),
and were introduced in a fixed quantity of the polyurethane foam into
a tank reactor with an agitator (the fluidizer 1). TDA was then
added three times by weight to the fixed quantity of the
polyurethane foam and stirred for one hour at 180°C for the
aminolysis.</p><p num="0056">The fluidized product was hydrolyzed in the same manner as
Example 1, except conditions shown in Table 3 were applied for the
hydrolysis. The decomposed and recovered substance was
obtained through the dehydration (simple distillation) process.
The recovery rate of TDA [%] is shown in Table 3.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Temperature (°C)</entry><entry align="center">Pressure (MPa)</entry><entry align="center">Water addition ratio (wt/wt)</entry><entry align="center">Recovery rate of TDA (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">260</entry><entry align="right">16</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="right">99</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 6</heading><p num="0057">A decomposition and recovery experiment was carried out
for the polyurethane foam produced in Example 1 with the 
apparatus used in Example 1. In the experiment, the soft
polyurethane foam was cut into small pieces, and the small pieces
of the foam were charged into a hopper (the introduction unit 10),
and were introduced in a fixed quantity of the polyurethane foam into
a tank reactor with an agitator (the fluidizer 1). The decomposed
and recovered substance after the dehydration process obtained in
Example 5 was further subjected to simple distillation under the
conditions of 15 Torr (2000 Pa) and 160°C. The resulting liquid
substance having the TDA concentration of 95% was recovered and
added four times by weight of the fixed quantity of the
polyurethane foam in the reactor and stirred for one hour at 180°C
for the aminolysis.</p><p num="0058">The fluidized product was hydrolyzed in the same manner as
Example 1, except conditions shown in Table 4 were applied for the
hydrolysis. The decomposed and recovered substance was
obtained through the simple distillation process. The recovery
rate of TDA [%] is shown in Table 4.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Temperature (°C)</entry><entry align="center">Pressure (MPa)</entry><entry align="center">Water addition ratio (wt/wt)</entry><entry align="center">Recovery rate of TDA (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">260</entry><entry align="right">16</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="right">98</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 7</heading><p num="0059">A decomposition and recovery experiment was carried out 
for the polyurethane foam produced in Example 1 with the
apparatus used in Example 1. In the experiment, the soft
polyurethane foam was cut into small pieces, and the small pieces
of the foam were charged into a hopper (the introduction unit 10),
and were introduced in a fixed quantity of the polyurethane foam into
a tank reactor with an agitator (the fluidizer 1). The decomposed
and recovered substance after the dehydration process obtained in
Example 5 was further subjected to simple distillation under the
conditions of 15 Torr (2000 Pa) and 160°C for recovery of
polypropylene glycol. The polypropylene glycol was added to the
polyurethane foam in the reactor and mechanically stirred to make
the polyurethane foam slurry. The slurry was hydrolyzed in the
same manner as Example 1, except conditions shown in Table 5
were applied for the hydrolysis. The decomposed and recovered
substance was obtained through the simple distillation process.
The recovery rate of TDA [%] is shown in Table 5.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Temperature (°C)</entry><entry align="center">Pressure (MPa)</entry><entry align="center">Water addition ratio (wt/wt)</entry><entry align="center">Recovery rate of TDA (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">280</entry><entry align="right">20</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="right">98</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0060">As described above, the apparatus for decomposition and
recovery according to the present invention decomposes
polyurethane resin and recovers the decomposed polyurethane as a 
polyamine compound or a polyol compound, which are the raw
materials of the polyurethane resin. The polyurethane resin is
fluidized before being subjected to hydrolysis. This configuration
enables the continuous processing and facilitates the removal of
foreign matters. Compared with the prior art apparatus that
hydrolyzes solid polyurethane resin in a reactor, this arrangement
advantageously decreases the water addition ratio and reduces the
reaction time, thereby reducing the volume of the reactor, lowering
the required level of the performance of the water supplier, and
eventually reducing the recycling cost.</p><p num="0061">Application of the aminolysis for the fluidization process
enables part of polyamine compound produced through the
hydrolysis to be recycled. Separation of the polyol produced
through the aminolysis prior to the hydrolysis process ensures the
size reduction of the whole apparatus and favorably decreases the
running cost.</p><p num="0062">The present invention is not restricted to the above
embodiments/examples or their modifications, but there may be
many other modifications, changes, and alterations without
departing from the scope or spirit of the main characteristics of
the present invention.</p><p num="0063">The scope and spirit of the present invention are limited
only by the terms of the appended claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An apparatus for decomposing a polyurethane resin and
recovering the decomposed polyurethane resin as a polyamine
compound and/or a polyol compound, said apparatus comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a fluidizer that fluidizes the polyurethane resin as a target
compound of hydrolysis decomposition;</claim-text><claim-text>a reactor that hydrolyzes the fluidized target compound of
decomposition with either one of supercritical water and high-temperature
high-pressure water to a decomposition product
mixture;</claim-text><claim-text>a water supplier that feeds either one of supercritical water
and high-temperature high-pressure water to said reactor; and</claim-text><claim-text>a post-processor that causes the decomposition product
mixture discharged from said reactor to be subjected to a post
treatment procedure, such as dehydration, addition, distillation,
separation, and liquid separation to recover the polyamine
compound and/or the polyol compound.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 1, wherein said fluidizer
comprises a decomposition tank, in which combining a polyamine
compound and the polyurethane resin causes aminolysis to thereby
decompose the polyurethane resin and to produce the resulting
fluidized target compound of hydrolysis decomposition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 1 or 2, further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a filter disposed in a pathway between the fluidizer and the
reactor to continuously feed the fluidized target compound to said
reactor.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>An apparatus according to one or more of claims 1 to 3, further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a reflux system that refluxes part of the decomposition
product mixture from a position downstream from said reactor
with respect to the mixture feeding direction to said fluidizer.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An apparatus according to one or more of claims 1 to 4, wherein
said post-processor comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a dehydrator that removes water from the decomposition
product mixture; and</claim-text><claim-text>a separating/recovering unit that separately recovers the
polyamine compound and the polyol compound from the dehydrated
decomposition product mixture.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 5 further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a water reflux system that refluxes water discharged from
said dehydrator to said water supplier.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 5 or 6, wherein said reflux
system is disposed between said dehydrator and said
separating/recovering unit.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 5, 6 or 7, wherein said post-processor
further comprises a rough separation unit disposed
between said dehydrator and said separating/recovering unit to
roughly divide the dehydrated decomposition product mixture into
a first portion mainly composed of the polyamine compound and a
second portion mainly composed of the polyol compound, and
   said reflux system refluxes the first portion mainly
composed of the polyamine compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 5, 6 or 7, wherein said post-processor
further comprises a rough separation unit that is
disposed between said dehydrator and said separating/recovering
unit to roughly divide the dehydrated decomposition product
mixture into a first portion mainly composed of the polyamine
compound and a second portion mainly composed of the polyol
compound, and
   said reflux system refluxes the second portion mainly
composed of the polyol compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 5, wherein said reflux
system refluxes the polyamine compound recovered by said
separating/recovering unit.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>An apparatus according to claim 5, wherein said reflux
system refluxes the polyol compound recovered by said
separating/recovering unit.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>An apparatus according to one or more of claims 5 to 11,
wherein said fluidizer comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a decomposition tank, in which combining a polyamine
compound and the polyurethane resin causes aminolysis to thereby
decompose the polyurethane resin and to produce the resulting
fluidized product; and</claim-text><claim-text>an intermediate separation tank that separates the
fluidized product into a target compound of hydrolysis
decomposition and a non-hydrolysis compound,
said apparatus further comprising:</claim-text><claim-text>a feeder that feeds the non-hydrolysis compound
discharged from said intermediate separation tank to said
separating/recovering unit.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure num="1"><img id="img-00340001" orientation="unknown" wi="158" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00340001.tif" inline="no" he="245"/></figure><figure num="2"><img id="img-00350001" orientation="unknown" wi="137" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00350001.tif" inline="no" he="118"/></figure></drawings><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="154" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="238" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="235" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>