<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1443032-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1443032" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="32605247" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040804"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1443032-A1" status="new" fvid="24128391"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1443032</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040804</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03001757-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03001757</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030128</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-03001757-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03001757</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030128</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22F   3/12        20060101AFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22F   3/12        20060101CFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23B  27/14        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23B  27/14        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23P  15/28        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23P  15/28        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/10        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/10        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/111       20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/117       20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/565       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/565       20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/577       20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/63        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/634       20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/64        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/64        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/645       20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/645       20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/81        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/81        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B23B  27/14C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  35/117</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  35/634B6+C/634D14</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  35/64</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  35/645</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:32D2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:32G4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:38D18</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:38D18+C/117+M/32D2+M/32G4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:52F+M/38D18</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:660F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:77</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:78G</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:78K</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:96</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:96D4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M04B235:96D6B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="IDT">B23B27/14C</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Werkzeugeinsatz und zugehöriges Herstellungsverfahren</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Cutting tool insert and method for producing the same</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Plaquette pour outil de coupe et procédé pour fabriquer la même</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-4543345-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4543345</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5348694-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5348694</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>CHOA, YONG-HO ET AL.:  "Microstructure and Mechanical Properties of Oxide Based Nanocomposites Fabricated by Spark Plasma Sintering" KEY ENGINEERING MATERIALS, vol. 132-136, 1997, pages 2009-2012, XP009012462</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>OH, SUNG-TAG ET AL.:  "Porous Alumina and Alumina-Based Nanocomposite facbricated by Pulse Current Sintering " CERAMIC TRANSACTIONS , CERAMIC PROCESSING SCIENCE VI, vol. 112, 2001, pages 565-570, XP001153008</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>RONGTI LI ET AL.:  "Microstructure and Mechanical Properties of Al2O3/SiC Nanocomposites Prepared by SPS" KEY ENGINEERING MATERIALS, vol. 224-226, 2002, pages 337-340, XP009012468</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SANDVIK AB</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SANDVIK AB</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Sandvik AB</last-name><address><street/><city>811 81 Sandviken</city><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BRANDT GUNNAR DR</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BRANDT, GUNNAR, DR.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BRANDT, GUNNAR, DR.</last-name><address><street>Skogsvagen 3</street><city>170 63 Solna</city><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Weber, Dieter, Dr.</last-name><address><street>Weber, Seiffert, Lieke Postfach 61 45</street><city>65051 Wiesbaden</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>CH</country><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>LI</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An improved cutting tool insert and a method for the preparation of such cutting tool insert, having
a sintered alumina and silicon carbide whisker composite material body, comprising the steps of
milling and mixing the powdered starting materials of said composite material and forming said
material into a preformed workpiece, heating up said workpiece at a heating rate of 20 to 60 °C
per minute to a sintering temperature of between 1600 to 2300 °C, and holding at said sintering
temperature for a holding time of 5 to 60 minutes at a pressure of between 20 to 100 MPa.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a cutting tool insert of an improved ceramic material, and a
method for preparing the same.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Background of the invention</u></b></heading><p num="0002">Ceramic materials for cutting tool applications include alumina, alumina-zirconia, alumina-TiC-TiN,
silicon nitride, sialon, and SiC-whisker reinforced alumina. The cutting tool environment puts
simultaneous high demands on the strength, toughness and thermal shock resistance in addition
to the obvious demands for high wear resistance.</p><p num="0003">The mechanical properties of ceramic materials are to a high extent influenced by internal and
external defects, such as inclusions of foreign matter, pores, large grains and cracks. In order to
improve reliability and performance of cutting tools made of ceramic materials, it is necessary to
identify detrimental defects in the products and to set up the processing route in order to minimize
undesirable features. Since ceramic materials have a completely elastic behaviour up to
temperatures of about 1000°C, the stress concentrations created by the defects cannot be
eliminated by relaxation due to plastic deformation. </p><p num="0004">Ceramic materials for metal cutting tools are produced by milling of the constituents in a liquid
and subsequent drying of the slurry. Spray drying is the preferred drying method for materials that
do not require hot pressing. Spray drying produces granules with a size of 50-200 microns. The
large granules give very good powder flow properties, which is essential for mass production of
blanks with uniaxial cold pressing.</p><p num="0005">It is now well-established that defects in a sintered body can be related to the pore size and
distribution in the green compact. This is especially important for materials that are sintered
without pressure or with low pressure (gas pressure sintering), since large pores will not be
eliminated. The granule characteristics, and especially their deformation behaviour, will be the
primary parameters that determine the defect structure in the green state. Considerable increases
in strength of the sintered material have been achieved by reducing the granule compression
strength, since dense and hard granules will retain their shape even after compression.</p><p num="0006">Besides pore size and pore distribution, also the grain size is essential to the mechanical
properties of ceramic materials. A fine and uniform grain size provides for a high strength and a
small variation of the strength. The grain size of ceramic materials is closely related to the
sintering conditions.</p><p num="0007">Alumina and alumina-zirconia materials are preferably produced by pressureless sintering in an
appropriate atmosphere. In many cases, this is the preferred sintering technique for ceramic
materials, since it is a relatively low-cost process and enables complex shaped parts to be
produced.</p><p num="0008">Silicon nitride and sialon materials are normally produced by gas pressure sintering, whereby a
gas pressure of about 0.1-1 MPa is applied, once closed porosity is reached in the material. This
enables higher densities to be reached at lower sintering temperatures, especially when using
low amounts of sintering additives to form a liquid phase.</p><p num="0009">Hot isostatic pressing (HIP) is another sintering technique that is used for materials that cannot
be consolidated without external pressure. Pressures of 1-10 MPa are normally used, but the
method demands an encapsulation, for example in glass, to transmit the gas pressure. HIP can
also be used to remove remaining porosity after conventional sintering or hot pressing to closed
porosity, the advantages being that HIP, due to the high pressure, is performed at a lower
temperature than the sintering temperature, why a more fine grained material is obtained.</p><p num="0010">Hot pressing (HP) is the preferred method for materials difficult to be sintered, like silicon whisker
reinforced alumina, and also for mixed ceramics, like alumina-TiC. The pressure of normally 25-35
MPa is uniaxially transferred to the material with graphite punches. Rather large cylindrical 
discs are obtained, which are then diamond saw cut to the required dimensions of the blanks.
The diamond saw cutting is a rather expensive part of the blank production process, amounting to
about 30 to 40% of the production costs per blank.</p><p num="0011">US patent 4 543 345 describes a method for the production of silicon carbide whisker reinforced
alumina with 5-60% by volume SiC-whiskers to a sintered density of greater than 99%. The
process requires a pressure of 28-70 MPa, a temperature of 1600-1900°C, and a hold time at
sintering temperature of 45 min to 2 hours. Pressures and sintering temperatures in the higher
range are needed for higher whisker loadings. The combination of long sintering times and high
sintering temperatures in this hot pressing sintering method leads to alumina grain growth in spite
of the grain growth inhibiting effect of the silicon carbide whiskers. Large alumina grains will affect
the performance in cutting tool applications, since the largest defect determines the strength of
the material.</p><p num="0012">Another method, spark plasma sintering (SPS), applies electrical energy pulses directly to the
gaps between the powder particles, which are placed between graphite punches. SPS utilises the
energy of the spark plasma generated by the spark discharges. The pressure is directly applied
on the powder bed in an uniaxial direction.</p><p num="0013">Another method uses a particulate solid as the pressure-transmitting medium, which is why such
method is referred to as "pseudo-isostatic". Such method can be used to consolidate preforms of
more complicated shape.</p><p num="0014">US patent 5 348 694 describes a sintering method, wherein the preformed green blank is heated
by electrical resistive heating of a granular pressure-transmitting medium, which is in contact with
the preform inside a die chamber. The pressure-transmitting medium is electrically conductive,
e.g. graphitic carbon granules. This electrical resistive heating method enables very high
temperatures and rapid heating times, making it suitable for materials that require high sintering
temperatures. The pressure that can be applied is limited by the strength of the material in the
rams and die, which for high temperatures is normally graphite. The pressure is therefore usually
not much higher than about 100 MPa.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Object of the invention</u></b></heading><p num="0015">It is the object of this invention to provide a cutting tool insert having a sintered alumina and
silicon carbide whisker composite material body and a method for preparing the same, wherein
the cutting tool insert exhibits improved wear resistance and toughness behaviour in metal cutting
applications. </p><p num="0016">This object is solved by providing a method for the preparation of a cutting tool insert having a
sintered alumina and silicon carbide whisker composite material body, comprising the steps of
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>milling and mixing the powdered starting materials of said composite material and forming
said material into a preformed workpiece,</li><li>heating up said workpiece at a heating rate of 20-60°C per minute for a sintering
temperature of between 1600-2300°C, and</li><li>holding at said sintering temperature for a holding time of 5-60 minutes at a pressure of
20-100 MPa.</li></ul></p><p num="0017">The method of the present invention will herein be referred to as "rapid sintering". The method
combines the use of high sintering temperature, a high temperature rise up to the sintering
temperature, and short holding times at the sintering temperature, and at the same time a high
pressure. The method of the present invention, having combined the aforementioned parameters,
results in a whisker reinforced ceramic material for cutting tools with improved performance due
to inhibition of defects due to grain growth. The method maintains a fine and uniform alumina
grain size due to rapid heating the sintering temperature and due to a short holding time at this
temperature, while maintaining full shrinkage and densification. The cutting tools produced
according to the method of the present invention exhibit superior wear resistance and toughness
behaviour over similar cutting tool materials having the same composition, but being produced by
a different sintering method.</p><p num="0018">A very surprising effect has been observed by the present inventor, which will be discussed and
evidenced in more detail below: Two materials of the same composition have been produced by
the hot pressing sintering method and according to the method of the present invention,
respectively. Both materials showed very similar or almost identical mechanical properties and
microstructure characteristics in respect of density, hardness, fracture toughness, and strength.
But, surprisingly the material produced according to the method of the present invention showed
much better cutting tool performance in respect of tool life and notch wear.</p><p num="0019">The afore-mentioned difference in tool performance of the material produced according to the
present invention is referred to a combination of the mean alumina grain size and other
microstructural material properties, which have not yet been explained in detail, but which appear
to be closely related and a result of the sintering process conditions specified in this invention.
Accordingly, in a preferred embodiment of the cutting tool insert produced by the method of the
present invention the mean alumina grain size is 2.0 µm or less, preferably less than 1.5 µm,
more preferred less than 1.0 µm, and most preferred less than 0.9 µm. </p><p num="0020">It has further been found that the improved performance of the cutting tool insert of the present
invention seems to be related to a low width of the alumina grain size distribution. Since the
alumina grain size distribution in the material of the present invention does not follow an ideal
Gaussian distribution, but is rather asymmetric, the grain size standard deviation is not a useful
measure for the alumina grain size distribution. The alumina grain size distribution is therefore
determined by the 80<sup>th</sup> percentile (P80) of the width of the alumina grain sizes. P80 is the value of
the alumina grain size (d), such that 80% of all alumina grain size measurements are less than
that value.</p><p num="0021">Improved performance of the cutting tool insert of the present invention is found in an
embodiment wherein the alumina in the composite material has a 80<sup>th</sup> percentile (P80) of less
than 2.5 µm, preferrably less than 2.0 µm, more preferred less than 1.8 µm, most preferred less
than 1.3 µm.</p><p num="0022">It has been found that these mean diameter and P80 values of the alumina in the composite
material of the invention are achieved by applying the rapid sintering method according to the
present invention, whereas standard hot pressing results in higher mean diameter and higher
P80 values accompanied by inferior cutting tool performance.</p><p num="0023">In a preferred embodiment of the invention the rapid sintering method comprises the steps of
heating up the workpiece to be sintered by applying electrical energy in the form of a DC current,
that at least partially goes through said workpiece. In another preferred embodiment said current
may either be unpulsed or pulsed DC current.</p><p num="0024">In another preferred embodiment, the method of the present invention includes the rapid sintering
method, as it is described in US patent 5,348,694. Accordingly, the method of the present
invention comprises the steps of providing a bed comprising a bed material of electrically
conductive, flowable particles within a contained zone, placing the workpiece in the bed, applying
a pressure to said bed, applying electrical energy to said electrically conductive, flowable particles
within the bed in a sufficient amount to heat the bed to the desired sintering temperature for the
workpiece within the desired heating rate. This method allows for a rapid heating up to the
sintering temperature at a steep heating ramp at a desired pressure of up to 100 MPa. This
method allows for high sintering temperatures compared to other known sintering methods with
high heating rates. The method further allows at the same time for high sintering pressures to 100
MPa, depending on the strength of the graphite tools. The bed material of electrically conductive,
flowable particles, useful in the method of the present invention, comprises graphite, preferably
spherical graphite or carbided graphitic material. </p><p num="0025">Rapid sintering according to the present invention includes a high heating rate or steep heating
ramp, respectively, high sintering temperatures, and short sintering times. All of these parameters
have been found contribute to small alumina grain sizes, small P80 values and to superior tool
performance, which seems to be the result of a combination of said small alumina grain sizes,
small P80 values and one or more other parameters, which is/are resulting from the rapid
sintering method.</p><p num="0026">Thus, in another preferred embodiment of the method of the present invention, the sintering
temperature is between 1800-2100°C, more preferably between 1900-2000°C. The heating rate
is preferably from 20-40°C per minute, and most preferably about 25°C per minute.</p><p num="0027">Even though holding times up to 60 minutes may be applied, depending on the composition of
the material, shorter holding times are preferred to avoid alumina grain growth. In a preferred
embodiment, the holding time is from 5 to 30 minutes, more preferably from 10 to 20 minutes,
and most preferably about 15 minutes.</p><p num="0028">A useful pressure for the method of the invention lies within the range of 20-100 MPa. In a more
preferred embodiment the pressure is from 30-100 MPa, most preferably from 40-100 MPa. In
most cases a pressure of about 50 MPa is suitable.</p><p num="0029">In another preferred embodiment, the composite material produced according to the method of
the present invention comprises alumina plus silicon carbide whiskers in a total proportion of at
least 90% by volume, more preferably in a total proportion of at least 95% by volume. The
proportion of silicon carbide whiskers in said composite material is preferably 5-70% by volume,
more preferably 15-50% by volume, and most preferred 20-45% by volume.</p><p num="0030">The composite material produced according to the method of the present invention may
additionally comprise a certain amount of sintering additives like magnesia or yttria. In a preferred
embodiment of the present invention, magnesia and/or yttria may each be comprised in the
composite material in a proportion of 0.01-5% by weight, preferably in a proportion of 0.02-1 % by
weight, most preferred in a proportion of 0.03-0.5% by weight.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Figures</u></b></heading><p num="0031"><dl tsize="9"><dt>Figure 1a</dt><dd>shows an example of a scanning electron micrograph in 8000 times magnification
of a sample produced according to the method of the present invention, described
in example 1 below and being treated according to example 5 below;</dd><dt>Figure 1b</dt><dd>shows the micrograph of Figure 1a after image processing as described in
example 5 below; </dd><dt>Figure 2a</dt><dd>shows an example of a scanning electron micrograph in 8000 times magnification
of a commercially available grade (commercial grade A, see example 6 below),
being treated according to example 5 below;</dd><dt>Figure 2b</dt><dd>shows the micrograph of Figure 2a after image processing as described in
example 5 below;</dd></dl></p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 1</u></b></heading><p num="0032">For comparison, cutting tool inserts of alumina-silicon carbide whisker composite material were
prepared, both conventionally with hot pressing and by rapid sintering according to the present
invention, using a direct electrically heated powder bed with preforms of the material to be
sintered. In this and the following examples, the method of the present invention will simply be
designated as "rapid sintering".</p><p num="0033">A mixture of 71% by volume alumina (Ceralox APA, ∼0.3 µm grain size) and 29% by volume
silicon carbide whiskers (Advanced Composite Materials Corp. SC-9, average diameter ∼0.6 µm)
were put together. 0.04% by weight each of magnesia (Magnesium Electron Ltd.) and yttria (A.C.
Starck, grade standard) as sintering additives and 1.25% by weight PVA (Mowiol 4-88), 1.5% by
weight PEG300 (Pluriol E-300), and 1.5% by weight PEG1500 (Pluriol E-1500) as pressing aids
to enable uniaxial cold pressing were added, and the composition was wet-milled to obtain a
homogeneous mixture.</p><p num="0034">For the conventional preparation with hot pressing (HP), the mixture was freeze dried to obtain
granules, cold pressed into a disc, and presintered at 600°C for one hour in air to remove the
pressing aid. Subsequently the material was hot pressed for one hour at 1875°C and 25 MPa.
The sintered disc was diamond saw cut into blanks, which were then ground to inserts with ISO-designation
RNGN 120700 T01 020.</p><p num="0035">For preparation with rapid sintering according to the present invention, the mixture was freeze
dried to obtain granules, cold pressed into blanks, which were then presintered at 600°C for one
hour in air to remove the pressing aid. The blanks were then coated with a thin BN-layer to
prevent reaction with the graphite of the electrically heated powder bed. The same coating with a
BN-layer had been applied to the above material in the hot pressing of discs. The blanks were
then placed in a die chamber filled with electrically conductive graphitic carbon, whereby a porous
graphitic carbon of spheroidal form (Superior Graphite Co., grade 9400) was used. Heating was
done by passing an electrical current through the medium. The temperature was raised with 25°C
per minute, and the sintering temperature was 1925°C, which was held for 15 minutes at a
pressure of 50 MPa. Blank temperature was calculated as a function of time and location in the 
die, using a computer model. The blanks were then allowed to cool down in the furnace, and no
additional heat treatment was performed. After sintering, the blanks were ground to inserts with
ISO-designation RNGN 120700 T01 020.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 2</u></b></heading><p num="0036">The samples (blanks) of example 1 (prepared by hot pressing and rapid sintering, respectively)
were tested in a grooving operation in heat resistant alloy of the type Inconel 718. A groove was
widened in two cuts by a total of about 30%. Tool life was reached when the largest dimension of
a damage on the flank or rake face exceeded 1 mm.</p><p num="0037">The following cutting conditions were used:
<sl><li>Cutting fluid: yes</li><li>Cutting speed: 250 m/min</li><li>Feed: 0.15 and 0.25 mm/rev</li><li>Depth of cut: 6 mm
<tables><table><tgroup cols="9"><tbody><row><entry nameend="9"  namest="1"><b>Number of cycles to tool life</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"  namest="1"><b>Feed</b></entry><entry align="left"  namest="2"><b>Sintering Method</b></entry><entry nameend="7" align="center" namest="3"><b>Number of Cycles</b></entry><entry align="center" namest="8"><b>Average</b></entry><entry align="center" namest="9"><b>Relative</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 1</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 2</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 3</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 4</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 5</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="1">0.15 mm/rev</entry><entry align="left">Hot pressing</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="2">Rapid Sint.</entry><entry align="left" namest="3">6</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">7</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">5</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">7</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">5</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">6</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">150</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="1">0.25 mm/rev</entry><entry align="left">Hot Pressing</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="2">Rapid Sint.</entry><entry align="left" namest="3">3</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">5</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">3</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">3</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">5</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">3.8</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">128</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></li></sl></p><p num="0038">At a feed rate of 0.15 mm/rev the increase in tool life is 50%, and at a feed rate of 0.25 mm/rev
the increase is 28%.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 3</u></b></heading><p num="0039">Using the samples (blanks) of example 1, notch wear was measured in facing operation in heat
resistant alloy of the type Inconel 718.</p><p num="0040">The following cutting conditions were used:
<sl><li>Cutting fluid: yes</li><li>Cutting speed: 220 m/min</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.5 mm</li><li>Feed: 0.11 mm/rev</li></sl></p><p num="0041">Notch wear was measured after two cuts. <tables><table><tgroup cols="9"><tbody><row><entry nameend="9" namest="1"><b>Notch wear (mm) after two cuts</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="1"><b>Sintering Method</b></entry><entry nameend="7" align="center" namest="2"><b>Notch wear (mm)</b></entry><entry align="left" namest="8"><b>Average</b></entry><entry align="left" namest="9"><b>Relative</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 1</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 2</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 3</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 4</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 5</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 6</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hot Pressing</entry><entry align="center">0.59</entry><entry align="center">0.58</entry><entry align="center">0.31</entry><entry align="center">0.71</entry><entry align="center">0.61</entry><entry align="center">0.72</entry><entry align="center">0.60</entry><entry align="left">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rapid Sintering</entry><entry align="center">0.43</entry><entry align="center">0.21</entry><entry align="center">0.27</entry> <entry align="center">0.58</entry><entry align="center">0.46</entry><entry align="center">0.66</entry><entry align="center">0.45</entry><entry align="left">75</entry> </row> </tbody> </tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0042">With the cutting tool insert produced according to the rapid sintering method of the present
invention, a reduction in notch wear to about 75% was achieved, or in other words, an increase in
notch wear resistance of about 25% was achieved.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 4</u></b></heading><p num="0043">The samples produced according to the methods of example 1 were characterized in respect of
physical and mechanical properties and microstructural characteristics. The measured
mechanical properties were density, hardness, fracture toughness, and strength, which are
indicated in table 3 below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><b>Mechanical Properties</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>Sintering Method</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Density g/cm<sup>3</sup></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Hardness HV10 GPa</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Fracture Toughness Mpam<sup>½</sup><!--footnotes removed--></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Strength MPa<!--footnotes removed--></b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hot Pressing</entry><entry align="center">3.73</entry><entry align="center">2080 ± 80</entry><entry align="center">6.9 ± 0.6</entry><entry align="center">995</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rapid Sintering</entry><entry align="center">3.73</entry><entry align="center">2110 ± 21</entry><entry align="center">6.5 ± 0.2</entry><entry align="center">1050<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0044">There are surprisingly only small differences between the two materials with respect to the
physical and mechanical properties, considering the large differences in cutting performance, i.e.
tool life and notch wear. It was highly surprising that two materials showing almost identical
mechanical properties in standard tests exhibited large differences in cutting performance. In a
retrospective view, this may be explained by the obvious differences in temperature, since
mechanical properties are determined at room temperature, whereas during examination of
cutting performance the cutting edge will experience temperatures above 1000°C. It is well-known
to experts in the art that mechanical properties and cutting tool performance often fall
apart due to this temperature difference, but it is not at all predictable whether cutting tool
performance is improved or worsened.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 5</u></b></heading><p num="0045">A more detailed microstructural characterization on the samples according to example 1 above
was made with the aid of automatic image analysis using an image of the grain structure 
produced by a scanning electrone microscope (SEM). A polished surface of a sample,
perpendicular to the pressing direction, was etched in hydrogen at 1000°C to reveal the alumina
grain boundaries, and thereafter it was etched in acid to remove any formed oxide or glassy
layers. These layers are formed due to the presence of silicon carbide whiskers, which might
oxidise during heat treatment. Scanning electron micrographs in 8000 times magnification were
then recorded (see figures 1a and 2a). The images were further processed using a computerized
image analysis system by filling in the grain boundaries with black line colour by hand. The areas
covered by silicon carbide whisker grains were also filled with black colour by hand. Since the
whiskers are orientated preferably in the plain perpendicular to the hot pressing direction, they
are easily identified due to their high aspect ratio. Further image processing in the image analyser
generated a black and white picture, where only the alumina grain boundaries and the SiC-whisker
grains were visible to facilitate the measurements (see figures 1b and 2b).</p><p num="0046">Determination of the mean grain size was based on measurement of the individual area of each
grain completely within the test area border. The measurement was repeated eight times for
different fields to obtain an adequate number of measurements. The equipment was calibrated,
so that area measurements were made in µm<sup>2</sup>. Between 450 and 1150 grains were measured for
each variant, depending on the grain size, which is about 50-100 grains per microscopic field.
The pixel density was 1280 x 960.</p><p num="0047">The equivalent grain diameter (microns) was calculated, assuming each grain is a perfect sphere
using the formula
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">A<st32:sub pos="post">i</st32:sub> = π d<st32:sub pos="post">i</st32:sub><st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>/4</st32:df><sl><li>wherein: A<sub>i</sub> = area for grain I, and</li><li>d<sub>i</sub> = equivalent diameter for grain i.</li></sl></p><p num="0048">The mean diameter (d<sub>mean</sub>) of the distribution was calculated using the formula
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center"><st32:italic>d<st32:sub pos="post">mean</st32:sub></st32:italic> = ∑<st32:italic>d<st32:sub pos="post">i</st32:sub></st32:italic>/<st32:italic>n</st32:italic>.</st32:df>
wherein is the number of measurements.</p><p num="0049">The 80<sup>th</sup> percentile (P80), which describes the width of the grain size distribution, is the value of
of the alumina grain size d, such that 80% of the measurements are less than that value. The
calculated values for mean diameter and 80<sup>th</sup> percentile (P80) for the two materials of example 1
are indicated in the following table 4: <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><b>Alumina grain size and P80</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Sintering Method</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Mean diameter (microns)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>P80 (microns)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hot Pressing</entry><entry align="center">1,26</entry><entry align="center">1,93</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rapid Sintering (15 min)</entry><entry align="center">0,77</entry><entry align="center">1,12</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0050">Table 4 shows that the material produced by rapid sintering according to the present invention
has smaller alumina mean diameter and smaller alumina grain size distribution, both essential for
the cutting performance. An increase in either of the parameters, which means an increase in the
volume fraction of relatively coarse grains, reduces the cutting performance.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 6</u></b></heading><p num="0051">A number of commercial materials based on alumina and silicon whiskers have been
characterized with respect to alumina grain size and distribution. All major suppliers are included
in this investigation. Measurements were made in an identical manner to what is described in
example 5, and the results are presented in table 5. The sample according to the present
invention was prepared according to example 1. All commercial materials had approximately the
same composition, namely 25 weight-% SiC-whiscers, a small amount of sintering additives, and
alumina as the remaining main constituent.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><b>Alumina grain size and P80</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Grade</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Mean diameter (microns)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>P80 (microns)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Commercial grade A</entry><entry align="center">1,31</entry><entry align="center">1,97</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Commercial grade B</entry><entry align="center">1,04</entry><entry align="center">1,48</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Commercial grade C</entry><entry align="center">1,58</entry><entry align="center">2,50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Commercial grade D</entry><entry align="center">1,34</entry><entry align="center">2,07</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rapid sintering (15 min)</entry><entry align="center">0,77</entry><entry align="center">1,12</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0052">All commercial materials showed a larger mean grain size and a larger P80 than the material
according to the present invention.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 7</u></b></heading><p num="0053">In order to study the influence of processing parameters, three different holding times during
sintering were evaluated. The samples were prepared according to the inventive method of
example 1, except for varying sintering times, i. e. the temperature increase was 25°C per
minute, the sintering temperature was 1925°C (in case of 10 min holding time, the sintering
temperature was slightly higher: 1950°C), and the pressure was 50 MPa for all variants. The
sintering times were 10 min, 15 min, and 22 min. After sintering, the blanks were ground into
inserts with ISO designation RNGN 120700 T01 020. </p><p num="0054">The mean alumina grain diameter and P80 were evaluated, using the same method, as
described for the previous examples. The results are shown in table 6.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Sintering time (min)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Sintering temp. (°C)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Mean diameter (microns)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>P80 (microns)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">1950</entry><entry align="center">0,88</entry><entry align="center">1,26</entry></row><row><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">1925</entry><entry align="center">0,77</entry><entry align="center">1,12</entry></row><row><entry align="center">22</entry><entry align="center">1925</entry><entry align="center">1,20</entry><entry align="center">1,73</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0055">Hardness, fracture toughness and density were also evaluated for the processing variants. The results are shown in table 7.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Sintering time (min)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Sintering temp. (°C)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Density (g/cm<sup>3</sup>)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Hardness (GPa)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Fracture toughness (MPa m<sup>½</sup><!--footnotes removed-->)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="right">10</entry><entry align="center">1950</entry><entry align="center">3,72</entry><entry align="center">2043±16</entry><entry align="center">5,8 ±0,1</entry></row><row><entry align="right">15</entry><entry align="center">1925</entry><entry align="center">3,73</entry><entry align="center">2110±21</entry><entry align="center">6,5 ±0,2</entry></row><row><entry align="right">22</entry><entry align="center">1925</entry><entry align="center">3,70-3,73</entry><entry align="center">2088 ±33</entry><entry align="center">5,6 ±0,6<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 8</u></b></heading><p num="0056">Notch wear of the processing variants of example 7 was measured in a facing operation in heat
resistant alloy of the type Inconel 718. Two of the above mentioned commercial materials were
used as references. Commercial grade A with a mean grain size typical for most investigated
commercial grades and grade B with the smallest mean grain size of the measured commercial
materials.</p><p num="0057">The following cutting conditions were used:
<sl><li>Cutting fluid: yes</li><li>Cutting speed: 220 m/min</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.5 mm</li><li>Feed: 0.11 mm/rev</li></sl></p><p num="0058">Notch wear was measured after four cuts. <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><b>Notch wear (mm) after four cuts</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>Grade</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Notch wear (mm; median)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Relative</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Commercial grade A</entry><entry align="center">0,84</entry><entry align="center">311</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Commercial grade B</entry><entry align="center">0,59</entry><entry align="center">219</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rapid sintering 10 min</entry><entry align="center">0,61</entry><entry align="center">226</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rapid sintering 15 min</entry><entry align="center">0,27</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rapid sintering 22 min</entry><entry align="center">0,77</entry><entry align="center">285</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0059">The notch wear resistance is sensitive to sintering time. The best notch wear resistance was
achieved for the 15 min sintering time. The alumina grain size is one parameter governing the
notch wear resistance, but cannot alone explain the results.</p><heading><b>Example 9</b></heading><p num="0060">The samples of the preceeding example 8 were also tested in a grooving operation in heat
resistant alloy of the type Inconel 718. A groove was widened in two cuts by a total of about 30%.
Tool life was reached when the largest dimension of a damage on the flank or rake face
exceeded 1 mm.</p><p num="0061">The following cutting conditions were used:
<sl><li>Cutting fluid: yes</li><li>Cutting speed: 250 m/min</li><li>Feed: 0.25 mm/rev</li><li>Depth of cut: 6 mm</li></sl><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><b>Number of cycles to tool life</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"><b>Variant</b></entry><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2"><b>Number of Cycles</b></entry><entry align="center" namest="4"><b>Average</b></entry><entry align="center" namest="5"><b>Relative</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 1</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Exp. 2</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Commercial grade A (prior art)</entry><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">11</entry><entry align="center">183</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Commercial grade B (prior art)</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rapid sintering 10 min</entry><entry align="center">14</entry><entry align="center">13</entry><entry align="center">13,5</entry><entry align="center">225</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rapid sintering 15 min</entry><entry align="center">13</entry><entry align="center">11</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">200</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rapid sintering 22 min</entry><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">6,5</entry><entry align="center">108</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>Method for the preparation of a cutting tool insert, having a sintered alumina and silicon
carbide whisker composite material body, comprising the steps of
milling and mixing the powdered starting materials of said composite material and forming
said material into a preformed workpiece,
heating up said workpiece at a heating rate of 20 to 60 °C per minute to a sintering
temperature of between 1600 to 2300 °C, and
holding at said sintering temperature for a holding time of 5 to 60 minutes at a pressure of
between 20 to 100 MPa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, further comprising the steps of
heating up said workpiece by applying electrical energy in the form of a DC current, that
at least partially goes through said workpiece.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method of claim 2, whereby the DC current is unpulsed.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method of claim 2, whereby the DC current is pulsed.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1 to 4, comprising the steps of
providing a bed comprising a bed material of electrically conductive, flowable particles
within a contained zone,
placing the workpiece in said bed,
applying a pressure to said bed,
heating up said workpiece by applying electrical energy to said electrically conductive,
flowable particles within the bed in a sufficient amount to heat the bed to said sintering
temperature for the workpiece within said heating rate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method of claim 5, wherein the bed material of electrically conductive, flowable
particles comprises graphite, preferably spherical graphite or carbided graphitic material.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1 to 6, wherein said sintering temperature is between 1800
to 2100 °C, preferably between 1900 to 2000 °C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1 to 7, wherein said heating rate is from 20 to 40 °C per
minute, preferably about 25 °C per minute.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1 to 8, wherein said holding time is from 5 to 30 minutes,
preferably from 10 to 20 minutes, most preferably about 15 minutes.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1 to 9 wherein said pressure is from 30 to 100 MPa,
preferably from 40 to 100 MPa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1 to 10, wherein said composite material comprises alumina
plus silicon carbide whiskers in a total proportion of at least 90 percent by volume,
preferably in a total proportion of at least 95 percent by volume.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1 to 11, wherein said composite material comprises silicon
carbide whiskers in a proportion of 5 to 70 percent by volume, preferably in a proportion of
15 to 50 percent by volume, most preferred in a proportion of 20 to 45 percent by volume.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1 to 12, wherein said alumina in said composite material has
mean diameter of less than 2.0 µm, preferably less than 1.5 µm, more preferred less than
1.0 µm, and most preferred less than 0.9 µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1 to 13, wherein said alumina in said composite material has
a 80th percentile (P80) of less than 2.5 µm, preferrably less than 2.0 µm, more preferred
less than 1.8 µm, most preferred less than 1.3 µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1 to 14, wherein said composite material additionally
comprises magnesia and/or yttria in a proportion of 0.01 to 5 percent by weight, preferably
in a proportion of 0.02 to 1 percent by weight, most preferred in a proportion of 0.03 to 0.5
percent by weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>Cutting tool insert, having a sintered alumina and silicon carbide whisker composite
material body, being prepared according to any of claims 1 to 15.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>Cutting tool insert of claim 16, wherein said alumina in said composite material has mean
diameter of less than 2.0 µm, preferably less than 1.5 µm, more preferred less than 1.0
µm, and most preferred less than 0.9 µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>Cutting tool insert of claim 17, wherein said alumina in said composite material has a 80th
percentile (P80) of less than 2.5 µm, preferably less than 2.0 µm, more preferred less
than 1.8 µm, most preferred less than 1.3 µm.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>