<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1350819-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1350819" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="28035932" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20031008"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1350819-A1" status="new" fvid="23867456"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1350819</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20031008</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03007384-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03007384</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030402</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002101347-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002101347</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020403</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  47/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  47/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  47/067       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  47/073       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  47/24        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09B  47/067H</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09B  47/06H</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C20</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C2D</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Tinte und Methode für die Aufzeichnung mittels eines Tintenstrahldruckers</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Inkjet recording ink and inkjet recording method</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Une encre et une méthode d'enregistrement par jet d'encre</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1270677-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1270677</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1469047-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1469047</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="EXA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1473335-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1473335</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="EXA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-1356837-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>1356837</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5882390-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5882390</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6123761-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6123761</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6241789-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6241789</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2001066648-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2001066648</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2002060994-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2002060994</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="EXA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2003000811-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2003000811</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="EXA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2003062323-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2003062323</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="EXA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>FUJI PHOTO FILM CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>210 Nakanuma Minami-Ashigara-shi</street><city>Kanagawa 250-01</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OZAWA TAKASHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OZAWA, TAKASHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Ozawa, Takashi, Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>200, Onakazato, Fujinomiya-shi</street><city>Shizuoka</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name><address><street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street><city>81925 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An ink comprising an aqueous medium and at least one
dye represented by the formula (I) as defined herein, which
is dissolved or dispersed in the aqueous medium, wherein
the ink permeates into a recording medium having an image-receiving
layer to a depth of 5 to 30 µm.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to an inkjet recording
ink which provides an image having high quality and
excellent preservability and ensures excellent ejection
stability.</p><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0002">Accompanying recent overspreading of computers,
inkjet printers are widely used for the printing on paper,
film, cloth or the like not only in offices but also at
homes.</p><p num="0003">The inkjet recording method includes a system of
jetting out a liquid droplet by applying a pressure using
a piezo element, a system of jetting out a liquid droplet
by generating bubbles in an ink under heat, a system of
using an ultrasonic wave, and a system of jetting out a
liquid droplet by suction using an electrostatic force.
The ink used for such inkjet recording systems includes an
aqueous ink, an oily ink and a solid (fusion-type) ink. 
Among these inks, the aqueous ink is predominating in view
of production, handleability, odor, safety and the like.</p><p num="0004">The dye used in such an inkjet recording ink is
required to have high solubility in a solvent, enable
high-density recording, provide good color, exhibit
excellent fastness to light, heat, air, water and
chemicals, ensure good fixing property to an image-receiving
material and less blurring, give an ink having
excellent storability, have high purity and no toxicity,
and be available at a low cost. However, it is very
difficult to find out a dye satisfying these requirements
in a high level. In particular, a dye having good cyan
color and excellent weather resistance is strongly
demanded.</p><p num="0005">Also, the inkjet recording is known to have a
problem that a phenomenon of metal gloss called bronze
which is deemed ascribable to regular reflected light on
the surface of dye particle is sometimes observed and this
deteriorates the image quality.</p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0006">Accordingly, an object of the present invention is
to provide an inkjet recording ink having good ejection 
stability, giving a high-quality image and ensuring good
image preservability under severe conditions, which is an
aqueous ink preferred in view of handleability, odor,
safety and the like.</p><p num="0007">The above-described object can be attained by the
followings. More specifically, according to the present
invention, the following inkjet recording ink and inkjet
recording method are provided.
<sl><li>(1) An inkjet recording ink comprising an aqueous
medium having dissolved or dispersed therein at least one
dye represented by the following formula (I), wherein the
ink permeates into a recording medium having an image-receiving
layer to a depth of 5 to 30 µm:
<img id="img-00030001" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030001.tif" inline="no" he="103"/>
wherein X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>, X<sub>3</sub> and X<sub>4</sub> each independently represents-SO-Z, 
-SO<sub>2</sub>-Z, -SO<sub>2</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>, a sulfo group, -CONR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub> or -CO<sub>2</sub>R<sub>1</sub>,
each Z independently represents a substituted or
unsubstituted alkyl group, a substituted or unsubstituted
cycloalkyl group, a substituted or unsubstituted alkenyl
group, a substituted or unsubstituted aralkyl group, a
substituted or unsubstituted aryl group or a substituted
or unsubstituted heterocyclic group, R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> each
independently represents a hydrogen atom, a substituted or
unsubstituted alkyl group, a substituted or unsubstituted
cycloalkyl group, a substituted or unsubstituted alkenyl
group, a substituted or unsubstituted aralkyl group, a
substituted or unsubstituted aryl group or a substituted
or unsubstituted heterocyclic group, Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> and Y<sub>4</sub> each
independently represents a monovalent substituent, a<sub>1</sub> to a<sub>4</sub>
and b<sub>1</sub> to b<sub>4</sub> each represents the number of substituent X<sub>1</sub>,
X<sub>2</sub>, X<sub>3</sub>, X<sub>4</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> or Y<sub>4</sub>, a<sub>1</sub> to a<sub>4</sub> each independently
represents a number of 0 to 4 but all are not 0 at the
same time, b<sub>1</sub> to b<sub>4</sub> each independently represents a number
of 0 to 3, provided that when at least one of a<sub>1</sub> to a<sub>4</sub> and
b<sub>1</sub> to b<sub>4</sub> represents a number of 2 or more, corresponding
plurality of substituents X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>, X<sub>3</sub>, X<sub>4</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> or Y<sub>4</sub>
may be the same or different, and M represents a hydrogen
atom, a metal atom or an oxide, hydroxide or halide
thereof.</li><li>(2) The ink as described in (1) above, wherein the 
dye represented by formula (I) is a dye represented by the
following formula (II):
<img id="img-00050001" orientation="unknown" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050001.tif" inline="no" he="112"/>
wherein X<sub>11</sub> to X<sub>14</sub>, Y<sub>11</sub> to Y<sub>18</sub> and M have the same meanings
as X<sub>1</sub> to X<sub>4</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub> to Y<sub>4</sub> and M in formula (I), respectively,
and a<sub>11</sub> to a<sub>14</sub> each independently represents an integer of
1 or 2.</li><li>(3) An inkjet recording method using the inkjet
recording ink described in (1) or (2) above.</li><li>(4) An inkjet recording method comprising jetting
out an ink droplet on an image-receiving material
according to recording signals to record an image on the
image-receiving material, the image-receiving material
comprising a support having thereon an image-receiving 
layer containing a white inorganic pigment particle,</li></sl>
wherein the ink droplet comprises the inkjet recording ink
described in (1) or (2) above.</p><heading><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0008">The present invention is described in detail below.</p><p num="0009">The dye used in the inkjet recording ink of the
present invention is a phthalocyanine dye, preferably a
dye represented by formula (I). The phthalocyanine dye is
a dye having fastness but this dye is known to be inferior
in the fastness to ozone gas when used as a dye for inkjet
recording.</p><p num="0010">In the present invention, an electron withdrawing
group is preferably introduced into the phthalocyanine
skeleton to have an oxidation potential nobler than 1.0 V
(vs SCE) and thereby reduce the reactivity with ozone
which is an electrophilic agent. A nobler oxidation
potential is more preferred and the oxidation potential is
more preferably nobler than 1.1 V (vs SCE) and most
preferably nobler than 1.2 V (vs SCE).</p><p num="0011">The oxidation potential value (Eox) can be easily
measured by one skilled in the art and the method therefor
is described, for example, in P. Delahay, <u style="single">New Instrumental</u><u style="single">Methods in Electrochemistry,</u> Interscience Publishers
(1954), A.J. Bard et al., <u style="single">Electrochemical Methods,</u> John
Wiley &amp; Sons (1980), and Akira Fujishima et al.,
<u style="single">Denkikagaku Sokutei Ho (Electrochemical Measuring Method),</u>
Gihodo Shuppan Sha (1984).</p><p num="0012">More specifically, a test sample is dissolved to a
concentration of 1×10<sup>-4</sup> to 1×10<sup>-6</sup> mol/liter in a solvent
such as dimethylformamide or acetonitrile containing a
supporting electrolyte such as sodium perchlorate or
tetrapropylammonium perchlorate and the oxidation
potential is measured as a value to SCE (saturated calomel
electrode) using a cyclic voltammetry or a direct current
polarography. This value sometimes deviates on the order
of tens of millivolt due to the effect of liquid junction
potential, liquid resistance of sample solution, or the
like, however, the reproducibility of potential can be
guaranteed by adding a standard sample (for example,
hydroquinone).</p><p num="0013">In order to univocally specify the potential, in the
present invention, the value (vs SCE) measured by a direct
current polarography in a dimethylformamide (concentration
of dye: 0.001 mol dm<sup>-3</sup>) containing 0.1 mol dm<sup>-3</sup> of tetrapropylammonium
perchlorate as the supporting electrolyte
is used as the oxidation potential of the dye. </p><p num="0014">The Eox value indicates the transferability of an
electron from the sample to the electrode and as the value
is larger (the oxidation potential is nobler), the
electron is less transferable from the sample to the
electrode, in other words, the oxidation less occurs. As
for the relationship with the structure of compound, the
oxidation potential becomes nobler by introducing an
electron withdrawing group and becomes baser by
introducing an electron donating group. In the present
invention, the oxidation potential is preferably rendered
nobler by introducing an electron withdrawing group into
the phthalocyanine skeleton so as to reduce the reactivity
with ozone which is an electrophilic agent. Accordingly,
when the Hammett's substituent constant σp value as a
measure for the electron withdrawing property or electron
donating property of substituent is used, the oxidation
potential can be rendered nobler by introducing a
substituent having a large σp value, such as sulfinyl
group, sulfonyl group and sulfamoyl group.</p><p num="0015">For such potential control, the phthalocyanine dye
represented by formula (I) is used in the present
invention.</p><p num="0016">In formula (I), X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>, X<sub>3</sub> and X<sub>4</sub> each independently
represents -SO-Z, -SO<sub>2</sub>-Z, -SO<sub>2</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>, a sulfo group, -CONR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>
or -CO<sub>2</sub>R<sub>1</sub>. Among these substituents, preferred are -SO-Z, 
-SO<sub>2</sub>-Z, -SO<sub>2</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub> and -CONR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>, more preferred are -SO<sub>2</sub>-Z
and -SO<sub>2</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>, and most preferred is -SO<sub>2</sub>-Z. In the case
where at least one of a<sub>1</sub> to a<sub>4</sub> showing the number of
substituent each represents a number of 2 or more, a
corresponding plurality of substituents X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>, X<sub>3</sub> or X<sub>4</sub>
may be the same or different and each independently
represents any one of the above-described groups. X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>,
X<sub>3</sub> and X<sub>4</sub> may be completely the same substituents, may be
substituents of the same kind but partially different as
in the case, for example, where X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>, X<sub>3</sub> and X<sub>4</sub> all are-SO<sub>2</sub>-Z
and Zs are different from each other, or may include
substituents different from each other, for example, -SO<sub>2</sub>-Z
and -SO<sub>2</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0017">Each Z independently represents a substituted or
unsubstituted alkyl group, a substituted or unsubstituted
cycloalkyl group, a substituted or unsubstituted alkenyl
group, a substituted or unsubstituted aralkyl group, a
substituted or unsubstituted aryl group, or a substituted
or unsubstituted heterocyclic group, preferably a
substituted or unsubstituted alkyl group, a substituted or
unsubstituted aryl group or a substituted or unsubstituted
heterocyclic group, and most preferably a substituted
alkyl group, a substituted aryl group or a substituted
heterocyclic group.</p><p num="0018">R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> each independently represents a hydrogen 
atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl group, a
substituted or unsubstituted cycloalkyl group, a
substituted or unsubstituted alkenyl group, a substituted
or unsubstituted aralkyl group, a substituted or
unsubstituted aryl group, or a substituted or
unsubstituted heterocyclic group, preferably a hydrogen
atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl group, a
substituted or unsubstituted aryl group, or a substituted
or unsubstituted heterocyclic group, most preferably a
hydrogen atom, a substituted alkyl group, a substituted
aryl group or a substituted heterocyclic group. However,
it is not preferred that R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> both are a hydrogen atom.</p><p num="0019">The substituted or unsubstituted alkyl group
represented by R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub> and Z is preferably an alkyl group
having from 1 to 30 carbon atoms, more preferably a
branched alkyl group because the solubility of dye and the
stability of ink are improved, and still more preferably
an alkyl group having an asymmetric carbon (use in the
racemic form). Examples of the substituent include those
described later as the substituent when Z, R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>,
Y<sub>3</sub> and Y<sub>4</sub> can further have a substituent. In particular, a
hydroxyl group, an ether group, an ester group, a cyano
group, an amido group and a sulfonamido group are
preferred because the aggregating property and fastness of
dye are enhanced. Other than these, the alkyl group may 
be substituted by a halogen atom or an ionic hydrophilic
group.</p><p num="0020">The substituted or unsubstituted cycloalkyl group
represented by R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub> and Z is preferably a cycloalkyl
group having from 5 to 30 carbon atoms, more preferably a
cycloalkyl group having an asymmetric carbon (use in the
racemic form) because the solubility of dye and the
stability of ink are improved. Examples of the
substituent include those described later as the
substituent when Z, R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> and Y<sub>4</sub> can further
have a substituent. In particular, a hydroxyl group, an
ether group, an ester group, a cyano group, an amido group
and a sulfonamido group are preferred because the
aggregating property and fastness of dye are enhanced.
Other than these, the cycloalkyl group may be substituted
by a halogen atom or an ionic hydrophilic group.</p><p num="0021">The substituted or unsubstituted alkenyl group
represented by R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub> and Z is preferably an alkenyl group
having from 2 to 30 carbon atoms, more preferably a
branched alkenyl group because the solubility of dye and
the stability of ink are improved, and still more
preferably an alkenyl group having an asymmetric carbon
(use in the racemic form). Examples of the substituent
include those described later as the substituent when Z,
R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> and Y<sub>4</sub> can further have a substituent. 
In particular, a hydroxyl group, an ether group, an ester
group, a cyano group, an amido group and a sulfonamido
group are preferred because the aggregating property and
fastness of dye are enhanced. Other than these, the
alkenyl group may be substituted by a halogen atom or an
ionic hydrophilic group.</p><p num="0022">The substituted or unsubstituted aralkyl group
represented by R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub> and Z is preferably an aralkyl group
having from 7 to 30 carbon atoms, more preferably a
branched aralkyl group because the solubility of dye and
the stability of ink are improved, and still more
preferably an aralkyl group having an asymmetric carbon
(use in the racemic form). Examples of the substituent
include those described later as the substituent when Z,
R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> and Y<sub>4</sub> can further have a substituent.
In particular, a hydroxyl group, an ether group, an ester
group, a cyano group, an amido group and a sulfonamido
group are preferred because the aggregating property and
fastness of dye are enhanced. Other than these, the
aralkyl group may be substituted by a halogen atom or an
ionic hydrophilic group. Incidentally, the number of
carbon atoms in the alkyl group does not contain carbon
atoms of substituents and this applies to other groups.</p><p num="0023">The substituted or unsubstituted aryl group
represented by R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub> and Z is preferably an aryl group 
having from 6 to 30 carbon atoms. Examples of the
substituent include those described later as the
substituent when Z, R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> and Y<sub>4</sub> can further
have a substituent. In particular, an electron
withdrawing group is preferred because the dye can be
noble in the oxidation potential and improved in the
fastness.</p><p num="0024">Examples of the electron withdrawing group for use
in the present invention include those having a positive
Hammett's substituent constant σp value. Among these,
preferred are a halogen atom, a heterocyclic group, a
cyano group, a carboxyl group, an acylamino group, a
sulfonamido group, a sulfamoyl group, a carbamoyl group, a
sulfonyl group, an imido group, an acyl group, a sulfo
group and a quaternary ammonium group, more preferred are
a cyano group, a carboxyl group, a sulfamoyl group, a
carbamoyl group, a sulfonyl group, an imido group, an acyl
group, a sulfo group and a quaternary ammonium group.</p><p num="0025">The heterocyclic group represented by R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub> and Z is
preferably a 5- or 6-membered ring and the ring may be
further condensed. Also, the heterocyclic group may be an
aromatic heterocyclic group or a non-aromatic heterocyclic
group. Examples of the heterocyclic group represented by
R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub> and Z are shown below in the form of a heterocyclic
ring by omitting the substitution site. The substitution 
site is not limited and for example, pyridine may be
substituted at the 2-position, 3-position and 4-position.
Examples include pyridine, pyrazine, pyrimidine,
pyridazine, triazine, quinoline, isoquinoline, quinazoline,
cinnoline, phthalazine, quinoxaline, pyrrole, indole,
furan, benzofuran, thiophene, benzothiophene, pyrazole,
imidazole, benzimidazole, triazole, oxazole, benzoxazole,
thiazole, benzothiazole, isothiazole, benzisothiazole,
thiadiazole, isoxazole, benzisoxazole, pyrrolidine,
piperidine, piperazine, imidazolidine and thiazoline. In
particular, an aromatic heterocyclic group is preferred.
Preferred examples thereof include, shown in the same
manner as above, pyridine, pyrazine, pyrimidine,
pyridazine, triazine, pyrazole, imidazole, benzimidazole,
triazole, thiazole, benzothiazole, isothiazole,
benzisothiazole and thiadiazole. These groups each may
have a substituent and examples of the substituent include
those described later as the substituent when Z, R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub>,
Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> and Y<sub>4</sub> can further have a substituent. Preferred
substituents are the same as the above-described
substituents of the aryl group and more preferred
substituents are the same as the above-described more
preferred substituents of the aryl group.</p><p num="0026">Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> and Y<sub>4</sub> each independently represents a
hydrogen atom, a halogen atom, an alkyl group, a 
cycloalkyl group, an alkenyl group, an aralkyl group, an
aryl group, a heterocyclic group, a cyano group, a
hydroxyl group, a nitro group, an amino group, an
alkylamino group, an alkoxy group, an aryloxy group, an
acylamino group, an arylamino group, a ureido group, a
sulfamoylamino group, an alkylthio group, an arylthio
group, an alkoxycarbonylamino group, a sulfonamido group,
a carbamoyl group, a sulfamoyl group, a sulfonyl group, an
alkoxycarbonyl group, a heterocyclic oxy group, an azo
group, an acyloxy group, a carbamoyloxy group, a silyloxy
group, an aryloxycarbonyl group, an aryloxycarbonylamino
group, an imido group, a heterocyclic thio group, a
phosphoryl group, an acyl group, a carboxyl group or a
sulfo group. These substituents each may further have a
substituent.</p><p num="0027">Among these, preferred are a hydrogen atom, a
halogen atom, an alkyl group, an aryl group, a cyano group,
an alkoxy group, an amido group, a ureido group, a
sulfonamido group, a carbamoyl group, a sulfamoyl group,
an alkoxycarbonyl group, a carboxyl group and a sulfo
group, more preferred are a hydrogen atom, a halogen atom,
a cyano group, a carboxyl group and a sulfo group, and
most preferred is a hydrogen atom.</p><p num="0028">When Z, R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> and Y<sub>4</sub> each is a group
which can further have a substituent, the group may 
further have the following substituent.</p><p num="0029">Examples of the substituent include a linear or
branched alkyl group having from 1 to 12 carbon atoms, a
linear or branched aralkyl group having from 7 to 18
carbon atoms, a linear or branched alkenyl group having
from 2 to 12 carbon atoms, a linear or branched alkynyl
group having from 2 to 12 carbon atoms, a linear or
branched cycloalkyl group having from 3 to 12 carbon atoms,
a linear or branched cycloalkenyl group having from 3 to
12 carbon atoms (these groups each is preferably a group
having a branched chain because the solubility of dye and
the stability of ink are improved, more preferably a group
having an asymmetric carbon, e.g., methyl, ethyl, propyl,
isopropyl, sec-butyl, tert-butyl, 2-ethylhexyl, 2-methylsulfonylethyl,
3-phenoxypropyl, trifluoromethyl,
cyclopentyl), a halogen atom (e.g., chlorine, bromine), an
aryl group (e.g., phenyl, 4-tert-butylphenyl, 2,4-di-tert-amylphenyl),
a heterocyclic group (e.g., imidazolyl,
pyrazolyl, triazolyl, 2-furyl, 2-thienyl, 2-pyrimidinyl,
2-benzothiazolyl), a cyano group, a hydroxyl group, a
nitro group, a carboxy group, an amino group, an alkyloxy
group (e.g., methoxy, ethoxy, 2-methoxyethoxy, 2-methane-sulfonylethoxy),
an aryloxy group (e.g., phenoxy, 2-methylphenoxy,
4-tert-butylphenoxy, 3-nitrophenoxy, 3-tert-butyloxycarbamoylphenoxy,
3-methoxycarbamoyl), an 
acylamino group (e.g., acetamido, benzamido, 4-(3-tert-butyl-4-hydroxyphenoxy)butanamido),
an alkylamino group
(e.g., methylamino, butylamino, diethylamino,
methylbutylamino), an anilino group (e.g., phenylamino, 2-chloroanilino),
a ureido group (e.g., phenylureido,
methylureido, N,N-dibutylureido), a sulfamoylamino group
(e.g., N,N-dipropylsulfamoylamino), an alkylthio group
(e.g., methylthio, octylthio, 2-phenoxyethylthio), an
arylthio group (e.g., phenylthio, 2-butoxy-5-tert-octylphenylthio,
2-carboxyphenylthio), an
alkyloxycarbonylamino group (e.g., methoxycarbonylamino),
a sulfonamido group (e.g., methanesulfonamido,
benzenesulfonamido, p-toluenesulfonamido), a carbamoyl
group (e.g., N-ethylcarbamoyl, N,N-dibutylcarbamoyl), a
sulfamoyl group (e.g., N-ethylsulfamoyl, N,N-dipropylsulfamoyl,
N-phenylsulfamoyl), a sulfonyl group
(e.g., methanesulfonyl, octanesulfonyl, benzenesulfonyl,
toluenesulfonyl), an alkyloxycarbonyl group (e.g.,
methoxycarbonyl, butyloxycarbonyl), a heterocyclic oxy
group (e.g., 1-phenyltetrazol-5-oxy, 2-tetrahydro-pyranyloxy),
an azo group (e.g., phenylazo, 4-methoxyphenylazo,
4-pivaloylaminophenylazo, 2-hydroxy-4-propanoylphenylazo),
an acyloxy group (e.g., acetoxy), a
carbamoyloxy group (e.g., N-methylcarbamoyloxy, N-phenyl-carbamoyloxy),
a silyloxy group (e.g., trimethylsilyloxy, 
dibutylmethylsilyloxy), an aryloxycarbonylamino group
(e.g., phenoxycarbonylamino), an imido group (e.g., N-succinimido,
N-phthalimido), a heterocyclic thio group
(e.g., 2-benzothiazolylthio, 2,4-di-phenoxy-1,3,5-triazole-6-thio,
2-pyridylthio), a sulfinyl group (e.g.,
3-phenoxypropylsulfinyl), a phosphonyl group (e.g.,
phenoxyphosphonyl, octyloxyphosphonyl, phenylphosphonyl),
an aryloxycarbonyl group (e.g., phenoxycarbonyl), an acyl
group (e.g., acetyl, 3-phenylpropanoyl, benzoyl), and an
ionic hydrophilic group (e.g., carboxyl, sulfo, phosphono,
quaternary ammonium).</p><p num="0030">In the case where the phthalocyanine dye represented
by formula (I) is water-soluble, the dye preferably has an
ionic hydrophilic group. Examples of the ionic
hydrophilic group include a sulfo group, a carboxyl group,
a phosphono group and a quaternary ammonium group. Among
these ionic hydrophilic groups, preferred are a carboxyl
group, a phosphono group and a sulfo group, more preferred
are a carboxyl group and a sulfo group. The carboxyl
group, the phosphono group and the sulfo group each may be
in the form of a salt and examples of the counter ion for
forming the salt include ammonium ion, alkali metal ion
(e.g., lithium ion, sodium ion, potassium ion) and organic
cation (e.g., tetramethylammonium ion,
tetramethylguanidium ion, tetramethylphosphonium). Among 
these counter ions, an alkali metal salt is preferred and
a lithium salt is more preferred because this salt
enhances the solubility of dye and improves the stability
of ink.</p><p num="0031">As for the number of ionic hydrophilic groups, the
phthalocyanine dye preferably has at least two ionic
hydrophilic groups, more preferably at least two sulfo
groups and/or carboxyl groups, within one molecule.</p><p num="0032">a<sub>1</sub> to a<sub>4</sub> and b<sub>1</sub> to b<sub>4</sub> each represents the number of
substituent X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>, X<sub>3</sub>, X<sub>4</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> or Y<sub>4</sub>. a<sub>1</sub> to a<sub>4</sub> each
independently represents a number of 0 to 4 but all are
not 0 at the same time. b<sub>1</sub> to b<sub>4</sub> each independently
represents a number of 0 to 4. When at least one of a<sub>1</sub> to
a<sub>4</sub> and b<sub>1</sub> to b<sub>4</sub> each represents a number of 2 or more, a
corresponding plurality of substituents of at least one of
X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>, X<sub>3</sub>, X<sub>4</sub>, Y<sub>1</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>, Y<sub>3</sub> or Y<sub>4</sub> may be the same or different.</p><p num="0033">a<sub>1</sub> and b<sub>1</sub> each independently represents a number of 0
to 4 satisfying the relationship of a<sub>1</sub>+b<sub>1</sub>=4. In particular,
a combination that a<sub>1</sub> represents 1 or 2 and b<sub>1</sub> represents 3
or. 2 is preferred, and a combination that a<sub>1</sub> represents 1
and b<sub>1</sub> represents 3 is most preferred.</p><p num="0034">The same relationship as that between a<sub>1</sub> and b<sub>1</sub> is
present in each of the pairs a<sub>2</sub> and b<sub>2</sub>, a<sub>3</sub> and b<sub>3</sub>, and a<sub>4</sub>
and b<sub>4</sub>, and the preferred combination is also the same.</p><p num="0035">M represents a hydrogen atom, a metal element or an 
oxide, hydroxide or halide thereof.</p><p num="0036">M is preferably a hydrogen atom, a metal element
such as Li, Na, K, Mg, Ti, Zr, V, Nb, Ta, Cr, Mo, W, Mn,
Fe, Co, Ni, Ru, Rh, Pd, Os, Ir, Pt, Cu, Ag, Au, Zn, Cd, Hg,
Al, Ga, In, Si, Ge, Sn, Pb, Sb and Bi, an oxide such as VO
and GeO, a hydroxide such as Si(OH)<sub>2</sub>, Cr(OH)<sub>2</sub> and Sn(OH)<sub>2</sub>,
or a halide such as AlCl, SiCl<sub>2</sub>, VCl, VCl<sub>2</sub>, VOCl, FeCl,
GaCl and ZrCl.</p><p num="0037">Among these, preferred are Cu, Ni, Zn and Al, and
most preferred is Cu.</p><p num="0038">Also, Pc (phthalocyanine ring) may form a dimer (for
example, Pc-M-L-M-Pc) or a trimer through L (divalent
linking group). At this time, Ms may be the same or
different.</p><p num="0039">The divalent linking group represented by L is
preferably an oxy group -O-, a thio group -S-, a carbonyl
group -CO-, a sulfonyl group -SO<sub>2</sub>-, an imino group -NH-, a
methylene group -CH<sub>2</sub>- or a group formed by combining two
or more of these groups.</p><p num="0040">As for the preferred combination of substituents in
the compound represented by formula (I), a compound where
at least one of various substituents is the preferred
group is preferred, a compound where a larger number of
various substituents are the preferred groups is more
preferred, and a compound where all substituents are the 
preferred groups is most preferred.</p><p num="0041">Among the phthalocyanine dyes represented by formula
(I), a phthalocyanine dye having a structure represented
by formula (II) is preferred. The phthalocyanine dye
represented by formula (II) of the present invention is
described in detail below.</p><p num="0042">In formula (II), X<sub>11</sub> to X<sub>14</sub> and Y<sub>11</sub> to Y<sub>18</sub> have the
same meanings as X<sub>1</sub> to X<sub>4</sub> and Y<sub>1</sub> to Y<sub>4</sub> in formula (I),
respectively, and preferred examples are also the same. M
has the same meaning as M in formula (I) and preferred
examples are also the same.</p><p num="0043">In formula (II), a<sub>11</sub> to a<sub>14</sub> each independently
represents an integer of 1 or 2 and preferably satisfy
4≤a<sub>11</sub>+a<sub>12</sub>+a<sub>13</sub>+a<sub>14</sub>≤6, and a<sub>11</sub>=a<sub>12</sub>=a<sub>13</sub>=a<sub>14</sub>=1 is more preferred.</p><p num="0044">X<sub>11</sub>, X<sub>12</sub>, X<sub>13</sub> and X<sub>14</sub> may be completely the same
substituents, may be substituents of the same kind but
partially different as in the case, for example, where X<sub>11</sub>,
X<sub>12</sub>, X<sub>13</sub> and X<sub>14</sub> all are -SO<sub>2</sub>-Z and Zs are different from
each other, or may include substituents different from
each other, for example, -SO<sub>2</sub>-Z and -SO<sub>2</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0045">In the phthalocyanine dye represented by formula
(II), the following combination of substituents is
particularly preferred.</p><p num="0046">X<sub>11</sub> to X<sub>14</sub> each independently represents
preferably -SO-Z, -SO<sub>2</sub>-Z, -SO<sub>2</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub> or -CONR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>, more 
preferably -SO<sub>2</sub>Z or -SO<sub>2</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>, most preferably -SO<sub>2</sub>-Z.</p><p num="0047">Each Z independently represents preferably a
substituted or unsubstituted alkyl group, a substituted or
unsubstituted aryl group or a substituted or unsubstituted
heterocyclic group, and most preferably a substituted
alkyl group, a substituted aryl group or a substituted
heterocyclic group. In particular, the case where an
asymmetric carbon is present in the substituent (use in
the racemic form) is preferred because the solubility of
dye and the stability of ink are enhanced. Also, the case
where a hydroxyl group, an ether group, an ester group, a
cyano group, an amido group or a sulfonamido group is
present in the substituent is preferred because the
aggregating property and fastness are improved.</p><p num="0048">R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> each independently represents preferably a
hydrogen atom, a substituted or unsubstituted alkyl group,
a substituted or unsubstituted aryl group or a substituted
or unsubstituted heterocyclic group, and most preferably a
hydrogen atom, a substituted alkyl group, a substituted
aryl group or a substituted heterocyclic group. However,
it is not preferred that R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> both are a hydrogen atom.
In particular, the case where an asymmetric carbon is
present in the substituent (use in the racemic form) is
preferred because the solubility of dye and the stability
of ink are enhanced. Also, the case where a hydroxyl 
group, an ether group, an ester group, a cyano group, an
amido group or a sulfonamido group is present in the
substituent is preferred because the aggregating property
and fastness are improved.</p><p num="0049">Y<sub>11</sub> to Y<sub>18</sub> each independently represents preferably a
hydrogen atom, a halogen atom, an alkyl group, an aryl
group, a cyano group, an alkoxy group, an amido group, a
ureido group, a sulfonamido group, a carbamoyl group, a
sulfamoyl group, an alkoxycarbonyl group, a carboxyl group
or a sulfo group, more preferably a hydrogen atom, a
halogen atom, a cyano group, a carboxyl group or a sulfo
group, and most preferably a hydrogen atom.</p><p num="0050">a<sub>11</sub> to a<sub>14</sub> each independently represents preferably 1
or 2 and it is particularly preferred that all are 1.</p><p num="0051">M represents a hydrogen atom, a metal element or an
oxide, hydroxide or halide thereof, more preferably Cu, Ni,
Zn or Al, and most preferably Cu.</p><p num="0052">In the case where the phthalocyanine dye represented
by formula (II) is water-soluble, the dye preferably has
an ionic hydrophilic group. Examples of the ionic
hydrophilic group include a sulfo group, a carboxyl group,
a phosphono group and a quaternary ammonium group. Among
these ionic hydrophilic groups, preferred are a carboxyl
group, a phosphono group and a sulfo group, more preferred
are a carboxyl group and a sulfo group. The carboxyl 
group, the phosphono group and the sulfo group each may be
in the form of a salt and examples of the counter ion for
forming the salt include ammonium ion, alkali metal ion
(e.g., lithium ion, sodium ion, potassium ion) and organic
cation (e.g., tetramethylammonium ion,
tetramethylguanidium ion, tetramethylphosphonium). Among
these counter ions, an alkali metal salt is preferred and
a lithium salt is more preferred because this salt
enhances the solubility of dye and improves the stability
of ink.</p><p num="0053">As for the number of ionic hydrophilic groups, the
phthalocyanine dye preferably has at least two ionic
hydrophilic groups, more preferably at least two sulfo
groups and/or carboxyl groups, within one molecule.</p><p num="0054">As for the preferred combination of substituents in
the compound represented by formula (II), a compound where
at least one of various substituents is the preferred
group is preferred, a compound where a larger number of
various substituents are the preferred groups is more
preferred, and a compound where all substituents are the
preferred groups is most preferred.</p><p num="0055">As for the chemical structure of the phthalocyanine
dye of the present invention, at least one electron
withdrawing group such as sulfinyl group, sulfonyl group
and sulfamoyl group is preferably introduced into 
respective four benzene rings of phthalocyanine such that
the total of σp values of the substituents in the entire
phthalocyanine skeleton becomes 1.6 or more.</p><p num="0056">The Hammett's substituent constant σp value is
briefly described. The Hammett's rule is a rule of thumb
advocated by L.P. Hammett in 1935 so as to quantitatively
discuss the effect of substituent on the reaction or
equilibrium of benzene derivatives and its propriety is
widely admitted at present. The substituent constant
determined by the Hammett's rule includes a σp value and a
σm value and these values can be found in a large number
of general publications but these are described in detail,
for example, in J.A. Dean (compiler), <u style="single">Lange's Handbook of
Chemistry,</u> 12th ed., McGraw-Hell (1979), and <u style="single">Kagakuno
Ryoiki (Chemistry Region),</u> special number, No. 122, pp.
96-103, Nankodo (1979).</p><p num="0057">Generally, in view of the synthesis method, the
phthalocyanine derivative represented by formula (I) is
inevitably a mixture of analogues differing in the site
where the substituents Xn (n=1 to 4) and Ym (m=1 to 4) are
introduced and in the number of the substituents
introduced. Accordingly, these analogue mixtures are
statistically averaged and represented by a formula in
many cases. In the present invention, it has been found
that when these analogue mixtures are classified into the 
following three types, a specific mixture is particularly
preferred. The phthalocyanine-base dye analogue mixtures
represented by formulae (I) and (II) are defined by
classifying these into the following three types based on
the substitution site.</p><heading>(1) β-Position substitution type:</heading><p num="0058">A phthalocyanine dye having specific substituents at
the 2- and/or 3-position, the 6- and/or 7-position, the
10- and/or 11-position, and the 14- and/or 15-position.</p><heading>(2) α-Position substitution type:</heading><p num="0059">A phthalocyanine dye having specific substituents at
the 1- and/or 4-position, the 5- and/or 8-position, the 9-and/or
12-position, and the 13- and/or 16-position.</p><heading>(3) α,β-Position mixed substitution type:</heading><p num="0060">A phthalocyanine dye having specific substitutions
at the 1- to 16-positions without any regularity.</p><p num="0061">In the present invention, phthalocyanine dye
derivatives different in the structure (particularly in
the substitution site) are described by using these β-position
substitution type, α-position substitution type
and α,β-position mixed substitution type.</p><p num="0062">The phthalocyanine derivative for use in the present
invention can be synthesized by combining the methods
described or cited, for example, in Shirai and Kobayashi,
<u style="single">Phthalocyanine -Kagaku to Kino- (Phthalocyanine -Chemistry</u><u style="single">and Function-),</u> pp. 1-62, IPC, and C.C. Leznoff and A.B.P.
Lever, <u style="single">Phthalocyanines - Properties and Applications,</u>
pp. 1-54, VCH, or methods analogous thereto.</p><p num="0063">The phthalocyanine compound represented by formula
(I) of the present invention can be synthesized, for
example, through sulfonation, sulfonyl chloridation and
amidation of an unsubstituted phthalocyanine compound as
described in International Patents 00/17275, 00/08103,
00/08101 and 98/41853 and JP-A-10-36471 (the term "JP-A"
as used herein means an "unexamined published Japanese
patent application"). In this case, sulfonation may take
place at any site of the phthalocyanine nucleus and the
number of sites sulfonated is difficult to control.
Accordingly, when a sulfo group is introduced under such
reaction conditions, the site and number of sulfo groups
introduced into the product cannot be specified and a
mixture of those different in the number of substituents
or in the substitution site inevitably results. If the
compound of the present invention is synthesized starting
from such a product, the compound of the present invention
is obtained as an α,β-position mixed substitution type
mixture containing several kinds of compounds different in
the number of substituents or in the substitution site
because the number of sulfamoyl groups substituted on the
heterocyclic ring or their substitution sites cannot be 
specified.</p><p num="0064">As described above, for example, when many electron
withdrawing groups such as sulfamoyl group are introduced
into the phthalocyanine nucleus, the oxidation potential
becomes nobler and the ozone resistance is increased.
However, according to the above-described synthesis method,
a phthalocyanine dye where the number of electron
withdrawing groups introduced is small, namely, the
oxidation potential is baser, is inevitably mingled.
Accordingly, in order to improve the ozone resistance, it
is preferred to use a synthesis method where the
production of a compound having a baser oxidation
potential is suppressed.</p><p num="0065">On the other hand, the phthalocyanine compound
represented by formula (II) of the present invention can
be synthesized, for example, by reacting a phthalonitrile
derivative (Compound P) shown below and/or a
diiminoisoindoline derivative (Compound Q) shown below
with a metal derivative represented by formula (III) or
may be derived from a tetrasulfophthalocyanine compound
obtained by reacting a 4-sulfophthalonitrile derivative
(Compound R) shown below with a metal derivative
represented by formula (III). <img id="img-00290001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00290001.tif" inline="no" he="219"/></p><p num="0066">In the formulae above, X<sub>p</sub> corresponds to X<sub>11</sub>, X<sub>12</sub>, X<sub>13</sub>
or X<sub>14</sub> in formula (II) and Y<sub>q</sub> and Y<sub>q'</sub> each corresponds to 
Y<sub>11</sub>, Y<sub>12</sub>, Y<sub>13</sub>, Y<sub>14</sub>, Y<sub>15</sub>, Y<sub>16</sub>, Y<sub>17</sub> or Y<sub>18</sub> in formula (II). In
Compound R, M' represents cation. Examples of the cation
represented by M' include alkali metal ion such as Li, Na
and K, and organic cation such as triethylammonium ion and
pyridinium ion.
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Formula (III):

M-(Y)<sub>d</sub></st32:che>
wherein M has the same meaning as M in formulae (I) and
(II), Y represents a monovalent or divalent ligand such as
halogen atom, acetate anion, acetylacetonate and oxygen,
and d represents an integer of 1 to 4.</p><p num="0067">That is, according to this synthesis method, a
specific number of desired substituents can be introduced.
Particularly, in the case of introducing a large number of
electron withdrawing groups so as to render the oxidation
potential nobler as in the present invention, this
synthesis method is very excellent as compared with the
above-described method for synthesizing the phthalocyanine
compound of formula (I).</p><p num="0068">The thus-obtained phthalocyanine compound
represented by formulae (II) is usually a mixture of
compounds represented by the following formulae (a)-1 to
(a)-4 which are isomers in respect to the substitution
site of each X<sub>p</sub>, namely, a β-position substitution type. <img id="img-00310001" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00310001.tif" inline="no" he="112"/><img id="img-00310002" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00310002.tif" inline="no" he="112"/><img id="img-00320001" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00320001.tif" inline="no" he="115"/><img id="img-00320002" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00320002.tif" inline="no" he="111"/></p><p num="0069">In the synthesis method above, when all Xp are the 
same, a β-position substitution type phthalocyanine dye
where X<sub>11</sub>, X<sub>12</sub>, X<sub>13</sub> and X<sub>14</sub> are completely the same
substituents can be obtained. On the other hand, when Xp
are different, a dye having substituents of the same kind
but partially different from each other or a dye having
substituents different from each other can be synthesized.
Among the dyes of formula (II), these dyes having electron
withdrawing substituents different from each other are
preferred because the solubility and aggregating property
of dye and the aging stability of ink can be controlled.</p><p num="0070">In the present invention, it has been found very
important in any substitution type for the improvement of
fastness that the oxidation potential is nobler than 1.0 V
(vs SCE). The great effect thereof cannot be expected at
all from the above-described known techniques.
Furthermore, although the cause is not particularly known,
there is a tendency that the β-position substitution type
is apparently more excellent in the color, light fastness,
ozone resistance and the like than the α,β-position mixed
substitution type.</p><p num="0071">Specific examples (Compounds I-1 to I-12 and 101 to
190) of the phthalocyanine dyes represented by formulae
(I) and (II) are set forth below, however, the
phthalocyanine dye for use in the present invention is not
limited to the following examples. </p><heading>Compounds:</heading><p num="0072"><img id="img-00340001" orientation="unknown" wi="124" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00340001.tif" inline="no" he="99"/><img id="img-00340002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00340002.tif" inline="no" he="107"/><img id="img-00350001" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350001.tif" inline="no" he="106"/><img id="img-00350002" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350002.tif" inline="no" he="105"/><img id="img-00360001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00360001.tif" inline="no" he="116"/><img id="img-00360002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00360002.tif" inline="no" he="111"/><img id="img-00370001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00370001.tif" inline="no" he="130"/><img id="img-00370002" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf"  file="00370002.tif" inline="no" he="108"/><img id="img-00380001" orientation="unknown" wi="161"  img-format="tif"  img-content="cf"  file="00380001.tif" inline="no" he="126"/><img id="img-00380002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00380002.tif" inline="no" he="104"/><img id="img-00390001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390001.tif" inline="no" he="124"/><img id="img-00390002" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390002.tif" inline="no" he="98"/></p><p num="0073">In the following Tables, specific examples of each
pair of (X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>), (Y<sub>11</sub>, Y<sub>12</sub>), (Y<sub>13</sub>, Y<sub>14</sub>), (Y<sub>15</sub>, Y<sub>16</sub>) and (Y<sub>17</sub>,
Y<sub>18</sub>) are independently in an irregular order. <img id="img-00410001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00410001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/><img id="img-00420001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00420001.tif" inline="no" he="232"/><img id="img-00430001" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00430001.tif" inline="no" he="229"/><img id="img-00440001" orientation="unknown" wi="150" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00440001.tif" inline="no" he="232"/><img id="img-00450001" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00450001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/><img id="img-00460001" orientation="unknown" wi="147" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00460001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/><img id="img-00470001" orientation="unknown" wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00470001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/></p><p num="0074">In the following Tables, each introduction site of
substituents (R<sub>1</sub>) and (R<sub>2</sub>) is in an irregular order within
the β-position substitution type. <img id="img-00490001" orientation="unknown" wi="145" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00490001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/><img id="img-00500001" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00500001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/><img id="img-00510001" orientation="unknown" wi="158" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00510001.tif" inline="no" he="229"/><img id="img-00520001" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00520001.tif" inline="no" he="229"/></p><p num="0075">The structural formula of the phthalocyanine
compound represented by M-Pc(X<sub>p1</sub>)<sub>m</sub>(X<sub>p2</sub>)<sub>n</sub> in Tables 8 to 11
is shown below:
<img id="img-00530001" orientation="unknown" wi="120" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00530001.tif" inline="no" he="92"/>
(wherein each X<sub>p1</sub> is independently X<sub>p1</sub> or X<sub>p2</sub>).</p><p num="0076">The phthalocyanine dye represented by formula (I)
can be synthesized according to the patent publications
described above. Furthermore, the phthalocyanine dye
represented by formula (II) can be synthesized by the
methods described in JP-A-2001-226275, JP-A-2001-96610,
JP-A-2001-47013 and JP-A-2001-193638. The starting
material, dye intermediate and synthesis route are not
limited to those described in these patent publications.</p><p num="0077">The inkjet recording ink of the present invention
contains the above-described phthalocyanine dye in an 
amount of preferably from 0.2 to 20 % by weight, more
preferably from 0.5 to 15 % by weight.</p><p num="0078">In combination with the above-described cyan dye,
other dyes may be used in the inkjet recording ink of the
present invention so as to adjust the color tone for
obtaining a full color image. Examples of the dye which
can be used in combination include the followings.</p><p num="0079">Examples of the yellow dye include aryl- or heteryl-azo
dyes having a phenol, a naphthol, an aniline, a
pyrazolone, a pyridone or an open chain-type active
methylene compound as the coupling component; azomethine
dyes having an open chain-type active methylene compound
as the coupling component; methine dyes such as
benzylidene dye and monomethine oxonol dye; and quinone-base
dyes such as naphthoquinone dye and anthraquinone dye.
Other examples of the dye species include quinophthalone
dye, nitro·nitroso dye, acridine dye and acridinone dye.
These dyes may be a dye which provides a yellow color for
the first time when a part of the chromophore is
dissociated. In this case, the counter cation may be an
inorganic cation such as alkali metal and ammonium, an
organic cation such as pyridinium and quaternary ammonium
salt, or a polymer cation having such a cation as a
partial structure.</p><p num="0080">Examples of the magenta dye include aryl- or 
heteryl-azo dyes having a phenol, a naphthol or an aniline
as the coupling component; azomethine dyes having a
pyrazolone or a pyrazolotriazole as the coupling
component; methine dyes such as arylidene dye, styryl dye,
merocyanine dye and oxonol dye; carbonium dyes such as
diphenylmethane dye, triphenylmethane dye and xanthene
dye; quinone-base dyes such as naphthoquinone,
anthraquinone and anthrapyridone; and condensed polycyclic
dyes such as dioxazine dye. These dyes may be a dye which
provides a magenta color for the first time when a part of
the chromophore is dissociated. In this case, the counter
cation may be an inorganic cation such as alkali metal and
ammonium, an organic cation such as pyridinium and
quaternary ammonium salt, or a polymer cation having such
a cation as a partial structure.</p><p num="0081">Examples of the cyan dye include azomethine dyes
such as indoaniline dye and indophenol dye; polymethine
dyes such as cyanine dye, oxonol dye and merocyanine dye;
carbonium dyes such as diphenylmethane dye,
triphenylmethane dye and xanthene dye; phthalocyanine
dyes; anthraquinone dyes; aryl- or heteryl-azo dyes having
a phenol, a naphthol or an aniline as the coupling
component; and indigo.thioindigo dyes. These dyes may be
a dye which provides a cyan color for the first time when
a part of the chromophore is dissociated. In this case, 
the counter cation may be an inorganic cation such as
alkali metal and ammonium, an organic cation such as
pyridinium and quaternary ammonium salt, or a polymer
cation having such a cation as a partial structure.</p><p num="0082">A black dye such as polyazo dye can also be used.</p><p num="0083">Examples of the water-soluble dye include a direct
dye, an acid dye, a food color, a basic dye and a reactive
dye. Preferred examples thereof include C.I. Direct Red 2,
4, 9, 23, 26, 31, 39, 62, 63, 72, 75, 76, 79, 80, 81, 83,
84, 89, 92, 95, 111, 173, 184, 207, 211, 212, 214, 218, 21,
223, 224, 225, 226, 227, 232, 233, 240, 241, 242, 243 and
247; C.I. Direct Violet 7, 9, 47, 48, 51, 66, 90, 93, 94,
95, 98, 100 and 101; C.I. Direct Yellow 8, 9, 11, 12, 27,
28, 29, 33, 35, 39, 41, 44, 50, 53, 58, 59, 68, 86, 87, 93,
95, 96, 98, 100, 106, 108, 109, 110, 130, 132, 142, 144,
161 and 163; C.I. Direct Blue 1, 10, 15, 22, 25, 55, 67,
68, 71, 76, 77, 78, 80, 84, 86, 87, 90, 98, 106, 108, 109,
151, 156, 158, 159, 160, 168, 189, 192, 193, 194, 199, 200,
201, 202, 203, 207, 211, 213, 214, 218, 225, 229, 236, 237,
244, 248, 249, 251, 252, 264, 270, 280, 288, 289 and 291;
C.I. Direct Black 9, 17, 19, 22, 32, 51, 56, 62, 69, 77,
80, 91, 94, 97, 108, 112, 113, 114, 117, 118, 121, 122,
125, 132, 146, 154, 166, 168, 173 and 199; C.I. Acid Red
35, 42, 52, 57, 62, 80, 82, 111, 114, 118, 119, 127, 128,
131, 143, 151, 154, 158, 249, 254, 257, 261, 263, 266, 289, 
299, 301, 305, 336, 337, 361, 396 and 397; C.I. Acid
Violet 5, 34, 43, 47, 48, 90, 103 and 126; C.I. Acid
Yellow 17, 19, 23, 25, 39, 40, 42, 44, 49, 50, 61, 64, 76,
79, 110, 127, 135, 143, 151, 159, 169, 174, 190, 195, 196,
197, 199, 218, 219, 222 and 227; C.I. Acid Blue 9, 25, 40,
41, 62, 72, 76, 78, 80, 82, 92, 106, 112, 113, 120, 127:1,
129, 138, 143, 175, 181, 205, 207, 220, 221, 230, 232, 247,
258, 260, 264, 271, 277, 278, 279, 280, 288, 290 and 326;
C.I. Acid Black 7, 24, 29, 48, 52:1 and 172; C.I. Reactive
Red 3, 13, 17, 19, 21, 22, 23, 24, 29, 35, 37, 40, 41, 43,
45, 49 and 55; C.I. Reactive Violet 1, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
16, 17, 22, 23, 24, 26, 27, 33 and 34; C.I. Reactive
Yellow 2, 3, 13, 14, 15, 17, 18, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 29,
35, 37, 41 and 42; C.I. Reactive Blue 2, 3, 5, 8, 10, 13,
14, 15, 17, 18, 19, 21, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29 and 38; C.I.
Reactive Black 4, 5, 8, 14, 21, 23, 26, 31, 32 and 34; C.I.
Basic Red 12, 13, 14, 15, 18, 22, 23, 24, 25, 27, 29, 35,
36, 38, 39, 45 and 46; C.I. Basic Violet 1, 2, 3, 7, 10,
15, 16, 20, 21, 25, 27, 28, 35, 37, 39, 40 and 48; C.I.
Basic Yellow 1, 2, 4, 11, 13, 14, 15, 19, 21, 23, 24, 25,
28, 29, 32, 36, 39 and 40; C.I. Basic Blue 1, 3, 5, 7, 9,
22, 26, 41, 45, 46, 47, 54, 57, 60, 62, 65, 66, 69 and 71;
and C.I. Basic Black 8.</p><p num="0084">The dye containing the phthalocyanine dye for use in
the present invention is substantially soluble or 
dispersible in water. More specifically, the solubility
of the dye in water at 20°C is preferably 10 % by weight
or more, more preferably 15 % by weight or more.</p><p num="0085">In the ink of the present invention, a pigment can
also be used in combination.</p><p num="0086">As the pigment for use in the present invention,
commercially available pigments and known pigments
described in various publications can be used. The
publication includes <u style="single">Color Index,</u> compiled by The Society
of Dyers and Colourists, <u style="single">Kaitei Shin Han Ganryo Binran
(Revised New Handbook of Pigments),</u> compiled by Nippon
Ganryo Gijutsu Kyokai (1989), <u style="single">Saishin Ganryo Oyo Gijutsu
(Newest Pigment Application Technology),</u> CMC Shuppan
(1986), <u style="single">Insatsu Ink Gijutsu (Printing Ink Technique),</u> CMC
Shuppan (1984), and W. Herbst and K. Hunger, <u style="single">Industrial
Organic Pigments,</u> VCH Verlagsgesellschaft (1993).
Specific examples of the organic pigment include azo
pigments (e.g., azo lake pigment, insoluble azo pigment,
condensed azo pigment, chelate azo pigment), polycyclic
pigments (e.g., phthalocyanine-base pigment,
anthraquinone-base pigment, perylene-base and perynone-base
pigment, indigo-base pigment, quinacridone-base
pigment, dioxazine-base pigment, isoindolinone-base
pigment, quinophthalone-base pigment,
diketopyrrolopyrrole-base pigment), dyeing lake pigments 
(lake pigments of acidic or basic dye) and azine pigments.
Specific examples of the inorganic pigment include yellow
pigments such as C.I. Pigment Yellow 34, 37, 42 and 53,
red-base pigments such as C.I. Pigment Red 101 and 108,
blue-base pigments such as C.I. Pigment Blue 27, 29 and
17:1, black-base pigments such as C.I. Pigment Black 7 and
magnetite, and white-base pigments such as C.I. Pigment
White 4, 6, 18 and 21.</p><p num="0087">The pigments having a preferred color tone for the
formation of an image include the followings. As the blue
to cyan pigment, phthalocyanine pigments, anthraquinone-type
indanthrone pigments (for example, C.I. Pigment Blue
60) and dyeing lake pigment-type triarylcarbonium pigments
are preferred, and phthalocyanine pigments are most
preferred (preferred examples thereof include copper
phthalocyanine such as C.I. Pigment Blue 15:1, 15:2, 15:3,
15:4 and 15:6, monochloro or low chlorinated copper
phthalocyanine, aluminum phthalocyanine such as pigments
described in European Patent 860475, nonmetallic
phthalocyanine such as C.I. Pigment Blue 16, and
phthalocyanine with the center metal being Zn, Ni or Ti,
and among these, C.I. Pigment Blue 15:3 and 15:4 and
aluminum phthalocyanine are more preferred).</p><p num="0088">As the red to violet pigment, azo pigments
(preferred examples thereof include C.I. Pigment Red 3, 5, 
11, 22, 38, 48:1, 48:2, 48:3, 48:4, 49:1, 52:1, 53:1, 57:1,
63:2, 144, 146 and 184, and among these, C.I. Pigment Red
57:1, 146 and 184 are more preferred), quinacridone-base
pigments (preferred examples thereof include C.I. Pigment
Red 122, 192, 202, 207 and 209 and C.I. Pigment Violet 19
and 42, and among these, C.I. Pigment Red 122 is more
preferred), dyeing lake pigment-type triarylcarbonium
pigments (preferred examples thereof include xanthene-base
C.I. Pigment Red 81:1 and C.I. Pigment Violet 1, 2, 3, 27
and 39), dioxazine-base pigments (for example, C.I.
Pigment Violet 23 and 37), diketopyrrolopyrrole-base
pigments (for example, C.I. Pigment Red 254), perylene
pigments (for example, C.I. Pigment Violet 29),
anthraquinone-base pigments (for example, C.I. Pigment
Violet 5:1, 31 and 33) and thioindigo-base pigments (for
example, C.I. Pigment Red 38 and 88) are preferred.</p><p num="0089">As the yellow pigment, azo pigments (preferred
examples thereof include monoazo pigment-type C.I. Pigment
Yellow 1, 3, 74 and 98, disazo pigment-type C.I. Pigment
Yellow 12, 13, 14, 16, 17 and 83, synthetic azo-type C.I.
Pigment 93, 94, 95, 128 and 155, and benzimidazolone-type
C.I. Pigment Yellow 120, 151, 154, 156 and 180, and among
these, those not using a benzidine-base compound as a raw
material are more preferred), isoindoline·isoindolinone-base
pigments (preferred examples thereof include C.I. 
Pigment Yellow 109, 110, 137 and 139,), quinophthalone
pigments (preferred examples thereof include C.I. Pigment
Yellow 138) and flavanthrone pigments (for example, C.I.
Pigment Yellow 24) are preferred.</p><p num="0090">As the black pigment, inorganic pigments (preferred
examples thereof include carbon black and magnetite) and
aniline black are preferred.</p><p num="0091">Other than these, an orange pigment (for example,
C.I. Pigment Orange 13 and 16) and a green pigment (for
example, C.I. Pigment Green 7) may be used.</p><p num="0092">The pigment which can be used in the present
invention may be the above-described pigment as it is or a
pigment after the surface treatment. For the surface
treatment, a method of coating the surface with resin or
wax, a method of attaching a surfactant, and a method of
binding a reactive substance (for example, a radical
generated from a silane coupling agent, an epoxy compound,
polyisocyanate or a diazonium salt) to the pigment surface
may be used and these are described in the following
publications and patents:
<sl><li>(1) <u style="single">Kinzoku Sekken no Seishitsu to Oyo (Properties
and Applications of Metal Soap),</u> Saiwai Shobo;</li><li>(2) <u style="single">Insatsu Ink Insatsu (Printing Ink Printing),</u>
CMC Shuppan (1984);</li><li>(3) <u style="single">Saishin Ganryo Oyo Gijutsu (Newest Pigment</u><u style="single">Application Technology),</u> CMC Shuppan (1986);</li><li>(4) U.S. Patents 5,554,739 and 5,571,311; and</li><li>(5) JP-A-9-151342, JP-A-10-140065, JP-A-10-292143
and JP-A-11-166145.</li></sl></p><p num="0093">Particularly, self-dispersible pigments prepared by
allowing a diazonium salt to act on carbon black described
in U.S. Patents of (4) and capsulated pigments prepared by
the method described in Japanese Patent Publications of
(5) are effective because dispersion stability can be
obtained without using an excess dispersant in the ink.</p><p num="0094">In the present invention, the pigment may be
dispersed by further using a dispersant. Various known
dispersants can be used according to the pigment used, for
example, a surfactant-type low molecular dispersant or a
polymer-type dispersant can be used. Examples of the
dispersant include those described in JP-A-3-69949 and
European Patent 549486. In using the dispersant, a
pigment derivative called synergist may also be added so
as to accelerate the adsorption of dispersant to the
pigment.</p><p num="0095">The particle size of the pigment which can be used
in the present invention is, after the dispersion,
preferably from 0.01 to 10 µm, more preferably from 0.05
to 1 µm.</p><p num="0096">As for the method of dispersing the pigment, known 
dispersion techniques used at the production of ink or
toner can be used. Examples of the dispersing machine
include vertical or horizontal agitator mill, attritor,
colloid mill, ball mill, three-roll mill, bar mill, super-mill,
impeller, disperser, KD mill, dynatron and pressure
kneader. These are described in detail in <u style="single">Saishin Ganryo
Oyo Gijutsu (Newest Pigment Application Technology),</u> CMC
Shuppan (1986).</p><p num="0097">In a recording medium having an image-receiving
layer, the ink of the present invention permeates to a
depth of 5 to 30 µm. With the permeation depth in this
range, an image having good cyan color and free from
generation of bronze can be obtained. The permeation
depth is preferably from 8 to 30 µm, more preferably from
10 to 30 µm.</p><p num="0098">The permeation depth can be measured, for example,
by cutting out a section or a slice of the recording
medium using a microtome and observing it through a
microscope.</p><p num="0099">The permeation depth varies depending on the
hydrophilic/hydrophobic balance due to the number of
hydrophilic group in the dye, the alkylene chain length in
the side chain, the amide bond and the like, but can be
controlled by the species of water-miscible organic
solvent which is described later, the amount of water-miscible 
organic solvent or the surfactant. For example,
when the dye is hydrophobic, the permeation is generally
shallow, however, the permeation can be promoted by
additionally adding 2-pyrrolidone, diethylene glycol,
triethylene glycol, glycerin, triethanolamine or the like
or increasing the amount thereof or by using a surfactant.</p><p num="0100">In order to attain a permeation depth in the desired
range, the water-miscible organic solvent is preferably
used to give a total content of 1 to 60 % by weight, more
preferably from 5 to 50 % by weight in the ink. The
amount of the surfactant used is preferably from 0.1 to
10 % by weight, more preferably from 0.5 to 6 % by weight.</p><p num="0101">The surfactant for use in the present invention is
described below.</p><p num="0102">Examples of the surfactant for use in the present
invention include anionic surfactants such as fatty acid
salts, ester salts of higher alcohol, alkylbenzenesulfonates,
sulfosuccinic acid ester salts, and phosphoric
acid ester salts of higher alcohol; cationic surfactants
such as aliphatic amine salts and quaternary ammonium
salts; nonionic surfactants such as ethylene oxide adducts
of higher alcohol, ethylene oxide adducts of alkylphenol,
ethylene oxide adducts of polyhydric alcohol fatty acid
ester, acetylene glycol and ethylene oxide adducts
thereof; amphoteric surfactants such as amino acid type 
and betaine type; and fluorine-containing or silicon-containing
compounds. These surfactants can be used
individually or in combination of two or more thereof.</p><p num="0103">When a surfactant is incorporated into the inkjet
recording ink of the present invention and the liquid
properties of the ink, such as surface tension, are
thereby adjusted, the ejection stability of ink can be
improved and an excellent effect can be provided on the
elevation of water resistance of image or prevention of
blurring of the printed ink.</p><p num="0104">The inkjet recording ink of the present invention
can be produced by dissolving the above-described phthalocyanine
dye in an aqueous medium, adding a specific amount
of a surfactant, and if desired, dissolving and/or
dispersing other additives. The "aqueous medium" as used
in the present invention means water or a mixture of water
and a slight amount of water-miscible organic solvent,
where additives such as wetting agent, stabilizer and
antiseptic are added, if desired.</p><p num="0105">At the preparation of the ink solution of the
present invention, in the case of a water-soluble ink, the
dye is preferably first dissolved in water and thereafter,
various solvents and additives are added, dissolved and
mixed to provide a uniform ink solution.</p><p num="0106">For dissolving the dye and the like, various methods 
such as stirring, ultrasonic irradiation and shaking can
be used. Among these, stirring is preferred. In
performing the stirring, various methods known in the art
can be used, such as flow stirring and stirring utilizing
the shearing force by means of a reversal agitator or a
dissolver. Also, a stirring method utilizing the shearing
force with the bottom surface of a container, such as
magnetic stirrer, can be advantageously used.</p><p num="0107">The preparation method of the aqueous ink for ink
jetting is described in detail in JP-A-5-148436, JP-A-5-295312,
JP-A-7-97541, JP-A-7-82515, JP-A-7-118584 and
Japanese Patent Application Nos. 2000-200780 and 2000-249799
and those described in these patent publications
can be utilized also in the preparation of the inkjet
recording ink of the present invention.</p><p num="0108">The aqueous medium may be a mixture mainly
comprising water, where a water-miscible organic solvent
is added, if desired. Examples of the water-miscible
organic solvent include alcohols (e.g., methanol, ethanol,
propanol, isopropanol, butanol, isobutanol, sec-butanol,
tert-butanol, pentanol, hexanol, cyclohexanol, benzyl
alcohol), polyhydric alcohols (e.g., ethylene glycol,
diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol, polyethylene glycol,
propylene glycol, dipropylene glycol, polypropylene glycol,
butylene glycol, hexanediol, pentanediol, glycerin, 
hexanetriol, thiodiglycol), glycol derivatives (e.g.,
ethylene glycol monomethyl ether, ethylene glycol
monoethyl ether, ethylene glycol monobutyl ether,
diethylene glycol monomethyl ether, diethylene glycol
monobutyl ether, propylene glycol monomethyl ether,
propylene glycol monobutyl ether, dipropylene glycol
monomethyl ether, triethylene glycol monomethyl ether,
ethylene glycol diacetate, ethylene glycol monomethyl
ether acetate, triethylene glycol monomethyl ether,
triethylene glycol monoethyl ether, ethylene glycol
monophenyl ether), amines (e.g., ethanolamine,
diethanolamine, triethanolamine, N-methyldiethanolamine,
N-ethyldiethanolamine, morpholine, N-ethylmorpholine,
ethylenediamine, diethylenetriamine, triethylenetetramine,
polyethyleneimine, tetramethylpropylenediamine) and other
polar solvents (e.g., formamide, N,N-dimethylformamide,
N,N-dimethylacetamide, dimethylsulfoxide, sulfolane, 2-pyrrolidone,
N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone, N-vinyl-2-pyrrolidone,
2-oxazolidone, 1,3-dimethyl-2-imidazolidinone,
acetonitrile, acetone). These water-miscible organic
solvents can be used in combination of two or more thereof.</p><p num="0109">In the case where the above-described phthalocyanine
dye is an oil-soluble dye, the ink solution can be
prepared by dissolving the oil-soluble dye in a high
boiling point organic solvent and emulsification-dispersing 
it in an aqueous medium.</p><p num="0110">The high boiling point organic solvent for use in
the present invention preferably has a boiling point of
150°C or more, more preferably 170°C or more.</p><p num="0111">Examples of the high boiling point organic solvent
include phthalic acid esters (e.g., dibutyl phthalate,
dioctyl phthalate, dicyclohexyl phthalate, di-2-ethylhexyl
phthalate, decyl phthalate, bis(2,4-di-tert-amylphenyl)
isophthalate, bis(1,1-diethylpropyl) phthalate), esters of
phosphoric acid or phosphone (e.g., diphenyl phosphate,
triphenyl phosphate, tricresyl phosphate, 2-ethylhexyl-diphenyl
phosphate, dioctylbutyl phosphate, tricyclohexyl
phosphate, tri-2-ethylhexyl phosphate, tridecyl phosphate,
di-2-ethylhexylphenyl phosphate), benzoic acid esters
(e.g., 2-ethylhexyl benzoate, 2,4-dichlorobenzoate,
dodecyl benzoate, 2-ethylhexyl-p-hydroxybenzoate), amides
(e.g., N,N-diethyldodecanamide, N,N-diethyllaurylamide),
alcohols or phenols (e.g., isostearyl alcohol, 2,4-di-tert-amylphenol),
aliphatic esters (e.g., dibutoxyethyl
succinate, di-2-ethylhexyl succinate, 2-hexyldecyl
tetradecanoate, tributyl citrate, diethyl azelate,
isostearyl lactate, trioctyl citrate), aniline derivatives
(e.g., N,N-dibutyl-2-butoxy-5-tert-octylaniline),
chlorinated paraffins (e.g., paraffins having a chlorine
content of 10 to 80%), trimesic acid esters (e.g., 
tributyl trimesate), dodecylbenzene,
diisopropylnaphthalene, phenols (e.g., 2,4-di-tert-amylphenyl,
4-dodecyloxyphenol, 4-dodecyloxycarbonylphenol,
4-(4-dodecyloxyphenylsulfonyl)phenol), carboxylic acids
(e.g., 2-(2,4-di-tert-amylphenoxy)butyric acid, 2-ethoxyoctanedecanoic
acid), alkylphosphoric acids (e.g.,
di-(2-ethylhexyl)phosphoric acid and diphenylphosphoric
acid). The high boiling point organic solvent can be used
in an amount of, in terms of the mass (weight) ratio to
the oil-soluble dye, from 0.01 to 3 times, preferably from
0.01 to 1.0 times.</p><p num="0112">These high boiling point organic solvents may be
used individually or as a mixture of several kinds [for
example, tricresyl phosphate and dibutyl phthalate,
trioctyl phosphate and di(2-ethylhexyl) sebacate, or
dibutyl phthalate and poly(N-tert-butylacrylamide)].</p><p num="0113">Examples of the high boiling point organic solvent
for use in the present invention, other than the above-described
compounds, and the synthesis method of these
high boiling organic solvents are described, for example,
in U.S. Patents 2,322,027, 2,533,514, 2,772,163, 2,835,579,
3,594,171, 3,676,137, 3,689,271, 3,700,454, 3,748,141,
3,764,336, 3,765,897, 3,912,515, 3,936,303, 4,004,928,
4,080,209, 4,127,413, 4,193,802, 4,207,393, 4,220,711,
4,239,851, 4,278,757, 4,353,979, 4,363,873, 4,430,421, 
4,430,422, 4,464,464, 4,483,918, 4,540,657, 4,684,606,
4,728,599, 4,745,049, 4,935,321 and 5,013,639, EP-A-276319,
EP-A-286253, EP-A-289820, EP-A-309158, EP-A-309159, EP-A-309160,
EP-A-509311, EP-A-510576, East German Patents
147,009, 157,147, 159,573 and 225,240A, British Patent
2091124A, JP-A-48-47335, JP-A-50-26530, JP-A-51-25133, JP-A-51-26036,
JP-A-51-27921, JP-A-51-27922, JP-A-51-149028,
JP-A-52-46816, JP-A-53-1520, JP-A-53-1521, JP-A-53-15127,
JP-A-53-146622, JP-A-54-91325, JP-A-54-106228, JP-A-54-118246,
JP-A-55-59464, JP-A-56-64333, JP-A-56-81836, JP-A-59-204041,
JP-A-61-84641, JP-A-62-118345, JP-A-62-247364,
JP-A-63-167357, JP-A-63-214744, JP-A-63-301941, JP-A-64-9452,
JP-A-64-9454, JP-A-64-68745, JP-A-1-101543, JP-A-1-102454,
JP-A-2-792, JP-A-2-4239, JP-A-2-43541, JP-A-4-29237,
JP-A-4-30165, JP-A-4-232946 and JP-A-4-346338.</p><p num="0114">The high boiling point organic solvent is used in a
mass (weight) ratio of 0.01 to 3.0 times, preferably from
0.01 to 1.0 times, to the oil-soluble dye.</p><p num="0115">In the present invention, the oil-soluble dye or
high boiling point organic solvent is used by
emulsification-dispersing it in an aqueous medium. At the
emulsification-dispersion, a low boiling point organic
solvent may be used in combination depending on the case
from the viewpoint of emulsifiability. The low boiling
point organic solvent which can be used in combination is 
an organic solvent having a boiling point of about 30°C to
150°C at atmospheric pressure. Preferred examples thereof
include esters (e.g., ethyl acetate, butyl acetate, ethyl
propionate, β-ethoxyethyl acetate, methylcellosolve
acetate), alcohols (e.g., isopropyl alcohol, n-butyl
alcohol, secondary butyl alcohol), ketones (e.g., methyl
isobutyl ketone, methyl ethyl ketone, cyclohexanone),
amides (e.g., dimethylformamide, N-methylpyrrolidone) and
ethers (e.g., tetrahydrofurane, dioxane), however, the
present invention is not limited thereto.</p><p num="0116">In the emulsification dispersion, an oil phase
obtained by dissolving the dye in a high boiling organic
solvent or depending on the case, in a mixed solvent of a
high boiling organic solvent and a low boiling organic
solvent is dispersed in an aqueous phase mainly comprising
water to form fine oil droplets of the oil phase. At this
time, in either one or both of the aqueous phase and the
oil phase, additives described later, such as surfactant,
wetting agent, dye stabilizer, emulsification stabilizer,
antiseptic and fungicide, can be added, if desired.</p><p num="0117">In the general emulsification method, an oil phase
is added to an aqueous phase, however, a so-called phase
inversion emulsification method of adding dropwise an
aqueous phase in an oil phase can also be preferably used.</p><p num="0118">In performing the emulsification dispersion of the 
present invention, various surfactants described above can
be used. Preferred examples thereof include anionic
surfactants such as fatty acid salt, alkylsulfuric ester
salt, alkylbenzenesulfonate, alkylnaphthalenesulfonate,
dialkylsulfosuccinate, alkylphosphoric ester salt,
naphthalenesulfonic acid formalin condensate and
polyoxyethylenealkylsulfuric ester salt, and nonionic
surfactants such as polyoxyethylene alkylallyl ether,
polyoxyethylene fatty acid ester, sorbitan fatty acid
ester, polyoxyethylene sorbitan fatty acid ester,
polyoxyethylene alkylamine, glycerin fatty acid ester and
oxyethylene oxypropylene block copolymer. Also, SURFYNOLS
(produced by Air Products &amp; Chemicals), which is an
acetylene-base polyoxyethylene oxide surfactant, is
preferably used. In addition, amine oxide-type amphoteric
surfactants such as N,N-dimethyl-N-alkylamine oxide are
preferred. Furthermore, surfactants described in JP-A-59-157636
(pages (37) to (38)) and <u style="single">Research Disclosure,</u> No.
308119 (1989) can be used.</p><p num="0119">For the purpose of stabilizing the dispersion
immediately after the emulsification, a water-soluble
polymer may also be added in combination with the
surfactant. As the water-soluble polymer, polyvinyl
alcohol, polyvinylpyrrolidone, polyethylene oxide,
polyacrylic acid, polyacrylamide, and copolymers thereof 
are preferably used. In addition, natural water-soluble
polymers such as polysaccharides, casein and gelatin are
also preferably used. Furthermore, for the stabilization
of the dye dispersion, a polymer which does not
substantially dissolve in an aqueous medium, such as
polyvinyl, polyurethane, polyester, polyamide, polyurea
and polycarbonate obtained by the polymerization of
acrylic acid esters, methacrylic acid esters, vinyl esters,
acrylamides, methacrylamides, olefins, styrenes, vinyl
ethers and acrylonitriles, can also be used in combination.
This polymer preferably contains -SO<sup>2-</sup> or -COO<sup>-</sup>. In the
case of using this polymer which does not substantially
dissolve in an aqueous medium, the polymer is preferably
used in an amount of 20 % by weight or less, more
preferably 10 % by weight or less, based on the high
boiling point organic solvent.</p><p num="0120">In preparing an aqueous ink by dispersing an oil-soluble
dye or a high boiling point organic solvent
according to the emulsification dispersion, control of the
particle size is important. In order to elevate the color
purity or density of an image formed by the ink jetting,
it is essential to reduce the average particle size. The
average particle size is, in terms of the volume average
particle size, preferably 1 µm or less, more preferably
from 5 to 100 nm. </p><p num="0121">The volume average particle size and particle size
distribution of the dispersed particles can be easily
measured by a known method such as static light scattering
method, dynamic light scattering method, centrifugal
precipitation method and the method described in <u style="single">Jikken
Kagaku Koza (Lecture of Experimental Chemistry),</u> 4th ed.,
pp. 417-418. For example, the ink solution is diluted
with distilled water such that the particle concentration
in the ink becomes from 0.1 to 1 % by weight, then, the
particle size can be easily measured by a commercially
available volume average particle size measuring apparatus
(for example, Microtrac UPA, manufactured by Nikkiso K.K.).
The dynamic light scattering method utilizing the laser
Doppler effect is particularly preferred because the
particle size can be measured even in the case of
particles having a small size.</p><p num="0122">The volume average particle size is an average
particle size weighted with the particle volume and is
obtained by multiplying the diameter of individual
particles in the gathering of particles with the volume of
the particle and dividing the sum total of the obtained
values by the total volume of particles. The volume
average particle size is described in Soichi Muroi,
<u style="single">Kobunshi Latex no Kagaku (Chemistry of Polymer Latex),</u>
page 119, Kobunshi Kanko Kai. </p><p num="0123">Also, it is revealed that the presence of coarse
particles greatly affects the printing performance. More
specifically, the coarse particle clogs the nozzle of head
or even if the nozzle is not clogged, forms a soil to
bring about failure or slippage in the ejection of ink and
seriously affect the printing performance. In order to
prevent these troubles, it is important that when an ink
is prepared, the number of particles having a particle
size of 5 µm or more and the number of particles having a
particle size of 1 µm or more are reduced to 10 or less
and 100 or less, respectively, in 1 µl of ink.</p><p num="0124">For removing these coarse particles, a known method
such as centrifugal separation or microfiltration can be
used. This separation step may be performed immediately
after the emulsification dispersion or may be performed
immediately before filling the ink in an ink cartridge
after various additives such as wetting agent and
surfactant are added to the emulsified dispersion.</p><p num="0125">A mechanically emulsifying apparatus is effective
for reducing the average particle size and eliminating
coarse particles.</p><p num="0126">As the emulsifying apparatus, known apparatuses such
as simple stirrer, impeller stirring system, in-line
stirring system, mill system such as colloid mill, and
ultrasonic system can be used, however, a high-pressure 
homogenizer is particularly preferred.</p><p num="0127">The mechanism of the high-pressure homogenizer is
described in detail in U.S. Patent 4,533,254 and JP-A-6-47264.
Examples of the commercially available apparatus
include Gaulin Homogenizer (manufactured by A.P. V Gaulin
Inc.), Microfluidizer (manufactured by Microfluidex Inc.)
and Altimizer (produced by Sugino Machine).</p><p num="0128">The recent high-pressure homogenizer with a
mechanism of pulverizing particles in an ultrahigh
pressure jet stream described in U.S. Patent 5,720,551 is
particularly effective for the emulsification dispersion
of the present invention. Examples of the emulsifying
apparatus using this ultrahigh pressure jet stream include
DeBEE2000 (manufactured by BEE International Ltd.).</p><p num="0129">In performing the emulsification by a high-pressure
emulsification dispersing apparatus, the pressure is 50
MPa or more, preferably 60 MPa or more, more preferably
180 MPa or more.</p> <p num="0130">A method of using two or more emulsifying
apparatuses, for example, emulsification in a stirring
emulsifier and then passing through a high-pressure
homogenizer, is particularly preferred. Also, a method of
once emulsification dispersing the dye solution by such an
emulsifying apparatus, adding additives such as wetting
agent and surfactant, and then again passing the 
dispersion through a high-pressure homogenizer until
filling the ink into a cartridge is preferred.</p><p num="0131">In the case of containing a low boiling point
organic solvent in addition to a high boiling point
organic solvent, the low boiling point solvent is
preferably removed in view of stability of the emulsified
product, safety and hygiene. For removing the low boiling
point solvent, various known methods can be used according
to the kind of solvent. Examples of the method include
evaporation, vacuum evaporation and ultrafiltration. This
removal of the low boiling point organic solvent is
preferably performed as soon as possible immediately after
the emulsification.</p><p num="0132">In the present invention, in the case of using the
ink as an inkjet recording ink, additives can be
appropriately selected and used in an appropriate amount
in addition to those compounds, such as drying inhibitor
for preventing clogging due to drying of ink at the
ejection port, permeation accelerator for attaining more
successful permeation of ink into paper, ultraviolet
absorbent, antioxidant, viscosity adjusting agent, surface
tension adjusting agent, dispersant, dispersion stabilizer,
fungicide, rust inhibitor, pH adjusting agent, defoaming
agent and chelating agent.</p><p num="0133">The drying inhibitor for use in the present 
invention is preferably a water-soluble organic solvent
having a vapor pressure lower than water.</p><p num="0134">Specific examples thereof include polyhydric
alcohols represented by ethylene glycol, propylene glycol,
diethylene glycol, polyethylene glycol, thiodiglycol,
dithiodiglycol, 2-methyl-1,3-propanediol, 1,2,6-hexanetriol,
acetylene glycol derivative, glycerin and
trimethylolpropane; lower alkyl ethers of polyhydric
alcohol, such as ethylene glycol monomethyl(or ethyl)
ether, diethylene glycol monomethyl(or ethyl) ether and
triethylene glycol monoethyl(or butyl) ether; heterocyclic
rings such as 2-pyrrolidone, N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone, 1,3-dimethyl-2-imidazolidinone
and N-ethylmorpholine; sulfur-containing
compounds such as sulfolane, dimethylsulfoxide
and 3-sulfolene; polyfunctional compounds such as
diacetone alcohol and diethanolamine; and urea derivatives.
Among these, polyhydric alcohols such as glycerin and
diethylene glycol are preferred. These drying inhibitors
may be used individually or in combination of two or more
thereof. The drying inhibitor is preferably contained in
the ink in an amount of 10 to 50 % by weight.</p> <p num="0135">Examples of the permeation accelerator for use in
the present invention include alcohols such as ethanol,
isopropanol, butanol, diethylene glycol monobutyl ether,
triethylene glycol monobutyl ether and 1,2-hexanediol, 
sodium laurylsulfate, sodium oleate and nonionic
surfactants. A sufficiently high effect can be obtained
by adding from 10 to 30 % by weight of the permeation
accelerator to the ink. The permeation accelerator is
preferably used within the amount range of causing no
blurring of printed letter or no print through.</p> <p num="0136">Examples of the ultraviolet absorbent which can be
used for improving the preservability of image in the
present invention include benzotriazole-base compounds
described in JP-A-58-185677, JP-A-61-190537, JP-A-2-782,
JP-A-5-197075 and JP-A-9-34057, benzophenone-base
compounds described in JP-A-46-2784, JP-A-5-194483 and U.S.
Patent 3,214,463, cinnamic acid-base compounds described
in JP-B-48-30492 (the term "JP-B" as used herein means an
"examined Japanese patent publication"), JP-B-56-21141 and
JP-A-10-88106, triazine-base compounds described in JP-A-4-298503,
JP-A-8-53427, JP-A-8-239368, JP-A-10-182621 and
JP-T-8-501291 (the term "JP-T" as used herein means a
"published Japanese translation of a PCT patent
application"), compounds described in <u style="single">Research Disclosure</u>
No. 24239, and compounds of absorbing ultraviolet light
and emitting fluorescent light, so-called fluorescent
brightening agents represented by stilbene-base compound
and benzoxazole-base compound.</p> <p num="0137">As the antioxidant used for improving the 
preservability of image in the present invention, various
organic discoloration inhibitors and metal complex-base
discoloration inhibitors can be used. Examples of the
organic discoloration inhibitor include hydroquinones,
alkoxyphenols, dialkoxyphenols, phenols, anilines, amines,
indanes, chromans, alkoxyanilines and heterocyclic rings.
Examples of the metal complex include nickel complex and
zinc complex. More specifically, compounds described in
patents cited in <u style="single">Research Disclosure,</u> Nos. 17643 (Items
VII-I to VII-J), 15162, 18716 (page 650, left column),
36544 (page 527), 307105 (page 872) and 15162, and
compounds included in formulae of representative compounds
and in exemplary compounds described in JP-A-62-215272
(pages 127 to 137) can be used.</p><p num="0138">Examples of the fungicide for use in the present
invention include sodium dehydroacetate, sodium benzoate,
sodium pyridinethione-1-oxide, ethyl p-hydroxybenzoate,
1,2-benzisothiazolin-3-one and salts thereof. The
fungicide is preferably used in the ink in an amount of
0.02 to 5.00 % by weight. These are described in detail
in <u style="single">Bokin Bobai Zai Jiten (Dictionary of Microbicide and
Fungicide),</u> compiled by Nippon Bokin Bobai Gakkai Jiten
Henshu Iinkai. Examples of the rust inhibitor include
acidic sulfite, sodium thiosulfate, ammon thioglycolate,
diisopropylammonium nitrite, pentaerythritol tetranitrate, 
dicyclohexylammonium nitrite and benzotriazole. The rust
inhibitor is preferably used in the ink in an amount of
0.02 to 5.00 by weight.</p><p num="0139">The pH adjusting agent for use in the present
invention is suitably used for adjusting the pH and
imparting dispersion stability. The pH of the ink is
adjusted to 8 to 11 at 25°C. If the pH is less than 8, the
solubility of dye decreases to readily cause clogging of a
nozzle, whereas if it exceeds 11, the water resistance
deteriorates. Examples of the pH adjusting agent include,
as basic one, organic bases and inorganic alkalis, and as
acidic one, organic acids and inorganic acids.</p><p num="0140">Examples of the organic base include triethanolamine,
diethanolamine, N-methyldiethanolamine and
dimethylethanolamine. Examples of the inorganic alkali
include hydroxides of alkali metal, such as sodium
hydroxide, lithium hydroxide and potassium hydroxide;
carbonates of alkali metal, such as sodium carbonate and
sodium hydrogencarbonate; and ammonium. Examples of the
organic acid include acetic acid, propionic acid,
trifluoroacetic acid and alkylsulfonic acid. Examples of
the inorganic acid include hydrochloric acid, sulfuric
acid and phosphoric acid.</p><p num="0141">The surface tension of the ink for use in the
present invention is preferably from 20 to 50 mN/m, more 
preferably from 20 to 40 mN/m, at 25°C. If the surface
tension exceeds 50 mN/m, ejection stability and printing
qualities such as blurring and whisker at the color mixing
are seriously deteriorated, whereas if the surface tension
of ink is less than 20 mN/m, printing failure may occur
due to attachment of ink to the hard surface at the
ejection.</p><p num="0142">The viscosity of the ink for use in the present
invention is preferably 30 mPa·s or less, more preferably
20 mPa·s or less. For the purpose of adjusting the
viscosity, a viscosity adjusting agent is sometimes used.
Examples of the viscosity adjusting agent include
celluloses, water-soluble polymers such as polyvinyl
alcohol, and nonionic surfactants. These are described in
detail in <u style="single">Nendo Chosei Gijutsu (Viscosity Adjusting
Technology),</u> Chap. 9, Gijutsu Joho Kyokai (1999), and
<u style="single">Inkjet Printer Yo Chemicals (98 Zoho) -Zairyo no Kaihatsu
Doko·Tenbo Chosa- (Chemicals for Inkjet Printer (Enlarged
Edition of 98) -Survey on Tendency·Prospect of Development
of Materials-),</u> pp. 162-174, CMC (1997).</p><p num="0143">In the present invention, a polymer fine particle
dispersion may also be used. This is described in detail
in Japanese Patent Application No. 2001-63780.</p><p num="0144">In the present invention, if desired, the above-described
various cationic, anionic or nonionic 
surfactants can be used as the dispersant or dispersion
stabilizer, and fluorine-base or silicone-base compounds,
chelating agents represented by EDTA, and the like can be
used as the defoaming agent.</p><p num="0145">The ink of the present invention can be used for
forming an image on known materials for recording, namely,
plain paper, resin coated paper, inkjet special paper
described; for example, in JP-A-8-169172, JP-A-8-27693,
JP-A-2-276670, JP-A-7-276789, JP-A-9-323475, JP-A-62-238783,
JP-A-10-153989, JP-A-10-217473, JP-A-10-235995,
JP-A-10-337947, JP-A-10-217597 and JP-A-10-337947, film,
electrophotographic common paper, cloth, glass, metal,
ceramic and the like.</p><p num="0146">The recording paper and recording film used in the
inkjet printing using the ink of the present invention are
described below. The support which can be used for the
recording paper or film is produced, for example, from a
chemical pulp such as LBKP and NBKP, a mechanical pulp
such as GP, PGW, RMP, TMP, CTMP, CMP and CGP, a waste
paper pulp such as DIP, or the like by mixing; if desired,
conventionally known additives such as pigment, binder,
sizing agent, fixing agent, cation agent and paper
strength increasing agent, and then sheeting the mixture
using various devices such as Fourdrinier paper machine
and cylinder paper machine. Other than these supports, 
synthetic paper or plastic film may be used. The
thickness of the support is preferably from 10 to 250 µm
and the basis weight is preferably from 10 to 250 g/m<sup>2</sup>. An
ink-accepting layer and a backcoat layer may be provided
on the support as it is or may be provided after providing
a size press or anchor coat layer using starch, polyvinyl
alcohol and the like. The support may also be subjected
to a flattening treatment by a calendering device such as
machine calender, TG calender and soft calender. In the
present invention, the support is preferably paper or
plastic film of which both surfaces are laminated with
polyolefin (for example, polyethylene, polystyrene,
polyethylene terephthalate, polybutene or a copolymer
thereof). In the polyolefin, a white pigment (for example,
titanium oxide or zinc oxide) or a tinting dye (for
example, cobalt blue, ultramarine or neodymium oxide) is
preferably added.</p><p num="0147">The image-accepting layer provided on the support
contains a pigment and an aqueous binder. The pigment is
preferably a white pigment and examples of the white
pigment include inorganic white pigments such as calcium
carbonate, kaolin, talc, clay, diatomaceous earth,
synthetic amorphous silica, aluminum silicate, magnesium
silicate, calcium silicate, aluminum hydroxide, alumina,
lithopone, zeolite, barium sulfate, calcium sulfate, 
titanium dioxide, zinc sulfide and zinc carbonate, and
organic pigments such as styrene-base pigment, acryl-base
pigment, urea resin and melamine resin. The white pigment
contained in the ink-accepting layer is preferably a
porous inorganic white pigment and a synthetic amorphous
silica and the like having a large pore area are more
preferred. The synthetic amorphous silica may be either a
silicic acid anhydride obtained by a dry production method
(gas phase method) or a silicic acid hydrate obtained by a
wet production method. In particular, a silicic acid
hydrate is preferred. These pigments may be used in
combination of two or more thereof.</p><p num="0148">Specific examples of the recording paper containing
the pigment in the image-receiving layer include those
disclosed in JP-A-10-81064, JP-A-10-119423, JP-A-10-157277,
JP-A-10-217601, JP-A-11-348409, JP-A-2001-138621, JP-A-2000-43401,
JP-A-2000-211235, JP-A-2000-309157, JP-A-2001-96897,
JP-A-2001-138627, JP-A-11-91242, JP-A-8-2087, JP-A-8-2090,
JP-A-8-2091, JP-A-8-2093, JP-A-8-174992, JP-A-11-192777
and JP-A-2001-301314.</p><p num="0149">Examples of the aqueous binder contained in the
image-accepting layer include water-soluble polymers such
as polyvinyl alcohol, silanol-modified polyvinyl alcohol,
starch, cationized starch, casein, gelatin, carboxymethyl
cellulose, hydroxyethyl cellulose, polyvinylpyrrolidone, 
polyalkylene oxide and polyalkylene oxide derivatives, and
water-dispersible polymers such as styrene butadiene latex
and acryl emulsion. These aqueous binders can be used
individually or in combination of two or more thereof.
Among these, polyvinyl alcohol and silanol-modified
polyvinyl alcohol are preferred in the present invention
in view of adhesion to the pigment and peeling resistance
of the ink-accepting layer.</p><p num="0150">The image-accepting layer may contain a mordant, a
water-proofing agent, a light fastness enhancer, an ozone
resistance enhancer, a surfactant and other additives in
addition to the pigment and the aqueous binder.</p><p num="0151">The mordant added to the image-accepting layer is
preferably immobilized and for this purpose, a polymer
mordant is preferably used.</p><p num="0152">The polymer mordant is described in JP-A-48-28325,
JP-A-54-74430, JP-A-54-124726, JP-A-55-22766, JP-A-55-142339,
JP-A-60-23850, JP-A-60-23851, JP-A-60-23852, JP-A-60-23853,
JP-A-60-57836, JP-A-60-60643, JP-A-60-118834,
JP-A-60-122940, JP-A-60-122941, JP-A-60-122942, JP-A-60-235134,
JP-A-1-161236 and U.S. Patents 2,484,430,
2,548,564, 3,148,061, 3,309,690, 4,115,124, 4,124,386,
4,193,800, 4,273,853, 4,282,305 and 4,450,224. An image-receiving
material containing the polymer mordant
described in JP-A-1-161236 (pages 212 to 215) is 
particularly preferred. When the polymer mordant
described in this patent publication is used, an image
having excellent image quality can be obtained and at the
same time, light fastness of the image is improved.</p><p num="0153">The water-proofing agent is effective for obtaining
a water-resistant image. The water-proofing agent is
preferably a cationic resin. Examples of the cationic
resin include polyamidopolyamine epichlorohydrin,
polyethyleneimine, polyaminesulfone, poly-dimethyldiallyl-ammonium
chloride and cation polyacrylamide. The content
of the cationic resin is preferably from 1 to 15 % by
weight, more preferably from 3 to 10 % by weight, based on
the entire solid content of the ink-accepting layer.</p><p num="0154">Examples of the light fastness enhance and the gas
resistance enhance include phenol compounds, hindered
phenol compounds, thioether compounds, thiourea compounds,
thiocyanic acid compounds, amine compounds, hindered amine
compounds, TEMPO compounds, hydrazine compounds, hydrazide
compounds, amidine compounds, vinyl group-containing
compounds, ester compounds, amide compounds, ether
compounds, alcohol compounds, sulfinic acid compounds,
saccharides, water-soluble reducing compounds, organic
acids, inorganic acids, hydroxy group-containing organic
acids, benzotriazole compounds, benzophenone compounds,
triazine compounds, heterocyclic compounds, water-soluble 
metal salts, organic metal compounds and metal complexes.</p><p num="0155">Specific compound examples thereof include those
described in JP-A-10-182621, JP-A-2001-260519, JP-A-2000-260519,
JP-B-4-34953, JP-B-4-34513, JP-B-4-34512, JP-A-11-170686,
JP-A-60-67190, JP-A-7-276808, JP-A-2000-94829, JP-T-8-512258
and JP-A-11-321090.</p><p num="0156">The surfactant functions as a coating aid, a
releasability improver, a slipperiness improver or an
antistatic agent. The surfactant is described in JP-A-62-173463
and JP-A-62-183457.</p><p num="0157">In place of the surfactant, an organic fluoro
compound may be used. The organic fluoro compound is
preferably hydrophobic. Examples of the organic fluoro
compound include a fluorine-containing surfactant, an oily
fluorine-base compound (for example, fluorine oil) and a
solid fluorine compound resin (for example, ethylene
tetrafluoride resin). The organic fluoro compound is
described in JP-B-57-9053 (columns 8 to 17), JP-A-61-20994
and JP-A-62-135826.</p><p num="0158">As the hardening agent, for example, the materials
described in JP-A-1-161236 (page 222), JP-A-9-263036, JP-A-10-119423
and JP-A-310547 can be used.</p><p num="0159">Other additives added to the ink-accepting layer
include a pigment dispersant, a thickener; a defoaming
agent, a dye, a fluorescent brightening agent, an 
antiseptic, a pH adjusting agent, a matting agent, a
hardening agent and the like. The ink-accepting layer may
be composed of either one layer or two layers.</p><p num="0160">In the recording paper or film, a backcoat layer may
also be provided. Examples of the component which can be
added to this layer include a white pigment, an aqueous
binder and other components. Examples of the white
pigment contained in the backcoat layer include white
inorganic pigments such as precipitated calcium carbonate,
heavy calcium carbonate, kaolin, talc, calcium sulfate,
barium sulfate, titanium dioxide, zinc oxide, zinc sulfide,
zinc carbonate, satin white, aluminum silicate,
diatomaceous earth, calcium silicate, magnesium silicate,
synthetic amorphous silica, colloidal silica, colloidal
alumina, pseudo-boehmite, aluminum hydroxide, alumina,
lithopone, zeolite, hydrolyzed halloysite, magnesium
carbonate and magnesium hydroxide, and organic pigments
such as styrene-base plastic pigment, acryl-base plastic
pigment, polyethylene, microcapsule, urea resin and
melamine resin.</p><p num="0161">Examples of the aqueous binder contained in the
backcoat layer include water-soluble polymers such as
styrene/maleate copolymer, styrene/acrylate copolymer,
polyvinyl alcohol, silanol-modified polyvinyl alcohol,
starch, cationized starch, casein, gelatin, carboxymethyl 
cellulose, hydroxyethyl cellulose and polyvinylpyrrolidone,
and water-dispersible polymers such as styrene butadiene
latex and acryl emulsion. Other components contained in
the backcoat layer include a defoaming agent, a foam
inhibitor, a dye, a fluorescent brightening agent, an
antiseptic, a water-proofing agent and the like.</p><p num="0162">A polymer latex may be added to a constituent layer
(including the back layer) of the inkjet recording paper
or film. The polymer latex is used for the purpose of
improving film properties, for example, stabilizing
dimension and preventing curling, adhesion or film
cracking. The polymer latex is described in JP-A-62-245258,
JP-A-62-1316648 and JP-A-62-110066. When a
polymer latex having a low glass transition temperature
(40°C or less) is added to a layer containing the mordant,
the layer can be prevented from cracking or curling. Also,
by adding a polymer latex having a high glass transition
temperature to the back layer, curling can be prevented.</p><p num="0163">The ink of the present invention is not limited on
the inkjet recording system and is used in a known system,
for example, an electric charge controlling system of
jetting out the ink by using the electrostatic induction
force, a drop-on-demand system (pressure pulse system)
using an oscillation pressure of a piezoelectric device,
an acoustic inkjet system of converting electric signals 
into acoustic beams, irradiating the beams on the ink and
jetting out the ink using the radiation pressure, or a
thermal inkjet system of heating the ink to form bubbles
and utilizing the generated pressure.</p><p num="0164">The inkjet recording system includes a system of
ejecting a large number of small volumes of so-called
photo-ink having a low concentration, a system designed to
improve the image quality by using a plurality of inks
substantially the same in hue but different in the
concentration, and a system using colorless transparent
ink.</p><p num="0165">The inkjet recording ink of the present invention
can be used for uses other than the inkjet recording, such
as a material for display image, an image-forming material
for interior decoration and an image-forming material for
outdoor decoration.</p><p num="0166">Examples of the material for display image include
various materials such as poster, wall paper, ornamental
goods (e.g., ornament, doll), handbill for commercial
advertisement, wrapping paper, wrapping material, paper
bag, vinyl bag, package material, billboard, image drawn
or attached to the side face of traffic (e.g., automobile,
bus, electric car), and clothes with a logo. In the case
of using the dye of the present invention as a material
for forming a display image, the image includes, in 
addition to a strict image, all patterns by a dye, which
can be acknowledged by a human, such as abstract design,
letter and geometrical pattern.</p><p num="0167">Examples of the material for interior decoration
include various materials such as wall paper, ornamental
goods (e.g., ornament, doll), member of luminaire, member
of furniture and design member of floor or ceiling. In
the case of using the dye of the present invention as a
material for forming an image, the image includes, in
addition to a strict image, all patterns by a dye, which
can be acknowledged by a human, such as abstract design,
letter and geometrical pattern.</p><p num="0168">Examples of the material for outdoor decoration
include various materials such as wall material, roofing
material, billboard, gardening material, outdoor
ornamental goods (e.g., ornament, doll), and member of
outdoor luminaire. In the case of using the dye of the
present invention as a material for forming an image, the
image includes, in addition to a strict image, all
patterns by a dye, which can be acknowledged by a human,
such as abstract design, letter and geometrical pattern.</p><p num="0169">In these uses, examples of the medium where the
pattern is formed include various materials such as paper,
fiber, cloth (including non-woven fabric), plastic, metal
and ceramic. Examples of the dyeing form include 
mordanting, printing and fixing of a dye in the form of a
reactive dyestuff having introduced thereinto a reactive
group. Among these, preferred is dyeing by mordanting.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLES</u></heading><p num="0170">The present invention is described below by
referring to Examples, however, the present invention is
not limited thereto.</p><heading>(Example 1)</heading><p num="0171">Deionized water was added to the following
components to make 1 liter and the resulting solution was
stirred for 1 hour under heating at 30 to 40°C. Thereafter,
the solution was filtered under reduced pressure through a
microfilter having an average pore size of 0.25 µm to
prepare an ink solution for cyan color.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Cyan dye of the Present Invention (Compound 154)</entry><entry align="left">17.5 g/liter</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diethylene glycol</entry><entry align="left">167 g/liter</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glycerin</entry><entry align="left">164 g/liter</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Triethylene glycol monobutyl ether</entry><entry align="left">125 g/liter</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Triethanolamine</entry><entry align="left">6.5 g/liter</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Benzotriazole</entry><entry align="left">0.07 g/liter </entry></row><row><entry align="left">PROXEL XL2</entry><entry align="left">3.5 g/liter</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Surfactant (w-1)</entry><entry align="left">10 g/liter</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0172">A magenta ink, a light magenta ink, a cyan ink, a
yellow ink a dark yellow ink and a black ink were prepared
by using a magenta dye, a yellow dye or a black dye as the
dye species in place of the cyan dye and changing the
additives, and thereby Ink Set 101 shown in Table 12 was
prepared. <tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">Light Cyan</entry><entry align="left">Cyan</entry><entry align="left">Light Magenta</entry><entry align="left">Magenta</entry><entry align="left">Yellow</entry><entry align="left">Dark Yellow</entry><entry align="left">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dye (g/liter)</entry><entry align="left">154</entry><entry align="left">154</entry><entry align="left">A-1</entry><entry align="left">A-1</entry><entry align="left">A-3</entry><entry align="left">A-3</entry><entry align="left">A-5</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">17.5</entry><entry align="left">68.0</entry><entry align="left">10.2</entry><entry align="left">30.8</entry><entry align="left">14.0</entry><entry align="left">10.0</entry><entry align="left">20.0</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">A-4</entry><entry align="left">A-4</entry><entry align="left">A-6</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">14.0</entry><entry align="left">10.0</entry><entry align="left">39.0</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">A-2</entry><entry align="left">A-7</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">13.0</entry><entry align="left">17.0</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">A-3</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">20.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diethylene glycol (g/liter)</entry><entry align="left">167</entry><entry align="left">110</entry><entry align="left">47</entry><entry align="left">76</entry><entry align="left">85</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Urea (g/liter)</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">37</entry><entry align="left">46</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glycerin (g/liter)</entry><entry align="left">164</entry><entry align="left">148</entry><entry align="left">198</entry><entry align="left">150</entry><entry align="left">154</entry><entry align="left">147</entry><entry align="left">120</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Triethylene glycol monobutyl ether (g/liter)</entry><entry align="left">125</entry><entry align="left">132</entry><entry align="left">105</entry><entry align="left">107</entry><entry align="left">130</entry><entry align="left">127</entry><entry align="left">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diethylene glycol monobutyl ether (g/liter)</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">230</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-Pyrrolidone (g/liter)</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">20</entry><entry align="left">40</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">80</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Surfactant (g/liter)</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Triethanolamine (g/liter)</entry><entry align="left">6.5</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">18</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Benzotriazole (g/liter)</entry><entry align="left">0.07</entry><entry align="left">0.09</entry><entry align="left">0.07</entry><entry align="left">0.08</entry><entry align="left">0.06</entry><entry align="left">0.08</entry><entry align="left">0.08</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Proxel XL2 (g/liter)</entry><entry align="left">3.5</entry><entry align="left">4.0</entry><entry align="left">5.0</entry><entry align="left">4.5</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">4</entry></row><row><entry nameend="5" align="left" namest="1">Deionized water was added to make 1 liter.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-00960001" orientation="unknown" wi="114" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00960001.tif" inline="no" he="61"/><img id="img-00960002" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00960002.tif" inline="no" he="62"/><img id="img-00960003" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00960003.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-00960004" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00960004.tif" inline="no" he="53"/><img id="img-00970001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00970001.tif" inline="no" he="59"/><img id="img-00970002" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00970002.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00970003" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00970003.tif" inline="no" he="47"/><img id="img-00970004" orientation="unknown" wi="99" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00970004.tif" inline="no" he="57"/></p><p num="0173">Ink Sets 102 to 108 were prepared in the same manner
as Ink Set 101 except that the dye species, surfactant
species and amount added of the light cyan ink and the
cyan ink of Ink Set 101 were changed as shown in Table 13
below. The permeation depth was measured by preparing a
solid image printed sample of cyan, cutting out the
section thereof using a microtome (Model MT2-B,
manufactured by SORVALL) and observing it through a
microscope.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Ink Set</entry><entry align="center">Light Cyan</entry><entry align="center">Cyan</entry><entry align="center">Permeation Depth, µm</entry><entry align="center">Remarks</entry></row><row><entry align="center">101</entry><entry align="center">154</entry><entry align="center">154</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">Invention</entry></row><row><entry align="center">102</entry><entry align="center">108</entry><entry align="center">108</entry><entry align="center">23</entry><entry align="center">Invention</entry></row><row><entry align="center">103</entry><entry align="center">109</entry><entry align="center">109</entry><entry align="center">23</entry><entry align="center">Invention</entry></row><row><entry align="center">104</entry><entry align="center">110</entry><entry align="center">110</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">Invention</entry></row><row><entry align="center">105</entry><entry align="center">110</entry><entry align="center">110</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">Comparison</entry></row><row><entry align="center">106</entry><entry align="center">149</entry><entry align="center">149</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">Comparison</entry></row><row><entry align="center">107</entry><entry align="center">EPSON genuine ink (PM-920C)</entry><entry align="center">EPSON genuine ink (PM-920C)</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">Comparison</entry></row><row><entry align="center">108</entry><entry align="center">A-1</entry><entry align="center">A-1</entry><entry align="center">11</entry><entry align="center">Comparison</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>(Inkjet Recording)</heading><p num="0174">Ink Sets 101 to 108 prepared above each was filled
in a cartridge of an inkjet printer PM920C (manufactured
by Seiko Epson Corporation) and an image was printed-on 
inkjet paper Photo-Gloss Paper EX produced by Fuji Photo
Film Co., Ltd. using the printer. The following
evaluations were performed and the results obtained are
shown in Table 13.
<sl><li>(1) As the printing performance (i), the cartridge was
set in the printer and after confirming the ejection of
ink from all nozzles, 20 sheets of A4 paper were output
and evaluated on the disorder of printing.
<sl><li>A: No disorder of printing from the start to the
end of printing.</li><li>B: Disorder of printing was generated.</li><li>C: Printing was disordered from the start to the
end of printing.</li></sl>As the printing performance (ii), the cartridge was
left standing at 60°C for 2 days and the disorder of
printing was evaluated by the same method as the printing
performance (i).</li><li>(2) As for the image preservability, a solid image
printed sample of cyan was prepared to have a reflection
density of 1 and evaluated on the following matters.</li></sl></p><heading>(i) Light Fastness</heading><p num="0175">The image density Ci immediately after printing was
measured by X-Rite 310 and thereafter, xenon light (85,000
lx) was irradiated on the image for 6 days using a weather
meter manufactured by Atlas. The image density Cf was 
again measured and the dye residual percentage Ci/Cf*100
was determined and evaluated. The dye residual percentage
was evaluated at three points having a reflection density
was 1, 1.5 and 2. The light fastness was rated A when the
dye residual percentage was 80% or more at any density,
rated B when less than 80% at two points, and rated C when
less than 80% at all densities.</p><heading>(ii) Heat Fastness</heading><p num="0176">The sample was stored for 5 days under the
conditions of 80 to 70% RH and the density before and
after the storage was measured by X-Rite 310. The dye
residual percentage was determined and evaluated. The dye
residual percentage was evaluated at three points having a
reflection density of 1, 1.5 and 2. The heat fastness was
rated A when the dye residual percentage was 90% or more
at any density, rated B when less than 90% at two points,
and rated C when less than 90% at all densities.</p><heading>(iii) Ozone Resistance</heading><p num="0177">The sample was stored for 7 days under the
conditions heated at 80°C while passing outside air and
the image density before and after the storage was
measured by a reflection densitometer (X-Rite 310TR). The
dye residual percentage was determined and evaluated. The
dye residual percentage was evaluated at three points
having a reflection density of 1, 1.5 and 2. The ozone 
resistance was rated A when the dye residual percentage
was 90% or more at any density, rated B when less than 90%
at two points, and rated C when less than 90% at all
densities.
<sl><li>(3) The image quality was evaluated as follows by
observing the presence or absence of generation of bronze
phenomenon with an eye.
<sl><li>○: No generation of bronze phenomenon.</li><li>×: Bronze phenomenon was generated.</li></sl></li></sl><img id="img-01020001" orientation="unknown" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01020001.tif" inline="no" he="232"/></p><p num="0178">It is seen that when the ink composition of the
present invention is used for the inkjet recording,
excellent printing performance is obtained and the fastness
and ozone resistance are also excellent. Furthermore, with
the ink of the present invention, an excellent image
quality free of bronze phenomenon is revealed.</p><p num="0179">The same effect as above are obtained even when the
image-receiving paper used in the present invention is
changed to PM photographic paper produced by Seiko Epson
Corporation or PR101 produced by Canon Inc.</p><p num="0180">According to the present invention, an inkjet
recording ink having high ejection stability, good color
and excellent weather resistance and capable of giving a
recorded image having excellent image quality can be
provided.</p><p num="0181">This application is based on Japanese Patent
application JP 2002-101347, filed April 3, 2002, the entire
content of which is hereby incorporated by reference, the
same as if set forth at length.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An ink comprising an aqueous medium and at least
one dye represented by the following formula (I) which is
dissolved or dispersed in the aqueous medium, wherein the
ink permeates into a recording medium having an image-receiving
layer to a depth of 5 to 30 µm:

wherein X1, X2, X3 and X4 each independently represents -SO-Z,
-SO2-Z, -SO2NR1R2, a sulfo group, -CONR1R2 or -CO2R1, each
Z independently represents a substituted or unsubstituted
alkyl group, a substituted or unsubstituted cycloalkyl
group, a substituted or unsubstituted alkenyl group, a
substituted or unsubstituted aralkyl group, a substituted
or unsubstituted aryl group or a substituted or
unsubstituted heterocyclic group, R1 and R2 each
independently represents a hydrogen atom, a substituted or
unsubstituted alkyl group, a substituted or unsubstituted
cycloalkyl group, a substituted or unsubstituted alkenyl
group, a substituted or unsubstituted aralkyl group, a
substituted or unsubstituted aryl group or a substituted or
unsubstituted heterocyclic group, Y1, Y2, Y3 and Y4 each
independently represents a monovalent substituent, a1 to a4
and b1 to b4 each represents a number of substituent X1, X2,
X3, X4, Y1, Y2, Y3 or Y4, a1 to a4 each independently
represents a number of 0 to 4, provided that at least one
of a1 to a4 does not represents 0, b1 to b4 each
independently represents a number of 0 to 4, provided that
when at least one of a1 to a4 and b1 to b4 each represents a
number of 2 or more, corresponding plurality of
substituents X1, X2, X3, X4, Y1, Y2, Y3 or Y4 may be the same
or different, and M represents a hydrogen atom, a metal
atom or an oxide, hydroxide or halide thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The ink according to claim 1, wherein the dye
represented by the formula (I) is a dye represented by the
following formula (II) :
wherein X11, X12, X13 and X14 each independently represents-SO-Z,
-SO2-Z, -SO2NR1R2, a sulfo group, -CONR1R2 or -CO2R1,
Y11 to Y18 each independently represents a monovalent
substituent, M represents a hydrogen atom, a metal atom or
an oxide, hydroxide or halide thereof, and a11 to a14 each
independently represents an integer of 1 or 2, provided
that when at least one of a11 to a14 each represents a
number of 2, corresponding plurality of substituents X11,
X12, X13 or X14 may be the same or different.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The ink according to claim 1, wherein an amount
of the dye represented by the formula (I) is from 0.2 to
20 % by weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The ink according to claim 2, wherein an amount
of the dye represented by the formula (II) is from 0.2 to
20 % by weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An inkjet recording method comprising ejecting of
the ink according to claim 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>An inkjet recording method comprising ejecting of
the ink according to claim 2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>An inkjet recording method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>preparing an image-receiving material which comprises
a support and an image-receiving layer comprising white
inorganic pigment particles; and</claim-text><claim-text>ejecting an ink droplet comprising the ink according
to claim 1 to the image-receiving material according to
recording signals so as to record an image on the image-receiving
material.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>An inkjet recording method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>preparing an image-receiving material which comprises
a support and an image-receiving layer comprising white
inorganic pigment particles; and</claim-text><claim-text>ejecting an ink droplet comprising the ink according
to claim 2 to the image-receiving material according to
recording signals so as to record an image on the image-receiving
material.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>