<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1209247-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1209247" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="24676237" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020529"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1209247-A1" status="new" fvid="23440589"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1209247</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020529</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01306073-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01306073</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010713</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-66695900-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>66695900</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000920</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  10/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  10/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  10/50        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  10/52        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/448       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/448       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  10/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  10/50</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  10/52</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  16/448K</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">CVD Aluminisierungsverfahren zur Herstellung einer modifizierten Platin-Aluminidbeschichtung für verbesserte Hochtemperaturleistung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">CVD aluminiding process for producing a modified platinum aluminide bond coat for improved high temperature performance</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé de dépôt chimique en phase vapeur pour la production d'un revêtement modifié adhésive d'aluminure de platine afin d'améliorer la performance à haute température</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0821078-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0821078</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4698244-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4698244</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5261963-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5261963</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5658614-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5658614</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5856027-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5856027</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEN ELECTRIC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1 River Road</street><city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NAGARAJ BANGALORE ASWATHA</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WILLIAMS JEFFREY LAWRENCE</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NAGARAJ, BANGALORE ASWATHA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WILLIAMS, JEFFREY LAWRENCE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NAGARAJ, BANGALORE ASWATHA</last-name><address><street>5196 Tranverse Court</street><city>West Chester, Ohio 45069</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WILLIAMS, JEFFREY LAWRENCE</last-name><address><street>11755 Norbourne Drive, Apartment 1013</street><city>Cincinnati, Ohio 45240</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Szary, Anne Catherine, Dr.</last-name><address><street>GE London Patent Operation, Essex House, 12-13 Essex Street</street><city>London WC2R 3AA</city> <country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents> </parties> <international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country> <country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A method of depositing by chemical vapor deposition a modified platinum
aluminide diffusion coating onto a superalloy substrate comprising the steps
of applying a layer of a platinum group metal to the superalloy substrate;
passing an externally generated aluminum halide gas through an internal gas
generator (8) which is integral with a retort (2), the internal gas generator (8)
generating a modified halide gas; and co-depositing aluminum and modifier
onto the superalloy substrate. In one form, the modified halide gas is hafnium
chloride and the modifier is hafnium with the modified platinum aluminum
bond coat comprising a single phase additive layer of platinum aluminide with
at least about 0.5 percent hafnium by weight percent and about 1 to about 15
weight percent of hafnium in the boundary between a diffusion layer and the
additive layer. The bond coat produced by this method is also claimed.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="93"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention relates generally to components of the hot section of gas
turbine engines, and in particular, to a CVD aluminiding process for producing
a modified platinum aluminide bond coat for improved high temperature
performance.</p><p num="0002">In gas turbine engines, for example, aircraft engines, air is drawn into the front
of the engine, compressed by a shaft-mounted rotary compressor, and mixed
with fuel. The mixture is burned, and the hot exhaust gases are passed
through a turbine mounted on a shaft. The flow of gas turns the turbine,
which turns the shaft and drives the compressor. The hot exhaust gases flow
from the back of the engine, providing thrust that propels the aircraft forward.</p><p num="0003">During operation of gas turbine engines, the temperatures of combustion
gases may exceed 3,000°F, considerably higher than the melting
temperatures of the metal parts of the engine, which are in contact with these
gases. The metal parts that are particularly subject to high temperatures, and
thus require particular attention with respect to cooling, are the hot section
components exposed to the combustion gases, such as blades and vanes
used to direct the flow of the hot gases, as well as other components such as
shrouds and combustors.</p><p num="0004">The hotter the exhaust gases, the more efficient is the operation of the jet
engine. There is thus an incentive to raise the exhaust gas temperature.
However, the maximum temperature of the exhaust gases is normally limited
by the materials used to fabricate the hot section components of the turbine.
In current engines, hot section components such as the turbine vanes and
blades are made of cobalt-based and nickel-based superalloys, and can
operate at temperatures of up to 2000°- 2300° F. </p><p num="0005">The metal temperatures can be maintained below melting levels with current
cooling techniques by using a combination of improved cooling designs and
thermal barrier coatings. In one approach, a thermal barrier coating system is
applied to the metallic turbine component, which becomes the substrate. The
thermal barrier coating system includes a ceramic thermal barrier coating that
is applied to the external surface of metal parts within engines to impede the
transfer of heat from hot combustion gases to the metal parts, thus insulating
the component from the hot exhaust gas. This permits the exhaust gas to be
hotter than would otherwise be possible with the particular material and
fabrication process of the component.</p><p num="0006">Thermal barrier coatings (TBCs) are well-known ceramic coatings, for
example, yttrium stabilized zirconia. Ceramic thermal barrier coatings usually
do not adhere optimally directly to the superalloys used in the substrates.
Therefore, an additional metallic layer called a bond coat is placed for
example, by chemical vapor deposition (CVD), between the substrate and the
TBC to improve adhesion of the TBC to the underlying component. In one
form, the bond coat is made of a diffusion nickel aluminide or platinum
aluminide, whose surface oxidizes to form a protective aluminum oxide scale
in addition to improving adherence of the ceramic TBC.</p><p num="0007">The bond coat temperature is critical to the life of the TBC and has been
limited to about 2100° F. Once the bond coat exceeds this temperature, the
coating system can quickly deteriorate, resulting in separation of the TBC
from the bond coat. The addition of small amounts of reactive elements to
platinum aluminide coatings, such as Hf, Si, Zr, and Y have been shown to
increase performance of such coatings.</p><p num="0008">U.S. Patent No. 5,658,614 to Basta et al. discloses a method of improving the
oxidation resistance of a platinum modified aluminide coating applied to a
nickel based superalloy substrate. In one embodiment, a hafnium-modified
aluminide coating was formed using a coating gas mixture of aluminum
trichloride, hydrogen and hafnium chloride. The first coating gas mixture was 
generated externally to a retort holding the platinum-plated workpiece that
was to be coated by passing hydrogen and hydrogen chloride over a pure
source of aluminum. A second mixture of Ar and HCI was generated in a
separate generator external to the retort that also contained a pure hafnium
bed, thereby forming hafnium chloride. The mixtures were then introduced
concurrently to the coating retort forming a hafnium modified outwardly grown,
single phase aluminide coating, as the gases flowed over the workpiece,
depositing Hf and Al.</p><p num="0009">U.S. Patent No. 5,989,733 to Warnes et al. is directed to a CVD outwardly
grown platinum aluminide diffusion coating on a nickel or cobalt based
superalloy substrate wherein the platinum modified aluminide diffusion coating
is modified to include a combination of hafnium and silicon in a concentration
of about 0.01 % by weight (w/o) to about 8 w/o of the outer additive layer of
the coating. The coating gas mixture was generated externally by passing
high purity hydrogen and high purity hydrogen chloride over a high purity pure
source of aluminum and then passing the mixture over a high purity pure
source of silicon, both sources at 290 ° C (554° F). and external of the retort.
A mixture of Ar and HCI was flowed in an external chloride generator through
a hafnium bed at 430° C (806° F). Both gas coating mixtures were then
introduced concurrently to the retort.</p><p num="0010">Prior modified platinum aluminum bond coat practice, as exemplified by the
foregoing U.S. patents, involves generating two or more distinct gas coating
mixtures in multiple external gas generators and concurrently introducing
these mixtures into the retort.</p><p num="0011">U.S. Patent No. 5,667,663 to Rickerby et al. discloses a method for adhering
a ceramic TBC layer to a superalloy article containing a predetermined
amount of aluminum. After applying a layer of platinum to the superalloy
article and heat treating the article, the aluminum diffuses from the superalloy
article into the platinum. In one embodiment, hafnium is added to the 
platinum layer by chemical vapor deposition to up to a level of 0.8 w/o.
Deposition of the aluminum by CVD is not disclosed.</p><p num="0012">What is needed are improved methods to apply these reactive element
modified diffusion bond coating systems. The present invention fulfills this
need, and further provides related advantages.</p><p num="0013">In one form, the present invention provides both an improved method of
producing coatings modified with reactive metals, such as hafnium-modified
coatings and the coatings produced by that method, utilizing a single gas
generation system in a diffusion coating process. An external system
generates an aluminum halide gas which, as it is flowed into the system,
passes over the reactive metal located between the external generator and
the workpiece or parts which are located within a coating retort, and
preferably the reactive metal is within, the coating retort where the parts to be
coated are located. As used herein, reactive metals include Zr, Hf, V, Nb, Ta,
Y, La and Ce. The reactive metal is activated by the aluminum halide gas to
form a mixture of aluminum halide gases and at least one reactive metal
halide gas species. In this manner, a reactive metal and aluminum are co-deposited
by an internal gas generation method onto the parts to be coated
as the gases pass over the parts to produce a modified single phase additive
layer of platinum aluminide.</p><p num="0014">In another form, the present invention comprises a chemical vapor deposited
outwardly grown platinum aluminide diffusion coating on a nickel or cobalt
based superalloy substrate wherein hafnium and aluminum are co-deposited
by an internal gas generation method onto the platinum-plated parts to
produce a single phase additive layer of platinum aluminide with up to about
0.5 percent hafnium by weight percent, and about 1 to about 15 weight
percent of hafnium in the boundary between the diffusion layer and the
additive layer. </p><p num="0015">In yet another embodiment, the present invention comprises a TBC system for
application to a superalloy substrate used in the hot section of a gas turbine
engine. A layer of a platinum group metal is first applied to the superalloy
substrate. A modified platinum aluminide diffusion coating is formed by
applying, by co-deposition, aluminum and at least one reactive metal, such as
hafnium, using chemical vapor deposition to the platinum group metal, the
coating comprising a single phase additive layer of platinum aluminide with at
least about 0.1 percent hafnium by weight (w/o) and about 0.1 to about 15
weight percent (w/o) of hafnium in the boundary formed by the diffusion layer
between the substrate and the additive layer; and a ceramic thermal barrier
coating applied to the modified platinum aluminide diffusion coating. The
amount in weight percentage of reactive metal will vary depending upon the
species selected.</p><p num="0016">While in the prior art, hafnium chloride and aluminum chloride gas coating
mixtures are separately generated externally then concurrently introduced into
the retort causing the hafnium and aluminum to precipitate out as they pass
over the workpiece, in the present invention, there is only one external gas
generator generating the gases bearing both the reactive metal species and
the aluminum. In the additive layer, there is a relatively low concentration of
the reactive metal so that the reactive metal is in solution with the platinum
and aluminum.</p><p num="0017">One advantage of the present invention is that the coating system produced
by this invention demonstrates increased service life resulting from improved
spallation resistance of the TBC system.</p><p num="0018">Another advantage of the present invention is that the process consists of a
single step that additionally coats the internal and external surfaces of an
article to be coated with the modified platinum aluminum coating. This one
step process allows for cost savings during the manufacturing process. </p><p num="0019">Still another advantage of the present invention is that the internal gas
generation process provides the capability for the modification of existing CVD
reactors to produce reactive element-modified coatings without the addition of
new external gas generation systems.</p><p num="0020">Yet another advantage of the present invention is that the process can be
easily adapted for use in airfoil material repair operations. It is advantageous
to have the ability to repair a damaged section of an airfoil, rather than having
to strip the entire TBC coating and completely re-bond and re-coat a TBC
coating to the entire part.</p><p num="0021">Another advantage of the present invention is that the CVD coating device
and process can be simplified as the device of the present invention requires
only one external gas generator.</p><p num="0022">Continuing and often interrelated improvements in processes and materials,
such as the improvements of the present invention, can provide cost
reductions and major increases in the performance of devices such as aircraft
gas turbine engines.</p><p num="0023">Other features and advantages of the present invention will be apparent from
the following more detailed description of the preferred embodiment, taken in
conjunction with the accompanying drawings which illustrate, by way of
example, the principles of the invention.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0024"><dl tsize="6"><dt>Fig. 1</dt><dd>a schematic of a CVD system of a version of the present invention; and</dd><dt>Fig. 2</dt><dd>is a cross-section at A-A of the internal gas generator of Fig. 1.</dd></dl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading><p num="0025">Referring now to the figures, where like parts have the same numbers, in
accordance with a preferred embodiment of the invention, there is shown in
Fig. 1 a schematic of a CVD system of a version of the present invention.</p><p num="0026">Articles to be coated (not shown), for example, components requiring
environmental coatings and/or thermal barrier coating systems were fixtured
in a retort 2 after applying a layer of platinum to the article using known
methods, for example, electroplating followed by an optional diffusion heat
treatment. When an optional diffusion heat treatment is performed, a mixture
of Pt and PtAl<sub>2</sub> and NiAl can be produced. This optional diffusion layer can be
grown into the substrate as Al and Ni from the substrate diffuse outwardly.
These components may be, for example, components located in the hot
section of a gas turbine engine, for example, a jet engine, such as, for
example, turbine blades and vanes, combustors, shrouds and other such
components.</p><p num="0027">An external generator 4 receiving a flow of gas from gas inlets 6 was used to
produce aluminum trichloride gas using standard CVD processes well known
in the art. A source of halide gas is introduced into the external generator that
includes a source of aluminum. The generator is maintained at an elevated
temperature by a heat source to allow for the formation of AlCl<sub>3</sub>. The
externally generated AlCl<sub>3</sub> gas was passed through an internal gas generator
8. The internal generator 8 was in the form of an array 20 of seven tubes 22
configured as shown in Fig. 2 to act as a fluid conduit from the external
generator to the retort 2 such that at least a portion of the array was disposed
within the retort 2 which can also be heated to an elevated temperature by an
independent heat source in order to control the rate of deposition of metal
from gases as will be explained. The portion of the tubes 22 disposed within
the retort was perforated in a manner and in a location that allowed active gas
to be released directly into the retort 2. A preselected number, three in the
preferred embodiment, of the outer tubes 22 were filled with hafnium metal 
chips as shown in Fig. 2. The number of tubes filled and the amount of
reactive metal chips in each tube can be varied to produce the desired partial
pressure of reactive metal halide, which will affect the concentration of
reactive metal deposited on the parts in the retort.</p><p num="0028">In the preferred embodiment, the AlCl<sub>3</sub> gas produced in the external generator
4 was passed over these hafnium chips, producing internally within the retort
2 a hafnium chloride gas. It is believed that the hafnium species was most
likely HfCl<sub>4</sub> with some lesser hafnium chloride species. At least a portion of
the AlCl<sub>3</sub> was reduced to either a dichloride or a monochloride. While there
was most likely a mixture of several metal chlorides, what is critical was that
at least some of the aluminum chloride coming from the external generator 4
activated the hafnium metal, in the preferred embodiment, contained within
the tubes and that aluminum chloride and hafnium chloride gases were
allowed to mix well before reaching the articles to be coated. An inert carrier
gas, for example hydrogen, helium, argon or nitrogen was flowed with AlCl<sub>3</sub>
through the remaining four tubes of the array. In this manner, the gases were
thoroughly mixed and both aluminum and hafnium were co-deposited onto the
part without the need for two external generators.</p><p num="0029">The resulting additive coating consisted of a single phase microstructure that
has been shown to significantly increase the furnace cycle test life of the
modified platinum aluminide bond coat. A single phase additive layer of
platinum aluminide was produced with at least about 0.1 w/o Hf, and about
0.1 to about 15 w/o Hf in the coating immediately below the additive layer in
the outermost portion of the diffusion layer. The Hf and Al diffuse inward from
the additive layer while some deposited Pt and Ni from the substrate also
diffuse through the additive layer to its outer surface. The aluminum content
of the coating as well as the platinum content of the coating can be adjusted
to be any operable amount by adjusting their amounts in the additive layer.
The single phase nature of the additive layer is believed to have occurred
because the hafnium and aluminum are in solution. In the diffusion zone 
immediately below the additive layer, the hafnium is believed to precipitate out
of solution, hence the amount of hafnium in this region can vary from the
amount in the single phase additive layer, as little as 0.1w/o Hf, up to 15 w/o
Hf.</p><p num="0030">A thermal barrier coating (TBC) such as yttrium-stabilized zirconia (YSZ) may
be deposited over the modified platinum aluminide bond coat of the present
invention using techniques well known in the art.</p><p num="0031">In the preferred embodiment illustrated in Fig. 2, the internal generator is in
the form of seven tubes, three of which are occupied by hafnium chips to
produce the coating having the composition as set forth above. It will be
understood by those skilled in the art that the number of tubes can be
increased or decreased as desired. It will be further understood by those
skilled in the art that the partial pressure of the reactive metal gases delivered
to the retort can be varied by increasing or decreasing the number of tubes
containing the reactive metals. The partial pressure may be controlled by
increasing or decreasing the amount and size of the reactive metal material in
the tubes over which the halide gas must pass. By increasing or decreasing
the available surface area of the reactive metal present, the activity of the
reaction between the reactive metal and the chloride gas will be increased or
decreased and the deposition rate can be controlled.</p><p num="0032">The composition of the coating is also modified to include more than one
reactive metal, if desired. For example, if it is desired that the composition of
the coating includes several reactive metals, then these reactive metals can
be added to the composition by including chips of these desired metals in one
or more of the tubes shown in Fig. 2. For example, if it is desired that a
coating include Nb and Ta in addition to Hf, then tubes in the internal
generator can include chips of Hf, Ta and Nb, which can be converted to
chloride-bearing species of each of these elements as the AlCl<sub>3</sub> is passed
over the metal chips. The desired partial pressure, and hence the amount of
each reactive element in the coating, can be adjusted by controlling the 
amount of metal chips in the tubes. More tubes have additional amounts of
these reactive metals added, or additional metals added to achieve both the
desired. composition and concentration in the coating.</p><p num="0033">Of course, following application of the additive layer in each of these
examples, an optional heat treatment of from about 1 to about 4 hours at
temperatures of from about 1800°F to about 2000°F (982-1093°C) is applied
to allow for additional diffusion of elements from the additive layer into the
diffusion layer as well as growth of the diffusion layer, and to allow elements
such as Pt and Ni to diffuse into the additive layer, if desired, prior to
application of a TBC. However, the optional heat treatment is not necessary,
since sufficient diffusion occurs while the substrate is within the retort during
CVD processing. Because the CVD process is applied at temperatures
between 1800-2200°F (982-1204°C) for periods of time of 1-4 hours, there is
sufficient time at elevated temperatures for diffusion to occur and for a
diffusion layer to form between the additive layer and unaffected substrate.</p><p num="0034">The following two examples demonstrate that the hafnium-modified platinum
aluminide bond coatings produced by the present invention resulted in
significant furnace cycle test life improvements and hence, increased bond
strength at 2125° F (1163°C).</p><p num="0035">A sample of 20 test coupons were prepared using a composition of Rene N5
superalloy, which nominally is 7.5 wt. % Co; 6.2 wt. % Al; 7 wt. % Cr; 6.5 wt.
% Ta; 5 wt. % W; 1.5 wt. % Mo; 3 wt. % Re; 0.15 wt. % Hf; 0.5 wt. % max Y;
0.05 wt. % C; 63.1 wt. % Ni; and 40 ppm B. All samples had a layer of
platinum applied utilizing electroplating followed by a heat treatment in the
temperature range of about 1800° - 2000°F (982-1093°C) for about 1 to 4
hours as is well known in the art to produce a thickness of about 0.3 mils.</p><p num="0036">Three samples received a platinum aluminide bond coat using prior art
chemical vapor deposition, to be used as a baseline. </p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0037">Nine test coupons were placed in a retort and heated to a temperature of
about 1100°C (2012°F). Utilizing the method of the present invention, three of
the outer tubes of the internal gas generator of Fig. 2 were completely filled
with hafnium chips. AlCl<sub>3</sub> gas was delivered to the hafnium filled tubes of the
internal gas generator from a prior art external Al gas generator at a
temperature of about 450°C (842°F) and a flow rate of about 3 liters per
minute (lpm). Hydrogen carrier gas was flowed through the center pipe at
about 189 lpm, through the inactive internal pipes (those without hafnium
chips) at about 19 lpm, and through the active internal pipes (those containing
the hafnium chips) at about 47 lpm for a total of about 480 minutes (not
including warm-up/purge/shutdown).</p><p num="0038">Following application of the modified platinum aluminide bond coat according
to the present invention, the nine test coupons and three baseline coupons
were subjected to furnace cycle testing. Each cycle of the furnace cycle test
consisted of heating the coupon to about 2125°F (1163°C) over a 10 minute
period, maintaining the coupon at a temperature of about 2125°F (1163°C) for
a period of about 45 minutes, and allowing the coupon to cool to a
temperature of about 200° F (93°C) over a nine minute period. This cycle was
repeated until there was bond failure.</p><p num="0039">The baseline coupons had an average furnace cycle test (FCT) life of 240
cycles, while the modified platinum aluminide bond coat of the present
invention had an average FCT life of 818 cycles, clearly signifying an FCT life
improvement (representing increased bond strength).</p><heading>EXAMPLE 2</heading><p num="0040">Eight test coupons were placed in a retort and heated to a temperature of
about 1100°C (2012°F). Utilizing the method of the present invention, three of
the outer tubes of the internal gas generator of Fig. 2 were filled
approximately three quarter full with hafnium chips. AlCl<sub>3</sub> gas was delivered to 
the hafnium filled tubes of the internal gas generator from a prior art external
Al gas generator at a temperature of about 450°C (842°F) and a flow rate of
about 3 liters per minute (lpm). Hydrogen carrier gas was flowed through the
center pipe at about 189 lpm, through the inactive internal pipes (those
without hafnium chips) at about 19 lpm, and through the active internal pipes
(those containing the hafnium chips) at about 47 lpm for a total of about 480
minutes (not including warm-up/purge/shutdown).</p><p num="0041">Following application of the modified platinum aluminide bond coat according
to the present invention, the eight test coupons and were subjected to furnace
cycle testing as described in Example 1 and compared to the FCT life of the
three baseline coupons described in Example 1.</p><p num="0042">The modified platinum aluminide bond coat had an average FCT life of 1008
cycles compared to the baseline coupons average FCT life of 240 cycles,
clearly signifying further improvement in FCT life (representing further
increased bond strength).</p><p num="0043">A major factor in arriving at the benefits of the present invention is that the
aluminum and reactive metals such as hafnium are co-deposited in solution
as a single phase in the additive layer utilizing only one external gas
generator.</p><p num="0044">It is believed that the processes of the present invention are also successfully
applicable to cobalt based superalloy substrates.</p><p num="0045">A further advantage of the present invention is that the process provides the
capability for modification of existing CVD reactors to produce hafnium-modified
coatings or coatings including a plurality of reactive metals without
the addition of new external gas generation systems.</p><p num="0046">Although the present invention has been described in connection with specific
examples and embodiments, those skilled in the art will recognize that the
present invention is capable of other variations and modifications within its 
scope. For example, although Hf modifier has been used as an exemplar, it is
envisioned other reactive metal modifiers may be utilized individually in place
of Hf or in combination with Hf and with themselves, as desired. These
examples and embodiments are intended as typical of, rather than in any way
limiting on, the scope of the present invention as presented in the appended
claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method of depositing a modified platinum aluminide diffusion coating
onto a superalloy substrate, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>applying a layer of a Pt-group metal over at least one surface of the
superalloy substrate;</claim-text><claim-text>placing the Pt-group metal-coated superalloy substrate into a CVD retort (2);</claim-text><claim-text>generating an Al-halide gas in an external gas generator(4);</claim-text><claim-text>generating a modified reactive metal-halide gas by passing a portion of the Al-halide
gas generated in the external gas generator (4) into a gas generator
that includes at least one reactive metal to produce a modified reactive metal-halide
gas;</claim-text><claim-text>mixing the Al-halide gas and the modified reactive metal-halide gas together;</claim-text><claim-text>passing the mixture of Al-halide gas and the reactive metal-halide gas over
the Pt-group-plated, superalloy substrate in the retort (2) for a preselected
period of time at a preselected temperature; and</claim-text><claim-text>co-depositing Al and the reactive metal onto the Pt-group plated superalloy
substrate to form a reactive metal-modified platinum group aluminide coating
over the substrate.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 wherein the step of generating a modified
reactive metal-halide gas includes contacting a portion of the Al-halide gas
with a gas generator that includes at least one reactive metal selected from
the group consisting of Hf, Zr, V, Nb, Ta, Y, La and Ce.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 or claim 2 wherein the step of generating a
modified metal-halide gas is accomplished by passing the Al-halide gas
through an internal gas generator (8).</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method of claim 3 wherein the internal gas generator (8) is
comprised of a plurality of tubes (22) having at least one of which includes at
least one reactive metal.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method of claim 4 wherein the internal gas generator (8) is
comprised of seven tubes (22) for transporting Al-halide gas from the external
gas generator (4) to the retort (2), at least one of the tubes (22) including a
source of at least one reactive metal for generating the modified reactive
metal-halide gas.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method of any preceding claim further including the step of
applying a ceramic thermal barrier coating over the reactive metal-modified
Pt-group aluminide coating.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method of claim 2 wherein the step of generating a modified
reactive metal-halide gas includes passing a portion of the Al-halide gas into a
gas generator that includes the reactive metal Hf.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method of claim 7 wherein the step of co-depositing Al and the
reactive metal includes codepositing Hf and Al onto a Pt-plated superalloy
substrate to form a Hf-modified platinum aluminide coating having a single
phase additive layer of platinum aluminum having at least about 0.1 w/o Hf
and a diffusion layer formed between the substrate and the additive layer, the
diffusion layer having a variable amount of Hf from about 0.1 w/o to about 15
w/o, Al, Pt and Ni.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method of any preceding claim wherein the step of passing the
mixture of Al-halide gas and the reactive metal-halide gas over the Pt-group-plated,
superalloy substrate in the retort (2) at a preselected temperature is
performed for about one to four hours.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method of any preceding claim wherein the step of passing the
mixture of Al-halide gas and the reactive metal-halide gas over the platinum
group-plated, superalloy substrate in the retort (2) for a preselected period of
time is performed at a temperature in the range of from about 1800°-2200°F.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The method of any preceding claim further including heat treating the
Pt-group-metal coated superalloy substrate for period of about 1-4 hours at a
temperature in the range of about 1800°-2000°F to develop a diffusion zone
between the deposited Pt-group metal and the substrate prior to placing the
substrate into the retort (2).</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The method of claim 2 wherein the step of generating a modified
reactive metal-halide gas by passing a portion of the Al-halide gas generated
in the external gas generator (4) into the gas generator (8) positioned in the
retort (2) between the substrate and the external gas generator (4).</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>Apparatus for co-depositing reactive metals and aluminum onto a
superalloy substrate comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a retort (2) suitable for holding the substrate;</claim-text><claim-text>means for heating the retort to a first elevated temperature;</claim-text><claim-text>a source of halide gas;</claim-text><claim-text>a source of Al within an external gas generator (4);</claim-text><claim-text>means for heating the external gas generator (4) to a second elevated
temperature;</claim-text><claim-text>means (6) for introducing the halide gas into the external gas generator (4) at
preselected pressures to form an Al-halide gas;</claim-text><claim-text>an internal gas generator (8) positioned between the external gas generator
(4) and the retort (2);</claim-text><claim-text>a fluid conduit for transporting Al-halide gas from the external gas generator
(4) to the retort (2) through the internal gas generator (8); and</claim-text><claim-text>a source of reactive metal to generate a reactive metal-halide gas.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The apparatus of claim 13 wherein the internal gas generator (8)
comprises a plurality of tubes (22) having a first end terminating in the
external gas generator (4) and a second end terminating in the retort (2).</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The apparatus of claim 14 wherein at least one tube (22) includes
reactive metal material so that Al-halide gas in the tube is converted to a
reactive metal gas.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The apparatus of claim 14 wherein the second end of the tubes (22)
terminating in the retort (2) include perforations across the tube walls to
promote mixing of the gases.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>