<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1281745-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1281745" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="19061674" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030205"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1281745-A1" status="new" fvid="23685419"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1281745</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030205</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02255267-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02255267</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020729</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2001229306-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2001229306</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010730</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  61/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  61/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K  11/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K  11/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  61/12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K  11/06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M09K211:14B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M09K211:14B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M09K211:14B4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M09K211:14B6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M09K211:14D6</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Polymere fluoresziernde Verbindung und deren Verwendung in einer Licht-emittierenden Vorrichtung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Polymeric fluorescent substance and polymer light-emitting device using the same</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Substance fluorescente polymerique et dispositif electroluminescent organique l'utilisant</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-6107452-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6107452</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6255449-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6255449</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000046321-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000046321</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000055927-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000055927</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>BERNIUS M., INBASEKARAN M., WOO E., WU W., WUJKOWSKI L.: "Light-emitting diodes based on fluorene polymers" THIN SOLID FILMS, vol. 363, - 2000 pages 55-57, XP002219114</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SUMITOMO CHEMICAL CO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SUMITOMO CHEMICAL COMPANY, LIMITED</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SUMITOMO CHEMICAL COMPANY, LIMITED</last-name><address><street>5-33, Kitahama 4-chome</street><city>Chuo-ku Osaka 541-8550</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DOI SHUJI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NOGUCHI TAKANOBU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TSUBATA YOSHIAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DOI, SHUJI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NOGUCHI, TAKANOBU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TSUBATA, YOSHIAKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DOI, SHUJI</last-name><address><street>2-13-1-1-201, Umezono</street><city>Tsukuba-shi, Ibaraki</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NOGUCHI, TAKANOBU</last-name><address><street>370-49, Minaminakatsuma</street><city>Tsukuba-shi, Ibaraki</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TSUBATA, YOSHIAKI</last-name><address><street>2-13-1-2-101, Umezono</street><city>Tsukuba-shi, Ibaraki</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Cresswell, Thomas Anthony</last-name><address><street>J.A. KEMP &amp;amp; CO. 14 South Square Gray's Inn</street><city>LONDON WC1R 5JJ</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Provided is a polymeric fluorescent substance comprising a copolymer which
has a substituent containing a specific aromatic amine structure below in the side
chain,
<img id="img-80000001" orientation="unknown" wi="78" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="80000001.tif" inline="no" he="22"/>
wherein X<sub>1</sub> is a divalent hydrocarbon group; Ar<sub>2</sub> is an arylene group or the like; and
Ar<sub>3</sub> and Ar<sub>4</sub> independently represent an aryl group or the like. The polymeric
fluorescent substance is preferably used for a light-emitting layer of a polymer LED
having high luminance and high light-emitting efficiency.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><heading>Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a polymeric
fluorescent substance and a polymer light-emitting device
(hereinafter, sometimes referred to as polymer LED) using
the same.</p><heading>Description of the Related Art</heading><p num="0002">Unlike with low molecular weight light-emitting
materials, polymeric light-emitting materials (polymeric
fluorescent substance) are soluble in a solvent, and can
form a light-emitting layer in a light emitting device by a
coating method, consequently, have been variously
investigated. In recent years, polymeric fluorescent
substances having a fluorene unit attract attention, and in
order to improve the performance, copolymers comprising a
fluorene unit and other unit have been studied.</p><p num="0003">Among the above copolymers, a copolymer comprising an
aromatic amine structure (hereinafter, may be referred to
as aromatic amine unit) as other unit is disclosed, for
example, a polymeric fluorescent substance comprising a
copolymer which comprises a fluorene unit and an aromatic
amine unit having a nitrogen atom in the main chain (WO 
99/54385).</p><p num="0004">However, the above known polymeric fluorescent
substance comprising a fluorene unit and an aromatic amine
unit having a nitrogen atom in the main chain has a problem
that luminance and light emitting efficiency are not yet
sufficient, when the polymeric fluorescent substance is
used as a light emitting layer.</p><p num="0005">An object of the present invention is to provide a
polymeric fluorescent substance comprising a copolymer
which has a substituent containing a specific aromatic
amine structure in the side chain, and when said polymeric
fluorescent substance is used for a light emitting layer,
high luminance and high light emitting efficiency are
attained, and to provide a polymer LED using the polymeric
fluorescent substance.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0006">Namely, the present invention relates to a polymeric
fluorescent substance exhibiting fluorescence in the solid
state and having a polystyrene reduced number average
molecular weight of 10<sup>3</sup> to 10<sup>8</sup>, which comprises one or more
repeating units represented by formula (1) and one or more
repeating units represented by formula (3),
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">-Ar<sub>1</sub>-</st32:che>
wherein Ar<sub>1</sub> represents an arylene group or a divalent
heterocyclic compound group and has 1 to 4 substituents 
represented by following formula (2),
<img id="img-00030001" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030001.tif" inline="no" he="23"/>
wherein X<sub>1</sub> represents a divalent hydrocarbon group; Ar<sub>2</sub>
represents an arylene group or a divalent heterocyclic
compound group; Ar<sub>3</sub> represents an aryl group or a
monovalent heterocyclic compound group; Ar<sub>2</sub> and Ar<sub>3</sub> may be
mutually connected to form a ring; Ar<sub>4</sub> represents an aryl
group or a monovalent heterocyclic compound group; Ar<sub>3</sub> and
Ar<sub>4</sub> may be mutually connected to form a ring; k is 0 or 1;
1 represents an integer of 1 to 3,
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">-Ar<sub>5</sub>-</st32:che>
wherein Ar<sub>5</sub> represents an arylene group or divalent
heterocyclic compound group represented by formula (4) or
(5):
<img id="img-00030002" orientation="unknown" wi="76" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030002.tif" inline="no" he="29"/>
wherein X<sub>2</sub> represents a group selected from O, S, SO, SO<sub>2</sub>,
N-R<sub>3</sub>, CR<sub>4</sub>R<sub>5</sub>, SiR<sub>6</sub>R<sub>7</sub>; R<sub>3</sub> to R<sub>7</sub> each independently represent a
group selected from a hydrogen atom, alkyl group, aryl
group and monovalent heterocyclic compound group; R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub>
each independently represent a group selected from alkyl
group, alkoxy group, alkylthio group, alkylsilyl group, 
alkylamino group, aryl group, aryloxy group, arylsilyl
group, arylamino group, arylalkyl group, arylalkoxy group,
arylalkylsilyl group, arylalkylamino group, arylalkenyl
group, arylalkynyl group, monovalent heterocyclic compound
group and cyano group; m and n are each independently
integers of 0 to 3; when m is two or more, a plurality of
R<sub>1</sub> may be the same or different; when n is two or more, a
plurality of R<sub>2</sub> may be the same or different; R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>7</sub> may
be connected to form a ring; when R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>7</sub> is a group
containing an alkyl chain, the alkyl chain may be
interrupted by a group containing a hetero atom,
<img id="img-00040001" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
wherein R<sub>8</sub> represents a group selected from alkyl group,
alkoxy group, alkylthio group, alkylsilyl group, alkylamino
group, aryl group, aryloxy group, arylsilyl group,
arylamino group, arylalkyl group, arylalkoxy group,
arylalkylsilyl group, arylalkylamino group, arylalkenyl
group, arylalkynyl group, monovalent heterocyclic compound
group and cyano group; j is an integer of 0 to 3; when j is
two or more, a plurality of R<sub>8</sub> may be the same or
different; when R<sub>8</sub> is a group containing an alkyl chain,
the alkyl chain may be interrupted by a group containing a
hetero atom. </p><p num="0007">Further, the present invention relates to a polymer
light-emitting device comprising a pair of electrodes
composed of an anode and a cathode at least one of which is
transparent or semitransparent and at least containing an
light emitting layer between the electrodes, wherein the
light emitting layer comprises the above polymeric
fluorescent substance.</p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0008">The polymeric fluorescent substance of the present
invention exhibits fluorescence in the solid state, and has
a polystyrene reduced number average molecular weights of
10<sup>3</sup> to 10<sup>8</sup>. The polymeric fluorescent substance comprises
repeating units represented by the above formulas (1) and
(3), respectively.</p><p num="0009">The total amount of the repeating unit represented by
formulas (1) and (3) is suitably 50 % by mole or more
based on all the repeating units. Moreover, the total
amount of the repeating unit represented by formula (1) is
suitably 0.1% by mole or more and 50% by mole or less based
on the total amount of the repeating unit represented by
formulas (1) and (3). More suitably, the total amount of
the repeating unit represented by formulas (1) and (3) is
50 % by mole or more based on all the repeating units, and
the total amount of the repeating unit represented by
formula (1) is 0.1% by mole or more and 50% by mole or less 
based on the total amount of the repeating unit represented
by formulas (1) and (3).</p><p num="0010">The repeating unit represented by the above formula
(1) is an arylene group or divalent heterocyclic compound
group having 1 to 4 substituents represented by the above
formula (2).</p><p num="0011">The repeating unit represented by the above formula
(3) is a divalent compound group represented by formula (4)
or (5). The repeating unit represented by the above formula
(4) is a biphenylene group bridging between two benzene
rings, which may have a substituent. The repeating unit
represented by the above formula (5) is a phenylene group
which may have a substituent. As a repeating unit
represented by formula (5), specifically exemplified is a
repeating unit of formula (6) which is a fluorene-2,7-diyl
group.
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="82" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/>
wherein R<sub>11</sub> and R<sub>12</sub> each independently represent a group
selected from a hydrogen atom, alkyl group, aryl group and
monovalent heterocyclic compound group; R<sub>9</sub> and R<sub>10</sub> each
independently represent a group selected from alkyl group,
alkoxy group, alkylthio group, alkylsilyl group, alkylamino 
group, aryl group, aryloxy group, arylsilyl group,
arylamino group, arylalkyl group, arylalkoxy group,
arylalkylsilyl group, arylalkylamino group, arylalkenyl
group, arylalkynyl group, monovalent heterocyclic compound
group and cyano group; h and i are each independently
integers of 0 to 3; when h is two or more, a plurality of
R<sub>9</sub> may be the same or different; when i is two or more, a
plurality of R<sub>10</sub> may be the same or different; R<sub>9</sub> to R<sub>12</sub> may
be connected to form a ring; when R<sub>9</sub> to R<sub>12</sub> is a group
containing an alkyl chain, the alkyl chain may be
interrupted by a group containing a hetero atom.</p><p num="0012">The arylene group is an atomic group of an aromatic
hydrocarbon in which two hydrogen atoms are removed. The
aromatic hydrocarbon is a hydrocarbon used as a matrix of
an aromatic compound, which contains a benzene ring. The
aromatic hydrocarbon also includes those containing a
condensed ring, and two or more of independent benzene
rings or condensed rings bonded through a group such as a
direct bond, a vinylene group or the like.</p><p num="0013">The arylene group usually has 6 to 60 carbon atoms,
and examples thereof include phenylene group, biphenylene
group, terphenylene group, fluorene diyl group,
naphthalenediyl group, anthracenediyl group, etc. Here, the
number of carbon atoms of the substituent is not counted as
the number of carbon atoms of the arylene group. </p><p num="0014">The divalent heterocyclic compound group means an
atomic group of a heterocyclic compound in which two
hydrogen atoms are removed. The heterocyclic compound means
an organic compound having a cyclic structure in which at
least one heteroatom such as oxygen, sulfur, nitrogen,
phosphorus, boron, etc. is contained in the cyclic
structure as the element other than carbon atoms.</p><p num="0015">The divalent heterocyclic compound group usually has
4 to 60 carbon atoms, and examples thereof include
furandiyl group, thienylene group, fluorenediyl group,
pyridinediyl group, pyrimidinediyl group, quinolinediyl
group, quinoxalinediyl group, etc. Here, the number of
carbon atoms of the substituent is not counted as the
number of carbon atoms of the divalent heterocyclic
compound group.</p><p num="0016">As the examples of Ar<sub>1</sub>, groups having a structure
obtained by combination of two or more of the above arylene
groups and divalent heterocyclic compound groups may be
included.</p><p num="0017">Among them, phenylene group, biphenylene group,
naphthalenediyl group, anthracenediyl group, pyridinediyl
group, thienylene group, quinolinediyl group, and
quinoxaline diyl group are more suitable.</p><p num="0018">Ar<sub>1</sub> has 1 to 4, preferably 1 to 2 substituents
represented by the above formula (2). </p><p num="0019">Ar<sub>1</sub> may have a substituent other than the substituent
represented by the above formula (2). As the substituent
other than the substituent represented by the above formula
(2), exemplified are alkyl group, alkoxy group, alkylthio
group, alkylsilyl group, alkylamino group, aryl group,
aryloxy group, arylsilyl group, arylamino group, arylalkyl
group, arylalkoxy group, arylalkylsilyl group,
arylalkylamino group, arylalkenyl group, arylalkynyl group,
monovalent heterocyclic compound group, cyano group, etc.
As the concrete examples, exemplified are the same groups
with those of R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> mentioned later.</p><p num="0020">X<sub>1</sub> in the above formula (2) means a divalent
hydrocarbon group. The divalent hydrocarbon group is an
atomic group of a hydrocarbon in which two hydrogen atoms
are removed, and usually has about 1 to 20 carbon atoms.
Specifically, alkylene group, alkenylene group, alkynylene
group, and polymethylene group are exemplified. More
specifically, methylene group, ethylene group, propylene
group, ethenylene group, ethynylene group, substituted
ethenylene group, trimethylene group, tetramethylene group,
etc. are exemplified. Among them, ethenylene group and
substituted ethenylene group are more suitable.</p><p num="0021">As the substituted ethenylene group, exemplified are
ethenylene groups having methyl group, ethyl group, phenyl
group or cyano group as the substituent. </p><p num="0022">Ar<sub>2</sub> of the above formula (2) is an arylene group or a
divalent heterocyclic compound group. Definition of the
arylene group and the divalent heterocyclic compound group
is the same with that of Ar<sub>1</sub>, and the concrete and
preferable examples are the same as those described about
Ar<sub>1</sub>.</p><p num="0023">Ar<sub>3</sub> and Ar<sub>4</sub> in the above formula (2) are each
independently an aryl group or a monovalent heterocyclic
compound group.</p><p num="0024">The aryl group usually has 6 to 60 carbon atoms, and
examples thereof include phenyl group, biphenyl group,
terphenyl group, fluorenyl group, naphtyl group,
anthrylgroup, and groups thereof having a substituent.</p><p num="0025">The monovalent heterocyclic compound group usually
has 4 to 60 carbon atoms, and examples thereof include
pyridinyl group, pyrimidinyl group, furanyl group, thienyl
group, quinolinyl group, quinoxalinyl group, and groups
thereof having a substituent.</p><p num="0026">Among them, phenyl group, naphtyl group, anthryl
group, pyridinyl group, thienyl group, quinolinyl group,
quinoxalinyl group, and groups thereof having a substituent
are more suitable. When Ar<sub>3</sub> and Ar<sub>4</sub> have a substituent,
examples of the substituent include alkyl group, alkoxy
group, alkylthio group, alkylsilyl group, alkylamino group,
aryl group, aryloxy group, arylsilyl group, arylamino 
group, arylalkyl group, arylalkoxy group, arylalkylsilyl
group, arylalkylamino group, arylalkenyl group, arylalkynyl
group, monovalent heterocyclic compound group, and cyano
group.</p><p num="0027">Ar<sub>2</sub> and Ar<sub>3</sub> may be mutually connected with a single
bond or a divalent hydrocarbon group. The divalent
hydrocarbon group which connects Ar<sub>2</sub> and Ar<sub>3</sub> mutually has
usually about one to 20 carbon atoms. Specifically,
alkylene group, alkenylene group, alkynylene group, and
polymethylene group are exemplified. More specifically,
methylene group, ethylene group, propylene group,
ethenylene group, ethynylene group, etc. are exemplified.
Among them, a single bond, methylene group, and ethenylene
group are preferable.</p><p num="0028">As the group having a structure in which Ar<sub>2</sub> and Ar<sub>3</sub>
are mutually connected with a single bond or a divalent
hydrocarbon group, exemplified are carbazolyl group and
substituted carbazolyl group. As the substituent of
substituted carbazolyl group, exemplified are alkyl group,
alkoxy group, alkylthio group, alkylsilyl group, alkylamino
group, aryl group, aryloxy group, arylsilyl group, aryl
amino group, arylalkyl group, arylalkoxy group,
arylalkylsilyl group, arylalkylamino group, arylalkenyl
group, arylalkynyl group, monovalent heterocyclic compound
group, and cyano group. </p><p num="0029">Ar<sub>3</sub> and Ar<sub>4</sub> may be mutually connected as the same
manner with the above case of Ar<sub>2</sub> and Ar<sub>3</sub>.</p><p num="0030">As the example represented by formula (2),
exemplified are those shown below. Further exemplified are
groups thereof having, on their benzene ring, one or more
substituents such as alkyl group, alkoxy group, alkylthio
group, alkylsilyl group, alkylamino group, aryl group,
aryloxy group, arylsilyl group, arylamino group, arylalkyl
group, arylalkoxy group, arylalkylsilyl group,
arylalkylamino group, arylalkenyl group, arylalkynyl group,
monovalent heterocyclic compound group and cyano group.
Also exemplified are groups thereof having, on their
ethenyl group, a substituent such as alkyl group, aryl
group and arylalkyl group. <img id="img-00130001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/><img id="img-00130002" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130002.tif" inline="no" he="95"/><img id="img-00130003" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130003.tif" inline="no" he="31"/><img id="img-00130004" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130004.tif" inline="no" he="34"/></p><p num="0031">Among them, the groups shown below are preferable. <img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="34"/><img id="img-00140002" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140002.tif" inline="no" he="29"/><img id="img-00140003" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140003.tif" inline="no" he="34"/></p><p num="0032">In the repeating unit represented by formula (1), Ar<sub>1</sub>
is preferably 1,4-phenylene group, and more preferably,
1,4-phenylene group having one or two substituents
represented by formula (2). Among the groups having two
substituents represented by formula (2), 1,4-phenylene
group having two substituents at 2,5-positions is further
preferable.</p><p num="0033">The repeating unit represented by the above formula
(3) is a divalent compound group represented by formula
(4), (5) or (6).</p><p num="0034">R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> in formula (4), R<sub>8</sub> in formula (5) and, R<sub>9</sub>
and R<sub>10</sub> in formula (6) each independently represent a group
selected from alkyl group, alkoxy group, alkylthio group,
alkyl silyl group, alkylamino group, aryl group, aryloxy 
group, arylsilyl group, arylamino group, arylalkyl group,
arylalkoxy group, arylalkylsilyl group, arylalkylamino
group, arylalkenyl group, arylalkynyl group, monovalent
heterocyclic compound group, and cyano group.</p><p num="0035">R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> in the repeating unit represented by the
above formula (4), R<sub>8</sub> in the repeating unit represented by
the above formula (5) and R<sub>9</sub> and R<sub>10</sub> in the repeating unit
represented by the above formula (6) are described as
follows when they are substituents other than cyano group.</p><p num="0036">The alkyl group may be any of linear, branched or
cyclic, and usually has about 1 to 20 carbon atoms, and
specific examples thereof include a methyl group, ethyl
group, propyl group, i-propyl group, butyl group, i-butyl
group, t-butyl group, pentyl group, isoamyl group, hexyl
group, cyclohexyl group, heptyl group, octyl group, 2-ethylhexyl
group, nonyl group, decyl group, 3,7-dimethyloctyl
group, lauryl group and the like, and
preferable are a pentyl group, isoamyl group, hexyl group,
octyl group, 2-ethylhexyl group, decyl group and 3,7-dimethyloctyl
group.</p><p num="0037">The alkoxy group may be any of linear, branched or
cyclic, and the number of carbon atoms is usually from 1 to
20, and specific examples thereof include a methoxy group,
ethoxy group, propyloxy group, i-propyloxy group, butoxy
group, i-butoxy group, t-butoxy group, pentyloxy group, 
isoamyloxy group, hexyloxy group, cyclohexyloxy group,
heptyloxy group, octyloxy group, 2-ethylhexyloxy group,
nonyloxy group, decyloxy group, 3,7-dimethyloctyloxy group,
lauryloxy group and the like, and preferable are a
pentyloxy group, isoamyloxy group, hexyloxy group, octyloxy
group, 2-ethylhexyloxy group, decyloxy group and 3,7-dimethyloctyloxy
group.</p><p num="0038">The alkylthio group may be any of linear, branched or
cyclic, and usually has about 1 to 20 carbon atoms, and
specific examples thereof include a methylthio group,
ethylthio group, propylthio group, i-propylthio group,
butylthio group, i-butylthio group, t-butylthio group,
pentylthio group, isoamylthio group, hexylthio group,
cyclohexylthio group, heptylthio group, octylthio group, 2-ethylhexylthio
group, nonylthio group, decylthio group,
3,7-dimethyloctylthio group, laurylthio group and the like,
and preferable are a pentylthio group, isoamylthio group,
hexylthio group, octylthio group, 2-ethylhexylthio group,
decylthio group and 3,7-dimethyloctylthio group.</p><p num="0039">The alkylsilyl group may be any of linear, branched
or cyclic, and usually has about 1 to 60 carbon atoms, and
specific examples thereof include a methylsilyl group,
ethylsilyl group, propylsilyl group, i-propylsilyl group,
butylsilyl group, i-butylsilyl group, t-butylsilyl group,
pentylsilyl group, isoamylsilyl group, hexylsilyl group, 
cyclohexylsilyl group, heptylsilyl group, octylsilyl group,
2-ethylhexylsilyl group, nonylsilyl group, decylsilyl
group., 3,7-dimethyloctylsilyl group, laurylsilyl group,
trimethylsilyl group, ethyldimethylsilyl group,
propyldimethylsilyl group, i-propyldimethylsilyl group,
butyldimethylsilyl group, t-butyldimethylsilyl group,
pentyldimethylsilyl group, isoamyldimethylsilyl group,
hexyldimethylsilyl group, heptyldimethylsilyl group,
octyldimethylsilyl group, 2-ethylhexyl-dimethylsilyl group,
nonyldimethylsilyl group, decyldimethylsilyl group, 3,7-dimethyloctyl-dimethylsilyl
group, lauryldimethylsilyl
group and the like, and preferable are a pentylsilyl group,
isoamylsilyl group, hexylsilyl group, octylsilyl group, 2-ethylhexylsilyl
group, decylsilyl group, 3,7-dimethyloctylsilyl
group, pentyldimethylsilyl group,
isoamyldimethylsilyl group, hexyldimethylsilyl group,
octyldimethylsilyl group, 2-ethylhexyl-dimethylsilyl group,
decyldimethylsilyl group and 3,7-dimethyloctyldimethylsilyl
group.</p><p num="0040">The alkylamino group may be any of linear, branched
or cyclic, may be a monoalkyl group or a dialkylamino
group, and usually has about 1 to 40 carbon atoms, and
specific examples thereof include a methylamino group,
dimethylamino group, ethylamino group, diethylamino group,
propylamino group, i-propylamino group, butylamino group, 
i-butylamino group, t-butylamino group, pentylamino group,
isoamylamino group, hexylamino group, cyclohexylamino
group, heptylamino group, octylamino group, 2-ethylhexylamino
group, nonylamino group, decylamino group,
3,7-dimethyloctylamino group, laurylamino group and the
like, and preferable are a pentylamino group, isoamylamino
group, hexylamino group, octylamino group, 2-ethylhexylamino
group, decylamino group and 3,7-dimethyloctylamino
group.</p><p num="0041">The aryl group usually has about 6 to 60 carbon
atoms, and specific examples thereof include a phenyl
group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenyl groups (C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> indicates 1
to 12 carbon atoms, the same in the following), C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylphenyl groups, 1-naphthyl group, 2-naphthyl group and
the like, and preferable are C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenyl groups
and C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylphenyl groups.</p><p num="0042">The aryloxy group usually has about 6 to 60 carbon
atoms, and specifically, a phenoxy group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkoxyphenoxy groups, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylphenoxy groups, 1-naphthyloxy
group, 2-naphthyloxy and the like are
exemplified, and preferable are a phenoxy group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkoxyphenoxy groups and C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylphenoxy groups.</p><p num="0043">The arylsilyl group usually has about six to 60
carbon atoms, and exemplified are phenylsilyl group, C<sub>1</sub> to
C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenylsilyl group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylphenylsilyl 
group, 1-naphtylsilyl group, 2-naphtylsilyl group,
dimethylphenylsilyl group, etc. C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxy phenyl
silyl group and C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyl phenyl silyl group are
preferable.</p><p num="0044">The arylamino group usually has about 6 to 60 carbon
atoms, and specific examples thereof include a phenylamino
group, diphenylamino group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenylamino
groups, di(C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenyl)amino groups, di(C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylphenyl)amino groups, 1-naphthylamino group, 2-naphthylamino
group, and the like, and preferable are C<sub>1</sub> to
C<sub>12</sub> alkylphenylamino groups and di(C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylphenyl)amino groups.</p><p num="0045">The arylalkyl group usually has about seven to 60
carbon atoms. Specifically, phenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyl group, C<sub>1</sub>
to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyl group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyl group, 1-naphtyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyl
group, 2-naphtyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyl group, etc. are
exemplified, and C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxy phenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyl
group, and C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyl phenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyl group are
preferable.</p><p num="0046">The arylalkoxy group usually has about 7 to 60 carbon
atoms, and specifically, phenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxy groups, C<sub>1</sub>
to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxy groups, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxy groups, 1-naphthyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkoxy groups, 2-naphthyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxy groups and the 
like are exemplified, and preferable are C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkoxyphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxy groups and C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxy groups.</p><p num="0047">The arylalkylsilyl group usually has about 7 to 60
carbon atoms. Specifically, phenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylsilyl
group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylsilyl group, C<sub>1</sub>
to C<sub>12</sub> alkylphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylsilyl group, 1-naphtyl-C<sub>1</sub>
to C<sub>12</sub> alkylsilyl group, 2-naphtyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylsilyl
group, phenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyldimethylsilyl group, etc. are
exemplified, and C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylsilyl
group, and C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylsilyl group
are preferable.</p><p num="0048">The arylalkylamino group has about 7 to 60 carbon
atoms. Specifically Phenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylamino group, C<sub>1</sub> to
C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylamino group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylamino group, di(C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkoxyphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyl)amino group, di(C1 to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkyl)amino group, 1-naphtyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylamino group, 2-naphtyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylamino group, etc.
are exemplified, and C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylamino group, and di(C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylphenyl-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkyl)amino group are preferable.</p><p num="0049">The monovalent heterocyclic compound group means a
remaining atomic group obtained by removing one hydrogen
atom from a heterocyclic compound, and the number of carbon 
atoms is usually from about 4 to 60, preferably from 4 to
20. The number of carbon atoms of a heterocyclic compound
group does not include the number of carbon atoms of a
substituent. Here, the term heterocyclic compound includes
organic compounds having a cyclic structure in which
elements constituting a ring is not composed only of a
carbon atom but also hetero atoms such as oxygen, sulfur,
nitrogen, phosphorus, boron and the like are contained in
the ring. Specifically, a thienyl group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylthienyl groups, pyrrolyl group, furyl group, pyridyl
group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylpyridyl groups and the like are
exemplified, and preferable are a thienyl group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylthienyl groups, pyridyl group are C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylpyridyl groups.</p><p num="0050">R<sub>3</sub> to R<sub>7</sub> in the repeating unit represented by the
above formula (4), and R<sub>11</sub> and R<sub>12</sub> in the repeating unit
represented by the above formula (6) each independently
represent a group selected from a hydrogen atom, alkyl
group, aryl group and monovalent heterocyclic compound
group.</p><p num="0051">R<sub>3</sub> to R<sub>7</sub> in X<sub>2</sub> of formula (4), and R<sub>11</sub> and R<sub>12</sub> in
formula (6) are described as follows when they are
substituents other than a hydrogen atom.</p><p num="0052">The alkyl group may be any of linear, branched or
cyclic, and usually has about 1 to 20 carbon atoms, and 
specific examples thereof include a methyl group, ethyl
group, propyl group, i-propyl group, butyl group, i-butyl
group, t-butyl group, pentyl group, isoamyl group, hexyl
group, cyclohexyl group, heptyl group, octyl group, 2-ethylhexyl
group, nonyl group, decyl group, 3,7-dimethyloctyl
group, lauryl group and the like, and
preferable are a pentyl group, isoamyl group, hexyl group,
octyl group, 2-ethylhexyl group, decyl group and 3,7-dimethyloctyl
group.</p><p num="0053">The aryl group usually has about 6 to 60 carbon
atoms, and specific examples thereof include a phenyl
group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenyl groups (C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> indicates 1
to 12 carbon atoms, the same in the following), C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
alkylphenyl groups, 1-naphthyl group, 2-naphthyl group and
the like, and preferable are C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkoxyphenyl groups
and C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylphenyl groups.</p><p num="0054">The monovalent heterocyclic compound group usually
has the carbon atoms from about 4 to 60, and exemplified,
specifically, a thienyl group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylthienyl
groups, pyrrolyl group, furyl group, pyridyl group, C<sub>1</sub> to
C<sub>12</sub> alkylpyridyl groups and the like, and preferable are a
thienyl group, C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylthienyl groups, pyridyl group
are C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylpyridyl groups.</p><p num="0055">In the repeating unit represented by the above
formula (4), m and n are each independently an integer of 0 
to 3. When m is two or more, a plurality of R<sub>1</sub> is the same
or different. When n is two or more, a plurality of R<sub>2</sub> is
the same or different. Any two of R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>7</sub> may be connected
to form a ring. Furthermore, when R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>7</sub> is a group
containing an alkyl chain, the alkyl chain may be
interrupted by a group containing a hetero atom.</p><p num="0056">In the repeating unit represented by the above
formula (5), j is an integer of 1 to 4. When j is two or
more, a plurality of R<sub>8</sub> is the same or different. When j is
two or more, any two of R<sub>8</sub> may be connected to form a ring.
Furthermore, when R<sub>8</sub> is a group containing an alkyl chain,
the alkyl chain may be interrupted by a group containing a
hetero atom.</p><p num="0057">In the repeating unit represented by the above
formula (6), h and i are each independently an integer of 0
to 3. When h is two or more, a plurality of R<sub>9</sub> is the same
or different. When i is two or more, a plurality of R<sub>10</sub> is
the same or different. Any two of R<sub>9</sub> to R<sub>12</sub> may be connected
to form a ring. Furthermore, when R<sub>9</sub> to R<sub>12</sub> is a group
containing an alkyl chain, the alkyl chain may be
interrupted by a group containing a hetero atom. Here, as
the hetero atom, oxygen atom, sulfur atom, nitrogen atom,
etc. are exemplified.</p><p num="0058">Examples of the group containing a hetero atom
include following groups. <img id="img-00240001" orientation="unknown" wi="108" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240001.tif" inline="no" he="29"/><img id="img-00240002" orientation="unknown" wi="108" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240002.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
Here, R means a hydrogen atom, alkyl group having 1 to 20
carbon atoms, aryl group having 6 to 60 carbon atoms, and
heterocyclic compound group having 4 to 60 carbon atoms.</p><p num="0059">The substituent containing an alkyl chain may be any
one of linear, branched and cyclic, or combination thereof,
and as the examples of not linear, exemplified are isoamyl
group, 2-ethylhexyl group, 3,7-dimethyloctyl group,
cyclohexyl group, 4-C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> alkylcyclohexyl group, etc. In
order to improve the solubility of the polymeric
fluorescent substance in a solvent, it is suitable that at
least one of the substituents in the above formula (1)
contains a cyclic or branched alkyl chain.</p><p num="0060">In order to obtain a material of strong fluorescence,
it is suitable that there is little symmetry in the form of
the repeating unit including substituent.</p><p num="0061">Furthermore, when R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>12</sub> are those including an
aryl group or a heterocyclic compound group as a part of
the structure, they may have further one or more
substituents. </p><p num="0062">Since light emitting property and life time as a
device may be deteriorated when a polymerizable group
remains as an end group of the polymeric fluorescent
substance, the end group may be protected by a stable
group. Those having a conjugation bond continuing to a
conjugated structure of the main chain are preferable, and
exemplified are structures connecting to an aryl group or a
heterocyclic compound group through a vinylene group.
Concretely, substituents represented by Chemical Formula 10
described in JP-A No. 9-45478, and the like are
exemplified.</p><p num="0063">Method for synthesizing the polymeric fluorescent
substance include a polymerization method by Suzuki
coupling reaction from the corresponding monomer, a
polymerization method by Grignard reaction, a
polymerization method by using nickel (0) catalyst, a
polymerization method by using an oxidizing agent such as
FeCl<sub>3</sub>, etc., a method by electrochemical oxidative
polymerization, and a method by decomposition of an
intermediate polymer having suitable leaving group. Among
them, in view of easiness of the reaction control, the
polymerization method by Suzuki coupling reaction, the
polymerization method by Grignard reaction, and the
polymerization method by using nickel (0) catalyst are
preferable. </p><p num="0064">This polymeric fluorescent substance may contain
other repeating unit than the repeating unit of formulae
(1) and (3) in the range wherein luminescent property and
charge transport property do not deteriorate. The
repeating unit of formulae (1) and (3) or other unit than
the repeating unit of formulae (1) and (3) may be connected
via a non-conjugated unit, or such non-conjugated part may
also contained in the repeating unit. As the linkage
structure, there are exemplified those shown in the
following chemical formula, combinations of those shown in
the following chemical formula with a vinylene group,
combinations of two or more of those shown in the following
chemical formula, and the like.</p><p num="0065">Here, R is selected from the same substituents as
described above, and Ar represents a hydrocarbon group
having 6 to 60 carbon atoms.
<img id="img-00260001" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00260001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/><img id="img-00260002" orientation="unknown" wi="112" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00260002.tif"  inline="no" he="22"/><img id="img-00260003" orientation="unknown" wi="112" img-format="tif"  img-content="cf"  file="00260003.tif"  inline="no" he="34"/></p><p num="0066">This polymeric fluorescent substance may also be a
random, block or graft copolymer, or a polymer having an
intermediate structure thereof, for example, a random
copolymer having blocking property.</p><p num="0067">From the viewpoint for obtaining a polymeric
fluorescent substance having high fluorescent quantum
yield, the repeating regularity is preferably lower, and
example, a random copolymer is more preferable than an
alternating copolymer. In order to obtain an alternating
copolymer, it is necessary to use monomers each having two
kind of active groups for polymerization. On the other
hand, a random copolymer can be obtained by charging a
plurality of monomers having one kind of active group in a
desired ratio, and the preparation is easily conducted.
Further, a random copolymer having a block property and a
block copolymer composed of blocks of ununiform sizes, or a
graft copolymer, are more preferable than a complete random
copolymer. Polymers of branching in the main chain and of
three or more terminals are also included. Further, a
dendrimer grown regularly and a structure containing random
branching are also included.</p><p num="0068">Further, as the polymeric fluorescent substance,
those emitting fluorescence in a solid state are suitably
used, since the material utilizes light emission from a
thin film. </p><p num="0069">As good solvents for the polymeric fluorescent
substance, there are exemplified chloroform, methylene
chloride, dichloroethane, tetrahydrofuran, toluene, xylene,
mesitylene, tetralin, decalin, n-butylbenzene and the like.
The polymeric fluorescent substance can be usually
dissolved in these solvents in an amount of 0.1 wt % or
more, though the amount differs depending on the structure
and molecular weight of the polymeric fluorescent
substance.</p><p num="0070">The polymeric fluorescent substance has a number-average
molecular weight of 10<sup>3</sup> to 10<sup>8</sup> in terms of
polystyrene, and the degree of polymerization thereof also
changes depending on repeating structures and proportion
thereof. From the standpoint of film forming property,
generally the total amount of repeating structures is
preferably from 20 to 10000, more preferably from 30 to
10000, particularly preferably from 50 to 5000.</p><p num="0071">When these polymeric fluorescent substances are used
as a light emitting material of a polymer LED, the purity
thereof exerts an influence on light emitting property,
therefore, it is preferable that a monomer before
polymerization is purified by a method such as
distillation, sublimation purification, re-crystallization
and the like before being polymerized and further, it is
preferable to conduct a purification treatment such as reprecipitation 
purification, chromatographic separation and
the like after the synthesis.</p><p num="0072">The polymeric fluorescent substance of the present
invention can be used not only as a light emitting
material, but also as an organic semiconductor material,
optical material, or as conductive material by doping.</p><p num="0073">A method of producing a polymeric fluorescent
substance of the present invention will be described below.</p><p num="0074">As the method of producing a polymeric fluorescent
substance of the present invention, for example, a method
described in JP-A No. 5-202355 is mentioned, when a
vinylene group is contained in the main chain. Namely,
there are exemplified methods such as polymerization of a
compound having an aldehyde group with a compound having a
phosphonium salt group, or of a compound having an aldehyde
group and a phosphonium salt group, according to a Wittig
reaction, polymerization of a compound having a vinyl group
with a compound having a halogen group, or of a compound
having a vinyl group and a halogen group, according to a
Heck reaction, polymerization of a compound having an
aldehyde group with a compound having an alkylphosphonate
group, or of a compound having an aldehyde group and an
alkylphosphonate group, according to a Horner-Wadsworth-Emmons
reaction, polycondensation of a compound having two
or more halogenated methyl groups, according to a dehydrohalogenating 
method, polycondensation of a compound
having two or more sulfonium salt groups, according to a
sulfonium salt-decomposing method, polymerization of a
compound having an aldehyde group with a compound having an
acetonitrile group, or of a compound having an aldehyde
group and an acetonitrile group, according to a Knoevenagel
reaction, polymerization of a compound having two or more
aldehyde groups, according to McMurry reaction, and the
like.</p><p num="0075">When a vinylene group is not contained in the main
chain, for example, a method of polymerization from
corresponding monomers by a Suzuki coupling reaction, a
method of polymerization by a Grignard reaction, a method
of polymerization using a Ni(0) catalyst, a method of
polymerization using an oxidizer such as FeCl<sub>3</sub> and the
like, a method of oxidation polymerization
electrochemically, a method of decomposition of an
intermediate polymer having a suitable releasing group, and
the like are exemplified.</p><p num="0076">Of these, the polymerization method by a Wittig
reaction, the polymerization method by a Heck reaction, the
polymerization method by a Horner-Wadsworth-Emmons method,
the polymerization method by a Knoevenagel reaction, the
polymerization method by a Suzuki coupling reaction, the
polymerization method by a Grignard reaction and the 
polymerization method using a Ni(0) catalyst are preferable
since structure control is easy in these methods.</p><p num="0077">Specifically, a compound used as a monomer, having a
plurality of reactive substituents is dissolved, if
necessary, in an organic solvent, and can be reacted at the
melting temperature or more and the boiling point or less
of the organic solvent using an alkali or suitable
catalyst, for example. For example, known methods can be
used, described in "Organic Reactions", vol. 14, pp. 270
to 490, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc., 1965, "Organic
Reactions , vol. 27, pp. 345 to 390, John Wiley &amp; Sons,
Inc., 1982, "Organic Synthesis" , Collective Volume VI,
pp. 407 to 411, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc., 1988, Chemical
Review, vol. 95, p. 2457 (1995), Journal of Organometallic
Chemistry, vol. 576, p. 147 (1999), Journal of Praktical
Chemistry, vol. 336, p. 247 (1994), Makromolecular
Chemistry Macromolecular Symposium, vol. 12, p. 229 (1987),
and the like.</p><p num="0078">It is preferable that the organic solvent used is
subjected to a deoxygenation treatment sufficiently and the
reaction is progressed under an inert atmosphere, generally
for suppressing a side reaction, though the treatment
differs depending on compounds and reactions used.
Further, it is preferable to conduct a dehydration
treatment likewise (however, this is not applicable in the 
case of a reaction in a two-phase system with water, such
as a Suzuki coupling reaction).</p><p num="0079">For the reaction, an alkali or suitable catalyst is
added appropriately. These may be selected according to
the reaction used. It is preferable that the alkali or
catalyst is soluble sufficiently in a solvent used for the
reaction. As the method of mixing an alkali or catalyst,
there is exemplified a method of adding a solution of an
alkali or catalyst slowly while stirring under an inner
atmosphere of argon and nitrogen and the like or a method
of slowly adding the reaction solution to a solution of an
alkali or catalyst, inversely.</p><p num="0080">More specifically, regarding the reaction conditions,
in the cases of a Wittig reaction, Horner reaction,
Knoevengel reaction and the like, an alkali in an amount of
equivalent or more, preferably from 1 to 3 equivalent of
based on the amount of functional groups of monomers is
used and reacted. The alkali is not particularly
restricted, and for example, metal alkolates such as
potassium-t-butoxide, sodium-t-butoxide, sodium ethylate,
lithium methylate and the like, hydride reagents such as
sodium hydride and the like, amides such as sodiumamide and
the like can be used. As the solvent, N,N-dimethylformamide,
tetrahydrofuran, dioxane, toluene and
the like are used. The reaction can be progressed at a 
reaction temperature of usually from room temperature to
about 150C. The reaction time is, for example, from 5
minutes to 40 hours, and time for sufficient progress of
polymerization may be permissible, and since there is no
necessity of leaving for a long period of time after
completion of the reaction, the reaction time is preferably
from 10 minutes to 24 hours. The concentration in the
reaction may advantageously be selected appropriately
within the range from about 0.01 wt% to the maximum
solution concentration since when the concentration is too
low, the reaction efficiency is poor and when too high, the
reaction control is difficult, and the usual range is from
0.1 wt% to 20 wt%. In the case of a Heck reaction,
monomers are reacted in the presence of a base such as
triethylamine and the like, using a palladium catalayst.
The reaction is effected at a reaction temperature of from
about 80 to 160C for a reaction time of about 1 to 100
hours, using a solvent having relatively high boiling point
such as N,N-dimethylformamide, N-methylpyrrolidone and the
like.</p><p num="0081">In the case of a Suzuki coupling reaction, palladium
[tetrakis(triphenylphosphine)], palladium acetates and the
like are used, for example, as a catalyst, and an inorganic
base such as potassium carbonate, sodium carbonate, barium
hydroxide and the like, an organic base such as 
triethylamine and the like, and an inorganic salt such as
cesium fluoride and the like, are added preferably in
equivalent amount, preferably in an amount of 1 to 10
equivalent based on monomers, and reacted. It may be also
permissible that an inorganic salt is used as an aqueous
solution and reacted in a two-phase system. As the
solvent, N,N-dimethylformamide, toluene, dimethoxyethane,
tetrahydrofuran and the like are exemplified. Depending on
the solvent, temperatures of 50 to 160C are preferably
used. It may also be permissible that the temperature is
raised near the boiling point of a solvent, to cause
reflux. The reaction time is from about 1 to 200 hours.</p><p num="0082">In the case of a Grignard reaction, exemplified is a
method in which a halide and metal Mg are reacted in an
ether-based solvent such as tetrahydrofuran, diethyl ether,
dimethoxyethane and the like to prepare a Grignard reagent
which is mixed with a separately prepared monomer solution,
and a nickel or palladium catalyst is added while paying
attention to excess reaction, then, the reaction
temperature is raised to reflux and the reaction is
effected. The Grignard reagent is used in the equivalent
amount, preferably in an amount of from 1 to 1.5
equivalent, more preferably from 1 to 1.2 equivalent, based
on monomers. Also in the case of polymerization by other
methods than those described above, the reaction can be 
effected by known methods.</p><p num="0083">Next, the polymer LED of the present invention will
be described. Regarding the structure of the polymer LED
of the present invention, a light-emitting layer is present
between an anode and a cathode at least one of which is
transparent or semi-transparent, and the polymeric
fluorescent substance of the present invention is contained
in the light-emitting layer.</p><p num="0084">As the polymer LED of the present invention, there
are listed polymer LEDs having an electron transporting
layer disposed between a cathode and a light emitting
layer, polymer LEDs having a hole transporting layer
disposed between an anode and a light emitting layer,
polymer LEDs having an electron transporting layer disposed
between a cathode and a light emitting layer and having a
hole transporting layer disposed between an anode and a
light emitting layer.</p><p num="0085">For example, the following structures a) to d) are
specifically exemplified.
<sl><li>a) anode/light emitting layer/cathode</li><li>b) anode/hole transporting layer/light emitting
layer/cathode</li><li>c) anode/light emitting layer/electron transporting
layer/ /cathode</li><li>d) anode/hole transporting layer/light emitting 
layer/electron transporting layer/cathode
(wherein, / indicates adjacent lamination of layers.
Hereinafter, the same)
Herein, the light emitting layer is a layer having
function to emit a light, the hole transporting layer is a
layer having function to transport a hole, and the electron
transporting layer is a layer having function to transport
an electron. Herein, the electron transporting layer and
the hole transporting layer are generically called a charge
transporting layer.The light emitting layer, hole transporting layer and
electron transporting layer may also each independently
used in two or more layers.Of charge transporting layers disposed adjacent to an
electrode, that having function to improve charge injecting
efficiency from the electrode and having effect to decrease
driving voltage of an device are particularly called
sometimes a charge injecting layer (hole injecting layer,
electron injecting layer) in general.For enhancing adherence with an electrode and
improving charge injection from an electrode, the above-described
charge injecting layer or insulation layer having
a thickness of 2 nm or less may also be provided adjacent
to an electrode, and further, for enhancing adherence of
the interface, preventing mixing and the like, a thin 
buffer layer may also be inserted into the interface of a
charge transporting layer and light emitting layer.The order and number of layers laminated and the
thickness of each layer can be appropriately applied while
considering light emitting efficiency and life of the
device.In the present invention, as the polymer LED having a
charge injecting layer (electron injecting layer, hole
injecting layer) provided, there are listed a polymer LED
having a charge injecting layer provided adjacent to a
cathode and a polymer LED having a charge injecting layer
provided adjacent to an anode.For example, the following structures e) to p) are
specifically exemplified.</li><li>e) anode/charge injecting layer/light emitting
layer/cathode</li><li>f) anode/light emitting layer/charge injecting
layer/cathode</li><li>g) anode/charge injecting layer/light emitting
layer/charge injecting layer/cathode</li><li>h) anode/charge injecting layer/hole transporting
layer/light emitting layer/cathode</li><li>i) anode/hole transporting layer/light emitting
layer/charge injecting layer/cathode</li><li>j) anode/charge injecting layer/hole transporting 
layer/light emitting layer/charge injecting layer/cathode</li><li>k) anode/charge injecting layer/light emitting
layer/electron transporting layer/cathode</li><li>l) anode/light emitting layer/electron transporting
layer/charge injecting layer/cathode</li><li>m) anode/charge injecting layer/light emitting
layer/electron transporting layer/charge injecting
layer/cathode</li><li>n) anode/charge injecting layer/hole transporting
layer/light emitting layer/electron transporting
layer/cathode</li><li>o) anode/hole transporting layer/light emitting
layer/electron transporting layer/charge injecting
layer/cathode</li><li>p) anode/charge injecting layer/hole transporting
layer/light emitting layer/electron transporting
layer/charge injecting layer/cathode</li> </sl></p><p num="0086">As the specific examples of the charge injecting
layer, there are exemplified layers containing an
conducting polymer, layers which are disposed between an
anode and a hole transporting layer and contain a material
having an ionization potential between the ionization
potential of an anode material and the ionization potential
of a hole transporting material contained in the hole
transporting layer, layers which are disposed between a 
cathode and an electron transporting layer and contain a
material having an electron affinity between the electron
affinity of a cathode material and the electron affinity of
an electron transporting material contained in the electron
transporting layer, and the like.</p><p num="0087">When the above-described charge injecting layer is a
layer containing an conducting polymer, the electric
conductivity of the conducting polymer is preferably 10<sup>-5</sup>
S/cm or more and 10<sup>3</sup> S/cm or less, and for decreasing the
leak current between light emitting pixels, more preferably
10<sup>-5</sup> S/cm or more and 10<sup>2</sup> S/cm or less, further preferably
10<sup>-5</sup> S/cm or more and 10<sup>1</sup> S/cm or less.</p><p num="0088">Usually, to provide an electric conductivity of the
conducting polymer of 10<sup>-5</sup> S/cm or more and 10<sup>3</sup> S/cm or
less, a suitable amount of ions are doped into the
conducting polymer.</p> <p num="0089">Regarding the kind of an ion doped, an anion is used
in a hole injecting layer and a cation is used in an
electron injecting layer. As examples of the anion, a
polystyrene sulfonate ion, alkylbenzene sulfonate ion,
camphor sulfonate ion and the like are exemplified, and as
examples of the cation, a lithium ion, sodium ion,
potassium ion, tetrabutyl ammonium ion and the like are
exemplified.</p> <p num="0090">The thickness of the charge injecting layer is for 
example, from 1 nm to 100 nm, preferably from 2 nm to 50
nm.</p> <p num="0091">Materials used in the charge injecting layer may
properly be selected in view of relation with the materials
of electrode and adjacent layers, and there are exemplified
conducting polymers such as polyaniline and derivatives
thereof, polythiophene and derivatives thereof, polypyrrole
and derivatives thereof, poly(phenylene vinylene) and
derivatives thereof, poly(thienylene vinylene) and
derivatives thereof, polyquinoline and derivatives thereof,
polyquinoxaline and derivatives thereof, polymers
containing aromatic amine structures in the main chain or
the side chain, and the like, and metal phthalocyanine
(copper phthalocyanine and the like), carbon and the like.</p><p num="0092">The insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm or
less has function to make charge injection easy. As the
material of the above-described insulation layer, metal
fluoride, metal oxide, organic insulation materials and the
like are listed. As the polymer LED having an insulation
layer having a thickness of 2 nm or less, there are listed
polymer LEDs having an insulation layer having a thickness
of 2 nm or less provided adjacent to a cathode, and polymer
LEDs having an insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm
or less provided adjacent to an anode.</p><p num="0093">Specifically, there are listed the following 
structures q) to ab) for example.
<sl><li>q) anode/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm
or less/light emitting layer/cathode</li><li>r) anode/light emitting layer/insulation layer having
a thickness of 2 nm or less/cathode</li><li>s) anode/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm
or less/light emitting layer/insulation layer having a
thickness of 2 nm or less/cathode</li><li>t) anode/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm
or less/hole transporting layer/light emitting
layer/cathode</li><li>u) anode/hole transporting layer/light emitting
layer/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm or
less/cathode</li><li>v) anode/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm
or less/hole transporting layer/light emitting
layer/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm or
less/cathode</li><li>w) anode/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm
or less/light emitting layer/electron transporting
layer/cathode</li><li>x) anode/light emitting layer/electron transporting
layer/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm or
less/cathode</li><li>y) anode/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm 
or less/light emitting layer/electron transporting
layer/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm or
less/cathode</li><li>z) anode/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm
or less/hole transporting layer/light emitting
layer/electron transporting layer/cathode</li><li>aa) anode/hole transporting layer/light emitting
layer/electron transporting layer/insulation layer having a
thickness of 2 nm or less/cathode</li><li>ab) anode/insulation layer having a thickness of 2 nm
or less/hole transporting layer/light emitting
layer/electron transporting layer/insulation layer having a
thickness of 2 nm or less/cathode</li></sl></p><p num="0094">In producing a polymer LED, when a film is formed
from a solution by using such polymeric fluorescent
substance soluble in an organic solvent, only required is
removal of the solvent by drying after coating of this
solution, and even in the case of mixing of a charge
transporting material and a light emitting material, the
same method can be applied, causing an extreme advantage in
production. As the film forming method from a solution,
there can be used coating methods such as a spin coating
method, casting method, micro gravure coating method,
gravure coating method, bar coating method, roll coating
method, wire bar coating method, dip coating method, spray 
coating method, screen printing method, flexo printing
method, offset printing method, inkjet printing method and
the like.</p><p num="0095">Regarding the thickness of the light emitting layer,
the optimum value differs depending on material used, and
may properly be selected so that the driving voltage and
the light emitting efficiency become optimum values, and
for example, it is from 1 nm to 1 m, preferably from 2 nm
to 500 nm, further preferably from 5 nm to 200 nm.</p><p num="0096">In the polymer LED of the present invention, light
emitting materials other than the above-described polymeric
fluorescent substance can also be mixed in a light emitting
layer. Further, in the polymer LED of the present
invention, the light emitting layer containing light
emitting materials other than the above-described polymeric
fluorescent substance may also be laminated with a light
emitting layer containing the above-described polymeric
fluorescent substance.</p><p num="0097">As the light emitting material, known materials can
be used. In a compound having lower molecular weight,
there can be used, for example, naphthalene derivatives,
anthracene or derivatives thereof, perylene or derivatives
thereof; dyes such as polymethine dyes, xanthene dyes,
coumarine dyes, cyanine dyes; metal complexes of 8-hydroxyquinoline
or derivatives thereof, aromatic amine, 
tetraphenylcyclopentane or derivatives thereof, or
tetraphenylbutadiene or derivatives thereof, and the like.</p><p num="0098">Specifically, there can be used known compounds such
as those described in JP-A Nos. 57-51781, 59-195393 and the
like, for example.</p><p num="0099">When the polymer LED of the present invention has a
hole transporting layer, as the hole transporting materials
used, there are exemplified polyvinylcarbazole or
derivatives thereof, polysilane or derivatives thereof,
polysiloxane derivatives having an aromatic amine in the
side chain or the main chain, pyrazoline derivatives,
arylamine derivatives, stilbene derivatives,
triphenyldiamine derivatives, polyaniline or derivatives
thereof, polythiophene or derivatives thereof, polypyrrole
or derivatives thereof, poly(p-phenylenevinylene) or
derivatives thereof, poly(2,5-thienylenevinylene) or
derivatives thereof, or the like.</p><p num="0100">Specific examples of the hole transporting material
include those described in JP-A Nos. 63-70257, 63-175860,
2-135359, 2-135361, 2-209988, 3-37992 and 3-152184.</p><p num="0101">Among them, as the hole transporting materials used
in the hole transporting layer, preferable are polymer hole
transporting materials such as polyvinylcarbazole or
derivatives thereof, polysilane or derivatives thereof,
polysiloxane derivatives having an aromatic amine compound 
group in the side chain or the main chain, polyaniline or
derivatives thereof, polythiophene or derivatives thereof,
poly(p-phenylenevinylene) or derivatives thereof, poly(2,5-thienylenevinylene)
or derivatives thereof, or the like,
and further preferable are polyvinylcarbazole or
derivatives thereof, polysilane or derivatives thereof and
polysiloxane derivatives having an aromatic amine compound
group in the side chain or the main chain. In the case of
a hole transporting material having lower molecular weight,
it is preferably dispersed in a polymer binder for use.</p><p num="0102">Polyvinylcarbazole or derivatives thereof are
obtained, for example, by cation polymerization or radical
polymerization from a vinyl monomer.</p><p num="0103">As the polysilane or derivatives thereof, there are
exemplified compounds described in Chem. Rev., <u style="single">89</u>, 1359
(1989) and GB 2300196 published specification, and the
like. For synthesis, methods described in them can be
used, and a Kipping method can be suitably used
particularly.</p><p num="0104">As the polysiloxane or derivatives thereof, those
having the structure of the above-described hole
transporting material having lower molecular weight in the
side chain or main chain, since the siloxane skeleton
structure has poor hole transporting property.
Particularly, there are exemplified those having an 
aromatic amine having hole transporting property in the
side chain or main chain.</p><p num="0105">The method for forming a hole transporting layer is
not restricted, and in the case of a hole transporting
layer having lower molecular weight, a method in which the
layer is formed from a mixed solution with a polymer binder
is exemplified. In the case of a polymer hole transporting
material, a method in which the layer is formed from a
solution is exemplified.</p><p num="0106">The solvent used for the film forming from a solution
is not particularly restricted providing it can dissolve a
hole transporting material. As the solvent, there are
exemplified chlorine solvents such as chloroform, methylene
chloride, dichloroethane and the like, ether solvents such
as tetrahydrofuran and the like, aromatic hydrocarbon
solvents such as toluene, xylene and the like, ketone
solvents such as acetone, methyl ethyl ketone and the like,
and ester solvents such as ethyl acetate, butyl acetate,
ethylcellosolve acetate and the like.</p><p num="0107">As the film forming method from a solution, there can
be used coating methods such as a spin coating method,
casting method, micro gravure coating method, gravure
coating method, bar coating method, roll coating method,
wire bar coating method, dip coating method, spray coating
method, screen printing method, flexo printing method, 
offset printing method, inkjet printing method and the
like, from a solution.</p><p num="0108">The polymer binder mixed is preferably that does not
disturb charge transport extremely, and that does not have
strong absorption of a visible light is suitably used. As
such polymer binder, polycarbonate, polyacrylate,
poly(methyl acrylate), poly(methyl methacrylate),
polystyrene, poly(vinyl chloride), polysiloxane and the
like are exemplified.</p><p num="0109">Regarding the thickness of the hole transporting
layer, the optimum value differs depending on material
used, and may properly be selected so that the driving
voltage and the light emitting efficiency become optimum
values, and at least a thickness at which no pin hole is
produced is necessary, and too large thickness is not
preferable since the driving voltage of the device
increases. Therefore, the thickness of the hole
transporting layer is, for example, from 1 nm to 1 m,
preferably from 2 nm to 500 nm, further preferably from 5
nm to 200 nm.</p><p num="0110">When the polymer LED of the present invention has an
electron transporting layer, known compounds are used as
the electron transporting materials, and there are
exemplified oxadiazole derivatives, anthraquinonedimethane
or derivatives thereof, benzoquinone or derivatives 
thereof, naphthoquinone or derivatives thereof,
anthraquinone or derivatives thereof,
tetracyanoanthraquinodimethane or derivatives thereof,
fluorenone derivatives, diphenyldicyanoethylene or
derivatives thereof, diphenoquinone derivatives, or metal
complexes of 8-hydroxyquinoline or derivatives thereof,
polyquinoline and derivatives thereof, polyquinoxaline and
derivatives thereof, polyfluorene or derivatives thereof,
and the like.</p><p num="0111">Specifically, there are exemplified those described
in JP-A Nos. 63-70257, 63-175860, 2-135359, 2-135361, 2-209988,
3-37992 and 3-152184.</p><p num="0112">Among them, oxadiazole derivatives, benzoquinone or
derivatives thereof, anthraquinone or derivatives thereof,
or metal complexes of 8-hydroxyquinoline or derivatives
thereof, polyquinoline and derivatives thereof,
polyquinoxaline and derivatives thereof, polyfluorene or
derivatives thereof are preferable, and 2-(4-biphenyl)-5-(4-t-butylphenyl)-1,3,4-oxadiazole,
benzoquinone,
anthraquinone, tris(8-quinolinol)aluminum and polyquinoline
are further preferable.</p><p num="0113">The method for forming the electron transporting
layer is not particularly restricted, and in the case of an
electron transporting material having lower molecular
weight, a vapor deposition method from a powder, or a 
method of film-forming from a solution or melted state is
exemplified, and in the case of a polymer electron
transporting material, a method of film-forming from a
solution or melted state is exemplified, respectively.</p><p num="0114">The solvent used in the film-forming from a solution
is not particularly restricted provided it can dissolve
electron transporting materials and/or polymer binders. As
the solvent, there are exemplified chlorine solvents such
as chloroform, methylene chloride, dichloroethane and the
like, ether solvents such as tetrahydrofuran and the like,
aromatic hydrocarbon solvents such as toluene, xylene and
the like, ketone solvents such as acetone, methyl ethyl
ketone and the like, and ester solvents such as ethyl
acetate, butyl acetate, ethylcellosolve acetate and the
like.</p><p num="0115">As the film-forming method from a solution or melted
state, there can be used coating methods such as a spin
coating method, casting method, micro gravure coating
method, gravure coating method, bar coating method, roll
coating method, wire bar coating method, dip coating
method, spray coating method, screen printing method, flexo
printing method, offset printing method, inkjet printing
method and the like.</p><p num="0116">The polymer binder to be mixed is preferably that
which does not extremely disturb a charge transport 
property, and that does not have strong absorption of a
visible light is suitably used. As such polymer binder,
poly(N-vinylcarbazole), polyaniline or derivatives thereof,
polythiophene or derivatives thereof, poly(p-phenylene
vinylene) or derivatives thereof, poly(2,5-thienylene
vinylene) or derivatives thereof, polycarbonate,
polyacrylate, poly(methyl acrylate), poly(methyl
methacrylate), polystyrene, poly(vinyl chloride),
polysiloxane and the like are exemplified.</p><p num="0117">Regarding the thickness of the electron transporting
layer, the optimum value differs depending on material
used, and may properly be selected so that the driving
voltage and the light emitting efficiency become optimum
values, and at least a thickness at which no pin hole is
produced is necessary, and too large thickness is not
preferable since the driving voltage of the device
increases. Therefore, the thickness of the electron
transporting layer is, for example, from 1 nm to 1 m,
preferably from 2 nm to 500 nm, further preferably from 5
nm to 200 nm.</p><p num="0118">The substrate forming the polymer LED of the present
invention may preferably be that does not change in forming
an electrode and layers of organic materials, and there are
exemplified glass, plastics, polymer film, silicon
substrates and the like. In the case of a opaque 
substrate, it is preferable that the opposite electrode is
transparent or semitransparent.</p><p num="0119">In the present invention, it is preferable that an
anode is transparent or semitransparent, and as the
material of this anode, electron conductive metal oxide
films, semitransparent metal thin films and the like are
used. Specifically, there are used indium oxide, zinc
oxide, tin oxide, and films (NESA and the like) fabricated
by using an electron conductive glass composed of indium 
tin  oxide (ITO) , indium  zinc  oxide and the like,which are
metal oxide complexes, and gold, platinum, silver, copper
and the like are used, and among them, ITO, indium  zinc 
oxide, tin oxide are preferable. As the fabricating
method, a vacuum vapor deposition method, sputtering
method, ion plating method, plating method and the like are
used. As the anode, there may also be used organic
transparent conducting films such as polyaniline or
derivatives thereof, polythiophene or derivatives thereof
and the like.</p><p num="0120">The thickness of the anode can be appropriately
selected while considering transmission of a light and
electric conductivity, and for example, from 10 nm to 10 
m, preferably from 20 nm to 1 m, further preferably from
50 nm to 500 nm.</p><p num="0121">Further, for easy charge injection, there may be 
provided on the anode a layer comprising a phthalocyanine
derivative conducting polymers, carbon and the like, or a
layer having an average film thickness of 2 nm or less
comprising a metal oxide, metal fluoride, organic
insulating material and the like.</p><p num="0122">As the material of a cathode used in the polymer LED
of the present invention, that having lower work function
is preferable. For example, there are used metals such as
lithium, sodium, potassium, rubidium, cesium, beryllium,
magnesium, calcium, strontium, barium, aluminum, scandium,
vanadium, zinc, yttrium, indium, cerium, samarium,
europium, terbium, ytterbium and the like, or alloys
comprising two of more of them, or alloys comprising one or
more of them with one or more of gold, silver, platinum,
copper, manganese, titanium, cobalt, nickel, tungsten and
tin, graphite or graphite intercalation compounds and the
like. Examples of alloys include a magnesium-silver alloy,
magnesium-indium alloy, magnesium-aluminum alloy, indium-silver
alloy, lithium-aluminum alloy, lithium-magnesium
alloy, lithium-indium alloy, calcium-aluminum alloy and the
like. The cathode may be formed into a laminated structure
of two or more layers.</p><p num="0123">The thickness of the cathode can be appropriately
selected while considering transmission of a light and
electric conductivity, and for example, from 10 nm to 10  
m, preferably from 20 nm to 1 m, further preferably from
50 nm to 500 nm.</p><p num="0124">As the method for fabricating a cathode, there are
used a vacuum vapor deposition method, sputtering method,
lamination method in which a metal thin film is adhered
under heat and pressure, and the like. Further, there may
also be provided, between a cathode and an organic layer, a
layer comprising an conducting polymer, or a layer having
an average film thickness of 2 nm or less comprising a
metal oxide, metal fluoride, organic insulation material
and the like, and after fabrication of the cathode, a
protective layer may also be provided which protects the
polymer LED. For stable use of the polymer LED for a long
period of time, it is preferable to provide a protective
layer and/or protective cover for protection of the device
in order to prevent it from outside damage.</p><p num="0125">As the protective layer, there can be used a polymer
compound, metal oxide, metal fluoride, metal borate and the
like. As the protective cover, there can be used a glass
plate, a plastic plate the surface of which has been
subjected to lower-water-permeation treatment, and the
like, and there is suitably used a method in which the
cover is pasted with an device substrate by a thermosetting
resin or light-curing resin for sealing. If space is
maintained using a spacer, it is easy to prevent an device 
from being injured. If an inner gas such as nitrogen and
argon is sealed in this space, it is possible to prevent
oxidation of a cathode, and further, by placing a desiccant
such as barium oxide and the like in the above-described
space, it is easy to suppress the damage of an device by
moisture adhered in the production process. Among them,
any one means or more are preferably adopted.</p><p num="0126">For obtaining light emission in plane form using the
polymer LED of the present invention, an anode and a
cathode in the plane form may properly be placed so that
they are laminated each other. Further, for obtaining
light emission in pattern form, there are a method in which
a mask with a window in pattern form is placed on the
above-described plane light emitting device, a method in
which an organic layer in non-light emission part is formed
to obtain extremely large thickness providing substantial
non-light emission, and a method in which any one of an
anode or a cathode, or both of them are formed in the
pattern. By forming a pattern by any of these methods and
by placing some electrodes so that independent on/off is
possible, there is obtained a display device of segment
type which can display digits, letters, simple marks and
the like. Further, for forming a dot matrix device, it may
be advantageous that anodes and cathodes are made in the
form of stripes and placed so that they cross at right 
angles. By a method in which a plurality of kinds of
polymeric fluorescent substances emitting different colors
of lights are placed separately or a method in which a
color filter or luminescence converting filter is used,
area color displays and multi color displays are obtained.
A dot matrix display can be driven by passive driving, or
by active driving combined with TFT and the like. These
display devices can be used as a display of a computer,
television, portable terminal, portable telephone, car
navigation, view finder of a video camera, and the like.</p><p num="0127">Further, the above-described light emitting device in
plane form is a thin self-light-emitting one, and can be
suitably used as a flat light source for back-light of a
liquid crystal display, or as a flat light source for
illumination. Further, if a flexible plate is used, it can
also be used as a curved light source or a display.</p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0128">The following examples further illustrate the present
invention in detail but do not limit the scope thereof.</p><p num="0129">Here, regarding the weight-average molecular weight
and number-average molecular weight, the polystyrene
reduced average molecular weight was obtained by gel
permeation chromatography (GPC) using chloroform as a
solvent.</p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0130">9,9-dioctyl-2,7-dibromofluorene 0.77g, 2,5-bis{2'-{4''-(N,N-diphenylamino)phenyl}ethenyl}-1,4-dibromobenzene
0.05, 2,2'-dipyridine 0.026g, anhydrous nickel chloride
0.0217g, triphenylphosphine 0.5g and zinc dust 0.8g were
charged into a reaction vessel, then, the atmosphere in the
reaction system was purged with argon gas. To this, 8.5ml
of N,N'-dimethylformamide (DMF) degassed beforehand by
argon gas bubbling was added.</p><p num="0131">Then, the mixed solution was reacted at 80C for 25
hours. The reaction was performed in argon gas atmosphere.
After the reaction, the solution was cooled and poured into
methanol. Next, resulting precipitates were filtrated and
collected. The precipitates were dried, then dissolved in
chloroform. The solution was filtrated to remove insoluble
materials, this solution was poured into methanol and
resulting precipitates were collected. The precipitates
were dried under reduced pressure to obtain a polymer
0.11g. This polymer is referred to as polymeric fluorescent
substance 1. The polystyrene reduced number average
molecular weight of polymeric fluorescent substance 1 was
5x10<sup>3</sup>.</p><p num="0132">From charging ratio of monomers, the ratio of the
repeating units of formula (7) and formula (8) in polymeric
fluorescent substance 1 is 95:5, and polymeric fluorescent
substance 1 is a random copolymer. <img id="img-00570001" orientation="unknown" wi="108" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00570001.tif" inline="no" he="28"/><img id="img-00570002" orientation="unknown" wi="108" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00570002.tif" inline="no" he="87"/></p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0133">9,9-dioctyl-2,7-dibromofluorene 0.548g, 2-{4'-(N,N-diphenylamino)}phenyl-1,4-dichlorobenzene
0.39g, 2,2'-dipyridine
0.624g, 1,5-cyclooctadiene 0.866g were charged
into a reaction vessel, then, the atmosphere in the
reaction system was purged with argon gas. To this, 20ml of
N,N'-dimethylformamide (DMF) degassed beforehand by argon
gas bubbling was added.</p><p num="0134">Then, bis(1,5-cyclooctadiene)nickel (0) 1.10g was
added to the mixed solution, and it was reacted at 70C for
20 hours. The reaction was performed in argon gas
atmosphere. After the reaction, the solution was cooled and 
poured into mixed solvent of methanol 25ml/ion-exchanged
water 50ml containing 10ml of 25%aqueous ammonia. Next,
resulting precipitates were filtrated and collected.</p><p num="0135">The precipitates were dried, then dissolved in
chloroform. The solution was filtrated to remove insoluble
materials, then the solvent was removed under reduced
pressure to collect resulting precipitates. The
precipitates were washed with acetone and dried under
reduced pressure to obtain a polymer 0.15g. This polymer is
referred to as polymeric fluorescent substance 2. The
polystyrene reduced number average molecular weight of
polymeric fluorescent substance 2 was 1.2x10<sup>4</sup>.</p><p num="0136">From charging ratio of monomers, the ratio of the
repeating units of formula (9) and formula (10) in
polymeric fluorescent substance 2 is 50:50, and polymeric
fluorescent substance 2 is a random copolymer.
<img id="img-00580001" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00580001.tif" inline="no" he="26"/><img id="img-00580002" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00580002.tif" inline="no" he="50"/></p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="0137">9,9-dioctyl-2,7-dibromofluorene 0.79g, 2-{2'-{4"-(N,N-diphenylamino)}phenyl}ethenyl}-1,4-dibromobenzene
0.081g, 2,2'-dipyridine 0.558g, 1,5-cyclooctadiene 0.432g
were charged into a reaction vessel, then, the atmosphere
in the reaction system was purged with argon gas. To this,
20ml of N,N'-dimethylformamide (DMF) degassed beforehand by
argon gas bubbling was added.</p><p num="0138">Then, bis(1,5-cyclooctadiene)nickel (0) 0.96g was
added to the mixed solution, and it was reacted at 70C for
16 hours. The reaction was performed in argon gas
atmosphere. After the reaction, the solution was cooled and
poured into mixed solvent of methanol 25ml/ion-exchanged
water 50ml containing 10ml of 25%aqueous ammonia. Next,
resulting precipitates were filtrated and collected.</p><p num="0139">The precipitates were dried, then dissolved in
chloroform. The solution was filtrated to remove insoluble
materials, then the solvent was removed under reduced
pressure to collect resulting precipitates. The
precipitates were washed with acetone and dried under
reduced pressure to obtain a polymer 0.5g. This polymer is
referred to as polymeric fluorescent substance 3. The
polystyrene reduced number average molecular weight of
polymeric fluorescent substance 3 was 7.7x10<sup>3</sup>.</p><p num="0140">From charging ratio of monomers, the ratio of the 
repeating units of formula (11) and formula (12) in
polymeric fluorescent substance 3 is 90:10, and polymeric
fluorescent substance 3 is a random copolymer.
<img id="img-00600001" orientation="unknown" wi="84" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00600001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/><img id="img-00600002" orientation="unknown" wi="84" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00600002.tif" inline="no" he="55"/></p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0141">9,9-dioctylfluorene-2,7-bis(ethylene boronate)
0.305g(0.575mmols), 2-{2'-{4''-(N,N-diphenylamino)phenyl}ethenyl}-1,4-dibromobenzene
0.309g(0.
547mmols) and aliquat336 (230mg, 0.57mmols) were dissolved
in toluene (10ml), and 10ml of aqueous solution of
potassium carbonate (240mg, 1.7mmols) was added to this.
Further, tetrakis(triphenylphosphine)palladium (1.3mg,
0.0011mmols) was added and refluxed for 10 hours with
heating. The organic layer was added to methanol dropwise,
and deposited precipitates were filtrated. The obtained
precipitates were dissolved in toluene, and added to 
methanol dropwise. The deposited precipitates were
filtrated to obtain a polymer 0.25g. This polymer is
referred to as polymeric fluorescent substance 4. The
polystyrene reduced number average molecular weight of
polymeric fluorescent substance 4 is 1.8x10<sup>4</sup>.</p><p num="0142">From charging ratio of monomers, the ratio of the
repeating units of formula (13) and formula (14) in
polymeric fluorescent substance 4 is 50:50, and polymeric
fluorescent substance 4 is an alternating copolymer.
<img id="img-00610001" orientation="unknown" wi="76" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00610001.tif" inline="no" he="23"/><img id="img-00610002" orientation="unknown" wi="76" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00610002.tif" inline="no" he="55"/></p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="0143">9,9-dioctylfluorene-2,7-bis(ethylene boronate)
0.309g(0.582mmols), 9,9-dioctyl-2,7-dibromofluorene
0.274g(0.499mmols), 2-{2'-{4''-(N,N-diphenylamino)
phenyl}ethenyl}-1,4-dibromobenzene 0.028g(0. 0554mmols) and
aliquat336 (230mg, 0.57mmols) were dissolved in toluene 
(10ml), and 10ml of aqueous solution of potassium
carbonate (240mg, 1.7mmols) was added to this. Further,
tetrakis(triphenylphosphine)palladium (1.3mg, 0.0011mmols)
was added and refluxed for 10 hours with heating. The
organic layer was added to methanol dropwise, and deposited
precipitates were filtrated. The obtained precipitates were
dissolved in toluene, and added to methanol dropwise. The
deposited precipitates were filtrated to obtain a polymer
0.34g. This polymer is referred to as polymeric fluorescent
substance 5. The polystyrene reduced number average
molecular weight of polymeric fluorescent substance 5 is
4.0x10<sup>4</sup>.</p><p num="0144">From charging ratio of monomers, the ratio of the
repeating units of formula (15) and formula (16) in
polymeric fluorescent substance 5 is 95:5, and polymeric
fluorescent substance 5 is a random copolymer consisting of
the repeating units of formula (15) and formula (16). Here,
the repeating unit of formula (15) inevitably exists next
to the repeating unit of formula (16).
<img id="img-00620001" orientation="unknown" wi="72" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00620001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/><img id="img-00630001" orientation="unknown" wi="91" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00630001.tif" inline="no" he="54"/></p><heading>Example 6</heading><p num="0145">9,9-dioctylfluorene-2,7-bis(ethylene boronate)
0.305g(0.576mmols), 9,9-dioctyl-2,7-dibromofluorene
0.271g(0.494mmols), 2,5-bis(3-(N-ethylcarbazolyl))-1,4-dibromobenzene
0.037g(0. 055mmols) and aliquat336 (230mg,
0.57mmols) were dissolved in toluene (10ml), and 10ml of
aqueous solution of potassium carbonate (240mg, 1.7mmols)
was added to this. Further,
tetrakis(triphenylphosphine)palladium (1.3mg, 0.0011mmols)
was added and refluxed for 10 hours with heating. The
organic layer was added to methanol dropwise, and deposited
precipitates were filtrated. The obtained precipitates were
dissolved in toluene, and added to methanol dropwise. The
deposited precipitates were filtrated to obtain a polymer
0.32g. This polymer is referred to as polymeric fluorescent
substance 6. The polystyrene reduced number average
molecular weight of polymeric fluorescent substance 6 is
3.1x10<sup>4</sup>. </p><p num="0146">From charging ratio of monomers, the ratio of the
repeating units of formula (17) and formula (18) in
polymeric fluorescent substance 6 is 95:5, and polymeric
fluorescent substance 6 is a random copolymer consisting of
the repeating units of formula (17) and formula (18). Here,
the repeating unit of formula (17) inevitably exists next
to the repeating unit of formula (18).
<img id="img-00640001" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00640001.tif" inline="no" he="25"/><img id="img-00640002" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00640002.tif" inline="no" he="78"/></p><heading>Example 7</heading><p num="0147">9,9-dioctylfluorene-2,7-bis(ethylene boronate)
0.305g(0.576mmols), 2,5-bis{2'-{4''-(N,N-diphenylamino)
phenyl}ethenyl}-1,4-dibromobenzene 0.424g(0. 548mmols) and
aliquat336 (230mg, 0.57mmols) were dissolved in toluene 
(10ml), and 10ml of aqueous solution of potassium
carbonate (240mg, 1.7mmols) was added to this. Further,
tetrakis(triphenylphosphine)palladium (1.3mg, 0.0011mmols)
was added and refluxed for 10 hours with heating. The
organic layer was added to methanol dropwise, and deposited
precipitates were filtrated. The obtained precipitates were
dissolved in toluene, and added to methanol dropwise. The
deposited precipitates were filtrated to obtain a polymer
0.14g. This polymer is referred to as polymeric fluorescent
substance 7. The polystyrene reduced number average
molecular weight of polymeric fluorescent substance 7 is
8.8x10<sup>4</sup>.</p><p num="0148">From charging ratio of monomers, the ratio of the
repeating units of formula (19) and formula (20) in
polymeric fluorescent substance 7 is 50:50, and polymeric
fluorescent substance 7 is an alternating copolymer.
<img id="img-00650001" orientation="unknown" wi="69" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00650001.tif" inline="no" he="26"/><img id="img-00660001" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00660001.tif" inline="no" he="90"/></p><heading>Comparative example 1</heading><p num="0149">9,9-dioctylfluorene-2,7-bis(ethylene boronate)
0.305g(0.574mmols), 9,9-dioctyl-2,7-dibromofluorene
0.300g(0.547mmols) and aliquat336 (230mg, 0.57mmols) were
dissolved in toluene (10ml), and 10ml of aqueous solution
of potassium carbonate (240mg, 1.7mmols) was added to this.
Further, tetrakis(triphenylphosphine)palladium (1.3mg,
0.0011mmols) was added and refluxed for 10 hours with
heating. The organic layer was added to methanol dropwise,
and deposited precipitates were filtrated. The obtained
precipitates were dissolved in toluene, and added to
methanol dropwise. The deposited precipitates were
filtrated to obtain a polymer 0.38g. This polymer is
referred to as polymeric fluorescent substance 8. The 
polystyrene reduced number average molecular weight of
polymeric fluorescent substance 8 was 6.9x10<sup>4</sup>. Polymeric
fluorescent substance 8 is a polymer consisting of the
repeating unit of formula (21).
<img id="img-00670001" orientation="unknown" wi="74" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00670001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/></p><heading>Comparative example 2</heading><p num="0150">9,9-dioctyl-2,7-dibromofluorene 0.548g, 2-{(N-phenyl)-N-(3-dimetylphenyl)}amino-1,4-dichlorobenzene
0.328g, 2,2'-dipyridine 0.624g, 1,5-cyclooctadiene 0.866g
were charged into a reaction vessel, then, the atmosphere
in the reaction system was purged with argon gas. To this,
20ml of N,N'-dimethylformamide (DMF) degassed beforehand by
argon gas bubbling was added.</p><p num="0151">Then, bis(1,5-cyclooctadiene)nickel (0) 1.108 was
added to the mixed solution, and it was reacted at 70C for
20 hours. The reaction was performed in argon gas
atmosphere. After the reaction, the solution was cooled and
poured into mixed solvent of methanol 25ml/ion-exchanged
water 50ml containing 10ml of 25%aqueous ammonia. Next,
resulting precipitates were filtrated and collected.</p><p num="0152">The precipitates were dried, then dissolved in 
chloroform. The solution was filtrated to remove insoluble
materials, then the solvent was removed under reduced
pressure to collect resulting precipitates. The
precipitates were washed with acetone and dried under
reduced pressure to obtain a polymer 0.10g. This polymer is
referred to as polymeric fluorescent substance 9. The
polystyrene reduced number average molecular weight of
polymeric fluorescent substance 9 was 6.8x10<sup>3</sup>.</p><p num="0153">From charging ratio of monomers, the ratio of the
repeating units of formula (22) and formula (23) in
polymeric fluorescent substance 9 is 50:50, and polymeric
fluorescent substance 9 is a random copolymer.
<img id="img-00680001" orientation="unknown" wi="75" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00680001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/><img id="img-00680002" orientation="unknown" wi="75" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00680002.tif" inline="no" he="36"/></p><heading>Comparative example 3</heading><p num="0154">9,9-dioctylfluorene-2,7-bis(ethylene boronate)
0.305g(0.575mmols), N,N-di(4-bromophenyl)-N-phenylamine
0.221g(0. 548mmols) and aliquat336 (220mg, 0.55mmols) were
dissolved in toluene (10ml), and 10ml of aqueous solution 
of potassium carbonate (238mg, 1.7mmols) was added to
this. Further, tetrakis(triphenylphosphine)palladium
(1.3mg, 0.0011mmols) was added and refluxed for 10 hours
with heating. The organic layer was added to methanol
dropwise, and deposited precipitates were filtrated. The
obtained precipitates were dissolved in toluene, and added
to methanol dropwise. The deposited precipitates were
filtrated to obtain a polymer 0.21g. This polymer is
referred to as polymeric fluorescent substance 10. The
polystyrene reduced number average molecular weight of
polymeric fluorescent substance 10 is 3.7x10<sup>4</sup>.</p><p num="0155">From charging ratio of monomers, the ratio of the
repeating units of formula (24) and formula (25) in
polymeric fluorescent substance 10 is 50:50, and polymeric
fluorescent substance 10 is an alternating copolymer.
<img id="img-00690001" orientation="unknown" wi="73" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00690001.tif" inline="no" he="23"/><img id="img-00690002" orientation="unknown" wi="73" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00690002.tif" inline="no" he="29"/></p><heading>Example 10</heading><p num="0156">Polymeric fluorescent substances 1-10 were soluble in
a solvent, such as toluene and chloroform.</p><heading>&lt;Evaluation of fluorescent property&gt;</heading><p num="0157">A 0.4 wt% solution of polymeric fluorescent substance
1 in chloroform was spin-coated on a quarts plate to form a
thin film of the polymeric fluorescent substance 1. The
ultraviolet visible absorption spectrum and the fluorescent
spectrum of this thin film were measured by using an
ultraviolet visible absorption spectrophotometer (UV3500
manufactured by Hitachi Ltd.) and a fluorescent
spectrophotometer (850 manufactured by Hitachi Ltd.),
respectively. For calculation of fluorescent intensity,
fluorescent spectrum when excited at 350 nm was used. The
relative value of fluorescent intensity was calculated by
dividing the area of fluorescent spectrum plotted against
wave number on the abscissa by absorption at 350 nm.</p><p num="0158">As the same manner with the above, fluorescent
spectra of polymeric fluorescence substances 2 to 10 in the
thin film state were obtained.</p><p num="0159">The polymeric fluorescent substances 1 to 10 had
fluorescent peak wavelength as shown Table 1. Each of
polymeric fluorescent substances 1 to 8 and 10 had a strong
fluorescence in visible region in the thin film state, but
polymeric fluorescent substance 9 had a very weak
fluorescence. <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Fluorescent characteristics of Polymeric fluorescent substance</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance</entry><entry align="center">Fluorescent peak wavelength (nm)</entry><entry align="center">Fluorescent strength (arbitrary unit)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 1</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 1</entry><entry align="center">484</entry><entry align="center">5.28</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 2</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 2</entry><entry align="center">422</entry><entry align="center">0.54</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 3</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 3</entry><entry align="center">452</entry><entry align="center">0.92</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 4</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 4</entry><entry align="center">454</entry><entry align="center">1.26</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 5</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 5</entry><entry align="center">428</entry><entry align="center">3.91</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 6</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 6</entry><entry align="center">480</entry><entry align="center">2.84</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 7</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 7</entry><entry align="center">486</entry><entry align="center">0.56</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 8</entry><entry align="center">428</entry><entry align="center">6.30</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 9</entry><entry align="center">422</entry><entry align="center">0.08</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 3</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 10</entry><entry align="center">436</entry><entry align="center">2.42</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 11</heading><heading>&lt;Production and evaluation of the device&gt;</heading><p num="0160">On a glass substrate on which an ITO film had been 
made at a thickness of 150 nm according to a sputtering
method, a film having a thickness of 50 nm was formed using
a solution (Baytron, manufactured by Bayer) of
poly(ethylenedioxythiophene)/polystyrenesulfonic acid by
spin coating, and the film was dried at 120C for 10
minutes on a hot plate. Next, polymeric fluorescent
substance 1 were spin-coated using 1.5wt% toluene
solution, to form a film having a thickness of about 70 nm.
Further, this film was dried at 80C for 1 hour under
reduced pressure, then, lithium fluoride was vapor-deposited
at 0.4 nm as a cathode buffer layer, calcium was
vapor-deposited at 25 nm and aluminum was vapor-deposited
at 40 nm as a cathode, to produce a polymer LED. In any
vapor deposition, the degree of vacuum was 1 to 810<sup>-6</sup>
Torr. Voltage was applied on the resulted device, to give
EL light emission from Polymeric fluorescent substance 1.
The intensity of EL light emission was approximately in
proportion to the current density.</p><p num="0161">In the same manner, devices using polymeric
fluorescent substances 6 and 8 were manufactured. By
applying voltage on the resulted devices, EL light
emissions from the polymeric fluorescent substances 6 and 8
were obtained, respectively. Intensity of EL light
emissions was almost proportional to the current density.</p><p num="0162">The characteristics of the resulted device are shown 
in Table 2. Compared with polymeric fluorescent substance 8
of Comparative Example 1, both of polymeric fluorescent
substance 1 of Example 1 and polymeric fluorescent
substance 6 of Example 6 had higher light-emitting
efficiency and maximum luminance, and also had a starting
voltage of light emission of equivalent or lower value.</p><p num="0163">Although polymeric fluorescent substance 8 of
Comparative Example 1 and polymeric fluorescent substance
10 of Comparative Example 3 had strong fluorescence (Table
1), when used for a device, the light emitting efficiency
was low and the luminance was also low.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Characteristics of Device using polymeric fluorescent substance</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Light emitting efficiency (cd/A)</entry><entry align="center">Starting voltage of light emission (V)</entry><entry align="center">Maximum luminance (cd/m<sup>2</sup>)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">polymeric fluorescent substance 1</entry><entry align="center">0.89</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry><entry align="right">3517</entry></row><row><entry align="center">polymeric fluorescent substance 7</entry><entry align="center">0.48</entry><entry align="center">4.6</entry><entry align="right">4426</entry></row><row><entry align="center">polymeric fluorescent substance 8</entry><entry align="center">0.09</entry><entry align="center">4.6</entry><entry align="right">749</entry></row><row><entry align="center">polymeric fluorescent substance 10</entry><entry align="center">0.08</entry><entry align="center">6.0</entry><entry align="right">1041</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 12</heading><p num="0164">2,5-(2,7-dimetyl-octyloxy)-1,4-dibromobenzene 0.41g,
2-{4'-(N,N-diphenylamino)}phenyl-1,4-dichlorobenzene 0.29g,
2,2'-dipyridine 0.68g were charged into a reaction vessel,
then, the atmosphere in the reaction system was purged with
argon gas. To this, 50ml of tetrahydrofuran(dehydrated)
degassed beforehand by argon gas bubbling was added.</p><p num="0165">Then, bis(1,5-cyclooctadiene)nickel (0) 1.2g was
added to the mixed solution, and it was reacted at 60C for
7 hours. The reaction was performed in argon gas
atmosphere. After the reaction, the solution was cooled and
poured into mixed solvent of methanol 100ml/ion-exchanged
water 100ml. Next, resulting precipitates were filtrated
and collected.</p><p num="0166">The precipitates were dried, then dissolved in
toluene. The solution was filtrated to remove insoluble
materials, purified by silica gel charged column, then the
solvent was removed under reduced pressure to collect
resulting precipitates. The precipitates were washed with
ethanol and dried under reduced pressure to obtain a
polymer 0.05g. This polymer is referred to as polymeric
fluorescent substance 11. The polystyrene reduced number
average molecular weight of polymeric fluorescent substance
11 was 2.1x10<sup>4</sup>.</p><p num="0167">From charging ratio of monomers, the ratio of the 
repeating units of formula (26) and formula (27) in
polymeric fluorescent substance 11 is 50:50, and polymeric
fluorescent substance 11 is a random copolymer.
<img id="img-00750001" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00750001.tif" inline="no" he="41"/><img id="img-00750002" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00750002.tif" inline="no" he="50"/></p><heading>Comparative example 4</heading><p num="0168">2,5-(2,7-dimetyl-octyloxy)-1,4-dibromobenzene 0.41g,
2-{N-(3-methylphenyl)-N-phenylamino}-1,4-dichlorobenzene
0.24g, 2,2'-dipyridine 0.68g were charged into a reaction
vessel, then, the atmosphere in the reaction system was
purged with argon gas. To this, 50ml of
tetrahydrofuran(dehydrated) degassed beforehand by argon
gas bubbling was added.</p><p num="0169">Then, bis(1,5-cyclooctadiene)nickel (0) 1.2g was
added to the mixed solution, and it was reacted at 60C for
7 hours. The reaction was performed in argon gas 
atmosphere. After the reaction, the solution was cooled and
poured into mixed solvent of methanol 100ml/ion-exchanged
water 100ml. Next, resulting precipitates were filtrated
and collected.</p><p num="0170">The precipitates were dried, then dissolved in
toluene. The solution was filtrated to remove insoluble
materials, purified by silica gel charged column, then the
solvent was removed under reduced pressure to collect
resulting precipitates. The precipitates were washed with
ethanol and dried under reduced pressure to obtain a
polymer 0.05g. This polymer is referred to as polymeric
fluorescent substance 12. The polystyrene reduced number
average molecular weight of polymeric fluorescent substance
12 was 6.6x10<sup>3</sup>.</p><p num="0171">From charging ratio of monomers, the ratio of the
repeating units of formula (28) and formula (29) in
polymeric fluorescent substance 12 is 50:50, and polymeric
fluorescent substance 12 is a random copolymer.
<img id="img-00760001" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00760001.tif" inline="no" he="40"/><img id="img-00770001" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00770001.tif" inline="no" he="38"/></p><heading>Example 13</heading><p num="0172">As the same manner with example 10, fluorescent
spectra of polymeric fluorescence substances 11 and 12 in
the thin film state were obtained.</p><p num="0173">The polymeric fluorescent substances 11 had a strong
fluorescence in visible region in the thin film state, but
polymeric fluorescent substance 12 had a weaker
fluorescence than polymeric fluorescent substance 11.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Fluorescent characteristics of Polymeric fluorescent substance 2</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance</entry><entry align="center">Fluorescent peak wavelength (nm)</entry><entry align="center">Fluorescent strength (arbitrary unit)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 12</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 11</entry><entry align="center">424</entry><entry align="center">1.22</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative example 4</entry><entry align="center">Polymeric fluorescent substance 12</entry><entry align="center">428</entry><entry align="center">0.46</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0174">The polymeric fluorescent substance of the present
invention comprising a copolymer which has a substituent 
containing a specific aromatic amine structure in the side
chain, shows high luminance and high light emitting
efficiency when used for a light emitting layer of a
polymer LED. Therefore, the polymer LED can be preferably
used for apparatus, such as a light source having a flat or
curved surface for lightning or as a back light of a liquid
crystal display, a segment display, and a dot matrix flat-panel
display.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A polymeric fluorescent substance exhibiting fluorescence in the solid state
and having a polystyrene reduced number average molecular weight of 103 to 108,
which comprises one or more repeating units of formula (1):
-Ar1-
wherein Ar1 represents an arylene group or a divalent heterocyclic compound group
and has 1 to 4 substituents of formula (2):

wherein X1 represents a divalent hydrocarbon group; Ar2 represents an arylene group
or a divalent heterocyclic compound group; Ar3 represents an aryl group or a
monovalent heterocyclic compound group; Ar2 and Ar3 may be mutually connected
to form a ring; Ar4 represents an aryl group or a monovalent heterocyclic compound
group; Ar3 and Ar4 may be mutually connected to form a ring; k is 0 or 1; and 1
represents an integer of 1 to 3,
and one or more repeating units of formula (3):
-Ar5-
wherein Ar5 represents an arylene group or divalent heterocyclic compound group of
formula (4):

wherein X2 represents a group selected from O, S, SO, SO2, N-R3, CR4R5 and SiR6R7;
R3 to R7 each independently represent a group selected from a hydrogen atom, alkyl
group, aryl group and monovalent heterocyclic compound group; R1 and R2 each
independently represent a group selected from alkyl group, alkoxy group, alkylthio
group, alkylsilyl group, alkylamino group, aryl group, aryloxy group, arylsilyl group,
arylamino group, arylalkyl group, arylalkoxy group, arylalkylsilyl group,
arylalkylamino group, arylalkenyl group, arylalkynyl group, monovalent heterocyclic
compound group and cyano group; m and n are each independently integers of 0 to 3;
when m is two or more, a plurality of R1 may be the same or different; when n is two
or more, a plurality of R2 may be the same or different; R1 to R7 may be connected to
form a ring; and when any of R1 to R7 is a group containing an alkyl chain, the alkyl
chain may be interrupted by a group containing a hetero atom,
or formula (5):

wherein R8 represents a group selected from alkyl group, alkoxy group, alkylthio
group, alkylsilyl group, alkylamino group, aryl group, aryloxy group, arylsilyl group,
arylamino group, arylalkyl group, arylalkoxy group, arylalkylsilyl group,
arylalkylamino group, arylalkenyl group, arylalkynyl group, monovalent heterocyclic
compound group and cyano group; j is an integer of 0 to 3; when j is two or more, a
plurality of R8 may be the same or different; and when R8 is a group containing an
alkyl chain, the alkyl chain may be interrupted by a group containing a hetero atom.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A substance according to claim 1 wherein the repeating unit of formula (3) is
a repeating unit of formula (6):

wherein R11 and R12 each independently represent a group selected from a hydrogen
atom, alkyl group, aryl group and monovalent heterocyclic compound group; R9 and
R10 each independently represent a group selected from alkyl group, alkoxy group,
alkylthio group, alkylsilyl group, alkylamino group, aryl group, aryloxy group,
arylsilyl group, arylamino group, arylalkyl group, arylalkoxy group, arylalkylsilyl
group, arylalkylamino group, arylalkenyl group, arylalkynyl group, monovalent
heterocyclic compound group and cyano group; h and i are each independently
integers of 0 to 3; when h is two or more, a plurality of R9 may be the same or
different; when i is two or more, a plurality of R10 may be the same or different; R9 to
R12 may be connected to form a ring; and when any of R9 to R12 is a group containing
an alkyl chain, the alkyl chain may be interrupted by a group containing a hetero
atom.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A substance according to claim 1 or 2, wherein the total amount of the
repeating units of formulas (1) and (3) is 50% by mole or more based on all the
repeating units, and the total amount of the repeating units of formula (1) is 0.1% by
mole or more and 50% by mole or less based on the total amount of the repeating
units of formulas (1) and (3).</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A polymer light-emitting device comprising a pair of electrodes composed of
an anode and a cathode at least one of which is transparent or semitransparent and
comprising at least a light-emitting layer between the electrodes, wherein the light-emitting
layer comprises a polymeric fluorescent substance according to any one of
claims 1 to 3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A device according to claim 4, wherein a layer comprising a conductive
polymer is disposed at least between one electrode and the light-emitting layer such
that the layer comprising a conductive polymer is adjacent to said electrode.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A device according to claim 4 or 5, wherein an insulation layer having a
thickness of 2nm or less is disposed at least between one electrode and the light-emitting
layer such that the insulation layer is adjacent to said electrode.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A device according to any one of claims 4 to 6, wherein a layer comprising an
electron-transporting compound is disposed between the cathode and the light-emitting
layer such that the layer comprising an electron-transporting compound is
adjacent to said light-emitting layer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A device according to any one of claims 4 to 7, wherein a layer comprising a
hole-transporting compound is disposed between the anode and the light-emitting
layer such that the layer comprising a hole-transporting compound is adjacent to said
light-emitting layer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A flat light source comprising a polymer light-emitting device according to
any one of claims 4 to 8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A segment display comprising a polymer light-emitting device according to
any one of claims 4 to 8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A dot matrix display comprising a polymer light-emitting device according to
any one of claims 4 to 8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A liquid crystal display comprising a polymer light-emitting device according
to any one of claims 4 to 8 as a back light.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>