<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1340883-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1340883" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="22201998" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030903"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1340883-A2" status="new" fvid="23847256"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1340883</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20030903</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03004162-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03004162</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030226</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-8696302-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>8696302</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020228</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/60        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/62        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/60D4B6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/60D4B8</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/62</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/68</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/68B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Aminocarbonsäure Brecherzusammensetzung für Aufbrechflüssigkeiten</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Aminocarboxylic acid breaker compositions for fracturing fluids</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Compositions d'agent de rupture à base d'acide aminocarboxylique, pour fluides de fracturation</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-4968442-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4968442</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5223159-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5223159</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5624886-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5624886</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BAKER HUGHES INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BAKER HUGHES INCORPORATED</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BAKER-HUGHES INCORPORATED</last-name><address><street>3900 Essex Lane Suite 1200 P.O. Box 4740</street><city>Houston Texas 77210-4740</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CREWS JAMES B</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CREWS, JAMES B.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CREWS, JAMES B.</last-name><address><street>5206 Sunshine Point</street><city>Willis, Texas 77318</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>von Füner, Nicolai</last-name><address><street>v. Füner Ebbinghaus Finck Hano Patentanwälte Mariahilfplatz 2&amp;amp;3</street><city>81541 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DK</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country> </ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>It has been discovered that aminocarboxylic acids are effective breakers
for polymer-gelled aqueous fracturing fluids, particularly in the temperature
range between about 120°F (49°C) and about 280° F (138°C). The aminocarboxylic
acids are believed to act directly on the polymer and not to any great
extent or not to as an effective extent on a crosslinking agent, if present. The
polymer may be a polysaccharide, and the aminocarboxylic acid may be
selected from the group including, but not necessarily limited to, tetrasodium
ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA), tetrasodium propylenediaminetetraacetic
acid (Na<sub>4</sub>PDTA), trisodium hydroxyethylenediaminetetraacetic acid
(Na4HEDTA), trisodium nitrilotriacetic acid (Na<sub>3</sub>NTA), salts of these acids, and
mixtures thereof.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="106"/></p> </abstract> <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">Field of the Invention</u> </heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to gelled treatment fluids used during
hydrocarbon recovery operations, and more particularly relates, in one embodiment,
to methods of "breaking" or reducing the viscosity of treatment fluids containing
polymer gelling agents used during hydrocarbon recovery operations.</p><heading><u style="single">Background of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0002">Hydraulic fracturing is a method of using pump rate and hydraulic pressure
to fracture or crack a subterranean formation. Once the crack or cracks
are made, high permeability proppant, relative to the formation permeability, is
pumped into the fracture to prop open the crack. When the applied pump rates
and pressures are reduced or removed from the formations the crack or fracture
cannot close or heal completely because the high permeability proppant keeps
the crack open. The propped crack or fracture provides a high permeability
path connecting the producing wellbore to a larger formation area to enhance
the production of hydrocarbons.</p><p num="0003">The development of suitable fracturing fluids is a complex art because
the fluids must simultaneously meet a number of conditions. For example, they
must be stable at high temperatures and/or high pump rates and shear rates
that can cause the fluids to degrade and prematurely settle out the proppant
before the fracturing operation is complete. Various fluids have been
developed, but most commercially used fracturing fluids are aqueous based
liquids that have either been gelled or foamed. When the fluids are gelled,
typically a polymeric gelling agent, such as a solvatable polysaccharide is used.
The thickened or gelled fluid helps keep the proppants within the fluid. Gelling
can be accomplished or improved by the use of crosslinking agents or
crosslinkers that promote crosslinking of the polymers together, thereby
increasing the viscosity of the fluid. However, crosslinking agents are not
always necessary to obtain a suitable gel. </p><p num="0004">The recovery of fracturing fluids may be accomplished by reducing the
viscosity of the fluid to a low value so that it may flow naturally from the formation
under the influence of formation fluids. Polymer gels generally require viscosity
breakers to be injected to reduce the viscosity or "break" the gel. Enzymes,
oxidizers, and inorganic acids are known polymer viscosity breakers.
Enzymes are effective within a pH range, typically a 2.0 to 10.0 range, with
increasing activity as the pH is lowered towards neutral from a pH of 10.0.</p><p num="0005">Many viscosity-breaking technologies are most effective only over limited
temperature ranges. For instance, persulfate oxidizers are generally too reactive
to be properly used above about 140°F (60°C) and bromate oxidizers do
not work until about 220°F (104°C) and above. Enzyme technology generally
works between about 150 to 220°F (66 to 104°C).</p><p num="0006">It would be desirable if a viscosity breaking system could be devised to
break fracturing fluids gelled with polymers, particularly over a temperature
range of about 120°F (49°C) and about 280° F (138°C), as an alternative to
enzyme technology.</p><heading><u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0007">Accordingly, it is an object of the present invention to provide a method
for breaking the viscosity of aqueous treatment fluids gelled with polymers used
in hydrocarbon recovery operations.</p><p num="0008">It is another object of the present invention to provide a composition and
method for breaking gelled aqueous fluids over a temperature range of about
120°F (49°C) and about 280° F (138°C).</p><p num="0009">Still another object of the invention is to provide a method and composition
for breaking the viscosity of aqueous fluids gelled polymers using relatively
inexpensive aminocarboxylic acids.</p><p num="0010">In carrying out these and other objects of the invention, there is provided,
in one form, a method for breaking the viscosity of polymer gelled aqueous
fluids comprising adding an effective amount of at least one aminocarboxylic
acid to act directly break down the gel. </p><heading><u style="single">Brief Description of the Drawings</u></heading><p num="0011"><sl><li>FIG. 1 is a graph of the effects of different amounts of Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA on a
BoraFRAQ® 30 borate crosslinked polymer gel at 150°F (66°C);</li><li>FIG. 2 is a graph of the effect of Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA on a BoraFRAQ® 30 borate
crosslinked polymer gel at 175°F (79°C);</li><li>FIG. 3 is a graph of the effect of Na<sub>4</sub>PDTA on a BoraFRAQ® 30 borate
crosslinked polymer gel at 175°F (79°C);</li><li>FIG. 4 is a graph of the effect of Na<sub>3</sub>HEDTA on a BoraFRAQ® 30 borate
crosslinked polymer gel at 220°F (104°C);</li><li>FIG. 5 is a graph of the effects of different amounts of Na<sub>3</sub>NTA on a
BoraFRAQ® 30 borate crosslinked polymer gel at 250°F (121°C);</li><li>FIG. 6 is a graph of the effects of different amounts of Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA (E39
Breaker) on 80 pptg linear guar polymer gel (WG-1L) at 150°F (66°C); and</li><li>FIG. 7 is a graph of the effects of different amounts of Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA (E39
Breaker) on 80 pptg linear guar polymer gel (WG-1 L) at 180°F (82°C).</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Detailed Description of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0012">Aminocarboxylic acids have been manufactured for several decades.
Their primary use has been the chelation of cations. It has now been
discovered that PDTA, EDTA, HEDTA and other aminocarboxylic acids and
their salts can be used to directly break the polymer in gelled fracturing fluids,
particularly at temperatures between about 120°F (49°C) and about 280°F
(138°C). While these agents can be used to break the polymer gel in
crosslinked polysaccharide fracturing fluids, they can also be used to break
other polysaccharide polymer fluids that do not employ crosslinkers. As will be
shown, it is believed that these aminocarboxylic acids act directly on the
polymer itself, and not the crosslinking ion, although it is acceptable if the
aminocarboxylic acids also act on the crosslinker. The gel breaking method of
this invention is expected to be an attractive alternative to using enzyme
technology or catalyzed oxidizer technology to break gels within this
temperature range. </p><p num="0013">In order to practice the method of the invention, an aqueous fracturing
fluid is first prepared by blending a hydratable polymer into an aqueous fluid.
The aqueous fluid could be, for example, water, brine, aqueous based foams or
water-alcohol mixtures. Any suitable mixing apparatus may be used for this
procedure. In the case of batch mixing, the hydratable polymer and the
aqueous fluid are blended for a period of time sufficient to form a hydrated
solution. The hydratable polymer that is useful in the present invention can be,
but are not necessarily limited to, any of the hydratable polysaccharides having
galactose or mannose monosaccharide components and are familiar to those
in the well service industry. These polysaccharides are capable of gelling in the
presence of a crosslinking agent to form a gelled base fluid, although as noted
it is not necessary that the polymer be crosslinked. For instance, suitable
hydratable polysaccharides are the galactomannan gums, guars and derivatized
guars, as non-limiting examples. Specific examples are guar gum and guar
gum derivatives. The preferred gelling agents are guar gum, hydroxypropyl
guar and carboxymethyl hydroxypropyl guar. The most preferred hydratable
polymers for the present invention are guar gum and carboxymethyl
hydroxypropyl guar and hydroxypropyl guar, in one non-limiting case.</p><p num="0014">The amount of polysaccharide included in the fracturing fluid is not particularly
critical so long as the viscosity of the fluid is sufficiently high to keep
the proppant particles suspended therein during the fluid injecting step. Thus,
depending on the application, the hydratable polymer is added to the aqueous
fluid in concentrations ranging from about 15 to 60 pounds per thousand
gallons (pptg) by volume of the total aqueous fluid (1.8 to 7.2 kg/m<sup>3</sup>). The most
preferred range for the present invention is about 20 to about 40 pptg (2.4 to
4.8 kg/m<sup>3</sup>)<sub>.</sub></p><p num="0015">In addition to the hydratable polymer, the fracturing fluids of the invention
include a borate crosslinking agent. The crosslinking agent can be any of
the conventionally used borate crosslinking agents that are known to those
skilled in the art. This includes any of the boron salts or boric acid as borate
crosslinking agents. Guar and derivatized guar gels, which are crosslinked by
the addition of borate ion donating materials are preferred within this 
embodiment over other crosslinking agents because they clean up faster and
yield higher sand pack permeability than guar gels crosslinked with other
crosslinking agents. However, other crosslinking agents that can be used with
this embodiment besides borate, may include, but are not limited to, titanate,
zirconate, and other metallic and semi-metallic high pH crosslinkers.</p><p num="0016">In the case of borate crosslinkers, the crosslinking agent is any material
that supplies borate ions in solution. The amount of borate ions in solution is
dependent on pH. Thus, the crosslinking agent can be any convenient source
of borate ions, for instance the alkali metal and the alkaline earth metal borates
and boric acid. A preferred crosslinking additive is preferably a common type of
borax present in the range from about 0.25 to in excess of 10.0 pptg of the total
aqueous fluid (0.03 to in excess of 1.2 lb/m<sup>3</sup>). Preferably, the concentration of
crosslinking agent is in the range from about 1.0 to about 3.0 pptg (0.12 to 0.34
kg/m<sup>3</sup>) by volume of the total aqueous fluid. Similar considerations apply to the
use of other crosslinkers.</p><p num="0017">Propping agents are typically added to the base fluid just prior to the
addition of the crosslinking agent. Propping agents include, but are not limited
to, for instance, quartz sand grains, glass and ceramic beads, bauxite grains,
walnut shell fragments, aluminum pellets, nylon pellets, and the like. The
propping agents are normally used in concentrations between about 1 to 14
pounds per gallon (120-1700 kg/m<sup>3</sup>) of fracturing fluid composition, but higher
or lower concentrations can be used as the fracture design requires. The base
fluid can also contain other conventional additives common to the well service
industry such as surfactants, biocides, non-emulsifiers and the like.</p><p num="0018">In general, and in one non-limiting embodiment of the invention, the
method is conducted at a temperature between about 120°F (49°C) and about
280° F (138°C), preferably between about 150°F (66°C) and about 260° F
(127°C).</p><p num="0019">In one non-limiting embodiment of the invention, the suitable aminocarboxylic
acids for use in the invention that are suitable include, but are not
limited to, tetrasodium ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA), tetrasodium
propylenediaminetetraacetic acid (Na<sub>4</sub>PDTA), trisodium 
hydroxyethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (Na<sub>4</sub>HEDTA), trisodium nitrilotriacetic
acid (Na<sub>3</sub>NTA), trisodium ethylenediaminetriacetic acid (Na<sub>3</sub>HEDTA), disodium
ethylenediaminediacetic acid (Na<sub>2</sub>H<sub>2</sub>EDDA), disodium calcium dihydrate
ethylenediaminediacetic acid (Na<sub>2</sub>Ca· 2H<sub>2</sub>O EDTA), tetraammonium
ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>4</sub>EDTA and potassium and ammonium
and other salts of these acids, the acids alone, and mixtures thereof. When
salts are employed, alkali metal and ammonium salts are preferred and
sodium, potassium and ammonium salts are particularly preferred, in a non-limiting
embodiment. Of course, any aminocarboxylic acid that performs the
functions required of these breakers may be used within the scope of this
invention. All of these aminocarboxylic acids were discovered to break polymer
gels by themselves.</p><p num="0020">More particularly, and in non-limiting embodiments of the invention,
Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA breaks borate crosslinked guar at from about 120°F (49°C) to about
220°F (104°C); where the optimum temperature application is from about
130°F (54°C) to about 200°F (93°C). Na<sub>4</sub>PDTA was found to break borate
crosslinked guar at from about 140°F (60°C) to about 230°F (110°C); where the
optimum temperature application is from about 150°F (66°C) to about 210°F
(99°C). In turn, Na<sub>4</sub>HEDTA was found to break borate crosslinked guar at from
about 180°F (82°C) to about 280°F (138°C); where the optimum temperature
application is from about 190°F (88°C) to about 240°F (116°C).</p><p num="0021">It was discovered that pentasodium diethylenetriaminepentaacetic acid
(Na<sub>5</sub>DTPA) and disodium hydroxyethyliminodiacetic acid (Na<sub>2</sub>HEIDA) did not
effectively break polymer fluids by themselves.</p><p num="0022">Any or all of the above aminocarboxylic acids may be provided in an extended
release form such as encapsulation by polymer or otherwise, pelletization
with binder compounds, absorbed on a porous substrate, and a combination
thereof. Specifically, the materials may be encapsulated to permit slow or
timed release of the aminocarboxylic acid materials. In non-limiting examples,
the coating material may slowly dissolve or be removed by any conventional
mechanism, or the coating could have very small holes or perforations therein
for the material within to diffuse through slowly. For instance, polymer encapsulation 
coatings such as used in fertilizer technology available from Scotts
Company, specifically POLY-S® product coating technology, or polymer encapsulation
coating technology from Fritz Industries could possibly be adapted to
the methods of this invention.</p><p num="0023">It is difficult, if not impossible, to specify with accuracy the amount of the
aminocarboxylic acid that should be added to a particular polymer gelled aqueous
fluid to fully break the gel, in general. For instance, a number of factors
affect this proportion, including but not necessarily limited to, the particular
polymer used to gel the fluid; the particular aminocarboxylic acid used to break
the gel; the temperature of the fluid; the starting pH of the fluid; whether an
enzyme breaker is also used; the particular nature of the enzyme breaker, if
present; the concentration of the enzyme; the nature and the concentration of
any pH buffers; and the complex interaction of these various factors. Nevertheless,
in order to give an approximate feel for the proportions of the aminocarboxylic
acid to be used in the method of the invention, the-amount of material
added may range from about 0.01 to about 20.0 gptg (the same values apply
for metric units, e.g. liters per thousand liters or m<sup>3</sup>/thousand m<sup>3</sup>), based on the
total weight of the fluid; preferably from about 0.1 to about 5.0 gptg, most
preferably from about 0.25 to about 2.0 gptg. Both solid and liquid forms of the
aminocarboxylic acids may be employed in the compositions and methods of
this invention. The aminocarboxylic acids may be applied in a water-based
liquid form with up to 50 wt.% active aminocarboxylic acid content. Expressed
in dry units, the amount of aminocarboxylic acid added to the polymer gelled
aqueous fluids may range from about 0.1 to 30.0 pptg (pounds per thousand
gallons) (0.01 - 3.4 kg/m<sup>3</sup>), preferably from about 0.5 to 10.0 pptg (0.06 - 1.2
kg/m<sup>3</sup>).</p><p num="0024">As noted, and as will be shown with reference to the various Examples,
it is believed that the aminocarboxylic acid breakers of this invention act directly
on the polymer itself, and not on any crosslinker that may be present, in accordance
with one non-limiting understanding of the invention. In another embodiment
of the invention, the aminocarboxylic acid breakers may act both directly
to break down the gel by acting upon the polymer itself, and by acting upon the 
crosslinking ion, if present, although it should be understood that the primary
breaking mechanism is the direct action of the aminocarboxylic acid on the
polymer. This issue will be discussed further with reference to FIGS. 6 and 7.
That is, over half of the effect of the gel breaking can be attributed to the direct
action of the aminocarboxylic acid, rather than to any action upon the
crosslinker, if any. In one particular non-limiting embodiment of the invention,
the polymer is not crosslinked.</p><p num="0025">In one non-limiting embodiment of the invention, the polymer gel breaker
system of this invention has an absence of chlorite compounds. Examples of
chlorite compounds explicitly absent include, but are not necessarily limited to,
alkali metal chlorite compounds and hypochlorite.</p><p num="0026">It is typically necessary to add pH buffers to the gelled aqueous fluid to
increase the pH to generate active borate ion for crosslinking the polymers, if
the polymer is crosslinked. Suitable buffers include, but are not necessarily
limited to sodium hydroxide, potassium hydroxide, sodium carbonate, sodium
sesquicarbonate, potassium carbonate, sodium bicarbonate, sodium
sesquicarbonate, and mixtures thereof. The amount of the pH buffer may range
from about 0.5 to about 30.0 pptg (about 0.06 to about 3.6 kg/m<sup>3</sup>), based on
the total volume of the entire fluid, preferably from about 1 to about 20 pptg
(about 0.12 to about 2.4 kg/m<sup>3</sup>)<sub>.</sub></p><p num="0027">In a typical fracturing operation, the fracturing fluid of the invention is
pumped at a rate sufficient to initiate and propagate a fracture in the formation
and to place propping agents into the fracture. A typical fracturing treatment
would be conducted by hydrating a 20 lb to 30 lb/1000 gal water (weight/volume)
(about 2.4 to about 3.6 kg/m<sup>3</sup>) glactomannan-based polymer, such as
guar, in a 2% (w/v) (166 lb/1000 gal (19.9 kg/m<sup>3</sup>)) KCI solution at a pH ranging
from about 6.0 to about 8.0. For crosslinking, this pH range may be from about
8.8 to about 10.5. The aminocarboxylic acid (or its salt) is added at this stage. It
should be understood throughout the specification and claims that more than
one aminocarboxylic acid (or its salt) may be employed at a time. During the
actual pumping, as described, the pH of the ambient temperature guar gel is
raised by the addition of a buffer to about 9.5 to about 12.5, followed by the 
addition of the aminocarboxylic acid breaker, crosslinking agent, proppant, and
other additives, if required.</p><p num="0028">The present invention will be explained in further detail in the following
non-limiting Examples that are only designed to additionally illustrate the
invention but not narrow the scope thereof.</p><heading>GENERAL PROCEDURE FOR EXAMPLES 1-7</heading><p num="0029">Using a Waring blender, 4.8 mls of BoraFRAQ® fracturing fluid (borate
crosslinked guar gum system available from Baker Hughes) was hydrated for
15 minutes within 500 mls of distilled water containing 10 grams KCI salt. An
aminocarboxylic acid such as 10.0 pptg of Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA (1.2 kg/m<sup>3</sup>) was added to
the hydrated guar fluid. Control samples of the guar polymer fluid were mixed
without adding any aminocarboxylic acid. Each sample was capped and
shaken vigorously for 60 seconds. The samples were placed in a water bath at
the indicated temperatures and visually observed every 30 minutes for viscosity
reduction difference between the samples. The samples with aminocarboxylic
acid (e.g. Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA) lost viscosity noticeably faster. Most gel breaking occurred
over the first two hours. Modifications to this general procedure are indicated.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0030">Example 1 tested Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA at 10.0 pptg (1.2 kg/m<sup>3</sup>) and 20.0 pptg (2.4
kg/m<sup>3</sup>) levels in BoraFRAQ® 30 borate crosslinked polymer gel at 150°F (66°C).
The results are compared against a fluid without using an aminocarboxylic acid
as plotted in FIG. 1. It may be seen that the viscosity of the gel was broken
quickly with this aminocarboxylic acid (about 0.5 hour), particularly at the 20.0
pptg (2.4 kg/m<sup>3</sup>) dosage.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 2</heading><p num="0031">Example 2 tested Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA at the 5.0 pptg (0.6 kg/m<sup>3</sup>) level in Bora-FRAQ®
30 borate crosslinked polymer gel at 175°F (79°C). The results are
compared against a fluid without using an aminocarboxylic acid as plotted in 
FIG. 2. It may be seen that the viscosity of the gel was broken quickly and
substantially after about 1 hour with this aminocarboxylic acid salt.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 3</heading><p num="0032">Example 3 tested Na<sub>4</sub>PDTA at the 5.0 pptg (0.6 kg/m<sup>3</sup>) level in Bora-FRAQ®
30 borate crosslinked polymer gel at 175°F (79°C). The results are
compared against a fluid without using an aminocarboxylic acid salt as plotted
in FIG. 3. It may be seen that the viscosity of the gel was broken quickly and
substantially after about 1 hour with this aminocarboxylic acid salt.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 4</heading><p num="0033">Example 4 tested Na<sub>4</sub>HEDTA at the 5.0 pptg (0.6 kg/m<sup>3</sup>) level in Bora-FRAQ®
30 borate crosslinked polymer gel at 220°F (104°C). The results are
compared against a fluid without using an aminocarboxylic acid salt as plotted
in FIG. 4. It may be seen that the viscosity of the gel was broken quickly and
substantially in advance of 1 hour with this aminocarboxylic acid salt.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 5</heading><p num="0034">Example 5 tested Na<sub>3</sub>NTA at the 2.0 pptg (0.24 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) and 5.0 pptg (0.6
kg/m<sup>3</sup>) levels in BoraFRAQ® 30 borate crosslinked polymer gel at 250°F
(121°C). The results are compared against a fluid without using an aminocarboxylic
acid salt as plotted in FIG. 5. It may be seen that the viscosity of the gel
was broken quickly over the course of 2 hours with this aminocarboxylic acid
salt at these dosages.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 6</heading><p num="0035">Example 6 tested the effects of E39 Breaker (39% bw aqueous solution
of Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA, available from Akzo Nobel) at the 1.0 gptg and 2.0 gptg levels in
80 pptg (9.6 kg/m<sup>3</sup>) WG-1L® non-crosslinked linear guar at 150°F (66°C). The
results are compared against a fluid without using an aminocarboxylic acid salt
as plotted in FIG. 6. It may be seen that the viscosity of the gel broke quickly
and substantially over the course of the first 2 hours with this aminocarboxylic 
acid at these dosages. Because this polymer gel was not crosslinked, this
Example demonstrates that the aminocarboxylic acid acts directly and predominantly
on the polymer itself, rather than only or substantially on any crosslinker
that may be present.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 7</heading><p num="0036">Example 7 tested the effects of E39 Breaker at the 0.5 gptg, 1.0 gptg
and 2.0 gptg levels in 80 pptg (9.6 kg/m<sup>3</sup>) WG-1L® non-crosslinked linear guar
at 180°F (82°C). The results are compared against a fluid without using an
aminocarboxylic acid as plotted in FIG. 7. It may be seen that the viscosity of
the gel was broken quickly and substantially over the course of the first hour
with this aminocarboxylic acid at these dosages. Because this polymer gel was
not crosslinked, this Example also demonstrates that the aminocarboxylic acid
acts directly and predominantly on the polymer itself, rather than only or
substantially on any crosslinker that may be present.</p><p num="0037">In the foregoing specification, the invention has been described with
reference to specific embodiments thereof, and has been demonstrated as
effective in providing a method and composition for a polymer gelled fracturing
fluid breaker mechanism. However, it will be evident that various modifications
and changes can be made thereto without departing from the scope of the
invention as set forth in the appended claims. Accordingly, the specification is
to be regarded in an illustrative rather than a restrictive sense. For example,
specific combinations or amounts of aminocarboxylic acids, crosslinkers,
buffers, and other components falling within the claimed parameters, but not
specifically identified or tried in a particular composition, are anticipated and
expected to be within the scope of this invention. Further, the method of the
invention is expected to work at other conditions, particularly temperature
conditions, than those exemplified herein.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for breaking the viscosity of polymer gelled aqueous fluids
comprising adding an effective amount of at least one aminocarboxylic acid to
directly break down the gel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 where the aminocarboxylic acid acts directly on
the polymer and not any crosslinking ion, if present.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 where the polymer gel is not crosslinked.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method of any of the above claims where the polymer is a
polysaccharide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method of any of the above claims where the aminocarboxylic acid
is selected from the group consisting of ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid
(EDTA), propylenediaminetetraacetic acid (PDTA),
hydroxyethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (HEDTA), nitrilotriacetic acid (NTA),
ethylenediaminetriacetic acid (HEDTA), ethylenediaminediacetic acid
(H2EDDA), dihydrate ethylenediaminediacetic acid (2H2O EDTA), salts of these
acids, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method of any of the above claims where the aminocarboxylic acid
is selected from the group consisting of the sodium salt, the potassium salt,
and the ammonium salt of the acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method of any of the above claims where the method is conducted
at a temperature between about 120°F (49°C) and about 280° F (138°C).</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method of any of the above claims where in adding the
aminocarboxylic acid, the amount of aminocarboxylic acid added ranges from
about 0.1 to about 30.0 pptg (from about 0.01 to about 3.4 kg/m3) based on the
total volume of fluid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>An aqueous fluid comprising
   water;
   at least one polymer forming an aqueous gel; and
   at least one aminocarboxylic acid in an amount effective to directly break
down the gel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The fluid of claim 9 in the absence of a crosslinker.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The fluid of claim 9 or 10 where the polymer is a polysaccharide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The fluid of any one of claims 9 through 11 where the aminocarboxylic
acid is selected from the group consisting of ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid
(EDTA), propylenediaminetetraacetic acid (PDTA), hydroxyethylenediaminetetraacetic
acid (HEDTA), nitrilotriacetic acid (NTA), ethylenediaminetriacetic
acid (HEDTA), ethylenediaminediacetic acid (H2EDDA), dihydrate ethylenediaminediacetic
acid (2H2O EDTA), salts of these acids, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The fluid of any one of claims 9 through 12 where the aminocarboxylic
acid is selected from the sodium salt, the potassium salt, and the ammonium
salt of the acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The fluid of any one of claims 9 through 13 where in adding the aminocarboxylic
acid, the amount of aminocarboxylic acid added ranges from about
0.1 to about 30.0 pptg (from about 0.01 to about 3.4 kg/m3) based on the total
volume of fluid.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>