<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1013681-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1013681" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22815497" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000628"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1013681-A1" status="new" fvid="22858080"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1013681</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000628</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99310053-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99310053</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991214</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-21853598-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>21853598</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981221</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   2/04        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   2/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 265/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 265/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 283/00        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 283/12        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 290/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 290/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 290/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/14        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09J 151/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09J 151/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F 290/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F 290/06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F 290/06F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09J 151/08S+B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Mit Organopolysiloxanen modifizierte Pfropfcopolymere</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Organopolysiloxane-modified graft copolymers</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Polymères greffés modifiés par un polysiloxane</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-5625005-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5625005</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5731379-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5731379</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998048771-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998048771</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DOW CORNING</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DOW CORNING CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DOW CORNING CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>3901 S. Saginaw Road</street><city>Midland Michigan 48686-0994</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KUO CHUNG MIEN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LILES DONALD TAYLOR</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KUO, CHUNG MIEN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LILES, DONALD TAYLOR</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KUO, CHUNG MIEN</last-name><address><street>2520 Abbott Road</street><city>Midland, Michigan 48642</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>LILES, DONALD TAYLOR</last-name><address><street>1205 Wakefield Drive</street><city>Midland, Michigan 48640</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kyle, Diana</last-name> <address><street>Elkington and Fife Prospect House 8 Pembroke Road</street><city>Sevenoaks, Kent TN13 1XR</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook> </agent> </agents> </parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>This invention relates to organopolysiloxane-modified
graft copolymers obtained by heating a mixture
comprising an ethylenically unsaturated monomer, a
polyethylene-polybutylene macromonomer, an
organopolysiloxane macromonomer, a free radical initiator,
and optionally a solvent. The copolymers of this invention
find utility in adhesives such as pressure sensitive
adhesives, contact adhesives, laminating adhesives, assembly
adhesives and release coatings.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention relates to organopolysiloxane-modified
graft copolymers. This invention also relates to a
method of making organopolysiloxane-modified graft copolymers
by heating a mixture comprising (A) an ethylenically
unsaturated monomer, (B) a polyethylene-polybutylene
macromonomer, (C) an organopolysiloxane macromonomer, (D) a
free radical initiator and (E) optionally a solvent.</p><p num="0002">Copolymers or thermoplastic elastomers prepared by
the anionic polymerization of conjugated dienes and/or
styrenes are a unique class of thermoplastics. They differ
fundamentally in polymeric structure such as linear
copolymers, diblock , triblock, radial and star polymer
structure and each block structure contributes unique
properties to the polymer. These copolymers can be
formulated with various other polymers and with a wide range
of resins, solvents and fillers. These copolymers find
utility in coatings, adhesives and sealants.</p><p num="0003">Copolymers having a functionalized endgroup which
have been prepared utilizing anionic polymerization are
disclosed. For example, U.S Patent 5,331,058 discloses a
process for anionically polymerizing a conjugated 1,3-diene
monomer which consists of contacting the monomer in an inert
hydrocarbon solvent with a monofunctional silyl ether
initiator to yield a polydiene having a molecular weight of
typically 1,000-10,000. It is further disclosed that the
reactive ends of the polymer chains may be terminated with a 
reactive group such as hydroxyl by treating the polymer with
ethylene oxide and that subsequent removal of the polymer's
relatively unreactive silyl end groups by reaction with
tetra-n-butylammonium fluoride produces a difunctional, chain
extendable, hydroxy terminated polydiene.</p><p num="0004">U.S. Patent 5,393,843 discloses hydrogenated
butadiene polymers having terminal functional groups, such as
hydroxyl groups, having a minimum viscosity at any molecular
weight when the 1,2 addition is between 30 and 70%.</p><p num="0005">U.S. Patent 5,478,899 discloses improved capping
of anionic polymers to make functionalized polymers by using
alkoxysilyl compounds having protected functional groups,
such as acetal groups, as the capping agent. It is further
disclosed that the protected functional groups are stable
under a variety of conditions and then readily convert to
more reactive terminal functional groups useful for making
adhesives, sealants and coatings.</p><p num="0006">Hydroxy functional poly(ethylene-butylene) is one
of the materials that can be prepared by the anionic
polymerization of butadiene and subsequent hydrogenation.
The hydrogenation process produces a polymer having a
saturated olefin backbone, a low viscosity, good water
permeability and good weatherability. The functionality in
the poly(ethylene-butylene) can be used in a variety of
thermoset and thermoplastic applications. Also, this type of
low viscosity, low molecular weight functionalized polymer 
which contains a polymerizable endgroup is a good
macromonomer for use in graft polymerizations.</p><p num="0007">Silicone polymers also find utility in similar
applications such as coatings, adhesives and sealants where
the polymers are often employed in the vulcanization process.
Silicone polymers possess favorable properties such as low
surface tension, excellent gas permeability, thermal
stability and resistance to ultraviolet light. Since
silicone polymers are not miscible with other organic based
polymers, distinct phase separation occurs readily for
silicone polymers in blends of the two materials, especially
when block copolymers or silicone graft copolymers are used.
Several copolymers containing an organic polymer segment and
a polydimethylsiloxane segment have been synthesized, both by
block, star block and graft polymerization. In block graft
copolymerization where for example a polystyrene-polydimethylsiloxanes
linear block copolymer is produced,
styrene, a lithium initiator and promoter are anionically
polymerized with hexamethylcyclotrisiloxane or coupling of
diblock copolymer to form a triblock copolymer.</p><p num="0008">U.S. Patent 5,276,095 discloses star block
copolymers comprised of vinyl aromatic hydrocarbon and/or
conjugated diene polymer arms and polydimethylsiloxane arms
radiating outwardly from a polyalkenyl aromatic coupling
agent core which is produced by first anionically
polymerizing a vinyl aromatic hydrocarbon and/or a conjugated
diene to produce living polymer arms, reacting the living 
polymer arms with a polyalkenyl aromatic coupling agent to
couple the arms thereto, polymerizing this coupled product
with hexamethylcyclotrisiloxane in the presence of a polar
promoter and then terminating the polymerization.</p><p num="0009">U.S. Patent 4,728,571 discloses release coating
compositions comprising polysiloxane-grafted copolymer and
blends thereof with other polymeric materials which are
useful on sheet materials and the backside of adhesive tapes.</p><p num="0010">U.S. Patent 4,981,903 discloses a composition
which can serve as a pressure sensitive or non-pressure
sensitive adhesive composition at room temperature comprising
a vinyl polymeric backbone with grafted pendant siloxane
polymeric moieties.</p><p num="0011">European Patent Application 0412704 discloses hair
care compositions comprising 0.1 to 10% of a copolymer having
a molecular weight of 10,000 to 1,000,000 which has a vinyl
polymeric backbone having grafted to it monovalent siloxane
polymeric moieties, the copolymer comprising a silicone
containing polymeric monomer and components selected from at
least one free radically polymerizable vinyl monomer and at
least one reinforcing monomer copolymerizable with the vinyl
monomer and from 0.5 to 99.5% of a carrier suitable for
application to hair.</p><p num="0012">European Patent Application 0412707 discloses hair
care compositions comprising 0.1% to 10% of a silicone
containing copolymer comprising a silicone-containing
macromer having a weight average molecular weight of from 
1,000 to 50,000 based on polydimethylsiloxane and components
selected from a lipophilic, low polarity free radically
polymerizable vinyl monomer such as methacrylic or acrylic
esters, a hydrophilic polar monomer which is copolymerizable
with the vinyl monomer such as acrylic acid,
dimethylaminoethyl methacrylate or vinyl pyrrolidone, and
mixtures thereof, and from 0.5% to 99.5% of a carrier
suitable for application to hair.</p><p num="0013">U.S. Patent 5,166,276 discloses a polymer suitable
for use in hair care products comprising a unit of a
hydrophilic ethylenically unsaturated monomer such as
dimethylaminoethyl methacrylate in a quantity of 15 to 99.9%
by weight, a unit of an ethylenically unsaturated monomer
having a polysiloxane group in a quantity of 0.1 to 85% by
weight and a unit of an optional hydrophobic unsaturated
monomer such as lauryl methacrylate in a quantity of 0 to
84.9% by weight.</p><p num="0014">Japanese Patent Publication 59126478 discloses a
coating composition prepared by dissolving silicone graft
copolymers prepared by the radical polymerization of a
straight chain silicone high molecular weight monomer (I) and
radically polymerizable monomer in a solution of film forming
resin solvent wherein (I) comprises the reaction product of a
living polymer prepared by the anionic polymerization of a
cyclic siloxane.</p><p num="0015">U.S. Patent 5,302,379 discloses a nail lacquer
containing a film forming resin, a plasticizer and a solvent 
wherein the film forming resin is a blend of (i) a graft
copolymer having a main backbone chain of acrylic ester units
and methacrylic ester units, with the main backbone chain
having grafted thereto pendant trialkoxysilyl groups and
pendant ethylene glycol dimethacrylate groups and (ii)
silsesquioxane resin.</p><p num="0016">U.S. Patent 5,281,666 discloses an improvement
upon the process for making block copolymers of vinyl
aromatic hydrocarbons and/or conjugated dienes and
polydimethylsiloxane by first anionically polymerizing the
vinyl aromatic hydrocarbon to make a living polymer block and
then adding hexamethylcyclotrisiloxane and a polar promoter
to polymerize a polydimethylsiloxane block at the end of the
living polymer block. The improvement comprises reacting the
living polymer blocks with a crossover reagent to decrease
the crossover time from the living polymer block
polymerization to the polydimethylsiloxane polymerization.</p><p num="0017">U.S. Patent 5,296,574 discloses a method for
producing, in the presence of both monomers, a block
copolymer of a polymer block of a vinyl aromatic hydrocarbon
(and/or a conjugated diene) and a polydimethylsiloxane which
comprises adding a vinyl aromatic hydrocarbon, an organo
alkali metal promoter, hexamethylcyclotrisiloxane and a polar
promoter to a solvent, at a temperature of 0 to 60°C.,
allowing the polymerization of the vinyl aromatic hydrocarbon
to proceed until the color of the vinyl aromatic hydrocarbon
lithium ion species which is initially produced fades, then 
raising the temperature to 60 to 120°C. wherein the
hexamethylcyclotrisiloxane polymerizes at the end of the
polystyrene blocks and then terminating the polymerization.</p><p num="0018">Unsaturated urea polysiloxanes have been disclosed
in combination with copolymerizable comonomers. For example,
U.S. Patent 5,480,946 discloses styrene functional
polysiloxanes which are obtained by the reaction of
aminoalkyl functional polysiloxanes with styrene isocyanates.
It further discloses the styrene functional urea
polysiloxanes have improved hydrolytic stability and are
useful, either alone or in combination with copolymerizable
monomers, in oxygen permeable coatings.</p><p num="0019">The present invention relates to
organopolysiloxane-modified graft copolymers obtained by a
method comprising heating a mixture comprising an
ethylenically unsaturated monomer, a polyethylene-polybutylene
macromonomer, an organopolysiloxane
macromonomer, a free radical initiator, and optionally a
solvent.</p><p num="0020">The present invention further relates to a method
of making organopolysiloxane-modified graft copolymers
comprising heating a mixture comprising an ethylenically
unsaturated monomer, a polyethylene-polybutylene
macromonomer, an organopolysiloxane macromonomer, a free
radical initiator, and optionally a solvent.</p><p num="0021">Thus it is the purpose of this invention to make a
polyacrylate resin graft copolymer using radically 
copolymerizable macromonomeric organopolysiloxanes and
macromonomeric polyethylene-polybutylene.</p><p num="0022">It is another purpose of this invention to produce
an acrylic silicone resin having long ethylene-butylene
polymeric grafts which can promote the miscibility of the
acrylic resin in blending them with polyolefins and thereby
make them suitable for making adhesives, release coatings and
personal care products.</p><p num="0023">This invention relates to organopolysiloxane-modified
graft copolymers obtained by a method comprising
heating a mixture comprising (A) an ethylenically unsaturated
monomer, (B) a polyethylene-polybutylene macromonomer, (C) an
organopolysiloxane macromonomer, (D) a free radical
initiator, and (E) optionally a solvent.</p><p num="0024">The ethylenically unsaturated monomer (A) must be
copolymerizable with components (B) and (C). Component (A)
is exemplified by alkyl acrylates such as by methyl acrylate,
ethyl acrylate, butyl acrylate, propyl acrylate, pentyl
acrylate, hexyl acrylate, octyl acrylate, 2-ethylhexyl
acrylate, nonyl acrylate, decyl acrylate, dodecyl acrylate,
tetradecyl acrylate and hexadecyl acrylate and by alkyl
methacrylates such as methyl methacrylate, ethyl
methacrylate, propyl methacrylate, isopropyl methacrylate, n-butyl
methacrylate, isobutyl methacrylate, sec-butyl
methacrylate, t-butyl methacrylate, n-hexyl methacrylate, n-octyl
methacrylate, isooctyl methacrylate, 2-ethylhexyl 
methacrylate, n-decyl methacrylate, tetradecyl methacrylate,
n-vinyl pyrrolidone, and combinations thereof.</p><p num="0025">Preferably the ethylenically unsaturated monomer
(A) is n-vinyl pyrrolidone or an ethylenically unsaturated
monomer having the formula:
<img id="img-00090001"  orientation="unknown" wi="25" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00090001.tif"  inline="no"  he="36"/>
wherein R is hydrogen or an alkyl group, R<sup>1</sup> is an alkyl group
having from 1 to 20 carbon atoms exemplified by methyl,
ethyl, propyl, butyl, pentyl, hexyl, octyl, decyl, dodecyl
and octadecyl. Preferably R is hydrogen or methyl and R<sup>1</sup> is
selected from the group consisting of methyl, ethyl, propyl
and butyl.</p><p num="0026">Generally, component (A), the ethylenically
unsaturated monomer, is present in an amount of from 20 to 90
weight percent, and preferably from 40 to 80 weight percent,
said weight percent being based on the total weight of the
formulation.</p><p num="0027">Component (B) is a polyethylene-polybutylene
macromonomer. The polyethylene-polybutylene macromonomer (B)
preferably has the formula: X-R<sup>2</sup>-(CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>m</sub>-(CH<sub>2</sub>CH(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>))<sub>n</sub>-R<sup>3</sup>
wherein X is an acryloyl terminated urethane group, R<sup>2</sup> is a
divalent hydrocarbon group having from 1 to 20 carbon atoms,
R<sup>3</sup> is an alkyl group having from 1 to 10 carbon atoms and the 
value of m+n is from 10 to 500, and preferably from 20-200.
The acryloyl terminated urethane group of X is preferably a
group having the formula
<img id="img-00100001"  orientation="unknown" wi="25" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="49"/>
wherein R<sup>4</sup> is hydrogen or an alkyl group. The alkyl groups
are as delineated above for R<sup>1</sup>. Preferably R<sup>4</sup> is hydrogen or
methyl.</p><p num="0028">The divalent hydrocarbon group R<sup>2</sup> is exemplified
by alkylene groups such as methylene, ethylene,
-CH<sub>2</sub>CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)-, propylene, -CH<sub>2</sub>CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)CH<sub>2</sub>-, butylene,
pentylene, trimethylene, 2-methyltrimethylene,
pentamethylene, hexamethylene, 3-ethyl-hexamethylene,
octamethylene, -(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>18</sub>- and cycloalkylene radicals such as
cyclohexylene, arylene radicals such as phenylene,
combinations of divalent hydrocarbon radicals such as
benzylene (-C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>4</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-) and alkyleneoxyalkylene groups
exemplified by -CH<sub>2</sub>-O-CH<sub>2</sub>-, -CH<sub>2</sub>-O-CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-,
-CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-O-CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-, -CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-O-CH<sub>2</sub>-, -CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OCH(CH<sub>3</sub>)CH<sub>2</sub>-,
-CH<sub>2</sub>OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>- and -CH<sub>2</sub>OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-. Preferably
R<sup>2</sup> is selected from ethylene, propylene and butylene. </p><p num="0029">The alkyl groups R<sup>3</sup> are exemplified by methyl,
ethyl, propyl, butyl, pentyl, hexyl, octyl and decyl.
Preferably R<sup>3</sup> is selected from methyl, ethyl, propyl and
butyl.</p><p num="0030">Preferably the polyethylene-polybutylene
macromonomer has the formula:
<img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="51" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="88"/>
wherein R<sup>2</sup>, R<sup>3</sup>, R<sup>4</sup>, m and n are as defined above.
Preferably, R<sup>2</sup> is selected from ethylene, propylene and
butylene, R<sup>3</sup> is selected from methyl, ethyl, propyl, n-butyl,
sec-butyl and tert-butyl, R<sup>4</sup> is hydrogen or methyl and the
value of m+n is from 20 to 200.</p><p num="0031">Generally, component (B), the polyethylene-polybutylene
macromonomer, is present in amount from 5 to 50
weight percent, and preferably from 10 to 30 weight percent, 
said weight percent being based on the total weight of the
formulation.</p><p num="0032">Component (C), the organopolysiloxane macromonomer
is exemplified by acryloxyalkyl-functional organopolysiloxanes,
methacryloxyalkyl-functional organopolysiloxanes
and isopropenylbenzyl dialkyl urea-functional
organopolysiloxanes. Preferred organopolysiloxanes are
exemplified by compounds having the formula:
<img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="39" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/>
wherein R<sup>5</sup> is an alkyl group as delineated above for R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>6</sup>
is an alkyl group having from 1 to 10 carbon atoms, a has a
value of at least 1, preferably at least 3, and more
preferably at least 10, and Y is selected from an
acryloxyalkyl group, a methacryloxyalkyl group and an
isopropenylbenzyl dialkyl urea group. Preferably R<sup>5</sup> is
methyl and R<sup>6</sup> is selected from methyl, ethyl, propyl, n-butyl,
sec-butyl and tert-butyl.</p><p num="0033">Preferably Y is a group having the formula
<img id="img-00120002" orientation="unknown" wi="28" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120002.tif" inline="no" he="44"/> 
wherein R<sup>7</sup> is hydrogen or an alkyl group as delineated above
for R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>8</sup> is a divalent hydrocarbon group as delineated
above for R<sup>2</sup>. Preferably R<sup>7</sup> is hydrogen or methyl and R<sup>8</sup> is
selected from ethylene, propylene and butylene. Preferably,
Y is selected from 3-methacryloxypropyl, 3-acryloxypropyl and
3-isopropenylbenzyl dimethyl urea.</p><p num="0034">Preferably the organopolysiloxane macromonomer (C)
has the formula:
<img id="img-00130001" orientation="unknown" wi="32" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="69"/>
wherein R<sup>5</sup>, R<sup>6</sup>, R<sup>7</sup>, R<sup>8</sup> and a are as defined above.
Preferably, R<sup>5</sup> is methyl, R<sup>6</sup> is selected from methyl, ethyl,
propyl, n-butyl, sec-butyl and tert-butyl, R<sup>7</sup> is hydrogen or
methyl, R<sup>8</sup> is selected from ethylene, propylene and butylene
and a has a value of 1 to 300.</p><p num="0035">Generally, component (C), the organopolysiloxane
macromonomer, is present in an amount from 0.5 to 20 weight
percent, and preferably from 5 to 10 weight percent, said 
weight percent being based on the total weight of the
formulation.</p><p num="0036">Component (D) in this invention is a free radical
initiator. Suitable free radical initiators are exemplified
by peroxide initiators, azo initiators, redox intitiators and
photochemical initiators. The peroxide initiators are
exemplified by diacyl peroxides, peroxyesters, dialkyl
peroxides and peroxydicarbonates. Especially preferred
peroxide initiators are exemplified by dibenzoyl peroxide,
t-butyl peroctoate, dicumyl peroxide, diisopropyl
peroxydicarbonate and a preferred azo initiator is 2,2-azobisisobutyronitrile.</p><p num="0037">Generally, component (D), the free radical
initiator, is present in an amount from 0.05 to 5 weight
percent, and preferably from 0.1 to 1 weight percent, said
weight percent being based on the total weight of the
formulation.</p><p num="0038">The optional component (E), the solvent, is
exemplified by aliphatic hydrocarbons such as pentane,
hexane, heptane, octane and nonane, aromatic hydrocarbons
such as benzene, toluene and xylene; ketones such as
acetone, methylethyl ketone and methylisobutyl ketone and
halogenated diluents such as fluorine-, chlorine- and
bromine-, substituted aliphatic or aromatic hydrocarbons
such as trichloroethane, perchloroethylene, bromobenzene,
and the like. Two or more solvents may be used together. 
The solvent is preferably selected from benzene, toluene and
xylene.</p><p num="0039">The amount of solvent is not critical and may be
readily determined by one skilled in the art. Generally,
component (E), the solvent, is present in an amount of up to
1000 parts by weight, and preferably from 100 to 300 parts by
weight, per 100 parts by weight of components (A)-(D).</p><p num="0040">The temperature at which the mixture of components
(A)-(D) and optionally (E) is heated is dependent on the type
of catalyst that is selected. However, it is preferred for
purposes of this invention that the mixture of components
(A)-(D) and optionally (E) is heated at a temperature of at
least 50°C. and preferably from 50°C. to 100°C.</p><p num="0041">This invention further relates to a method of
making organopolysiloxane-modified graft copolymers
comprising heating a mixture comprising (A) an ethylenically
unsaturated monomer, (B) a polyethylene-polybutylene
macromonomer, (C) an organopolysiloxane macromonomer, (D) a
free radical initiator, and (E) optionally a solvent.
Components (A)-(E) are as delineated above including
preferred embodiments thereof and amounts thereof and the
temperature at which components (A)-(E) are heated is as
delineated above including preferred embodiments thereof.</p><p num="0042">The organopolysiloxane-modified graft copolymers
of the present invention are miscible when blended with
polyolefins and it is believed that the copolymers of this
invention will show more surface lubricity (low friction) 
than do copolymers which do not contain polydimethylsiloxane
grafts. The copolymers of this invention find utility in
adhesives (including pressure sensitive adhesives, contact
adhesives, laminating adhesives and assembly adhesives) and
release coatings.</p><p num="0043">The instant invention will be explained in greater
detail below through working examples. In the examples,
parts indicates weight parts, Mn is an abbreviation for
number-average molecular weight and Mw is an abbreviation for
weight-average molecular weight, both Mn and Mw were measured
by GPC based on polystyrene linear polymer standards.</p><p num="0044">The following materials were prepared:</p><p num="0045">An omega-methacryloxypropyl terminated
polydimethylsiloxane was prepared in the following manner:
100 grams (g) of hexamethylcyclotrisiloxane was dissolved in
150 (g) of xylene in a 500 ml 3-necked flask. This mixture
was stirred under nitrogen at room temperature. This mixture
was then subjected to a silylation treatment using
trimethylchlorosilane and n-butyl lithium as described by
U.S. Patent 5,399,649 to remove water or silanol impurities
from hexamethylcyclotrisiloxane. A syringe containing 2.4
(g) of trimethylsilanol was then added to the mixture. The
reaction was then started by adding 8 (g) of
dimethylformamide to the mixture and the mixture was then
stirred at room temperature. When the degree of conversion
of hexamethylcyclotrisiloxane was greater than 85%, a 10 mole
percent excess of the capping agent, methacryloxypropyl-dimethylchlorosilane 
was introduced into the mixture and the
reaction was maintained at 25°C. for 3 hours. The polymer
was obtained from solution by stripping and filtration. The
resulting polymer was a omega-methacryloxypropyl-terminated
polydimethylsiloxane having a degree of polymerization of
120.</p><p num="0046">Omega-methacryloyl urethane terminated
poly(ethylene-butylene) was prepared as follows: This
material was prepared according to the disclosure of U.S.
Patent 5,478,899 which discloses a process which comprises
the anionic polymerization of 1,3-butadiene using a monolithium
initiator and terminating the polymerization step by
the addition of an alkoxy silyl compound. The end group of
the polybutadiene was then converted to hydroxyl
functionality with acid and the unsaturated diene in the
polymer backbone was further hydrogenated. Next, 40 (g) of
the omega-hydroxyl terminated poly(ethylene-butylene)
compound was reacted with 1.4 (g) of methacryloyl isocyanate
in the presence of a few drops of stannous octoate catalyst
at a temperature of 60°C. for 4 hours to produce omega-methacryloyl
urethane terminated poly(ethylene-butylene).
Excess methacryloyl isocyanate was then reacted with a few
drops of water. Next, the polymer was dissolved in hexane
and the solution stirred under activated carbon to remove
color from the solution. After the solvent was removed by
filtration, molar mass analysis showed that the omega-methacryloyl
urethane terminated poly(ethylene-butylene) had 
a molecular weight (Mn) of 7112 and a Mw/Mn of 1.08 based on
GPC analysis using a polystyrene standard for the molecular
weight calibration.</p><p num="0047">An alpha secondary amino terminated
polydimethylsiloxane was prepared as follows: an alpha-hydroxyl-terminated
polydimethylsiloxane having a number
average molecular weight of 10,000 was prepared by the
anionic polymerization of hexamethylcyclotrisiloxane as
taught by U.S. Patent 5,399,649. The alpha-hydroxyl-terminated
polydimethylsiloxane was then reacted with a 10
mol % excess amount of cyclic organosilylamine (1,2,3,4-tetramethyl-aza-2-silacyclopentane)
at room temperature to
form alpha secondary amino terminated polydimethylsiloxane.</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Example 1</u></heading><p num="0048">32 (g) of ethyl acrylate, 8 (g) of the omega-methacryloyl
urethane terminated poly(ethylene-butylene)
compound prepared above and 65(g) of toluene were placed in a
250 ml 3-necked flask equipped with a thermometer, a
mechanical stirrer, a nitrogen inlet tube and a reflux
condenser. After bubbling with nitrogen for 15 minutes, 0.25
weight percent of an initiator, VAZO®-64 (2,2-azobisisobutyronitrile
from E.I. DuPont Co., Wilmington, Del.), the
weight percent being based on the weight of the ethyl
acrylate (the co-monomer), was added to the mixture. The
flask was then placed in a silicone oil bath at 65°C. under a
nitrogen atmosphere for 24 hours. After the polymerization,
the resulting copolymer was recovered out of the solvent. 
The resulting compound was a graft copolymer containing
poly(ethyl acrylate) segments and a urethane functional
poly(ethylene-butylene) graft, the graft copolymer having a
number average molecular weight (Mn) of 106,500 and an Mw/Mn
of 2.84</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0049">In a 250 ml 3-necked flask, 35 (g) of 2 ethylhexyl
acrylate, 7.5 (g) of the omega-methacryloxypropyl-terminated
polydimethylsiloxane prepared above and 7.5 (g) of the omega-methacryloyl
urethane-terminated poly(ethylene-butylene)
prepared above, 75 (g) of toluene and 0.1 (g) of VAZO®-64
(2,2-azobisisobutyronitrile from E.I. DuPont Co., Wilmington,
Del.) were added. The mixture was heated in a 70°C. oil bath
under a nitrogen atmosphere with stirring for 24 hours. The
reaction was then terminated by allowing the flask to cool to
room temperature. The resultant polymer solution poured into
methanol and the highly viscous polymer was recovered by
evaporation of solvent under reduced pressure. The resulting
compound was a graft copolymer containing poly(2-ethylhexyl
acrylate) segments, a urethane functional poly(ethylenebutylene)
graft and a methacryloxypropyl functional
polydimethylsiloxane graft, the graft copolymer having a
number average molecular weight (Mn) of 40,150 and an Mw/Mn
of 4.528.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0050">To a 250 ml 3-necked flask was added 70 parts of
methyl acrylate, 15 parts of the omega-methacryloxypropyl-terminated 
polydimethylsiloxane prepared above, 15 parts of
the omega-methacryloyl urethane-terminated poly(ethylene-butylene),
250 parts of toluene and 0.15 parts of VAZO®-64
(2,2-azobisisobutyronitrile from E.I. DuPont Co., Wilmington,
Del.) were added. The mixture was heated in a 70°C. oil bath
under a nitrogen atmosphere with stirring for 24 hours. The
reaction was then terminated by allowing the flask to cool to
room temperature. The resultant polymer solution poured into
methanol and the highly viscous polymer was recovered by
evaporation of solvent under reduced pressure. The resulting
compound was a graft copolymer containing poly(methyl
acrylate) segments, a urethane functional poly(ethylenebutylene)
graft and a methacryloxypropyl functional
polydimethylsiloxane graft, the graft copolymer having a
number average molecular weight (Mn) of 45,150 and an Mw/Mn
of 3.33.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><p num="0051">A 3-isopropenylbenzyl dimethyl urea-terminated
polydimethylsiloxane macromonomer having a molecular weight
of 10,000 was prepared. A 100 ml two necked flask was
charged with 62.23 (g) of the alpha secondary amino
terminated polydimethylsiloxane prepared above. Next,
moisture was removed from the flask by drying the material on
a vacuum line for an hour. The flask was pressurized with
nitrogen and a 10 mole percent excess of 3-isopropenyl benzyl
dimethyl isocyanate was introduced to the reaction flask
through a rubber septum. The flask contents were maintained 
at 25°C. and stirred with a magnetic stirrer. Analysis using
gas phase chromatography showed more than 96% of the 3-ispropenyl
benzyl dimethyl isocyanate converted after 12
hours of mixing. The excess amount of 3-isopropenyl benzyl
dimethyl isocyanate was reacted with a few drops of water.
The mixture was then stripped under vacuum at 70°C. to remove
excess isocyanate. The resulting polydimethylsiloxane was a
clear liquid linear polymer. <sup>13</sup>C-NMR spectra of polymer
showed the isocyanate group (123.4 ppm) converted to urea
(158.3 ppm). Gel permeation chromatography (GPC) revealed a
number average molecular weight (Mn) of 10,460 and a weight
average molecular weight (Mw) of 11,510 based on calibration
against polystyrene standards.</p><p num="0052">To a 250 ml 3-necked flask was added 70 parts of
n-vinyl pyrrolidone, 15 parts of the 3-isopropenylbenzyl
dimethyl urea terminated polydimethylsiloxane prepared above,
15 parts of the urethane functional poly(ethylene-butylene)
prepared above, 250 parts of toluene and 0.15 parts of VAZO®-64
(2,2-azobisisobutyronitrile from E.I. DuPont Co.,
Wilmington, Del.). The mixture was heated in a 70°C. oil
bath under a nitrogen atmosphere with stirring for 24 hours.
The reaction was then terminated by allowing the flask to
cool to room temperature. The resultant polymer solution
poured into methanol and the highly viscous polymer was
recovered by evaporation of solvent under reduced pressure.
The resulting compound was a graft copolymer containing a
poly(n-vinyl pyrrolidone) segment, a 3-isopropenylbenzyl 
dimethyl urea functional polydimethylsiloxane graft and a
urethane functional poly(ethylene-butylene) graft. The graft
copolymer had a number average molecular weight (Mn) of
163,000 and an Mw/Mn of 4.0.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method of making an organopolysiloxane-modified
graft copolymer comprising heating a mixture
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(A) an ethylenically unsaturated monomer;</claim-text><claim-text>(B) a polyethylene-polybutylene macromonomer;</claim-text><claim-text>(C) an organopolysiloxane macromonomer;</claim-text><claim-text>(D) a free radical initiator; and</claim-text><claim-text>(E) optionally a solvent.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1, wherein (A) is
selected from methyl acrylate, ethyl acrylate, butyl
acrylate, propyl acrylate, pentyl acrylate, hexyl acrylate,
octyl acrylate, 2-ethylhexyl acrylate, nonyl acrylate, decyl
acrylate, dodecyl acrylate, tetradecyl acrylate, hexadecyl
acrylate, methyl methacrylate, ethyl methacrylate, propyl
methacrylate, isopropyl methacrylate, n-butyl methacrylate,
isobutyl methacrylate, sec-butyl methacrylate, t-butyl
methacrylate, n-hexyl methacrylate, n-octyl methacrylate,
isooctyl methacrylate, 2-ethylhexyl methacrylate, n-decyl
methacrylate, tetradecyl methacrylate, n-vinylpyrrolidone,
polyacrylic acid, polymethylacrylic acid and combinations
thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1, wherein (A) is
n-vinylpyrrolidone or an ethylenically unsaturated monomer
having the formula

wherein R is hydrogen or methyl and R1 is
methyl, ethyl, propyl or butyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1
to 3, wherein (B) is a
polyethylene-polybutylene macromonomer having the formula:
X-R2-(CH2CH2)m-(CH2CH(C2H5))n-R3 wherein X is an acryloyl
terminated urethane group, R2 is a divalent hydrocarbon group
having from 1 to 20 carbon atoms, R3 is an alkyl group having
from 1 to 10 carbon atoms and the value of m+n is from 10 to
500.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A method according to claim 4, wherein X is a
group having the formula

wherein R4 is hydrogen or an alkyl group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1
to 3, wherein (B) is a
polyethylene-polybutylene macromonomer having the formula:

wherein R2 is ethylene, propylene or butylene, R3 is
methyl, ethyl, propyl, n-butyl, sec-butyl or tert-butyl,
R4 is hydrogen or methyl and the value of m+n
is from 20 to 200.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1
to 6, wherein (C) is
selected from acryloxyalkyl-functional organopolysiloxanes,
methacryloxyalkyl-functional organopolysiloxanes and
isopropenylbenzyl dialkyl urea-functional
organopolysiloxanes.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1
to 6, wherein (C) is
an organopolysiloxane having the formula:

wherein R5 is an alkyl group having from 1 to 20 carbon
atoms, R6 is an alkyl group having from 1 to 10 carbon atoms,
a has a value of at least 1 and Y is an acryloxyalkyl
group, a methacryloxyalkyl group or an
isopropenylbenzyl dialkyl urea group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method according to claim 8, wherein Y is a
group having the formula

wherein R7 is hydrogen or an alkyl group and R8 is a divalent
hydrocarbon group having from 1 to 20 carbon atoms.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1
to 6, wherein (C) is
an organopolysiloxane having the formula:

wherein R5 is methyl, R6 is methyl, ethyl, propyl, n-butyl,
sec-butyl or tert-butyl, R7 is hydrogen or
methyl, R8 is ethylene, propylene or butylene and a
has a value of 1 to 300.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1
to 10, wherein (D) is
selected from peroxide initiators, azo initiators, redox
intitiators and photochemical initiators.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A method according to claim 11, wherein (D) is a
peroxide initiator selected from dibenzoyl peroxide, t-butyl
peroctoate, dicumyl peroxide, diisopropyl peroxydicarbonate
and 2,2-azobisisobutyronitrile.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1
to 12, wherein (E) is
selected from pentane, hexane, heptane, octane, nonane,
benzene, toluene, xylene, acetone, methylethyl ketone,
methylisobutyl ketone, trichloroethane, perchloroethylene
and bromobenzene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1
to 13, wherein the method comprises heating the
mixture at a temperatue of 50 to 100°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A coating, sealant or adhesive
comprising a copolymer obtained by a method according
to any of claims 1 to 14.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="176" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="267" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="177" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="265" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>