<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1050555-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1050555" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="23185136" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20001108"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1050555-A1" status="new" fvid="22977176"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1050555</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20001108</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00109093-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00109093</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000503</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-30640199-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>30640199</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990506</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B65D  81/26        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B65D  81/26        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/30        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/138       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/17        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/37        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K  15/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K  15/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K  15/32        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   3/00P</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   3/22</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Sauerstoff bindendes System und Zusammensetzungen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Oxygen scavenging system and compositions</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Système désoxygénant et compositions</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0520257-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0520257</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4675356-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4675356</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5507980-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5507980</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CRYOVAC INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CRYOVAC, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Cryovac, Inc.</last-name><address><street>100 Rogers Bridge Road, Building A</street><city>Duncan, S.C. 29334-0464</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>EBNER CYNTHIA LOUISE</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>HALLOCK JOHN SCOTT</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>EBNER, CYNTHIA LOUISE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HALLOCK, JOHN SCOTT</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>EBNER, CYNTHIA LOUISE</last-name><address><street>102 North Staghorn Lane</street><city>Greer, SC 29650</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HALLOCK, JOHN SCOTT</last-name><address><street>10313 Coniston Court</street><city>Potomac, Maryland 20854</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>UEXKÜLL &amp;amp; STOLBERG</last-name><address><street>Patentanwälte Beselerstrasse 4</street><city>22607 Hamburg</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An oxygen scavenging system and composition capable of providing
good oxygen absorption activity and capabilities, wherein the system
comprises a modified anionic hydrotalcite particulate material and a transition
metal ion source.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single"><b>Field of the Invention</b></u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a novel oxygen scavenging system and
resultant compositions that can be used to retain product quality and improve
shelf life of oxygen sensitive materials. The subject compositions can be
formed into shaped structures, e.g., films, coatings, 3-dimensional solids,
fibers, webs and the like, as well as to shaped products into or onto which said
compositions or structure are incorporated, applied to or be made part of a
container structure.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>Background of the Invention</b></u></heading><p num="0002">The present oxygen scavenging system comprises a modified anionic
hydrotalcite-like particulate in combination with a transition metal ion or a
source for said ion. It may be formed into a composition composed of said
system in a carrier which permits the system to combine with oxygen when in
the presence of moisture. Specifically, the composition utilizes modified
anionic hydrotalcite-like particulates which have certain anionic groups and a
transition metal ion or source for said ion, as fully described herein below.
The particulate containing oxygen scavenging composition of the present
invention has unexpectedly been found to provide effective absorption of
oxygen from the interior of a container without adversely affecting the color,
taste or smell of the packaged products contained therein which is normally
associated with conventional agents and/or oxidation by-products thereof.</p><p num="0003">The subject oxygen scavenging system and the resultant composition
have been found to provide high scavenging activity and capacity. The
resultant composition has the ability to effectively chemically combine with
oxygen, such as from the interior of a container, without undue migration of
the components of the oxygen scavenging system or their oxidation by-product(s)
out of the composition's matrix. The inhibition of migration is of
particular advantage in that it significantly reduces or eliminates adverse 
effects on the color, taste, or smell of articles in contact with the composition
as well as provides a means of using high levels of scavenging components
while meeting government regulations directed to amounts of extraneous
material permitted in food products.</p><p num="0004">In order to enhance preservation, it is standard practice to package food
and other materials within laminated packaging material that generally
includes a barrier layer, that is, a layer having a low permeability to oxygen.
The sheet material can be thin, in which event it is wrapped around the
material being packaged, or it can be sufficiently thick that it forms a shaped
container body that is provided with a lid or other separate closure. The
polymeric sheet material may constitute some or all of the interior exposed
surface area of the container or its closure means.</p><p num="0005">It is known to include an oxygen scavenger agent in sheet material.
The oxygen scavenger agent reacts with oxygen that is trapped in the package
or that permeates into the package. This is described in, for instance, U.S. Pat.
Nos. 4,536,409 and 4,702,966 and the prior art discussed in these references.
U.S. Pat. No. 4,536,409, for example, describes cylindrical containers formed
from such sheet material and provided with metal lids.</p><p num="0006">When the container is formed of a glass or metal body and is provided
with a hermetically sealed metal closure, the permeation of oxygen through the
body and the closure is theoretically impossible because of the impermeability
of the materials forming the body and closure. As a practical matter, metal
cans can reliably prevent oxygen ingress. However, some oxygen ingress may
occur by diffusion through the gasket or the like positioned between a
container body and its lid or end portion. It has long been recognized that
when conventional containers of these types are used for the storage of oxygen
sensitive materials, the shelf life of the stored materials is very limited. The
quality of the packaged material tends to deteriorate over time, in part because 
dissolved oxygen typically is present in the package from the time it is filled;
and in part due to oxygen ingress which occurs during storage.</p><p num="0007">When the container is in the form of a can, the can end or other closure
in many instances includes push components or pull components which are
intended to be, respectively, pushed or pulled in order to allow removal of the
fluid or other material in the container without removing the entire closure
from the container. These push or pull components are often defined by
discontinuities or lines of weakness in the panel of the closure. Problems that
can arise at these lines of weakness or discontinuities include the risk of
permeation of oxygen into the container and the risk of corrosion of the metal
where the normal protective lacquer coating is ruptured at the lines of
weakness or at the discontinuities.</p><p num="0008">It is desirable to extend the shelf-life of packaged products using
materials capable of being fabricated into or as part of a film, liner material,
closure, gasket or other member of a package intended for storage of oxygen
sensitive products.</p><p num="0009">Various types of oxygen scavengers have been proposed for this
purpose. For example, it is well known to package iron powder in a sachet for
use with dry foods. See Mitsubishi Gas Chemical Company, Inc.'s literature
titled "Ageless® - A New Age in Food Preservation" (date unknown).
However, these materials require the addition of water soluble salts to enhance
the oxygen scavenging rate. In the presence of moisture, the salts and iron
tend to migrate into liquids, producing off-flavors. Similarly, United States
Patent No. 4,536,409 issued to Farrell et al. recommends potassium sulphite as
a scavenger, with similar results.</p><p num="0010">It is known in the art that ascorbate compounds (ascorbic acid, its
alkali metal salts, optical isomers, and derivatives thereof) as well as sulfites,
bisulfites, phenolics, etc. can be oxidized by molecular oxygen, and can thus
serve as an oxygen scavenging material. For example, United States Patent 
No. 5,075,362, issued to Hofeldt et al., discloses the use of ascorbate
compounds in container closures as oxygen scavengers.</p><p num="0011">United States Patent No. 5,284,871 issued to Graf relates to the use of
an oxygen scavenging composition made of a solution of a reducing agent and
dissolved species of copper which are blended into foods, cosmetics and
pharmaceuticals. Copper ascorbate is used in the examples. The reference
indicates that relatively high level of Cu<sup>2+</sup> (∼ 5 ppm) are required in the food
for scavenging to be effective but indicates that small amounts of the Cu<sup>2+</sup> may
combine with oxygen in food to cause food spoilage. In order to avoid
spoilage, one is required to reduce the amount of headspace O<sub>2</sub> or partially
flush the container with an inert gas (Col. 5, lines 32-39). A paper by E. Graf,
"Copper (II) Ascorbate: A Novel Food Preservation System", Journal of
Agricultural Food Chemistry, Vol. 42, pages 1616-1619 (1994) identifies
copper gluconate as a preferred raw material.</p><p num="0012">It is also well known in the scientific literature (See "Polymer
Compositions Containing Oxygen Scavenging Compounds", Teumac, F.N.; <u style="single">et
al.</u> WO 91/17044, published Nov. 4, 1991, filed on May 1, 1991) that the
oxidation rate of ascorbate compounds can be increased significantly by the
use of catalysts. Typical oxidation catalysts for ascorbic acid and its
derivatives are water soluble transition metal salts.</p><p num="0013">In each of the above references, the active component of the oxygen
scavenging systems utilized agents which readily transfer into the food or other
packaged product or materials or which produce oxidation by-products which
are known to adversely affect a wide range of packaged material.</p><p num="0014">Hydrotalcite is a naturally occurring mineral commonly classified as a
clay. Generally speaking, clays break down into broad groups of being
cationic materials which are commonly found in nature or anionic materials,
which is rarely found in nature. These materials are used in a wide range of
applications, such as industrial absorbents, catalysts, fillers, decolorizing 
agents and the like. Naturally occurring hydrotalcite are hydroxide-carbonate
minerals of the formula
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Mg<sub>6</sub>Al<sub>2</sub>(OH)<sub>16</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>·4H<sub>2</sub>O</st32:che>
It is well known that the hydrotalcite mineral is strongly bonded to the
carbonate. The carbonate may be driven off by thermal calcination.</p><p num="0015">Recently, hydrotalcites with anions other than carbonate have been
synthesized. They are generally layered double hydroxides (LDH) which
include anionic hydrotalcite-like compounds (HTLC). They have been
described in U.S. Patents 5,399,329 and 5,507,980 as well as by W. T. Reiche
in Chem Tech (1986) 58-63, the teachings of which are incorporated herein in
their entirety by reference. These new materials have anions in its crystal
structure which are easily exchanged.</p><p num="0016">It is highly desired to provide an effective oxygen scavenging system
and composition which have high oxygen absorption rate and capacity.</p><p num="0017">It is further desired to provide an oxygen scavenging system and
composition which are capable of inhibiting the release of oxidation by-product(s)
which may adversely effect the color, taste or smell of the packaged
material.</p><p num="0018">It is further desired to provide an effective oxygen scavenging
composition which has the active scavenger system contained within a carrier
and the system still provides a high oxygen absorption rate and capacity.</p><p num="0019">It is further desired to provide an effective oxygen scavenging system
which is thermally stable and, thereby, capable of allowing the packaging
system to be formed and processed by conventional techniques which include
elevated temperature processing steps.</p><p num="0020">It is still further desired to provide an effective oxygen scavenging
system and composition which has the system contained within a carrier 
suitable for forming at least part of a package or container which enhances the
storage stability of oxygen-sensitive articles contained therein.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>Summary of the Invention</b></u></heading><p num="0021">The present invention is directed to a composition comprising a carrier
having uniformly distributed therein an oxygen scavenging system capable of
exhibiting high initial oxygen scavenging activity and enhanced oxygen
scavenging capacity while avoiding undue migration of the components of the
composition and its oxidation by product(s) from the carrier. The inhibition to
migration significantly reduces or eliminates adverse effects of color, taste and
smell of packaged articles which are in contact with or contained in a container
having said composition. Specifically, the present composition comprises a
carrier having a combination of a modified anionic hydrotalcite-like material
and a transition metal ion source, as fully described herein below.</p><p num="0022">The present invention is further directed to shaped structures
containing or derived from the subject composition. Such structures can
comprise one or more layers of a film suitable for forming a closed package
(e.g., pouch) as well as semi rigid or rigid containers, including closures, such
as closure sealants, closure gaskets, fluid-applied sealant compositions (e.g.,
melt-applied crown cap gasket compositions), cap liner discs, and the like,
formed with or containing the subject composition.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>Detailed Description</b></u></heading><p num="0023">The present invention is directed to an oxygen scavenging composition
comprising a carrier having uniformly distributed therein an effective oxygen
scavenging system comprising a modified anionic hydrotalcite-like material
and a transition metal ion source distributed therein, as fully described herein
below. </p><p num="0024">The present invention further provides an improved container for
packaging materials, such as food, beverages and the like, which are
susceptible to oxidative degradation. The present improved container is
capable of retaining product quality and enhanced shelf life of the packaged
material without adversely affecting the color, taste or smell of the packaged
material by the present oxygen scavenging composition. It further provides a
packaging system which can have high levels of oxygen scavenger agent
therein while meeting government regulatory standards related to amounts of
such agents contained in food products.</p><p num="0025">The term "system", as used herein and in the appended claims, refers to
active oxygen scavenging agents comprising at least one modified anionic
hydrotalcite-like material in combination with at least one transition metal ion
source. The transition metal ion source may be present as a transition metal
compound which forms a substantially homogeneous mixture with modified
anionic hydrotalcite-like material; or as a transition metal compound coated on
the surface of the modified anionic hydrotalcite-like particulate material; or as
transition metal ions substituted for at least a portion of the non-transition
metal ions, M<sup>II</sup> and even M<sup>III</sup>, of the modified anionic hydrotalcite particulate
material; or a combination thereof.</p><p num="0026">The term "composition" as used herein and in the appended claims
refers to the active oxygen scavenging agents forming the system and a carrier
component. The carrier can be a polymer matrix in which the particulate
material forming the subject oxygen scavenging system is substantially
uniformly distributed, or a film or mat (woven or non-woven) having the
particulate material substantially uniformly distributed therein or deposited
thereon, or a moisture permeable pouch or sachet which contain the subject
particulate material distributed therein.</p><p num="0027">The anionic hydrotalcite-like material which is a component of the
oxygen scavenger system of the present invention has the general formula: <st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">[ M<st32:sup pos="post">II</st32:sup> <st32:sub pos="post">1-x</st32:sub>M<st32:sup pos="post">III</st32:sup> <st32:sub pos="post">x</st32:sub> (OH)<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub> ] <st32:sup pos="post">x+</st32:sup> M<st32:sup pos="post">I</st32:sup> <st32:sub pos="post">y</st32:sub> [ A<st32:sup pos="post">a-</st32:sup> <st32:sub pos="post"><st32:frac align="centre">x+y<st32:over>a</st32:over></st32:frac></st32:sub>·nH<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub>O ] <st32:sup pos="post">(x+y)-</st32:sup></st32:df>
wherein M<sup>II</sup> represents magnesium (preferred), calcium, zinc, nickel, copper or
cobalt or mixtures thereof in their plus 2 valence state, M<sup>III</sup> represents
aluminum (preferred), chromium, or iron or mixtures thereof in their plus 3
valence state. In certain instances the present HTLC may further contain
cations M<sup>I</sup> which represents an alkali metal cation selected from sodium
(preferred), potassium or mixtures thereof having a plus 1 valence state. M<sup>I</sup>
may be present, when "a" (as defined below) has a value of at least 2, in a
molar amount y equal to a value of from 0 to about 0.5. The molar ratio of M<sup>II</sup>
to M<sup>III</sup> is from 1 to 5; OH represent hydroxyl groups; x has a numerical value
of from about 0.1 to 0.5; and n has a numerical value of from 0 to 4 and
generally from 1 to 4.</p><p num="0028">The symbol A of the above formula represents, at least in part, an
oxygen scavenger group containing anion. Such oxygen scavenger group
containing anion may be, for example, inorganic anions such as bisulfite,
dithionite and the like which are capable of reacting with oxygen or organic
anions such as, for example, ascorbates, thiolates or phenolates and the like
which are capable of reacting with oxygen. The remainder of the anion A
being residual anion of the precursor HTLC, as fully described herein below.
The anion A should be at least about 60 mole %, preferably at least about 80
mole % and most preferably at least about 90 mole % in the form of the
oxygen scavenging inorganic or organic anions described above with the
remainder being residual anions of the original hydrotalcite and/or other
anions. The symbol "a" of the above formula represents the numerical value
of the valence of the anion A. For example, the value of "a" for a dithionite
anion is 2 while the value of "a" for the bisulfite, ascorbate or phenolate is 1. 
The value of "a" for the residual anion will depend on the identity of the anion
and, in general, will have a value of from 1 to 3.</p><p num="0029">In general, when the subject modified anionic hydrotalcite-like material
has anions A which predominately represents monovalent anions, such as
bisulfite, phenolate or ascorbate, as described above, or is formed in a manner
which does not yield M<sup>I</sup> as part of the resultant product, the subject oxygen
scavenger agent of the present invention can be represented by the general
formula:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">[ M<st32:sup pos="post">II</st32:sup> <st32:sub pos="post">1-x</st32:sub>M<st32:sup pos="post">III</st32:sup> <st32:sub pos="post">x</st32:sub> (OH)<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub> ] <st32:sup pos="post">x-</st32:sup> [ A<st32:sup pos="post">a-</st32:sup> <st32:sub pos="post"><st32:frac align="centre">x<st32:over>a</st32:over></st32:frac></st32:sub>·nH<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub>O ] <st32:sup pos="post">x-</st32:sup></st32:df>
wherein each symbol is the same as defined above.</p><p num="0030">The term "ascorbate anion" as used herein and in the appended claims
refers to the deprotonated species of ascorbic acid in either its D or L form and
any derivative, or analog thereof, including, for example, erythorbic acid and
mixtures thereof. It is preferred that the ascorbate anion be selected from the
deprotonated species of D- or L- ascorbic acid, or fatty acid derivatives of
ascorbic acid as well as mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0031">The term "phenolate anion" as used herein and in the appended claims
refers to (i) deprotonated hydroxyl group containing aromatic ring or
condensed aromatic ring compound. Examples of phenolic compounds from
which the phenolate anion can be derived include phenol, pyrocatechol,
recorcinol, pyrogallol, pyrochatechol monoethyl ether, resorcinal monoethyl
ether, hydroquinone, 1,2,4-trihydroxybenzene, tetrahydroquinone, 2,4-dibutylphenol
and the like; or (ii) hydroxyl group containing aromatic ring or
condensed aromatic ring compounds which further contain a deprotonated
carboxylic acid group such as salicylate anion, 3-hydroxy benzoate, 4-hydroxy
benzoate, 3,4,5-trihydroxybenzoate and the like. </p><p num="0032">The term "hydrotalcite-like" is a recognized term in the art (See Cavani
et al, Catalyst Today <u style="single">11</u> 173 1991) and is used herein in a manner consistent
with such usage.</p><p num="0033">The subject modified anionic hydrotalcite-like materials can be formed
by a variety of means. In one instance, an anionic HTLC having a labile anion
can be used as the precursor in forming the present material. The anion of the
precursor anionic hydrotalcite-like material should be sufficiently labile to be
readily exchanged with the oxygen scavenger anion. HTLC having lower
alkanoic acid anions, such as a C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>5</sub> monocarboxylic acid anion (e.g., anions
of formic, acetic, propionic, or butyric acid or the like) is a preferred anionic
HTLC to be used as the precursor material. The formation of such precursor
material is disclosed in U.S. Patent 5,399,329, the entire teachings of which
are incorporated herein by reference. The present oxygen scavenging anionic
hydrotalcite-like component of the subject system is formed by anion
exchange of the above-described precursor material, in the absence of oxygen,
with alkali metal or akaline earth metal salts of an oxygen-scavenger anion,
described herein above.</p><p num="0034">Alternately, the subject modified anionic hydrotalcite-like material can
be formed by reacting, in the absence of oxygen, either the salt or conjugated
acid (protonated form) of at least one of the subject oxygen scavenger anions
with HTLC having carbonate anions. The reaction may be carried out in
deoxygengated water as the reaction media. The reaction product is washed
with deoxygenated water in the absence of atmospheric oxygen to produce a
water insoluble oxygen scavenger active material of the present invention.</p><p num="0035">Still another manner of forming the subject modified anionic
hydrotalcite-like material utilizes previously calcined hydrotalcite. The
calcined hydrotalcite without associated anions can be reacted with conjugate
acids of the above-described oxygen scavenging anions in the absence of
oxygen to yield the subject materials. In the case of bisulfite, this may be 
accomplished using a solution of sulfur dioxide in water. In yet another
method, an appropriate source of trivalent metal (such as aluminum hydroxide)
may be reacted, in the absence of oxygen, with an appropriate source of
divalent metal (such as magnesium oxide or nickel hydroxide) in the presence
of conjugate acids of the above described oxygen scavenging anions to yield
the subject materials.</p><p num="0036">The preferred modified anionic hydrotalcite-like material used to form
the oxygen scavenger system of the present invention has magnesium as M<sup>II</sup>.
However, the magnesium may be at least partially substituted with a transition
metal ion, such as cations selected from nickel, cobalt, zinc, copper,
manganese or mixtures thereof. Further, the preferred material has aluminum
as M<sup>III</sup>. However, the aluminum may be partially (up to about 50 mole
percent) substituted from the family of cations selected from chromium, iron
or mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0037">It is believed, though not meant to be a limitation on the present
invention, that the precursor HTLC has the capacity to have the oxygen
scavenger anions described above become part of the structure of the HTLC.
Because the present oxygen scavenging HTLC has a plate-like structure with a
small thickness of about 0.005 to 0.1 microns (typically from 0.02 to 0.06
microns) and an aspect ratio of breadth to thickness of at least about 50 and
generally in the range of from 50 to 5000 and typically from 50 to 1000, the
major ion exchange occurs on the plate surface. This permits the oxygen
scavenger anion to be capable of readily reacting with oxygen in the presence
of moisture to provide a desired oxygen scavenger agent. Further, it is
believed that the presently modified HTLC reacts with any oxidation by-products
(through the hydroxyl group) or the oxidation by-products which may
form are adsorbed on or absorbed within the crystal structure of the subject
modified HTLC. </p><p num="0038">The subject oxygen scavenger agent is formed by anion exchange to
provide an oxygen scavenger anion containing HTLC as described above. The
anion A of the present agent should be at least about 60 mole percent oxygen
scavenger anion, with preferably at least about 80 mole percent and most
preferably at least about 90 mole percent. Lesser mole percentages may be
acceptable where the lower amount still provides sufficient oxygen scavenging
activity for a particular application. The exact percentage can be readily
determined by one skilled in the art. However, the high degree of anionic sites
located on the surface of the HTLC provides the ability to provide an oxygen
scavenger of high capacity. Such capacity enables one to achieve extended
storage capacity of the resultant packaged product. The amount of oxygen
scavenging agent will depend on the anticipated application of the resultant
scavenging composition. When large amounts of composition are used to
scavenge small volumes of oxygen (such as in can coating applications), the
amount of oxygen scavenging agent can be as low as about 0.5 weight percent
of the composition and preferably at least 1 weight percent of the composition.
In other conventional applications, such as cap liners and the like, where the
loading of the particulate in the polymer carrier is low and/or the amount of
composition is small, the amount of oxygen scavenging agent should be at
least about 2 weight percent, preferably from 2 to 20 weight percent, more
preferably from 4 to 15 weight percent based on the weight of the composition.
The exact amount of oxygen scavenging agent required for a particular
application can be readily determined by the artisan. The present invention
provides a means of achieving a wide range of scavenger agent content
including high weight percentages.</p><p num="0039">The oxygen scavenging system of the present invention has been found
to provide a high degree of oxygen scavenging activity, rate and capacity when
the agent is placed in the presence of oxygen and moisture. Thus, the
presently described HTLC system must be maintained in the absence of 
oxygen during formation and the absence of oxygen or moisture during
storage. When the present system is formulated into an oxygen scavenging
composition with a carrier, such as a polymeric matrix, the carrier should be
able to maintain the system substantially free from moisture to the degree
needed to trigger (initiate) a high rate of oxygen scavenging to occur to
provide preservation of the packaged goods contemplated.</p><p num="0040">Although modified HTLC has the ability to scavenge oxygen when
used alone, it has been unexpectedly found that the present system comprising
modified HTLC and a transition metal ion source provides a composition
which has enhanced oxygen scavenging activity and capacity. Thus, the
present system and composition are capable of initially removing oxygen
within the atmosphere of a container at a high initial rate and has the capacity
to remove greater amounts of oxygen per unit of the system than obtainable by
compositions which merely contain a modified HTLC. Further, this
unexpected enhanced scavenging activity and capacity is provided for by the
present system without allowing the initial components of the present system
and/or any resultant oxidation by-products migrate into and adversely effect
the color, taste, or smell of the articles contained within the resultant container.</p><p num="0041">The modified HTLC oxygen scavenging component of the present
system is used in combination with small amounts of transition metal ions.
These ions can be provided by the presence of an inorganic or organic
transition metal compound and/or by ion replacement with some M<sup>II</sup> and/or
M<sup>III</sup> of the HTLC. This admixture or combination has been found to provide a
composition having enhanced oxygen scavenging activity and capacity.</p><p num="0042">It has been unexpectedly found that one can obtain a highly effective
oxygen scavenger by combining the above-described modified HTLC with a
transition metal compound. The transition metal compound may be in the
form of a salt, chelate, complex or compound in which the transition metal is
associated with other elements or groups by ionic or covalent bonds. </p><p num="0043">The transition metals found useful herein are those of the series of
metals of the Periodic Table in which the filling of the outermost shell to eight
electrons is interrupted to bring the penultimate shell from 8 to 12 or 32
electrons. These elements use both their penultimate shell orbits as well as
outermost shell orbits in bonding. Thus, the transition elements include
elements of the first transition series of the Periodic Table composed of
elements 21 through 29 (Sc, Ti, V, Cr, Mn, Fe, Co, Ni and Cu or mixtures
thereof) and, of these, the preferred metals are cobalt, copper, iron, tin, nickel
and manganese, or mixtures thereof with copper and cobalt being most
preferred. The positive oxidation state of the metal when introduced as part of
the system is not necessarily that of the active state which causes enhanced
activity and capacity to the system.</p><p num="0044">Transition metal compounds suitable for providing the presence of the
metal ion may be in the form of an organic transition metal complex, chelant
or organic carboxylic acid salt. Examples of suitable organic transition metal
compounds are:
<sl><li>(1) Metal Salts of mono-, di- and poly-carboxylic acids having a carbon
chain length of C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> or so. The carbon chain can be aliphatic or
aromatic, substituted or unsubstituted, may contain unsaturation or may
be a fatty acid. Illustrative examples of such metal salts are:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>aliphatic monocarboxylic acids such as, formic, acetic,
propionic, butyric, valeric, caproic, caprylic, capric, lauric,
tridecanoic, myristic, pentadecanoic acids and the like;</li><li>aliphatic dicarboxylic acids such as, oxalic, malonic, succinic,
glutaric, adipic, pimelic, azelaic, sebacic acids and the like;</li><li>poly-carboxylic acids such as, citric acid and the like;</li><li>acids containing unsaturation such as, oleic, linoleic, sorbic,
glutaconic, hydromuconic, octenedioic acids and the like; </li><li>aromatic acids such as, benzoic, salicylic and the like and may
be unsubstituted or substituted;</li><li>fatty acids such as, higher carbon monoacids, preferably having
the carboxyl group located terminally, for example palmitic,
stearic, nonadecanoic acids and the like;</li></ul>The acid may be substituted with hydrocarbyl groups which may be
composed of straight or branched chains, typically an aliphatic group
having 1-6 carbon atoms or an aromatic group, for example,
cyclohexanebutyric acid and 2-ethylhexanoic acid. Further, the acids
may have other substitution groups such as aldehyde or hydroxyl
groups, for example, as contained in glyoxylic acid, glycolic acid, or
gluconic acid and the like;</li><li>(2) Metal Chelate acid/base complexes such as those formed with
ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid, phthalocyanine, tetraphenyl porphines
and naphthalocyanines, and the like;</li><li>(3) Metal Sulfonic acid containing compounds such as p-toluenesulfonic
acid and the like;</li><li>(4) Metal Ionomer salt in which a polymeric counterion is employed. Such
ionomers are well known in the art; or</li><li>(5) Metal Ligands in which the transition metal is associated with
acetylacetonate, benzoylacetonate, 2,2,6,6-tetramethyl-3,5-heptanedionate
and the like.</li></sl></p><p num="0045">The preferred organic transition metal compounds are, for example,
cobalt (II) neodecanoate, cobalt (II) oleate, cobalt (II) 2-ethylhexanoate, copper
(II) stearate, copper (II) 2-ethylhexanoate, copper (II) palmitate, copper (II)
acetate, copper (II) gluconate, cobalt (II) acetate, iron (II) acetate, iron (III)
acetylacetonate, iron (II) gluconate, manganese (II) acetate, nickel (II) 2-ethylhexanoate
and the like. </p><p num="0046">Alternately, the transition metal compound may be in the form of an
inorganic transition metal salt. The salt may be a water-soluble or a water-insoluble
salt. The salts may be transition metal halides, sulfites, sulfates,
sulfides, phosphites, phosphates, pyrophosphates, phosphides, hypophosphites,
nitrites, nitrates, oxides, carbonates, hydroxides, chlorates, bromates,
chromates, chromites, titanates, borides, perchlorates, tetrafluoroborates,
tungstates and the like and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0047">Examples of such salts include Copper (I or II) sulfide, Copper (I or II)
bromide, Copper (I or II) chloride, Copper (I or II) oxide, Copper (II)
carbonate, Copper (II) fluoride, Copper (II) hydroxide, Copper (I or II) iodide,
Copper (II) nitrate, Copper (II) nitrite, Copper (II) sulfate, Cobalt (II) bromide,
Cobalt (II) carbonate, Cobalt (II) choride, Cobalt (II) hydroxide, Cobalt (II)
nitrate, Cobalt (II) sulfate, Cobalt (II or III) oxide, Iron (II or III) bromide, Iron
(II or III) chloride, Iron (II or III) fluoride, Iron (III) nitrate, Iron (II or III)
oxide, Iron (II or III) perchlorate, Iron (III) phosphate, Iron (II or III) sulfate,
Iron (II) sulfide, Manganese (II) bromide, Manganese (II) carbonate,
Manganese (II) chloride, Manganese (II, III or IV) oxide, Manganese (II)
hypophosphite, Manganese (II) nitrate, Manganese (II) sulfate, Nickel (II)
bromide, Nickel (II) chloride, Nickel (II) hyrdoxide, Nickel (II) oxide. The
preferred inorganic salts useful in forming the present oxygen scavenger
system and composition are copper (II) sulfate, copper (I) chloride, copper (II)
chloride, cobalt (II) sulfate, iron (II) chloride, iron (III) chloride, iron (II)
sulfate, manganese (II) sulfate, tin (II) sulfate and nickel (II) sulfate.</p><p num="0048">The term "compound" as used herein and in the appended claims
refers, except where specifically indicated otherwise, to materials which have
the transition metal in a valence state other than zero and are bound to a
counter moiety, such as in a salt, complex, chelate or other form which
provides a stable material. </p><p num="0049">The oxygen scavenging system of the present invention comprise
modified HTLC oxygen scavenger and a transition metal ion source. When
the transition metal ion source is in the form of an inorganic or organic
transition metal compound, as described above, it may be physically mixed
with the particulate modified HTLC to provide a substantially uniform mixture
of the modified HTLC and transition metal compound. This mixture is
uniformly distributed in the carrier to provide the oxygen scavenging
composition of the present invention. The physical mixture can be formed by
initially mixing the modified HTLC and the transition metal compound and
then introducing this mixture into a carrier. Alternately, the modified HTLC
and the transition metal compound can be separately mixed with the carrier
and then each of the loaded carriers can be mixed together to provide a
uniform mixture of the transition metal compound and the modified HTLC in
a carrier matrices.</p><p num="0050">Alternately, the modified HTLC can be coated with the transition metal
compound to provide an intimate mixture of the two components forming the
oxygen scavenger system of the present invention. As stated above, modified
HTLC has a layered structure and, thereby, provides a high surface area which
can be at least partially coated with a transition metal compound. This coating
can be done by any conventional manner such as by treating modified HTLC
with a solution of transition metal compound to the point of incipient wetness
and then removing the solvent. The present modified HTLC/transition metal
compound system can be an intimate mixture of modified HTLC and
transition metal compound in combination with modified HTLC coated with
transition metal compound.</p><p num="0051">Still further, the transition metal compound can be used as a source of
transition metal ion which is ion exchanged with a portion of the non-transition
metals (e.g., Ca<sup>+2</sup>, Mg<sup>+2</sup>) of the modified HTLC. This can be
accomplished by introducing a transition metal compound (preferably as a salt) 
into the reagents used to form modified HTLC. Alternately, one can contact a
previously formed modified HTLC with a solution of a transition metal salt for
a period of time and elevated temperature to cause ion exchange to occur (e.g.,
at least 60 minutes, preferably from 120 to 360 minutes contact time. It is
desirable to wash the resultant modified HTLC with water or a water-alcohol
mixture to remove the exchanged salt by-product. The resultant product may
be composed of modified HTLC which has transition metal compound
intimately admixed therewith and/or coated on its surface as well as transition
metal ion as part of the modified HTLC.</p><p num="0052">The aqueous solution used to coat the transition metal compound onto
and/or ion-exchange the transition metal ion with the modified HTLC must be
free of oxygen. The process should be done in an oxygen free atmosphere.
The oxygen scavenging combination of the present invention has been found
to provide effective oxygen scavenging activity and rate when the agent is
placed in the presence of oxygen and moisture. Thus, the presently described
oxygen scavenging compositions of the invention must be maintained in the
absence of oxygen during formation and the absence of oxygen or moisture
during storage. When the present system is formulated into an oxygen
scavenging composition with a carrier, such as a polymeric matrix, the carrier
should be able to maintain the agent substantially free from moisture to the
degree required to trigger (initiate) a high rate of oxygen scavenging to occur.</p><p num="0053">The amount of the modified HTLC oxygen scavenging component of
the system will depend on the anticipated application of the resultant
scavenging composition. When large amounts of composition are used to
scavenge small volumes of oxygen (such as might be the case if a relatively
thick polymeric coating were used to coat the entire interior surface of a can),
the amount of modified HTLC oxygen scavenging component can be as low as
about 0.05 weight percent of the composition and preferably at least 1 weight
percent of the composition. Generally speaking, the modified HTLCs may be 
used in the range of 0.05-90% based on total weight of the composition; more
preferably 0.5-40%; and most preferably 1.0-25% based on total weight of
composition. In some conventional applications, such as cap liners, crown
gasket compositions, can sealants, and the like, where the loading of the
particulate in the polymer carrier is low and/or the amount of composition is
small, the amount of modified hydrotalcite oxygen scavenging component can
be at least about 1 weight percent, preferably from 2 to 40 weight percent, and
more preferably from 3 to 25 weight percent based on the weight of the
composition.</p><p num="0054">The amount of modified HTLC oxygen scavenging component
required for a particular application can be readily determined by the artisan.
When the oxygen scavenger particulate is incorporated into a gasket, the
amount is normally at least 0.05 weight percent (e.g., 0.05 to 90%) based on
the total weight of the composition, generally at least 1% and preferably at
least 2% (e.g. 2 to 9%, preferably 2 to 40% and more preferably from 2 to
25%). In the case of a plastisol, lacquer, or hot melt applied to the center panel
of a closure, where the carrier does not otherwise serve as a gasket, the amount
can be much higher. For example, loadings of 20 to 60 weight percent, or in
some cases up to 90 weight percent are workable. When the composition is in
the form of a film, mat, pouch or sachet, the oxygen scavenger should be
present in an amount to effectively scavenge oxygen during the contemplated
storage period of the container for the appropriate contents. An amount of
from about 0.01 to 2 grams of scavenging combination will effectively
scavenge oxygen of a container of normal size. The present invention
provides the ability to achieve a wide range of modified HTLC scavenger
agent content including high weight percentages.</p><p num="0055">The transition metal component described above should be present in
the subject composition in mole ratio of modified HTLC to transition metal of
the transition metal compound of from about 3000:1 to 1:1 with from 2000:1 
to 5:1 being preferred and from 100:1 to 10:1 being most preferred. In certain
applications the ratio may be greater or lesser to provide for effective
scavenging of oxygen.</p><p num="0056">Exemplary modified HTLC and transition metal compound suitable for
use in the present invention are finely divided solids that are particularly suited
to replace part or all of the filler commonly found in sealant, coating, or film
compositions which are applications contemplated herein. The particulate size
of these components may range from 10 to 500 microns with from 20 to 50
microns being preferred.</p><p num="0057">The subject composition as a whole is effectively anhydrous, that is, it
provides a moisture content lower than needed to trigger (initiate at a
substantial rate) oxygen scavenging. Thus, it is preferred that the carrier
component of the composition be a polymeric matrix which is also preferably
anhydrous. Generally, the polymeric matrix substantially protects the
scavenger from moisture under normal atmospheric conditions and, therefore,
the oxygen scavenger agent remains substantially inert to scavenging activity.
However, once a high degree of moisture is attained, as in a closed package
environment of food products, the scavenging activity is initiated or triggered.
Moisture ingress into the polymeric matrix carrying the composition is
conventionally accelerated by common practices such as hot filling,
sterilization, pasteurization, retort and the like. The polymer matrix should be
sufficiently permeable to permit moisture and oxygen to pass into the matrix's
mass and contact the particulate material.</p><p num="0058">In one embodiment of the present invention, the carrier of the subject
composition comprises a polymeric matrix material, that is to say polymeric
material (including optional additives such as plasticizers, fillers, surfactants,
etc.) that will form a solid matrix having distributed therein the oxygen
scavenging system of the presnt invention. The polymeric matrix carrier
should be selected with regard to the nature of the composition (film, 
dispersion, latex, plastisol, dry blends, solution or melt) and its utilization as
part of the container and/or closure in a conventional manner.</p><p num="0059">The carrier may be chosen from at least one polymeric material that
can form a solid, or semi-solid matrix. The polymeric carrier can be derived
from a variety of polymers which are available from a variety of bulk physical
configurations such as films, dispersion, latex, plastisol, dry blend, solution, or
melt (e.g., thermoplastic meltable polymer). The particular physical
configuration of the polymer selected will depend on the end structure into
which the subject composition is eventually formed or incorporated. The
polymeric matrix is derived from polymer types which may be thermoplastic
or thermosetting.</p><p num="0060">The primary functions served by the polymer matrix for purposes of the
present invention are to provide a compatible carrier (a material which is
stable under normal packaging temperature conditions and does not deactivate
the oxygen scavenger activity of the present modified hydrotalcite transition
metal ion system) for the oxygen scavenging system which is fully described
herein above and to permit ingress of both oxygen and water into the
composition under dictated conditions and in a manner which permits them to
come in contact with the components of the system. The scope of the polymer
in general can be very broad. However, the polymer matrix may also be
selected to perform additional functions depending on the physical
configuration in which it is provided in a final structure into which it is shaped
or incorporated. Thus, the particular polymer or mixture of polymers selected
ultimately will be determined by the end use in which it exerts its oxygen
scavenging effect.</p><p num="0061">Accordingly, suitable polymers from which the polymeric matrix may
be derived include polyolefins, vinyl polymers, polyethers, polyesters,
polyamides, phenol-formaldehyde condensation polymers, polysiloxanes, ionic 
polymers, polyurethanes, acrylics and naturally occurring polymers such as
cellulosics, tannins, polysaccharides, and starches.</p><p num="0062">Suitable materials for use as the polymeric matrix component of latex
compositions, e.g., for can ends, are described in U.S. 4,360,120; U.S.
4,368,828 and EP 0182674. Suitable polymeric materials for use when the
compositions are organic solutions or aqueous dispersions are described in
U.S. 4,360,120; U.S. 4,368,828; and GB 2,084,601. Suitable materials for use
in thermoplastic compositions include the materials proposed in U.S.
4,619,848; U.S. 4,529,740; U.S. 5,014,447; U.S. 4,698,469; GB 1,112,023;
GB 1,112,024; GB 1,112,025 and EP 129309. The teachings of each of the
references cited herein above are incorporated herein by reference in their
entirety.</p><p num="0063">In particular, the polymeric carrier can be generally selected from
polyolefins as, for example, polyethylene, polypropylene, ethylene/propylene
copolymers, acid modified ethylene/propylene copolymers, polybutadiene,
butyl rubber, styrene/butadiene rubber, carboxylated styrene/butadiene,
polyisoprene, styrene/isoprene/styrene block copolymers,
styrene/butadiene/styrene block copolymers, styrene/ethylene/ butylene/styrene
block copolymers, ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymers, ethylene/acrylate and
ethylene/ (meth) acrylate copolymers (for instance, ethylene/butyl acrylate or
ethylene/butyl methacrylate copolymers), ethylene/vinyl alcohol copolymers,
ethylene or propylene/carbon monoxide alternating copolymers, vinyl chloride
homopolymers and copolymers, vinylidene dichloride polymers and
copolymers, styrene/acrylic polymers, polyamides, and vinyl acetate polymers,
and blends of one or more of these. Polyethylenes found useful in forming the
subject composition include high density polyethylene (HDPE), low density
polyethylene (LDPE), linear low density polyethylene (LLDPE), ultra-low
density polyethylene (ULDPE) and the like as well as copolymers formed from
ethylene with one or more other lower alkenes (e.g., octene) and the like. </p><p num="0064">Compositions according to the invention particularly useful to form
films and the like may comprise a thermoplastic polymer as, for example,
polyethylene or copolymers of polyethylene such as, ethylene/vinyl acetate and
the like or polyethylene blends such as, blends of HDPE and butyl rubber;
polyethylene and ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer; as well as polyethylene
and styrene/butadiene/styrene block polymer and the like. The polyethylene, if
used, is preferably a low density polyethylene, and may be a very low or ultra
low density polyethylene which may be branched or linear. The ethylene/vinyl
acetate copolymer, if used, preferably has a melt index in the range 3 to 15,
preferably 5 to 10, and generally contains 5 to 40%, preferably 5 to 30%, vinyl
acetate.</p><p num="0065">Particularly preferred compositions for use as liners and the like for
semi-rigid packages (e.g., cans) are a plastisol or a dry blend of polymer.
These may be used in combination with a plasticizer for forming the polymer
matrix. Suitable materials for use when the compositions are plastisols include
vinyl chloride homopolymers and copolymers. Instead of preparing such
compositions as true plastisols, they may be provided as dry blends of the
polymer and plasticizer. The proportion of plasticizer present in a vinyl resin
plastisol may be any conventional proportion, typically from 30 to 150 weight
parts of plasticizer per hundred weight parts of vinyl resin.</p><p num="0066">The polymer carrier may be formed from various thermosetting resins
such as polyurethanes, phenolics, epoxy-ester resins, epoxy resins, polyesters
and alkyds. These resins are normally formed into solutions or suspensions
with organic liquids and applied to the inner surface of a container followed by
application of elevated temperature to remove the liquid and cause
solidification (e.g., by crosslinking) of the resin coating on the substrate.</p><p num="0067">The polymer matrix carrier of the subject composition may be selected
from those used to form coatings on at least a portion of the interior surface of
a package (e.g., a rigid container such as a can, can lid, box, carton, or the 
like). The polymer matrix can be selected from polymer classes commonly
referred to as epoxides, phenolics (e.g., phenol-formaldehyde condensation
polymer), lacquers (e.g., cellulose esters or ethers, shellac, alkyl resins and the
like), polyurethanes and the like. The carrier matrix may be mixed with the
components of the above described oxygen scavenger system to provide
encapsulated particulates which may be subsequently used in a second
polymer matrix or applied onto (such as by solvent or melt application) the
surface of a second carrier material.</p><p num="0068">Polymeric carriers used to form the composition may further contain
conventional plasticizers, including phthalates, adipates, glycols, citrates and
epoxidized oils and the like as, for example, dioctyl phthalate, diisooctyl
phthalate or diisodecyl phthalate, which are readily available. Other usable
plasticizers are butyl benzyl phthalate, acetyl tributyl citrate, ethyl diphenyl
phosphate and diisobutyl phthalate. One particularly useful combination of
plasticizers for use with a vinyl chloride/vinyl acetate copolymer resin is a
mixture of diisodecyl phthalate and diisooctyl phthalate in a weight ratio of
about 7-8:1.</p><p num="0069">In addition, the carriers of the invention may further contain inert filler,
slip aids, process aids, pigments, stabilizers, anti-oxidants, tackifying resins,
foaming agents and other conventional additives in conventional amounts,
depending upon the nature of the composition and its final use.</p><p num="0070">If the carrier comprises a thermoplastic polymer, the total amount of
such additives is generally below 10%, most preferably below 3%, based on
the total weight of the composition. However, when the carrier is in the form
of a plastisol, dispersion, organic solution or latex, the amounts of additives
based on total weight of the composition may be higher. When an anti-oxidant
is incorporated, it should be present in amounts capable of stabilizing the
polymeric composition against degradation due to free-radicals formed during
processing. However, the amount of anti-oxidant should be small enough to 
permit the subject modified HTLC/transition metal compound oxygen
scavenger system of the present composition to effectively react with
molecular oxygen. The specific amount will depend on the anti-oxidant used
and can be determined by minor experimentation. In certain instances, the
amount of filler normally used may be at least partially replaced by the
presently required solid particulate modified HTLC oxygen scavenging agent
which has been mixed, coated or ion-exchanged with the transition metal
compound, as described herein above.</p><p num="0071">A preferred aspect of the invention is that the oxygen scavenger system
should remain substantially inert in the composition and in the gasket or other
solid deposit formed with the subject composition until the composition is on
or in a sealed container. Exposure of the composition to high humidity that
normally exists within a sealed container will, therefore, result in sufficient
permeation of moisture into the composition and cause the subject oxygen
scavenger system to initiate oxygen scavenging to a high degree. This will
result in improved shelf life of the packaged material. In addition, the
scavenging reaction can be further accelerated by heating the composition
sufficiently while in the closed container to cause increased permeation of
moisture. Thus, the oxygen scavenger system will preferably remain
substantially inert in the carrier until the scavenging reaction is accelerated by
heating in the presence of moisture.</p><p num="0072">The scavenging reaction of the present composition can be accelerated
by pasteurizing (typically at 50°-100° C.) or sterilizing (typically at 100°-150°
C.) the container after filling it with an aqueous fill and sealing it. This
triggering appears to be a consequence of the subject composition, when
heated, permitting moisture to permeate into the composition and contact the
subject oxygen scavenger system. The moisture becomes trapped in the
composition, thereby bringing the scavenger system into contact with
sufficient water to permit reaction with the oxygen present. This oxygen may 
permeate through the composition either from oxygen trapped within the
container when it was filled or which subsequently enters the container from
the surrounding atmosphere.</p><p num="0073">While some conventional oxygen scavenging agents degrade when
subjected to elevated temperatures, the subject oxygen scavenger system has
been found to be stable to elevated temperatures commonly experienced in
processing polymers into films or coatings, removing solvents from plastisol
compositions, pasteurization, sterilization and the like processes commonly
encountered in packaging technology.</p><p num="0074">The composition of the invention may be formulated in any convenient
form, such as a melt extrusion, plastisol, organic solution, dry blend, latex or
dispersion. The main ingredients of the composition, apart from the oxygen
scavenger system and carrier, are normally typical of those conventionally
present for the intended purpose. It is preferred that the total composition
should be non-aqueous (i.e., an anhydrous solution, plastisol or thermoplastic
melt) so as to prevent initiation of the reaction of the scavenger within the
composition.</p><p num="0075">The subject composition can be utilized to form a film which carries
the present oxygen scavenger system. The carrier can be formed from a
polymeric material, such as those described herein above, capable of forming a
film and upon the surface thereof is deposited the present oxygen scavenger
composition. The film may be composed of a single layer or of a plurality of
layers. The surface of the film can be coated with the subject oxygen
scavenger composition by forming a suspension or dispersion of the
particulates in a polymer and depositing the suspension or dispersion by a
conventional means, such as spraying or knife coating application or the like,
directly onto the surface of the carrier film. The particular nature of the carrier
film will depend upon the application contemplated and the ability of the 
carrier formed to have the oxygen scavenger adhered to its surface and
substantially retain its integrity during use.</p><p num="0076">The carrier can, alternately, be in the form of a fibrous (woven or non-woven)
mat. The subject oxygen scavenger composition is contained in the
interstices of the mat structure. The fibers forming the mat may be formed
from any suitable material or synthetic fiber such as cotton, glass, nylon,
polyethylene, and copolymers of ethylene with one or more ethylenically
unsaturated monomer, polypropylene and copolymers of propylene with one or
more ethylenically unsaturated monomer and the like. The particular nature of
the carrier mat will depend upon the application of its use and the ability of the
mat to retain the cmponents of the oxygen scavenger system within the
interstices of the mat structure during use. The scavenger can be deposited
into the mat structure by any means such as by dipping the mat into a
dispersion or suspension of the scavenger system and then removing the liquid
from the mat or by first forming particulates of scavenger/polymer
composition which is melt deposited onto and into the mat structure.</p><p num="0077">In another embodiment, the subject oxygen scavenger system can be
retained within a carrier in the form of a pouch or sachet of suitable size to be
inserted in a container having an oxygen sensitive material therein. The pouch
or sachet should be sufficiently porous to permit moisture and oxygen to
penetrate through the pouch or sachet forming material at ambient temperature
conditions. The subject oxygen scavenger composition is thus composed of
the pouch or sachet carrier having therein the oxygen scavenger system, per se,
or contained in a polymer matrix and provided for in the form of small
particles of sufficient particulate size to permit the sachet structure to retain the
particulate therein. The pouch or sachet can be formed from natural or
synthetic materials such as paper, cotton cloth, polymer films and the like in
manners well known to the packaging technology. </p><p num="0078">A fourth embodiment is to utilize a carrier in the form of a porous
inorganic material, such as a ceramic having the present oxygen scavenger
system distributed therein. The ceramic can be formed into any desired shape
(e.g., spheres, cubes, cylinders and the like) and size which is suitable for
insertion into the container having the oxygen sensitive material. Useful
porous inorganic materials include conventional clay, cement pastes and the
like.</p><p num="0079">It has been found that the above described oxygen scavenger
compositions can be used for the preservation of oxygen sensitive foods stored
at ambient conditions. The present compositions have an advantage over those
compositions having oxygen scavengers directly mixed into and forming a
filler of a polymer matrix because the present compositions inhibit the release
of scavenger agent and/or oxidation by-products which may contaminate the
food material. The oxygen scavenger system of the present invention is
composed of particulate material that contains, as a part of its structure, a
moisture-triggerable oxygen scavenging moiety. It has been found that the
nature of the system is such that the oxygen scavenging moiety is highly
reactive with molecular oxygen yet is bound to the hydrotalcite in a manner
which substantially prevents migration of the oxygen scavenging moiety or its
oxidized product into the packaged material. Therefore, the present invention
unexpectedly provides a highly desired oxygen scavenger composition which
does not cause discoloration or detract from taste of the packaged food
product.</p><p num="0080">The amount of the subject oxygen scavenger agent containing
particulate is dependent on the type of application. When the particulate is
incorporated into a gasket, the amount is normally at least 0.5 weight percent
based on the polymeric matrix material, generally at least 1% and preferably at
least 2%. It is generally unnecessary for the amount to be above 20% and 4%-10%
is often a convenient maximum. </p><p num="0081">In the case of a plastisol, lacquer, or hot melt applied to the center
panel of a closure, where the matrix does not otherwise serve as a gasket,
scavenger particulate loadings can be much higher. For example, loadings of
20 weight percent to 60%, or in some cases up to 90% are workable.</p><p num="0082">When the composition is in the form of a film, mat, pouch or sachet,
the oxygen scavenger should be present in an amount to effectively scavenge
oxygen during the contemplated storage period of the container for the
appropriate contents. An amount in the range of from 0.01 to 2 grams of the
oxygen scavenging agent having at least about 60 mole percent oxygen
scavenging anion A is normally sufficient to provide desired oxygen
scavenging capacity in a normal size (50-1000 ml) container.</p><p num="0083">The present composition can be used as part of a package container
which can provide storage stability to the material packaged therein without
detracting from the material's taste, odor or smell. The present composition
should be exposed to the inner atmosphere of the resultant sealed container in
any form such as a coating on all or a part of the inner surface of the container
body or closure means (e.g., lid, can end) or as an insert in the form of a film,
mat, pouch, sachet or ceramic structure.</p><p num="0084">The composition of the invention in the form of a film can, for
example, be laminated to paperboard to form gable-top cartons. The film may
further comprise oxygen barrier layers and/or heat sealable layers.</p><p num="0085">The invention formed with a polymer carrier in the form of a film can
be applied as a center panel lining on a container closure. The closure can be a
cap, can end, lid stock or film. The invention also includes container closures
carrying a solid deposit formed on the closure from a polymer matrix or film
composition and that is positioned to seal around, or over a line of weakness
in, the closure. The solid deposit can be a gasket deposited around the closure
and formed from the composition. Instead of, or in addition to the deposit
being such a gasket, the composition can be deposited on the inner face of a 
closure at a position where there is a discontinuity or line of weakness around
a push or pull component for opening a container sealed by the closure. The
closure occupies, as is conventional, only a minor part of the exposed surface
area of the closed container, often less than 25% of the surface area. Thus, the
area of the solid deposit can be very small relative to the area of the container.
Despite this, the invention can give greatly improved storage stability to the
contents.</p><p num="0086">The invention also includes filled containers sealed with such closures.
The sealed container comprises a container body, the closure fitted on it, and
the packaged material that is contained within the container body. The
container body is preferably of glass or metal. The closure is preferably of
metal. The packaged material can be any beverage, foodstuff or other material
that is to be stored within the container but the invention is of particular value
when the filling is a material whose shelf-life or product quality is normally
restricted due to oxygen ingress or contamination during storage. The
container body can be a can, generally of metal, in which event the closure is a
can end. Generally the entire closure is of metal or polymeric material but the
panel of the closure can include a removable component of either metal or
polymeric material.</p><p num="0087">Instead of a can body, the container body can be a bottle or jar in which
event the closure is a cap. The bottle or jar is preferably of glass but it can be
of polymeric material with very low oxygen permeability. The cap can be of
polymeric material, for instance a polypropylene, that may include a barrier
layer. Generally, the cap is formed of metal and may include a push or pull
component of metal or polymeric material. The cap may be a crown cap such
as a pry-off or twist-off crown, a twist-on cap, lug cap, press-on/twist-off, or
press-on/pry-off cap, a screw-on cap, roll-on metal cap, continuous thread cap,
or any other conventional form of metal cap or polymeric cap suitable for
closing the bottle or jar. </p><p num="0088">A gasket is normally provided between the container body and the
closure. This gasket can be used to carry the composition of the invention (in
particular, as a polymer matrix containing composition) either as a blend in the
gasket composition or as a separate component applied on or near the gasket
but it is possible for the composition of the invention to be utilized elsewhere
on the closure or elsewhere in the container. In that event the gasket-forming
composition can be any unaltered conventional composition suitable for
forming the gasket.</p><p num="0089">When the closure is a cap, the subject scavenger composition may form
an overall gasket or a portion of an overall gasket. This is typically true for
small diameter caps such as those less than 50 mm in diameter. For large
diameter caps, the gasket is a ringlike gasket and may be deposited in a
conventional manner from the gasket-forming composition. For instance, a
ringlike gasket can be formed on a cap by being applied in liquid form as a
ring and can then be converted to solid form by drying, heating to cure or
cooling to set a thermoplastic, as appropriate. The oxygen scavenging
composition could be blended into the gasket material, deposited on the gasket
material, or applied to an area of the cap not covered by the gasket (the center
panel). The gasket-forming composition may, for this purpose, be a
dispersion, latex, plastisol, dry-blend, suitable thermoplastic composition or
organic solution. The cap, carrying the gasket, is then pressed on to an
appropriate sealing face around the open end of the filled container body and
closed in conventional manner.</p><p num="0090">If the composition is formed with a thermoplastic polymer matrix, it
may be applied as a low viscosity melt while the cap is spinning, so as to
throw the composition into the form of a ring, or it may be applied as a melt
which is then molded into the desired shape, often a disc having a thickened
ring-like portion. Further, the gasket can be in the form of a pre-formed ring 
or disc which is retained (e.g., by mechanical or adhesive means) within the
cap.</p><p num="0091">If the closure is a can end, the oxygen scavenging composition is
typically not used in the gasket composition because, under typical can
seaming conditions, the gasket is not substantially exposed to oxygen in the
pack. Also, the seams are not particularly vulnerable to oxygen ingress. The
oxygen scavenging composition is typically applied on a center panel or other
interior surface in the can, such as applied as a coating of a can.</p><p num="0092">It is particularly preferred that the gasket or coating on the container
closure be formed by applying a fluid or molten composition of the present
invention formed with a fluid polymer matrix and solidifying it on the closure.
The method of application and solidification is generally conventional. It is
particularly preferred that the container and can end should both be of metal or
the container body should be of glass and the closure of metal or plastic, since
the use of the defined compositions for forming the gasket then appears to give
particularly beneficial results. In particular, excellent results are achievable
when the container body is a glass bottle and the closure is a metal cap.</p><p num="0093">Instead of or in addition to using the fluid or meltable polymer matrix
composition of the invention for forming a gasket, it is possible to deposit the
composition elsewhere on the inner face of the closure. It may be applied as an
overall coating of the inner face of the panel of the closure or it may be applied
over only part of the inner face. In particular, when the panel includes one or
more push or pull components defined in the panel by discontinuities or lines
of weakness the composition may be applied primarily to cover just the
discontinuity or line of weakness. For instance one type of closure, usually a
can end, includes at least one, and often two, push components that are defined
by partial score lines through the metal panel such that finger pressure can
push a circular area of the panel into the container, so as to allow access to the
contents of the container. Thus there may be a small push component to allow 
release of pressure and a larger push component to allow pouring of liquid
from the container. Such a system is described in, for instance, DE 3,639,426.
In particular, the composition of the first embodiment of the present invention
may be deposited as an annulus (or a disc) covering the line of weakness. The
line of weakness may merely be a weakened line in the metal panel but it can
be a total cut around the push component, for instance as in DE 3,639,426, in
which event the push component generally has an area slightly larger than the
opening in the panel that is defined by the cut line and the composition of the
invention can then form a seal between the push component and the remainder
of the panel of the closure.</p><p num="0094">In all instances where push or pull components are to be formed within
a metal panel, there is a serious risk that the formation of the push or pull
components may damage the polymeric lacquer coating that is generally
present on the inner surface of the metal panel. This can expose the metal to
corrosion. Application of a composition of the present invention to a container
as described herein can both inhibit corrosion of the metal container as well as
improve storage stability of the contents of the container, especially water
bearing contents, such as beer.</p><p num="0095">In addition to use in metal, glass and plastic containers, the
compositions can be used in a cardboard or laminated container such as a juice
box. Such a container is a cardboard carton or tube with an interior liner. The
composition can be placed in or laminated to the interior liner of the cardboard
package, along a line of weakness at the package closure, or at any other
convenient location in the package. Alternately, the present composition can
be placed within the container as a film, mat or sachet.</p><p num="0096">Further, the composition of the present invention can be compounded
and extruded, injection molded or thermo-formed into desired shapes when the
polymer matrix is a thermoplastic resin. For example, the subject
compositions can be formed into films per se or as a component of a film 
composition used to prepare flexible packaging, such as bags, or the films can
be laminated onto metal stock which can then be formed into cans and
closures. Also, the compositions may be included in flexible packaging such
as multilayer films or laminates or as a ribbon, patch, label or coating on a
thermoplastic bag or lidstock. When the subject composition is part of a
multi-layer film, the layer formed of the present composition may be the
surface layer which will be exposed to the inner surface of the resultant
flexible package or an inner layer which is covered by a surface layer having
sufficient permeability to permit the O<sub>2</sub> and moisture to penetrate into and
contact the layer containing the present composition. Thus, the term "exposed
to the interior", as used herein and in the appended claims shall mean either
direct or indirect exposure of the subject composition to the inner atmosphere
of a sealed container having packaged product contained therein.</p><p num="0097">The compositions can also be used in conjunction with or as a portion
of a tamper-evident membrane for pharmaceuticals and foods.</p><p num="0098">The following examples are given for illustrative purposes only and are
not meant to be a limitation on the teaching herein or on the claims appended
hereto. All parts and percentages are by weight unless otherwise stated.</p><p num="0099">To test for oxygen scavenging capability, each sample was tested in
triplicate by being placed in gas impermeable, vacuum sealed containers fitted
with a septum to allow gas to be introduced and gas samples removed for
periodic analysis. Containers having a sample were injected with 100 cc of
room air (ca. 20.6% O<sub>2</sub>) and pasteurized at 60°C for 45 minutes and then
stored in the dark to avoid photo-oxidation. The headspace oxygen
concentration was measured at regular intervals by withdrawing samples
which were then analyzed using a MOCON® Model HS-750 Headspace
Oxygen Analyzer. All samples were prepared and tested in triplicate and the
data was averaged to obtain the reported values. </p><heading><u style="single">Example I</u></heading><heading>Preparation of bisulfite-functional hydrotalcite</heading><p num="0100">Under a nitrogen atmosphere, 45 parts of sodium bisulfite were
dissolved in 255 parts deionized water which had previously been purged with
argon. To this solution were added 20 parts of an uncalcined, carbonate-functional
hydrotalcite with a Mg/Al ratio of 1.0 ([Mg<sub>.5</sub>Al<sub>.5</sub>(OH)<sub>2</sub>](CO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>.25</sub>
·xH<sub>2</sub>0) (from Alcoa, HTC-10L). The slurry was stirred for 1 hour under argon
with heating to about 60 °C. The solids were then collected via vacuum
filtration under an argon atmosphere and washed with 600 parts deoxygenated,
nitrogen-purged water. The solids were then taken up in 300 parts argon
purged water and stirred for 1 hour before again filtering and washing with
1500 parts nitrogen-purged water. The product was dried in a vacuum oven at
80 °C for 6 hours to yield a fine white powder. This product was labeled
"HTLC/Bisulfite I".</p><heading><u style="single">Example II</u></heading><p num="0101">A series of samples were made by introducing 0.2 part of
HTLC/Bisulfite I of Example 1 into 3" by 4" gas impermeable pouches
followed by the addition of a transition metal salt in the amount indicated in
Table 1 below (all salt additions were equimolar in metal ion). The pouches
were fitted with septa and heat sealed under vacuum. To each pouch 0.2 part
water followed by 100 cc of air were introduced via the septa. The oxygen
content of each pouch was measured at regular intervals thereafter by
withdrawing 3 cc samples of the atmosphere in the pouches via gas syringe
and injecting into a MOCON® model HS 750 Headspace O<sub>2</sub> Analyzer.
Samples without added water were also monitored to test stability in air; these
dry samples showed no significant scavenging. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1"><b>Soluble Transition Metal Catalysts</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"><b>Run</b></entry><entry align="center" namest="2"><b>DESCRIPTION</b></entry><entry align="center" namest="3"><b>Salt Amount (g)</b></entry><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="4"><b>Oxygen Scavenging</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>1 hr. µ mol/g</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>1 day µ mol/g</b> </entry><entry align="center"><b>7 days µ mol/g</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Control</entry> <entry align="left">HTLC Bisulfite I</entry> <entry align="center">-</entry> <entry align="center">313 ± 0</entry><entry align="right">616 ± 61</entry><entry align="right">616 ± 62</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">Manganese (II) Sulfate Monohydrate</entry><entry align="center">0.011</entry><entry align="center">313 ± 45</entry><entry align="right">659 ± 44</entry><entry align="right">715 ± 25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">Iron (II) Sulfate Heptahydrate</entry><entry align="center">0.018</entry><entry align="center">372 ± 26</entry><entry align="right">682 ± 66</entry><entry align="right">766 ± 45</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">Iron(III) Sulfate Pentahydrate<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.032</entry><entry align="center">469 ± 22</entry><entry align="right">721 ± 77</entry><entry align="right">760 ± 80</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">Iron (II) Chloride Tetrahydrate</entry><entry align="center">0.013</entry><entry align="center">290 ± 67</entry><entry align="right">759 ± 63</entry><entry align="right">850 ± 58</entry></row><row><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">Iron (III) Chloride Hexahydrate</entry><entry align="center">0.017</entry><entry align="center">417 ± 13</entry><entry align="right">640 ± 38</entry><entry align="right">703 ± 43</entry></row><row><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="left">Nickel (II) Sulfate Hexahydrate</entry><entry align="center">0.017</entry><entry align="center">298 ± 47</entry><entry align="right">687 ± 55</entry><entry align="right">771 ± 70</entry></row><row><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="left">Copper (II) Sulfate Pentahydrate</entry><entry align="center">0.016</entry><entry align="center">253 ± 100</entry><entry align="right">549 ± 60</entry><entry align="right">787 ± 34</entry></row><row><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="left">Copper(I) Chloride</entry><entry align="center">0.006</entry><entry align="center">413 ± 16</entry><entry align="right">727 ± 30</entry><entry align="right">769 ± nd<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0102">The above data shows that the presence of transition metal salt
increased the oxygen activity and capacity of the anionic hydrotalcite to
provide improved oxygen scavenging systems.</p><heading><u style="single">Example III</u></heading><p num="0103">A series of samples were made in which a portion of the magnesium
ions of the hydrotalcite was ion exchanged with transition metal ions to
produce a transition metal ion rich anionic HTLC.</p><p num="0104">Under a nitrogen atmosphere, 1 part of a transition metal salt was
introduced into 85 parts deionized, argon purged water and stirred until
dissolved. To this solution 20 parts of an uncalcined carbonate-functional
hydrotalcite (Mg/Al ratio of 1.0; [Mg<sub>0.5</sub>Al<sub>0.5</sub>(OH)<sub>2</sub>](CO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>25</sub>·H<sub>2</sub>O] (HTC-10
Alcon) was added and the slurry was heated to 95°C for one hour while
stirring under argon. The slurry was allowed to cool to 40°C and then 15 parts 
of sodium bisulfite was added to the slurry. The slurry was again heated to
95°C and maintained at that temperature for one hour. The slurry was then
allowed to cool to room temperature. The slurry was vacuum filtered under a
nitrogen atmosphere and washed with 500 parts of nitrogen purged water to
remove magnesium salt by-product. The resultant moist solid was dried in a
vacuum oven at 80°C for about 6 hours. Table 2 below provides the identity
and amount of transition metal salt used, the ion exchanged product yield, and
the amount of transition metal (of the respective salt) and the sulfur (of the
bisulfite) analyzed by ICP.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><b>ICP Analysis</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>Description</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Tran. Metal Salt Used Part</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>HTLC/Bisulfite Trans. Metal Ion Product Parts</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Trans. Metal (Wt %)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>S (Wt %)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Manganese (II) Sulfate Monohydrate</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">17.4</entry><entry align="center">1.17 ± 0.07</entry><entry align="center">4.6 ± 0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Iron (II) Sulfate Heptahydrate</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">17.9</entry><entry align="center">0.70 ± 0.03</entry><entry align="center">4.6 ± 0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Iron(III) Sulfate Pentahydrate</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">17.0</entry><entry align="center">0.137 ± 0.003</entry><entry align="center">4.75 ± 0.09</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Iron (II) Chloride Tetrahydrate</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">17.4</entry><entry align="center">0.97 ± 0.02</entry><entry align="center">4.9 ± 0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Iron (III) Chloride Hexahydrate</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">0.136 ± 0.003</entry><entry align="center">4.64 ± 0.09</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Nickel (II) Sulfate Hexahydrate</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">17.4</entry><entry align="center">1.10 ± 0.02</entry><entry align="center">4.8 ± 0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Copper (II) Sulfate Pentahydrate</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">1.21 ± 0.02</entry><entry align="center">5.4 ± 0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Copper(I) Chloride</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">21.1</entry><entry align="center">2.68 ± 0.05</entry><entry align="center">7.7 ± 0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Copper (II) Chloride dihydrate</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">18.6</entry><entry align="center">1.69 ± 0.03</entry><entry align="center">5.4 ± 0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tin (II) Sulfate</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">18.4</entry><entry align="center">1.70 ± 0.03</entry><entry align="center">4.73 ± 0.09</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cobalt (II) Sulfate Hydrate<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">2.4</entry><entry align="center">227</entry><entry align="center">1.01 ± 0.02</entry><entry align="center">7.6 ± 0.2<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example IV</u></heading><heading>Preparation of bisulfite-functional hydrotalcite</heading><p num="0105">Under a nitrogen atmosphere, 90 parts of sodium bisulfite were
dissolved in 510 parts deionized water which had previously been purged of
oxygen with nitrogen. To this solution were added 100 parts of uncalcined
HTLC acetate, having a sheet-like morphology and the formula
[Mg<sub>.75</sub>Al<sub>.25</sub>(OH)<sub>2</sub>](O<sub>2</sub>CCH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>.25</sub>·xH<sub>2</sub>0 (obtained from LaRoche Industries,
Inc.). The slurry was stirred for 1 hour under nitrogen, and then the solids
were collected via vacuum filtration under a nitrogen atmosphere. The
material was taken up in 600 parts nitrogen-purged deionized water and stirred
for 1 hour. The solids were again collected via vacuum filtration and washed
with 6000 parts nitrogen-purged water. The material was dried for 9 hours at
80°C in a vacuum oven to yield approximately 60 parts of a fine white powder
labeled HTLC/Bisulfite II.</p><p num="0106">A series of oxygen scavenging systems were prepared from the above
HTLC/Bisulfite II by forming a physical mixture of the HTLC/Bisulfite II with
a cobalt compound in amounts indicated in Table III. The amount utilized was
based on the amount required to react with 20.6 cc oxygen in the test pouches.
In each case where the transition metal is part of the formed oxygen
scavenging system, the oxygen was rapidly consumed within the first hour of
testing. The results are given in Table III below. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1"><b>Soluble Co(II) Catalysis of Hydrotalcite (Bi)sulfite Oxidation</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center">Run</entry><entry align="left"><b>DESCRIPTION</b></entry><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>% of 1 week Capacity @ 1 hour</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>% of 1 week Capacity @ 1 day</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>CAPACITY @ 1 week</b> (mL O<sub>2</sub>/g)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Control</entry><entry align="left">HTLC/Bisulfite II</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">23</entry><entry align="right">95</entry><entry align="center">31.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">Sheet-like HTLC/Bisulfite CoSO<sub>4</sub></entry><entry align="left">II + 5%</entry><entry align="right">91</entry><entry align="right">98</entry><entry align="center">34.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">Sheet-like HTLC/Bisulfite CoSO<sub>4</sub></entry><entry align="left">II + 0.5%</entry><entry align="right">84</entry><entry align="right">96</entry><entry align="center">30.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">Sheet-like HTLC/Bisulfite B<sub>12</sub></entry><entry align="left">II + 5% Vit.</entry><entry align="right">73</entry><entry align="right">99</entry><entry align="center">31.1</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example V</u></heading><heading><b>Co:Al sheet-like hydrotalcite exchanged with bisulfite</b></heading><p num="0107">Example 6 from U.S. Patent 5,518,704 (Aristech Chemical
Corporation) was modified as follows. 15.13 g pseudoböhmite (Versal 700,
LaRoche) and 13.7 g acetic acid were slurried in 500 mL water in a 3 L flask
fitted with a condenser and then heated to 55 °C for 30 min. with stirring. 40.9
g Co(OH)<sub>2</sub> were added to the slurry followed by 1.5 L nitrogen-purged water.
The mixture was heated to 90 °C for 6 h. under argon and then allowed to cool
to ambient temperature. The slurry was extremely difficult to vacuum filter
and so was rotary evaporated at 60 °C to a thick sludge. A portion of this was
partially dried in a vacuum oven at 80 °C. 25 g of this crude product was
placed in an argon-purged solution of 22.5 g sodium metabisulfite in 127.5 g
water and stirred overnight. The slurry was vacuum filtered, rinsed with 1 L
water, and dried in a vacuum oven at 80 °C for 6 h. to yield 2.5 g of a purple
powder. </p><heading><u style="single">Example VI</u></heading><heading><b>Mg:Al:Co sheet-like hydrotalcite exchanged with bisulfite</b></heading><p num="0108">7.75 g pseudoböhmite (Versal 700, LaRoche) and 6.85 g acetic acid
were slurried in 500 ml water in a 3 L flask fitted with a condenser and then
heated to 55 °C for 30 min. with stirring. 8.41 g Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub> (MagChem-325,
Martin Magnesia Specialties) and 1.02 g Co(OH)<sub>2</sub> were added to the slurry
followed by 750 mL nitrogen-purged water. The mixture was heated to 90 °C
for 6 h. under argon and then allowed to cool to 40 °C. 36.0 g sodium bisulfite
were added and stirred for 1 h. After sitting overnight the slurry had partially
settled. It was easily vacuum filtered and washed with 2 L water. The yield of
purplish powder after drying in the vacuum oven at 80 °C for 6 h. was 19.4 g.</p><heading><u style="single">Example VII</u></heading><p num="0109">The ion exchanged samples of Examples V and VI were tested for
capacity to absorb oxygen according to the procedure of Example IV above.
The results showed very rapid scavenging of oxygen by the ion exchanged
materials as shown in Table IV below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1"><b>Co(II)-Containing Hydrotalcite Bisulfites with Sheet-like Morphology</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>DESCRIPTION</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>% of 1 week Capacity @ 1 hour</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>% of 1 week Capacity @ 1 day</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>CAPACITY @ 1 week</b> (mL O<sub>2</sub>/g)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Co:Al Sheet-like Hydrotalcite Bisulfite</entry><entry align="right">96</entry><entry align="right">100</entry><entry align="center">38.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mg:Co:Al Sheet-like Hydrotalcite Bisulfite</entry><entry align="right">97</entry><entry align="right">100</entry><entry align="center">21.9</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An oxygen scavenger composition comprising a carrier having
substantially uniformly distributed therein a combination of a hydrotalcite-like
material and a transition metal compound, said hydrotalcite-like material being
present in from 0.05 to 90 weight percent of said composition and represented
by the formula:
[ MII 1-xMIII x (OH)2 ] x+ MI y [ Aa- x+ya·nH2O ] (x+y)-
wherein MI represents an alkali metal selected from sodium or potassium; MII
represents magnesium, zinc, nickel, copper, cobalt and mixtures thereof; MIII
represents aluminum, chromium, iron and mixtures thereof; A represents an
anion, at least 60 mole percent of said anion composed of oxygen scavenger
anion selected from bisulfite, dithionite, ascorbate, thioilate, phenolate or
mixtures thereof; x is a numerical value of from about 0.1 to 0.5; a is an
average numerical value of the valence of A; y represents 0 when "a" is less
than 2 and a value of from 0 to 0.5 when "a" is at least 2; and n is a numerical
value of from 0 to 4;
<claim-text><claim-text>and said transition metal compound is present in an amount such that the molar
ratio of the hydrotalcite-like material to transition metal ion is from 3000:1 to 1:1.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein said transition metal
compound has a transition metal selected from Sc, Ti, V, Cr, Mn, Fe, Co, Ni,
Sn, Cu or mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 2 wherein the transition metal is
selected from Co, Cu, Fe or mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the oxygen scavenger
anion A is selected from ascorbate anion, thiolate anion, phenolate anion or
mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 2 wherein the oxygen scavenger
anion A is selected from ascorbate anion, thiolate anion, phenolate anion or
mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the oxygen scavenger
anion A is bisulfite, dithionate or mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 2 wherein the oxygen scavenger
anion A is bisulfite, dithionate or mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 4 wherein the oxygen scavenger
anion A is ascorbate anion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 5 wherein the oxygen scavenger
anion A is ascorbate anion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the carrier is a
thermoplastic resin selected from the group consisting of polyethylene,
ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymers, vinyl chloride homopolymers, vinyl
chloride copolymers and blends thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 5 wherein the carrier is a
thermoplastic resin selected from the group consisting of polyethylene,
ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymers, vinyl chloride homopolymers, vinyl
chloride copolymers and blends thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 7 wherein the carrier is a
thermoplastic resin selected from the group consisting of polyethylene,
ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymers, vinyl chloride homopolymers, vinyl
chloride copolymers and blends thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the carrier is a polymer
matrix comprising polyethylene selected from the group consisting of high,
low, very low, ultra low, and linear low density polyethylenes, blends thereof
and blends of said polyethylene with other polymers.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the carrier is a polymer
matrix comprising a mixture of at least one polyethylene and at least one
ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the carrier is a polymer
matrix comprising a polymer selected from the group consisting of polyolefin,
ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer, butyl rubber, styrene/butadiene rubber,
styrene/butadiene/styrene block copolymers, isoprene, styrene/isoprene/styrene
block copolymers styrene/ethylene/butylene/styrene block copolymers, and
mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the carrier is a polymeric
matrix comprising an epoxide, phenolic, polyurethane, polyvinyl chloride
homopolymer, polyvinyl chloride copolymers and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A product that is a container having an interior cavity suitable to
contain an oxygen sensitive material which has, as at least part of said
container and exposed to the interior of said container, the composition of
Claim 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A product that is a container having an interior cavity suitable to
contain an oxygen sensitive material which has, as at least part of said
container and exposed to the interior of said container, the composition of
Claim 2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A product that is a container having an interior cavity suitable to
contain an oxygen sensitive material which has, as at least part of said
container and exposed to the interior of said container, the composition of
Claim 5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>A product that is a container having an interior cavity suitable to
contain an oxygen sensitive material which has, as at least part of said
container and exposed to the interior of said container, the composition of
Claim 7.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="243" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="236" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>