<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1362841-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1362841" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="29268589" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20031119"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1362841-A1" status="new" fvid="23886540"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1362841</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20031119</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03252946-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03252946</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030512</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-6379502-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6379502</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020514</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  51/54        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  51/573       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C  51/573+65/24</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Isolierung von Dianhydriden</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Process to isolate dianhydrides</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour isoler des dianhydrides</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-3213166-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>3213166</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4318857-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4318857</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4340545-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4340545</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4584388-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4584388</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2003050165-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2003050165</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="E" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEN ELECTRIC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1 River Road</street><city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GUGGENHEIM THOMAS LINK</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MONGILIO DAVID ANTHONY</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GUGGENHEIM, THOMAS LINK</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MONGILIO, DAVID ANTHONY</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GUGGENHEIM, THOMAS LINK</last-name><address><street>7160 Upton Road</street><city>Mount Vernon, Indiana 47620</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MONGILIO, DAVID ANTHONY</last-name><address><street>11220 High Point Drive</street><city>Evansville, Insiana 47712</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Szary, Anne Catherine, Dr.</last-name><address><street>GE London Patent Operation, Essex House, 12-13 Essex Street</street><city>London WC2R 3AA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A process to isolate dianhydride from an exchange reaction comprises extracting a
bisimide/anhydride exchange reaction aqueous phase with an organic solution
comprising an exchange catalyst at a first temperature and pressure to form an
extracted aqueous phase comprising water, exchange catalyst and a dianhydride
precursor; removing water from the extracted aqueous phase at a second temperature
and pressure to form a molten phase, wherein the second pressure is less than the first
pressure; removing water and exchange catalyst from the molten phase at a third
temperature and pressure to form an isolation mixture; and converting the dianhydride
precursor in the isolation mixture to dianhydride at a fourth temperature and pressure,
wherein the fourth temperature is greater than the second and third temperatures and
the fourth pressure is less than the second and third pressures.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The disclosure relates to the isolation of dianhydrides. In particular, the disclosure
relates to the isolation of dianhydrides with low color.</p><p num="0002">Polymers such as polyetherimide are most desirably colorless or very light colored
(have low color). Polyetherimide is typically produced by reacting dianhydrides with
diamines. It is therefore desirable that the dianhydrides and diamines have low color
in order to produce polyetherimide with low color.</p><p num="0003">A process to isolate dianhydride from an exchange reaction comprises extracting a
bisimide/anhydride exchange reaction aqueous phase with an organic solution
comprising an exchange catalyst at a first temperature and pressure to result in an
extracted aqueous phase comprising water, exchange catalyst and a dianhydride
precursor; removing water from the extracted aqueous phase at a second temperature
and pressure to form a molten phase wherein the second pressure is less than the first
pressure; removing water and exchange catalyst from the molten phase at a third
temperature and pressure to form an isolation mixture; and converting the dianhydride
precursor in the isolation mixture to dianhydride at a fourth temperature and pressure,
wherein the fourth temperature is greater than the second and third temperatures and
the fourth pressure is less than the second and third pressures.</p><p num="0004">In another aspect, a process to isolate dianhydride from an exchange reaction
comprises extracting a bisimide/anhydride exchange reaction aqueous phase with an
organic solution comprising an exchange catalyst at a first temperature and pressure to
form an extracted aqueous phase comprising water, exchange catalyst and dianhydride
precursor; feeding the extracted aqueous phase to a flash vessel operated at a second
temperature and pressure to form a molten phase; feeding the molten phase to a falling
film evaporator operated at a third temperature and pressure to produce an isolation
mixture having an exchange catalyst to dianhydride precursor ratio of about 0.4 to
about 0.8; converting the dianhydride precursor in the isolation mixture to dianhydride
in a wiped film evaporator at a fourth temperature and pressure. </p><p num="0005">In another aspect, a system for dianhydride isolation comprises a flash vessel that
receives an extracted aqueous phase from an extraction column and forms a molten
phase, a falling film evaporator in fluid communication with a first outlet of the flash
vessel, wherein the falling film evaporator receives the molten phase from the flash
vessel and forms an isolation mixture; and a wiped film evaporator in fluid
communication with a first outlet of the falling film evaporator, wherein the wiped
film evaporator receives the isolation mixture from the falling film evaporator and
comprises a first outlet for collection of the isolated dianhydride.</p><p num="0006">The invention will now be described in more detail, by way of example, with
reference to Figure 1 which is a schematic representation of a system for the isolation
of dianhydride.</p><p num="0007">A process to isolate dianhydride from an exchange reaction comprises extracting a
bisimide/anhydride exchange reaction aqueous phase with an organic solution
comprising an exchange catalyst at a first temperature and pressure to form an
extracted aqueous phase comprising water, exchange catalyst and dianhydride
precursor. A majority of the water is then removed from the extracted aqueous phase
at second temperature and pressure to form a molten phase, preferably in a flash
vessel. The molten phase is then subjected to reduced pressure (a vacuum) at a third
temperature, preferably in a falling film evaporator, to remove catalyst, water and
optionally residual starting materials, and form an isolation mixture. The dianhydride
precursor in the isolation mixture is then converted to dianhydride at a fourth
temperature under further reduced pressure, preferably in a wiped film evaporator.
This process can be performed batchwise or in a continuous manner. Preferably the
process is continuous.</p> <p num="0008">The conditions of isolation of the dianhydride, namely the separation of the precursor
from the exchange reaction and its subsequent conversion to dianhydride can have a
significant effect on the color of the isolated dianhydride. Factors that contribute to
the development of color in the dianhydride include the residence time of the
dianhydride precursor(s) at elevated temperatures, in that long precursor residence
times can result in highly colored dianhydride. Unexpectedly it has been discovered 
by the inventors hereof that by reducing the amount of catalyst in the isolation mixture
prior to converting the dianhydride precursor to dianhydride, dianhydride with
significantly less color can be produced, even with increased residence time at
elevated temperatures.</p><p num="0009">In another embodiment, the process to isolate dianhydride from an exchange reaction
proceeds wholly or partially in the absence of air. The exposure of the catalyst to air
in the presence of the dianhydride precursor at elevated temperatures can increase the
color of the dianhydride. Without being bound by theory, it is thought that exposure
of the exchange catalyst to air at elevated temperatures results in a reactive
intermediate that, in turn, reacts with the dianhydride precursor or dianhydride to form
highly colored impurities.</p><p num="0010">Dianhydrides are typically produced by the exchange reaction shown in Scheme I
below. Molten bismide 1 is combined with phthalic anhydride 2 in the presence of
water and an exchange catalyst. The exchange reaction produces phthalimide 3 and a
precursor of the dianhydride such as the tetra acid salt 4.
<img id="img-00030001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030001.tif" inline="no" he="63"/></p><p num="0011">The dianhydride precursor is subsequently converted to dianhydride 5.
<img id="img-00030002" orientation="unknown" wi="60" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030002.tif" inline="no" he="32"/></p><p num="0012">The divalent bonds of the -K- group are in the 3,3', 3,4', 4,3', or the 4,4' positions, and K
includes O, S, SO<sub>2</sub> and O-W-O wherein W includes, but is not limited, to divalent
radicals of formula (I).
<img id="img-00040001"  orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif"  inline="no"  he="22"/><img id="img-00040002"  orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040002.tif" inline="no" he="16"/><img id="img-00040003" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040003.tif" inline="no" he="27"/><img id="img-00040004" orientation="unknown" wi="65" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040004.tif" inline="no" he="25"/>
and
<img id="img-00040005" orientation="unknown" wi="84" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040005.tif" inline="no" he="25"/>
wherein Q includes but is not limited to a divalent moiety selected from the group
consisting of -O-, -S-, -C(O)-, -SO<sub>2</sub>-, -SO-, -C<sub>y</sub>H<sub>2y</sub>- (y being an integer from 1 to 5),
and halogenated derivatives thereof, including perfluoroalkylene groups. A preferred
dianhydride is 2,2-bis(4-(3,4-dicarboxyphenoxy)phenyl)propane dianhydride.</p> <p num="0013">R is a monovalent organo radical selected from the group consisting of C<sub>1-8</sub> alkyl
radicals and C<sub>6-13</sub> aromatic radicals. Y represents a positive ion, the identity of which
is not particularly limited. Typically Y is the protonated form of the exchange
catalyst.</p> <p num="0014">Exchange catalysts include, but are not limited to, C<sub>1-20</sub> trialkylamines. A preferred
exchange catalyst is triethylamine. The exchange catalyst used in the exchange
reaction as described above and the exchange catalyst present in the extraction column 
may be the same trialkylamine or different trialkylamines. Preferably they are the
same.</p> <p num="0015">In the exchange reaction molten bisimide is typically combined with about 3 to about
8 molar excess of molten anhydride in the presence of about 60 to about 80 weight
percent (wt %) water based on the total weight of the reaction mixture water and about
0.5 to about 15 mole percent (mol%) of exchange catalyst with respect to anhydride at
about 150 to about 210°C. The exchange reaction is agitated for about 0.5 to about 3
hours. It has been observed that when the exchange reaction is run in a liquid full
reactor and the reactants are added to the top of the reactor, a layer comprising mostly
exchange catalyst can form. Formation of the exchange catalyst layer effectively
removes catalyst from the reaction, causing a significant decrease in the production of
dianhydride precursor. It is therefore preferable for the reactants to be added to the
bottom of the reactor. When the reactants are added to the bottom of the reactor, no
exchange catalyst layer forms and all of the exchange catalyst is available to
participate in the reaction.</p><p num="0016">The precursor of the dianhydride resulting from the exchange reaction is resident in
the aqueous phase. As will be appreciated by one of ordinary skill in the art, one
dianhydride precursor is a tetra acid and may be present as such, or any number of the
acid groups may be deprotonated and present in salt form. It is believed that a mixture
of protonated and deprotonated species is present in the aqueous phase. The aqueous
phase may also contain phthalic anhydride in salt form.</p><p num="0017">The aqueous phase resulting from the exchange reaction is extracted with an organic
solution containing an exchange catalyst, preferably in an extraction column. The
aqueous phase is contacted with the organic solution for about 1 to about 3, preferably
about 1 to about 2, and more preferably about 1 to about 1.5 hours. The catalyst is
present in the organic solution to convert any exchange reaction intermediate products
to dianhydride precursor. Extraction preferably occurs at first temperature of about
135 to about 190°C and a first pressure of about 3,000 to about 17,000 torr, preferably
about 10,000 to about 12,000 torr, to facilitate the conversion of intermediates. The
organic solution typically contains about 1 to about 7, preferably about 2 to about 5 
and more preferably about 3 to about 4 wt% catalyst, based on the total weight of the
organic solution. Suitable organic solvents for use in the organic solution include, but
are not limited to, alkyl benzenes with alkyl groups having from 1 to 5 carbons,
benzene, and halogenated aromatics. When using an extraction column, the aqueous
phase from the exchange reaction is typically fed into the top of the extraction column
while the organic solution is fed into the bottom of the exchange column.</p><p num="0018">After extraction the aqueous phase is subjected to a second temperature and pressure
to remove water, preferably in a flash vessel, to form a molten phase, typically for
about 60 to about 120 minutes. Useful pressures are less than about 1050, preferably
less than about 850 and more preferably less than or equal to about 800 torr but
greater than or equal to about 300 torr. The second pressure is less than the first
pressure. Useful temperatures are about 100 to about 180, preferably about 140 to
about 160, and more preferably about 145 to about 155°C. After removal the water
may then be condensed. The condensed water may then be chilled and used in the
condensers associated with later water and/or catalyst removal as described below or
recycled back to the exchange reaction.</p><p num="0019">The molten phase is subjected to a third temperature and pressure for about 5 to about
30 minutes to remove catalyst, additional water and optionally residual starting
materials such as phthalic anhydride to form an isolation mixture that has a catalyst to
dianhydride precursor ratio of about 0.4 to about 0.8, preferably about 0.5 to about 0.7
and more preferably about 0.6 to about 0.65. Useful temperatures are less than about
260, preferably less than about 220 and more preferably less than about 200°C.
Additionally, the temperature is greater than about 150, preferably greater than about
170 and more preferably greater than about 180°C. Useful pressures are less than
about 400, preferably less than about 200 and more preferably less than about 150
torr. The pressure is greater than about 30, preferably greater than about 50 and more
preferably greater than about 100 torr.</p><p num="0020">In a preferred embodiment, the molten phase is fed to a falling film evaporator. As
readily understood by one of ordinary skill in the art, the number of tubes, the length
of the tubes and the diameter of the tubes contained in the falling film evaporator 
determines the overall surface area for the formation of the film and hence relates to
the rate at which the volatile materials are removed, primarily residual water, catalyst
and optionally residual starting materials such as phthalic anhydride. It is well within
the skill of one with ordinary skill in the art to match the surface area of the falling
film evaporator to the desired flow rate of the process stream in a continuous process
and to desired extent of water and catalyst removal. The volatile materials are
preferably taken overhead to a condenser, such as a chilled spray condenser, wherein
the volatile material is condensed through the use of a chilled spray. When the
condensed material contains phthalic anhydride it is typically present in salt form.
The condensed material itself may then be chilled in a heat exchanger and used as the
spray in the same spray condenser, another spray condenser or recycled for use in the
exchange reaction.</p><p num="0021">The falling film evaporator is maintained at a reduced pressure of less than about 400,
preferably less than about 200 and more preferably less than about 150 torr. The
pressure of the falling film evaporator is greater than about 30, preferably greater than
about 50 and more preferably greater than about 100 torr. The temperature of the oil
heating the tubes of the falling film evaporator is less than about 260, preferably less
than about 220 and more preferably less than about 200°C. Additionally, the
temperature of the oil in the falling film evaporator tubes is greater than about 150,
preferably greater than about 170 and more preferably greater than about 180°C. The
temperature of the falling film evaporator is preferably less than the temperature of the
wiped film evaporator.</p><p num="0022">The isolation mixture is subjected to a fourth temperature and pressure for typically
about 5 to about 30 minutes to convert the dianhydride precursor to dianhydride. The
amount of time as well as the temperature is generally dependent upon the identity of
the dianhydride and is readily determined by one of ordinary skill in the art.
Generally, useful temperatures are less than about 350, preferably less than about 310
and more preferably less than about 295°C. The fourth temperature is typically greater
than about 250, more preferably greater than about 270, and most preferably greater
than about 275°C. Useful pressures are less than about 50, preferably less than about
30 and more preferably less than about 25 torr. The fourth pressure is greater than 
about 5, preferably greater than about 10 and more preferably greater than about 20
torr. The conversion of the dianhydride precursors to dianhydride is a cyclization with
the concurrent formation of water. Advantageously, trace water, catalyst, and other
residual volatile materials such as phthalic anhydride are also removed as vapor under
the conditions required for conversion.</p><p num="0023">In a preferred embodiment, the conversion of the dianhydride precursor proceeds in a
wiped film evaporator. The oil temperature of the wiped film evaporator is
maintained at a temperature less than about 350, preferably less than about 310 and
more preferably less than about 295°C. The oil temperature of the wiped film
evaporator is greater than about 250, more preferably greater than about 270, and most
preferably greater than about 275°C. The wiped film evaporator is maintained at a
reduced pressure of less than about 50, preferably less than about 30 and more
preferably less than about 25 torr. The pressure of the wiped film evaporator is
greater than about 5, preferably greater than about 10 and more preferably greater than
about 20 torr.</p><p num="0024">The volatile materials removed in the wiped film evaporator are taken to a chilled
spray condenser operated in a manner similar to that described above for the chilled
spray condenser associated with the falling film evaporator. Material condensed in
the spray condenser associated with the falling film evaporator may be chilled and
used in the spray condenser associated with the wiped film evaporator.</p><p num="0025">Use of the above described process results in dianhydride with low color. Color may
be quantified by the yellowness index as determined according to ASTM D1925.
Dianhydride produced by the above described method, on a commercial scale, has a
yellowness index of about 5 to about 8 with an average of about 6, a decrease of about
3 units when compared to dianhydride produced by prior art methods. Without being
bound by theory, it is believed that the reduction of the yellowness index results from
the removal of a greater amount of exchange catalyst from the precursor containing
mixture before exposure to the high temperatures of the wiped film evaporator than
has previously been possible. The dianhydride isolated using the above-described
process has a catalyst content of less than about 50, preferably less than about 35 and 
more preferably less than about 20 parts per million (ppm). In contrast, dianhydride
isolated by prior art methods has an average triethylamine content of about 50 to about
100 ppm and the triethylamine content is difficult to control.</p><p num="0026">Figure 1 is a schematic representation of a system for the isolation of dianhydride. In
Figure 1, the extracted aqueous phase from the extraction column is passed through
heat exchanger 2 and fed to flash vessel 4. In flash vessel 4 water and optionally some
exchange catalyst are removed as a vapor, affording a molten product phase
comprising dianhydride precursor. The water vapor from flash vessel 4 is received by
condenser 6 where it is condensed into water and collected in an accumulator 8. Flash
vessel 4 is in fluid connection with falling film evaporator 10 which receives the
molten phase from flash vessel 4. Flash vessel 4 may optionally have a recycle stream
12 that is fed through a heat exchanger 14 before returning to the flash vessel. In
falling film evaporator 10 exchange catalyst, further water and optionally phthalic
anhydride are removed as vapor to form an isolation mixture. The exchange catalyst
and water vapor mixture is received by chilled spray condenser 16 where it is
condensed to a liquid phase that is optionally recycled via recycle stream 18. The
optional recycle stream 18 passes through chiller 20. Wiped film evaporator 22 is in
fluid communication with falling film evaporator 10 and receives the isolation
mixture. The isolation mixture comprises dianhydride precursors which are converted
to dianhydride in the wiped film evaporator 22. Trace water, some residual exchange
catalyst as well as other residual volatile materials are removed as a vapor from the
isolation mixture in the wiped film evaporator. The vapor from the wiped film
evaporator is received by chilled spray condenser 24, which is in fluid communication
with the wiped film evaporator. Chilled spray condenser 24 condenses the vapor from
the wiped film evaporator to a liquid phase which may be recycled to the chilled spray
condenser via recycle stream 26 that passes through chiller 28 or employed in the
bisimide/anhydride exchange reaction. Dianhydride is collected from an outlet in the
wiped film evaporator.</p><p num="0027">The invention is further illustrated by the following non-limiting examples. </p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0028">Laboratory studies were conducted to simulate the isolation of dianhydride with flash
vessel and wiped film evaporator as well as a flash vessel, falling film evaporator and
wiped film evaporator. The laboratory set up constituted a flask placed in a gas
chromatography oven. The flask was attached to a glass dual bulb Kugelrohr type
extension located outside the GC oven by a glass extension piece. The dual bulb was
attached to a Kugelrohr oscillating drive and a vacuum pump. The dual bulb was
cooled by a dry ice/methylene chloride bath.</p><p num="0029">The flask was charged with aqueous effluent from the plant aqueous extraction
column and a slight vacuum was applied to the flask as the flask was oscillated. The
vacuum was lowered slowly until a full vacuum was obtained (about 0.5 torr or less).
Once a full vacuum was established one of two temperature programs were initiated in
the gas chromatography oven. Program A simulated an isolation process employing a
flash vessel and a wiped film evaporator (control). Program B simulated an isolation
process employing a flash vessel, falling film evaporator and wiped film evaporator.
At the conclusion of each temperature program the oven door was opened and the
flask was allowed to cool while still oscillating. The dianhydride, 2,2-bis(4-(3,4-dicarboxyphenoxy)phenyl)propane
dianhydride, was removed from the flask and
tested for yellowness according to ASTM D1925. Results from duplicate runs are
shown in Table 1. <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Experiment No.</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Temperature/Time Program</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Yellowness Index</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">1<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">A</entry><entry align="center">7.64</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">A</entry><entry align="center">7.76</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">A</entry><entry align="center">8.54</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">A</entry><entry align="center">7.87</entry></row><row><entry align="left">5<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">A</entry><entry align="center">7.54</entry></row><row><entry align="left">6<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">A</entry><entry align="center">7.92</entry></row><row><entry align="left">7<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">A</entry><entry align="center">8.79</entry></row><row><entry align="left">8<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">A</entry><entry align="center">8.04</entry></row><row><entry align="left">std dev =</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.41</entry></row><row><entry align="left">mean =</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">8.01</entry></row><row><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="left">B</entry><entry align="center">7.64</entry></row><row><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">B</entry><entry align="center">7.26</entry></row><row><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="left">B</entry><entry align="center">7.47</entry></row><row><entry align="left">std dev =</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.19</entry></row><row><entry align="left">mean =</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">7.46<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0030">Following laboratory experimentation, a falling film evaporator was installed in the
plant and operated as described above for the preferred embodiments. The average
yellowness index of the isolated dianhydride decreased 3 units after installation of the
falling film evaporator in the plant. The larger decrease in the yellowness index of the
dianhydride produced in the plant when compared to the yellowness index of the 
dianhydride produced in the lab can be ascribed to the decreased incidence of air in
the plant compared to the laboratory conditions.</p><p num="0031">While preferred embodiments have been shown and described, various modifications
and substitutions may be made thereto without departing from the scope of the
invention. Accordingly, it is to be understood that the present invention has been
described by way of illustration and not limitations.</p><p num="0032">For completeness various aspects of the invention are set out in the following
numbered clauses:
<sl><li>1. A process to isolate dianhydride from an exchange reaction comprising
extracting a bisimide/anhydride exchange reaction aqueous phase with an organic
solution comprising an exchange catalyst at a first temperature and pressure to form
an extracted aqueous phase comprising water, exchange catalyst and dianhydride
precursor;

removing water from the extracted aqueous phase at a second temperature and
pressure to form a molten phase wherein the second pressure is less than the first
pressure;

removing water and exchange catalyst from the molten phase at a third temperature
and pressure to form an isolation mixture; and

converting the dianhydride precursor in the isolation mixture to dianhydride at a
fourth temperature and pressure, wherein the fourth temperature is greater than the
second and third temperatures and the fourth pressure is less than the second and third
pressures.</li><li>2. The process of clause 1, wherein the dianhydride has the formula
<img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="28"/> 
wherein the divalent bonds of -K- group are in the 3,3', 3,4', 4,3', or the 4,4' positions,
and K includes O, S, SO<sub>2</sub>, and O-W-O wherein W is a divalent radical of formula (I)
<img id="img-00130001" orientation="unknown" wi="110" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="21"/><img id="img-00130002" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130002.tif" inline="no" he="17"/><img id="img-00130003" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130003.tif" inline="no" he="27"/><img id="img-00130004" orientation="unknown" wi="65" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130004.tif" inline="no" he="25"/>
and
<img id="img-00130005" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130005.tif" inline="no" he="27"/>
wherein Q is a divalent moiety selected from the group consisting of -O-, -S-, -C(O)-,
-SO<sub>2</sub>-, -SO-, -C<sub>y</sub>H<sub>2y</sub>-, and halogenated derivatives thereof, and further wherein y is an
integer from 1 to 5.</li><li>3. The process of clause 2, wherein the dianhydride is 2,2-bis(4-(3,4-dicarboxyphenoxy)phenyl)propane
dianhydride.</li><li>4. The process of any of the preceding clauses, wherein the exchange catalyst is
triethylamine.</li><li>5. The process any of the preceding clauses, wherein the second temperature is
about 100 to about 180°C and the second pressure is about 300 to about 1050 torr.</li><li>6. The process any of the preceding clauses, wherein the third temperature is
about 150 to about 260°C and the third pressure is about 30 to about 400 torr. </li><li>7. The process any of the preceding clauses, wherein the fourth temperature is
about 250 to about 350°C and the fourth pressure is about 5 to about 50 torr.</li><li>8. The process any of the preceding clauses, wherein the isolation mixture has an
exchange catalyst to dianhydride ratio of about 0.4 to about 0.8.</li><li>9. The process any of the preceding clauses, wherein the dianhydride has an
average yellowness index of about 6.</li><li>10. The process any of the preceding clauses, wherein the process is performed
wholly or partially in the absence of air.</li><li>11. The process any of the preceding clauses, further comprising removing
anhydride from the molten phase at the third temperature and pressure.</li><li>12. A system for dianhydride isolation comprising

a flash vessel 4 that receives an extracted aqueous phase from an extraction column
and forms a molten phase;

a falling film evaporator 10 in fluid communication with a first outlet of the flash
vessel 4, wherein the falling film evaporator 10 receives the molten phase from the
flash vessel 4 and forms an isolation mixture; and

a wiped film evaporator 22 in fluid communication with a first outlet of the falling
film evaporator 10, wherein the wiped film evaporator 22 receives the isolation
mixture from the falling film evaporator 10 and further wherein the wiped film
evaporator 22 comprises a first outlet for collection of isolated dianhydride.</li><li>13. The system of Clause 12, wherein the system further comprises a first heat
exchanger 2 disposed at an inlet of the flash vessel 4.</li><li>14. The system of Clauses 12 or 13, wherein the system further comprises a
condenser 6 disposed at a second outlet of the flash vessel 4 that receives an aqueous
phase from the flash vessel 4. </li><li>15. The system of Clauses 12-14, further comprising a recycle stream 18 at the
flash vessel 4 wherein the recycle stream 18 flows through a second heat exchanger
14.</li><li>16. The system of Clauses 12-15, further comprising a recycle stream 18 at the
falling film evaporator 10.</li><li>17. The system of Clauses 12-16, further comprising a first chilled spray
condenser 16 disposed at a second outlet of said falling film evaporator 10.</li><li>18. The system of Clause 17, further comprising a second chilled spray condenser
24 disposed at a second outlet of the wiped film evaporator 22 wherein the second
chilled spray condenser 24 receives and utilizes condensate from the first chilled spray
condenser 16.</li><li>19. The system of Clauses 12-18, further comprising a second chilled spray
condenser 24 disposed at a second outlet of the wiped film evaporator 22.</li><li>20. The system of Clause 12-19, wherein the first chilled spray condenser 16
receives and utilizes condensate from the condenser 6.</li><li>21. The system of Clause 12-20, wherein the system is operated wholly or partially
in the absence of air.</li></sl></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process to isolate dianhydride from an exchange reaction comprising
extracting a bisimide/anhydride exchange reaction aqueous phase with an organic
solution comprising an exchange catalyst at a first temperature and pressure to form
an extracted aqueous phase comprising water, exchange catalyst and dianhydride
precursor;
removing water from the extracted aqueous phase at a second temperature and
pressure to form a molten phase wherein the second pressure is less than the first
pressure;
removing water and exchange catalyst from the molten phase at a third temperature
and pressure to form an isolation mixture; and
converting the dianhydride precursor in the isolation mixture to dianhydride at a
fourth temperature and pressure, wherein the fourth temperature is greater than the
second and third temperatures and the fourth pressure is less than the second and third
pressures.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, wherein the dianhydride has the formula

wherein the divalent bonds of -K- group are in the 3,3', 3,4', 4,3', or the 4,4' positions, and
K includes O, S, SO2, and O-W-O wherein W is a divalent radical of formula (I)
and

wherein Q is a divalent moiety selected from the group consisting of -O-, -S-, -C(O)-,
-SO2-, -SO-, -CyH2y-, and halogenated derivatives thereof, and further wherein y is an
integer from 1 to 5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The process of claim 1 or claim 2, wherein the exchange catalyst is
triethylamine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The process any of the preceding claims, wherein the second temperature is
about 100 to about 180°C and the second pressure is about 300 to about 1050 torr.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The process any of the preceding claims, wherein the third temperature is
about 150 to about 260°C and the third pressure is about 30 to about 400 torr.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The process any of the preceding claims, wherein the fourth temperature is
about 250 to about 350°C and the fourth pressure is about 5 to about 50 torr.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The process any of the preceding claims, wherein the isolation mixture has an
exchange catalyst to dianhydride ratio of about 0.4 to about 0.8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The process any of the preceding claims, wherein the process is performed
wholly or partially in the absence of air.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The process any of the preceding claims, further comprising removing
anhydride from the molten phase at the third temperature and pressure.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A system for dianhydride isolation comprising
a flash vessel 4 that receives an extracted aqueous phase from an extraction column
and forms a molten phase;
a falling film evaporator 10 in fluid communication with a first outlet of the flash
vessel 4, wherein the falling film evaporator 10 receives the molten phase from the
flash vessel 4 and forms an isolation mixture; and
a wiped film evaporator 22 in fluid communication with a first outlet of the falling
film evaporator 10, wherein the wiped film evaporator 22 receives the isolation
mixture from the falling film evaporator 10 and further wherein the wiped film
evaporator 22 comprises a first outlet for collection of isolated dianhydride.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>