<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1288022-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1288022" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="19082749" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030305"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1288022-A1" status="new" fvid="23674623"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1288022</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030305</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02018277-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02018277</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020822</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2001254608-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2001254608</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010824</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C   1/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C   9/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C   9/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/103       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60C   1/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   3/00P5+L7/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/103+L7/00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Öko-Reifen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Eco tire</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Pneu écologique</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0794073-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0794073</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0943466-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0943466</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0988999-A2"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0988999</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1074582-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1074582</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-1166846-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>1166846</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SUMITOMO RUBBER IND</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SUMITOMO RUBBER INDUSTRIES LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SUMITOMO RUBBER INDUSTRY, LTD.</last-name><address><street>6-9, Wakinohama-cho, 3-chome, Chuo-ku</street><city>Kobe-shi, Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HOCHI KAZUO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HORIGUCHI TAKUYA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KIKUCHI NAOHIKO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HOCHI, KAZUO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HORIGUCHI, TAKUYA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KIKUCHI, NAOHIKO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hochi, Kazuo, Sumitomo Rubber Industries, Ltd.</last-name><address><street>6-9, 3-chome, Wakinohama-cho, Chuo-ku</street><city>Kobe-shi, Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Horiguchi, Takuya Sumitomo Rubber Industries, Ltd.</last-name><address><street>6-9, 3-chome, Wakinohama-cho, Chuo-ku</street><city>Kobe-shi, Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kikuchi, Naohiko, Sumitomo Rubber Industries, Ltd.</last-name><address><street>6-9, 3-chome, Wakinohama-cho, Chuo-ku</street><city>Kobe-shi, Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Manitz, Finsterwald &amp;amp; Partner GbR</last-name><address><street>Postfach 31 02 20</street><city>80102 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook> </agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country> <country>GB</country> </ep-contracting-states> </designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An earth-friendly tire using raw materials derived from non-petroleum
resources instead of all or part of raw materials derived from
petroleum resources currently used for tires.The tire is prepared by
using a natural rubber instead of a synthetic rubber; an inorganic filler
and/or a biofiller instead of carbon black; vegetable oil instead of
petroleum oil; and natural fiber instead of synthetic fiber so that the tire
comprises a non-petroleum raw material in an amount of at least 75 %
by weight based on the total weight of the tire.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to an eco tire comprising raw
materials derived from non-petroleum resources.</p><p num="0002">More than half of the whole weight of a tire on the market
today is made of raw materials derived from petroleum resources. For
example, a common radial tire for automobiles is made of about 20 % by
weight of a synthetic rubber, about 20 % by weight of carbon black
based on the total weight of a tire, and other components such as an
aromatic oil and a synthetic fiber, which means that such a tire contains
more than 50 % of petroleum raw materials based on the total weight.</p><p num="0003">However, it seems that there is a limit for using raw materials
derived from petroleum resources considering recent serious interests to
ecological problems and CO<sub>2</sub> emission control, as well as forecasted
rising of petroleum price caused by limited reserve and declining
production of petroleum.</p><p num="0004">In view of the above problems, an object of the present
invention is to provide an eco tire by using raw materials derived from
non-petroleum resources instead of all or part of conventional raw
materials for tire derived from petroleum resources.</p><p num="0005">That is, the present invention relates to a tire comprising a
raw material derived from non-petroleum resources in an amount of at
least 75 % by weight based on the total weight of the tire.</p><p num="0006">It is preferable to use a natural rubber, an inorganic filler 
and/or biofiller, a vegetable oil, and a natural fiber as raw a material
derived from non-petroleum resources.</p><p num="0007">More than half of the whole weight of a tire on the market
today is made of raw materials derived from petroleum resources. For
example, synthetic rubbers used as a rubber component, such as
styrene-butadiene rubber (SBR), butadiene rubber (BR) and butyl
rubber (IIR) are prepared by polymerizing the monomers extracted from
the C<sub>4</sub> fractions obtained by naphtha cracking of crude petroleum.
Carbon black used as a filler is prepared by atomization and heat
decomposition of crude petroleum under atmosphere where bunker oil is
burned. Petroleum oils used as a process oil, such as aromatic oil,
naphthene oil and paraffin oil are heavy oil components obtained by
atomospheric distillation of crude petroleum. Polyester, a synthetic
fiber used for case cord and others, is prepared by polycondensation of
ethylene glycol with dimethyl terephtalate or terephthalic acid, where
ethylene glycol is obtained from ethylene and dimethyl terephtalate or
terephthalic acid is obtained from paraxylene, both ethylene and
paraxylene being refined from crude petroleum. Waxes, antioxidants,
resins, adhesives and vulcanization accelerators are also prepared from
petroleum resources.</p><p num="0008">According to the present invention, an eco-tire (ecology-conscious
tire) comprising at least 75 % by weight, preferably at least
85 % by weight, and more preferably at least 95 % by weight of non-petroleum
raw materials is achieved by using non-petroleum raw
materials instead of petroleum raw materials such as synthetic rubbers, 
carbon black, petroleum oils and synthetic fibers. When the amount of
the non-petroleum raw materials is less than 75% by weight, effect of
reducing the consumption of petroleum resources remains small.
Among petroleum raw materials, synthetic rubber and carbon black are
main components of a tire, and thus it is preferable to use non-petroleum
raw materials instead of these components. Analyzed part
by part, tread contains petroleum raw materials most, which amounts to
about 23 % of the whole weight of a tire. Then, side wall, case topping,
inner liner, breaker topping and bead follow in order, and therefore it is
preferable to use non-petroleum raw materials instead of petroleum raw
materials in these parts. Herein, examples of raw materials derived
from non-petroleum resources include vegetable resources, minerals,
coal, natural gas, shells, eggshell, crushed bone and crustacean shells.</p><p num="0009">Examples of non-petroleum raw materials used instead of
synthetic rubber are a natural rubber and a modified natural rubber
obtained by modifying a natural rubber. It is preferable that at least
75 % by weight, further at least 85% by weight of synthetic rubber is
replaced by natural rubber. When the replacement by natural rubber
is less than 75 % by weight, effect of reducing the consumption of
petroleum resources remains small and rolling resistance tends to
increase.</p><p num="0010">Examples of non-petroleum raw materials used instead of
carbon black are inorganic fillers such as silica, sericite, calcium
carbonate, clay, alumina, talc, magnesium carbonate, aluminium
hydroxide, magnesium hydroxide, magnesium oxide and titanium oxide;
and biofillers including vegetable polysaccharides such as starch and
cellulose and animal polysaccharides such as chitin and chitosan. 
Among them, silica is preferable in order to ensure the reinforcement of
rubber.</p><p num="0011">When silica is used, it is preferable that silica has a BET
specific surface area of 150 to 250 m<sup>2</sup>/g. When the BET specific surface
area of silica is less than 150 m<sup>2</sup>/g, reinforcing property tends to be
inferior. When the BET specific surface area of silica is more than 250
m<sup>2</sup>/g, there is a tendency that dispersibility is inferior, agglomerattion is
caused and thus a tire has decreased physical properties.</p><p num="0012">It is preferable that at least 75 % by weight, further at least
85 % by weight of carbon black is replaced by an inorganic filler and/or
a biofiller. When the total amount of the inorganic filler and the biofiller
is less than 75% by weight, effect of reducing the consumption of
petroleum resources remains small and rolling resistance tends to
increase.</p><p num="0013">When the inorganic filler is used instead of carbon black, it is
preferable to use a silane coupling agent together. There is no
particular limit for the kind of silane coupling agent as long as it is
currently used in the field of production of tires. Examples of silane
coupling agents are bis(3-triethoxysilylpropyl)tetrasulfide, bis(3-trimethoxysilylpropyl)tetrasulfide,
bis(2-triethoxysilylpropyl)tetrasulfide,
3-mercaptopropyltriethoxysilan and 2-mercaptoethyltrimethoxysilane.
These silane coupling agents may be used alone or in any combination.
Among them, bis(3-triethoxysilylpropyl)tetrasulfide and 3-mercaptopropyltriethoxysilan
are preferable from the viewpoint of
reinforcing property and processability, and bis(3-triethoxysilylpropyl)tetrasulfide
is particularly preferable from the
viewpoint of processability. </p><p num="0014">When silane coupling agent is used together with an
inorganic filler, it is preferable to use 3 to 20 % by weight of silane
coupling agent based on the inorganic filler. When the amount of silane
coupling agent is less than 3 % by weight, the effect of adding silane
coupling agent is insufficient. When the amount of silane coupling
agent is more than 20 % by weight, the effect to be obtained remains
small in spite of cost increase.</p><p num="0015">Examples of non-petroleum raw materials used instead of
petroleum oils include vegetable oils such as castor oil, cotton seed oil,
linseed oil, rape seed oil, soya bean oil, palm oil, cocoanut oil, arachis oil,
rosin, pine oil, pine tar, tall oil, corn oil, rice oil, safflower oil, sesame oil,
olive oil, sunflower oil, palm kernel oil, camellia oil, jojoba oil,
macadamia nut oil, safflower oil and tung oil. Among them, rape seed
oil, palm oil and cocoanut oil are preferable from the viewpoint of their
supply, price and softening effect.</p><p num="0016">Among these vegetable oils, preferable examples are oils
having low unsaturation degree, such as semi-drying oils having an
iodine number of 100 to 130, and non-drying oil or solid oil having an
iodine number of at most 100. Herein, the iodine number is defined as
the amount of iodine based on gram, which can be absorbed by 100 g of
oil. When the iodine number of the oil is more than 130, there is a
tendency that tan δ is increased and hardness is decreased to cause
increase of rolling resistance and decrease of steering stability.</p><p num="0017">It is preferable that at least 75 % by weight, further at least
85 % by weight of petroleum oil is replaced by vegetable oil. When the
amount of vegetable oil is less than 75 % by weight, effect of reducing the
consumption of petroleum resources remains small and rolling 
resistance tends to increase.</p><p num="0018">It is preferable to blend vegetable oil so that the hardness of
rubber becomes 40 to 90 after vulcanization. When the hardness of
rubber is less than 40, there is a tendency that required rigidity cannot
be achieved. When the hardness of rubber is more than 90,
processability tends to be inferior.</p><p num="0019">Examples of non-petroleum raw materials used instead of
synthetic fiber include rayon and acetate which are made from wood
pulp, and cupro which is made from cotton seed crude linter. Among
them, rayon is preferable because of its high strength required for a tire.</p><p num="0020">The tire of the present invention can be prepared according to
a conventional method, but non-petroleum raw materials is used
instead of all or part of the petroleum raw materials which has been used
so far.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLES</u></heading><p num="0021">The present invention is explained in detail based on
Examples below, but not limited thereto. "Part(s)" and "%" in the
following examples mean "part(s) by weight" and "% by weight",
respectively, unless otherwise specified.</p><p num="0022">Materials used in Examples and Comparative Examples are
summarized below.</p><heading>[Raw materials derived from petroleum resources]</heading><p num="0023"><sl><li>SBR: SBR1502 available from Sumitomo Chemical Co., Ltd.</li><li>BR: BR150B available from Ube Industries, Ltd.</li><li>IIR: Cl-IIR1068 available from Exxon Chemical Japan Ltd.</li><li>Carbon black (ISAF): Diablack I available from Mitsubishi Chemical 
Corporation</li><li>Carbon black (FEF): Diablack E available from Mitsubishi Chemical
Corporation</li><li>Carbon black (GPF): Diablack G available from Mitsubishi Chemical
Corporation</li><li>Carbon black (HAF): Diablack HA available from Mitsubishi Chemical
Corporation</li><li>Carbon black (LM-HAF): Diablack LH available from Mitsubishi
Chemical Corporation</li><li>Aromatic oil: Process X-140 available from Japan Energy Corporation</li><li>Mineral oil: Diana Process PA32 available from Idemitsu Kosan Co., Ltd.</li><li>Wax: Ozoace 0355 available from Nippon Seiro Co., Ltd.</li><li>Antioxidant: Antigen 6C available from Sumitomo Chemical Co., Ltd.</li><li>Cured resin :Sumilite resin PR12686 available from Sumitomo Bakelite
Co., Ltd.</li><li>Adhesive (COST): COST-F available from Japan Energy Corporation</li><li>Adhesive (S.620): Sumicanol 620 available from Sumitomo Chemical Co.,
Ltd.</li><li>Vulcanization Accelerator: Nocceler NS available from Ohuchi Shinko
Kagaku Kogyo Co., Ltd.</li></sl></p><heading>[Raw materials derived from non-petroleum resources]</heading><p num="0024"><sl><li>Natural rubber: RSS#3</li><li>Silica: Ultrasil VN3 available from Degussa Hules Co.</li><li>Coupling Agent: Si-69 available from Degussa Hules Co.</li><li>Sericite: KM-S available from Nippon Forum Co., Ltd.</li><li>Calcium carbonate: Hakuenka CC available from SHIRAISHI KOGYO
KAISHA LTD. </li><li>Vegetable oil: Purified palm oil J(S) available from Nisshin Oil Mills, Ltd.</li><li>Stearic Acid: Stearic acid Tsubaki available from NOF Corporation</li><li>Zinc oxide: Zinc Oxide available from Mitsui Mining and Smelting Co.,
Ltd.</li><li>Sulfur: powdery sulfur available from Tsurumi Chemicals Co., Ltd.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 1</u></heading><p num="0025">Kneading was carried out according to compounds listed in
Table 1, and tread A (40 % of the tire weight), side wall A (17 % of the tire
weight), inner liner A (8 % of the tire weight), clinch apex A (3 % of the
tire weight), bead apex A (5 % of the tire weight), breaker topping A (8 %
of the tire weight) and carcass ply topping A (3 % of the tire weight) were
formed. Steel cord (8 % of the tire weight) was used for the breaker, and
cord (5 % of the tire weight) made of 1840 dtex/2 rayon was used for the
carcass ply.</p><p num="0026">An unvulcanized tire was prepared by assembling the above
components and other parts (3 % of the tire weight) on a tire forming
machine in a usual manner, and the tire was heated and pressed in a
vulcanizing machine to obtain an eco-tire comprising 97 % by weight of
non-petroleum raw materials (tire size: 195/65R15 91S).</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 1</u></heading><p num="0027">Kneading was carried out according to compounds listed in
Table 1, and tread B, side wall B, inner liner B, clinch apex B, bead apex
B, breaker B and carcass ply B were formed. A conventional tire
comprising 44 % of non-petroleum raw materials was prepared in the
same manner as in Example 1 except that a cord made of 1670 dtex/2 
polyester was used for the carcass ply. <img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="148" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/></p><p num="0028">The tires prepared in Example and Comparative Example
were subjected to the following durability test and performance
evaluations.</p><heading>1) High speed durability</heading><p num="0029">Evaluation of high speed durability was carried out in
accordance with JIS D4230 "tire for automobiles" S range high speed
durability test A.</p><heading>2) Rolling resistance coefficient (RRC)</heading><p num="0030">Rolling resistance was measured under the condition of
speed of 80 km/h, air pressure of 250 kPa and load of 4.0 kN. Rolling
resistance coefficient was obtained by dividing the rolling resistance
value with the load value, and multiplying the result by 10<sup>4</sup>. The
smaller the coefficient is, the lower and the more excellent the heat
build-up characteristic is.</p><heading>3) Braking test</heading><p num="0031">Friction coefficient µ was determined from the brake stopping
distance, which was measured by stopping the automobile mounted
with the prepared tire, running at a speed of 100 km/h on dry asphalt
road and wet asphalt road. The friction coefficient µ is represented as
an index to the µ value of Comparative Example 1 as 100.</p><heading>4) Evaluation test on real automobile</heading><p num="0032">Grip, rigidity and riding comfort characteristics were
evaluated by using a real automobile with an engine size of 2000 cc,
which was mounted with the prepared tire and run on dry asphalt road
and wet asphalt road in a test course. The results are represented in
score based on the value of Comparative Example 1 as 6. The higher
the score is, the better the properties are. Only well-trained drivers can 
detect the score difference of 0.5 point.</p><p num="0033">The results are shown in Table 2. Table 2 shows that the
eco-tire of Example 1 has smaller rolling resistance, better fuel
consumption and equally excellent high speed durability and other
properties compared with the conventional tire of Comparative Example
1.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Test</entry><entry align="center">Ex. 1</entry><entry align="center">Com. Ex. 1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">High speed durability</entry><entry align="center">Passed</entry><entry align="center">Passed</entry></row><row><entry align="left">RRC</entry><entry align="center">80</entry><entry align="center">91</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Braking test</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dry µ (index)</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Wet µ (index)</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Organoleptic test on automobile</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dry grip (score)</entry><entry align="center">5.5</entry><entry align="center">6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Wet grip (score)</entry><entry align="center">5.5</entry><entry align="center">6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rigidity (score)</entry><entry align="center">5.5</entry><entry align="center">6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Riding comfort (score)</entry><entry align="center">5.5</entry><entry align="center">6</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0034">According to the present invention, a new and earth-friendly
tire in anticipation of decline of petroleum supply can be prepared by
using a natural rubber instead of a synthetic rubber, an inorganic filler
and/or a biofiller instead of carbon black, vegetable oil instead of
petroleum oil, and natural fiber instead of synthetic fiber so that the tire
comprises a non-petroleum raw materials in an amount of at least 75 %
by weight based on the total weight of the tire.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A tire comprising a raw material derived from a non-petroleum
resource in an amount of at least 75 % by weight based on the
total weight of said tire.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The tire of Claim 1, wherein the raw material derived from
a non-petroleum resource includes a natural rubber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The tire of Claim 1 or 2, wherein the raw material derived
from a non-petroleum resource includes an inorganic filler and/or a
biofiller.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The tire of Claim 1, 2 or 3, wherein the raw material
derived from a non-petroleum resource includes vegetable oil.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The tire of Claim 1, 2, 3 or 4, wherein the raw material
derived from a non-petroleum resource includes a natural fiber.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>