<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1110985-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1110985" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="23820177" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010627"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1110985-A2" status="new" fvid="23171350"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1110985</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20010627</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00125301-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00125301</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001128</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-45828799-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>45828799</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991210</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/66        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/76        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/80        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  18/66P2A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  18/76D2B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  18/80B3D2E</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Einstufenpolyurethanelastomere mit niedrigem Druckverformungsrest</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">One-shot polyurethane elastomers with very low compression sets</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Elastomères de polyuréthane en une seule phase ayant une déformation permanente réduite</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0393545-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0393545</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5350778-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5350778</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5539010-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5539010</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BAYER AG</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BAYER CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Bayer Corporation</last-name><address><street>100 Bayer Road</street><city>Pittsburgh, PA 15205</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CLINE ROBERT L</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GILBERT CORRINE M</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MARKUSCH PETER H</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SARPESHKAR ASHOK M</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CLINE, ROBERT L.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GILBERT, CORRINE M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MARKUSCH, PETER H.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SARPESHKAR, ASHOK M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CLINE, ROBERT L.</last-name><address><street>302 West Madison</street><city>Paden City, WV 26159</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GILBERT, CORRINE M.</last-name><address><street>2105 Irwin St.</street><city>Aliquippa, PA 15001</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MARKUSCH, PETER H.</last-name><address><street>111 Lynbrook Drive</street><city>McMurray, PA 15317</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SARPESHKAR, ASHOK M.</last-name><address><street>458 Diablo Drive</street><city>Upper St. Clair, PA 15241</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Perchenek, Nils, Dr.</last-name><address><street>Bayer AG KB-RP Patente und Lizenzen</street><city>51368 Leverkusen</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>CY</country><country>FI</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>This invention relates to a process for the production of
polyurethane elastomers having low compression sets. The process
comprises reacting A) an isocyanate component comprising methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate) containing the 2,4'-isomer of methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate), with B) an isocyanate-reactive component, optionally, in the
presence of C) one or more additives. The reaction components are
processed via the one-shot process at an isocyanate index of 90 to 130.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to a process for the production of
polyurethane elastomers which exhibit low compression sets. These
polyurethane elastomers are prepared by the one-shot process, by
reacting a methylene diphenyl diisocyanate having a 2,4'-isomer content of
at least 20% by weight, with an isocyanate-reactive component having an
average functionality of at least 3.0, optionally, in the presence of
additives, at an isocyanate index of 90 to 130. It is preferred that the
resultant polyurethane elastomers have a compression set of 10% or less.</p><p num="0002">Liquid room temperature stable polyisocyanates based on 2,4'- and
4,4'-diphenylmethane diisocyanates containing varying amounts of the
2,4'-isomer are known and described in, for example, U.S. Patents
4,118,411, 5,350,778, 5,563,232 and 5,585,452. These liquid
polyisocyanates are capable of reacting with a suitable polyol component
to form molded products via the one-shot process.</p><p num="0003">The process of molded articles having a closed surface layer by the
isocyanate polyaddition process is known. Such articles may be made, for
example, by introducing a reactive (optionally, foamable) mixture based on
compounds containing several reactive hydrogen atoms and
polyisocyanates into a mold (see, e.g., German Auslegeshrift No.
1,196,864). The compounds with reactive hydrogen atoms typically used
are polyethers containing hydroxyl groups. Examples of suitable
polyisocyanates include 2,4- and 2,6-toluene diisocyanate, their isomeric
mixtures and polyphenyl polymethylene polyisocyanates obtained by
aniline-formaldehyde condensation followed by phosgenation. Water
and/or fluorinated hydrocarbons may be used as blowing agents. Catalysts
known to those in the art to be useful for the production of polyurethanes
are generally also used. </p><p num="0004">Depending upon the starting components (and chain lengthening
agents such as glycols or diamines if used), it is possible to obtain both
elastic and rigid products and variations between these extremes by this
procedure. For molded articles that must withstand heavy wear, it is
customary to use slightly branched raw materials because such materials
yield a product having elastomer-like characteristics. Molded articles of
this kind have been produced on a technical scale (e.g., as shoe soles in
the shoe manufacturing industry, bowling balls, encapsulations for
transformers, self-leveling flooring compositions for gyms, resins for the
encapsulation of air bag sensors, etc.).</p><p num="0005">U.S. Patent 4,774,263 describes a one-shot process for the
production of elastic molded articles having a closed surface layer by the
reaction injection molding technique without using an external mold
release agent. The reaction mixture used in the '263 patent comprises a
di- and/or polyisocyanate in which all of the isocyanate groups are
aromatically bound, a polyether, a diamine, and, optionally, auxiliary
agents and additives.</p><p num="0006">U.S. Patent 5,719,229 describes polyurethane elastomers having
reduced surface skinning and improved green strength prepared by
reaction of polyester-based isocyanate prepolymers with diol chain
extenders in the presence of certain surface skinning retardants. Various
approaches to eliminate surface skinning and improve green strength have
been reported. E.g., U.S. Patents 3,806,486, 3,635,906, 4,401,804,
4,551,498, and 4,618,667.</p><p num="0007">U.S. Patent 5,059,672 describes elastomeric reaction products of
an aromatic isocyanate, an aliphatic isocyanate having a functionality of at
least two, and an aromatic diamine. Suitable aromatic isocyanates include
aromatic isocyanates, aromatic isocyanate terminated aliphatics, aromatic
isocyanate terminated cycloaliphatics, aromatic isocyanate terminated
quasi-prepolymers, and aromatic isocyanate terminated prepolymers.
Suitable aliphatic isocyanates include isocyanate terminated aliphatics, 
cycloaliphatic isocyanates containing at least two isocyanate groups,
isocyanate terminated quasi-prepolymers and isocyanate terminated
prepolymers. Chain extenders, fillers, pigments, etc., may also be
included.</p><p num="0008">Various polyurethanes and elastomers which may be prepared from
an isocyanate, a chain extender and optionally a polyol, in the presence of
various catalysts are known and described in, for example, U.S. Patents
4,447,590, 4,523,005, 4,621,113 and 5,208,315, and Canadian Patent
971,184. The catalysts described in these references are standard
polyurethane catalysts such as, for example, dibutyl tin dilaurate or dibutyl
tin oxide.</p><p num="0009">U.S. Patent 4,115,429 describes low temperature, stable liquid
diphenylmethane diisocyanates which are useful isocyanate components
in the manufacturing of one-shot polyurethane elastomers. Also, see U.S.
Patent 3,644,457 in this regard.</p><p num="0010">Low compression set polyurethane elastomers are specifically
useful in gasket applications and other applications where dynamic
mechanical properties are required, i.e., shock absorbers. Very low
compression set polyurethanes can usually only be obtained by the so
called "hot cast elastomer process" where isocyanate prepolymers based
on MDI with very low NCO content (usually less than 10%) are reacted at
elevated temperatures (i.e., 80°C) with a chain extender (i.e., 1,4-butanediol).
The hot melt cast elastomer process does not only require
high temperatures but is also expensive and demands equipment with
very high accuracy to mix the components due to mix ratios ranging from
90:10 to even 95:5. The one-shot process on the other hand, can be
performed at ambient temperatures and allows more robust mix ratios of
about 1:1 to about 1:3. However, polyurethane made by the one-shot
process as known by the art have not shown the desirable low
compression set. </p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0011">This invention relates to a process for the production of
polyurethane elastomers having low compression sets. This process
comprises reacting A) an isocyanate component with B) an isocyanate-reactive
component, optionally in the presence of C) one or more
additives, with the components being processed via the one-shot process
at an isocyanate index of 90 to 130, preferably 95 to 110. It is preferred
that the resultant polyurethane elastomers of this process have a
compression set of less than 10%.</p><p num="0012">Component A) the isocyanate component comprises: A)1) 20 to
100% by weight, preferably from 30 to 95% by weight and more preferably
from 25 to 85% by weight, of methylene bis (phenyl isocyanate)
comprising: (a) from 20 to 80% by weight of 4,4'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate); (b) from 20 to 80% by weight of 2,4'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate); and (c) from 0.1 to 5% by weight of 2,2'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate), with the percents by weight of components A)1 )(a), A)1 )(b)
and A)1 )(c) totaling 100% by weight of component A)1). Component A)
additionally comprises: A)2) from 0 to 80% by weight, preferably from 5 to
70% by weight, and more preferably from 15 to 75% by weight, of an
isocyanate-reactive compound containing two hydroxyl groups and having
a molecular weight of 62 to 6,000, preferably 200 to 6,000, and most
preferably 200 to 2,000. The percents by weight of components A)1) and
A)2) total 100% by weight of component A). In the embodiment wherein A)
the isocyanate component comprises an isocyanate prepolymer which is
prepared by reacting A)1) with A)2), it is preferred that these prepolymers
have an NCO group content of about 8 to about 23%, a functionality of
about 2.0, a urethane content of about 2 to about 15%, preferably about 2
to about 10%, and a viscosity of 400 to 5,000 mPa·s at 25°C.</p><p num="0013">Component B), the isocyanate-reactive component comprises: B)1)
from 40 to 80% by weight, preferably from 40 to 70% by weight and more
preferably from 40 to 60% by weight, based on 100% by weight of 
component B), of an isocyanate-reactive component containing hydroxyl
and/or amine groups, and having a molecular weight of more than 1,000
(preferably of from 2,000 to 6,000), and a functionality of about 3 to about
5 (preferably about 3); B)2) from 10 to 40% by weight, preferably from 10
to 30% by weight and more preferably from 10 to 20% by weight, based on
100% by weight of component B), of an isocyanate-reactive component
containing from about 3 to about 5 hydroxyl-groups, and having a
molecular weight of about 800 or less (preferably about 130 to 600); and
B)3) from 5 to 40% by weight, preferably from 5 to 20% by weight and
more preferably from 5 to 10% by weight, based on 100% by weight of
component B), of an isocyanate-reactive component containing about 2
hydroxyl groups, and having a molecular weight of from about 62 to about
200. Components A) and B) may be reacted in the presence of C) one or
more additives.</p><p num="0014">This invention also relates to a polyurethane elastomer, preferably
having a compression set of less than 10%, which comprises:
<sl><li>A) an isocyanate component comprising:
<sl><li>1) 20 to 100% by weight, based on 100% by weight of
component A), of methylene bis(phenyl isocyanate)
comprising:
<sl><li>(a) from 20 to 80% by weight of 4,4'-methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate),</li><li>(b) from 20 to 80% by weight of 2,4'-methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate),</li><li>(c) from 0.1 to 5% by weight of 2,2'-methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate),

with the percents by weight of components A)1)(a),
A)1)(b) and A)1)(c) totaling 100% by weight of
component A)1),</li></sl>
and </li><li>2) from 0 to 80% by weight, based on 100% by weight of
component A), of an isocyanate-reactive compound
containing two hydroxyl groups and having a
molecular weight of 62 to 6,000;</li></sl></li><li>B) a polyol component comprising:
<sl><li>1) from 40 to 80% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of component B), of an isocyanate-reactive
component containing hydroxyl and/or amine groups,
and having a molecular weight of more than 1,000,
and a functionality of about 3 to about 5,</li><li>2) from 10 to 40% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of component B), of an isocyanate-reactive
component containing from about 3 to about 5
hydroxyl-groups and having a molecular weight of
about 800 or less,

and</li><li>3) from 5 to 40% by weight, based on 100% by weight of
component B), of an isocyanate-reactive component
containing about 2 hydroxyl groups, and having a
molecular weight of from about 62 to 200;</li></sl>
and, optionally,</li><li>C) one or more additives,
wherein the components are processed via the one-shot process at an
isocyanate index of 90 to 130.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0015">Suitable isocyanates to be used as component A) of the present
invention comprise A)1) methylene bis(phenyl isocyanate) mixtures
containing (a) from 20 to 80% by weight, preferably from 30 to 80% by
weight, and most preferably from 35 to 55% by weight of 4,4'-methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate); (b) from 20 to 80% by weight, preferably from 40 to
70% by weight, and most preferably from 45 to 65% by weight of 2,4'-methylene 
bis(phenyl isocyanate); and (c) from 0.1 to 5%, preferably from
0.1 to 2.0% by weight, and most preferably from 0.5 to 2.0% by weight of
2,2'-methylene bis(phenyl isocyanate), with the %'s by weight of A)1)(a),
A)1)(b) and A)1)(c) totaling 100% by weight of A)1).</p><p num="0016">In accordance with the present invention, it is also possible that
component A) comprises an isocyanate prepolymer. Suitable prepolymers
comprise the reaction product of A)1) a methylene bis(phenyl isocyanate)
mixture as described above, with A)2) an isocyanate-reactive component
in a ratio such that the resultant product contains isocyanate groups.
These isocyanate prepolymers are the reaction products of A)1) with A)2),
and comprise from 20 to 100%, preferably from 30 to 95% and more
preferably from 25 to 85% by weight of A)1) a methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate) mixture comprising (a), (b) and (c) described above; and from
0 to 80%, preferably from 5 to 75%, and more preferably from 15 to 70%
by weight of A)2) an isocyanate-reactive component, wherein the percents
by weight of component A)1) and A)2) totals 100% by weight of
component A).</p><p num="0017">Suitable isocyanate-reactive components to be used as component
A)2) of the present invention for forming the isocyanate prepolymer
include, for example, compounds containing two hydroxyl groups capable
of reacting with isocyanate-groups of component A)1), have an OH
number of from about 18 to 1806 (preferably from about 28 to about 750),
and a molecular weight of from about 62 to about 6,000 (preferably of from
about 200 to about 2,000). Examples of suitable compounds include, but
are not limited to, ethylene glycol, diethylene glycol, dipropylene glycol,
triethylene glycol, tripropylene glycol, tetrapropylene glycol, neopentyl
glycol, trimethylpentane diol, etc., as well as higher molecular weight
alkoxylation adducts of suitable initiator compounds including, for example,
ethylene glycol, diethylene glycol, dipropylene glycol, triethylene glycol,
tripropylene glycol, tetrapropylene glycol, neopentyl glycol,
trimethylpentane diol, etc., which are commonly referred to polyether 
polyols, with polyether diols having molecular weights of 500 to 6,000
being preferred, and those having molecular weights of about 1,000 to
about 4,000 being more preferred. Preferred hydroxyl-group containing
compounds to be used as component A)2) are diethylene glycol,
dipropylene glycol, tripropylene glycol and trimethylpentane diol, as well as
polyether diols having molecular weights of 1,000 to 4,000.</p><p num="0018">It is particularly preferred that an isocyanate prepolymer having an
NCO group content of about 10% be used as component A), wherein
component A)2) comprises a polyether diol. Isocyanate prepolymers such
as these result in the lowest compression set in the resultant polyurethane
elastomers of the present invention.</p><p num="0019">Component B) the isocyanate-reactive component of the present
invention comprises 1) from 40 to 80% by weight, preferably 40 to 70% by
weight, and more preferably 40 to 60% by weight, based on 100% by
weight of component B), of an isocyanate-reactive component having a
molecular weight of more than about 1,000, preferably from about 2,000 to
about 6,000, more preferably from about 3,000 to about 6,000, and having
a functionality of about 3 to about 5, and preferably about 3. Such
compounds may contain hydroxyl groups, amine groups or a mixture
thereof, provided that the total number of isocyanate-reactive groups
present satisfies the above functionality requirements. Examples of
suitable compounds to be used as component B)1) include the polyethers,
polyesters, polythioethers, polyacetals, polycarbonates, and amine
terminated polyethers containing from about 3 to about 5 isocyanate-reactive
groups of the type known for the production of polyurethanes.</p><p num="0020">The high molecular weight polyethers suitable for use in
accordance with the invention are known and may be obtained, for
example, by polymerizing tetrahydrofuran or epoxides such as, for
example, ethylene oxide, propylene oxide, butylene oxide, styrene oxide or
epichlorohydrin in the presence of suitable catalysts, such as, for example,
BF<sub>3</sub> or KOH, or by chemically adding these epoxides, preferably, ethylene 
oxide and propylene oxide, in admixture or successively to components
containing reactive hydrogen atoms such as alcohols or amines.

Examples of suitable alcohols and amines include the low molecular
weight chain extenders set forth hereinafter, glycerin, triethanolamine,
trimethylolpropane, sucrose, ethanolamine, and ethylene diamine. It is
preferred to use polyethers which contain substantial amounts of primary
hydroxyl groups in terminal positions (greater than 80% by weight, based
on all of the terminal hydroxyl groups present in the polyether).</p><p num="0021">Polyether polyols are preferably used as component B)1) in the
invention. Preferred polyethers include, for example, those compounds
based on tri-functional starters such as, for example, glycerin,
trimethylolpropane, triethanolamine or ethanolamine.</p><p num="0022">Suitable polyesters, polythioethers, polyacetals, polycarbonates and
other polyhydroxyl compounds which may be used in accordance with the
invention may be found, for example, in High Polymers, Volume XVI,
"Polyurethanes, Chemistry and Technology," by Saunders-Frisch,
Interscience Publishers, New York, London, Vol. I, 1962, pages 32-42 and
44-54, and Volume II, 1964, pages 5-6 and 198-199; and in Kunststoff-Handbuch,
Vol. VII, Vieweg-Hochtlen, Carl Hanser Verlag, Munich, 1966,
pages 45-71.</p><p num="0023">Also suitable are so-called amine terminated polyethers containing
primary or secondary aromatically or aliphatically bound amino groups,
wherein amino end groups can also be attached to the polyether chain
through urethane or ester groups. It is preferred that the amine-terminated
polyethers have a molecular weight in the range of from 1,000 to 6,000
and a functionality of 3 or higher. These amine terminated polyethers can
be prepared by any of several methods known in the art. For example,
amine terminated polyethers can be prepared from polyhydroxyl polyether
(e.g., polypropylene glycol ethers) by a reaction with ammonia in the
presence of Raney nickel and hydrogen (Belgian Patent No. 634,741).
Polyoxyalkylene polyamines can be prepared by reaction of the 
corresponding polyol with ammonia and hydrogen in the presence of a
nickel, copper, chromium catalyst (U.S. Patent 3,654,370). The
preparation of polyethers containing amino end groups by the
hydrogenation of cyanoethylated polyoxypropylene ethers is described in
Germany Patent 1,193,671. Other methods for the preparation of
polyoxyalkylene (polyether) amines are described in U.S. Patents
3,155,728 and 3,236,895 and in French Patent No. 1,551,605. French
Patent No. 1,466,708 discloses the preparation of polyethers containing
secondary amino end groups. Also useful are the polyether polyamines
described in U.S. Patents 4,396,729, 4,433,067, 4,444,910 and 4,530,941.</p><p num="0024">Aminopolyethers obtained by the hydrolysis of compounds
containing isocyanate end groups can be employed herein. For example,
in a process disclosed in German Offenlegungsschrift 2,948,419,
polyethers containing hydroxyl groups (preferably two or three hydroxyl
groups) react with polyisocyanate groups are then hydrolyzed in a second
step to amino groups. Processes for the production of useful amine
terminated polyethers using isocyanate hydrolysis techniques are
described in U.S. Patents 4,386,218, 4,456,730, 4,472,568, 4,501,873,
4,515,923, 4,525,534, 4,540,720, 4,578,500 and 4,565,645; European
Patent 097,299; and German Offenlegungsschrift 2,948,419, all the
disclosures of which are herein incorporated by reference. Similar
products are also described in U.S. Patents 4,506,039, 4,525,590,
4,532,266, 4,532,317, 4,723,032, 4,724,252, 4,855,504 and 5,283,364.</p><p num="0025">The amine terminated polyethers used in the present invention are
in many cases mixtures with any of the above-mentioned compounds.</p><p num="0026">In another embodiment, the polyhydroxyl compound B)1) may
additionally comprise: i) a dispersion of a polyurea and/or polyhydrazodicarbonamide
in a relatively high molecular weight organic compound
containing at least two hydroxyl groups; ii) a polymer polyol prepared by
polymerizing an ethylenically unsaturated monomer or monomers in a
relatively high molecular weight organic compound containing at least two 
hydroxyl groups; or iii) blends thereof. It is possible to use these types of
polyols either alone, or in conjunction with the conventional polyethers
described hereinabove.</p><p num="0027">These types of polyols are known, and can be characterized as
hydroxyl containing compounds which contain high molecular weight
polyadducts, polycondensates, or polymers in finely dispersed or dissolved
form. Such polymers may be obtained by polyaddition reactions (for
example, reactions between polyisocyanates and aminofunctional
compounds) and polycondensation reactions (for example, between
formaldehyde and phenols and/or amines) in situ in the hydroxyl group
containing compound. Such processes are described in, for example,
German Auslegeschriften 1,168,075 and 1,260,142, the disclosures of
which are herein incorporated by reference, and in German
Offenlegungsschriften 2,324,134, 2,423,984, 2,512,385, 2,513,815,
2,550,796, 2,550,797, 2,550,833, 2,550,862, 2,633,293, and 2,639,254,
the disclosures of which are herein incorporated by reference. See also
U.S. Patents 3,325,421, 4,042,537, 4,089,835, 4,293,470, 4,296,213,
4,374,209, and 4,786,706, the disclosures of which are herein
incorporated by reference. Polyols of this type are commercially available
from Bayer Corporation and Bayer AG. Also useful are the so-called
polymer polyols obtained by polymerizing one or more ethylenically
unsaturated monomers in a hydroxy group containing compound. Polyols
modified by vinyl polymers, of the type formed, for example, by
polymerizing styrene or acrylonitrile in the presence of polyether polyol are
also suitable, as are polybutadienes containing OH groups. Such polymer
polyols are described in U.S. Patents 3,383,351, 3,304,273, 3,523,093,
3,110,685, and RE 28,715 and 29,118, and German Patent 1,152,536, the
disclosures of which are herein incorporated by reference. Polymer
polyols are commercially available from Bayer AG, BASF, and Union
Carbide. </p><p num="0028">Suitable compounds to be used as component B)2) in the present
invention include, for example, isocyanate-reactive compounds containing
on average 3 to 5 hydroxyl-groups and having a molecular weight of about
800 or less, preferably of about 130 to about 600. Some examples of
suitable compounds include pentaerythritol, trimethylolpropane, glycerol,
mixtures thereof, and other tri- and/or tetra- and/or penta-functional
polyethers, and tri- and/or tetra-and/or penta-functional polyesters, such
as, for example, polycaprolactone triols. Suitable tri-, tetra- and/or penta-functional
polyethers include, for example, compounds prepared by the
alkoxylation (preferably, ethoxylation and/or propoxylation) of glycerol,
trimethylolpropane, pentaerythritol, monoethanolamine, and other tri- or
tetra- or penta-functional starter compounds, provided that the above
mentioned molecular weight limits are satisfied. It is, of course, also
possible to use mixtures of the above identified tri- and tetra-functional
compounds or mixtures of other starter compounds may be used as
component B)2) or as a starter for preparing polyethers to be used as
component B)2) provided that the molecular weight and functionality
requirements described above are satisfied. Preferred compounds to be
used as component B)2) include trifunctional polyethers prepared by
alkoxylation of glycerol, trimethylolpropane and ethanolamine.</p><p num="0029">Suitable compounds to be used as component B)3) of the present
invention include those isocyanate-reactive compounds containing about 2
hydroxyl groups and having a molecular weight in the range of from about
62 to about 200. Some examples of these suitable compounds include, but
are not limited to, 2-methyl-1,3-propanediol, ethylene glycol, 1,2- and 1,3-propanediol,
1,3- and 1,4- and 2,3-butanediol, 1,6-hexanediol, 1,10-decanediol,
diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol, tetraethylene glycol,
dipropylene glycol, tripropylene glycol, neopentyl glycol, cyclohexanedimethanol,
2,2,4-trimethylpentane-1,3- diol, etc. Preferred diols include,
for example, 1,4-butanediol, dipropylene glycol, and diethylene glycol. </p><p num="0030">In accordance with the present invention, components A) and B)
are present in amounts such that the isocyanate index (NCO Index) of the
reaction mixture is from about 90 to about 130, preferably from about 95 to
about 110, and most preferably from about 100 to about 105. The term
"Isocyanate Index" as used herein is defined as the equivalents of
isocyanate which are reacted with 100 equivalents of isocyanate-reactive
hydrogen containing materials.</p><p num="0031">Suitable additives to be used as component C) in the present
invention include, for example, catalysts, surface-active additives, such as,
emulsifiers. Some examples of suitable catalysts include the tertiary
amines, organometallic compounds, particularly organotin catalysts, such
as, for example, tin carboxylates and bismuth carboxylates, tin-sulfur
catalysts, etc. Examples include N-stearyl-N',N'-bis-(hydroxyethyl)urea,
oleyl polyoxyethylene amide, stearyl diethanol amide, isostearyl
diethanolamide, polyoxyethylene glycol monoleate, a pentaerythritol/adipic
acid/oleic acid ester, a hydroxy ethyl imidazole derivative of oleic acid, N-stearyl
propylene diamine and the sodium salts of castor oil sulfonates or
of fatty acids. Alkali metal or ammonium salts of sulfonic acid, such as,
dodecyl benzene sulfonic acid or dinaphthyl methane sulfonic acid and
also fatty acids may also be used as surface-active additives.</p><p num="0032">Suitable anti-oxidants include, for example, Irganox 245, and
suitable UV stabilizers include, for example, Tinuvin 765. However, any of
the known anti-oxidants and/or UV stabilizers may be used. As set forth
hereinabove, specific advantages have been found in reaction mixtures
containing anti-oxidants and/or UV stabilizers. It is preferred that a
stabilizer selected from the group consisting of anti-oxidants, UV-stabilizers,
hindered amine light stabilizers, and mixtures thereof is added
to the mixture containing isocyanate-reactive components.</p><p num="0033">It is also possible to use the known internal mold release agents,
such as, for example, zinc stearate, in the RIM process of the invention.
This IMR is described in U.S. Patents 4,269,945 and 4,585,803, the 
disclosures of which are herein incorporated by reference, and in
Canadian Patent 1,180,146.</p><p num="0034">Pigments may also be added to the B-side of the reaction mixture.
Usually when pigments are added, they are typically dispersed in a
hydroxyl group containing compound (such as, for example, a polyether, a
polyester, or a chain extender, etc.). When this is done, the weight of the
hydroxyl group containing compound is considered in determining the
percent by weight of components B)1), B)2) and B)3) as set forth
hereinabove. In addition, it is also possible to include additives, such as,
for example, viscosity depressants, surfactants, and plasticizers in one of
the components.</p><p num="0035">In preparing polyurethanes according to the present invention, the
isocyanate and the isocyanate-reactive components, both maintained at
ambient or slightly elevated temperature, are mixed until a homogenous
mixture is obtained. The mix ratio is chosen so that the most preferred
index is achieved. Mixing of the two components may be achieved by
employing either a two- or three-stream machine capable of metering the
components accurately. The reacting mixture is poured into a suitable
mold and cured completed at ambient or an elevated temperature in an
oven. After the material has solidified, it may be demolded and allowed to
further post-cure at either ambient or elevated temperature.</p><p num="0036">Prior to mixing with the isocyanate, the isocyanate-reactive
component is prepared by blending the individual components described
in the invention with the optional catalyst, filler and other additives. It is
preferable to degas this mixture, especially when inorganic fillers are
employed.</p><p num="0037">As used herein, the term "molecular weight" refers to the number
average molecular weight as determined by end-group analysis.</p><p num="0038">The following examples further illustrate details for the process of
this invention. The invention, which is set forth in the foregoing disclosure,
is not to be limited either in spirit or scope by these examples. Those 
skilled in the art will readily understand that known variations of the
conditions of the following procedures can be used. Unless otherwise
noted, all temperatures are degrees Celsius and all parts and percentages
are parts by weight and percentages by weight, respectively.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLES</u></heading><p num="0039">The following components were used in the working examples:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="9"><dt><u style="single">Polyol 1</u>:</dt><dd>a glycerol started propylene oxide/ethylene oxide (87:13 wt.
ratio) polyether polyol, having an OH number of about 35, a
functionality of about 3 and a molecular weight of about 4800</dd><dt><u style="single">Polyol 2</u>:</dt><dd>a propylene glycol started propylene oxide (100%) polyether
polyol, having an OH number of about 112, a functionality of
about 2 and a molecular weight of about 1000</dd><dt><u style="single">Polvol 3</u>:</dt><dd>a trimethylolpropane started propylene oxide (100%)
polyether polyol, having an OH number of about 370, a
functionality of about 3 and a molecular weight of about 450</dd><dt><u style="single">Polyol 4</u>:</dt><dd>a propylene glycol started propylene oxide/ethylene oxide
(80:20 wt. ratio) polyether polyol, having an OH number of
about 28, a functionality of about 2 and a molecular weight of
about 4000</dd><dt><u style="single">Polyol 5</u>:</dt><dd>1,4-butanediol</dd></dl><dl compact="compact" tsize="26"><dt><u style="single">Baylith L Paste</u> :</dt><dd>a mixture of a synthetic alumino-silicate in castor oil</dd><dt><u style="single">Dow Corning Antifoam 1500</u>:</dt><dd>100% silica-filled polydimethyl siloxane,
an FDA approved antifoaming agent
used to prevent foam in food and
chemical processes</dd><dt><u style="single">Catalyst A</u>:</dt><dd>a dibutyltin dilaurate catalyst, commercially available as
Dabco T-12 from Air Products and Chemical Inc. Allentown,
PA</dd><dt><u style="single">Isocyanate A</u>:</dt><dd>diphenylmethane diisocyanate having an isomer
distribution comprising 44% by weight of the 4,4'-isomer,
54% by weight of the 2,4'-isomer and about 
2% by weight of the 2,2'-isomer. This diisocyanate has
an NCO content of about 33.6%, a functionality of
about 2.0 and a viscosity of less than about 25 mPa·s
at 25°C</dd><dt><u style="single">Isocyanate B</u>:</dt><dd>4,4'-diphenylmethane diisocyanate having an NCO
content of about 33.6%, a functionality of about 2.0
and a viscosity of less than about 25 mPa·s at 25°C</dd><dt><u style="single">Isocyanate C</u>:</dt><dd>an isocyanate prepolymer having an NCO group
content of about 23% and a viscosity of about 400-
700 mPa·s at 25°C, comprising the reaction product of
about 86.8% by weight of Isocyanate A and about
13.2% by weight of tripropylene glycol</dd><dt><u style="single">Isocyanate D</u>:</dt><dd>an isocyanate prepolymer having an NCO group
content of about 23%, a viscosity of between about
500 and about 800 mPa·s at 25°C and comprising the
reaction product of about 86.8% by weight of
Isocyanate B and about 13.2% by weight of
tripropylene glycol</dd><dt><u style="single">Isocyanate E</u>:</dt><dd>an isocyanate prepolymer having an NCO group
about 27.5% by weight of Isocyanate A, about 10% by
weight of Isocyanate B, and about 62.5% by weight of
Polyol 1</dd></dl></p><p num="0040">The following polyol blends were used in the examples:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="25"><dt><u style="single">Polyol Blend A</u> comprised:</dt><dd>63.53 pbw Polyol 1
18.18 pbw Polyol 3
9.09 pbw Polyol 5
9.09 pbw Baylith Paste L
0.10 pbw Dow Corning Antifoam 1500
0.005 pbw Catalyst A</dd></dl></p><p num="0041">Polyol Blend A was characterized by an equivalent weight of 267
and a functionality of 2.33.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="25"><dt><u style="single">Polyol Blend B</u> comprised:</dt><dd>52.43 pbw Polyol 2
28.23 pbw Polyol 4
10.08 pbw Polyol 5
9.07 pbw Baylith Paste L
0.13 pbw Dow Corning Antifoam 1500
0.005 pbw Catalyst A</dd></dl></p><p num="0042">Polyol Blend B was characterized by an equivalent weight of 281
and a functionality of 2.0.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="25"><dt><u style="single">Polyol Blend C</u> comprised:</dt><dd>47.19 pbw Polyol 2
25.41 pbw Polyol 4
18.15 pbw Polyol 5
9.07 pbw Baylith Paste L
0.13 pbw Dow Corning Antifoam 1500
0.005 pbw Catalyst A</dd></dl></p><p num="0043">Polyol Blend C was characterized by an equivalent weight of 191
and a functionality of 2.0.</p><p num="0044">The polyurethane castings in Examples 1-9, as set forth in Tables 1
and 2, were prepared according to the following procedure:

The polyol blend and the isocyanate were hand mixed at 25-30°C
for 1.5-2.0 minutes, and then cast into a 105-110°C book-case mold which
measured 8 in. x 16 in. x 0.125 in. and into button molds (also pre-heated
to 105-110°C). (One button mold was used for each example.) The cast
samples were allowed to cure at 105-110°C in the molds for 16 hours,
before being demolded. After 1 week at room temperature, the samples
were tested for various physical and mechanical properties. The results
are set forth in Tables 1 and 2 below. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry>Examples 1-3: 2,4'-rich MDI with decreasing NCO group contents</entry></row><row><entry>Example 4: Comparative</entry></row><row><entry>Example 5: decreasing 2,4'-isomer content of Example 2</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">Example 1</entry><entry align="left">Example 2</entry><entry align="left">Example 3</entry><entry align="left">Example 4</entry><entry align="left">Example 5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyol Blend A (grams)</entry><entry align="left">230</entry><entry align="left">200</entry><entry align="left">132</entry><entry align="left">230</entry><entry align="left">200</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Isocyanate A (grams)</entry><entry align="left">112.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Isocyanate C (grams)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">141.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Isocyanate E (grams)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">220</entry></row> <row><entry align="left">Isocyanate B (grams)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">112.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Isocyanate D (grams)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">75.1</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">NCO:OH Ratio</entry> <entry align="left">1.05</entry><entry align="left">1.05</entry><entry align="left">1.05</entry><entry align="left">1.05</entry><entry align="left">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compression Set (%)</entry><entry align="left">5.13</entry><entry align="left">1.83</entry><entry align="left">0.37</entry><entry align="left">12.9</entry><entry align="left">4.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Strength (psi)</entry><entry align="left">1072</entry><entry align="left">3222</entry><entry align="left">362</entry><entry align="left">1644</entry><entry align="left">2536</entry></row><row><entry align="left">100% Modulus (psi)</entry><entry align="left">334</entry><entry align="left">1552</entry><entry align="left">199</entry><entry align="left">981</entry><entry align="left">1970</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elongation (%)</entry><entry align="left">249</entry><entry align="left">280</entry><entry align="left">212</entry><entry align="left">188</entry><entry align="left">227</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Die C Tear (pli)</entry><entry align="left">97</entry><entry align="left">219</entry><entry align="left">88</entry><entry align="left">154</entry><entry align="left">254</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Taber Abrasion (wt. loss in mg/1000 cycles)</entry><entry align="left">273</entry><entry align="left">295</entry><entry align="left">131</entry><entry align="left">328</entry><entry align="left">248</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hardness Shore A (1 sec/5 sec)</entry><entry align="left">63/60</entry><entry align="left">89/86</entry><entry align="left">51/51</entry><entry align="left">85/83</entry><entry align="left">91/86</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry>Examples Using a Linear Polyol Blend: Examples 6-9 are comparative</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">Example 6</entry><entry align="left">Example 7</entry><entry align="left">Example 8</entry><entry align="left">Example 9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyol Blend B (grams)</entry><entry align="left">208</entry><entry align="left">208</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyol Blend C (grams)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">1776</entry><entry align="left">176</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Isocyanate C (grams)</entry><entry align="left">140.2</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">174.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Isocyanate D (grams)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">142</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">176.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">NCO:OH Ratio</entry><entry align="left">1.05</entry><entry align="left">1.05</entry><entry align="left">1.05</entry><entry align="left">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compression Set (%)</entry><entry align="left">42</entry><entry align="left">25</entry><entry align="left">79</entry><entry align="left">48</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Strength (psi)</entry><entry align="left">1691</entry><entry align="left">2178</entry><entry align="left">3224</entry><entry align="left">3292</entry></row><row><entry align="left">100% Modulus (psi)</entry><entry align="left">281</entry><entry align="left">687</entry><entry align="left">1197</entry><entry align="left">2299</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elongation (%)</entry><entry align="left">493</entry><entry align="left">358</entry><entry align="left">363</entry><entry align="left">271</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Die C Tear (pli)</entry><entry align="left">177</entry><entry align="left">263</entry><entry align="left">461</entry><entry align="left">447</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Taber Abrasion (wt. loss in mg/1000 cycles)</entry><entry align="left">230</entry><entry align="left">214</entry><entry align="left">252</entry><entry align="left">162</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hardness Shore A (1 sec/5 sec)</entry><entry align="left">65/58</entry><entry align="left">78/75</entry><entry align="left">88/81</entry><entry align="left">89/88</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0045">The polyurethane castings in Examples 10-11, as set forth in Table
3, were prepared according to the following procedure:

The polyol blend and the isocyanate were hand mixed at 25-30°C
for 1.5-2.0 minutes, and then cast into a room temperature book-case
mold which measured 8 in. x 16 in. x 0.125 in., and into room temperature
(i.e. 25-30°C ) button molds. (One button mold was used for each
example.) The cast samples were left in the molds and allowed to remain
there for 4 days at room temperature before demolding. Each sample was
then post-cured at 100°C for 16 hours. The samples were then post-cured
for an additional 7 days (i.e. 1 week) at room temperature, before being
tested for various physical and mechanical properties. The results are set
forth in Table 3 below. </p><p num="0046">Example 10 is representative of the present invention and
Example 11 is comparative.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">Example 10</entry><entry align="left">Example 11</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyol Blend A (grams)</entry><entry align="left">225</entry><entry align="left">225</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Isocyanate C (grams)</entry><entry align="left">159</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Isocyanate D (grams)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">163.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Post Cure</entry><entry align="left">100°C</entry><entry align="left">100°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">NCO:OH Ratio</entry><entry align="left">1.05</entry><entry align="left">1.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compression Set (%)</entry><entry align="left">5.4</entry><entry align="left">18.34</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Strength (psi)</entry><entry align="left">1881</entry><entry align="left">2026</entry></row><row><entry align="left">100% Modulus (psi)</entry><entry align="left">527</entry><entry align="left">1741</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elongation (%)</entry><entry align="left">260</entry><entry align="left">123</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Die C Tear (pli)</entry><entry align="left">158</entry><entry align="left">199</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Taber Abrasion (wt. loss in mg/1000 cycles)</entry><entry align="left">233</entry><entry align="left">142</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hardness Shore A (1 sec/5 sec)</entry><entry align="left">84/75</entry><entry align="left">89/86</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0047">Although the invention has been described in detail in the foregoing
for the purpose of illustration, it is to be understood that such detail is
solely for that purpose and that variations can be made therein by those
skilled in the art without departing from the spirit and scope of the
invention except as it may be limited by the claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process for producing a polyurethane elastomer having a
low compression set, comprising reacting:
<claim-text><claim-text>A) an isocyanate component comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>1) 20 to 100% by weight, based on 100% by weight of
component A), of methylene bis(phenyl isocyanate)
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) from 20 to 80% by weight of 4,4'-methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate),</claim-text><claim-text>(b) from 20 to 80% by weight of 2,4'-methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate),</claim-text><claim-text>(c) from 0.1 to 5% by weight of 2,2'-methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate),</claim-text></claim-text>
with the percents by weight of components A)1)(a),
A)1)(b) and A)1)(c) totaling 100% by weight of
component A)1),
and</claim-text><claim-text>2) from 0 to 80% by weight, based on 100% by weight of
component A), of an isocyanate-reactive compound
containing two hydroxyl groups and having a
molecular weight of 62 to 6,000;</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>B) an isocyanate-reactive component comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>1) from 40 to 80% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of component B), of an isocyanate-reactive
component containing hydroxyl and/or amine groups,
and having a molecular weight of more than 1,000,
and a functionality of about 3 to about 5,</claim-text><claim-text>2) from 10 to 40% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of component B), of an isocyanate-reactive
component containing from about 3 to about 5
hydroxyl-groups, and having a molecular weight of
about 800 or less;
and</claim-text><claim-text>3) from 5 to 40% by weight, based on 100% by weight of
component B), of an isocyanate-reactive component
containing about 2 hydroxyl groups, and having a
molecular weight of from about 62 to about 200;</claim-text></claim-text>
and, optionally,</claim-text><claim-text>C) one or more additives,</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein the components are processed via the one-shot process at an
isocyanate index of 90 to 130.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein the resultant polyurethane
elastomer is characterized by a compression set of less than about 10%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein A) said isocyanate
component comprises a prepolymer having an NCO group content of
about 8 to about 23%, a functionality of about 2, a urethane content of
about 2 to 15% and a viscosity of about 400 to about 5,000 mPa·s at 25°C,
and comprises the reaction product of A)1) and A)2).</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The process of Claim 3, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>A)1) comprises from 30 to 95% by weight of methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),
and</claim-text><claim-text>A)2) comprises from 5 to 70% by weight of an isocyanate-reactive
compound containing two hydroxyl groups and having a molecular
weight of 200 to 6,000.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The process of Claim 3, wherein A)1) said methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate) comprises
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) from 30 to 80% by weight of 4,4'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),</claim-text><claim-text>(b) from 20 to 70% by weight of 2,4'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),
and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) from 0.1 to 2.0% by weight of 2,2'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),</claim-text></claim-text>
with the %'s by weight of A)1)(a), A)1)(b) and A)1)(c) totaling 100% by
weight of A)1).</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The process of Claim 3, wherein A)1) said methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate) comprises
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) from 35 to 55% by weight of 4,4'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),</claim-text><claim-text>(b) from 45 to 65% by weight of 2,4'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),
and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) from 0.5 to 2.0% by weight of 2,2'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),
with the %'s by weight of A)1)(a), A)1)(b) and A)1)(c) totaling 100% by
weight of A)1).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein component B)1) has a
molecular weight of from about 2,000 to about 6,000 and a functionality of
about 3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein component B)2) has a
molecular weight of about 130 to about 600 and a functionality of about 3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein the resultant polyurethane
elastomer is post cured at a temperature of 80°C or higher.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein the resultant polyurethane
elastomer is post cured at a temperature of 100°C or higher.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein the isocyanate index is 95
to 110.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A polyurethane elastomer having a low compression set, and
which comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>A) an isocyanate component comprising:<claim-text><claim-text>1) 20 to 100% by weight, based on 100% by weight of
component A), of methylene bis(phenyl isocyanate)
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) from 20 to 80% by weight of 4,4'-methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate),</claim-text><claim-text>(b) from 20 to 80% by weight of 2,4'-methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate),</claim-text><claim-text>(c) from 0.1 to 5% by weight of 2,2'-methylene
bis(phenyl isocyanate),</claim-text></claim-text>
with the percents by weight of components A)1)(a),
A)1)(b) and A)1)(c) totaling 100% by weight of
component A)1);
and</claim-text><claim-text>2) from 0 to 80% by weight, based on 100% by weight of
component A), of an isocyanate-reactive compound
containing two hydroxyl groups and having a
molecular weight of 62 to 6,000;</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>B) an isocyanate-reactive component comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>1) from 40 to 80% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of component B), of an isocyanate-reactive
component containing hydroxyl and/or amine groups,
and having a molecular weight of more than 1,000,
and a functionality of about 3 to about 5,</claim-text><claim-text>2) from 10 to 40% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of component B), of an isocyanate-reactive
component containing from about 3 to about 5
hydroxyl-groups and having a molecular weight of
about 800 or less,
and</claim-text><claim-text>3) from 5 to 40% by weight, based on 100% by weight of
component B), of an isocyanate-reactive component
containing about 2 hydroxyl groups, and having a
molecular weight of from about 62 to 200;</claim-text></claim-text>
and, optionally,</claim-text><claim-text>C) one or more additives,
wherein the components are processed via the one-shot process at an
isocyanate index of 90 to 130.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The polyurethane elastomer of Claim 12, which is
characterized by a compression set of less than about 10%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The polyurethane elastomer of Claim 12, wherein A) said
isocyanate component comprises a prepolymer having an NCO group
content of about 8 to about 23%, a functionality of about 2, a urethane
content of about 2 to 15% and a viscosity of about 400 to about 5,000
mPa·s at 25°C, and comprises the reaction product of A)1) and A)2).</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The polyurethane elastomer of Claim 14, wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>A)1) comprises from 30 to 95% by weight of methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),
and</claim-text><claim-text>A)2) comprises from 5 to 70% by weight of an isocyanate-reactive
compound containing two hydroxyl groups and having a molecular
weight of 200 to 6,000.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The polyurethane elastomer of Claim 14, wherein A)1) said
methylene bis(phenyl isocyanate) comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) from 30 to 80% by weight of 4,4'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),</claim-text><claim-text>(b) from 20 to 70% by weight of 2,4'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),
and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) from 0.1 to 2.0% by weight of 2,2'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),</claim-text></claim-text>
with the %'s by weight of A)1)(a), A)1)(b) and A)1)(c) totaling 100% by
weight of A)1).</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The polyurethane elastomer of Claim 14, wherein A)1) said
methylene bis(phenyl isocyanate) comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) from 35 to 55% by weight of 4,4'-methylene bis(phenyl isocyanate),</claim-text><claim-text>(b) from 45 to 65% by weight of 2,4'-methylene bis(phenyl isocyanate),
and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) from 0.5 to 2.0% by weight of 2,2'-methylene bis(phenyl
isocyanate),</claim-text></claim-text>
with the %'s by weight of A)1)(a), A)1)(b) and A)1)(c) totaling 100% by
weight of A)1).</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The polyurethane elastomer of Claim 12, wherein component
B)1) has a molecular weight of from about 2,000 to about 6,000 and a
functionality of about 3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The polyurethane elastomer of Claim 12, wherein component
B)2) has a molecular weight of about 130 to about 600 and a functionality
of about 3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The polyurethane elastomer of Claim 12, wherein the
resultant polyurethane elastomer is post cured at a temperature of 80°C or
higher.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>The polyurethane of Claim 12, wherein the resultant
polyurethane elastomer is post cured at a temperature of 100°C or higher.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>The polyurethane elastomer of Claim 12, wherein the
isocyanate index is 95 to 110.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>