<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1006162-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1006162" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="27315328" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000607"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1006162-A1" status="new" fvid="22834618"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1006162</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000607</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99123940-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99123940</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991203</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-12645599-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>12645599</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990506</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-12645699-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>12645699</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990506</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-36189798-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>36189798</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981203</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/16        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/18        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/16</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/18</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Wässrige radierbare Tintenzusammensetzung für Schreibgeräte und Schreibgeräte die diese benutzen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Rubber-erasable aqueous ink composition for writing material and writing materials using the same</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition d'encre aqueuse effaçable pour accessoire d'écriture et accessoires d'écriture utilisant cette composition</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0061886-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0061886</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5120359-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5120359</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199301 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A18, AN 1993-004709 XP002132471 &amp; JP 04 332776 A (SAKURA KUREPASU KK), 19 November 1992 (1992-11-19)</text><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PILOT INK CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>THE PILOT INK CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>THE PILOT INK CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>3-17, Midorimachi Showa-ku</street><city>Nagoya-shi, Aichi-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HAYASHI HIROYUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KITO TSUTOMU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NAKAMURA HIROYUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HAYASHI, HIROYUKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KITO, TSUTOMU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NAKAMURA, HIROYUKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hayashi, Hiroyuki, The Pilot Ink Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>3-17, Midorimachi, Showa-ku</street><city>Nagoya-shi, Aichi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kito, Tsutomu, The Pilot Ink Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>3-17, Midorimachi, Showa-ku</street><city>Nagoya-shi, Aichi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Nakamura, Hiroyuki, The Pilot Ink Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>3-17, Midorimachi, Showa-ku</street><city>Nagoya-shi, Aichi</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name><address><street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street><city>81925 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition contains water, a water-soluble polar solvent, and
a particulate adhesive colored resin. The particulate
adhesive colored resin contains a pigment and an adhesive resin
which is adhesive on at least a part of a surface thereof. The
particulate adhesive colored resin has a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 70% by weight
of all the particles.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">1. Field of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a rubber-erasable
aqueous ink for a writing material composition and writing
materials including same incorporated therein. More
particularly, the present invention relates to a rubber-erasable
aqueous ink for a writing material composition which
gives onto paper writing that can be easily erased by an eraser
but can be retained thereon even when normally rubbed with
finger or paper. Even more particularly, the present invention
relates to a rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition which, when heated, exhibits a permanent fixability
such that writing cannot be erased even when vigorously rubbed.</p><heading><u style="single">2. Description of the Related Art</u></heading><p num="0002">Many proposals have been heretofore made on ink
compositions which provide writing that can be erased by an
eraser. These ink compositions can be roughly divided into two
groups, i.e., oil ink including a colorant and a vehicle
containing a resin dissolved in an organic solvent as a main
solvent and aqueous ink including these components dissolved
in water as a main solvent. Examples of the oil ink include
rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material compositions
for ball point pen including a pigment, a specific organic
solvent and an elastomer resin having rubber elasticity as
disclosed in US Patents 4,389,499, 4,390,646 and 4,391,927.
The foregoing ink composition includes a resin having a high
molecular weight and thus exhibits a high viscosity. In this 
arrangement, it is tried to prevent the pigment from penetrating
deep into paper together with the solvent, making the writing
formed by the pigment on paper erasable by an eraser. However,
the foregoing ink composition can be practically erased by an
eraser for a short period of time after writing but can be erased
less gradually with time.</p><p num="0003">Another disadvantage of the foregoing oil ink composition
is that since the solvent used is hardly volatile and thus is
normally slow-drying after applied to paper, the ink
composition which has just been applied, even when lightly
rubbed with finger or hand, causes the undried portion to move
to blank area (area around the writing), causing remarkable
stain on paper as well as on finger or hand, even on clothing.</p><p num="0004">On the other hand, many proposals have been recently made
on rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition including water as a main solvent. One of these
proposals is a rubber-erasable ink composition including a
pigment in an amount of from 1 to 50%, a resin having a
film-forming temperature of not lower than 40°C in an amount
of from 3 to 50%, an organic solvent in an amount of 0.5 to 50%
and water in an amount of from 7 to 60% based on the total weight
of ink as disclosed in JP-A-4-332776. Since the foregoing ink
composition includes a general-purpose pigment that can easily
penetrate deep into paper, it can be fairly erased by an eraser.
Further, since the resin cannot form a film at room temperature,
the film (writing) can be poorly preserved.</p><p num="0005">Another proposal is an erasable ink composition including
a water-insoluble polymer-capsuled colorant obtained by 
subjecting at least one emulsion-polymerizable monomer
including a colorant dissolved therein to polymerization under
emulsion polymerization conditions as disclosed in US Patent
5,661,197. In this proposal, a capsuled colorant including a
colorant incorporated in a water-insoluble polymer is prepared
under emulsion polymerization conditions. The resulting
capsuled colorant includes finely divided particles having a
diameter of not more than 1 µm. As a result, when the ink
composition is applied to paper, the finely divided colorant
particles penetrate deep into paper and are trapped by paper.
Thus, the foregoing ink composition can be poorly erased by an
eraser. Further, the water-insoluble dye to be incorporated
in the capsuled colorant is liable to extraction in the aqueous
vehicle with the water-soluble polar solvent or surfactant in
the aqueous vehicle. The dye thus extracted dyes the surface
of paper to an extent such that the trace of writing can be left
unerased even when rubbed with an eraser.</p><p num="0006">A further proposal is an erasable ink having a viscosity
of from 5 to 35 mPa · s including a resin having a film-forming
temperature of not higher than 0°C and a glass transition
temperature of not higher than 0°C, a particulate colored resin
having a particle diameter of from 1 µm to 20 µm and water as
disclosed in US Patent 5,621,021. In an attempt to prevent the
trace of the writing from being left unerased when rubbed, the
foregoing erasable ink includes colored resin particles having
a great diameter which can less penetrate deep into paper.
Nevertheless, the particulate resin used has a particle
diameter which is not so small enough and thus can easily 
penetrate deep into paper. Thus, the particulate colored resin
exhibits an enhanced adhesivity to the surface of paper and to
each other. Accordingly, the foregoing erasable ink differs
greatly in rubber-erasability from paper to paper.</p><p num="0007">Further, the use of the foregoing conventional
rubber-erasable ink compositions for important document such
as official document which allows no alteration and document
containing date and amount of money is limited.</p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0008">It is an object of the present invention to provide ink
composition which can eliminate the foregoing disadvantages of
the foregoing erasable ink compositions, that is, can not only
be fairly erased by an eraser but also be fairly retained on
paper.</p><p num="0009">As a result of the inventor's extensive studies of such
ink composition, the inventors paid their attention to the fact
that the use of finely divided particles having a particle
diameter of not greater than about 1 µm as at least one of
coloring element and bonding element has an adverse effect on
the rubber-erasability of the conventional ink compositions.</p><p num="0010">The foregoing particles concerning coloring element and
bonding element can penetrate less deep into paper or can easily
prevent themselves from penetrating deep into paper if they have
a sufficient particle diameter. Taking into account the normal
distribution of the particles which have just been prepared,
if the particles are distributed in a range of from 2 µm to 20 
µm, they can almost prevent themselves from penetrating deep
into paper. These conditions must be applied both to coloring
particles and bonding particles. In other words, even if the
particle diameter of the coloring agent falls within the range
of from 2 µm to 20 µm, when the particle diameter of the bonding
particles falls within the range of from 0.1 µm to 1 µm as in
general-purpose resin dispersion, the bonding particles
penetrate deep into paper to strongly fix the coloring particles
to the surface of paper from behind, making it impossible to
obtain a good rubber-erasability. On the contrary, if the
particulate coloring agent has a particle diameter of from 0.1
µm to 1 µm, the coloring agent itself penetrates deep into paper
regardless of the particle diameter of the bonding particles,
making it impossible to obtain a good rubber-erasability. It
can therefore be presumed that all the conventional ink
compositions are liable to penetration of particulate coloring
agent and/or adhesive into paper and thus can attain neither
good rubber-erasability nor high fretting resistance. It was
thus found concerning the relationship between the penetration
of particles into paper and the particle diameter that if the
particles concerning coloring element and bonding element have
a particle diameter of not less than about 2 µm, the penetration
of particles into paper can be lessened or eliminated. The
present invention has thus been worked out.</p><p num="0011">Further, an unprecedented knowledge was found that the
incorporation of "heat-sensitive element" in a particulate
colored ink composition containing coloring agent particles and
bonding particles or the incorporation of "heat-sensitive 
element" having particles distributed in a particle diameter
range of from 2 µm to 20 µm in an ink composition containing
particles having coloring properties and adhesive properties
makes it possible to provide a writing that can be permanently
fixed when subjected to heat treatment. The present invention
has thus been worked out.</p><heading><u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u></heading><p num="0012">In the accompanying drawings:
<sl><li>Fig. 1 is an enlarged vertical section of writing formed
by the rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition of the present invention including a particulate
adhesive colored resin incorporated therein;</li><li>Fig. 2 is an enlarged vertical section of writing formed
by the rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition of the present invention including a particulate
colored resin and a particulate adhesive resin incorporated
therein;</li><li>Fig. 3 is an enlarged vertical section of writing formed
by the rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition of the present invention including a particulate
thermoplastic colored resin and a particulate adhesive resin
incorporated therein;</li><li>Fig. 4 is an enlarged vertical section illustrating the
writing of Fig. 3 which has been subjected to heat treatment;</li><li>Fig. 5 is an enlarged vertical section of writing formed
by the rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition of the present invention including a particulate 
adhesive colored resin and a particulate thermoplastic resin
incorporated therein; and</li><li>Fig. 6 is an enlarged vertical section illustrating the
writing of Fig. 5 which has been subjected to heat treatment.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">DETATLED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0013">The present invention will be described in detail as
follows.</p><p num="0014">According to the present invention, a rubber-erasable
aqueous ink for a writing material composition includes a
particulate adhesive colored resin, water and a water-soluble
polar solvent. The particulate adhesive colored resin is made
of a pigment and an adhesive resin. At least a part of the
surface of the particulate adhesive colored resin is adhesive.
The particulate adhesive colored resin has a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 70% by weight
of all the particles. Further, it is preferable that a
rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material composition
as defined above, includes a particulate thermoplastic resin
having a particle diameter distribution such that the amount
of particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm
is not less than 70% by weight of all the particles.</p><p num="0015">Further, according to the present invention, the
rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material composition
including at least a particulate colored resin containing a
pigment, a particulate adhesive resin, water, and a water-soluble
polar solvent, wherein the particulate colored resin 
and particulate adhesive resin each having a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 70% by weight
of all the particles. Moreover, the rubber-erasable aqueous
ink for a writing material composition as defined above, wherein
the particulate colored resin is a particulate colored
thermoplastic resin.</p><p num="0016">Furthermore, the rubber-erasable aqueous ink includes a
shear-thinning agent incorporated therein and exhibiting a
viscosity of from 25 to 160 mPa ·s (determined at 25°C by means
of an EMD type viscometer) and a shear-thinning index of from
0.1 to 0.7 at 100 rpm. The present invention further provides
a ballpoint pen, a marking pen and the like using this
rubber-erasable aqueous ink.</p><p num="0017">In a first aspect of the present invention, a rubber-erasable
aqueous ink for a writing material composition
including a particulate adhesive colored resin incorporated
therein, the particulate adhesive colored resin having a
particle diameter distribution such that the amount of
particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is
not less than 70% by weight of all the particles.</p><p num="0018">The particulate adhesive colored resin will be further
described hereinafter.</p><p num="0019">In order to lessen or eliminate the penetration of
particles (pigment and/or resin) into paper, the particulate
adhesive colored resin includes particles containing both
coloring element and bonding element having a particle diameter
of from 2 µm to 20 µm which exhibit adhesive properties to satisfy 
both requirements for good rubber-erasability and high fretting
resistance (preservability of writing at ordinary times).</p><p num="0020">A great feature of the foregoing rubber-erasable aqueous
ink for a writing material composition is that the particulate
adhesive colored resin used exhibits the following properties:
<sl><li>(1) Extremely low penetration into paper; and</li><li>(2) Adhesive properties satisfying both good rubber-erasability
and high fretting resistance.</li></sl></p><p num="0021">In other words, the use of such a particulate adhesive
colored resin essentially makes it possible to eliminate the
necessity of adding a resin or adhesive for providing adhesive
properties. Further, the use of the particulate adhesive
colored resin essentially makes it possible to eliminate the
necessity of adding a coloring agent for coloring. In other
words, again, the foregoing particulate adhesive colored resin
itself has two functions, i.e., bonding and coloring.</p><p num="0022">Referring to the writing formed by the foregoing
rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material composition,
the inventors adduce as follows the reason why the writing thus
formed exhibits both a good rubber-erasability and a high
fretting resistance at the same time. In other words, when the
writing formed by the ink composition of the present invention
is observed under microscope, the particulate adhesive colored
resin 1 is, of course, observed present on the surface of paper
10. The most of the particles 1 are observed point-bonded to
each other as shown in Fig. 1. Further, the gap between the
particles is occupied by the space. Accordingly, when rubbed
with an eraser, the writing can be fairly erased because it is 
formed by aggregates of the adhesive colored resin particles
1. When normally rubbed, the writing cannot be peeled off up
to a predetermined frictional force because it is bonded to
paper by a predetermined adhesion developed by the bonding of
the particulate adhesive colored resin 1 to the surface of paper
10.</p><p num="0023">Accordingly, the foregoing writing is similar to writing
formed by pencil in characteristics and thus can be erased by
an eraser. Further, the foregoing writing can withstand
ordinary friction of sheets of paper or fretting by hand or
finger during writing. The preservability or fretting
resistance of writing at ordinary times is almost equal to that
of the writing formed by a pencil having a hardness of "HB" or
"H".</p><p num="0024">The adhesive properties of the foregoing particulate
adhesive colored resin are meant to indicate that the
particulate material can be erased by an eraser but exhibits
the lowest required adhesivity with respect to light fretting.
In other words, if the particulate adhesive colored resin
exhibits too strong an adhesivity, it can be less erased by an
eraser or cannot be fairly erased unless rubbed by an eraser
with a strong frictional force. On the contrary, if the
particulate adhesive colored resin exhibits too weak an
adhesivity, it can be easily peeled even when lightly rubbed.
Accordingly, the adhesivity of the particulate adhesive colored
resin needs to be adjusted such that a good rubber-erasability
and a high fretting resistance can be attained at the same time. </p><p num="0025">The foregoing adhesive properties are not determined by
the glass transition point (Tg) of the adhesive resin alone.
In general, the adhesive properties are determined by various
factors. Examples of the main factors determining the adhesive
properties include characteristics of resin itself, such as
crystallizability, fluidity, glass transition point,
molecular weight and crosslink density. Many such factors have
complicated participation in the determination of the adhesive
properties. For example, styrene-butadiene rubber (SBR)
having a glass transition point of - 58°C exhibits no adhesivity
at room temperature and thus is rubber-like and brittle. On
the other hand, a butyl polyacrylate having a glass transition
point of - 45°C exhibits a strong adhesivity at room
temperature.</p><p num="0026">The foregoing particulate adhesive colored resin is not
specifically limited in its preparation method so far as the
particulate colored resin containing a pigment is adhesive at
least on the surface thereof. The foregoing particulate
adhesive colored resin can be obtained by a known technique for
synthesis of resins. Examples of the form of the particulate
adhesive colored resin include a structure wherein the entire
resin constituting the particulate colored resin is a
homogeneous polymer composition having an adhesivity, a
structure composed of a particulate colored resin the surface
of which is entirely coated with a polymer composition having
an adhesivity, and a structure composed of a particulate colored
resin a part of the surface of which is formed by a polymer
composition having a continuous or discontinuous adhesivity. </p><p num="0027">The preparation of the foregoing particulate adhesive
colored resin can be accomplished by suspension polymerization
method, suspension polycondensation method, suspension
addition reaction method, seed polymerization method,
dispersion polymerization method or submerged drying method.
In order to obtain the foregoing structure wherein the entire
resin constituting the particulate colored resin is a
homogeneous polymer composition having an adhesivity,
suspension polymerization method or submerged solvent
evaporation method can be mainly used. On the other hand, in
order to obtain the structure composed of a particulate colored
resin a part or whole of the surface of which is formed by a
polymer composition having a continuous or discontinuous
adhesivity, suspension polymerization method, suspension
polycondensation method, suspension addition reaction method,
seed polymerization method, dispersion polymerization method
and submerged solvent evaporation method can be used in proper
combination. Alternatively, a secondary surface modification
method can be used.</p><p num="0028">As an index for providing the particulate adhesive
colored resin with a proper adhesivity, it is preferred that
the particulate adhesive colored resin thus obtained exhibit
a glass transition point of lower than 40°C. If the adhesive
resin used exhibits a glass transition point of not lower than
40°C, the resulting writing exhibits a weak adhesivity at room
temperature and thus cannot attain a desired fretting
resistance. </p><p num="0029">The polymerization method concerning the preparation of
the particulate adhesive colored resin will be further
described hereinafter. Suspension polymerization method is a
method by emulsifying or dispersing a water-insoluble monomer
or oligomer having a pigment dispersed therein in water as fine
oil droplets in the presence of a dispersing agent, and then
subjecting the emulsion or dispersion to polymerization under
suspension polymerization conditions in the presence of a
lipophilic initiator. In general, it is said that the size of
particles obtained by the suspension polymerization method
ranges from scores of micrometer to several millimeters. By
properly selecting the kind of emulsifier, dispersion
stabilizer and viscosity adjuster, a particulate adhesive
colored resin having a particle diameter distribution of from
2 µm to 20 µm desirable for the present invention can be
synthesized.</p><p num="0030">Suspension polycondensation method or suspension
addition reaction method is a method which includes dispersing
a pigment in a polycondensable or addition-reactive monomer or
prepolymer optionally in the presence of a solvent, emulsifying
or dispersing the dispersion as fine oil droplets in the
presence of a hydrophilic dispersing agent, and then subjecting
the emulsion or dispersion to polymerization by
polycondensation reaction or addition reaction. Seed
polymerization method is a method which includes allowing a
previously synthesized particulate resin as a seed to absorb
the same or different kind of a monomer for further
polymerization so that the seed grows. In the present invention, 
seed polymerization method can be preferably used in the
preparation of a particulate adhesive colored resin by
secondary treatment.</p><p num="0031">Dispersion polymerization method is a method which
includes polymerization of a monomer in a solvent which
dissolves the monomer therein but doesn't dissolve a polymer
therein in the presence of a dispersion stabilizer so that the
polymer thus produced is precipitated to obtain particles.
Similarly to the seed polymerization method, the dispersion
polymerization method can be preferably used mainly in the
preparation of a particulate adhesive colored resin by
secondary treatment.</p><p num="0032">The foregoing secondary treatment is a treatment which
includes modifying primary particles (including a pigment and
a resin) obtained so that they are rendered adhesive regardless
of whether or they are adhesive.</p><p num="0033">Submerged solvent evaporation method is a method which
includes subjecting a dispersion obtained by dispersing a
pigment in a polymer dissolved in a solvent to suspension
emulsification in water in the presence of a hydrophilic
dispersing agent, and then distilling the solvent off the
emulsion under heating or reduced pressure to obtain a
particulate polymer. Similarly to the suspension
polymerization method, the submerged solvent evaporation
method can be used mainly in the synthesis of a particulate
adhesive colored resin having a homogeneous polymer
composition. </p><p num="0034">A preferred polymerization method for obtaining the
particulate adhesive colored resin of the present invention is
suspension polymerization method.</p><p num="0035">The particle diameter of the particulate adhesive colored
resin will be further described hereinafter.</p><p num="0036">The particulate adhesive colored resin to be incorporated
in the rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition of the present invention needs to have a particle
diameter distribution such that the amount of particles having
a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 70%
by weight of all the particles, preferably the amount of
particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 15 µm is
not less than 80% by weight of all the particles.</p><p num="0037">The particle diameter and the rubber-erasability of the
foregoing particulate adhesive colored resin are closely
related to each other. If the proportion of particles having
a particle diameter of less than 2 µm is too great, the proportion
of particles penetrating into the gap between paper fibers is
remarkably great, making it impossible to obtain a good
rubber-erasability. On the contrary, if the proportion of
particles having a particle diameter of greater than 2 µm is
too great, the resulting writing can be easily peeled off when
rubbed with hand or finger, making it difficult to attain a
satisfactory fretting resistance. Further, the resulting ink
can be hardly discharged from the outlet of various writing
materials such as fiber pen, plastic pen, felt tip and ball tip.</p><p num="0038">The particulate adhesive colored resin obtained by the
foregoing various polymerization method may be optionally 
subjected to dry classification or wet classification such as
centrifugal sedimentation so that the particle diameter
distribution thereof satisfies the foregoing requirements.</p><p num="0039">The wet classification can be accomplished by subjecting
the dispersion of the particulate material in a medium such as
water to classification by centrifugal sedimentation or natural
sedimentation method. The removal of coarse grains can be
effectively accomplished by filtration through a filter paper,
filter or the like.</p><p num="0040">On the other hand, the dry classification can be
accomplished by subjecting a dried particulate material to
classification by means of a machine such as variable impactor,
cyclon, classiclon, turbo classifier and micron separator.
Classification may be repeated by a plurality of times to obtain
a desired particle size distribution. The dry classification
is used also in the classification of toner for
electrophotographic copy.</p><p num="0041">The use of the foregoing classification methods singly
or in combination makes it possible to obtain a particulate
material having a particle diameter distribution such that the
amount of particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to
20 µm is not less than 70% by weight of all the particles.
Further, in order to obtain a particulate material having a more
uniform particle diameter, i.e., particulate material
including particles the diameter of which falls within a narrow
range, the foregoing classification may be repeated.
Alternatively, a method may be used involving the expansion of
undesirable particle diameter range. </p><p num="0042">However, since the foregoing particulate adhesive
colored resin normally stays adhesive, it can be hardly
subjected to dry classification in general. Therefore, the
particles are preferably adjusted such that the amount of
particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is
not less than 70% by weight of all the particles as much as
possible during its preparation. If classification is
required, wet classification may be used. For example,
filtration by a filter paper, filter or the like or centrifugal
sedimentation is preferably used.</p><p num="0043">The reactive monomer to be used in the preparation of the
particulate adhesive colored resin by radical polymerization
such as suspension polymerization, seed polymerization and
dispersion polymerization will be further described
hereinafter.</p><p num="0044">As the reactive monomer to be used in the present
invention there may be used a substantially water-insoluble or
difficultly water-soluble reactive monomer.</p><p num="0045">Examples of radical-polymerizable monofunctional
monomer employable as such include acrylic acid esters such as
ethyl acrylate, methyl acrylate, n-propyl acrylate, i-propyl
acrylate, n-butyl acrylate, i-butyl acrylate, t-butyl acrylate,
amyl acrylate, hexyl acrylate, 2-ethylhexyl acrylate,
cyclohexyl acrylate, n-octyl acrylate, nonyl acrylate, decyl
acrylate, undecyl acrylate, lauryl acrylate, myristyl acrylate,
cetyl acrylate, stearyl acrylate, 2-methoxyethyl acrylate,
2-ethoxyethyl acrylate, benzyl acrylate, 2-hydroxyethyl
acrylate and glycidyl acrylate, methacrylic acid esters such 
as methyl methacrylate, ethyl methacrylate, n-propyl
methacrylate, i-propyl methacrylate, n-butyl methacrylate,
i-butyl methacrylate, t-butyl methacrylate, amyl methacrylate,
hexyl methacrylate, 2-ethylhexyl methacrylate, cyclohexyl
methacrylate, n-octyl methacrylate, nonyl methacrylate, decyl
methacrylate, undecyl methacrylate, lauryl methacrylate,
myristyl methacrylate, cetyl methacrylate, stearyl
methacrylate, 2-methoxyethyl methacrylate, 2-ethoxyethyl
methacrylate, benzyl methacrylate, 2-hydroxyethyl
methacrylate, and glycidyl methacrylate; aromatic monomers
such as styrene, α-methylstyrene, β-methylstyrene,
vinyltoluene, t-butylstyrene, chlorostyrene, vinylbenzyl
chloride and vinyl pyridine; unsaturated nitriles such as
acrylonitrile, and unsaturated esters of saturated carboxylic
acid such as vinyl acetate. The prefixes n, i and t in the
foregoing monomers indicate normal, iso and tertiary,
respectively.</p><p num="0046">These monofunctional monomers may be used singly or in
the form of proper mixture depending on the desired adhesivity.
A hydrophilic monomer such as acrylic acid and methacrylic acid
may be optionally added in an amount of not more than 5% by weight
based on the total weight of monomers to provide the suspended
particles with dispersion stability.</p><p num="0047">Examples of polyfunctional monomer employable herein
include ethylene glycol dimethacrylate, diethylene glycol
dimethacrylate, neopentyl glycol dimethacrylate, trimethylol
propane trimethacrylate, pentaerythritol tetramethacrylate,
ethylene glycol diacrylate, diethylene glycol diacrylate, 
neopentyl glycol diacrylate, trimethylol propane triacrylate,
pentaerythritol tetraacrylate, divinylbenzene, triethylene
glycol divinyl ether, butadiene, and isoprene.</p><p num="0048">In the present invention, a monofunctional monomer alone
may be subjected to polymerization free from polyfunctional
monomer. In practice, however, the monofunctional monomer is
preferably used in combination with a bifunctional or
polyfunctional monomer to enhance the physical strength of the
particulate adhesive colored resin. The ratio of
polyfunctional monomer to monofunctional monomer is preferably
from 2: 100 to 10 : 100. If the proportion of the polyfunctional
monomer falls below 2, the resulting particulate material
exhibits a reduced physical strength and, when rubbed with an
eraser, can be destroyed to cause the pigment to be exposed,
easily staining the surface of paper. On the contrary, if the
proportion of the polyfunctional monomer exceeds 10, the
resulting particulate material tends to have a reduced
adhesivity, making it impossible to obtain a desired fretting
resistance.</p><p num="0049">Further, the addition of the polyfunctional monomer also
makes a great contribution to the stability of the particulate
adhesive colored resin during preparation or in the ink
composition. In other words, the adhesive colored resin
particles can easily be aggregated to each other because they
stay adhesive at room temperature and have a relatively great
particle diameter. In order to eliminate or lessen these
difficulties, the polyfunctional monomer can be used in an 
amount defined above to provide the particulate material with
an enhanced physical strength and hence an enhanced stability.</p><p num="0050">Examples of the initiator to be used in the foregoing
polymerization method include the following substantially
water-insoluble or difficultly water-soluble compounds. The
use of a water-soluble initiator causes emulsion polymerization
reaction, resulting in the formation of fine particles having
a diameter of not more than 1 µm. Thus, such a water-soluble
initiator is not suitable for the preparation of the particulate
adhesive colored resin of the present invention.</p><p num="0051">Examples of the initiator employable herein include
organic peroxides such as benzoyl peroxide, t-butyl benzoate,
lauroyl peroxide, m-toluyl peroxide, t-butyl peroxypivalate,
cumyl peroxy neodecanoate, octanoyl peroxide, decanoyl
peroxide and t-butyl peroxy isopropyl carbonate, azo compounds
such as 2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile, 2,2'-azobis(2,4-dimethylvaleronitrile),
2,2'-azobispropionitrile, 2,2'-azobisvaleronitrile
and 1,1'-azobis(cyclohexane-1-carbonitrile),
and other ordinary free radical-generating
compounds.</p><p num="0052">The method for obtaining the particulate adhesive colored
resin by suspension polycondensation or suspension addition
reaction will be further described hereinafter. In the former
method, a reactive monomer, oligomer or prepolymer can be used.
As such a compound there may be used a resin selected from the
group consisting of acrylic resin, acryl polyol, epoxy resin,
urethane resin, acrylurethane resin and silicone resin which
becomes adhesive after reacted. In some detail, a pigment is 
dispersed in a solution containing the foregoing reactive resin.
A crosslinking agent is further added to the dispersion as
necessary. The dispersion is then emulsified in a dispersant
containing a dispersing agent to a desired particle diameter.
Thereafter, the reaction temperature is raised to accelerate
the reaction. In this manner, the desired particulate adhesive
colored resin can be obtained.</p><p num="0053">Referring to the method for obtaining the particulate
adhesive colored resin by submerged solvent evaporation, a
pigment is uniformly dispersed in a solution of a polymer having
an adhesivity in a water-insoluble solvent. The dispersion is
then emulsified in a dispersant containing a hydrophilic
dispersing agent to a desired particle diameter. Thereafter,
the evaporation can be distilled off under heating or reduced
pressure to obtain the desired particulate adhesive colored
resin. If necessary, a crosslinking agent is added to the
material before or after emulsification to modify the physical
properties of the original polymer. The polymer to be used in
the submerged solvent evaporation method is not specifically
limited so far as it is adhesive. In practice, however, any
of acrylic acid ester resins, acryl styrene copolymer resins,
acrylic acid ester copolymer resins, methacrylic acid ester
resins, methacrylic acid ester copolymer resins, ethylenevinyl
acetate resins, ethylene-acryl copolymer resins, vinyl
acetate resins, polyester resins and alkyd resins may be used.</p><p num="0054">The emulsification in the foregoing submerged solvent
evaporation method may be accomplished by phase reversion
method. </p><p num="0055">Referring to the adjustment of the adhesivity of the
particulate adhesive colored resin of the present invention,
a resin having a desired viscosity can be obtained by (1)
changing the kind of monomers having a latent adhesivity or
mixing these monomers to obtain a desired adhesive resin or (2)
adjusting the amount of polyfunctional monomer (crosslinking
monomer). In order to further adjust the adhesivity of the
particulate adhesive colored resin, a tackifier such as rosin,
rosin derivative, coumarone-indene resin, polyterpene resin,
nonreactive phenol resin and petroleum hydrocarbon resin may
be added. Alternatively, a plasticizer such as mineral oil,
liquid polybutene, lanolin and dibasic acid ester, a pigment
or an extender pigment may be properly added.</p><p num="0056">The particulate adhesive colored resin may includes a
pigment incorporated therein as a coloring means. This is
because a dye is disadvantageous in that if used as a coloring
agent, it moves from the particulate adhesive colored resin to
paper, giving stain that cannot be erased even with an eraser.</p><p num="0057">Referring to the method for coloring the particulate
adhesive resin, the pigment is dispersed in a monomer, oligomer,
prepolymer or polymer in the presence of a dispersing agent
optionally with a solvent added thereto. Thereafter, various
particulate adhesive colored resins including a pigment
incorporated therein are prepared according to various reaction
processes. The pigment may be uniformly dispersed in the
particulate material or may be unevenly localized in the
particulate material. </p><p num="0058">Examples of the foregoing pigment include organic
pigments such as azo pigment, anthraquinone pigment, condensed
polyazo pigment, thioindigo pigment, metal complex pigment,
phthalocyanine pigment, perynone pigment, perylene pigment,
dioxazine pigment and quinacridone pigment, and inorganic
pigments such as carbon black, aniline black, ultramarine,
chrome yellow pigment, titanium oxide and iron oxide. These
pigments may be properly used singly or in admixture as
necessary. Further, as a special pigment there may be used a
fluorescent pigment, metal powder pigment, pearl pigment,
light-storing pigment, reversibly heat-decolorable pigment,
electrically-conductive pigment or the like. The foregoing
pigments may be subjected to surface treatment by a known method
for the purpose of enhancing the dispersibility in the solution
of monomer or the like.</p><p num="0059">The foregoing particulate adhesive colored resin is
preferably incorporated in an amount of from 5 to 35% by weight
based on the ink composition. If the amount of the particulate
adhesive colored resin falls below 5% by weight, a good color
density cannot be obtained. On the contrary, if the amount of
the particulate adhesive colored resin exceeds 35% by weight,
the proportion of solid content in the ink composition is raised,
occasionally preventing smooth discharge of ink. Accordingly,
the added amount of the particulate adhesive colored resin can
be properly determined within the above defined range depending
on the desired color density or purpose of the particulate
adhesive colored resin itself. </p><p num="0060">Two or more such particulate adhesive colored resins
having different adhesivities, color tones, color densities and
particle diameter distributions may be used in admixture as
necessary.</p><p num="0061">Further, the proportion of the pigment in the particulate
adhesive colored resin is preferably from 2 to 30% by weight.
In particular, a particulate adhesive colored resin having a
pigment homogeneously dispersed therein can be hardly adjusted
particularly in its particle diameter if the pigment content
exceeds 30% by weight. On the contrary, if the pigment content
falls below 2% by weight, a writing showing a good color density
can be hardly obtained. For a heterogeneous particulate
adhesive colored resin, too, the same conditions can be used
during the preparation of primary particles.</p><p num="0062">Further, the ink composition of the present invention may
includes a nonadhesive particulate colored material having the
same particle diameter distribution as the particulate adhesive
colored resin for the purpose of giving complementary colors
or adjusting adhesivity. Such a nonadhesive particulate
colored material may be incorporated in a weight proportion of
not more than 40 per 100 of the particulate adhesive colored
resin as necessary.</p><p num="0063">The foregoing rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition includes a particulate thermoplastic
resin incorporated therein having the particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 70% by weight
of all the particles In this arrangement, the resulting writing, 
when heated by a heating machine such as iron or under a heat
roller as in copying machine, can be provided with a permanent
fixability such that it cannot be erased even when rubbed with
eraser or finger.</p><p num="0064">The particulate thermoplastic resin will be further
described hereinafter.</p><p num="0065">Specific examples of the resin constituting the foregoing
particulate thermoplastic resin include thermoplastic resins
such as styrene resin, acrylic resin, epoxy resin, polyester
resin, styrene-acryl copolymer resin, polyvinyl chloride resin,
polyamide, urethane resin, polymethyl methacrylate, polyol
resin, acryl-urethane copolymer, phenolic resin, polyethylene,
polyacrylonitrile, styrene-butadiene copolymer and
acrylonitrile-butadiene copolymer. The resin constituting
the foregoing particulate thermoplastic resin is limited to
these compounds. Any compounds which can be used as resin
component for electrophotographic toner may be used.</p><p num="0066">The preparation of the foregoing particulate
thermoplastic resin can be accomplished by any known method for
the preparation of electrophotographic toner such as grinding
method and polymerization method.</p><p num="0067">In order to obtain the particulate thermoplastic resin
of the present invention having a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 70% by weight
of all the particles, grinding method, suspension
polymerization method or dispersion polymerization method may
be preferably used. Emulsion polymerization method causes the 
formation of fine particles having a particle diameter
distribution such that most of the particles have a particle
diameter of not more than 1 µm and thus is not appropriate for
the preparation of the particulate resin of the present
invention.</p><p num="0068">The particulate thermoplastic resin may be colored with
the foregoing pigment to enhance the density of the writing.
Alternatively, a particulate thermoplastic resin which has been
separately colored may be added to the particulate
thermoplastic resin to enhance the density and fixability of
the writing.</p><p num="0069">Referring to desirable thermal properties of the
particulate thermoplastic resin, the particulate
thermoplastic resin exhibits a softening point of from 60°C to
180°C and a melt flow index (MI) of from 0.1 to 30, preferably
from 0.1 to 20.</p><p num="0070">The preparation of the particulate thermoplastic resin
by polymerization method will be described hereinafter.</p><p num="0071">The foregoing particulate thermoplastic resin is
preferably prepared by subjecting a radical-polymerizable
monomer to at least one polymerization selected from the group
consisting of suspension polymerization, dispersion
polymerization and seed polymerization.</p><p num="0072">The reactive monomers and radical initiators to be used
in the preparation of the foregoing thermoplastic resin by
radical polymerization such as suspension polymerization, seed
polymerization and dispersion polymerization may be selected 
from the previously mentioned starting materials from which the
particulate adhesive colored resin is prepared.</p><p num="0073">The preparation of the particulate thermoplastic resin
by grinding method can be accomplished by a process including
melt-mixing the foregoing thermoplastic resin over a heat roll
or extruder, coarsely processing the material into chip, and
then atomizing the chip by means of a grinder.</p><p num="0074">More particularly, a known method for the preparation of
ground electrophotographic toner may be used.</p><p num="0075">The foregoing particulate thermoplastic resin can be
adjusted by wet classification method or dry classification
method to have a desired particle diameter distribution.</p><p num="0076">As the wet or dry classification method there may be used
one described above.</p><p num="0077">The content and weight proportion of the particulate
adhesive colored resin and the particulate thermoplastic resin
to be incorporated in the ink composition will be further
described hereinafter.</p><p num="0078">Referring to the content of each of these particulate
materials in the ink composition, it is preferred that the
content of the particulate adhesive colored resin and the
particulate thermoplastic resin be from 5 to 30% by weight and
from 1 to 15% by weight, respectively, and the weight ratio of
the particulate thermoplastic resin to the particulate adhesive
colored resin is from 2 : 100 to 50 : 100.</p><p num="0079">If the content of the particulate adhesive colored resin
falls below 5% by weight, neither a good color density nor a
good fretting resistance can be obtained. On the contrary, if 
the content of the particulate adhesive colored resin exceeds
30% by weight, the proportion of solid content in the ink
composition is raised, occasionally preventing smooth
discharge of ink.</p><p num="0080">If the content of the particulate thermoplastic resin
falls below 1% by weight, a good heat-fixability cannot be
obtained. On the contrary, if the content of the particulate
thermoplastic resin exceeds 15% by weight, the resulting
fretting resistance can be deteriorated. Further, if the
mixing ratio of the particulate thermoplastic resin to the
particulate adhesive colored resin falls below 2, a good
heat-fixability cannot be obtained. On the contrary, if the
mixing ratio of the particulate thermoplastic resin to the
particulate adhesive colored resin exceeds 50, the resulting
fretting resistance can be deteriorated.</p><p num="0081">As second aspect of the present invention, the
rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material composition
will be further described, including at least a particulate
colored resin containing a pigment, a particulate adhesive
resin, water, and a water-soluble polar solvent, the
particulate colored resin and particulate adhesive resin each
having a particle diameter distribution such that the amount
of particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm
is not less than 70% by weight of all the particles.</p><p num="0082">The foregoing particulate colored resin is a particulate
material which can be colored to give a visible writing.
Further, the foregoing particulate colored resin needs to have
a particle diameter distribution such that the amount of 
particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is
not less than 70% by weight of all the particles to prevent the
penetration into paper.</p><p num="0083">The foregoing particulate colored resin may be a
particulate colored resin having a pigment homogeneously
dispersed in a particulate resin or a particulate colored resin
having a particulate resin covered by a pigment.</p><p num="0084">Examples of the resin constituting the foregoing
particulate colored resin include polystyrene, acrylic resin,
epoxy resin, melamine resin, polyester, polyvinyl chloride,
benzoguanamine resin, polyamide, urethane resin, polymethyl
methacrylate, acryl-urethane copolymer, phenolic resin,
polyethylene, polyacrylonitrile, styrene-acryl copolymer,
styrene-butadiene copolymer, and acrylonitrile-butadiene
copolymer.</p><p num="0085">As the pigment for coloring the foregoing resin there may
be used one previously mentioned.</p><p num="0086">The foregoing particulate colored resin can be obtained
by using any known preparation method such as grinding method,
polymerization method and spray dry method. Specific examples
of the foregoing polymerization method include suspension
polymerization method, suspension polycondensation method,
dispersion polymerization method, and emulsion polymerization
method. Microcapsulization method may be used.</p><p num="0087">In order to obtain a particulate colored material of the
present invention having a particle diameter distribution such
that most of the particles have a particle diameter of from 2
µm to 20 µm, grinding method, suspension polymerization method, 
suspension polycondensation method or dispersion
polymerization method may be preferably used. Particularly
preferred among these polymerization methods are suspension
polymerization method and grinding method.</p><p num="0088">Emulsion polymerization method causes the formation of
fine particles having a particle diameter distribution such
that most of the particles have a particle diameter of not more
than 1 µm and thus is not appropriate for the preparation of
the particulate resin of the present invention.</p><p num="0089">As the foregoing particulate colored resin there may be
used a commercially available product. Examples of the
commercially available product employable herein include
Technopolymer MBX-5 (trade name of particulate colored resin
produced by Sekisui Plastic Co., Ltd.) and Art Pearl C-800
(trade name of particulate colored resin produced by Negami
Chemical Industrial Co., Ltd.).</p><p num="0090">As the particulate colored resin there may also be used
a microcapsuled pigment obtained by capsulating or solid-dissolving
a colored material having a pigment dispersed in a
medium in a shell made of a resin wall membrane material by
microcapsulizing method.</p><p num="0091">Examples of the wall membrane material constituting the
shell include gelatin, shellac, gum arabic, rosin, rosin ester,
ethyl cellulose, carboxymethyl cellulose, paraffin,
tristearin, polyvinyl alcohol, polyethylene, polypropylene,
acrylic resin, vinyl resin, polyisobutene, polyurethane,
polybutadiene, polyester, polyamide, epoxy resin, phenolic 
resin, silicone resin, polystyrene, and melamine resin. These
wall membrane materials may be used singly or in admixture.</p><p num="0092">Examples of the microcapsulization method employable
herein include coacervation method, in-situ polymerization
method, interfacial polymerization method, submerged film
curing method, method involving the phase separation from an
aqueous solution, method involving the phase separation from
an organic solvent, melt dispersion cooling method, air
suspension coating method, and spray drying method.</p><p num="0093">If the foregoing particulate colored resin is a
particulate thermoplastic colored resin, the resulting writing,
when heated by a heating means such as iron or under a heat roller
as in copying machine, can be provided with a permanent
fixability such that it cannot be erased even when rubbed with
an eraser or finger.</p><p num="0094">The foregoing particulate thermoplastic colored resin
may be a particulate colored resin having a pigment
homogeneously dispersed in a particulate thermoplastic resin
or a particulate colored resin having a particulate
thermoplastic resin covered by a pigment.</p><p num="0095">As the resin to be incorporated in the foregoing
particulate thermoplastic colored resin there may be used one
to be used in the foregoing particulate thermoplastic resin.</p><p num="0096">The foregoing particulate thermoplastic colored resin
can be obtained by using any known method for the preparation
of electrophotographic toner such as grinding method,
polymerization method and spray dry method. </p><p num="0097">Specific examples of the foregoing polymerization method
include suspension polymerization method, suspension
polycondensation method, dispersion polymerization method,
and microcapsulization method.</p><p num="0098">In order to obtain the particulate thermoplastic colored
resin of the present invention having a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 70% by weight
of all the particles, grinding method, suspension
polymerization method or dispersion polymerization method may
be preferably used. Emulsion polymerization method causes the
formation of fine particles having a particle diameter
distribution such that most of the particles have a particle
diameter of not more than 1 µm and thus is not appropriate for
the preparation of the particulate resin of the present
invention.</p><p num="0099">The thermal properties of the particulate thermoplastic
colored resin will be further described hereinafter.</p><p num="0100">The thermoplastic resin to be incorporated in the
foregoing particulate thermoplastic colored resin or the
particulate thermoplastic colored resin itself exhibits a
softening point of from 60°C to 180°C and a melt flow index (MI)
of from 0.1 to 30.0, preferably from 0.1 to 20, in order that
the resulting writing, when heated, can be rendered resistant
to erasure by an eraser. The foregoing softening point, MI and
heat-fusibility are closely related to each other. If the
softening point falls below 60°C, the writing can be transferred
to another sheet of paper which has been laminated thereon or 
causes the two sheets of paper to be glued (blocking). On the
contrary, if the softening point exceeds 180°C, it requires the
use of a high temperature heating means or heat roller that can
deteriorated the quality of paper. Further, if MI falls below
0.1, the resulting thermoplastic resin exhibits too small a
fluidity during heating to obtain a sufficient fixability. On
the contrary, if MI exceeds 30, the resulting writing can be
transferred to the foregoing heating means to thin the writing
or stain the heating means. Further, when heated, the
thermoplastic resin can easily penetrate into paper,
deteriorating the fixability or impairing the sharpness of the
writing.</p><p num="0101">The foregoing softening point can be measured by a ring
and ball softening point measuring method according to JIS K2531.
MI can be measured by A method according to JIS K7210. These
measurements are effected at a temperature of 125°C under a load
of 10 kg.</p><p num="0102">As the reactive monomer and radical initiator to be used
in the preparation of the foregoing particulate thermoplastic
colored resin by a suspension polymerization method involving
radical polymerization there may be used the previously
mentioned starting materials from the particulate adhesive
colored resin is prepared.</p><p num="0103">The weight proportion of the pigment and thermoplastic
resin constituting the particulate thermoplastic colored resin
will be further described hereinafter.</p><p num="0104">Referring to the weight ratio of the pigment and
thermoplastic resin constituting the particulate 
thermoplastic colored resin, the proportion of the
thermoplastic resin is preferably from 2 to 40 per 1 of the
pigment. If the proportion of the thermoplastic resin falls
below 2, the resulting particulate thermoplastic colored resin
doesn't exhibit a good fixability. On the contrary, if the
proportion of the thermoplastic resin exceeds 40, the resulting
color density is lowered, making it difficult to obtain a
writing showing a good color density.</p><p num="0105">The particulate adhesive resin to be incorporated in the
ink composition in combination with the foregoing particulate
colored resin or thermoplastic colored resin will be further
described hereinafter.</p><p num="0106">The foregoing particulate adhesive resin acts to bond the
foregoing particulate colored resin or particulate
thermoplastic colored resin which is not adhesive to paper to
paper, rendering the writing resistant to fretting as well as
erasable by an eraser. The adhesivity of the particulate
adhesive resin itself and the content of the particulate
adhesive resin in the ink composition are determined within a
good range such that the desired rubber-erasability and
fretting resistance can be satisfied. The particulate
adhesive resin, too, needs to have a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 70% by weight
of all the particles to prevent or lessen its penetration into
paper.</p><p num="0107">The process for the preparation of the foregoing
particulate adhesive resin is not specifically limited so far 
as it is adhesive at least on the surface layer thereof. Any
known method for the synthesis of particulate resin may be used.</p><p num="0108">Examples of the form of the particulate adhesive resin
include a structure wherein the entire resin constituting the
particulate adhesive resin is a homogeneous polymer composition
having an adhesivity, a structure including a particulate
adhesive resin the surface of which is entirely coated with a
polymer composition having an adhesivity, a structure including
a multi-layer particulate adhesive resin at least surface of
which is adhesive, and a structure including a particulate
adhesive resin a part of the surface of which is formed by a
polymer composition having a continuous or discontinuous
adhesivity.</p><p num="0109">The foregoing particulate adhesive resin can be obtained
by suspension polymerization method, suspension
polycondensation method, suspension addition reaction method,
seed polymerization method, dispersion polymerization method,
submerged solvent evaporation method or the like. In order to
obtain the structure wherein the entire resin constituting the
particulate adhesive resin is a homogeneous polymer composition
having an adhesivity, suspension polymerization method,
dispersion polymerization method, seed polymerization method
or submerged solvent evaporation method may be mainly used. On
the other hand, in order to obtain the structure including a
multi-layer particulate adhesive resin at least surface of
which is adhesive, suspension polymerization method,
suspension polycondensation method, suspension addition
reaction method, seed polymerization method, dispersion 
polymerization method and submerged solvent evaporation method
can be used in proper combination. Alternatively, a secondary
surface modification method can be used. As the foregoing
multi-layer particulate adhesive resin there may be used one
which is hard in the center thereof but adhesive on the surface
layer thereof.</p><p num="0110">The foregoing secondary treatment is a treatment which
includes modifying primary particles obtained so that they are
rendered adhesive regardless of whether or they are adhesive.</p><p num="0111">The preparation of the particulate adhesive resin is
preferably accomplished by at least one polymerization method
selected from the group consisting of suspension polymerization
method, dispersion polymerization method and seed
polymerization method, more preferably seed polymerization
method or dispersion polymerization method. These
polymerization methods can provide a particulate material
showing a sharp (acute) particle diameter distribution curve
(particulate material having a sharp particle diameter
distribution). Thus, classification following the reaction
can be substantially omitted.</p><p num="0112">The adhesive properties of the foregoing particulate
adhesive resin are meant to indicate that the particulate
material itself can be erased by an eraser but exhibits the
lowest required adhesivity with respect to light fretting. In
other words, if the particulate adhesive resin exhibits too
strong an adhesivity, it can be less erased by an eraser or cannot
be fairly erased unless rubbed by an eraser with a strong
frictional force. On the contrary, if the particulate adhesive 
resin exhibits too weak an adhesivity, it can be easily peeled
even when lightly rubbed. Accordingly, the adhesivity of the
particulate adhesive resin needs to be adjusted such that a good
rubber-erasability and a high fretting resistance can be
attained at the same time.</p><p num="0113">As an index for providing the particulate adhesive resin
with a proper adhesivity, it is preferred that the particulate
adhesive resin thus obtained exhibit a glass transition point
of lower than 40°C, more preferably lower than 20°C. If the
adhesive resin used exhibits a glass transition point of not
lower than 40°C, the resulting writing exhibits a weak
adhesivity at room temperature and thus cannot attain a desired
fretting resistance.</p><p num="0114">The polymer to be used in the preparation of the foregoing
particulate adhesive resin is not specifically limited so far
as it is adhesive. The same polymer as used in the particulate
adhesive colored resin can be used.</p><p num="0115">The reactive monomers and radical initiators to be used
in the preparation of the foregoing particulate adhesive resin
by radical polymerization such as suspension polymerization,
seed polymerization and dispersion polymerization may be
selected from the previously mentioned starting materials from
which the particulate colored resin is prepared.</p><p num="0116">As the method for preparing the foregoing particulate
adhesive resin by suspension polycondensation method,
suspension addition reaction method or submerged solvent
evaporation method there may be used the same method as
mentioned above. </p><p num="0117">As the method for adjusting the adhesivity of the
foregoing particulate adhesive resin there may be used the same
method as used for the particulate adhesive colored resin.</p><p num="0118">The method for adjusting the particle diameter
distribution of the particulate colored resin and the
particulate adhesive resin as mentioned above will be further
described hereinafter.</p><p num="0119">The foregoing particulate colored resin and particulate
adhesive resin can be adjusted to have a desired particle
diameter distribution by wet or dry classification method.</p><p num="0120">The wet or dry classification method can be accomplished
by the foregoing method.</p><p num="0121">However, the foregoing particulate adhesive resin stays
adhesive at room temperature and thus can be adjusted by the
same method for the adjustment of the particle diameter
distribution of the foregoing particulate adhesive colored
resin.</p><p num="0122">The content and weight proportion of the particulate
colored resin and the particulate adhesive resin to be
incorporated in the ink composition will be further described
hereinafter.</p><p num="0123">Referring to the content of each of these particulate
materials in the ink composition, it is preferred that the
content of the particulate colored resin and the particulate
adhesive resin be from 5 to 30% by weight and from 0.5 to 15%
by weight, respectively, and the weight ratio of the particulate
adhesive resin to the particulate colored resin is from 2 : 100
to 200 : 100, preferably from 5 : 100 to 150 : 100. </p><p num="0124">If the content of the particulate colored resin falls
below 5% by weight, a good color density cannot be obtained.
On the contrary, if the content of the particulate adhesive
resin exceeds 30% by weight, the proportion of solid content
in the ink composition is raised, occasionally preventing
smooth discharge of ink. Also in the case where the particulate
thermoplastic colored resin is used, the same content and weight
proportion as for the particulate colored resin is preferred.</p><p num="0125">If the content of the particulate adhesive resin falls
below 0.5% by weight, a good fretting resistance cannot be
obtained. On the contrary, if the content of the particulate
adhesive resin exceeds 15% by weight, it is occasionally
difficult to obtain a good rubber-erasability. Further, if the
ratio of the particulate adhesive resin to the particulate
colored resin falls below 2, a good fretting resistance cannot
be obtained. On the contrary, if the ratio of the particulate
adhesive resin to the particulate colored resin exceeds 200,
a good rubber-erasability can hardly be obtained.</p><p num="0126">Referring to the configurational characteristics of the
writing formed on paper by the foregoing rubber-erasable
aqueous ink for a writing material composition, the dried
writing formed on paper by an ink composition including the
foregoing particulate colored resin 2 and particulate adhesive
resin 3 includes particles point-bonded to each other and to
the surface of paper 10 as shown in Fig. 2. In this arrangement,
a two-dimensional network with a particulate adhesive resin 3
as a nucleus is continuously or discontinuously formed on the
surface of paper 10. The foregoing configurational 
characteristics provide a good rubber-erasability and a good
fretting resistance at the same time.</p><p num="0127">Further, in the writing formed by the ink composition
including the particulate thermoplastic colored resin and the
particulate adhesive resin, the particulate adhesive resin 3
is point-bonded to the particulate thermoplastic colored resin
21 and to the surface of paper 10 with an adhesivity as shown
in Fig. 3. In this arrangement, a two-dimensional network with
a particulate adhesive resin 3 as a nucleus is continuously or
discontinuously formed on the surface of paper 10.</p><p num="0128">Further, when the writing thus formed is subjected to heat
treatment, the particulate thermoplastic colored resin 21 melts
to show a deformation from the original independent particle,
causing aggregation of all the particles in the writing. At
the same time, the resin melts to penetrate into paper,
providing the writing with a high fixability such that it cannot
be erased even when rubbed with an eraser as shown in Fig. 4.</p><p num="0129">Further, in the writing formed by the ink composition
including the particulate adhesive colored resin and the
particulate thermoplastic resin, the particulate adhesive
colored resin 1 is point-bonded to the surface of paper 10 and
to the particulate thermoplastic resin 4 as shown in Fig. 5.
In this arrangement, a network with resin particles point-bonded
to each other is continuously or discontinuously formed
on the surface of paper. When the writing thus formed is
subjected to heat treatment, the particulate thermoplastic
resin 4 melts to show a deformation, causing aggregation of all
the particles 1 in the writing. At the same time, the resin 
melts to penetrate into paper 10, exerting an enhanced effect
of bonding to paper and hence providing the writing with a high
fixability such that it cannot be erased even when rubbed with
an eraser as shown in Fig. 6.</p><p num="0130">The preparation of the ink composition can be
accomplished by homogeneously dispersing the foregoing various
particulate materials in a vehicle containing water and a
water-soluble polar solvent.</p><p num="0131">The foregoing water-soluble polar solvent is used for the
purpose of inhibiting the drying of the ink at the tip of writing
materials, rendering the writing water-resistant or like
purposes. As the water-soluble polar solvent there may be
effectively used any general-purpose solvent compatible with
water. For example, polyvalent alcohols such as ethylene
glycol, diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol, 1,3-propanediol,
propylene glycol, butylene glycol, dipropylene
glycol, thiodiethylene glycol, sorbitol, glycerin and
polyethylene glycol, ethylene glycol monomethyl ether,
diethylene glycol monomethyl ether, triethanolamine, 2-pyrrolidone,
N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone, dimethylformamide, etc.
may be used singly or in combination. The amount of the
water-soluble polar solvent to be added is preferably from 2
to 35% by weight based on the weight of the ink composition.</p><p num="0132">The ink composition of the present invention may includes
general-purpose additives such as preservative, anti-foaming
agent, oxidation inhibitor, stabilizer, pH adjuster and
surfactant incorporated therein as necessary. </p><p num="0133">Referring to the foregoing additives, as the pH adjuster
there may be used an inorganic salt such as sodium carbonate,
sodium phosphate and sodium acetate or an organic basic compound
such as water-soluble amine compound. As the rust preventive
there may be used benzotriazole, tolyl triazole, dicyclohexyl
ammonium nitrite, diisopropyl ammonium nitrite, saponin or the
like.</p><p num="0134">As the preservative or mildew-proofing agent there may
be used carbolic acid, sodium salt of 1,2-benzthiazoline-3-on,
sodium benzoate, sodium dehydroacetate, potassium sorbate,
propyl paraoxybenzoate, 2,3,5,6-tetrachloro-4-(methylsulfonyl)pyridine
or the like.</p><p num="0135">As the wetting agent there may be used urea, nonionic
surfactant, sorbit, mannitol, sucrose, dextrose, reduced
starch hydrolyzate, sodium pyrophosphate or the like. Further,
a fluorine-based surfactant or silicone-based, nonionic,
anionic or cationic surfactant may be used as an ink penetration
improver. An anti-foaming agent or dispersing agent such as
dimethyl polysiloxane may be used.</p><p num="0136">The foregoing additives are so-called general-purpose
additives. These additives may be properly selected from the
group consisting of known compounds as necessary.</p><p num="0137">Further, the aqueous vehicle medium may include a known
water-soluble resin or aqueous resin emulsion incorporated
therein for the purpose of enhancing the fluidity of the ink,
stabilizing the dispersibility of the ink and closely adjusting
the adhesivity of the ink. </p><p num="0138">Writing materials including the foregoing rubber-erasable
aqueous ink for a writing material composition
incorporated therein will be described hereinafter.</p><p num="0139">The writing materials including the foregoing rubber-erasable
aqueous ink for a writing material composition
incorporated therein may be a marking pen having a structure
arranged to supply the ink into the tip of the writing materials
on which a fiber chip, felt chip or plastic chip is mounted from
an ink occluding material made of a bundle of fibers received
in a cylindrical holder, the ink occluding material impregnated
with the ink, a structure having the ink directly received in
a cylindrical holder with a pectinated ink flow adjusting member
or an ink flow adjusting member made of a bundle of fibers being
interposed therebetween, or a structure having the ink directly
received in a cylindrical holder having a valve mechanism
arranged to supply a predetermined amount of the ink into the
tip of the writing materials.</p><p num="0140">On the other hand, when the ink composition of the present
invention is used for ball point pen, the particulate material
tends to undergo sedimentation in the ink composition because
the particulate material used have a relatively great particle
diameter. For this reason, the ink composition may include a
shear-thinning agent incorporated therein. If the resulting
ink composition exhibits a viscosity of from 25 to 160 mPa
· s as determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by means of an EMD type
viscometer and a shear-thinning index of from 0.1 to 0.7 at 100
rpm, writing materials which are free from sedimentation and 
separation of particulate material and thus are stable with time
can be obtained.</p><p num="0141">If the ink viscosity at 100 rpm exceeds 160 mPa ·s , the
resulting ink dischargeability is deteriorated, disabling
writing or causing blurring. On the contrary, if the ink
viscosity at 100 rpm falls below 25 mPa ·s, the dispersion
stability of the particulate material cannot be sufficiently
maintained. In other words, if the shear-thinning index falls
outside the above defined range, the resulting effect is not
optimum, impairing the effect of inhibiting the separation of
the particulate adhesive colored resin, the ink
dischargeability and the writing performance.</p><p num="0142">The shear-thinning index of the ink as used hereinabove
is n value obtained by substituting for an experimental formula
(T = Kj<sup>n</sup> where K and n are calculated constants) obtained from
rheological measurements made by a viscometer such as shear
stress (T) and shear rate (j).</p><p num="0143">As the foregoing shear-thinning agent there may be used
any compound known as such. Examples of the shear-thinning
agent employable herein include xanthan gum, welan gum,
succinoglycan composed of organic acid-modified
heteropolysaccharide as monosaccharide (average molecular
weight: about 1,000,000 to 8,000,000), gua gum, locust bean gum
and derivative thereof, hydroxyethyl cellulose, alginic acid
alkyl ester, polymer having a molecular weight of from 100,000
to 150,000 mainly composed of methacrylic acid alkyl ester,
glycomannan, gelatinizable hydrocarbon extracted from
seaweeds such as agar and carrageenan, benzylidene sorbitol and 
benzylidene xylitol or derivative thereof, and crosslinkable
acrylic acid polymer. These shear-thinning agents may be used
singly or in admixture.</p><p num="0144">Further examples of the shear-thinning agent employable
herein include nonionic surfactants having HLB value of from
8 to 12 selected from the group consisting of
polyglycerinaliphatic acid esters, polyoxyethylenesorbitan
aliphatic acid esters, polyoxyethylenecastor oils,
polyoxyethylenelanolin, lanolinalcohol, beeswax derivatives,
polyoxyethylene alkyl ethers, polyoxypropylene alkyl ethers,
polyoxyethylene alkyl phenyl ethers and aliphatic acid amides,
neutralization product of dialkyl or dialkenylsulfosuccinic
acid, mixture of N-alkyl-2-pyrrolidone and anionic surfactant,
and mixture of polyvinyl alcohol and acrylic resin. These
shear-thinning agents may be used singly or in admixture.</p><p num="0145">The foregoing shear-thinning agent may be used in an
amount of from 0.1 to 20% by weight based on the weight of the
ink composition.</p><p num="0146">Referring next to the particle diameter of the
particulate material to be incorporated in the rubber-erasable
aqueous ink for a writing material composition for ball point
pen, it is preferred that the entire particulate material
incorporated in the ink composition have a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 80% by weight
of all the particles, preferably such that a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle 
diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 90% by weight
of all the particles.</p><p num="0147">The particle diameter distribution of the ink composition
for ball point pen needs to be restricted more greatly than that
of other writing materials to allow smooth passage of the
particulate material through the narrow gap in the vicinity of
the portion receiving ball at the tip of ball point pen. Though
depending on the structure of ball point pen, a particulate
material is preferably used having a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 80% by weight
of all the particles. More preferably, a particulate material
is used having a particle diameter distribution such that the
amount of particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to
10 µm is not less than 90% by weight of all the particles. If
the proportion of particles having a particle diameter of not
less than 10 µm is too great, coarse particles don't pass and
thus are accumulated in the vicinity of the foregoing ball-receiving
portion, disabling writing.</p><p num="0148">The particulate adhesive colored resin or the stabilizer
for particulate adhesive resin to be used in the preparation
of the rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition for ball point pen will be further described
hereinafter.</p><p num="0149">As the ball rotates during writing, the foregoing
particulate adhesive resin material tends to aggregate or
conglomerate to each other under the action of extreme pressure
in the vicinity of the ball-receiving portion. Therefore, it 
is preferred that the ink composition include a particulate
adhesive material incorporated therein.</p><p num="0150">As the foregoing stabilizer there may be used an anionic
surfactant or amphoteric surfactant. Preferably, an
amphoteric surfactant is used singly or in combination with an
anionic surfactant. The stabilizer is oriented on the surface
of the particulate adhesive material to exert a remarkable
effect of inhibiting the aggregation or conglomeration of the
adhesive material particles in the vicinity of the ball-receiving
portion.</p><p num="0151">As the foregoing anionic surfactant to be used herein
there may be used alkyl sulfate,
polyoxyethylenealkylethersulfate, sulfosuccinate, sulfonate,
taurin derivative, sarcosine derivative, amide ether sulfate,
alkyl phosphate, polyoxyethylenealkyletherphosphate,
aliphatic acid salt, alkyl ether aliphatic acid salt or the like.
Examples of these anionic surfactants include sodium
laurylsulfate, triethanolamine laurylsulfate, sodium
myristylsulfate, sodium polyoxyethylenelaurylethersulfate,
triethanolamine polyoxyethylenelaurylethersulfate,
dioctylsodium sulfosuccinate, sodium laurylsulfoacetate, N-lauroylmethyltaurinsodium,
N-myristoylmethyltaurin
triethanolamine, lauroylsarcosinesodium,
oleylsarcosinepotassium, myristoylsarcosinesodium, sodium
sulfate of polyoxy palm oil aliphatic acid monoethanolamide,
sodium laurylphosphate, sodium polyoxyethylenecetyl
etherphosphate, triethanolamine polyoxyethylenenonylphenyl
etherphosphate, triethanolamine dipolyoxyethylenelaurylether 
phosphate, triethanolamine tripolyoxyethylenelaurylether
phosphate, triethanolamine of palm oil aliphatic acid, and
sodium polyoxyethylenelauryletheracetate.</p><p num="0152">As the foregoing amphoteric surfactant there may be used
an alkylbetain type, alkylaminobetain type, imidazoline type,
glycin type or etheraminoxide type surfactant. Examples of
these amphoteric surfactants include betain
lauryldimethylaminoacetate, amidepropyldimethylamino acid
betain of palm oil aliphatic acid, amidepropylbetain laurate,
2-alkyl-N-carboxymethyl-N-hydroxyethylimidazoliniumbetain,
laurylhydroxysulfobetain, polyoctylpolyaminoethylglycin,
lauryldimethylaminoxide, and alkyldimethylaminoxide of
polyoxyethylene palm oil.</p><p num="0153">The structure and shape of ball point pen itself are not
specifically limited. General-purpose structures and shapes
which have been heretofore known may be used. For example, a
ball point pen can be exemplified having a structure including
an ink receiving tube having a cylindrical holder filled with
an ink composition, the ink receiving tube communicating to the
tip in which a ball is mounted, a follower being mounted close
to the end face of the ink composition.</p><p num="0154">Referring further to the foregoing ball point pen filled
with an ink composition, the conventional general-purpose
mechanism is useful as the structure of the tip thereof.
Examples of such a mechanism employable herein include a tip
having a ball held in a ball-holding portion formed by
externally pressure-deforming a metallic pipe inward in the
vicinity of the tip thereof, a tip having a ball held in a 
ball-holding portion formed by drilling or otherwise cutting
a metallic material, and a tip formed by cutting a metallic pipe
or metallic material having a ball held energized by a spring
therein.</p><p num="0155">The foregoing ball may be made of a material such as hard
metal, stainless steel, ruby and ceramic having a diameter of
from about 0.3 to 1.2 mm.</p><p num="0156">As the foregoing ink-receiving tube for receiving the ink
composition there may be preferably used, e.g., a formed product
made of a thermoplastic resin such as polyethylene,
polypropylene and polyethylene terephthalate because it causes
little evaporation of ink and can be easily produced.</p><p num="0157">The foregoing ink-receiving tube to be used herein
preferably has an inner diameter of from 2.5 to 10 mm.</p><p num="0158">Further, the foregoing ink-receiving tube can be formed
by a transparent, colored transparent or semitransparent
material to allow the confirmation of the color or remaining
amount of ink.</p><p num="0159">The foregoing ink-receiving tube may be directly
connected to the tip. Alternatively, the foregoing ink-receiving
tube and the tip may be connected to each other with
a connecting member.</p><p num="0160">The foregoing ink-receiving tube may have a refill for
ball point pen received in a cyclic holder. Alternatively, the
ink may be directly received in a cylindrical holder having a
tip mounted on the forward end thereof as an ink-receiving body.</p><p num="0161">The refill to be received in the cylindrical holder
preferably has an inner diameter of from 2.5 to 5 mm. The 
cylindrical holder in which the ink is directly received
preferably has an inner diameter of from 4 to 10 mm.</p><p num="0162">The foregoing ink-receiving tube in which the ink
composition is directly received preferably has an ink follower
packed at the rear end thereof.</p><p num="0163">As the foregoing ink follower there may be used either
a liquid or solid material. As the foregoing liquid ink
follower there may be used a nonvolatile medium such as
polybutene and silicone oil. The foregoing medium may include
silica, aluminum silicate or the like incorporated therein as
necessary.</p><p num="0164">As the solid ink follower there may be used a formed resin
material.</p><p num="0165">These liquid and solid ink follower may be used in
combination.</p><p num="0166">The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition of the present invention can be prepared by adding
a dispersion containing a particulate adhesive colored resin
and optionally a particulate thermoplastic resin or a
particulate colored resin or particulate thermoplastic colored
resin and a particulate adhesive resin to a medium including
water and a water-soluble polar solvent, adding proper
additives, if any, to the mixture, and then stirring the mixture
to make a dispersion. The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a
writing material composition thus prepared is then packed into
writing materials in the form of ball point pen, marking pen
such as magic pen and felt pen, fountain pen and writing brush
for use. </p><heading><u style="single">Examples</u></heading><p num="0167">The present invention will be further described in the
following examples, but the present invention should not be
construed as being limited thereto.</p><p num="0168">For the measurement of particle diameter distribution in
the following examples, a laser diffraction type particle size
distribution meter [SALD 1100, produced by Shimadzu Corp.] was
used. For the measurement of glass transition temperature, a
differential scanning calorimeter [DSC 8230L, produced by
Rigaku Corp.] was used.</p><p num="0169">The figure used in mixing proportion indicates parts by
weight.</p><p num="0170">Examples and comparative examples of the ink composition
including a particulate adhesive colored resin of the present
invention or the ink composition including a particulate
colored resin and a particulate adhesive resin of the present
invention will be described hereinafter.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 1</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate adhesive
colored resin</u></heading><p num="0171">Into a 2-literiter separable flask were charged 480.0
parts of water in which 20.0 parts of a polyvinyl alcohol
[Gosenol GL-03, produced by The Nippon Synthetic Chemical
Industry Co., Ltd.] were then dissolved to make a dispersant.</p><p num="0172">To the foregoing dispersant was then added a coloring
composition consisting of 8.0 parts of carbon black (Printex
L, produced by Degussa-Huls Japan Co., Ltd.), 46.0 parts of
butyl acrylate, 46.0 parts of styrene and 2.0 parts of 
2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile. The mixture was then stirred at
a high speed to make droplets having a particle diameter of about
7 µm. Stirring continued for 6 hours during which the reaction
mixture was subjected to suspension polymerization at a
temperature of 60°C.</p><p num="0173">The reaction solution was then allowed to cool to room
temperature. In order to remove the polyvinyl alcohol from the
dispersant, the reaction solution was washed with 600.0 parts
of water, and then subjected to centrifugal separation to
separate a particulate adhesive black material therefrom.</p><p num="0174">The slurry of particulate adhesive black material thus
obtained was washed with 600.0 parts of water, and then again
subjected to centrifugal separation to separate the particulate
material therefrom. The particulate material was then
adjusted with water to a solid content of 50% by weight to obtain
a dispersion of particulate adhesive black resin A.</p><p num="0175">The particulate adhesive black resin constituting the
dispersion A thus obtained exhibited a glass transition
temperature of 8°C, an average particle diameter of 8.2 µm and
a particle diameter distribution such that the amount of
particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 15 µm is
not less than 92.5% by weight of all the particles.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Preparation of rubber-erasable aqueous ink composition</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dispersion of particulate adhesive black resin A</entry><entry align="center">40.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethylene glycol</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Penetrating agent [Acetynol EH, produced by Kawaken Finechemical Co., Ltd.]</entry><entry align="center">0.3 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">49.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0176">The foregoing components were mixed, and then stirred by
a disper until homogeneity was attained to obtain an ink
composition.</p><p num="0177">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 5.8 mPa ·s (determined at 25°C by an ELD type viscometer).
EXAMPLE 2</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate adhesive colored resin</u></heading><p num="0178">Into a 2-liter separable flask were charged 475.0 parts
of water in which 25.0 parts of a polyvinyl alcohol [Gosenol
GL-03, produced by The Nippon Synthetic Chemical Industry Co.,
Ltd.] were then dissolved to make a dispersant.</p><p num="0179">To the foregoing dispersant was then added a coloring
composition consisting of 11 parts of a red organic pigment
(CINQUASIA Scarlet RT-787-D, produced by Ciba Geigy Inc.), 80.1
parts of butyl acrylate, 3.6 parts of methyl methacrylate, 5.3
parts of ethylene glycol dimethacrylate and 2.0 parts of t-butyl
peroxy pivalate. The mixture was then stirred at a high
speed to make droplets having a particle diameter of about 5
µm. Stirring continued for 6 hours during which the reaction
mixture was subjected to suspension polymerization at a
temperature of 60°C.</p><p num="0180">The reaction solution was then allowed to cool to room
temperature. The reaction solution was thoroughly washed in
the same manner as in Example 1, and then subjected to
centrifugal separation. The particulate material thus
separated was then adjusted with water to a solid content of 
50% by weight to obtain a dispersion of particulate adhesive
red resin B.</p><p num="0181">The particulate adhesive red resin constituting the
dispersion B thus obtained exhibited a glass transition
temperature of - 32°C, an average particle diameter of 5.8 µm
and a particle diameter distribution such that the amount of
particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 15 µm is
not less than 90.5% by weight of all the particles.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Preparation of rubber-erasable aqueous ink composition</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dispersion of particulate adhesive red resin B</entry><entry align="center">40.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethylene glycol</entry><entry align="center">8.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silicone-modified anti-foaming agent</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Preservative (Proxel XL-2, produced by Zeneca Corp.)</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Succinoglycan (organic acid-modified heteropolysaccharide; average molecular weight: approx. 1,000,000 to 8,000,000)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Phosphoric acid ester-based surface active agent [Plysurf M208B, produced by Dai-ichi Kogyo Seiyaku Co., Ltd.]</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">51.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0182">The foregoing components were mixed, and then stirred by
a disper until homogeneity was attained to obtain an ink
composition. </p><p num="0183">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 44 mPa ·s (determined at 25°C by an ELD type viscometer) and
a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.246.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 3</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate adhesive colored resin</u></heading><p num="0184">Into a 2-liter separable flask were charged 485.0 parts
of water in which 15.0 parts of methyl cellulose [Metrose
90SH-100, produced by Shin-Etsu Chemical Co., Ltd.] were then
dissolved to make a dispersant.</p><p num="0185">To the foregoing dispersant was then added a coloring
composition consisting of 10.0 parts of carbon black (Printex
L, produced by Degussa-Huls Japan Co., Ltd.), 81.0 parts of
butyl acrylate, 5.4 parts of methyl methacrylate, 3.6 parts of
ethylene glycol dimethacrylate and 2.0 parts of 2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile.
The mixture was then stirred at a high
speed to make droplets having a particle diameter of about 5
µm. Stirring continued for 6 hours during which the reaction
mixture was subjected to suspension polymerization at a
temperature of 60°C.</p><p num="0186">The reaction solution was then allowed to cool to room
temperature. The reaction solution was thoroughly washed in
the same manner as in Example 1, and then subjected to
centrifugal separation. The particulate material thus
separated was then adjusted with water to a solid content of
50% by weight to obtain a dispersion of particulate adhesive
black resin C.</p><p num="0187">The particulate adhesive black resin constituting the
dispersion C thus obtained exhibited a glass transition 
temperature of - 33°C, an average particle diameter of 5.6 µm
and a particle diameter distribution such that the amount of
particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is
not less than 88.5% by weight of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of rubber-erasable aqueous ink composition</u></heading><p num="0188">An ink composition was then prepared in the same manner
as in Example 2 except that 40 parts of the dispersion of
particulate adhesive red resin B used in the preparation of ink
composition were replaced by 40 parts of the dispersion of
particulate adhesive black resin C.</p><p num="0189">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 43 mPa · s (determined at 25°C by an ELD type viscometer)
and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.240.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 4</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate adhesive colored resin</u></heading><p num="0190">Into a 2-liter separable flask were charged 485.0 parts
of water in which 15.0 parts of methyl cellulose [Metrose
90SH-100, produced by Shin-Etsu Chemical Co., Ltd.] were then
dissolved to make a dispersant.</p><p num="0191">To the foregoing dispersant was then added a coloring
composition consisting of 12.0 parts of a blue organic pigment
(CROMOPHTAL Blue A3R, produced by Ciba Geigy Inc.), 79.2 parts
of butyl acrylate, 7.0 parts of ethyl methacrylate, 1.8 parts
of divinylbenzene and 2.0 parts of t-butylperoxy pivalate. The
mixture was then stirred at a high speed to make droplets having
a particle diameter of about 5 µm. Stirring continued for 6
hours during which the reaction mixture was subjected to
suspension polymerization at a temperature of 60°C. </p><p num="0192">The reaction solution was then allowed to cool to room
temperature. The reaction solution was thoroughly washed in
the same manner as in Example 1, and then subjected to
centrifugal separation. The particulate material thus
separated was then adjusted with water to a solid content of
50% by weight to obtain a dispersion of particulate adhesive
blue resin D.</p><p num="0193">The particulate adhesive blue resin constituting the
dispersion D thus obtained exhibited a glass transition
temperature of - 32°C, an average particle diameter of 6.5 µm
and a particle diameter distribution such that the amount of
particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is
not less than 93.5% by weight of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of rubber-erasahle aqueous ink composition</u></heading><p num="0194">An ink composition was then prepared in the same manner
as in Example 2 except that 40 parts of the dispersion of
particulate adhesive red resin B used in the preparation of ink
composition were replaced by 5.0 parts of a particulate
nonadhesive black material (Artpearl C-800, produced by Negami
Chemical Industrial Co., Ltd.; average particle diameter: 6.2
µm) and 30.0 parts of the dispersion of particulate adhesive
blue material and the amount of water was changed from 51.1 parts
to 56.1 parts.</p><p num="0195">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 44 mPa·s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an ELD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.260.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 5</u></heading><p num="0196"><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Preparation of rubber-erasable aqueous ink composition </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dispersion of particulate adhesive blue resin D</entry><entry align="center">40.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diethylene glycol</entry><entry align="center">9.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silicone-modified anti-foaming agent</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Preservative (Proxel XL-2, produced by Zeneca Corp.)</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hexaglyceryl monoisostearate [S Face IS-601, produced by Sakamoto Yakuhin Kogyo Co., Ltd.; HLB: 10.8]</entry><entry align="center">9.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Phosphoric acid ester-based surface active agent [Plysurf M208B, produced by Dai-ichi Kogyo Seiyaku Co., Ltd.]</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">41.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0197">Among these components, water and diethylene glycol were
mixed. To the mixture was then added hexaglyceryl
monoisostearate. To the mixture was then added the dispersion
of particulate adhesive blue resin D with stirring by a disper.
To the mixture were then added the anti-foaming agent,
preservative and lubricant. Stirring continued to obtain an
ink composition.</p><p num="0198">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 43 mPa ·s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an ELD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.232.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 6</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate adhesive resin</u></heading><p num="0199">Into a 2-liter separable flask equipped with an agitator
were charged 600 parts of water in which 0.2 parts of sodium 
laurylsulfate and 20 parts of methyl cellulose [Metrose
90SH-100, produced by Shin-Etsu Chemical Co., Ltd.] were then
dissolved to make a dispersant. To the foregoing dispersant
was then added an oil phase solution consisting of 120 parts
of butyl acrylate, 10 parts of methyl methacrylate, 2 parts of
ethylene glycol dimethacrylate and 2.0 parts of 2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile.
The mixture was then stirred at 400
rpm until the average particle diameter reached about 6 µm.
Subsequently, the suspension was heated to a temperature of 70°C
in an atmosphere of nitrogen for 6 hours during which it
underwent suspension polymerization. The reaction solution
was then allowed to cool to room temperature. The reaction
solution was diluted with 1,000 parts of water, subjected to
solid-liquid separation by centrifugal separation method, and
then adjusted with water to a solid content of 40% to obtain
a dispersion of particulate adhesive resin A.</p><p num="0200">The particulate material constituting the foregoing
dispersion of particulate adhesive resin A exhibited an average
particle diameter of 7.8 µm and a particle diameter distribution
such that the amount of particles having a particle diameter
of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 85% by weight of all the
particles.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Preparation of ink composition</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Particulate black resin [Artpearl C-800, produced by Negami Chemical Industrial Co., Ltd.; average particle diameter:

   6.1 µm; particles having a particle diameter distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 95.0% by weight of all the particles]</entry><entry align="center">20.0 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dispersion of particle adhesive resin A</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethylene glycol</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Penetrating agent [Acetynol EH, produced by Kawaken Finechemical Co., Ltd.]</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silicone-modified anti-foaming agent</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">59.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0201">The foregoing components were mixed, and then stirred by
a disper until homogeneity was attained to obtain an ink
composition.</p><p num="0202">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 6.7 mPa ·s (determined at 25°C by an ELD type viscometer).</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 7</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate adhesive resin</u></heading><p num="0203">Into a 2-liter separable flask were charged 480 parts of
water in which 20 parts of a polyvinyl alcohol [Gosenol GL-03,
produced by The Nippon Synthetic Chemical Industry Co.,
Ltd.] were then dissolved to make a dispersant.</p><p num="0204">To the foregoing dispersant was then added a coloring
composition consisting of 10 parts of carbon black (Printex L,
produced by Degussa-Huls Japan Co., Ltd.), 60 parts of methyl
methacrylate, 30 parts of ethylene glycol dimethacrylate and
2.0 parts of 2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile. The mixture was
then stirred at a high speed to make droplets having a particle
diameter of about 5 µm. The suspension was further stirred at 
a temperature of 70°C for 6 hours during which it underwent
suspension polymerization.</p><p num="0205">The reaction solution was then allowed to cool to room
temperature, diluted with 1,000 parts of water, subjected to
solid-liquid separation by centrifugal separation method, and
then adjusted with water to a solid content of 50% to obtain
a dispersion of particulate black resin A.</p><p num="0206">The particulate material constituting the foregoing
dispersion of particulate black resin A exhibited an average
particle diameter of 5.8 µm and a particle diameter distribution
such that the amount of particles having a particle diameter
of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 88% by weight of all the
particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate adhesive resin</u></heading><p num="0207">The reaction procedure of Example 6 was followed except
that the oil phase solution of particulate adhesive resin A was
replaced by 78 parts of butyl acrylate, 52 parts of ethyl
methacrylate and 1 part of t-butyl peroxy pivalate. However,
stirring was effected at 500 rpm until the average particle
diameter of 4 µm was attained.</p><p num="0208">The particulate adhesive resin thus obtained was then
adjusted with water to a solid content of 40% to obtain a
dispersion of particulate adhesive resin B.</p><p num="0209">The particulate adhesive resin constituting the
dispersion B thus obtained exhibited an average particle
diameter of 4.8 µm and a particle diameter distribution such
that the amount of particles having a particle diameter of from
2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 90% by weight of all the particles. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Preparation of ink composition</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dispersion of particulate black resin A</entry><entry align="center">40.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dispersion of particulate adhesive resin B</entry><entry align="center">7.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethylene glycol</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Urea</entry><entry align="center">5.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silicone-modified anti-foaming agent</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Preservative (Proxel XL-2, produced by Zeneca Corp.)</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Succinoglycan (organic acid-modified heteropolysaccharide; average molecular weight: approx. 1,000,000 to 8,000,000)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Phosphoric acid ester-based surface active agent [Plysurf M208B, produced by Dai-ichi Kogyo Seiyaku Co., Ltd.]</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">36.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0210">The foregoing components were mixed, and then stirred by
a disper until homogeneity was attained to obtain an ink
composition.</p><p num="0211">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 53 mPa · s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an ELD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.251.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 8</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate colored resin</u></heading><p num="0212">Into a 2-liter beaker were charged 480.0 parts of water
in which 20.0 parts of a polyvinyl alcohol [Gosenol GL-03,
produced by The Nippon Synthetic Chemical Industry Co., Ltd.]
were then dissolved to make a dispersant. </p><p num="0213">To the foregoing dispersant was then added a coloring
composition consisting of 15 parts of a phthalocyanine-based
blue organic pigment (Fastgen Blue 5007, produced by DAINIPPON
INK &amp; CHEMICALS, INC.), 85 parts of an epoxy resin (bisphenol
A/diglycidylether-based epoxy resin; epoxy equivalent: 184 -
194) and 60 parts of ethyl acetate. The mixture was then stirred
at a high speed to make droplets having a particle diameter of
about 5 µm. The mixture was heated to a temperature of 60°C
with stirring where a solution of 21 parts of an epoxy resin
hardener (aliphatic polyamine) in 200 parts of water was then
added dropwise thereto in about 1 hour. Subsequently, the
reaction solution was heated to a temperature of 80°C where it
was then stirred for 5 hours to cause ethyl acetate to evaporate.</p><p num="0214">The reaction solution was allowed to cool to room
temperature, washed with 1,000 parts of water, subjected to
solid-liquid separation by centrifugal separation method, and
then adjusted with water to obtain a dispersion of particulate
blue resin B having a solid content of 50% by weight.</p><p num="0215">The particulate material constituting the dispersion B
thus obtained exhibited an average particle diameter of 6.7 µm
and a particle diameter distribution such that the amount of
particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is
not less than 91% by weight of all the particles.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Preparation of ink composition</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dispersion of particulate blue resin B</entry><entry align="center">36.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dispersion of particulate adhesive resin A</entry><entry align="center">12.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethylene glycol</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silicone-modified anti-foaming agent</entry><entry align="center">0.1 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Preservative (Proxel XL-2, produced by Zeneca Corp.)</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hexaglyceryl monoisostearate [S Face IS-601, produced by Sakamoto Yakuhin Kogyo Co., Ltd.; HLB: 10.8]</entry><entry align="center">9.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Phosphoric acid ester-based surface active agent [Plysurf M208B, produced by Dai-ichi Kogyo Seiyaku Co., Ltd.]</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">31.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0216">Among these components, water and ethylene glycol were
mixed. To the mixture was then added hexaglyceryl
monoisostearate. To the mixture were then added the dispersion
of particulate adhesive blue resin H and the dispersion of
particulate adhesive resin G with stirring by a disper. To the
mixture were then added the anti-foaming agent, preservative
and lubricant. Stirring continued to obtain an ink
composition.</p><p num="0217">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 58 mPa · s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an ELD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.271.</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 1</u></heading><p num="0218"><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Preparation of aqueous ink composition</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbon black-processed pigment [Sandye Super BLACK C, produced by Sanyo Colorworks, Ltd.; solid content: 36%; average particle diameter: 0.2 µm]</entry><entry align="center">20.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Acryl emulsion [Boncoat 9404, produced by DAINIPPON INK &amp; CHEMICALS, INC.; average particle diameter: 0.1 µm; glass transition temperature: 48°C]</entry><entry align="center">20.0 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethylene glycol</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Penetrating agent [Acetynol EH, produced by Kawaken Finechemical Co., Ltd.]</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">49.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0219">The foregoing components were mixed, and then stirred by
a disper until homogeneity was attained to obtain an ink
composition.</p><p num="0220">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 3.4 mPa · s (determined at 25°C by an ELD type viscometer).</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 2</u></heading><p num="0221"><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Preparation of aqueous ink composition</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbon black-processed pigment [Sandye Super BLACK C, produced by Sanyo Colorworks, Ltd.; solid content: 36%; average particle diameter: 0.2 µm]</entry><entry align="center">20.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Acryl emulsion [Boncoat ST-372, produced by DAINIPPON INK &amp; CHEMICALS, INC.; average particle diameter: 0.2 µm; glass transition temperature: - 11°C]</entry><entry align="center">20.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethylene glycol</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Penetrating agent [Acetynol EH, produced by Kawaken Finechemical Co., Ltd.]</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">49.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0222">The foregoing components were mixed, and then stirred by
a disper until homogeneity was attained to obtain an ink
composition.</p><p num="0223">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 2.5 mPa ·s (determined at 25°C by an ELD type viscometer).</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 3</u></heading><p num="0224"><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Preparation of aqueous ink composition</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Particulate nonadhesive black resin [Art Pearl C-800; average particle diameter: 6.2 µm, produced by Negami Chemical Industrial Co., Ltd.]</entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Styrene butadiene latex [Nipol 4850A, produced by Nippon Zeon Co., Ltd.; average particle diameter: 0.3 µm]</entry><entry align="center">30.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethylene glycol</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry></row> <row><entry align="left">Penetrating agent [SN Wet 366, produced by Sannopco Limited]</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">44.5</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">Total</entry> <entry align="center">100.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0225">The foregoing components were mixed, and then stirred by
a disper until homogeneity was attained to obtain an ink
composition.</p><p num="0226">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 8.2 mPa ·s (determined at 25°C by an ELD type viscometer).</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 4</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate adhesive colored resin</u></heading><p num="0227">A dispersion of particulate adhesive red resin B' was
prepared in the same manner as in Example 2 except that the same 
composition as that of the dispersion of particulate adhesive
red resin B was stirred at a high speed to make droplets having
a particle diameter of about 1 µm.</p><p num="0228">The particulate adhesive red resin thus obtained
exhibited a glass transition temperature of - 32°C, an average
particle diameter of 0.9 µm and a particle diameter distribution
such that the amount of particles having a particle diameter
of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 29.0% by weight of all
the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of aqueous ink composition</u></heading><p num="0229">An ink composition was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 2 except that 40 parts of the dispersion of particulate
adhesive red resin B were replaced by 40 parts of the dispersion
of particulate adhesive red resin B'.</p><p num="0230">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 46 mPa ·s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an ELD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.257.</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 5</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate adhesive colored resin</u></heading><p num="0231">A dispersion of particulate adhesive red resin C' having
a solid content of 50% by weight was prepared in the same manner
as in Example 3 except that 10.0 parts of carbon black were
replaced by C. I. Solvent Black 50 (Oleosol Black AR, produced
by TAOKA CHEMICAL CO., LTD.).</p><p num="0232">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
adhesive black resin C' thus obtained exhibited a glass
transition temperature of - 33°C, an average particle diameter
of 5.3 µm and a particle diameter distribution such that the 
amount of particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to
10 µm is not less than 90.5% by weight of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of aqueous ink composition</u></heading><p num="0233">An ink composition was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 4 except that 40 parts of the dispersion of particulate
adhesive blue resin D were replaced by 40 parts of the dispersion
of particulate adhesive black resin C'.</p><p num="0234">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 45 mPa · s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an ELD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.250.</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 6</u></heading><p num="0235">An ink composition was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 6 except that 20 parts of the particulate black resin
were replaced by 20 parts of a carbon black-processed pigment
[Sandye Super BLACK C, produced by Sanyo Colorworks, Ltd.; solid
content: 36%; average particle diameter: 0.2 µm].</p><p num="0236">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 7.2 mPa ·s (determined by an ELD type viscometer at 25°C).</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 7</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate colored resin</u></heading><p num="0237">A dispersion of particulate black resin A' having a solid
content of 50% by weight was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 7 except that the same composition as that of the
dispersion of particulate colored resin A was stirred at a high
speed to make droplets having a particle diameter of about 2
µm.</p><p num="0238">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
particulate black resin A' thus obtained exhibited an average 
particle diameter of 2.8 µm and a particle diameter distribution
such that the amount of particles having a particle diameter
of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 58% by weight of all the
particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate adhesive resin</u></heading><p num="0239">A dispersion of particulate adhesive resin A' having a
solid content of 40% by weight was prepared in the same manner
as in Example 6 except that the same composition as that of the
dispersion of particulate adhesive resin A was stirred at a high
speed to make droplets having a particle diameter of about 2
µm.</p><p num="0240">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
particulate adhesive A' resin thus obtained exhibited an
average particle diameter of 2.3 µm and a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 53.0% by weight
of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0241">An ink composition was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 7 except that 40 parts of the dispersion of particulate
black resin A and 7.0 parts of the dispersion of particulate
adhesive resin B were replaced by 40 parts of the dispersion
of particulate black resin A' and 7.0 parts of the dispersion
of particulate adhesive resin A', respectively.</p><p num="0242">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 57 mPa · s (determined by an ELD type viscometer at 25°C and
100 rpm) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.269.</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 8</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate adhesive resin</u></heading><p num="0243">A dispersion of particulate adhesive resin B' having a
solid content of 40% by weight was prepared in the same manner
as in Example 7 except that the same composition as that of the
dispersion of particulate adhesive resin B was stirred at a high
speed to make droplets having a particle diameter of about 2
µm.</p><p num="0244">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
particulate adhesive resin B' thus obtained exhibited an
average particle diameter of 3.2 µm and a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 61% by weight
of all the particles</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0245">An ink composition was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 8 except that 12 parts of the dispersion of particulate
adhesive resin A were replaced by 12 parts of the dispersion
of particulate adhesive B'.</p><p num="0246">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 61 mPa ·s (determined by an ELD type viscometer at 25°C and
100 rpm) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.282.
<u style="single">Preparation of sample marking pen</u></p><p num="0247">The ink compositions of Examples 1 and 6 and Comparative
Examples 1 to 3 and 5 were each packed into a marking pen of
the type including a valve mechanism provided in an aluminum
cylindrical holder arranged such that when a tip formed at the
forward end of the pen by binding a bundle of fibers with a resin
is pressed against the surface of paper during writing, the ink 
in the cylindrical holder is then introduced into the tip. Thus,
sample marking pens were prepared.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of sample ball point pen</u></heading><p num="0248">The ink compositions of Examples 2 to 5, 7 and 8 and
Comparative Examples 4, 5, 7 and 8 were each packed into a ball
point pen of the type including a stainless steel tip holding
a hard metal ball having a diameter of 0.7 mm fitted at one end
of a polypropylene cylindrical holder, an ink follower
(silicone grease-based material) centrifugally packed close to
the rear end of the ink pack and a rear plug fitted at the rear
end of the holder. Thus, sample ball point pens were prepared.</p><heading><u style="single">Erasability test and fretting resistance test</u></heading><p num="0249">Using the foregoing various sample pens, a circle having
a diameter of 2 cm was continuously drawn on the surface of a
report paper (Model No. Re-116AN, produced by KOKUYO CO., LTD.).
The resulting writing was then rubbed with an eraser [STAR Radar,
produced by Seed Rubber Industry Co., Ltd.] after 5 seconds and
1 day to judge difficulty in erasure.</p><p num="0250">For the fretting resistance test, a filter paper (No. 2
filter paper, produced by ADVANTEC CO., LTD.) was put on the
writing after 1 hour in an arrangement such that the smooth
surface thereof faced the writing. The filter paper was then
reciprocally slid along the writing 10 times under a load of
45.5 g/cm<sup>2</sup> to judge the fretting resistance of the writing.</p><p num="0251">The results of erasability test and fretting resistance
test, the average particle diameter of the particulate adhesive
colored resin, particulate colored resin and particulate
adhesive resin (Comparative Examples 1 to 3 include a coloring 
agent and a particulate resin), the form of writing materials
and the color tone of writing are set forth in the tables below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Example No.</entry><entry nameend="3" align="center"  namest="2">Erasability test</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">Fretting resistance test</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Average particle diameter of particulate adhesive colored resin</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">Form of writing materials</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">Color tone of writing</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Erasability after 5 seconds</entry><entry align="center">Erasability after 1 day</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 1</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Δ</entry><entry align="center">8.2 µm</entry><entry align="center">Marking pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 2</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">5.8 µm</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Red</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 3</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">5.6 µm</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 4</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">6.5 µm</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Blue black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 5</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">6.5 µm</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Yellow</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center"  namest="1">Example No.</entry><entry nameend="3"  align="center"  namest="2">Erasability test</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">Fretting resistance test</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Average particle diameter of particulate colored resin</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">Average particle diameter of particulate adhesive resin</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">Form of writing materials</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">Color tone of writing</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Erasability after 5 seconds</entry><entry align="center">Erasability after 1 day</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 6</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">6.1 µm</entry><entry align="center">7.8 µm</entry><entry align="center">Marking pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 7</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">5.8 µm</entry><entry align="center">4.8 µm</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 8</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">6.7 µm</entry><entry align="center">4.8 µm</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Blue</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Example No.</entry><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Erasability test</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">Fretting resistance test</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Average particle diameter of coloring agent</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">Average particle diameter of particulate resin</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">Form of writing materials</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">Color tone of writing</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Erasability after 5 seconds</entry><entry align="center">Erasability after 1 day</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">0.2 µm</entry><entry align="center">0.1 µm</entry><entry align="center">Marking pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">0.2 µm</entry><entry align="center">0.2 µm</entry><entry align="center">Marking pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 3</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">6.2 µm</entry><entry align="center">0.3 µm</entry><entry align="center">Marking pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Compara tive Example 4</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">X</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">X</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">○</entry><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="5">0.9 µm</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">Red</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Compara tive Example 5</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">○</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">X</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">○</entry><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="5">5.3 µm</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">Black</entry></row><row><entry>*Regarding to Comparative Examples 4 and 5, the average particle diameter of particulate adhesive resin is described.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Example No.</entry><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Erasability test</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">Fretting resistance test</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Average particle diameter of particulate colored resin</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">Average particle diameter of particulate adhesive resin</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">Form of writing materials</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">Color tone of writing</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Erasability after 5 seconds</entry><entry align="center">Erasability after 1 day</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 6</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">0.2 µm</entry><entry align="center">7.8 µm</entry><entry align="center">Marking pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 7</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">2.8 µm</entry><entry align="center">2.3 µm</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 8</entry><entry align="center">Δ</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">6.7 µm</entry><entry align="center">3.2 µm</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Blue</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0252">The judgment symbols for erasability and fretting
resistance in the tables above indicate the following:</p><heading><u style="single">Erasability</u></heading><p num="0253"><dl compact="compact" tsize="3"><dt>O:</dt><dd>Easily erased;</dd><dt>Δ :</dt><dd>Erased by 10 times rubbing but writing left slightly;</dd><dt>X:</dt><dd>Not erased by 10 times rubbing</dd></dl></p><heading><u style="single">Fretting resistance</u></heading><p num="0254"><dl compact="compact" tsize="2"><dt>O:</dt><dd>Little or no peeling of writing;</dd><dt>Δ:</dt><dd>Writing slightly peeled but can be sufficiently
recognized</dd><dt>X:</dt><dd>Writing mostly peeled and cannot be recognized</dd></dl></p><p num="0255">Examples and comparative examples of the ink composition
including the particulate thermoplastic colored resin and
particulate adhesive resin of the present invention and the ink
composition including the particulate adhesive colored resin
and particulate thermoplastic resin of the present invention
will be described hereinafter.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 9</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate thermoplastic colored resin</u></heading><p num="0256">80 parts of a styrene-butyl acrylate-maleic acid
copolymer (monomerratio: 70 : 20 : 10), 10 parts of a polystyrene
and 10 parts of carbon black [MA-100, produced by Mitsubishi
Chemical Corporation] were mixed, melt-kneaded over a heat roll
mill, cooled, coarsely ground by a hammer mill, finely ground
by a jet mill, and then classified by an air classifier to obtain
a particulate thermoplastic black resin A.</p><p num="0257">The particulate thermoplastic black resin A thus obtained
exhibited an average particle diameter of 8.2 µm, a softening
point of 130°C, MI value of 3.0 and a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 78% by weight
of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate adhesive resin</u></heading><p num="0258">The same composition as in Example 6 was processed in the
same manner as in Example 6 to obtain a dispersion of particulate
adhesive resin C.</p><p num="0259">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
particulate adhesive resin C thus obtained exhibited an average
particle diameter of 5.8 µm and a particle diameter distribution
such that the amount of particles having a particle diameter
of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 85% by weight of all the
particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0260">20 parts of the dispersion of particulate thermoplastic
black resin A, 10 parts of the dispersion of adhesive resin C,
10.0 parts of ethylene glycol, 0.3 parts of a penetrating agent 
[Acetynol EH, produced by Kawaken Finechemical Co., Ltd.], 0.1
parts of a silicone-modified anti-foaming agent and 59.6 parts
of water were mixed, and then stirred by a disper until
homogeneity was attained to obtain an ink composition.</p><p num="0261">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 6.7 mPa · s (determined by an ELD type viscometer at 25°C).</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 10</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate adhesive colored resin</u></heading><p num="0262">2,000 parts of a polyoxypropylene(2 <sup>.</sup>2)-2 <sup>.</sup>2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)propane
and 28 parts of glycerin were poured into
a four-necked round flask equipped with a stirring rod, a
thermometer, an intake tube and a condenser. Nitrogen gas was
then introduced into the flask through the intake tube to keep
the interior of the flask in an atmosphere of nitrogen. The
flask was then heated by a mantel heater to heat the mixture
to a temperature of 52°C. To the mixture were then added 750
parts of fumaric acid and 1.2 parts of hydroquinone. The
mixture was heated to a temperature of 200°C where it then
continued to undergo reaction for about 10 hours while the water
of reaction being removed.</p><p num="0263">The foregoing mixture was allowed to cool to room
temperature, subjected to solid-liquid separation, and then
dried to obtain a thermoplastic polyester resin.</p><p num="0264">100 parts of the foregoing polyester resin and 20 parts
of a phthalocyanine-based blue organic pigment (Fastgen Blue
5007, produced by DAINIPPON INK &amp; CHEMICALS, INC.) were mixed,
melt-kneaded over a heat roll mill, cooled, coarsely ground by
a hammer mill, finely ground by a jet mill, and then classified 
by an air classifier to obtain a particulate thermoplastic blue
resin B.</p><p num="0265">The particulate thermoplastic blue resin B thus obtained
exhibited an average particle diameter of 6.3 µm, a softening
point of 140°C, MI value of 2.0 and a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 96.0% by weight
of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate adhesive resin</u></heading><p num="0266">The reaction procedure of Example 6 was followed except
that the oil phase solution of particulate adhesive resin A was
replaced by 110 parts of 2-ethylhexyl acrylate, 20 parts of
butyl methacrylate, 1 part of divinylbenzene and 2 parts of
2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile.</p><p num="0267">However, stirring was effected at 500 rpm until the
average particle diameter of 4 µm was attained.</p><p num="0268">The particulate adhesive resin thus obtained was then
adjusted with water to a solid content of 40% to obtain a
dispersion of particulate adhesive resin D.</p><p num="0269">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
particulate adhesive resin D thus obtained exhibited an average
particle diameter of 4.2 µm and a particle diameter distribution
such that the amount of particles having a particle diameter
of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 98.0% by weight of all
the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0270">20 parts of a particulate thermoplastic blue resin B, 7
parts of the dispersion of particulate adhesive resin D, 10 
parts of ethylene glycol, 5 parts of urea, 0.1 parts of a
silicone-modified anti-foaming agent, 0.2 parts of a
preservative (Proxel XL-2, produced by Zeneca Corp.), 0.2 parts
of succinoglycan (organic acid-modified heteropolysaccharide;
average molecular weight: approx. 1,000,000 to 8,000,000), 0.2
parts of a phosphoric acid ester-based surfactant [Plysurf
M208B, produced by Dai-ichi Kogyo Seiyaku Co., Ltd.], 1 part
of triethanolamine polyoxylaurylethersulfate [SBL-4T,
produced by Nikko Chemicals Co., Ltd.] and 55.5 parts of water
were mixed, and then stirred by a disper until homogeneity was
attained to obtain an ink composition.</p><p num="0271">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 53 mPa · s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an ELD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.251.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 11</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate thermoplastic colored resin</u></heading><p num="0272">Into a 2-liter separable flask were poured 600 parts of
water in which 0.2 parts of sodium laurylsulfate and 20 parts
of methyl cellulose [Metrose 90SH-100, produced by Shin-Etsu
Chemical Co., Ltd.] were then dissolved to make a dispersant.</p><p num="0273">To the foregoing dispersant was then added an oil phase
solution consisting of 20 parts of a red organic pigment
(CINQUASIA Scarlet RT-787-D, produced by Ciba Geigy Inc.), 115
parts of styrene, 25 parts of butyl acrylate, 0.05 parts of
1,6-hexanediol diacrylate, 3 parts of 2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile
and 30 parts of toluene. The mixture
was then stirred at 400 rpm to make droplets having an average
particle diameter of about 6 µm. Subsequently, in an atmosphere 
of nitrogen, the suspension was heated to a temperature of 70°C
where stirring continued for 6 hours during which the reaction
mixture was subjected to suspension polymerization.</p><p num="0274">The reaction solution was heated to a temperature of 100°C
where toluene and residual monomers were then azeotropically
distilled off. The reaction solution was allowed to cool to
room temperature, washed with 2,000 parts of water, subjected
to solid-liquid separation by centrifugal separation method,
and then adjusted with water to a solid content of 50% by weight
to obtain a dispersion of particulate thermoplastic red resin
C.</p><p num="0275">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
particulate thermoplastic red resin C thus obtained exhibited
an average particle diameter of 6.1 µm, a softening point of
146°C, MI value of 2.0 and a particle diameter distribution such
that the amount of particles having a particle diameter of from
2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 85% by weight of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate adhesive resin</u></heading><p num="0276">The reaction procedure of Example 6 was followed except
that the oil phase solution of particulate adhesive resin A was
replaced by 78 parts of butyl acrylate, 52 parts of ethyl
methacrylate and 1 part of t-butyl peroxy pivalate. However,
stirring was effected at 500 rpm until the average particle
diameter of 4 µm was attained.</p><p num="0277">The particulate adhesive resin thus obtained was then
adjusted with water to a solid content of 40% to obtain a
dispersion of particulate adhesive resin E. </p><p num="0278">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
particulate adhesive resin E thus obtained exhibited an average
particle diameter of 4.8 µm and a particle diameter distribution
such that the amount of particles having a particle diameter
of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 90% by weight of all the
particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0279">To 10 parts of ethylene glycol were added 5.2 parts of
dioctylsodium sulfosuccinate [OTP-100, produced by Nikko
Chemicals Co., Ltd.] and 7.7 parts of amidepropyldimethylamino
acid betain of palm oil aliphatic acid [AM-3130N, produced by
Nikko Chemicals Co., Ltd.]. To the mixture were then added 36
parts of the dispersion of particulate thermoplastic red resin
C, 8 parts of the dispersion of particulate adhesive resin E
and 32.5 parts of water with stirring by a disper. To the
mixture were then added 0.1 parts of a silicone-modified
anti-foaming agent and 0.5 parts of a preservative (Proxel XL-2,
produced by Zeneca Corp.). The mixture was then stirred to
obtain an ink composition.</p><p num="0280">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 81 mPa ·s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an ELD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.283.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 12</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate adhesive colored resin</u></heading><p num="0281">Into a 2-liter separable flask were charged 480 parts of
water in which 20 parts of a polyvinyl alcohol [Gosenol GL-03,
produced by The Nippon Synthetic Chemical Industry Co.,
Ltd.] were then dissolved to make a dispersant. </p><p num="0282">To the foregoing dispersant was then added an oil phase
solution consisting of 8 parts of carbon black (Printex L,
produced by Degussa-Huls Japan Co., Ltd.), 45 parts of butyl
acrylate, 45 parts of styrene, 2 parts of divinylbenzene and
2 parts of 2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile. The mixture was then
stirred at 400 rpm to make droplets having an average particle
diameter of about 8 µm. Subsequently, in an atmosphere of
nitrogen, the suspension was heated to a temperature of 70°C
where stirring continued for 6 hours during which the reaction
mixture was subjected to suspension polymerization.</p><p num="0283">The reaction solution was then allowed to cool to room
temperature. The reaction solution was diluted with 1,000
parts of water, subjected to solid-liquid separation by
centrifugal separation method, and then adjusted with water to
a solid content of 50% to obtain a dispersion of particulate
adhesive black resin E.</p><p num="0284">The particulate material constituting the foregoing
dispersion of particulate adhesive black resin E exhibited an
average particle diameter of 9.1 µm and a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 82% by weight
of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of dispersion of particulate thermoplastic resin</u></heading><p num="0285">2,000 parts of a polyoxypropylene(2 <sup>.</sup>2)-2 <sup>.</sup>2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)propane
and 45 parts of a
polyoxypropylene(6)sorbitol were poured into a four-necked
round flask equipped with a stirring rod, a thermometer, an
intake tube and a condenser. Nitrogen gas was then introduced 
into the flask through the intake tube to keep the interior of
the flask in an atmosphere of nitrogen. The flask was then
heated by a mantel heater to heat the mixture to a temperature
of 52°C. To the mixture were then added 730 parts of fumaric
acid and 1.2 parts of hydroquinone. The mixture was heated to
a temperature of 200°C where it then continued to undergo
reaction for about 10 hours while the water of reaction being
removed.</p><p num="0286">The foregoing mixture was allowed to cool to room
temperature, subjected to solid-liquid separation, dried,
coarsely ground by a hammer mill, finely ground by a jet mill,
and then classified by an air classifier to obtain a particulate
thermoplastic resin A.</p><p num="0287">The particulate thermoplastic resin A thus obtained
exhibited an average particle diameter of 7.4 µm, a softening
point of 130°C, MI value of 6.0 and a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 78% by weight
of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0288">40 parts of the dispersion of particulate adhesive black
resin E, 8 parts of the particulate thermoplastic resin A, 10
parts of ethylene glycol, 0.3 parts of a penetrating agent
[Acetynol EH, produced by Kawaken Finechemical Co., Ltd.], 0.1
parts of a silicone-modified anti-foaming agent and 41.6 parts
of water were mixed, and then stirred by a disper until
homogeneity was attained to obtain an ink composition. </p><p num="0289">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 7.2 mPa · s (determined at 25°C by an ELD type viscometer).</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 13</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate adhesive colored resin</u></heading><p num="0290">Into a 2-liter separable flask were charged 475 parts of
water in which 25 parts of a polyvinyl alcohol [Gosenol GL-03,
produced by The Nippon Synthetic Chemical Industry Co.,
Ltd.] were then dissolved to make a dispersant.</p><p num="0291">To the foregoing dispersant was then added an oil phase
solution consisting of 11 parts of a red organic pigment
(CINQUASIA Scarlet RT-787-D, produced by Ciba Geigy Inc.), 80
parts of butyl acrylate, 4 parts of methyl methacrylate, 5 parts
of ethylene glycol dimethacrylate and 2 parts of t-butyl peroxy
pivalate. The mixture was then stirred at 400 rpm to make
droplets having an average particle diameter of about 6 µm.
Subsequently, in an atmosphere of nitrogen, the suspension was
heated to a temperature of 70°C where stirring continued for
6 hours during which the reaction mixture was subjected to
suspension polymerization.</p><p num="0292">The reaction solution was allowed to cool to room
temperature, diluted with 1,000 parts of water, subjected to
solid-liquid separation by centrifugal separation method, and
then adjusted with water to a solid content of 50% by weight
to obtain a dispersion of particulate adhesive red resin F.</p><p num="0293">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
particulate adhesive red resin F thus obtained exhibited an
average particle diameter of 5.8 µm and a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle 
diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 97% by weight
of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate thermoplastic resin</u></heading><p num="0294">Into a 2-liter separable flask were charged 600 parts of
water in which 0.2 parts of sodium laurylsulfate and 20 parts
of methyl cellulose [Metrose 90SH-100, produced by Shin-Etsu
Chemical Co., Ltd.] were then dissolved to make a dispersant.</p><p num="0295">To the foregoing dispersant was then added a mixture of
134 parts of styrene, 6 parts of butyl acrylate and 3 parts of
2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile. Stirring continued at 400 rpm to
make droplets having an average particle diameter of about 6
µm. Subsequently, the suspension was heated to a temperature
of 70°C in an atmosphere of nitrogen for 6 hours during which
it underwent suspension polymerization.</p><p num="0296">The reaction solution was then allowed to cool to room
temperature. The reaction solution was washed with 2,000 parts
of water, subjected to solid-liquid separation by centrifugal
separation method, and then adjusted with water to a solid
content of 50% to obtain a dispersion of particulate
thermoplastic resin B.</p><p num="0297">The particulate material constituting the foregoing
dispersion of particulate thermoplastic resin B exhibited an
average particle diameter of 6.4 µm, a softening point of 125°C,
MI value of 15.0 and a particle diameter distribution such that
the amount of particles having a particle diameter of from 2
µm to 10 µm is not less than 93% by weight of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0298">36 parts of the dispersion of particulate adhesive red
resin F, 10 parts of the particulate thermoplastic resin B, 10
parts of ethylene glycol, 5 parts of urea, 0.1 parts of a
silicone-modified anti-foaming agent, 1 part of a preservative
(Proxel XL-2, produced by Zeneca Corp.), 0.2 parts of
succinoglycan (organic acid-modified heteropolysaccharide;
average molecular weight: approx. 1,000,000 to 8,000,000), 0.2
parts of a phosphoric acid ester-based surfactant [Plysurf
M208B, produced by Dai-ichi Kogyo Seiyaku Co., Ltd.], 1 part
of sodium laurylsulfate [SLS, produced by Nikko Chemicals Co.,
Ltd.] and 36.5 parts of water were mixed, and then stirred by
a disper until homogeneity was attained to obtain an ink
composition.</p><p num="0299">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 51 mPa ·s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an ELD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.224.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE 14</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate adhesive colored resin</u></heading><p num="0300">Into a 2-liter separable flask were charged 485 parts of
water in which 0.2 parts of sodium laurylsulfate and 15 parts
of Metrose 90SH-100 [methyl cellulose, produced by Shin-Etsu
Chemical Co., Ltd.] were then dissolved to make a dispersant.</p><p num="0301">To the foregoing dispersant was then added a coloring
composition consisting of 10 parts of carbon black (Printex L,
produced by Degussa-Huls Japan Co., Ltd.), 81 parts of butyl
acrylate, 5.4 parts of methyl methacrylate, 3.6 parts of
ethylene glycol dimethacrylate and 2 parts of 2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile.
Stirring continued at 400 rpm until 
the average particle diameter reached about 5 µm. Subsequently,
the suspension was heated to a temperature of 70°C in an
atmosphere of nitrogen for 6 hours during which it underwent
suspension polymerization.</p><p num="0302">The reaction solution was then allowed to cool to room
temperature. The reaction solution was diluted with 1,000
parts of water, subjected to solid-liquid separation by
centrifugal separation method, and then adjusted with water to
a solid content of 50% to obtain a dispersion of particulate
adhesive black resin G.</p><p num="0303">The particulate material constituting the foregoing
dispersion of particulate adhesive black resin G exhibited an
average particle diameter of 5.4 µm and a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 84% by weight
of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0304">An ink composition was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 11 except that the dispersion of particulate
thermoplastic red resin C, the dispersion of particulate
adhesive resin C and water were replaced by 36 parts of the
dispersion of particulate adhesive black resin G, 16 parts of
the dispersion of particulate thermoplastic resin B and 24.5
parts of water, respectively.</p><p num="0305">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 79 mPa · s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an EMD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.291.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate thermoplastic colored resin</u></heading><p num="0306">The particulate thermoplastic black resin A of Example
9 was further finely ground to obtain a particulate
thermoplastic black resin A'.</p><p num="0307">The particulate thermoplastic black resin A' thus
obtained exhibited an average particle diameter of 3.0 µm, a
softening point of 130°C, MI value of 9.0 and particles having
a particle diameter distribution such that the amount of
particles having a particle diameter of less than 2 µm is 39%
by weight of all the particles and particles having a particle
diameter distribution such that the amount of particles having
a particle diameter from 2 µm to 20 µm is 61% by weight of all
the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0308">An ink composition was prepared from the same composition
in the same manner as in Example 9 except that the particulate
thermoplastic black resin A was replaced by the particulate
thermoplastic black resin A'.</p><p num="0309">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 7.1 mPa · s (determined by an ELD type viscometer at 25°C).</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 10</u></heading><p num="0310">An ink composition was prepared from the same composition
in the same manner as in Example 10 except that the particulate
adhesive resin D was replaced by an acryl emulsion [Boncoat
ST-372, produced by DAINIPPON INK &amp; CHEMICALS, INC.; solid
content: 40%; average particle diameter: 0.2 µm; particles a
particle diameter distribution such that the amount of
particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is
not less than 2% by weight of all the particles]. </p><p num="0311">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 52 mPa · s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an ELD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.248.</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 11</u></heading><p num="0312">An ink composition was prepared from the same composition
in the same manner as in Example 2 except that the particulate
thermoplastic blue resin B was replaced by a particulate
thermosetting black resin [Artpearl C-800, produced by Negami
Chemical Industrial Co., Ltd.; average particle diameter: 6.1
µm; particles having a particle diameter distribution such that
the amount of particles having a particle diameter of from 2
µm to 20 µm is not less than 95% by weight of all the particles].</p><p num="0313">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 54 mPa · s (determined at 25°C and 100 rpm by an ELD type
viscometer) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.254.</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 12</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate thermoplastic colored resin</u></heading><p num="0314">A dispersion of thermoplastic red resin C' having a solid
content of 40% by weight was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 2 except that 115 parts of styrene, 25 parts of butyl
acrylate and 0.05 parts of 1,6-hexanediol diacrylate used in
the preparation of the dispersion of particulate thermoplastic
red resin were replaced by 112 parts of styrene, 28 parts of
butyl acrylate and 0.6 parts of divinylbenzene, respectively.</p><p num="0315">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
particulate thermoplastic red resin C' exhibited an average
particle diameter of 5.8 µm, a softening point of 210°C, MI value
of 0.05 and a particle diameter distribution such that particles 
having a particle diameter distribution such that the amount
of particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm
is not less than 92% by weight of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0316">An ink composition was prepared from the same composition
in the same manner as in Example 11 except that 36 parts of the
dispersion of particulate thermoplastic red resin C were
replaced by 36 parts of the dispersion of particulate
thermoplastic red resin C'.</p><p num="0317">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 85 mPa · s (determined by an ELD type viscometer at 25°C and
100 rpm) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.292.</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 13</u></heading><p num="0318">A dispersion of particulate adhesive black resin E'
having a solid content of 50% by weight was prepared in the same
manner as in Example 12 except that the dispersion of
particulate adhesive black resin E thus prepared was stirred
at a high speed to make droplets having a particle diameter of
about 2 µm.</p><p num="0319">The particulate material thus obtained exhibited an
average particle diameter of 2.1 µm and a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of less than 2 µm is 45% by weight of all the particles
and the amount of particles having a particle diameter of from
2 µm to 20 µm is 55% by weight of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0320">An ink composition was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 4 except that 40 parts of the dispersion of particulate 
adhesive black resin E of Example 12 were replaced by 40 parts
of the dispersion of particulate adhesive black resin E'.</p><p num="0321">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 7.9 mPa · s (determined by an ELD type viscometer at 25°C).</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 14</u></heading><p num="0322">A dispersion of particulate thermoplastic resin B' having
a solid content of 50% by weight was prepared in the same manner
as in Example 13 except that the dispersion of particulate
thermoplastic resin B thus prepared was stirred at a high speed
to make droplets having a particle diameter of about 2 µm.</p><p num="0323">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
particulate resin B' thus obtained exhibited an average
particle diameter of 2.2 µm, a softening point of 125°C, MI value
of 15.0 and a particle diameter distribution such that the
amount of particles having a particle diameter of less than 2
µm is 47% by weight of all the particles and the amount of
particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is
53% by weight of all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0324">An ink composition was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 13 except that 10 parts of the dispersion of particulate
thermoplastic resin B were replaced by 10 parts of the
dispersion of particulate thermoplastic resin B'.</p><p num="0325">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 58 mPa · s (determined by an ELD type viscometer at 25°C and
100 rpm) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.241.</p><heading><u style="single">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 15</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of particulate thermoplastic resin</u></heading><p num="0326">A dispersion of thermoplastic resin B" having a solid
content of 50% by weight was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 13 except that 134 parts of styrene and 6 parts of butyl
acrylate used in the preparation of the dispersion of
particulate thermoplastic resin B were replaced by 136 parts
of styrene, 4 parts of butyl acrylate and 0.08 parts of
divinylbenzene, respectively.</p><p num="0327">The particulate material constituting the dispersion of
particulate resin B" exhibited an average particle diameter of
6.7 µm, a softening point of 190°C, MI value of 0.3 and a particle
diameter distribution such that the amount of particles having
a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is 91% by weight of
all the particles.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of ink composition</u></heading><p num="0328">An ink composition was prepared in the same manner as in
Example 14 except that 16 parts of the dispersion of particulate
thermoplastic resin B were replaced by 16 parts of the
dispersion of particulate thermoplastic resin B".</p><p num="0329">The ink composition thus obtained exhibited a viscosity
of 83 mPa · s (determined by an ELD type viscometer at 25°C and
100 rpm) and a shear-thinning index (n) of 0.298.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of sample marking pen</u></heading><p num="0330">The ink compositions of Examples 9 and 12 and Comparative
Examples 9 and 13 were each packed into a marking pen of the
same type as mentioned above to prepare sample marking pens.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of sample ball point pen</u></heading><p num="0331">The ink compositions of Examples 10, 11, 13 and 14 and
Comparative Examples 10, 11, 12, 14 and 15 were each packed into 
a ballpoint pen of the same type as mentioned above to prepare
sample ball point pens.</p><heading><u style="single">Erasability test, fretting resistance test and heat fixability
test</u></heading><p num="0332">Using the foregoing various sample pens, a circle having
a diameter of 2 cm was continuously drawn on the surface of a
report paper (Model No. Re-116AN, produced by KOKUYO CO., LTD.).
The resulting writing was then rubbed 10 times with an eraser
[STAR Radar, produced by Seed Rubber Industry Co., Ltd.] under
a load of 2.0 kg applied to the end face thereof (area: 1.7 cm<sup>2</sup>)
after 5 seconds and 1 day. In this manner, the writing was
visually observed for its erasability.</p><p num="0333">For the fretting resistance test, the writing was allowed
to stand for 1 hour. A filter paper (No. 2 filter paper,
produced by ADVANTEC CO., LTD.) was then put on the writing in
an arrangement such that the smooth surface thereof faced the
writing. The filter paper was then reciprocally slid along the
writing 10 times under a load of 45.5 g/cm<sup>2</sup>. In this manner,
the writing was visually observed for fretting resistance</p><p num="0334">For the heat fixability test, a circle having a diameter
of 2 cm was continuously drawn on the surface of a report paper
(Model No. Re-116AN, produced by KOKUYO CO., LTD.). The sheet
of paper on which writing had been made was then put on the intake
port (manual tray) of a copying machine (Canon NP6045).
Subsequently, copying was made with no original sheet placed
on the exposure table. In this manner, the sheet of paper on
which writing had made was heated in contact with the heat roller
in the copying machine. The writing thus heated was then rubbed 
10 times with an eraser [STAR Radar, produced by Seed Rubber
Industry Co., Ltd.] under a load of 2.0 kg applied to the end
face thereof (area: 1.7 cm<sup>2</sup>). In this manner, the writing was
visually observed for fixability.</p><p num="0335">The results of erasability test, fretting resistance test
and heat-fixability test, the form of writing materials and the
color tone of writing of the foregoing examples and comparative
examples are set forth in the tables below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Example No.</entry><entry align="center">Rubber-erasability test</entry><entry align="center">Fretting resistance test</entry><entry align="center">Heat-fixability test</entry><entry align="center">Form of writing materials</entry><entry align="center">Color tone of writing</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 9</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Marking pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 10</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Blue</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 11</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Red</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 12</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Marking pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 13</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Red</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example 14</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables>
[0135]
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Example No.</entry><entry align="center">Rubber-erasability test</entry><entry align="center">Fretting resistance test</entry><entry align="center">Heat-fixability test</entry><entry align="center">Form of writing materials</entry><entry align="center">Color tone of writing</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 9</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Marking pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 10</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Blue</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 11</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Blue</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 12</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Δ</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Red</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 13</entry><entry align="center">X</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Marking pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 14</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Δ</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Red</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative Example 15</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">○</entry><entry align="center">Δ</entry><entry align="center">Ball point pen</entry><entry align="center">Black</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0336">The judgment symbols for erasability, fretting
resistance and heat-fixability in the tables above indicate the
following:</p><heading><u style="single">Erasability</u></heading><p num="0337"><dl compact="compact" tsize="2"><dt>○:</dt><dd>Easily erased;</dd><dt>X:</dt><dd>Not erased by 10 times rubbing</dd></dl></p><heading><u style="single">Fretting resistance</u></heading><p num="0338"><dl compact="compact" tsize="2"><dt>○:</dt><dd>Little or no peeling of writing;</dd></dl></p><heading><u style="single">Heat-fixability</u></heading><p num="0339"><dl compact="compact" tsize="2"><dt>○:</dt><dd>Little or no peeling of writing;</dd><dt>Δ:</dt><dd>Writing slightly peeled but can be sufficiently
recognized</dd><dt>X:</dt><dd>Writing mostly peeled and cannot be recognized</dd></dl></p><p num="0340">The ink composition of the present invention includes a
particulate adhesive colored resin or a particulate colored
resin and a particulate adhesive resin dispersed in a medium,
the particulate adhesive colored resin, particulate colored
resin and particulate adhesive resin each having a particle
diameter distribution such that the amount of particles having
a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 70%
by weight of all the particles. Since the ink composition of
the present invention includes a particulate material that can
little penetrate into paper and can satisfy both a good
rubber-erasability and a good fretting resistance, a
rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material composition
can be provided which gives writing on paper that can be easily
erased by an eraser but can exhibit a good preservability such
that it cannot be erased even when normally rubbed with finger 
or paper. Further, writing materials including the rubber-erasable
aqueous ink for a writing material composition
incorporated therein can be provided.</p><p num="0341">Further, the ink composition including a particulate
adhesive colored resin and a particulate thermoplastic resin
or a particulate thermoplastic colored resin and a particulate
adhesive resin dispersed in a medium can provide a rubber-erasable
aqueous ink for a writing material composition having
a permanent fixability which gives writing that can be easily
erased by an eraser as mentioned above but, when heated, cannot
be erased by an eraser and writing materials including such a
rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material composition
incorporated therein.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition comprising water, a water-soluble polar solvent,
and a particulate adhesive colored resin comprising a pigment
and an adhesive resin which is adhesive on at least a part of
a surface thereof, the particulate adhesive colored resin
having a particle diameter distribution such that the amount
of particles having a particle diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm
is not less than 70% by weight of all the particles.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 1, wherein the amount
of the particulate adhesive colored resin is contained in the
rubber-erasable aqueous ink in an amount of from 5 to 35% by
weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 1, wherein the weight
ratio of the adhesive resin to the pigment constituting the
particulate adhesive colored resin is from 2 : 1 to 40 : 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 1, wherein the
particulate adhesive colored resin is prepared by suspension
polymerization method.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 4, wherein the
particulate adhesive colored resin prepared by suspension
polymerization method includes a polymerized adhesive resin
having a crosslinked structure including a radical-polymerizable
monofunctional monomer and a polyfunctional
monomer, the weight ratio of the polyfunctional monomer to the
monofunctional monomer being from 2 : 100 to 10 : 100.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 1, wherein the
particulate adhesive colored resin exhibits a glass transition
temperature of lower than 40°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 1, wherein the
particulate adhesive colored resin includes a pigment
substantially homogeneously dispersed in an adhesive resin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 1, wherein the
particulate adhesive colored resin, when applied to and dried
on a paper, is point-bonded to the surface of paper in such an
arrangement that the various adhesive colored resin particles
are present independently of each other or scattered.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 1, including a
particulate thermoplastic resin having a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 70% by weight
of all the particles.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 9, wherein the
particulate thermoplastic resin exhibits a softening point of
from 60°C to 180°C and a melt flow index (MI) of from 0.1 to
30.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 9, wherein the
particulate thermoplastic resin is a particulate material
prepared by subjecting a radical-polymerizable monomer to
polymerization selected from the group consisting of suspension
polymerization, dispersion polymerization and seed
polymerization or a particulate material obtained by grinding
a particulate thermoplastic resin in a grinding process.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 9, wherein the
particulate adhesive colored resin and the particulate
thermoplastic resin are contained in an amount of from 5 to 30%
by weight and from 1 to 15% by weight, respectively, the weight
ratio of the particulate adhesive colored resin to the
particulate thermoplastic resin being from 100 : 2 to 100 : 50.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 9, wherein the
particulate adhesive colored resin, when applied to and dried
on a paper, is present in such an arrangement that particles
are point-bonded to each other and to the surface of paper, and
the particulate thermoplastic resin, when heated, melts to fix
the writing to the surface of paper.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing material
composition comprising a particulate adhesive resin, water, a
water-soluble polar solvent and a particulate colored resin
containing a pigment, the particulate colored resin and
particulate adhesive resin each having a particle diameter
distribution such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 20 µm is not less than 70% by weight
of all the particles.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 14, wherein the
particulate colored resin is a particulate material obtained
by subjecting a polymerizable composition including at least
a pigment and a radical-polymerizable monomer to polymerization
under suspension polymerization conditions.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 14, wherein the
particulate colored resin is a particulate material obtained
by a process which includes melt-mixing a resin and a pigment,
and then grinding the mixture in a grinding process.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 15, wherein the weight
ratio of the resin to the pigment constituting the particulate
colored resin is from 2 : 1 to 40 : 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 14, wherein the
particulate adhesive resin is a particulate material prepared
by polymerization selected from the group consisting of
suspension polymerization, dispersion polymerization and seed
polymerization.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 14, wherein the
particulate colored resin and particulate adhesive resin are
incorporated therein in an amount of from 5 to 30% by weight
and from 0.5 to 15% by weight, respectively, and the weight ratio
of the particulate colored resin to the particulate adhesive
resin is from 100 : 2 to 100 : 200.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 14, wherein the
particulate adhesive colored resin, when applied to and dried
on a paper, is present in such an arrangement that particles
are point-bonded to each other and to the surface of paper.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 14, wherein the
particulate colored resin is a particulate colored
thermoplastic resin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 21, wherein the
particulate colored thermoplastic resin exhibits a softening
point of from 60°C to 180°C and a melt flow index (MI) of from
0.1 to 30.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 21, wherein the
particulate colored resin is a particulate material obtained
by subjecting a polymerizable composition including at least
a pigment and a radical-polymerizable monomer to polymerization
under suspension polymerization conditions or a particulate
material obtained by a process which includes melt-mixing a
thermoplastic resin and a pigment, and then grinding the mixture
in a grinding process.</claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 21, wherein the weight
ratio of the thermoplastic resin to the pigment constituting
the particulate colored thermoplastic resin is from 2 : 1 to
40 : 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="25"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 21, wherein the
particulate colored thermoplastic resin and particulate
adhesive resin are incorporated therein in an amount of from
5 to 30% by weight and from 0.5 to 15% by weight, respectively,
and the weight ratio of the particulate colored thermoplastic
resin to the particulate adhesive resin is from 100 : 2 to 100 :
200.</claim-text></claim><claim num="26"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to any one of claims 21 to 25,
wherein the particulate adhesive colored resin, when applied
to and dried on a paper, is present in such an arrangement that
particles are point-bonded to each other and to the surface of
paper, and the particulate thermoplastic colored resin, when
heated, melts to fix the writing to the surface of paper.</claim-text></claim><claim num="27"><claim-text>A marking pen including a rubber-erasable aqueous
ink for a writing material composition according to any one of
claims 1 to 26 incorporated therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="28"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 1, including a
shear-thinning agent incorporated therein and exhibiting a
viscosity of from 25 to 160 mPa .s (determined at 25°C by means
of an EMD type viscometer) and a shear-thinning index of from
0.1 to 0.7 at 100 rpm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="29"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 28, wherein including
a particle diameter distribution of all the particles contained
therein is such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 80% by weight
of all the particles contained therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="30"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 28, further including
a stabilizer for the particulate colored adhesive resin or
particulate adhesive resin incorporated therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="31"><claim-text>A ball point pen including a rubber-erasable aqueous
ink for a writing material composition for ball point pen
according to any one of claims 28 to 30 incorporated therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="32"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 14, including a
shear-thinning agent incorporated therein and exhibiting a
viscosity of from 25 to 160 mPa .s (determined at 25°C by means
of an EMD type viscometer) and a shear-thinning index of from
0.1 to 0.7 at 100 rpm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="33"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 32, wherein including
a particle diameter distribution of all the particles contained
therein is such that the amount of particles having a particle
diameter of from 2 µm to 10 µm is not less than 80% by weight
of all the particles contained therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="34"><claim-text>The rubber-erasable aqueous ink for a writing
material composition according to claim 32, further including
a stabilizer for the particulate colored adhesive resin or
particulate adhesive resin incorporated therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="35"><claim-text>A ball point pen including a rubber-erasable aqueous
ink for a writing material composition for ball point pen
according to any one of claims 32 to 34 incorporated therein.</claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure num="1"><img id="img-01040001" orientation="unknown" wi="167" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="01040001.tif" inline="no" he="218"/></figure><figure num="2"><img id="img-01050001" orientation="unknown" wi="152" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="01050001.tif" inline="no" he="218"/></figure></drawings><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="176" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="270" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="179" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="267" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>