<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1424125-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1424125" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="32298082" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040602"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1424125-A1" status="new" fvid="24047685"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1424125</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040602</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03256944-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03256944</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031103</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-30666402-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>30666402</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021127</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  23/00        20060101AFI20080110BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  23/00        20060101CFI20080110BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  23/76        20060101CLI20080110BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  23/843       20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  23/88        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  23/887       20060101ALI20080110BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  37/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  37/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  37/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07B  61/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07B  61/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  45/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  45/34        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  45/35        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  51/16        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  51/25        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 253/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 253/24        20060101ALN20080110BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 253/26        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 255/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 255/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  23/00B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  23/887H</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C 253/26</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C  45/34</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C  45/35+47/22</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C  51/25B+57/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01J23:887B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07C255:08</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung eines Antimon enthaltenden Mischmetalloxidkatalysators und so erhaltener Katalysator</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Process for preparing an antimony based mixed metal oxide catalyst and catalyst obtained</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé de préparation d'un catalyseur d'oxydes mixtes comprenant d'antimoine et catalyseur ainsi obtenu</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-4547484-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4547484</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000072962-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000072962</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>SOLUTIA INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SOLUTIA INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Solutia Inc.</last-name><address><street>575 Maryville Centre Drive</street><city>St. Louis, Missouri 63141</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TWAY CATHY L</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TWAY, CATHY L.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TWAY, CATHY L.</last-name><address><street>511 wakefield Drive</street><city>League City Texas 77573</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Harrison, Ivor Stanley</last-name><address><street>Withers &amp;amp; Rogers, Goldings House, 2 Hays Lane</street><city>London SE1 2HW</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A process for preparing an antimonate-based mixed metal oxide catalyst in a
catalytically active oxidized state, wherein the catalyst is represented by the empirical
formula Me<sub>a</sub>Sb<sub>b</sub>X<sub>c</sub>Q<sub>d</sub>R<sub>e</sub>O<sub>f</sub>, wherein Me, X, Q, R, a, b, c, d, e, and f are as defined
herein, comprising (a) contacting an aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry with HNO<sub>3</sub> and one or
more Me compounds, and, optionally, one or more compounds selected from X, Q, or
R compounds to form a first mixture; (b) heating and drying the first mixture to form
a solid product; and (c) calcining the solid product to form the catalyst, the catalysts
prepared by the process, and the use of the catalysts in ammoxidation and oxidation
processes. The catalysts of the invention are particularly useful for the production of
acrylonitrile from propylene, ammonia, and an oxygen-containing gas.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to a process for the production of
antimonate-based mixed metal oxide catalysts and the catalysts produced therefrom.
This invention further relates to use of the antimonate-based mixed metal oxide
catalysts of the invention in reactions for the ammoxidation or oxidation of organic
compounds.</p><p num="0002">It is known that antimony-containing metal oxide catalysts,
specifically those comprising the oxides of antimony and at least one metal selected
from the group consisting of iron, cobalt, nickel, tin, uranium, chromium, copper,
manganese, titanium, and cerium are useful for the production of aldehydes and
carboxylic acids through oxidation of organic compounds, i.e. olefins, the production
of dienes, unsaturated aldehydes and unsaturated acids through oxidative
dehydrogenation of olefins, and the production of nitriles through ammoxidation of
olefins, alcohols and aldehydes.</p><p num="0003">Various catalytic processes are known for the oxidation or
ammoxidation of olefins. Such processes commonly react an olefin or an olefin-ammonia
mixture with oxygen in the vapor phase in the presence of a catalyst. For
the production of acrolein and acrylonitrile, propylene is the generally used olefin
reactant, and for the production of methacrolein and methacrylonitrile, isobutene is
the generally used olefin reactant.</p><p num="0004">Many catalysts are disclosed as suitable in the oxidation and/or
ammoxidation of olefins, including those catalysts disclosed in U.S. Patent Nos.
5,094,990; 4,590,175; 4,547,484; 4,487,850; and 4,413,155. One such catalyst is
described in U.S. Patent No. 4,547,484. This catalyst is represented by the empirical
formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Sb<sub>a</sub>U<sub>b</sub>Fe<sub>c</sub>Bi<sub>d</sub>Mo<sub>c</sub>O<sub>f</sub></st32:che>
wherein a is 1 to 10, b is 0.1 to 5, c is 0.1 to 5, d is 0.001 to 0.1, e is 0.001 to 0.2, and f
is a number taken to satisfy the valence requirements of Sb, U, Fe, Bi, and Mo in the
oxidation states in which they exist in the catalyst. The processes for preparing these 
catalysts involve the addition of solid, generally powdered, antimony, added as
antimony metal or Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> to the reactor.</p><p num="0005">Although the yield and selectivity of the above-described catalysts
are generally satisfactory, the commercial utility of a catalyst system is highly
dependent upon the cost of the system, the conversion of the reactant(s), the yield of
the desired product(s), and the stability of the catalyst during operation. In many
cases, a reduction in the cost of a catalyst system on the order of a few cents per
pound or a small percent increase in the yield of the desired product represents a
tremendous commercial economical advantage. Since it is well known that the
economics of acrylonitrile manufacture dictate increasingly higher yields and
selectivity of conversion of reactants to acrylonitrile in order to minimize the
difficulties attending the purification of the product and handling of large recycle
streams, research efforts are continually being made to define new or improved
catalyst systems and methods and processes of making new and old catalyst systems
to reduce the cost and/or upgrade the activity and selectivity of such catalyst systems.
A catalyst having improved reproducibility and homogeneity, and containing
substantially less α-Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> while having equivalent or better catalyst performance is
desired. The discovery of the improved catalysts of the present invention and the
method of preparing the improved catalysts of the present invention is therefore
believed to be a decided advance in the state of the art.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0006">According to the invention, a process for preparing an antimonate-based
mixed metal oxide catalyst in a catalytically active oxidized state is provided
wherein the catalyst is represented by the empirical formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Me<sub>a</sub>Sb<sub>b</sub>X<sub>c</sub>Q<sub>d</sub>R<sub>e</sub>O<sub>f</sub></st32:che>
wherein Me is at least one element selected from Fe, Co, Ni, Sn, U, Cr, Cu, Mn, Ti,
Th, Ce, Pr, Sm, or Nd; X is at least one element selected from V, Mo, or W; Q is at
least one element selected from Li, Na, K, Rb, Cs, Be, Mg, Ca, Sr, Ba, Sc, Y, La, Zr,
Hf, Nb, Ta, Re, Ru, Os, Rh, Ir, Pd, Pt, Ag, Au, Zn, Cd, Hg, Al, Ga, In, Tl, Ge, Pb, As,
or Se; R is at least one element selected from Bi, B, P, or Te; and the subscripts a, b,
c, d, e, and f denote atomic ratios and are as follows: a is 0.1 to 15, b is 1 to 100, c is 0 
to 20, d is 0 to 20, e is 0 to 10, and f is a number taken to satisfy the valence
requirements of the metals present in the catalyst in the oxidation states in which they
exist in the catalyst, comprising:
<sl><li>(a) contacting an aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry with HNO<sub>3</sub> and one or more Me
compounds, and, optionally, one or more compounds selected from X, Q, or R
compounds to form a first mixture;</li><li>(b) heating and drying the first mixture to form a solid product; and</li><li>(c) calcining the solid product to form the catalyst.</li></sl></p><p num="0007">Further according to the invention, antimonate-based mixed metal
oxide catalysts in a catalytically active oxidized state prepared according to the
process of the present invention are provided.</p><p num="0008">Still further according to the invention, ammoxidation, oxidation,
and oxydehydrogenation processes utilizing the antimonate-based mixed metal oxide
catalysts of the present invention which are prepared according to the process of the
present invention are provided.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0009">Not Applicable.</p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading><p num="0010">Catalysts that can be prepared according to the process of the
present invention include, but are not limited to, those catalysts having the empirical
formulae described in U.S. Patent Nos. 5,094,990; 4,590,175; 4,547,484; 4,487,850;
and 4,413,155, the disclosures of which are incorporated by reference herein in their
entirety.</p><p num="0011">This invention provides an antimonate-based mixed metal oxide
catalyst in a catalytically active oxidized state wherein the catalyst is represented by
the empirical formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Me<sub>a</sub>Sb<sub>b</sub>X<sub>c</sub>Q<sub>d</sub>R<sub>e</sub>O<sub>f</sub></st32:che>
wherein Me is at least one element selected from Fe, Co, Ni, Sn, U, Cr, Cu, Mn, Ti,
Th, Ce, Pr, Sm, or Nd; X is at least one element selected from V, Mo, or W; Q is at
least one element selected from Li, Na, K, Rb, Cs, Be, Mg, Ca, Sr, Ba, Sc, Y, La, Zr,
Hf, Nb, Ta, Re, Ru, Os, Rh, Ir, Pd, Pt, Ag, Au, Zn, Cd, Hg, Al, Ga, In, TI, Ge, Pb, As, 
or Se; R is at least one element selected from Bi, B, P, or Te; and the subscripts a, b,
c, d, e, and f denote atomic ratios and are as follows:
<sl><li>a is 0.1 to 15, preferably 0.1 to 10, and more preferably 0.1 to 5;</li><li>b is 1 to 100, preferably 1 to 50, and more preferably 1 to 10;</li><li>c is 0 to 20, preferably 0.001 to 5, more preferably 0.001 to 0.2, and most preferably
0.01 to 0.2;</li><li>d is 0 to 20, and preferably 0 to 10;</li><li>e is 0 to 10, preferably 0.001 to 5, more preferably 0.001 to 0.2, and most preferably
0.01 to 0.2; and</li><li>f is a number taken to satisfy the valence requirements of the metals present in the
catalyst in the oxidation states in which they exist in the catalyst.</li></sl></p><p num="0012">A particularly preferred catalyst of the invention is represented by
the empirical formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">U<sub>a'</sub>Fe<sub>a</sub>Sb<sub>b</sub>Mo<sub>c</sub>Bi<sub>e</sub>O<sub>f</sub></st32:che>
wherein a and a' are independently selected from 0.1 to 5, preferably 0.1 to 1; b is 1 to
10, preferably 1 to 5; c is 0.001 to 0.2, preferably 0.01 to 0.1; and e is 0.001 to 0.2,
preferably 0.01 to 0.05.</p><p num="0013">The catalysts of the present invention are prepared by an improved
process comprising:
<sl><li>(a) contacting an aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry with HNO<sub>3</sub> and one or more Me
compounds, preferably Me oxide or Me nitrate compounds, and, optionally, one or
more compounds selected from X, Q, or R compounds to form a first mixture;</li><li>(b) heating and drying the first mixture to form a solid product; and</li><li>(c) calcining the solid product to form the catalyst.</li></sl></p><p num="0014">The preferred Me elements are selected from Fe, Co, Ni, Sn, U, Cr,
Cu, Mn, Ti, Th, or Ce, with Fe and U being currently most preferred. The preferred R
elements are selected from Bi, Te, or P, with Bi being currently most preferred. The
currently preferred X element is Mo. The preferred Q elements are selected from Mg,
Ca, Zr, Nb, Ta, Zn, Al, Ga, and Pb. When more than one element of a particular
group, i.e. more than one Me element, is present in the catalyst, the subscript of each
element of a particular group is independently selected according to the definition of
that specific subscript. For example, if Me is selected to include U and Fe, each 
subscript "a" is independently selected from 0.1 to 15, preferably 0.1 to 10, and more
preferably 0.1 to 5.</p><p num="0015">The compounds containing Me suitable for use in the process of
the invention include oxide and nitrate compounds. Examples of suitable Me
compounds include, but are not limited to, triuranium octoxdide, uranium dioxide,
uranyl nitrate, and ferric nitrate. When Me is iron (III), the Fe compounds also can
include Fe<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>, Fe(OH)<sub>3</sub> and FeCl<sub>3</sub>. When Me is iron (III), the preferred Fe
compound is ferric nitrate.</p><p num="0016">Suitable compounds containing elements X, Q, and R for use in the
process of the invention include compounds capable of dissolving under acid
conditions such as oxide, nitrate, chloride and sulfate compounds, or reaction products
thereof. The preferred compounds are oxide and nitrate compounds. For example,
the compounds containing elements X, Q, and R can be added as the oxide or nitrate,
as a corresponding salt, or optionally added as the oxide or nitrate and reacted <i>in situ</i>
with a suitable compound to produce the corresponding salt. Examples of suitable X
compounds include molybdenum oxide, tungsten oxide, vanadium oxide, ferric
molybdate, ammonium molybdate, ammonium metatungstate, and ammonium
metavanadate. Examples of suitable R compounds include bismuth trioxide, bismuth
nitrate, tellurium dioxide, phosphoric acid, ammonium salts of phosphoric acid,
phosphorus pentoxide, and boric acid. Examples of suitable Q compounds include
potassium nitrate, magnesium oxide, magnesium nitrate, zirconiuim oxide, aluminum
oxide, aluminum nitrate, zinc oxide, and zinc nitrate.</p><p num="0017">The process of the present invention requires that a slurry of Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
be contacted with HNO<sub>3</sub>. In the process of the invention, HNO<sub>3</sub> can be added to the
aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry or the aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry can be added to HNO<sub>3</sub>. It is
currently preferred to add HNO<sub>3</sub> to the aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry. The aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
slurry can be prepared and used immediately in the preparation of the catalyst of the
invention, or the aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry can be prepared and stored for later use in the
preparation of the catalyst of the invention. The aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry can be prepared
by any conventional technique known in the art. In addition, commercially available
Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurries can also be used, e.g. colloidal Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is commercially available and
would work very well in the process of the invention. It is currently preferred that the 
aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry be prepared under high shear or mixed under high shear prior to
contacting the aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry with the HNO<sub>3</sub>. The use of the aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
slurry in the process of the present invention results in a catalyst having improved
homogeneity and substantially less α-Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> in the final catalyst while having
equivalent or better catalyst performance than the catalysts prepared using powdered
antimony oxide.</p><p num="0018">The first mixture is preferably heated prior to the heating and
drying of step (b), preferably before addition of the compound of element X, in order
to convert the initial α-Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> to other crystalline oxides of antimony, including
β-Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and other antimony oxides i.e. at least a portion of the antimony trioxide
being converted to higher oxidation states such as antimony tetroxide and antimony
pentoxide. It is particularly preferred to utilize this heating step when a uranium
oxide is added to the first mixture. The time required to induce formation of the
desired crystalline oxides of antimony can vary and will depend, at least in part, on
the temperature employed. Generally, a time period of about 1 hour to about 6 hours,
preferably about 2 to about 5 hours, at temperatures from about 80°C to about 110°C
is sufficient.</p><p num="0019">The catalyst of the present invention can be employed with or
without a support. In some applications, it is advantageous to include in the catalyst a
support material which functions by providing a large surface area for the catalyst and
by creating a harder and more durable catalyst for use in the highly abrasive
environment of a fluidized bed reactor. This support material can be any of those
commonly proposed for such use, such as, for example, silica, zirconia, alumina,
titania, antimony pentoxide sol, or other oxide substrates. From the point of view of
availability, cost, and performance, silica is usually a satisfactory support material and
is preferably in the form of silica sol for easy dispersion.</p><p num="0020">The proportions in which the components of the supported
catalysts are present can vary widely, but it is usually preferred that the support
provides from about 10% to about 90%, and more preferably about 35% to about 65%
by weight of the total combined weight of the catalyst and the support. To
incorporate a support into the catalyst, the support material is preferably slurried
along with the first mixture in water, preferably after the heating step used to form the 
crystalline oxides of antimony, at an appropriate pH while maintaining slurry fluidity.
When the support material is basic, the pH can be about 7 to about 9. When the
support material is acidic, such as acidic silica sol, low pH slurries (pH ≤ 4) are
desirable. The preparation of the slurry will be dependent on the specific support
material used, and such preparation conditions will be readily apparent to those
skilled in the art.</p><p num="0021">The pH of the first mixture is adjusted, if necessary, prior to the
heating and drying of step (b). Depending on the specific catalyst being prepared, the
pH may need to be adjusted upward or downward.</p><p num="0022">At this point, the intimately mixed slurry is heated to remove the
bulk of the aqueous phase. The concentrated slurry contains a certain amount of
water and it is desirable to remove this water by some form of drying process to form
a dry catalyst precursor. This can take the form of a simple oven drying process in
which the water-containing solid phase is subjected to a temperature that is
sufficiently high to vaporize the water and completely dry the solid phase.</p><p num="0023">An alternate drying process which may be employed is the so-called
spray-drying process. In this process, which is preferred for use in the present
invention, water-containing solid phase particles are sprayed into contact with hot gas
(usually air) so as to vaporize the water. The drying is controlled by the temperature
of the gas and the distance the particles travel in contact with the gas. It is generally
desirable to adjust these parameters to avoid too rapid drying as this results in a
tendency to form dried skins on the partially dried particles of the solid phase which
are subsequently ruptured as water occluded within the particles vaporizes and
attempts to escape. At the same time, it is desirable to provide the catalyst in a form
having as little occluded water as possible. Therefore, where a fluidized bed reactor is
to be used and microspheroidal particles are desired, it is advisable to choose the
conditions of spray-drying with a view to achieving substantial complete drying
without particle rupture.</p><p num="0024">Following the drying operation, the catalyst precursor is calcined to
form the active catalyst. The calcination is usually conducted in air at essentially
atmospheric pressure and at a temperature of about 500°C to about 1150°C, preferably
from about 600°C to about 900°C. The time to complete the calcination can vary and 
will depend upon the temperature employed. In general the time can be anything up
to 24 hours, but for most purposes, a time period from about 1 hour to about 4 hours
at the designated temperature is sufficient.</p><p num="0025">A preferred process for forming the catalysts of the present
invention is described hereafter using the currently preferred catalyst of the invention
represented by the empirical formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">U<sub>a'</sub>Fe<sub>a</sub>Sb<sub>b</sub>Mo<sub>c</sub>Bi<sub>e</sub>O<sub>f</sub></st32:che>
wherein a and a' are independently selected from 0.1 to 5, b is 1 to 10, c is 0.001 to
0.2, and e is 0.001 to 0.1. While the preferred process is described for the currently
preferred catalyst, the preferred process can be utilized with any catalyst of the
present invention by choosing the appropriate reaction components and specific
reaction conditions.</p><p num="0026">In a preferred embodiment, this invention provides a process for
preparing an antimonate-based mixed metal oxide catalyst in a catalytically active
oxidized state, said catalyst represented by the empirical formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">U<sub>a'</sub>Fe<sub>a</sub>Sb<sub>b</sub>Mo<sub>c</sub>Bi<sub>e</sub>O<sub>f</sub></st32:che>
wherein the subscripts a, a', b, c, e, and f denote atomic rations and are as follows: a is
0.1 to 5, a' is 0.1 to 5, b is 1 to 10, c is 0.001 to 0.2, e is 0.001 to 0.2, and f is a number
taken to satisfy the valence requirements of Sb, U, Fe, Bi, and Mo present in said
catalyst in the oxidation states in which they exist in said catalyst, comprising:
<sl><li>(a) contacting an aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry with HNO<sub>3</sub>, oxides or nitrates of
bismuth, and oxides or nitrates of uranium to form a first mixture;</li><li>(b) heating the first mixture at a temperature and for a time sufficient to
induce formation of the desired crystalline oxides of antimony (including β-Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and
other antimony oxides, e.g. at least a portion of the antimony trioxide being converted
to higher oxidation states such as antimony tetroxide and antimony pentoxide) and
form a second mixture;</li><li>(c) adding an aqueous solution of a ferric compound to the second mixture
to form a third mixture;</li><li>(d) adjusting the pH of the third mixture to about 7 to about 8.5, thereby
forming a hydrated mixed oxide precipitate in an aqueous phase; </li><li>(e) separating the hydrated mixed oxide precipitate from the aqueous
phase;</li><li>(f) forming an aqueous slurry of the hydrated mixed oxide precipitate
component;</li><li>(g) adding a molybdate to the hydrated mixed oxide component slurry;</li><li>'(h) forming the hydrated mixed oxide - molybdate component slurry into
dry particles; and</li><li>(i) calcining the dry particles to form the catalyst.</li></sl></p><p num="0027">In the formation of the first mixture, it is currently preferred to
contact the HNO<sub>3</sub> with the aqueous Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry prior to contacting the aqueous
Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry with the oxides or nitrates of bismuth and uranium. Although the order
of addition is not critical, it is currently preferred to add the HNO<sub>3</sub> to the aqueous
Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> slurry. The oxides or nitrates of bismuth and uranium can be added together or
separately in either order. It is currently preferred to add the oxides or nitrates of
bismuth prior to the oxides or nitrates of uranium. The currently preferred bismuth
and uranium compounds are bismuth oxide (Bi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) and triuranium octoxide (U<sub>3</sub>O<sub>8</sub>).
If bismuth and uranium oxides are used, it is preferred to add the bismuth oxide, heat
the slurry to a temperature of about 60°C, and then begin addition of the uranium
oxide. If bismuth and uranium nitrates are used, it is preferred not to heat the slurry
until after the addition of both compounds is completed.</p><p num="0028">The first mixture is heated to form the second mixture, in order to
convert alpha-antimony trioxide to beta-antimony trioxide and other crystalline oxides
of antimony, at least a portion of the antimony trioxide being converted to higher
oxidation states such as antimony tetroxide and antimony pentoxide. The time
required to induce formation of the desired crystalline oxides of antimony can vary
and will depend, at least in part, on the temperature employed. Generally, a time
period of about 1 hour to about 6 hours, preferably about 2 to about 5 hours, at
temperatures from about 80°C to about 110°C is sufficient.</p><p num="0029">After the heating period is completed, an aqueous solution of ferric
compound, preferably ferric nitrate, e.g. Fe(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> 9H<sub>2</sub>O, is added to the second
mixture, optionally having been cooled to a temperature of about 40°C to about 60°C
prior to the ferric compound addition. The pH of the resultant mixture is adjusted to 
about 7 to about 8.5, such as by using aqueous ammonia. The resulting hydrated
mixed oxides precipitate and are then separated from the aqueous phase and
thoroughly washed to remove substantially all occluded impurities, most notably
ammonium nitrate. The hydrated mixed oxides precipitate component is subsequently
reslurried to form an aqueous slurry.</p><p num="0030">The molybdate may be introduced to the hydrated mixed oxide
component slurry as any compound that does not interfere with catalysis or neutralize
the catalyst. Ammonium molybdate has been successfully employed to introduce the
molybdate, and is currently preferred, being the simplest to prepare (from
molybdenum trioxide and aqueous ammonia).</p><p num="0031">The catalyst of the present invention can be employed with or
without a support. In some applications, it is advantageous to include in the catalyst a
support material which functions by providing a large surface area for the catalyst and
by creating a harder and more durable catalyst for use in the highly abrasive
environment of a fluidized bed reactor. This support material can be any of those
commonly proposed for such use, such as, for example, silica, zirconia, alumina,
titania, antimony pentoxide sol, or other oxide substrates. From the point of view of
availability, cost, and performance, silica is usually a satisfactory support material and
is preferably in the form of silica sol for easy dispersion.</p><p num="0032">The proportions in which the components of the supported
catalysts are present can vary widely, but it is usually preferred that the support
provides from about 10% to about 90%, more preferably about 35% to about 65%,
and most preferably about 45% to about 55%, by weight of the total combined weight
of the catalyst and the support. To incorporate a support into the catalyst, the support
material is preferably slurried along with the molybdate in the hydrated mixed oxide
component slurry at an appropriate pH while maintaining slurry fluidity. When the
support material is basic, the pH can be about 7 to about 9. When the support
material is acidic, such as acidic silica sol, low pH slurries (pH ≤ 4) is desirable. The
preparation of the slurry will be dependent on the specific support material used, and
such preparation conditions will be readily apparent to those skilled in the art.</p><p num="0033">The resultant slurry is milled, such as by using a ball mill, for a
period of time sufficient to reduce the solid particles to a size less than 10 µ diameter. 
For example, a typical time for slurry milling is about 20 hours. Thereafter, the pH of
the slurry is adjusted, if necessary, to about 8 to about 9.</p><p num="0034">Optionally, the milled slurry can be heated to a suitable
temperature, e.g. about 95°C to about 105°C, and held for a suitable time, e.g. about 2
to about 6 hours. If a slurry heating is used, the heated slurry is milled a second time
as described above. The heated slurry can optionally be cooled prior to the milling
operation if desired.</p><p num="0035">At this point, the intimately mixed slurry is dried and calcined as
described above to produce the catalyst of the invention.</p><p num="0036">The catalysts of the invention can be utilized in the ammoxidation
and oxidation, of olefins.</p><heading><u style="single">Ammoxidation</u></heading><p num="0037">A wide variety of different reactants can be ammoxidized in
accordance with the present invention to produce nitriles. For example, olefins such
as propylene, isobutylene, 2-methyl-1-pentene, 1,4-hexadiene, and the like, alcohols
such as methanol, t-butyl alcohol, and aldehydes such as acrolein and methacrolein
can be readily converted to nitriles in accordance with the present invention. In
general, compounds which can be converted to nitriles by the ammoxidation reaction
using the catalysts of the present invention include 1 to 9 carbon atom hydrocarbons,
unsubstituted or substituted with oxygen or hydroxy. Preferred starting materials are
olefins, aldehydes and alcohols containing 1 or 4 carbon atoms.</p><p num="0038">The general ammoxidation process for converting olefins, alcohols
and aldehydes to nitriles is well known. See, for example, U.S. Pat. No. 3,546,138,
the disclosure of which is incorporated herein by reference. In general, the
ammoxidation reaction is accomplished by contacting the reactant, oxygen and
ammonia with a particular catalyst in the vapor phase. The reaction can be carried out
in the same manner and under the conditions generally set forth in this patent.</p><p num="0039">In the most frequently used ammoxidation processes, a mixture of
olefin, ammonia, and oxygen (or air) is fed into a reactor and through a bed of catalyst
particles at elevated temperatures. Such temperatures are usually in the range of
about 400°C to about 550°C, and preferably about 425°C to about 500°C, and the
pressure is from about 1 atmosphere to about 6 atmospheres (100 kPa to about 600 
kPa). The ammonia and olefin are required stoichiometrically in equimolar amounts,
but it is usually necessary to operate with a molar ratio of ammonia to olefin in excess
of 1 to reduce the incidence of side reactions. Likewise, the stoichiometric oxygen
requirement is 1.5 times the molar amount of olefin. The feed mixture is commonly
introduced into the catalyst bed at a W/F (defined as the weight of the catalyst in
grams divided by the flow of reactant stream in ml/sec. at standard temperature and
pressure) in the range of about 2 g-sec/ml to about 15 g-sec/ml, preferably from about
3 g-sec/ml to about 10 g-sec/ml.</p><p num="0040">The ammoxidation reaction is exothermic and for convenience in
heat distribution and removal, the catalyst bed is desirably fluidized. However, fixed
catalyst beds may also be employed with alternative heat removal means such as
cooling coils within the bed.</p><p num="0041">The catalyst as prepared by the process of this invention is
particularly well adapted for use in such a process in that improved yields of and
selectivities to the desired product(s) are experienced due to the unique and novel
catalyst preparation procedures employed herein.</p><heading><u style="single">Oxidation</u></heading><p num="0042">As previously indicated, the catalysts of this invention can also be
employed in the catalytic oxidation of olefins to various different reaction products.</p><p num="0043">The reactants used in the oxidation to oxygenated compounds are
oxygen and an olefin such as propylene, isobutylene and other olefins having up to
three contiguous carbon atoms (i.e. three carbon atoms arranged in a straight chain).</p> <p num="0044">The olefins may be in admixture with paraffinic hydrocarbons,
such as ethane, propane, butane and pentane; for example, a propylene-propane
mixture may constitute the feed. This makes it possible to use ordinary refinery
streams without special preparation.</p><p num="0045">The temperature at which this oxidation is conducted may vary
considerably depending upon the catalyst, the particular olefin being oxidized and the
correlated conditions of the rate of throughput or contact time and the ratio of olefin
to oxygen. In general, when operating at pressures near atmospheric, i.e., 0.1-10
atmospheres, temperatures in the range of 150°C to 600°C may be advantageously
employed. However, the process may be conducted at other pressures, and in the case 
where superatmospheric pressures, e.g., above 10 atmospheres are employed,
somewhat lower temperatures are possible. In the case where this process is
employed to convert propylene to acrolein, a temperature range of 200°C to 500°C has
been found to be optimum at atmospheric pressure.</p><p num="0046">While pressures other than atmospheric may be employed, it is
generally preferred to operate at or near atmospheric pressure, since the reaction
proceeds well at such pressures and the use of expensive high pressure equipment is
avoided, and formation of undesired byproducts and waste is diminished.</p><p num="0047">The apparent contact time employed in the process is not critical
and it may be selected from a broad operable range that may vary from 0.1 to 50
seconds. The apparent contact time may be defined as the length of time in seconds
which a unit volume of gas measured under the conditions of reaction is in contact
with the apparent unit volume of the catalyst. It may be calculated, for example, from
the apparent volume of the catalyst bed, the average temperature and pressure of the
reactor, and the flow rates of the several components of the reaction mixture.</p><p num="0048">The optimum contact time will, of course, vary depending upon the
olefin being treated, but in the case of propylene and isobutylene, the preferred
contact time is 0.15 to 15 seconds.</p> <p num="0049">A molar ratio of oxygen to olefin between about 0.5:1 to 5:1
generally gives the most satisfactory results. For the conversion of propylene to
acrolein, a preferred ratio of oxygen to olefin is from about 1:1 to about 2:1. The
oxygen used in the process may be derived from any source; however, air is the least
expensive source of oxygen and is preferred for that reason.</p> <p num="0050">Inert diluents such as nitrogen and carbon dioxide, may be present
in the reaction mixture.</p> <p num="0051">In carrying out the foregoing ammoxidation and oxidation
processes, any apparatus of the type suitable for carrying out oxidation reactions in
the vapor phase may be employed. The processes may be conducted either
continuously or intermittently. The catalyst may be a fixed-bed employing a large
particulate or pelleted catalyst or, in the alternative, a fluid-bed catalyst may be
employed. </p><p num="0052">The following examples illustrating the invention are described in
order to facilitate a clear understanding of the invention. It should be understood,
however, that the examples, while indicating preferred embodiments, are given by
way of illustration only and are not to be construed as limiting the invention since
various changes and modifications within the spirit of the invention will become
apparent to those skilled in the art from the description.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLES</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Abbreviations and Source of Material</u></heading><p num="0053"><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></b></entry><entry align="left">Antimony trioxide ― Great Lakes Chemical</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>HNO<sub>3</sub></b></entry><entry align="left">Nitric acid, 70% A.C.S. reagent grade - VWR Scientific Products</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>U<sub>3</sub>O<sub>8</sub></b></entry><entry align="left">Triuranium octoxide - Starmet Corporation</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Bi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></b></entry><entry align="left">Bismuth oxide - Ferro Corporation</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>NH<sub>4</sub>OH</b></entry><entry align="left">Ammoniuim hydroxide, 28%, A.C.S. reagent grade - VWR Scientific Products</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Fe(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></b></entry><entry align="left">Ferric nitrate, 7% Fe solution - Bluegrass Chemicals</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>SiO<sub>2</sub></b></entry><entry align="left">Silica Sol ― Ondeo Nalco</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>MoO<sub>3</sub></b></entry><entry align="left">Molybdenum trioxide - Climax Molybdenum</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0054">As used herein, the following terms are defined in the following
manner:
<sl><li>1. "W/F" is defined as the weight of the catalyst in grams divided by the flow rate of
the reactant stream in mL/sec measured at STP, the units being g-sec/mL. </li><li>2. "Propylene (C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>6</sub>) conversion" is defined as:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center"><st32:frac align="centre">moles C<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub>H<st32:sub pos="post">6</st32:sub> in feed - moles C<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub>H<st32:sub pos="post">6</st32:sub> in effluent <st32:over>moles C<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub>H<st32:sub pos="post">6</st32:sub> in feed</st32:over></st32:frac>x 100</st32:df></li><li>3. "Acrylonitrile (AN) selectivity" is defined as:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center"><st32:frac align="centre">moles AN in effluent<st32:over>moles C<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub>H<st32:sub pos="post">6</st32:sub> in feed converted</st32:over></st32:frac>x 100</st32:df></li><li>4. "Acrylonitrile (AN) yield" is defined as:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center"><st32:frac align="centre">moles AN formed <st32:over>moles C<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub>H<st32:sub pos="post">6</st32:sub> feed</st32:over></st32:frac>x 100</st32:df></li><li>5. "Catalyst Activity Index (CAI)" is defined as:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">-{1n[1 - (% conversion/100)]}x 100/catalyst weight</st32:df></li></sl></p><p num="0055">The evaluation of the catalysts of Examples 1-6 was conducted in a
fluidized bed reaction vessel having an inside diameter of about 41 mm to determine
acrylonitrile selectivity and yield and propylene conversion. The amount of catalyst
used in the evaluation ranged between 360 grams and 440 grams and was adjusted in
order to get a propylene conversion between 98.5 - 99.2%. A reactant mixture of 7.7
mole percent propylene (C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>6</sub>), 8.4 mole percent ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>), and the balance air
was passed upward through the catalyst bed at a rate sufficient to give the value of
W/F desired. The bed temperature was maintained at 460°C and the pressure at about
207 kPa (30 psia).</p><p num="0056">All catalyst preparation reactions were conducted in a jacketed
stainless steel (∼10 L) reactor using a heat exchanger and a variable speed agitator
(paddle blade impeller, no baffles). In the examples of the invention, HNO<sub>3</sub> was
charged at a controlled rate using a Cole-Parmer Masterflex® peristaltic pump with a
number 16 Norprene® line. A 15 minute HNO<sub>3</sub> charge time corresponded to a
charge rate of 48.2 mL/min, a 30 minute HNO<sub>3</sub> charge time corresponded to a charge
rate of 24 mL/min, and a 45 minute HNO<sub>3</sub> charge time corresponded to a charge rate
of 16 mL/min.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0057">A catalyst of the composition U<sub>1</sub>Fe<sub>2.03</sub>Sb<sub>5.63</sub>Mo<sub>0.12</sub>Bi<sub>0.061</sub>O<sub>f</sub> ― 50%
SiO<sub>2</sub> was prepared in the following manner. The reactor was charged with 1324 g
water, and the agitator started at 210 rpm. 590 g of Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> was charged to the reactor
and the reactor contents were stirred for 30 min after completion of the Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
addition. The HNO<sub>3</sub> charge pump was set for 15 min. addition and 1020 g of HNO<sub>3</sub> 
was charged to the reactor with stirring. After completion of the HNO<sub>3</sub> charge, 10.2 g
of Bi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> was charged to the reactor. The reactor contents were then heated to 58-60°C.
Once the temperature reached 60°C, the reactor temperature controller was set
to 88°C and 201.8 g of U<sub>3</sub>O<sub>8</sub> was charged to the reactor. Upon completion of the
U<sub>3</sub>O<sub>8</sub> addition, the temperature of the reactor contents was raised to 100°C and the
reactor contents were held at 100°C for 4 hours. The reactor heating was
discontinued, cooling water was applied to the reactor jacket, and 1135 g of deionized
(DI) ice was added to the reactor. When the reactor contents reached a temperature of
52°C, 1166 g of a chilled Fe(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> solution was charged to the reactor. After
completion of the Fe(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> addition, the reactor contents were cooled to 32°C. A
NH<sub>4</sub>OH solution (1349 mL 28% NH<sub>4</sub>OH/1051 mL H<sub>2</sub>O) was prepared and NH<sub>4</sub>OH
charged to the reactor to adjust the pH. The time at which the reactor contents
reached a pH of 5 was recorded, 189 g H<sub>2</sub>O were added, and the pH held for 15 min.
After the 15 min hold, NH<sub>4</sub>OH addition resumed until the pH reached 8. After the pH
reached 8, 3026 g H<sub>2</sub>O were added and the reactor agitator speed was reduced to 100
rpm. The reactor was allowed to sit overnight.</p><p num="0058">The hydrated mixed metal oxide precipitate was separated from the
mother liquor via vacuum filtration and the wet cake was reslurried in 20 liters of
deionized water and filtered again to remove the ammonium nitrate formed during
precipitation.</p><p num="0059">3300 g of washed filtercake was mixed with 2337 g of SiO<sub>2</sub> sol and
a 3.4 wt% Molybdenum solution, prepared by dissolving 12.05 g MoO<sub>3</sub> into a dilute
NH<sub>4</sub>OH (37 ml 28% NH<sub>4</sub>OH/187 ml H<sub>2</sub>O) solution. Additional dilution water was
added to lower the solids level of the slurry to 25% by weight. The slurry was ball
milled for 20 hours and spray dried at an outlet temperature of 83 - 85 °C. The spray
dried particles were then calcined at 400°C for 1 hour, then at 850 °C for 1 hour to
give the final catalyst.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0060">A catalyst of the composition U<sub>1</sub>Fe<sub>2.03</sub>Sb<sub>5.63</sub>Mo<sub>0.12</sub>Bi<sub>0.061</sub>O<sub>f</sub> ― 50%
SiO<sub>2</sub> was prepared according to the procedure of Example 1 except the initial reactor
agitator speed was 180 rpm, the HNO<sub>3</sub> charge pump was set for 30 min. addition, and 
the reactor agitator speed was increased to 210 rpm after completion of the Fe(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>
addition.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><p num="0061">A catalyst of the composition U<sub>1</sub>Fe<sub>2.03</sub>Sb<sub>5.63</sub>Mo<sub>0.12</sub>Bi<sub>0.061</sub>O<sub>f</sub> ― 50%
SiO<sub>2</sub> was prepared according to the procedure of Example 1 except the initial reactor
agitator speed was 150 rpm, the HNO<sub>3</sub> charge pump was set for 45 min. addition, and
the reactor agitator speed was increased to 210 rpm after completion of the Fe(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>
addition.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 4</u></heading><p num="0062">A catalyst of the composition U<sub>1</sub>Fe<sub>2.03</sub>Sb<sub>5.63</sub>Mo<sub>0.12</sub>Bi<sub>0.061</sub>O<sub>f</sub> ― 50%
SiO<sub>2</sub> was prepared according to the procedure of Example 1 except the HNO<sub>3</sub> charge
pump was set for 45 min. addition.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 5</u></heading><p num="0063">A catalyst of the composition U<sub>1</sub>Fe<sub>2.03</sub>Sb<sub>5.63</sub>Mo<sub>0.12</sub>Bi<sub>0.061</sub>O<sub>f</sub> ― 50%
SiO<sub>2</sub> was prepared according to the procedure of Example 1 except the initial reactor
agitator speed was 150 rpm, and the reactor agitator speed was increased to 210 rpm
after completion of the Fe(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> addition.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 6</u> (Control)</heading><p num="0064">A catalyst of the composition U<sub>1</sub>Fe<sub>2.03</sub>Sb<sub>5.63</sub>Mo<sub>0.12</sub>Bi<sub>0.061</sub>O<sub>f</sub> - 50%
SiO<sub>2</sub> was prepared in the following manner. 1020 g of HNO<sub>3</sub> and 10.2 g of Bi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
were charged to the reactor and the reactor agitator started at 60 rpm. The reactor
contents were then heated to 58-60°C. Once the temperature reached 60°C, the
reactor temperature controller was set to 88°C and 201.8 g of U<sub>3</sub>O<sub>8</sub> was charged to the
reactor. Upon completion of the U<sub>3</sub>O<sub>8</sub> addition, the temperature of the reactor
contents was held at 90°C to 95°C for 30 min. 1324 g H<sub>2</sub>O were added to the reactor,
the reactor contents reheated to 90°C to 95°C, and the reactor agitator speed increased
to 150 rpm. 590 g of Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> powder was charged to the reactor. Upon completion of 
the Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> powder addition, the temperature of the reactor contents was raised to
100°C and the reactor contents were held at 100°C for 4 hours. The reactor heating
was discontinued, cooling water was applied to the reactor jacket, and 1135 g of
deionized (DI) ice was added to the reactor. When the reactor contents reached a
temperature of 52°C, 1166 g of a chilled Fe(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> solution was charged to the reactor.
Upon completion of the Fe(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> addition, the reactor agitator speed was increased to
210 rpm and the reactor contents were cooled to 32°C. A NH<sub>4</sub>OH solution (1349 mL
28% NH<sub>4</sub>OH/1051 mL H<sub>2</sub>O) was prepared and NH<sub>4</sub>OH charged to the reactor to
adjust the pH. The time at which the reactor contents reached a pH of 5 was recorded,
189 g H<sub>2</sub>O were added, and the pH held for 15 min. After the 15 min hold, NH<sub>4</sub>OH
addition resumed until the pH reached 8. After the pH reached 8, 3026 g H<sub>2</sub>O were
added and the reactor agitator speed was reduced to 100 rpm. The reactor was
allowed to sit overnight.</p><p num="0065">The hydrated mixed metal oxide precipitate was separated from the
mother liquor via vacuum filtration and the wet cake was reslurried in 20 liters of
deionized water and filtered again to remove the ammonium nitrate formed during
precipitation.</p><p num="0066">3140 g of washed filtercake was mixed with 2499 g of SiO<sub>2</sub> sol and
a 3.4 wt% Molybdenum solution, prepared by dissolving 12.74 g MoO<sub>3</sub> into a dilute
NH<sub>4</sub>OH (40 ml 28% NH<sub>4</sub>OH/198 ml H<sub>2</sub>O) solution. Additional dilution water was
added to lower the solids level of the slurry to 25% by weight. The slurry was ball
milled for 20 hours and then spray dried at an outlet temperature of 83 - 85 °C. The
spray dried particles were then calcined at 400°C for 1 hour, then at 850 °C for 1 hour
to give the final catalyst.</p><p num="0067">All reactor slurries of the invention (Examples 1 - 5) appeared
more homogeneous than the reactor slurry of the control (Example 6).</p><heading><u style="single">Example 7</u></heading><p num="0068">The performance of the catalysts of Examples 1 - 6 in the
ammoxidation of propylene (C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>6</sub>) to acrylonitrile (AN) was determined by
conducting ammoxidation reactions according to the procedure described above. The 
parameters for the ammoxidation reactions are given in Table 1. The catalyst
performance results were determined and are given in Table 2. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Catalyst</b></entry><entry align="center">1 (inv)</entry><entry align="center">2 (inv)</entry><entry align="center">3 (inv)</entry><entry align="center">4 (inv)</entry><entry align="center">5 (inv)</entry><entry align="center">6 (con)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Reaction Temp., °C</b></entry><entry align="left">460</entry><entry align="left">460</entry><entry align="left">460</entry><entry align="left">460</entry><entry align="left">460</entry><entry align="left">460</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Reaction Pressure, x10<sup>2</sup> kPa</b></entry><entry align="left">2.07</entry><entry align="left">2.07</entry><entry align="left">2.07</entry><entry align="left">207</entry><entry align="left">2.07</entry><entry align="left">2.07</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Feed Mole Percent, %</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>6</sub></b></entry><entry align="left">7.7</entry><entry align="left">7.7</entry><entry align="left">7.7</entry><entry align="left">7.7</entry><entry align="left">7.7</entry><entry align="left">7.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>NH<sub>3</sub></b></entry><entry align="left">8.4</entry><entry align="left">8.4</entry><entry align="left">8.4</entry><entry align="left">8.4</entry><entry align="left">8.4</entry><entry align="left">8.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Air</b></entry><entry align="left">Balance</entry><entry align="left">Balance</entry><entry align="left">Balance</entry><entry align="left">Balance</entry><entry align="left">Balance</entry><entry align="left">Balance</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>W/F, g-sec/mL</b></entry><entry align="left">3.339</entry><entry align="left">3.723</entry><entry align="left">3.406</entry><entry align="left">3.642</entry><entry align="left">3.654</entry><entry align="left">4.120</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-00210001" orientation="unknown" wi="133" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00210001.tif" inline="no" he="191"/></p><p num="0069">The results in Table 2 demonstrate that the catalysts of the
invention have a higher AN selectivity and are more active, i.e. higher CAI, than the
control catalyst, i.e. the catalysts of the invention using the slurry addition of Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
are improved over the control catalyst using addition of Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> powder. In addition,
CO and CO<sub>2</sub> yields are improved over the control catalyst.</p><p num="0070">The catalysts of Examples 1- 6 were analyzed using X-ray
diffraction (XRD) using a Philips APD 3600 base XRD instrument equipped with
APD 3710 electronics to determine if there were any differences in the crystalline
oxide compositions of the final catalyst.</p><p num="0071">The α-Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> crystalline phase observed in the control catalyst
(Example 6) is more pronounced than in all of the catalysts of the invention
(Examples 1 - 5). The catalysts of the invention show increased levels of AN active
antimonate phases, FeSbO<sub>4</sub>, USbO<sub>5</sub>, and USb<sub>3</sub>O<sub>10</sub>, and a decreased level of the α-Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>
crystalline phase relative to the control catalyst (Example 6).</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process for preparing an antimonate-based mixed metal oxide catalyst in a
catalytically active oxidized state, said catalyst represented by the empirical formula:
MeaSbbXcQdReOf
wherein Me is at least one element selected from Fe, Co, Ni, Sn, U, Cr, Cu, Mn, Ti, Th,
Ce, Pr, Sm, or Nd; X is at least one element selected from V, Mo, or W; Q is at least
one element selected from Li, Na, K, Rb, Cs, Be, Mg, Ca, Sr, Ba, Sc, Y, La, Zr, Hf, Nb,
Ta, Re, Ru, Os, Rh, Ir, Pd, Pt, Ag. Au, Zn, Cd, Hg, Al, Ga, In, Tl, Ge, Pb, As, or Se; R
is at least one element selected from Bi, B, P, or Te; and the subscripts a, b, c, d, e, and
f denote atomic ratios and are as follows: a is 0.1 to 15, b is 1 to 100, c is 0 to 20, d is 0
to 20, a is 0 to 10, and f is a number taken to satisfy the valence requirements of the
metals present in said catalyst in the oxidation states in which they exist in said
catalyst, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a. contacting an aqueous Sb2O3 slurry with HNO3 and one or more Me compounds,
and, optionally, one or more compounds selected from X, Q, or R compounds to
form a first mixture;</claim-text><claim-text>b. heating and drying said first mixture to form a solid product;
and</claim-text><claim-text>c. calcining said solid product to form said catalyst</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The process of claim 1 further comprising adding a support material selected from
silica, zirconia, alumina, or titania to said first mixture prior to drying said first
mixture, wherein said catalyst contains from about 10% to about 90% by weight of said
support material based on the total weight of said catalyst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The process of claim 2 wherein said catalyst contains from about 35% to about 65% by
weight of said support material based on the total weight of said catalyst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The process of claim 2 or 3 wherein said support material is silica sol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The process of any preceding claim, wherein c is 0.01 to 10, and a is 0.01 to 5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The process of claim 5 wherein Me is selected from Fe, Co, Ni, Sn, U, Cr, Cu, Mn, Ti,
Th, or Ce; and R is selected from Bi, Te, or P.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The process of claim 6 wherein Mea comprises Fea and Ua', and a and a' are
independently selected from 0.1 to 10.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The process of claim 7 wherein R is Bi, and X is Mo.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The process of claim 8 wherein said catalyst is represented by the empirical formula:
Ua',FeaSbbMoc,BieOf
wherein a and a' are independently selected from 0.1 to 5, b is 1 to 10, c is 0.001 to 0.2,
and a is 0.001 to 0.2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The process of any preceding claim wherein the calcining temperature is from about
500°C to about 1150°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The process of claim 9, comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>a. contacting an aqueous Sb2O3 slurry with HNO3, oxides or nitrates of bismuth, and
oxides or nitrates of uranium to form a first mixture;</claim-text><claim-text>b. heating said first mixture at a temperature and for a time sufficient to induce
formation of desired crystalline oxides of antimony and form a second mixture;</claim-text><claim-text>c. adding an aqueous solution of a ferric compound to said second mixture to form a
third mixture;</claim-text><claim-text>d. adjusting the pH of said third mixture to about 7 to about 8.5, thereby forming a
hydrated mixed oxide precipitate in an aqueous phase;</claim-text><claim-text>e. separating the hydrated mixed oxide precipitate from the aqueous phase;</claim-text><claim-text>f. forming an aqueous slurry of the hydrated mixed oxide precipitate component;</claim-text><claim-text>g. adding a molybdate to the hydrated mixed oxide component slurry;</claim-text><claim-text>h. forming the hydrated mixed oxide - molybdate component slurry into dry particles;
and</claim-text><claim-text>i. calcining the dry particles to form said catalyst.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The process of claim 11 wherein a is 0.1 to 1, a' is 0.1 to 1, b is 1 to 5, c is 0.01 to 0.1,
and e is 0.01 to 0.05.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The process of claim 11 wherein said first mixture is formed from bismuth trioxide,
and triuranium octoxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The process of claim 13 wherein said third mixture is formed from ferric nitrate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The process of any of claims 11 to 14 wherein said first mixture is heated at a
temperature from about 80°C to about 110°C for a period from about 1 hour to about 6
hours.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The process of any of claims 11 to 15 wherein the molybdate is ammonium molybdate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The process of any of claims 11 to 16 as dependent on any of claims 2 to 10 wherein
said support material is added to said hydrated mixed oxide component slurry prior to
adding said molybdate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The process of any of claims 11 to 17 wherein said dry particles are formed by
spray-drying an aqueous slurry.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>An antimonate-based mixed metal oxide catalyst in a catalytically active oxidized state,
said catalyst represented by the empirical formula:
MeaSbbXcQdReOf
wherein Me is at least one element selected from Fe, Co, Ni, Sn, U, Cr, Cu, Mn, Ti, Th,
Ce, Pr, Sm, or Nd; X is at least one element selected from V, Mo, or W; Q is at least
one element selected from Li, Na, K, Rb, Cs, Be, Mg, Ca, Sr, Ba, Sc, Y, La, Zr, Hf, Nb,
Ta, Re, Ru, Os, Rh, Ir, Pd, Pt, Ag, Au, Zn, Cd, Hg, Al, Ga, In, Tl, Ge, Pb, As, or Se; R
is at least one element selected from Bi, B, P, or Te; and the subscripts a, b, c, d, e and
g denote atomic ratios and are as follows: a is 0.1 to 15, b is 1 to 100, c is 0 to 20, d is 0
to 20, e is 0 to 10, and f is a number taken to satisfy the valence requirements of the
metals present in said catalyst in the oxidation states in which they exist in said catalyst,
wherein said catalyst is prepared by the process of claim 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>An antimonate-based mixed metal oxide catalyst in a catalytically active oxidized state,
said catalyst represented by the empirical formula:
Ua'FeaSbbMocBieOf
wherein the subscripts a, a', b, c, e, and f denote atomic ratios and are as follows: a is
0.1 to 5, a' is 0.1 to 5, b is 1 to 10, c is 0.001 to 0.2, e is 0.001 to 0.1, and f is a number
taken to satisfy the valence requirements of Sb, U, Fe, Bi, and Mo present in said
catalyst in the oxidation states in which they exist in said catalyst, wherein said catalyst
is prepared by the process of claim 11.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>An ammoxidation process for producing a nitrile in which a reactant selected from an
olefin, an aldehyde, or an alcohol is contacted with oxygen and ammonia in the vapour
phase in the presence of a catalyst at elevated temperature, wherein said catalyst is
represented by the empirical formula:
MeaSbbXcQdReOf
wherein Me is at lest one element selected from Fe, Co, Ni, Sn, U, Cr, Cu, Mn, Ti, Th,
Ce, Pr, Sm, or Nd; X is at least one element selected from V, Mo, or W; Q is at least
one element selected from Li, Na, K, Rb, Cs, Be, Mg, Ca, Sr, Ba, Sc, Y, La, Zr, Hf, Nb,
Ta, Re, Ru, Os, Rh, Ir, Pd, Pt, Ag, Au, Zn, Cd, Hg, Al, Ga, In, Tl, Ge, Pb, As, or Se; R
is at least one element selected from Bi, B, P, or Te; and the subscripts a, b, c, d, e, and
f denote atomic ratios and are as follows: a is 0.1 to 15, b is 1 to 100, c is 0 to 20, d is 0
to 20, e is 0 to 10, and f is a number taken to satisfy the valence requirements of the
metals present in said catalyst in the oxidation states in which they exist in said catalyst,
and said catalyst is prepared by the process of claim 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>An ammoxidation process for producing a nitrile in which a reactant selected from an
olefin, an aldehyde, or an alcohol is contacted with oxygen and ammonia in the vapour
phase in the presence of a catalyst at elevated temperature, wherein said catalyst is
represented by the empirical formula:
Ua'FeaSbbMocBieOf
wherein the subscripts a, a', b, c, e and f denote atomic ratios and are as follows: a is 0.1
to 5, a' is 0.1 to 5, b is 1 to 10, c is 0.001 to 0.2, e is 0.001 to 0.1 and f is a number
taken to satisfy the valence requirements of Sb, U, Fe, Bi, and Mo present in said
catalyst in the oxidation states in which they exist in said catalyst, and said catalyst is
prepared by the process of claim 11.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>An oxidation process for producing an aldehyde or a carboxylic acid in which an olefin
is contacted with oxygen in the vapour phase in the presence of a catalyst at elevated
temperature, wherein said catalyst is represented by the empirical formula:
MeaSbbXcQdReOf
wherein Me is at least one element selected from Fe, Co, Ni, Sn, U, Cr, Cu, Mn, Ti, Th,
Ce, Pr, Sm, or Nd; X is at least one element selected from V, Mo, or W; Q is at least
one element selected from Li, Na, K, Rb, Cs, Be, Mg, Ca, Sr, Ba, Sc, Y, La, Zr, Hf, Nb,
Ta, Re, Ru, Os, Rh, Ir, Pd, Pt, Ag, Au, Zn, Cd, Hg, Al, Ga, In, Tl, Ge, Pb, As, or Se; R
is at least one element selected from Bi, B, P, or Te; and the subscripts a, b, c, d, e and f
denote atomic ratios and are as follows: a is 0.1 to 15, b is 1 to 100, c is 0 to 20, d is 0
to 20, e is 0 to 10, and f is a number taken to satisfy the valence requirements of the
metals present in said catalyst in the oxidation states in which they exist in said catalyst,
and said catalyst is prepared by the process of claim 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>An oxidation process for producing an aldehyde or carboxylic acid in which an olefin is
contacted with oxygen in the vapour phase in the presence of a catalyst at elevated
temperature, wherein said catalyst is represented by the empirical formula:
Ua'FeaSbbMocBieOf
wherein the subscripts a, a', b, c, e, and f denote atomic ratios and are as follows: a is
0.1 to 5, a' is 0.1 to 5, b is 1 to 10, c is 0.001 to 0.2, e is 0.001 to 0.1, and f is a number
taken to satisfy the valence requirements of Sb, U, Fe, Bi, and Mo present in said
catalyst, and said catalyst is prepared by the process of claim 11.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>