<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1046685-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1046685" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="23138705" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20001025"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1046685-A1" status="new" fvid="22984562"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1046685</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20001025</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00303234-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00303234</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000417</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-29566599-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>29566599</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990421</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C20</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Herstellung von verbesserten Tinten für Tintenstrahldrucker durch Verwendung spezieller Polymere</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Preparation of improved inks for ink-jet printers using specific polymers</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Production des encres améliorés pour imprimantes à jet d'encre utilisant des polymeres spécifiques</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0591916-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0591916</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5698017-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5698017</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HEWLETT PACKARD CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HEWLETT-PACKARD COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hewlett-Packard Company</last-name><address><street>3000 Hanover Street</street><city>Palo Alto, California 94304</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GORE MAKARAND P</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GORE, MAKARAND P.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GORE, MAKARAND P.</last-name><address><street>1210 NE Conroy Pl.</street><city>Corvallis, OR 97330</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Colgan, Stephen James</last-name><address><street>CARPMAELS &amp;amp; RANSFORD 43 Bloomsbury Square</street><city>London WC1A 2RA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The invention relates to an improved system for inkjet printing which results
in images with increased permanence as measured by transfer of color from the image
when the image is subjected to mechanical and/or chemical abrasion. The invention
provides a fusible material that may be combined with any or all of the color inks
used to create the image, or it may be used as a colorless fluid applied pre- or post-printing.
The permanence of images produced by the system are comparable to those
produced by Electrophotography.</p><p>The invention also relates to a printing apparatus that contains a means for fusing
the image using heat applied after the printed substrate is ejected from the printer.
Methods for utilizing these improvements and examples of them are described.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>TECHNICAL FIELD</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to printing technology. More specifically, it relates
to an improved ink composition for use in inkjet printers. Even more specifically, it
relates to the use of an improved ink composition, equipment, and methods to produce
permanent printed images on a variety of substrates by an inkjet printer using
hereinbefore water soluble polymers.</p><heading>BACKGROUND ART</heading><p num="0002">Along with the computerization of offices in the 1980's came electronically
controlled non-impact printers such as the ink jet and laser printers. Drop-on-demand
inkjet printers can be piezo or thermal (bubble jet). In piezo ink jet systems, ink
droplets are ejected by an oscillating piezo crystal. However, the thermal ink jet
dominates the drop-on-demand office ink jet market. In this system, rapid heating
behind the ink nozzles cause a bubble of vapor to form in the ink. The resulting
bubble expansion and ink ejection from the inkjet printer cartridge causes printing to
appear on the substrate.</p><p num="0003">Full-color inkjet printers are more common than color lasers and are much more
economical. The main advantage of inkjet printers over lasers and other non-impact
printing techniques include their low cost and simplicity. Thermal inkjet systems are
capable of dispensing ink rapidly and accurately. The technology of this and other
inkjet systems are discussed in the <i>Chemistry and Technology of Printing and
Imaging Systems,</i> edited by P. Gregory, published by Chapman &amp; Hall, 1996.
Representative thermal inkjet systems and cartridges are discussed in U.S. patents
4,500,895 to Bucket al., 4,513,298 to Scheu, and 4,794,409 to Cowger et al., which
are all hereby incorporated by reference. </p><p num="0004">The technology of inkjet printers has undergone many changes and
improvements since they first appeared. Research has been conducted to ensure that
the images produced are of consistent high quality. Thus, it is important that the
images be waterfast and do not smear, smudge, run, or the like when exposed to
chemical or mechanical abrasion. Non-smearing of the image when portions of the
printed page are highlighted with colored markers is of particular interest.
Oftentimes, the image produced by the inkjet printer on paper is not satisfactorily
fixed and smears, bluffing the printed image when subjected to highlighting. This
type of image is not regarded as permanent.</p><p num="0005">Image permanence is defined as transference of color from the substrate when the
image printed thereon is subjected to chemical and mechanical abrasion. Highlighting
is oftentimes the form of chemical and mechanical abrasion experienced. This
transference of color is measured by optical density (mOD). More permanent images
have lower milli-Optical Density (mOD) values.</p><p num="0006">Another desired feature of printed images is light fastness. As used herein, light
fastness will mean that the images do not fade when exposed to light. Light fastness
is another measure of permanence as used herein. Light fastness is measured by
exposing printed images to intense light in light chambers (fadomers) and comparing
print density before and after the exposure.</p><p num="0007">There have been many past attempts at improving the permanence of water-based
inkjet printing systems. Included among these attempts are US patent 5,549,740 to
Takahashi et al., US patent 5,640,187 to Kashiwakazi et al., and US patent 5,792,249
to Shirota et al. which utilizes an additional or "fifth" pen to apply a colorless fluid on
to the substrate. As will be seen in the comparative testing, the mOD values for the
images printed thereon are quite high.</p><p num="0008">Another highly efficient printing system in common use currently is laser printers.
In a laser printer or copier, light from a laser beam is used to discharge areas of a
photoreceptor to create an electrostatic image of the page to be printed. The image is
created by the printer controller, a dedicated computer in the printer, and is passed to
the print engine. The print engine transcribes an array of dots created by the printer
controller into a printed image. The print engine includes a laser scanning assembly, 
photoreceptor, toner hopper, developer unit, Corotrons, discharge lamp, fuser, paper
transport, paper input feeders, and paper output trays.</p><p num="0009">The final stage of laser printing or copying is to fix toner onto the paper. Toner is
very fine plastic powder which is transferred from the photoreceptor. Once
transferred from the photoreceptor, it lies on the paper in a very thin coating with
nothing to hold it in place. In order to fix the toner to the paper, it is heated by
passing between a pair of very hot rollers, so that the plastic melts around the fibers of
the paper and is "fused" into place. The image is now fixed permanently onto the
paper.</p><p num="0010">The fuser of a typical laser printer is of particular interest to the printing system of
this invention. In these systems, fusing or melting the polymeric resin in which the
colorant is embedded converts the discrete toner particles into an amorphous film.
This film becomes the permanent image that results in electrophotographic copy or
laser printed copy. However, the laser printer toners are incompatible with water.
Since most inkjet materials are water-based, it is not possible to use laser toners in
inkjet printers, and, therefore, Inkjet technology has not yet found a way to make the
printed image permanent.</p><p num="0011">Another printing technology that is inherently more permanent than water-based
inkjet are hot-melt inks. These materials are solid at room temperature and are similar
to wax crayons. The colorants used in these materials are solvent dyes that are
soluble in the ink vehicle or pigment dispersions. Like laser toners, these materials
are incompatible with the inks used in inkjet printing.</p><p num="0012">U.S. patents 5,817,169 and 5,698,017, both to Sacripante et al., disclose hot melt
ink compositions which use oxazoline as a vehicle used for the colorant in a
nonaqueous, hot melt inkjet ink. One of the advantages of this technology is the waxy
nature of the hot melt ink creates images that are more waterfast and may be
successfully utilized on plain papers. This technology is in contrast with the instant
invention, which utilizes an ordinary aqueous four-color ink pen set.</p><p num="0013">Accordingly, a need remains for a printing system using water-based inkjet
technology, which produces permanent images. These permanent images will be
consistent and stable with respect to a variety of printed substrates. An ideal situation
would be combining the convenience and safety of aqueous inkjet inks with the 
permanence of electrophotographic copies. The present invention satisfies this in a
unique manner, which is described herein.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0014">The invention relates to a fusible material, which is added to aqueous ink
formulations and provides an improved printed image, which is especially suitable for
use with inkjet technology.</p><p num="0015">Another feature of the invention to demonstrate a method for printing
permanent images using inkjet technology which comprises a fusible material
formulated with the four-pen ink-set commonly found in water-based color inks used
in inkjet printing. The fusible material of the present invention can be formulated as a
colorless fluid applied either before or after the color inks are applied to the substrate.
The images and print quality achieved by the use of such a fusible material in
waterborne ink formulations are comparable in permanence and print quality to those
of laser printers and copiers. These images, in black or color, are permanent and will
not smear, smudge, run, or the like when exposed to mechanical or chemical abrasion.</p><p num="0016">The invention also relates to a printing device incorporating the ejection of
droplets of fluid on to a substrate and producing a printed page with a permanent
image. In this embodiment, the inkjet printer is equipped with a fuser. The fuser of a
typical laser printer is commercially available and has been modified for use in an
inkjet printer to provide superior image quality and permanence to the printed
substrate. In a similar fashion, incandescent lamps or other suitable heating means
may be employed.</p><p num="0017">This invention also provides an improved printing system which produces
consistent high quality printed images regardless of the type or quality of printing
substrate, such as different types or qualities of paper or transparent sheets used to
make overhead projections (transparencies), being used.</p><p num="0018">In accordance with the foregoing, the present invention relates to an improved
printing system for producing stable, water-fast, permanent printed images. The
system combines the ease and versatility of traditional water-based inkjet technology
with the permanence of laser printing or copying technology (Electrophotography). </p><p num="0019">These and features and advantages of the current invention will be described
below in the Detailed Description and succinctly outlined in the claims that follow.</p><heading>DETAILED DISCLOSURE</heading><p num="0020">The present invention relates to an improved printing system that is capable of
producing permanent images on a variety of substrates using waterborne inkjet
printing. The invention allows for the inclusion of fusible materials into water-based
inks and demonstrates the increased permanence of the images produced.</p><p num="0021">The standard ink set components known and used in inkjet printers comprise
four colors of ink, namely yellow, magenta, cyan, and black. This set is often referred
to as a "four pen" system. These four pens are made of various materials and are
formulated into aqueous inks.</p><p num="0022">Each of the standard four pens contains a water-soluble or insoluble dye
having an anionic group, or when a pigment is used as a colorant, the pigment is
either self-dispersing or is aided in solubility by a dispersant. In many applications,
both pigments and dyes are used for coloring the ink. The ink formulation also
typically contains water, a water-miscible solvent, and other components such as a
biocide, viscosity modifiers, a pH adjuster, preservatives, surfactants, and the like.</p><heading><u style="single">Fusible Polymers</u></heading><p num="0023">The fusible materials used in the instant ink formulations for permanence must
be made soluble or miscible with the other water soluble ingredients in the ink. It has
been found that certain polymers, which behave similar to hydrophobic toners in
thermoplastic properties, can be prepared and dissolved in an aqueous medium. The
fusible polymers have successfully been synthesized and shown to perform in
aqueous ink systems to produce images with the quality and permanence here to
before only achieved in Electrophotography.</p><p num="0024">Among the properties of interest for application of some of these polymers
include glass transition temperature (Tg) and Melt Index (MI). As used herein, glass
transition temperature (Tg) will mean the transition that occurs when a liquid is
cooled to an amorphous or glassy solid. It also may be the change in an amorphous
region of a partially crystalline polymer from a viscous, rubbery state to a hard or
brittle one brought about by change in temperature. In this invention, the materials 
which are used to improve permanence of the images produced by inkjet printing
fluid have a Tg that may range from about 40 to about 140 degrees C. A more
preferred range of glass transition temperatures will range from about 50 to about 90
degrees C. Melt index (MI) values for the instant materials may range from about 400
to about 3000 grams/10 minutes. A more preferred range may be from about 1800 to
about 2500 grams/10 minutes. A still more preferred range is from about 2000 and
2250 g/10 min.</p><p num="0025">Presented herein are representative examples of syntheses of fusible polymers
that provide permanence to the images formed by the materials and processes of the
instant invention.</p><p num="0026">The first groups of polymers are synthesized by condensation reactions to
"graft" substitutes on a "backbone" polymer chain. For example, a polymer of
styrene/maleic anhydride of molecular weight 1600 (average) is treated with
ammonium hydroxide in refluxing tetrahydrofuran, THF, to produce an amide-acid
derivative; the derivative is then treated with additional ammonium hydroxide or
ammonium bicarbonate and water. Evaporation of THF will give the aqueous
polymer. The average molecular weight of the polymers herein can range from about
900 to about 500,000, preferably from about 1,000 to about 100,000, even more
preferably from about 1,000 to about 50,000.</p><p num="0027">In another example, a polymer of styrene/maleic anhydride of molecular
weight 1900 (wt average) is treated with PEG amine in anhydrous refluxing THF to
produce a amide-acid derivative; as before, the derivative is treated with butyl amine
to give the desired polymer. In yet another example, (olefin) styrene/maleic
anhydride polymer of MW 1900 is treated with PEG 350 methylether (0.5 equivalent
to PEG to anhydride ratio) in refluxing THF, followed by butyl amine to produce the
aqueous solution of the polymer. In all instances the resulting polymers have suitable
Tg to form films.</p><p num="0028">Thus, the fusible materials above can be selected from amide-acid derivatives
of alkene/maleic anhydride and ammonium hydroxide polymers; amide-acid
derivatives of alkene/maleic anhydride and polyethylene glycol (PEG) amine
polymers; polymers of alkene/maleic anhydride and adducts with PEG (having a
molecular weight of about 100 to about 5,000) monomethyl ethers; and mixtures or 
precursors thereof. The structures and chemistry useful in the practice of invention
is as shown in Figure 1:
<img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="74"/>
wherein m, n, and p represent repeating units, wherein m is from 0 to about 18, n is
from about 3 to about 1,000, and p is from about 2 to about 1,000. R1 can be a
branched alkyl chain with aromatic or aliphatic groups or a straight chain alkyl group
along the main polymer chain with from about C2 to C50, preferably from about C2
(ethylene) to about C8 (Octyl) carbons; R can be an alkyl chain, a branched alkyl
chain, or ring of from about C2 to about C50, of which some carbons may be
hydroxylated. The counter ion for carboxylate groups in water solution may be an
ammonium species or a metal cation.</p><p num="0029">The second special group of compounds useful for the practice of the
invention are polyoxazolines, polyoxazolins, and intermediates and precursors
thereof.. As shown in Figure 2, below, and described in literature (See for example,
U.S. patents 5,817,169; 5,629,396; 5,644,006; 5,670,590; 5,240,744; and 4,658,011
herein, incorporated by reference), compounds of this series are converted by effect of
heat, dehydration and catalytic polymerization. One example useful herein is Poly-2-ethyl-2-oxazoline
available from Polymer Chemistry Innovations, Tucson, Arizona,
but it will be apparent to any one familiar with the art that other amides, oxazolines,
(Note these may be present in the inks as mixtures due to the nature of the chemistry
they undergo), and polymers can be used in the practice of this invention to impart
thermosetting properties to printed inks. </p><p num="0030">Figure 2:
<img id="img-00080001" orientation="unknown" wi="141"  img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080001.tif" inline="no" he="88"/>
   wherein R1, R2 and R3, independently, can be H, alkyl chains, branched alkyl
chains or rings of between C2 and C50; some carbons may be in hydroxylated form.</p><p num="0031">As will be seen in the Examples, the images made permanent by the ink
formulation of this invention are very resistant to smear. This allows enhanced image
quality, demonstrated by the transfer of less than 100 mOD. In this invention, mOD
is measured by running a water-based yellow highlighter (Sanford "Major Accent"
Highlighting Marker high pH labeled "Fluorescent") across black lines printed on
white bond paper. The amount of ink that smears from the lines relates directly to the
permanence of the inkjet ink.</p><p num="0032">One of the ways to include the fusible material of this invention is to include it
in a clear fluid that is not part of the four-color ink set. This technology is sometimes
called a "fifth" pen. Fifth pen technology has been used to optimize image quality
and water-fastness, but has not been successfully used to improve permanence.
However, when using the 5<sup>th</sup> pen to eject the fusible material composition of this
invention, the colorless, waterborne liquid coats the substrate and imparts permanence
to the printed image</p><p num="0033">When the fusible material of this invention is used in a colorless fluid 5<sup>th</sup> pen
device, the amount of fluid used to impart permanence to the image may range from
about 0.1 to about 4 times the amount of color ink(s) used in forming the image. In 
other words, there would be a minimum of one drop of colorless fluid applied to the
substrate for every ten drops of ink applied. The colorless layer may be applied either
over or under the color ink layer.</p><p num="0034">These clear fluids increase permanence of the color ink images by forming a
pigment/polymer dispersant on the surface of the substrate. This reduces penetration
of colorant in the media and helps improve the image color, optical density, and
brightness of the printed image. The fusible material may also be added to any or all
of the colored inks of the standard four-color pen set.</p><p num="0035"><u style="single">Pigments</u> - When a pigment is used as a coloring material in the ink
composition of the present invention, the amount of pigment used is within the range
from about 0.5 to about 20 weight percent. A more preferable range of pigment
ranges from about 1 to about 15 % by weight, still more preferably is a range of from
about 2% to about 12% by wt.</p><p num="0036">An example of a pigment used forblack ink is carbon black. The carbon black
may be produced by either a furnace or channel method. The primary particle size of
this material ranges from 15 to 40 µm, specific surface area is 50 to 300 m2/g, and has
oil absorption from 40 to 150 ml/100 g, the volatile component is 0.5 to 10%, and the
pH value may range from 2 to 9. Examples of suitable commercially available carbon
blacks include No. 2300, No. 900, MCF88, No. 33, No. 40, No. 45, No. 52, MA&amp;,
MA8, No. 2200B, Raven 1255, Regal 400R, Regal 330R, Regal 660 R, Mogul L,
Color Black FW1, Color Black FW18, Color Black S170, Color Black S150, Printex
35, and Printex U.</p><p num="0037">In this invention, the black colorants that are employed include Novofil Black
BB-03, and Hostafine Black TS. The Novafil material is a pigment that is
approximately 27% pigment dispersion based on anionic dispersing agents. It
contains C.I. Pigment Black 7, carbon black and is an ultrafine pigment dispersion
suitable for all water based inkjet application. These pigments are available from
Clairiant Corp., Coventry, R.I.</p><p num="0038">Hostafine Black TS contains hydrophilic ultrafine pigment dispersions based
on non-ionic dispersing and wetting agents. It contains carbon black and has a
pigment concentration of 33%. </p><p num="0039">Other black colorants, which may be used, include those listed in the Color
Index and in Textile Chemist and Colorist reference publications. Water-soluble
black colorants are commercially available from colorant vendors such as Cabot
Corporation, Orient Chemical, and other manufacturers. Surface modified colorants
from these manufacturers are initially water insoluble colorants which, by certain
modifications, are solubilized or stabilized as fine dispersions in water to prevent
agglomeration. See U.S. Pat. Nos. 5,707,432; 5,630,868; 5,571,311; and 5,554,739
for a discussion of modified carbon black pigments and methods of attaching
functionalized groups to aid in their solubility.</p><p num="0040">Examples of pigments used for a yellow ink include C.I. Pigment Yellow 1,
C.I. Pigment Yellow 2, C.I. Pigment Yellow 3, C.I. Pigment Yellow 13, C.I. Pigment
Yellow 16, C.I. Pigment Yellow 83, and the like. Examples of pigments used for
magenta ink include C.I. Pigment Red 5, C.I. Pigment Red 7, C.I. Pigment Red 12,
C.I. Pigment Red 48 (ca), C.I. Pigment Red 48 (mn), C.I. Pigment Red 57 (Ca), C.I.
Pigment Red 112, C.I. Pigment Red 122, and the like. Examples of pigments used for
a cyan include C.I. Pigment Blue 1, C.I. Pigment Blue 2, C.I. Pigment Blue 3, C.I.
Pigment Blue 15:3, C.I. Pigment Blue 16, C.I. Pigment Blue 22, C.I. Vat Blue 4, C.I.
Vat Blue 6, and the like. Pigments whose performance properties are satisfactory
when formulated for the present invention are considered to be within its scope.</p><p num="0041">In the instant invention, colorants used include Hostafine Rubine F6B and
Hostafine Blue B2G available from Clamant, Coventry, RI. Hostafines are
hydrophilic ultrafine pigment dispersions based on nonionic dispersing and wetting
agents, available in all colors. In this disclosure, Hostafine Rubine F6B is magenta
with a 40% pigment content. Hostafine Blue B2G is blue with 40% pigment as well.
These colorants are manufactured for suitability with water-based inkjet inks.</p><p num="0042">Any pigment, dye, or pigment-resin system available and compatible with the
other formulated ingredients of the fusible material of this invention may be used as
colorants. An important factor that the formulator must keep in mind is thermal
instability exhibited by certain tri- and tetrakis-azo dyes. Such thermal instability
may lead to charring of insoluble deposits (kogation), which is to be avoided.</p><p num="0043"><u style="single">Dyes</u> - Dyes, whether water-soluble or water-insoluble, may be employed in the
practice of the present invention. Examples of water-soluble dyes include the sulfonate 
and carboxylate dyes, specifically, those tat are commonly employed in ink-jet
printing. Specific examples include: Sulforhodamine B (sulfonate), Acid Blue 113
(sulfonate), Acid Blue 29 (sulfonate), Acid Red 4 (sulfonate), Rose Bengal
(carboxylate), Acid Yellow 17 (sulfonate), Acid Yellow 29 (sulfonate), Acid Yellow 42
(sulfonate), Acridine Yellow G (sulfonate), Nitro Blue Tetrazolium Chloride
Monohydrate or Nitro BT, Rhodamine 6G, Rhodamine 123, Rhodamine B, Rhodamine
B Isocyanate, Safranine O, Azure B, Azure B Eosinate, Basic Blue 47, Basic Blue 66,
Thioflacin T (Basic Yellow 1), and Auramine O (Basic Yellow 2), all available from
Aldrich Chemical Company. Examples of water-insoluble dyes include azo, xanthene,
methine, polymethine, and anthroquinone dyes. Specific examples of water-insoluble
dyes include Ciba-Geigy Orasol Blue GN, Ciba-Geigy Orasol Pink, and Ciba-Geigy
Orasol Yellow.</p><p num="0044">The ink formulation comprises a colorant plus a vehicle. A typical
formulation for an ink useful in the practice of this invention includes the colorant,
present in about 0.5 to about 20 weight percent, one or more co-solvents, present from
0 to 50 weight percent, one or more water-soluble surfactants, present in about 0.1 to
40 weight percent, one or more high molecular weight colloids present in from 0 to
about 3 weight percent. The balance of the formulation is purified water. The
colorless fluid is similar except for the absence of a colorant.</p><p num="0045">One or more co-solvents may be added to the formulation of the ink of this
invention. Classes of co-solvents include, but are not limited to, aliphatic alcohols,
aromatic alcohols, diols, glycol ethers, polyglycol ethers, caprolactams, formamides,
acetamides, and long chain alcohols. Examples of such compounds include primary
aliphatic alcohols, secondary aliphatic alcohols, 1,2-alcohols, 1,3-alcohols, 1,5-alcohols,
ethylene glycol alkyl ethers, propylene glycol alkyl ethers, higher homologs
of polyethylene glycol alkyl ethers, N-alkyl caprolactams, unsubstituted caprolactams,
both substituted and unsubstituted formamides, both substituted and unsubstituted
acetamides, and the like.</p><p num="0046">One class of preferred co-solvents that provides water miscibility to polymers
is glycols. A particularly preferred glycol is polyethylene glycol, commonly
abbreviated as PEG. Polyethylene glycol is hydrophilic. </p><p num="0047">A preferred surfactant employed in the present invention includes
Noigen10™. Noigen10™ is a commercially available polymerizable surfactant
available from the Montello Company of Tulsa, Oklahoma. Noigen10™ contains
polyethylene glycol as a hydrophilic group and an octyl or nonyl phenol as a
hydrophobic group. This type of surfactant, which can accommodate both
hydrophobic and hydrophilic moieties, is a preferred ingredient in the formation of the
fusible material of this invention.</p><p num="0048">However, other water-soluble surfactants may be employed in the formulation
of the vehicle of the ink of this invention. The purpose of surfactants as described
herein is to facilitate the miscibility of the ingredients of the ink composition. This is
especially important if the fusible material of the ink composition contains both
hydrophilic and hydrophobic groups. The surfactant(s) used are known by those
skilled in the art of ink formulation and may be alkyl polyethylene oxides, alkyl
phenyl polyethylene oxides, polyethylene oxide block copolymers, acetylenic
polyethylene oxides, polyethylene oxide (di)esters, polyethylene oxide amines,
protonated polyethylene oxide amines, protonated polyethylene oxide amides,
dimethicone copolyols, substitued amine oxides, and the like. The amount of
surfactant added to the formulation of this invention may range from less than one to
about 10 weight percent. A more preferred amount is from 1 to about 3 weight
percent.</p><p num="0049">Consistent with the formulation of this invention, various other additives may
be employed to optimize the properties of the ink composition for specific
applications. Examples of these additives are those added to inhibit the growth of
harmful microorganisms. These additives may be biocides, fungicides, and other
microbial agents, which are routinely used in ink formulations. Examples of suitable
microbial agents include, but are not limited to, Nuosept (Nudex, Inc.), Ucarcide
(Union carbide Corp.), Vancide (R.T. Vanderbilt Co.), and Proxel (ICI America).</p><p num="0050">Sequestering agents such as EDTA (ethylene diamine tetra acetic acid) may be
included to eliminate the deleterious effects of heavy metal impurities, and buffer
solutions may be used to control the pH of the ink. Viscosity modifiers may also be
present, as well as other additives known to those skilled in the art to modify
properties of the ink as desired. </p><p num="0051">Each of the ingredients in the fusible material are present for a specific
reason. For example, particle size and distribution, stability, surface tension, and
various rheological properties are primarily controlled by the type and amount of
surfactant employed.</p><p num="0052">Kogation refers to the charring of insoluble deposits on the printer's heating
elements. This clogs the inkjet print heads and is a problem common to thermal inkjet
printers. For the fusible materials to be resistant to kogation, they must be soluble or
miscible in the ink solvents at higher temperatures or in super heated solvent/water
vapor. The invention allows inclusion of fusible materials in water based inks used in
inkjet printing. These materials are soluble in the ink composition at higher
temperatures or in super-heated solvent/water vapor. As used herein, superheating
means the heating of a substance above the temperature at which a change of state
would ordinarily happen without the change of state occurring.</p><p num="0053">Fuser Device - The printing system of this invention includes a printing
apparatus that is equipped with suitable heating means. Heat fusion is most often the
way that the image formed by toner particles used in electrophotography are fixed to
the printed substrate. Most systems employ a heated roller to fix the image although
any other means of supplying heat is included within the scope of this invention.</p><p num="0054">The heated roller is often a rubber roller impregnated with silicone oil which is
preheated to about 90 degrees C. It may also be a metal roller heated with
incandescent light or a lamp equipped with a reflector. Certain laser printers employ
a ceramic heating element in the fusion stage. When the copier or printer is switched
on, waiting time until the machine is ready to use is associated with heating the roller.</p><p num="0055">The heating means is designed to melt (or fuse) the toner on to the substrate.
In high speed systems, flash fusion may be used. Flash fusion involves the use of
heated lamps with a specific heat output are used to rapidly heat the toner which then
adheres to the substrate. Fusers are commercially available from such companies that
manufacture laser printers such as Hewlett-Packard, Canon, Ricoh, and Panasonic. In
all cases, the toner particles used in Electrophotography are hydrophobic.</p><p num="0056">A typical laser printer commonly available is the Hewlett-Packard Laser Jet
4L Printer. In the fusing stage, toner is fused into the substrate by heat and pressure
to produce a permanent image. The substrate (usually paper) passes between a 
ceramic heating element protected by a thin Teflon sleeve and a soft pressure roller.
This melts the toner and presses it into the substrate. Other laser printers use a
halogen heating lamp and require frequent warm-up periods to maintain a minimum
standby temperature.</p><p num="0057">Polymer Synthesis - Syntheses of substituted polymers are performed using
Styrene/Maleic anhydride polymers of MW ∼1900 available form Polysciences,
Warrington, PA. The type and amount of amine/alcohol for the condensation reaction
can be chosen to achieve desired properties such as Tg (glass transition temperature,
Melt Index, Hardness etc. Specific examples of polymer syntheses are described
below:</p><p num="0058">The following examples and comparative examples are intended to illustrate
the invention in further detail and not to limit the invention in any way whatsoever.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0059">Polymer A: Polystyrene/Maleic anhydride polymer, M.W.1900, available
from Polysciences, Warrington, PA (18.0 g), is added to a solution of Jeffamine
M1000 (22.2 g) (EO/PO Amine, M.W.100, EO/PO 19/3, available from Huntsman
Chemical), Hexyl amine (6.75 g) and triethyl amine (9.0 g) in dry THF. The mixture
is refluxed for 2h and stirred at room temperature overnight. The resulting solution is
poured in water (400 g) and the organic solvents are removed under reduced pressure
(10 mm) and at 40°C until the weight is 200 g. Additional water is added to bring the
weight to 470.0 g, which results in a 10% nominal concentration of polymer A.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 2</heading><p num="0060">Polymer B: Polystyrene/Maleic anhydride polymer, M.W.1900, available
from Polysciences, Warrington, PA (19.0 g), is suspended in water (75 g) and a
solution of 30% Ammonium Hydroxide ( 6.6 g) is added and after 0.5h of stirring the
mixture is heated to 85°C for 0.5h. The mixture is then cooled and the pH is adjusted
to 8.5 using Ammonium Bicarbonate. Water is added to bring the weight to 200 g to
produce a 10% nominal concentration of polymer B.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 3</heading><p num="0061">Polymer C: Polystyrene/Maleic anhydride polymer, M.W.1900, available from
Polysciences, Warrington, PA (18.0 g), is added to a solution of PEG350 Methyl 
ether(8.04 g) (available from Aldrich chemical Co., Milwaukee), and the mixture is
refluxed for 1 h. Butyl amine (6.75 g) is added and after 15 min reflux, the mixture is
stirred overnight. Water (170 g) is added followed by ammonium bicarbonate (3.65
g) and the organic components are evaporated under reduced pressure at 50°C.
Additional water is added to bring the weight to 270.0 g, which results in a 10%
nominal concentration of polymer C.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 4</heading><p num="0062">Synthesis of a 'primer polymer', which is not smear resistant, but boosts the
performance of fusible materials. See US patent applications, Serial Nos. 09/120,046
and 09/120,270, both filed July 21, 1998.</p><p num="0063">A primer polymer used to improve the performance of fusible materials is
synthesized as follows: 5684.9 g water and 24.0 g potassium persulfate is charged in
a reactor. The organic part of the monomer feed (747.0 g methyl methacrylate
(MMA), 1073.7 g hexyl acrylate (HA), 280.1 g methoxy polyethylene glycol (350)
methacrylate (from Polysciences, Inc.) 233.4 g (acrylic acid) AA, and 23.3 g iso-octyl
thioglycolate

(from Zeneca, Inc.) is added to the feed tank, followed by the water phase of the
monomer feed (1082.2 g water and 65.4 g Rhodcal). The monomer feed is emulsified
until a stable monomer feed is obtained. After the reactor phase reaches 90°C the
addition of the monomer feed (150 min) is started. Directly after finishing monomer
feed 1 the feed tank is rinsed with 75.0 g water. After this addition the reactor is kept
at 90°C for another 30 min, after which the burn up reaction is performed. After the
burn up the reaction is cooled down to 30°C and 28.7 g Proxel GXL in 30.0 g water is
added. Extra water should be added if necessary for solids correction. Additionally, a
pH correction is performed by the addition of 26.1 g of an aqueous 10% KOH
solution to obtain a pH of 8.24. After filtration over 50 µm filter almost no sediment
is obtained.

Synthesis data and smear performance results from the synthesis of the primer
polymer are as follows: </p><heading><u style="single">Monomer ratio MMA/HA/MPEG(350)MA/AA 32/46/12/10</u></heading><p num="0064"><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2"  namest="1">Polymer prepared at 25% solids</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium Persulfate</entry><entry align="center">1.03% on monomers</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rhodacal RS710</entry><entry align="center">2.80% on monomers</entry></row><row><entry align="left">BRIJ 92</entry><entry align="center">1.55% on monomers</entry></row><row><entry align="left">iso-octyl thioglycolate</entry><entry align="center">1.00% on monomers</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>EXAMPLE 5</heading><heading><u style="single">Ink formulation Procedure</u></heading><p num="0065">The table below indicates the amount and type of ingredients used to prepare
samples of ink formulated with the polymers synthesized by the above procedures.
All the inks are filtered through 5 micron nylon filters available from Micron
Separations, Inc. The inks are filled in HP 850C pens and warmed to 60° C before
printing.</p><heading>Ink formulation A:</heading><p num="0066"><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Novofil black BB-03</entry><entry align="center">Hostafine Black TS</entry><entry align="center">Hostfine Black TS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pigment Concentrate</entry><entry align="center">14.8 g</entry><entry align="center">13.3 g</entry><entry align="center">15 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-Pyrrolidine</entry><entry align="center">10.0 g</entry><entry align="center">10.0 g</entry><entry align="center">10.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1,5 Pentanediol</entry><entry align="center">10.0 g</entry><entry align="center">10.0 g</entry><entry align="center">10.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer A solution</entry><entry align="center">21.4 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer B solution</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">21.4 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Poly(2-ethyl-2oxazoline)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">5.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">33.8 g</entry><entry align="center">35.3 g</entry><entry align="left">50.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Multranol 4012</entry><entry align="center">10.0 g</entry><entry align="center">10.0 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">TetraEthylene Glycol</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">10.0 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables> 
Ink formulation B:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Ingredient</entry><entry align="center">Quantity (wt%)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Cabojet 300 (10% conc.) Black</entry><entry align="center">27.01</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Polymer C solution (10%)</entry><entry align="center">30.14</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Primer Polymer</entry><entry align="center">6.39</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Leg-1</entry><entry align="center">8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Surfanol-465</entry><entry align="center">0.07</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Coco betaine</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Dodecanol</entry><entry align="center">0.14</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Leg-7</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2Pyrrolidone</entry><entry align="center">7.02</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Neopentyl Alcohol</entry><entry align="center">0.41</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Water</entry><entry align="center">19.87</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0067">Notes on the ink formulation ingredients:
<sl><li>Poly(2-ethyl-2oxazoline) is obtained from Polymer chemistry innovations of Tucson,
Arizona. 2-Pyrrolidine is used as a penetrant, used to facilitate interaction between
the ink and the substrate</li><li>1,5-Pentanediol and tetraethylene glycol are used as humectants, to maintain moisture
and keep the pen from drying</li><li>Multranol 4012, LEG 1, LEG 7, Coco betaine, Surfanol 465 are commercially
available surfactants.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Permanence Testing: Procedures</u></heading><p num="0068">The smear resistance which serves as a measure of mechanical and chemical
(solvent) abrasion is measured by transfer of amount of color in milli optical density
(mOD) units measured using MacBeth RD918 optical density meter (available form
MacBeth, a division of Kollmorgen Instruments Corporation, New Windsor, NY).
After running basic (fluorescent) highlighters twice over a set of bars printed using an
ink jet printer containing the respective inks.</p><p num="0069">The permanence of images demonstrated by electrophotography (laser printing
or copying), show the least transfer and lowest mOD numbers. Since the MacBeth 
instrument reports mOD units of transferred color in this experiment, the lower
number indicates less transfer. Therefore, the lower numbers indicate better
performance. The markers used for this purpose are available from Sanford
corporation or any office supply center under the name 'Major Accent' read through
highlighting marker and 'fluorescent' (alkaline highlighting marker).</p><p num="0070">The tables below show comparative values of some of the commercially
available transfer obtained from such smear tests. The process of 'fusion' is
important for imparting permanence to the inks of the invention. Therefore, the
comparison of 'before fusion' and 'after fission' data indicates the efficiency of the
particular fusible material. Fusion indicates a treatment through heat press HIX N800
3 seconds at 190°C or running the paper through a fuser attached to an ink jet printer
so the paper path directly coincides with the fuser uptake. The fuser is set at 200°C
with a residence time of 3 sec. Experiments are performed across a set of five papers
to prove effectiveness of this approach on a variety of paper substrates.</p><p num="0071">As can be seen in Tables 1 -- 3, polymers A, B and C of the instant invention
produced comparable results. The five papers used are champion data copy (CDCY),
Gilbert bond (GBND), Stora Papyrus MultiCopy (PMCY), Stora Papyrus Natura
(PNAT) and union Camp Jamestown (UCJT) available commercially.</p><p num="0072">Paper's propensity to absorb moisture because of the hydrophilic nature of he
cellulose from which it is made has considerable implications for its behavior with
various ink formulations. Paper in an ambient relative humidity of 50% can contain
up to eight weight percent water. This moisture can become the controlling factor in
the performance of the paper as a substrate in both electophotography and inkjet
printing.</p><heading>Permanence Testing Results:</heading><p num="0073"><tables><table><tgroup cols="12"><tbody><row><entry nameend="12"  namest="1">Two pass highlighter smear 5 min after printing

Novofil black BB-03 and Polymer A in ink formulation

Values in mOD</entry></row><row><entry nameend="6"  align="center" namest="1">Alkaline</entry><entry align="center" namest="7"/><entry nameend="12" align="center" namest="8">Acid</entry></row><row><entry align="center">FUSER</entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry><entry align="center"> </entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Before</entry><entry align="center">243.3</entry><entry align="center">330.0</entry><entry align="center">117.6</entry><entry align="center">220.0</entry><entry align="center">280.0</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">220.0</entry><entry align="center">280.0</entry><entry align="center">96.7</entry><entry align="center">197.0</entry><entry align="center">266.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">After</entry><entry align="center">68.0</entry><entry align="center">75.0</entry><entry align="center">86.7</entry><entry align="center">70.0</entry><entry align="center">40.0</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">53.3</entry><entry align="center">63.3</entry><entry align="center">30.0</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">23.3</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table> </tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="12"><tbody><row><entry nameend="12" namest="1">Two pass highlighter 5 min after printing

Hostafine Balck TS and Polymer B in Ink Formulation

Values in mOD</entry></row><row><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="1">Alkaline</entry><entry align="center" namest="7"/><entry nameend="12" align="center" namest="8">Acid</entry> </row> <row><entry align="center">FUSER</entry> <entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry><entry align="center"> </entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Before</entry><entry align="center">216.7</entry><entry align="center">320.0</entry><entry align="center">186.7</entry><entry align="center">463.3</entry><entry align="center">196.7</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">196.0</entry><entry align="center">286.0</entry><entry align="center">140.0</entry><entry align="center">286.7</entry><entry align="center">40.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">After</entry><entry align="center">97.0</entry><entry align="center">113.3</entry><entry align="center">90.7</entry><entry align="center">96.7</entry><entry align="center">20.0</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">85.0</entry><entry align="center">95.7</entry><entry align="center">71.0</entry><entry align="center">86.7</entry><entry align="center">12.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">Smear resistance of Poly(2-ethyl-2-Oxazoline)
with <u style="single">Hostfine Black TS</u> colorant (values in mOD)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Fuser</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">UJCT</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Before</entry><entry align="right">400</entry><entry align="right">384</entry><entry align="center">353</entry><entry align="right">544</entry><entry align="right">516</entry></row><row><entry align="center">After</entry><entry align="right">147</entry><entry align="right">118</entry><entry align="center">98</entry><entry align="right">138</entry><entry align="right">128</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">Smear resistance of Polymer C
with surface modified colorant (values in mOD)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Fuser</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">UJCT</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Before</entry><entry align="center">400</entry><entry align="center">384</entry><entry align="center">353</entry><entry align="right">544</entry><entry align="right">516</entry></row><row><entry align="center">After</entry><entry align="center">98</entry><entry align="center">85</entry><entry align="center">77</entry><entry align="right">114</entry><entry align="right">103</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="12"><tbody><row><entry nameend="12" namest="1">Comparative Example A: HP 2000C printer black ink:

Two pass highlighter 5 min after printing

HP 2000C Black

Values in mOD</entry></row><row><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="1">Alkaline</entry><entry align="center" namest="7"/><entry nameend="12" align="center" namest="8">Acid</entry></row><row><entry align="center">FUSER</entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry><entry align="center"> </entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Before</entry><entry align="center">272.50</entry><entry align="center">249.67</entry><entry align="center">230.67</entry><entry align="center">389.00</entry><entry align="center">393.50</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">237.33</entry><entry align="center">219.00</entry><entry align="center">207.33</entry><entry align="center">472.00</entry><entry align="center">277.67</entry></row><row><entry align="center">After</entry><entry align="center">318.50</entry><entry align="center">275.50</entry><entry align="center">309.50</entry><entry align="center">479.17</entry><entry align="center">473.67</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">157.17</entry><entry align="center">154.00</entry><entry align="center">212.33</entry><entry align="center">361.17</entry><entry align="center">317.50</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="12"><tbody><row><entry nameend="12" namest="1">Comparative Example B: Canon BJC 800 J printer Black ink with clear under
printing fluid (5<sup>th</sup> Pen):

Two pass highlighter 5 min after printing

Canon BJ F 800 Black, Values in mOD</entry></row><row><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="1">Alkaline</entry><entry align="center" namest="7"/><entry nameend="12" align="center" namest="8">Acid</entry></row><row><entry align="center">FUSER</entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry><entry align="center"> </entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Before</entry><entry align="right">435</entry><entry align="right">560</entry><entry align="right">557</entry><entry align="right">433</entry><entry align="right">384</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">453</entry><entry align="right">367</entry><entry align="right">467</entry><entry align="right">360</entry><entry align="right">327</entry></row><row><entry align="center">After</entry><entry align="right">454</entry><entry align="right">527</entry><entry align="right">535</entry><entry align="right">503</entry><entry align="right">407</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">333</entry><entry align="right">325</entry><entry align="right">327</entry><entry align="right">253</entry><entry align="right">358</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="12"><tbody><row><entry nameend="12" namest="1">Comparative Example C: mOD results from electrophotographic (laser printer HP
Laser Jet 4L Printer C2003A)

Two pass highlighter 5 min after printing

Laser Printer, Values in mOD</entry></row><row><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="1">Alkaline</entry><entry align="center" namest="7"/><entry nameend="12" align="center" namest="8">Acid</entry></row><row><entry align="center">FUSER</entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry><entry align="center"> </entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Before</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry></row><row><entry align="center">After</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="12"><tbody><row><entry nameend="12" namest="1">Comparative Example D: mOD results from electrophotographic copy Lanier 6765
Office Copier.

Two pass highlighter 5 min after printing

Laser Copier, Values in MOD</entry></row><row><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="1">Alkaline</entry><entry align="center" namest="7"/><entry nameend="12" align="center" namest="8">Acid</entry></row><row><entry align="center">FUSING</entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry><entry align="center"> </entry><entry align="center">CDCY</entry><entry align="center">GBND</entry><entry align="center">PMCY</entry><entry align="center">PNAT</entry><entry align="center">UCJT</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Before</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry><entry align="center">NA</entry></row><row><entry align="center">After</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0074">It can be seen that the permanence testing results of the instant invention,
using a variety of pigments and more than one fusible material (Tables 1-4) exhibit
much better permanence as compared to images produced by other inkjet printers.
The mOD values before fusing, as seen in the above tables, are as low as 40, and are
much lower than those in Tables 5 and 6. The mOD values in Table 5 (Hewlett-Packard)
and Table 6 (Canon) are for current state of the art inkjet printers. They are
consistently greater than 200.</p><p num="0075">The mOD values for the same Examples and Comparative Examples in the
above Tables after fusion are striking. The mOD values for the examples of the
invention drop as low as 100 or less. In the comparative examples, the mOD values
range from 154 to 535. In many cases, the mOD values are even higher after than
before fusing. This shows that the inks in currently used and commercially available
inkjet printers do not produce images that are made permanent by fusion.</p><p num="0076">In contrast, the values for mOD shown in Table 7 (HP Laser Jet 4L Printer
C2003A) and Table 8 (Lanier 6765 Office Copier) are less than 10.</p><p num="0077">It is clear that this invention closely matches the permanence of
electrophotography with the desirable features of inkjet technology.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An inkjet ink composition suitable for producing a permanent image on a
substrate; said inkjet ink comprises one or more fusible materials; wherein said
fusible materials are selected from the groups consisting of:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) amide-acid derivatives of alkene/maleic anhydride and ammonium
hydroxide polymers;</claim-text><claim-text>b) amide-acid derivatives of of alkene/maleic anhydride and polyethylene
glycol (PEG) amine polymers;</claim-text><claim-text>c) polymers of alkene/maleic anhydride and adducts with PEG
monomethyl ethers;</claim-text><claim-text>d) polyoxazolines;</claim-text><claim-text>e) polyoxazolins; and</claim-text><claim-text>f) mixtures of precursors thereof.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The ink composition of Claim 1 wherein said fusible has a glass transition
temperature ranging from between 40 to 140C, preferably between 50 to 90°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The ink composition of Claim 1 wherein said ink further comprises water,
colorant, and a co-solvent and additives selected from the group consisting of
biocides, viscosity modifiers, materials for pH adjustment, sequestering agents,
preservatives, surfactants, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The ink composition according to Claim 1 wherein said fusible material is a
soluble polymer having the following repeating structure:

wherein R1 is selected from the group consisting of: alkyl chains; branched alkyl
chains with aromatic or aliphatic groups of from C2 to C50 carbons; and mixtures
thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The ink composition according to Claim 1 wherein said fusible material is a
soluble polymer having the following structure:

wherein R1, R2, and R3 are, independently, H, alkyl chains, branched alkyl
chains, rings of from C2 and C50, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The ink composition according to Claim 1 wherein said fusible material is a
soluble polymer having the following structure:

wherein R1, R2, and R3 are, independently, H, alkyl chains, branched alkyl
chains, rings of from C2 and C50, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A 5th pen composition for use with inkjet ink compositions comprising one or
more fusible materials wherein said 5th pen composition is deposited onto a
substrate either before or after a color-containing ink and wherein said 5th pen
composition produces a permanent image on said substrate; said fusible
materials are selected from the groups consisting of:<claim-text><claim-text>a) amide-acid derivatives of alkene/maleic anhydride and ammonium
hydroxide polymers;</claim-text><claim-text>b) amide-acid derivatives of of alkene/maleic anhydride and polyethylene
glycol (PEG) amine polymers;</claim-text><claim-text>c) polymers of alkene/maleic anhydride and adducts with PEG
monomethyl ethers;</claim-text><claim-text>d) polyoxazolines;</claim-text><claim-text>e) polyoxazolins; and</claim-text><claim-text>f) mixtures of precursors thereof.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A 5th pen composition according to Claim 7 which is deposited onto a
substrate in an amount ranging from 0.1 to 4 times the amount of color-containing
ink, and wherein said fusible material has a glass transition
temperature ranging from between 40 to 140C, preferably between 50 and
90°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The 5th pen composition according to Claim 7 wherein said fusible material is
a soluble polymer having the following repeating structure:

wherein R1 is selected from the group consisting of: alkyl chains; branched
alkyl chains with aromatic or aliphatic groups of from C2 to C50 carbons; and
mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The 5th pen composition according to Claim 7 wherein said fusible material is
a soluble polymer having the following structure:
wherein R1, R2, and R3 are, independently, H, alkyl chains, branched alkyl
chains, rings of from C2 and C50, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The 5th pen composition according to Claim 7 wherein said fusible material is
a soluble polymer having the following structure:

wherein R1, R2, and R3 are, independently, H, alkyl chains, branched alkyl
chains, rings of from C2 and C50, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A method for creating permanent images on a variety of substrates with inkjet
printers wherein said inkjet printer contains a color-containing ink
composition and a fusible material composition and wherein said image
undergoes minimal transference of color upon chemical or mechanical
abrasion as measured by mOD values ranging between 0 and 50; and wherein
said fusible materials are selected from the groups consisting of:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) amide-acid derivatives of alkene/maleic anhydride and ammonium
hydroxide polymers;</claim-text><claim-text>b) amide-acid derivatives of of alkene/maleic anhydride and polyethylene
glycol (PEG) amine polymers;</claim-text><claim-text>c) polymers of alkene/maleic anhydride and adducts with PEG
monomethyl ethers;</claim-text><claim-text>d) polyoxazolines;</claim-text><claim-text>e) polyoxazolins; and</claim-text><claim-text>f) mixtures of precursors thereof.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The method of Claim 12 wherein said permanent image is created on said
substrate by applying a color-containing ink composition and a fusible
material; wherein said fusible material is applied before or after said color-containing
ink or is contained in said color-containing ink composition and
wherein a heat source is applied to said substrate which fuses the image onto
the substrate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The method for creating permanent images on a substrate according to Claim
12 wherein said fusible material is contained in at least one color-containing
ink.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The method of Claim 12 wherein said fusible material is contained in a 5th
pen composition which is in addition to said color-containing ink composition.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="156" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="241" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="156" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="234" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>