<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1148086-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1148086" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25682492" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20011024"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1148086-A1" status="new" fvid="23290444"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1148086</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20011024</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01303457-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01303457</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010412</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="CA-2343436-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>CA</country><doc-number>2343436</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010406</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-55359300-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>55359300</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000420</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/00        20060101C I20070224RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/36        20060101A I20070224RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   9/00        20060101A I20070224RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   9/00        20060101C I20070224RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   9/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08J   9/14+L25/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08J   9/14B+L25/04</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Geschlossenzelliger Schaum von vinylaromatischen Polymeren und Verfahren zu dessen Herstellung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Closed cell foam from vinyl aromatic polymer and process for its preparation</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Mousse de polymère vinyl aromatique à cellules fermées et son procédé de préparation</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0601783-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0601783</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5166221-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5166221</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5206271-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5206271</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5576094-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5576094</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5585411-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5585411</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5830924-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5830924</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NOVA CHEM INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NOVA CHEMICALS INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Nova Chemicals Inc.</last-name><address><street>Westpoint Center, 1550 Coraopolis Heights Road</street><city>Moon Township, Pennsylvania 15108</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KRUPINSKI STEVEN M</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KRUPINSKI, STEVEN M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KRUPINSKI, STEVEN M.</last-name><address><street>922 Chestnut Ridge Drive</street><city>Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania 15205</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Harrison, David Christopher</last-name><address><street>MEWBURN ELLIS York House 23 Kingsway</street><city>London WC2B 6HP</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data> </bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The melt of polyvinyl aromatic polymers comprising from 10 to 45
weight % of star branched polymer prepared using a combination of
thermal and tetra functional peroxide initiation has an improved melt
strength permitting better foam formation for extrusion foam blown with
conventional blowing agents and inert gases including CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to polymeric foams. More particularly
the present invention relates to foams of vinyl aromatic polymers that
comprise from 10 to 45 weight % of a star branched vinyl aromatic
polymer.</p><p num="0002">In the manufacture of extrusion foam there are competing factors to
balance. One needs to consider the viscosity or melt flow rate of the
polymer as it impacts on the extruder output and the melt strength of the
polymer, and particularly of the foaming mass as it leaves the extruder as
this impacts on the bubble stability or the foam stability. If one makes a
very low viscosity polymer it will flow through the extruder easily. However
a low viscosity polymer tends to have a low melt strength and the resulting
foam tends to have a lower stability. Accordingly, there is a tendency for
foams of low viscosity to collapse upon extrusion or shortly after leaving
the extruder.</p> <p num="0003">It has been known for some time that the melt strength of a polymer
may be improved by lightly cross linking the polymer. The paper "Some
Effects of Crosslinking Upon the Foaming Behavior of Heat Plastified
Polystyrene", L.C. Rubens <i>Journal of Cellular Plastics, April 1965,</i> 311-320
discloses that polystyrene, containing small amounts (about 0.03 weight
%) of divinyl benzene, may be foamed with CO<sub>2</sub> and the polymer has good
foam stability and good foam volume. This technology is also the subject
matter of U.S. patents 2,848,427 and 2,848,428 issued August 19, 1958 to
Louis C. Rubens assigned to The Dow Chemical Company. The
technology comprised forming a cross linked polystyrene polymer then 
impregnating it in solid state with CO<sub>2</sub> then releasing the pressure and
letting the polymer expand. This technology was not strongly relevant to
extrusion foam techniques.</p> <p num="0004">The cross linking technology was further applied in U.S. patent
3,960,784 issued June 1, 1976 to Louis C. Rubens assigned to The Dow
Chemical Company. This patent teaches concurrent impregnation of a
polymer with a blowing agent and a cross linking agent. The polystyrene
is prepared at temperatures from about 60°C to 120°C, preferably from
about 70°C to 100°C (Column 3 lines 25-26). These temperature ranges
are indicative of suspension polymerization and concurrent or post
polymerization impregnation with the blowing agent and cross linking
agent (see Example 3) although the polymer could be molded into thin
sheets for the impregnation step. This reference does not teach an
extrusion foam.</p> <p num="0005">While divinyl benzene is useful in suspension polymerization it
tends to produce gels in bulk or solution polymerization. In a bulk or
solution polymerization the use of tetra functional initiators significantly
reduces gels. Typically no or very low levels (e.g. less than 0.5 weight %,
more generally less than 0.1 weight %) of gels (i.e. insoluble polymer in
typical solvents) are produced.</p><p num="0006">With the Montreal protocol on reducing the use of CFCs and
HCFCs and regulations regarding the permissible discharge of volatile
organic compounds (VOCs) there was increase pressure on polymer foam
industry to move to other blowing agents such as CO<sub>2</sub> or N<sub>2</sub>.
Representative of this type of art is Monsanto's Australian Patent 529339 
allowed 17/3/83. The patent teaches the formation of a foam by extruding
polystyrene and injecting CO<sub>2</sub> into the extruder. Interestingly there is no
mention of cross linking agents or branched polystyrene in the patent.
U.S. patent 5,250,577 issued October 5, 1993 to Gary C. Welsh is similar
as it pertains to extrusion foaming polystyrene in an extrusion process
using CO<sub>2</sub> as the sole blowing agent. Again there is no reference in U.S.
patent 5,250,577 to the use of cross linking agents.</p><p num="0007">At about this time U.S. patent 5,266,602 issued to Walter et al.
assigned to BASF. The patent teaches foaming a branched polystyrene.
The foaming agent is conventional (e.g. C<sub>4-6</sub> alkanes). The polymer is
prepared in the presence of a peroxide initiator other than a benzoyl
compound and a moderator (chain transfer agent) such as a mercaptan
(e.g. t-dodecyl mercaptan) and a "branching agent". The branching agent
contains a second unsaturation as a point for the polymer to branch.
Suitable agents include divinyl benzene, butadiene and isoprene. These
types of branching agents would not produce the star branched polymers
referred to herein. The actual polymerization process appears to be a
suspension process. Additionally there is no reference in the disclosure to
blowing the polystyrene with anything other than conventional alkane
blowing agents.</p><p num="0008">U.S. patent 5,576,094 issued November 19, 1996 to Callens et al.
assigned to BASF teaches extruding slab foamed polystyrene blown with
CO<sub>2</sub> or a mixture of CO<sub>2</sub> and C<sub>1-6</sub> alcohols or ethers of C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl alkoxy
compounds. The polystyrene is a branched polystyrene preferably having
at least 50%, more preferably 60% of the polymer being a star branched 
styrene butadiene block polymer. The polymer has a VICAT softening
temperature not greater than 100°C. This teaches against the subject
matter of the present invention. Additionally the polymer has a melt index
MVI 200/5 of at least 5 mL/10 minutes.</p><p num="0009">U.S. patent 5,830,924 issued November 3, 1998 to Suh et al.
assigned to The Dow Chemical Company claims a process for extruding a
closed cell foam using CO<sub>2</sub> or a mixture of CO<sub>2</sub>, conventional alkane
blowing agents and a polystyrene in which from 50 to 100 weight % of the
polystyrene is star branched (i.e. branched). This teaches away from the
subject matter of the present invention which requires a different type of
polymer and lower weight % of star branched vinyl aromatic polymer.</p><p num="0010">U.S. patent 5,760,149 issued June 2, 1998 to Sanchez et al.
discloses tetrafunctional (monoperoxycarbonate) compounds that are
useful as initiators for olefin monomers including styrene. The patent also
teaches a process for polymerizing polystyrene. However, there is no
teaching in the patent of foaming the resulting polymer using extrusion
techniques.</p><p num="0011">The present invention seeks to provide a novel process for
extrusion foaming of styrenic polymers in which the styrenic polymer
comprises less than 50 weight % of branched styrenic polymer.</p><p num="0012">The present invention provides a closed cell foam comprising from
C<sub>8-12</sub> vinyl aromatic polymer formed from:
<sl><li>i) from 60 to 100 weight % of one or more C<sub>8-12</sub> vinyl aromatic
monomers; and </li><li>ii) from 0 to 40 weight % of one or more monomers selected
from the group consisting of C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl esters of acrylic or methacrylc acid
and acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile;
which polymer may be grafted onto or occluded within from 0 to 12 weight
% of one or more rubbery polymers selected from the group consisting of:
<sl><li>a) co- and homopolymers of C<sub>4-5</sub> conjugated diolefins; and</li><li>b) copolymers comprising from 60 to 85 weight % of one or
more C<sub>4-5</sub> conjugated diolefins and from 15 to 40 weight % of a monomer
selected from the group consisting of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile,
said vinyl aromatic polymer comprising 10 to 45 weight % of a star
branched polymer and having a VICAT softening temperature not less
than 100°C.</li></sl>In a further embodiment the present invention provides a process
for preparing the above closed cell foam comprising injecting into a molten
mass of C<sub>8-12</sub> vinyl aromatic polymer formed from:</li><li>i) from 60 to 100 weight % of one or more C<sub>8-12</sub> vinyl aromatic
monomers; and</li><li>ii) from 0 to 40 weight % of one or more monomers selected
from the group consisting of C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl esters of acrylic or methacrylc acid
and acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile;
which polymers are grafted onto from 0 to 12 weight % of one or more
rubbery polymers selected from the group consisting of:
<sl><li>a) co- and homopolymers of C<sub>4-5</sub> conjugated diolefins; and</li><li>b) copolymers comprising from 60 to 85 weight % of one or
more C<sub>4-5</sub> conjugated diolefins and from 15 to 40 weight % of a monomer
and 
selected from the group consisting of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile,
said polymer comprising 10 to 45 weight % of a star branched polymer
and having a VICAT softening temperature not less than 100°C; at a
temperature from 140 to 235°C and a pressure from 1500 to 3500 psi from
2 to 15 weight % of one or more blowing agents selected from the group
consisting of C<sub>4-6</sub> alkanes, CFCs, HCFCs, HFCs, CO<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> and
maintaining said C<sub>8-12</sub> vinyl aromatic polymer in a molten state and
thoroughly mixing said blowing agent with said polymer and extruding said
mixture of blowing agent and polymer.</li></sl></li></sl></p><p num="0013">The present invention also provides a process for polymerizing a
vinyl aromatic monomer to form a vinyl aromatic polymer comprising from
5 to 45 weight % of star branched vinyl aromatic polymer, said process
comprising feeding a mixture comprising:
<sl><li>i) from 60 to 100 weight % of one or more C<sub>8-12</sub> vinyl aromatic
monomers; and</li><li>ii) from 0 to 40 weight % of one or more monomers selected
from the group consisting of C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl esters of acrylic or methacrylc acid
and acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile;
which polymer may be grafted onto or occluded within from 0 to 12 weight
% of one or more rubbery polymers selected from the group consisting of:
<sl><li>a) co- and homopolymers of C<sub>4-5</sub> conjugated diolefins; and</li><li>b) copolymers comprising from 60 to 85 weight % of one or
more C<sub>4-5</sub> conjugated diolefins and from 15 to 40 weight % of a monomer
selected from the group consisting of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile,</li></sl></li><li>iii) from 0.01 to 0.1 weight % of a tetrafunctional peroxide initiator of the
formula:
<img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="26"/>
wherein R<sup>1</sup> is selected from the group consisting of C<sub>4-6</sub> t-alkyl radicals;
and R is a neopentyl group, in the absence of a cross linking agent to a
series of two or more continuous stirred tank reactors, to provide a
relatively low temperature initial reaction zone at a temperature from 100
to 130°C and a relatively higher temperature subsequent reaction zone at
a temperature from 130 to 160°C and maintaining a ratio of residence time
in said relatively lower temperature reaction zone to said relatively higher
temperature reaction zone from 1:1 to 3:1 and recovering the resulting
polymer.</li></sl></p><p num="0014">As used in this specification "star branched" polymer means having
multiple, preferably at least 3, most preferably 4, branches eminating from
a common node.</p><p num="0015">The styrenic polymers of the present invention may be co- or
homopolymers of C<sub>8-12</sub> vinyl aromatic monomers. Some vinyl aromatic
monomers may be selected from the group consisting of styrene, alpha
methyl styrene and para methyl styrene. Preferably the vinyl aromatic
monomer is styrene.</p><p num="0016">The styrenic polymer may be a copolymer comprising from 60 to
100 weight % of one or more C<sub>8-12</sub> vinyl aromatic monomers; and from 0 to
40 weight % of one or more monomers selected from the group consisting 
of C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl esters of acrylic or methacrylc acid and acrylonitrile and
methacrylonitrile. Suitable esters of acrylic and methacrylic acid include
methyl acrylate, ethyl acyrlate, butyl acrylate, methyl methacrylate, ethyl
methacrylate and butyl methacrylate.</p><p num="0017">The polymers of the present invention may be rubber modified.
That is the polymer may be grafted onto or occluded within from 0 to 12
weight % of one or more rubbery polymers selected from the group
consisting of:
<sl><li>i) co- and homopolymers of C<sub>4-5</sub> conjugated diolefins; and</li><li>ii) copolymers comprising from 60 to 85 weight % of one or
more C<sub>4-5</sub> conjugated diolefins and from 15 to 40 weight % of a monomer
selected from the group consisting of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile.</li></sl></p><p num="0018">The rubbery polymer may be selected from a number of types of
polymers. The rubbery polymer may comprise from 40 to 60, preferably
from 40 to 50 weight % of one or more C<sub>8-12</sub> vinyl aromatic monomers
which are unsubstituted or substituted by a C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl radical and from 60
to 40, preferably from 60 to 50 weight % of one or more monomers
selected from the group consisting of C<sub>4-5</sub> conjugated diolefins. Such
polymers are known as the styrene butadiene rubbers (SBR). The rubber
may be prepared by a number of methods, preferably by emulsion
polymerization. This process is well known to those skilled in the art and
described for example in Rubber Technology, Second Edition, edited by
Maurice Morton, Robert E. Krieger Publishing Company Malabar, Florida,
1973, reprint 1981 - sponsored by the Rubber Division of the American
Chemical Society. </p><p num="0019">The rubbery polymer may be a nitrile rubber comprising from 15 to
40 weight % of one or more monomers selected from the group consisting
of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile, preferably acrylonitrile, and from 85 to
60 weight % of one or more C<sub>4-6</sub> conjugated diolefins. The polymers may
be prepared by a number of methods, preferably by emulsion
polymerization. This process is well known to those skilled in the art and
described for example in the aforementioned reference.</p><p num="0020">The rubber may be a co- or homopolymer of one or more C<sub>4-6</sub>
conjugated diolefins such as butadiene (1,3-butadiene) or isoprene,
preferably butadiene. The polybutadiene may have a molecular weight
(Mw) from about 260,000 to 300,000, preferably from about 270,000 to
280,000. Polybutadiene has a steric configuration. The polymer may
have a cis configuration ranging from about 50% up to 99%. Some
commercially polymers have a cis content of about 55% such as
TAKTENE® 550 (trademark of Bayer AG) or DIENE® 55 (trademark of
Firestone). Some commercially available butadiene has a cis
configuration from about 60 to 80% such as Firestone's DIENE® 70.
Some high cis-butadiene rubbers may have a cis configuration of 95% or
greater, preferably greater than 98% (TAKTENE® 1202).</p><p num="0021">If present, preferably the rubber is present in an amount from about
3 to 10 weight % based on the total composition fed to the reactor (i.e.
monomers and rubber). Polybutadiene is a particularly useful rubber.</p><p num="0022">The process for making HIPS is well known to those skilled in the
art. The rubber is "dissolved" in the styrene monomer (actually the rubber
is infinitely swollen with the monomer). This results in two co-continuous 
phases. The resulting "solution" is fed to a reactor and polymerized
typically under shear. When the degree of polymerization is about equal
to the weight % of rubber in the system it inverts (e.g. the styrene/styrene
polymer phase becomes continuous and the rubber phase becomes
discontinuous. After phase inversion the polymer is finished in a manner
essentially similar to that for finishing polystyrene.</p><p num="0023">The polymer is prepared using conventional bulk, solution, or
suspension polymerization techniques. However, there is added to the
first reactor (i.e. the lower temperature reactor) from about 0.01 to 0.1
weight % (100 to 1000 ppm) of a tetrafunctional peroxide initiator of the
formula:
<img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="59" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
wherein R<sup>1</sup> is selected from the group consisting of C<sub>4-6</sub> t-alkyl radicals and
R is a neopentyl group. The reaction is conducted in the absence of a
cross linking agent. Preferably the tetrafunctional peroxide is present in
the feed to the first reactor (i.e. the lower temperature reactor) in an
amount from about 200 to 400 ppm (0.02 to 0.04 weight %), most
preferably from 250 to 350 ppm (0.025 to 0.035 weight %).</p><p num="0024">Suitable tetrafunctional peroxide initiators include initiators selected
from the group consisting of tetrakis-(t-amylperoxycarbonyloxymethyl)
methane, tetrakis-(t-butylperoxycarbonyloxymethyl) methane, 1,2,3,4-tetrakis
(t-amylperoxycarbonyloxy) butane and the tetrakis (t-C<sub>4-6</sub> alkyl
monoperoxycarbonates). A particularly useful initiator is the compound of 
the above formula wherein R is a nenopentyl group and R<sup>1</sup> is a tertiary
amyl or tertiary butyl radical.</p><p num="0025">Typically in a bulk or solution process the monomer mixture and
optionally rubber is polymerized in at least two continuous stirred tank
reactors. The first reaction temperature is kept at a relatively low
temperature from about 100 to 130°C, preferably from 120 to 130°C and
then at a relatively higher temperature from about 130 to 160°C, preferably
from about 135 to 145°C. In the polymerization process there are
competing initiation reactions. The initiation may be thermal without the
use of the initiator or it may be initiated by the peroxy carbonate initiator.
The residence time in each temperature zone is controlled so that the
amount of polymerization initiated thermally (which results in a linear
polymer) and by the peroxy carbonate initiator (in which about half of the
resulting polymer is branched) is controlled so that not more than 50
weight % of the resulting polymer is branched. For example if the reaction
is controlled so that the ratio of residence time at the lower temperature to
time at higher temperature is from 1:1 to 3:1, preferably from 1.5:1 to
2.5:1, most preferably about 2:1 (i.e. 1.8:1 to 2.2:1). The weight ratio of
linear to star branched polymer is controlled to greater than 1:1 (e.g.
greater than 50:50). Preferably, the vinyl aromatic polymer or styrenic
polymer will comprise from about 10 to 45, preferably from about 15 to 40,
most preferably from about 15 to 30 weight % of a star branched polymer.</p><p num="0026">In a suspension process the monomers, optionally including
dissolved rubber, may be either first partially polymerized in a continuously
stirred tank system. The partially polymerized monomer mixture has 
stabilizers or suspending agents added to it to help suspend it in the
aqueous phase as an oil in water suspension. Typically the stabilizer or
suspending agent is added in an amount from 0.1 to 2.0 weight %,
preferably from 0.5 to 1.0 weight %.</p><p num="0027">Useful stabilizers or suspending agents are well known to those
skilled in the art. Useful stabilizers or suspending agents include polyvinyl
alcohol, gelatin, polyethylene glycol, hydroxyethyl cellulose, carboxymethyl
cellulose, polyvinyl pyrrolidone, polyacrylamides, salts of poly (meth)
acrylic acid, salts of phosphonic acids, salts of phosphoric acid and salts of
complexing agents such as ethylene diamine tetraacetic acid (EDTA).</p><p num="0028">Generally the salts are ammonium, alkali and alkaline earth metal
salts of the foregoing stabilizers or suspending agents. For example
tricalcium phosphate is a suitable suspending agent.</p><p num="0029">The tetra functional initiator may be added to the monomer mixture
prior to polymerization in the bulk or mass reactor or just prior to
suspension batch polymerization in the suspension batch reactor. The
suspension batch reactor is generally operated at lower temperatures than
the bulk reactor. However, the suspension batch reaction is finished at
higher temperatures from about 120 to 150°C, typically from about 125 to
135°C.</p><p num="0030">The resulting polymer has a number of unique properties that make
it suitable for extrusion foaming and particularly suitable for extrusion
foaming using inorganic blowing agents such as CO<sub>2</sub> or N<sub>2</sub>. The polymer
has a VICAT softening temperature (as measured by DIN 53460 is
equivalent to ISO 306 is equivalent to ASTM D 1525-96) of greater than 
100°C, preferably from 105°C to 115°C. The polymer has a mean melt
strength at 210°C of not less than 12.5 cN.</p><p num="0031">The melt strength and the stretch ratio test are determined using a
Rosand® Capillary Rheometer. The mean melt strength is determined by
extrusion of a melt at 210°C of the polymer through a circular 2 mm
diameter flat die, length to diameter (L/D) of the die is 20:1. The strand is
extruded at a constant shear rate of 20 sec<sup>-1</sup>. The strand is attached to a
haul off unit which increases in speed with time. The strand is attached to
a digital balance scale to measure the force of draw on the polymer. As
the speed of the haul off unit increases the draw force increases. As a
result the strand breaks. The draw force immediately prior to break is
defined as the melt strength. The stretch ratio is defined as the ratio of the
velocity of draw to the extrusion velocity at the die exit. The test is
repeated at least three times to determine an average value.</p><p num="0032">The polymer may have a melt flow at condition G (230°C/5 Kg load
of less than 5 g/10 minutes, preferably less than 3 g/10 minutes, most
preferably of less than 2 g/10 minutes. Additionally, the polymer has a Mz
which exceeds typical high heat crystal polystyrene resins by at least
40,000, preferably by greater than 60,000.</p><p num="0033">The polymer may be foamed using conventional extrusion foaming
equipment. The extruder may be a back to back type or it may be a
multizoned extruder having at least a first or primary zone to melt the
polymer and inject blowing agent and a second extruder or zone.</p><p num="0034">In the primary extruder or zone the polymer melt is maintained at
temperatures from about 425°F to 450°F (about 218 to 232°C). Once the 
polymer is melted, blowing agent is injected into the melt at the end of the
primary extruder or zone. In the primary extruder or zone there will be a
high shear zone to promote thorough mixing of the blowing agent with the
polymer melt. Such a zone may comprise a number of pin mixers.</p><p num="0035">The polymer melt containing dissolved or dispersed blowing agent
is then fed from the primary extruder to the secondary extruder or passes
from a primary zone to a secondary zone within the extruder maintained at
a melt temperature of 269°F to 290°F (about 132°C to 143°C). In the
secondary extruder or zone the polymer melt and entrained blowing agent
passes through the extruder barrel by the action of an auger screw having
deep flights and exerting low shear upon the polymer melt. The polymer
melt is cooled by means of cooling fluid, typically oil which circulates
around the barrel of the extruder. Generally the melt is cooled to a
temperature of from about 250°F to about 290°F (about 121°C to 143°C).</p><p num="0036">The blowing agent may be selected from the group consisting of
C<sub>4-6</sub> alkanes, CFCs, HFCs, HCFCs, CO<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>, air and mixtures thereof.
The blowing agent may be CO<sub>2</sub> per se or N<sub>2</sub> per se. The blowing agent
may comprise from 20 to 95 weight % of a blowing agent selected from the
group consisting of one or more C<sub>4-6</sub> alkanes (as described below) and
from 80 to 5 weight % of CFCs, HFCs and HCFCs (as described below).
Suitable C<sub>4-6</sub> alkanes include butane, pentane and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0037">The blowing agent may comprise from 30 to 95, preferably from 70
to 95, most preferably from 80 to 90 weight % of CO<sub>2</sub> and from 70 to 5,
preferably from 30 to 5, most preferably from 20 to 10 weight % of one or
more compounds selected from the group consisting of C<sub>1-2</sub> halogenated 
alkanes and C<sub>4-6</sub> alkanes. Suitable C<sub>1-2</sub> halogenated alkanes include the
chloroflurocarbons (CFCs); hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs) and the
hydrochlorofluorocarbons (HCFCs) such as trichlorofluoromethane
(CFC-11); dichlorodifluoromethane (CFC-12); trichlorotrifluoroethane
(CFC-113); dichlorotetrafluoroethane (CFC-114); dichlorofluoromethane
(CFC-21); chlorodifluoromethane (HCFC-22); difluoromethane (HFC-32);
2-chloro-1,1,1,2-tetrafluoroethane (HCFC-124); pentafluoroethane (HFC-125);
1,1,1,2-tetrafluoroethane (HCFC-124); 1,1-dichloro-1-fluoroethane
(HCFC-141b); 1-chloro-1,1-difluoroethane (HCFC-142b); trifluoroethane
(HFC-143a); 1,1-difluoroethane (HFC-152a); tetrafluoroethane (HFC-134a);
and dichloromethane. However, due to environmental concerns it
is preferred to use alkanes such as C<sub>4-6</sub> alkanes which have not been
halogenated such as butane, pentane, isopentane and hexane. The
blowing agent system may be used in amounts from 2 to 15, preferably
from 2 to 10, most preferably from about 3 to 8 weight % based on the
weight of the polymer.</p><p num="0038">The pressure within the extruder should be sufficient to keep the
blowing agent in the polymer melt. Typically, the pressures in the melt
after the blowing system has been injected will be from about 1500 to
3500 psi, preferably from about 2000 to about 2500 for CO<sub>2</sub>. The CO<sub>2</sub> and
the other blowing agent may be injected separately into the melt. If this is
done, preferably the alkane and/or halogenated alkane will be injected
upstream of the CO<sub>2</sub> as these types of blowing agents have a plasticizing
effect on the polymer melt which may help the CO<sub>2</sub> go into the melt. The
alkane blowing agent and the CO<sub>2</sub> may also be mixed prior to injection into 
the extruder as is disclosed in U.S. patent 4,424,287 issued January 3,
1984 assigned to Mobil Oil Corporation.</p><p num="0039">To improve the cell size and/or distribution throughout the polymer
small amounts of a nucleating agent may be incorporated into the polymer
blend or solution. These agents may be physical agents such as talc or
they may be agents which release small amounts of CO<sub>2</sub> such as citric
acid and alkali or alkaline earth metal salts thereof and alkali or alkaline
earth metal carbonates or bicarbonates. Such agents may be used in
amounts from about 500 to 5,000 ppm, typically from about 500 to 2,500
ppm based on the polymer melt or blend.</p><p num="0040">The polymer melt or blend may also contain the conventional
additives such as heat and light stabilizers (e.g. hindered phenols and
phosphite or phosphonite stabilizers) typically in amounts of less than
about 2 weight % based on the polymer blend or solution.</p><p num="0041">The foam is generally extruded at atmospheric pressure and as a
result of the pressure release on the melt, the melt foams. The foam is
cooled to ambient temperature typically below about 25°C, which is below
the glass transition temperature of the polymer and the foam is stabilized.
One of the advantages of the present invention is that the foamed polymer
melt has better melt strength than the foamed polymer melts of the prior
art and there is less foam collapse.</p><p num="0042">The foam may be extruded onto rollers as a relatively thick slab
typically from about 1 to 3 inches thick. The foam density may vary from 2
to 15 Ibs/ft<sup>3</sup> (from about 0.03 to 0.24 g/cm<sup>3</sup>). The slab is cut into
appropriate lengths (8 feet) and is generally used in the construction 
industry. Thinner foams, typically from about 1/16 to about 1/4 inches (62
to 250 mils) thick may be extruded as slabs or as thin walled tubes which
are expanded and oriented over an expanding tubular mandrel to produce
a foam tube which is slit to produce sheet. These relatively thin sheets are
aged, typically 3 or 4 days and then may be thermoformed into items such
as coffee cups, meat trays or "clam shells".</p><p num="0043">The present invention will now be illustrated by the following nonlimiting
examples in which, unless otherwise indicated parts means parts
by weight (grams) and percent means weight percent.</p><heading><b>Example 1: Polymer Preparation</b></heading><p num="0044">Styrene monomer and 0.028 weight % of a tetra t-alkylperoxy
carbonate sold by Ato Chemie under the trade mark JWEB50 were first
fed into a continuously stirred tank reactor maintained at 120°C. The
residence time in the first reactor was about 2.5 hours. The partially
polymerized mixture from the first reactor was then fed to a second
continuously stirred tank reactor maintained at 140°C. The residence time
in the second reactor was about 1 hour. The resulting polymer was then
devolatilized in a falling strand devolatilizer and recovered and pelletized.</p><p num="0045">The reaction conditions were such that about 64% of the polymer
was thermally initiated and linear. About 36% of the polymer was initiated
by the peroxide and about half of the resulting polymer was star branched.
The polymer had an Mz from 40,000 to 75,000 greater than conventional
high heat crystal. </p><heading><b>Example 2</b></heading><p num="0046">The procedure of Example 1 was repeated except that the amount
of initiator was 0.045 weight %.</p><heading><b>Example 3</b></heading><p num="0047">The procedure of Example 1 was repeated except that zinc stearate
was also included in the polymer in an amount of about 0.1 weight %.</p><heading><b>Physical Properties</b></heading><p num="0048">The physical properties of the resins prepared in Examples 1, 2 and
3 were compared to NOVA Chemicals' VEREX™ 1280 polystyrene resin
and 1230 polystyrene resin (both linear crystal polystyrene resins used in
extrusion foam applications), and Dow's resin 685D (a branched
polystyrene resin). The results are set forth in Table 1.</p><heading><b>Example 4</b></heading><p num="0049">The above samples together with the reference samples were
extrusion foamed using pentane as the blowing agent. The average cell
diameter of the foam was measured. The results are set out in Table 2.</p><p num="0050">The foams extruded well and the cell data suggests that the foam
stability good. The resulting foams have good toughness. <img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="137" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="221"/><img id="img-00200001" orientation="unknown" wi="147" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00200001.tif" inline="no" he="232"/></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A closed cell foam comprising from C8-12 vinyl aromatic polymer
formed from:
<claim-text><claim-text>i) from 60 to 100 weight % of one or more C8-12 vinyl aromatic
monomers; and</claim-text><claim-text>ii) from 0 to 40 weight % of one or more monomers selected
from the group consisting of C1-4 alkyl esters of acrylic or methacrylc acid
and acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile;
which polymer may be grafted onto or occluded within from 0 to 12 weight
% of one or more rubbery polymers selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) co- and homopolymers of C4-5 conjugated diolefins; and</claim-text><claim-text>b) copolymers comprising from 60 to 85 weight % of one or
more C4-5 conjugated diolefins and from 15 to 40 weight % of a monomer
selected from the group consisting of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile,
said vinyl aromatic polymer comprising 10 to 45 weight % of a star
branched polymer and having a VICAT softening temperature not less
than 100°C</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The closed cell foam according to claim 1, wherein the star
branched vinyl aromatic polymer is present in an amount from 15 to 40
weight % of the vinyl aromatic polymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The closed cell foam according to claim 1 or claim 2, having a mean
melt strength at 210°C of not less than 12.5 cN.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The closed cell foam according to any one of claims 1 to 3, wherein
the vinyl aromatic polymer has a VICAT softening temperature from 105
to 115°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The closed cell foam according to any one of the preceding claims,
wherein the C8-12 vinyl aromatic monomer is selected from the group
consisting of styrene, alpha methyl styrene and para methyl styrene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The closed cell foam according to any one of the preceding claims,
wherein the vinyl aromatic polymer is prepared by solution or bulk
polymerization in the presence of from 0.01 to 0.1 weight % of a tetra
functional peroxide initiator of the formula:

wherein R1 is selected from the group consisting of C4-6 t-alkyl radicals and
R is a neopentyl group, in the absence of a cross linking agent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The closed cell foam according to claim 6, wherein the tetrafunctional
initiator is selected from the group consisting of tetrakis-(t-amylperoxycarbonyloxymethyl)
methane, and tetrakis-(t-butylperoxycarbonyloxymethyl)
methane.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The closed cell foam according to any one of the preceding claims,
wherein the C8-12 vinyl aromatic polymer is a homopolymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The closed cell foam according to claim 8, wherein the C8-12 vinyl
aromatic polymer is polystyrene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The closed cell foam according to any one of the preceding claims,
having a melt flow at condition G of less than 2.5 g/10 minutes.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The closed cell foam according to any one of the preceding claims,
which contains no rubbery polymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The closed cell foam according to any one of claims 1 to 10, wherein
the rubbery polymer is present in an amount from 3 to 10 weight %.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A process for preparing a closed cell foam according to any one of
the preceding claims, comprising injecting into a molten mass of C8-12 vinyl
aromatic polymer formed from:
<claim-text><claim-text>i) from 60 to 100 weight % of one or more C8-12 vinyl aromatic
monomers; and</claim-text><claim-text>ii) from 0 to 40 weight % of one or more monomers selected from
the group consisting of C1-4 alkyl esters of acrylic or methacrylic acid and
acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile;
   which polymers are grafted onto from 0 to 12 weight % of one or more
rubbery polymers selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) co- and homopolymers of C4-5 conjugated diolefins; and</claim-text><claim-text>b) copolymers comprising from 60 to 85 weight % of one or
more C4-5 conjugated diolefins and from 15 to 40 weight % of a monomer
selected from the group consisting of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile,
said polymer comprising 10 to 45 weight % of a star branched polymer
and having a VICAT softening temperature not less than 100°C; at a
temperature from 140 to 235°C and a pressure from 1500 to 3500 psi from
2 to 15 weight % of one or more blowing agents selected from the group
consisting of C4-6 alkanes, CFCs, HCFCs, HFCs, CO2, N2 and mixtures
thereof and maintaining said C8-12 vinyl aromatic polymer in a molten state
and thoroughly mixing said blowing agent with said polymer and extruding
said mixture of blowing agent and polymer.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The process according to claim 13, wherein the blowing agent is one
or more blowing agents selected from the group consisting of one or more
C4-6 alkanes.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The process according to claim 14, wherein the blowing agent is
selected from the group consisting of pentane, butaine and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The process according to claim 13, wherein the blowing agent
comprisises from 20 to 95 weight % of a blowing agent selected from the
group consisting of one or more C4-6 alkanes and from 80 to 5 weight % of
CFCs, HFCs and HCFCs.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The process according to claim 16, wherein said one or more C4-6
alkanes is selected from the group consisting of pentane, butaine and
mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The process according to claim 13, wherein said blowing agent is
CO2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The process according to claim 13, wherein the blowing agent
comprises from 30 to 95 weight % of CO2 and from 70 to 5 weight % of one
or more blowing agent selected from the group consisting of C4-6 alkanes
and CFCs, HFCs and HCFCs.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The process according to claim 19, wherein the blowing agent
comprises from 70 to 95 weight % of CO2 and from 30 to 5 weight % of one
or more C4-6 alkane blowing agents selected from the group consisting of
pentane, butane and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>A process for polymerizing a vinyl aromatic monomer to form a vinyl
aromatic polymer comprising from 5 to 45 weight % of star branched vinyl
aromatic polymer, said process comprising feeding a mixture comprising:<claim-text><claim-text>i) from 60 to 100 weight % of one or more C8-12 vinyl aromatic
monomers; and</claim-text><claim-text>ii) from 0 to 40 weight % of one or more monomers selected
from the group consisting of C1-4 alkyl esters of acrylic or methacrylc acid
and acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile;
which polymer may be grafted onto or occluded within from 0 to 12 weight
% of one or more rubbery polymers selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) co- and homopolymers of C4-5 conjugated diolefins; and</claim-text><claim-text>b) copolymers comprising from 60 to 85 weight % of one or
more C4-5 conjugated diolefins and from 15 to 40 weight % of a monomer
selected from the group consisting of acrylonitrile and methacrylonitrile,
and</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>iii) from 0.01 to 0.1 weight % of a tetrafunctional peroxide initiator
of the formula:

wherein R1 is selected from the group consisting of C4-6 t-alkyl radicals and
R is a neopentyl group, in the absence of a cross linking agent to a series
of two or more continuous stirred tank reactors, to provide a relatively low
temperature initial reaction zone at a temperature from 100 to 130°C and a
relatively higher temperature subsequent reaction zone at a temperature
from 130 to 160°C and maintaining a ratio of residence time in said
relatively lower temperature reaction zone to said relatively higher
temperature reaction zone from 1:1 to 4:1 and recovering the resulting
polymer.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>