<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2003087217-A1" country="WO" doc-number="2003087217" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="28790284" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20031023"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2003087217-A1" status="new" fvid="78641842"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2003087217</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20031023</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-0311123-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>0311123</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20030410</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-12127802-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>12127802</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020412</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>C08L  23/06</main-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  47/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  47/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  49/04        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  49/04        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/04        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  91/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  91/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01M   2/16        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01M   2/16        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01M   6/16        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01M   6/16        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01M  10/06        20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01M  10/06        20060101C I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01M  10/36        20060101C I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01M  10/40        20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29C  47/00B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/06+B4Z</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01M  10/052</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01M  10/06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01M  10/40</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01M   2/16C3</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L29C223:04C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L29C305:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L29C305:39</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L29C305:39S</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L29C49:04</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">ULTRAHIGH MOLECULAR WEIGHT POLYETHYLENE ARTICLES AND METHOD OF MANUFACTURE</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">ARTICLES EN POLYETHYLENE DE MASSE MOLECULAIRE TRES ELEVEE ET PROCEDE DE FABRICATION DESDITS ARTICLES</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-3351495-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3351495</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5326391-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5326391</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5336573-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5336573</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5665488-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5665488</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6124059-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6124059</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DARAMIC INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WHEAR KEVIN J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YARITZ JOSEPH G</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DARAMIC, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WHEAR, KEVIN, J.</name></addressbook> </applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YARITZ, JOSEPH, G.</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants> <inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WHEAR KEVIN J</name> <address><country>US</country> </address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YARITZ JOSEPH G</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WHEAR, KEVIN, J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YARITZ, JOSEPH, G.</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An article of manufacture comprises an ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene (UHMWPE) mixed with a processing oil and a lubricant selected from the group consisting of fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, glycol esters, PEG esters, glycerol esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, mercaptan ethoxylates, modified ethoxylates, amide surfactants, phosphate esters, phosphonate esters, phosphite esters, alkyl sulfates, fatty acid ethers, alkyl ether sulfates, alkylaryl ether sulfates, sulfanates, naphthalene sulfonates, sulfosuccinates, sulfonated esters, sulfonated amides, alkyl ether carboxylates, alkylaryl ether carboxylates, quaternary amines, amino quaternary amines, ethoxylated amines, imidazoline derivatives, betaines, sultaines, aminopropionate, catechol derivatives, saturated fatty acids, unsaturated fatty acids, and combinations thereof. The method for making those articles is also disclosed.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>L'invention concerne un article manufacturé, qui comprend un polyéthylène de masse moléculaire très élevée (PEhpm) mélangé avec de l'huile de mise en oeuvre et un lubrifiant sélectionné dans le groupe constitué par les composés suivants: esters d'acide gras, esters d'acide gras éthoxylés, esters glycoliques, esters de PEG, esters de glycérol, esters éthoxylés, esters de sorbitol, esters de sorbitol éthoxylés, éthoxylates aromatiques, éthoxylates d'alcool, éthoxylates de mercaptan, éthoxylates modifiés, tensioactifs d'amide, esters phosphoriques, esters de phosphonate, esters de phosphite, sulfates d'alkyle, éthers d'acide gras, sulfates d'alkyléther, sulfates d'alkylaryléther, sulfanates, sulfonates de naphtalène, sulfosuccinates, esters sulfonés, amides sulfonés, carboxylates d'alkyléther, carboxylates d'alkylaryléther, amines quaternaires, amines amino-quaternaires, amines éthoxylés, dérivés d'imidazoline, betaïnes, sultaïnes, aminopropionate, dérivés de catéchol, acides gras saturés, acides gras insaturés, et leurs combinaisons. L'invention concerne en outre un procédé de fabrication desdits articles.</p></abstract><description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="2"/>--><p num="p0001"> U TRAHIGH MOLECULAR WEIGHT POLYETHYLENE ARTICLES AND METHOD OF MANUFACTURE</p><p num="p0002">Field of the Invention The invention is directed to ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene (UHMWPE) articles and their manufacture.</p><p num="p0003">Background of the Invention UHMWPE is difficult to process because the resin does not flow when melted. Berins, M.L., ed. , Plastics Engineering Handbook of the Society of the Plastic Industry, Chapman &amp; Hall, New York City, NY (1991), p. 52. Consequently, UHMWPE is processed by sintering, compression molding, ram extrusion, or gel processing. Sintering is a process where resins are agglomerated by solid-state diffusion. Heat and pressure are usually essential. Compression molding is a process where resins are shaped between the faces of a mold by heat and pressure. Ram extrusion is a process where resins are shaped by forcing it through a die. The force is provided by a ram. U.S. Patent Nos . 5,234,652 and 5,399,308 disclose a dry extrusion process for a mixture consisting of resins and lubricant. Gel processing is a process where resins are formed into gels for subsequent processing. The gel is a dilute solution or suspension 
<!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>-->
of resin in a solvent, e.g., an extractable solvent (or oil or plasticizer) .</p><p num="p0004">UHMWPE is gel spun into fibers. In gel spinning, the primary mechanism of solidification is the gelling of the polymer solution by cooling to form a gel filament consisting of precipitated polymer and solvent. Solvent removal is accomplished following solidification by washing in a liquid bath. This process is also used to form microporous films. See U.S. Patent Nos . 4,588,633 and 5,248,461. In U.S. Patent No. 4,588,633, the gel solution consists of 2-4% by weight of UHMWPE. See Examples 1-12. In U.S. Patent No. 5,248,461, the gel solution consists of up to 20% by weight of UHMWPE. See Examples 1-20. These membranes are useful as, among other things, separators for electrochemical cells. See U.S. Patent Nos. 4,588,633, column 4, lines 30-36 and 5,248,461, column 4, lines 57-60.</p><p num="p0005">Another variant of gel processing is gel processing with a filler. For example, see U.S. Patent Nos. 3,351,495, 4,833,172, and 5,948,557. Generally, UHMWPE, a processing oil (or plasticizer) , and a filler are mixed in an extruder and subsequently made into microporous sheets. In U.S. Patent No. 3,351,495, the solution consisted of up to 20% by volume of UHMWPE. See Examples 6, 8, 18, 19, 20, and 21. The microporous membranes 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
formed were used as separators for batteries. See column 1, lines 24-33. In U.S. Patent Nos. 4,833,172 and 5,948,557, a calcium/zinc stearate lubricant, PETRAC<sup>®</sup> CZ-81, is added to the solution. See Tables 1 and 2, respectively. The microporous membranes formed were used as labels, diffusion membranes, and separators. See U.S. Patent No. 5,948,557, column 1, lines 27-41.</p><p num="p0006">There is a need to improve the processability of UHMWPE.</p><p num="p0007">Summary of the Invention An article of manufacture comprises an ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene (UHMWPE) mixed with a processing oil and a lubricant selected from the group consisting of fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, glycol esters, PEG esters, glycerol esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, mercaptan ethoxylates, modified ethoxylates, amide surfactants, phosphate esters, phosphonate esters, phosphite esters, alkyl sulfates, fatty acid ethers, alkyl ether sulfates, alkylaryl ether sulfates, sulfonates, naphthalene sulfonates, sulfosuccinates, sulfonated esters, sulfonated amides, alkyl ether carboxylates, alkylaryl ether carboxylates, quaternary amines, amino quaternary amines, ethoxylated amines, imidazoline derivatives, betaines, sultaines, aminopropionates, catechol derivatives, saturated fatty acids, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
unsaturated fatty acids, and combinations thereof. The method for making those articles is also disclosed.</p><p num="p0008">Description of the Invention An article of manufacture is any shaped article. For example, articles of manufacture may include, but is not limited to, films, fibers, sheets, plates, slabs, bars, rods, billets, and blocks. Preferably, these articles are made by an extrusion process. These articles also may be microporous, for example, microporous sheets and films.</p><p num="p0009">Ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene (UHMWPE) is a polyethylene polymer having a weight average molecular weight greater than 5x10<sup>s</sup>. The polymer is either a homopolymer of ethylene or a copolymer of ethylene, with at most 10 mol% of one or more alpha-olefins . The polymer may be a blend with UHMWPE comprising at least 50% by weight of the blend and the balance being other polymers, such as, for example, polyolefins and synthetic and natural rubbers . The preferred weight average molecular weight is greater than 2xl0<sup>6</sup>. The most preferred UHMWPE has a weight average molecular weight greater than 5x10<sup>s</sup>. UHMWPE resins are commercially available as GUR from Ticona LLC of Summit, NJ, STAMYLAN from DSM of Geleen, Netherland, UTEC from Polyailden of Camacari, Brazil, and HI-ZEX Million, LUBMER, and MIPELON, each 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
from Mitsui Chemical of Tokyo, Japan. GUR 4130 (molecular weight about 4-5 million) and GUR 4170 (molecular weight about 8-9 million) are preferred.</p><p num="p0010">Processing oil (or processing plasticizer) have little solvating effect on the UHMWPE at lower temperatures (e.g. 60° C) , but have a significant solvating effect at elevated temperatures (e.g. 200°) . Such oils include paraffinic oils, naphthalenic oils, and aromatic oils, as well as other materials including the phthalate ester plasticizers such as dibutyl phthalate, bis (2- ethylene) phthalate, diisodecyl phthalate, dicyclohexyl phthalate, butyl benzyl phthalate, and ditridecyl phthalate. Additional oils, plasticizers, and/or solvents are mentioned in U.S. Patent Nos. 3,351,495; 4,588,633; 4,833,172; 5,248,461; and 5,948,557 are incorporated herein by reference .</p><p num="p0011">The filler includes any particulate filler as is well known in the art. For example, see U.S. Patent Nos. 3,351,495; 4,833,172; and 5,948,557 each is incorporated herein by reference. Preferably, the filler is a silica. Such fillers are commercially available under the tradename HiSil<sup>®</sup> from PPG Industries, Inc. of Pittsburgh, PA, SIPERANT from Degussa AG of Wesseling, Germany, ZEOSIL from Rhodia, Inc. of Cranberry, NJ or KETJENSIL from Akzo Chemie of Compiegne, France. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
 Minor amounts of auxiliary components may be added. Such auxiliary components include: carbon black, stabilizers, and antioxidants . The compounds are conventional and known in the art.</p><p num="p0012">Lubricants are compounds that, when added to an UHMWPE mixture, improve the processability of the UHMWPE mixture. Improved processability refers to a reduction in fusion time (the time it takes the polymeric system to melt (or dissolve) into a flowable solution) . Improved processability is also seen as a reduction in energy consumption by the motor and as a reduction in mixture temperature when comparing systems with and without the lubricants. The results arising from this phenomenon include, but are not limited to, decreasing energy consumption, decreased thermal and mechanical degradation of the polymer, increased polymer strength, decreased machine wear, and increased polymer throughputs .</p><p num="p0013">Such lubricants are selected from the material classes consisting of: fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, glycol esters, PEG esters, glycerol esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, mercaptan ethoxylates, modified ethoxylates, amide surfactants, phosphate esters, phosphonate esters, phosphite esters, alkyl sulfates, fatty acid ethers, alkyl ether sulfates, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>-->
alkylaryl ether sulfates, sulfonates, naphthalene sulfonates, sulfosuccinates, sulfonated esters, sulfonated amides, alkyl ether carboxylates, alkylaryl ether carboxylates, quaternary amines, amino quaternary amines, ethoxylated amines, imidazoline derivatives, betaines, sultaines, aminopropionate, catechol derivatives, saturated fatty acids, unsaturated fatty acids, and combinations thereof. Preferably, the lubricants are selected from the material classes consisting of: fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, PEG esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, phosphate esters, phosphonate esters, phosphite esters and combinations thereof. Most preferred are sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, and aromatic ethoxylates.</p><p num="p0014">Such lubricants are commercially available. An exemplary list is set out in the Table below. Such lubricants specifically exclude the metallic salts of stearic acid (e.g., Zn stearate and Ca stearate) and lubricants containing same. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>--></p><p num="p0015">TABLE</p><p num="p0016"><img id="imgf000009_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="172" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000009_0001.tif" inline="no" he="218"/><!-- EPO <DP n="10"/>--></p><p num="p0017"><img id="imgf000010_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="171" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000010_0001.tif" inline="no" he="94"/></p><p num="p0018">The components, UHMWPE, filler (optional) , processing oil, and lubricant, are mixed. In formulations with filler, the weight ratio of polymer to filler may range from 1:1 to 1:5, 1:3 being preferred. The ratio of UHMWPE and filler to oil may range from 1:1 to 1:2, 1:1.5 being preferred. The lubricant may comprise up to 15 weight% of the formulation, with 0.2 to 8% being preferred. In formulation without filler, the polymer may comprise up to 80% by weight of the mixture, preferably in the range of 20-65% by weight. The ratio of oil to lubricant may range from 3:1 to 1:3, with the range of 2:1 to 1:2 being preferred. The components are preferably mixed in a continuous fashion, for example, in a twin 
<!-- EPO <DP n="11"/>-->
screw extruder or a Brabender extruder or a screw extruder with a blown film die.</p><p num="p0019">After mixing, the mixture is shaped. Shaping will depend upon the particular article desired, as is known in the art. For example, if a film or sheet is desired, then the appropriate die may be added to the extruder. After shaping, the articles are most often subjected to a step to remove the processing oil or solvent from the article (gel), (e.g., an extraction (or washing or leaching) step to remove processing oil and lubricant) . This step is conventional. For example, see U.S. Patent Nos. 3,351,495; 4,588,633; 4,833,172; 5,248,461; and 5,948,557 each is incorporated herein by reference. In formulations with filler, the extruded sheets are preferably subjected to an extraction step to remove processing oil. After extraction, these sheets may have about 0.5% (nominally 0%) to 30% by weight oil remaining, preferably 5-25%, and most preferably 10-20%. It is understood that it is impossible to remove all of the processing oil and lubricant from any of the mixtures, so at least a trace amount will remain in the final articles. In formulations without fillers, the extruded sheets are preferably subjected to an extraction step. After extraction, these sheets may have only residual amounts of oil and lubricant. Articles may be subjected to stretching or tentering before, during, or after extraction. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="12"/>-->
 Preferably, these articles are formed into microporous sheets or films. Such microporous sheets and films may be used as labels, diffusion membranes, and separators in electrochemical devices (e.g., batteries, capacitors, and fuel cells) . A battery is an electrochemical device having an anode, a cathode, an electrolyte, and a separator sandwiched between the anode and the cathode and impregnated with the electrolyte. Formulation with filler are used preferably in lead acid batteries. Formulations without filler are used preferably in lithium batteries.</p><p num="p0020">Examples In the following examples, set out in Tables 1-8, ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene (GUR 4130 and GUR 4170 from Ticona LLC of Summit, NJ) , filler (specifically silica, HiSil from PPG of Pittsburgh, PA), processing oil (naphthalenic oil from Calumet Co. of Princeton, LA) , and lubricant (as identified in the tables) were blended together and extruded from a twin screw extruder. The extruded product, a sheet, was subjected to an extraction step for the removal of processing oil. During extrusion, torque (%KW) and melt temperature were measured for comparison to control (examples without additive) and indicates the amount of energy needed to mix the components. After extraction, the amount of oil remaining in the article of manufacture (final oil %) was determined by a 
<!-- EPO <DP n="13"/>-->
extraction technique in which: a dried, 1.33 inch (3.38 cm) X 6 inch (15.24 cm) piece of sheet was weighed (Wl) and then immersed in 200 ml of fresh, room temperature hexane in a ultrasonic bath for at least 15 minutes; then the sample is dried and reweighed (W2) . The % oil is [ (W1-W2) /Wl] * 100. Two samples are averaged. Additionally, basis weight was measured in conventional fashion, and thickness (web) by ASTM D 374, MD tensile by ASTM D 638, porosity by Battery Council International (BCI) TM-3.207, and ER by BCI TM-3.218 using a conventional tester from Palico Instrument Limited of Circle Pines, MN. Puncture strength generally follows ASTM D3763 except as noted below: The instrument used was a Chatillon digital force guage DFIS 10 on a motorized test stand TCM 201. Chatillon/Ametek is located in Largo, FL. The puncture tip is slightly rounded and 1.930 mm in diameter, and the platform hole is 6.5 mm in diameter. The travel speed is set at 300 mm/min, and at least 10 measurements are averaged across a representative area of the sample. This method is generally independent of sample size, and representative area of the sample refers to across the width and length of a reasonably sized sample. The peak force needed to puncture the sample is recorded in units of N or lbs.</p><p num="p0021">In Tables 1-5, ingredients were mixed at the throat of the extruder, and in Tables 6-8, the lubricant was injected through the extruder' s barrel . 
<!-- EPO <DP n="14"/>-->
 TABLE 1</p><p num="p0022"><img id="imgf000014_0001"  orientation="portrait" wi="170" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000014_0001.tif"  inline="yes"  he="96"/></p><p num="p0023">TABLE 2</p><p num="p0024"><img id="imgf000014_0002"  orientation="portrait" wi="170" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000014_0002.tif" inline="yes" he="96"/><!-- EPO <DP n="15"/>-->
 TABLE 3</p><p num="p0025"><img id="imgf000015_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000015_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="96"/></p><p num="p0026">TABLE 4</p><p num="p0027"><img id="imgf000015_0002" orientation="portrait" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000015_0002.tif" inline="no" he="96"/><!-- EPO <DP n="16"/>-->
 TABLE 5</p><p num="p0028"><img id="imgf000016_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000016_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="96"/></p><p num="p0029">TABLE 6</p><p num="p0030"><img id="imgf000016_0002" orientation="portrait" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000016_0002.tif" inline="yes" he="96"/><!-- EPO <DP n="17"/>-->
 TABLE 7</p><p num="p0031"><img id="imgf000017_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000017_0001.tif" inline="no" he="96"/></p><p num="p0032">TABLE 8</p><p num="p0033"><img id="imgf000017_0002" orientation="portrait" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000017_0002.tif" inline="yes" he="96"/><!-- EPO <DP n="18"/>-->
 In the following examples, set out in Table 9, ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene (GUR 4130 from Ticona LLC of Summit, NJ) , processing oil (naphthalenic oil from Calumet Co. of Princeton, LA) , and lubricant (as identified in the table) were blended together and extruded from a twin screw extruder . The extruded product was observed as it exited the extruder die and categorized by appearance scale 1-10. A rating of 10 meant a smooth product that appeared well mixed, and a rating of 1 meant a very grainy and rough appearance .</p><p num="p0034">TABLE 9</p><p num="p0035"><img id="imgf000018_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000018_0001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/></p><p num="p0036">A = Phosphate Ester; fatty alcohol blend phosphate esters; Rhodafac L0-11A LA from Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0037">B = Phosphate Ester; Bis (2-ethylhexyl) phosphate ester from Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0038">C = Phosphate Ester; Bis (2-ethylhexyl) + mono (2-ethylhexyl) phosphate esters from Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0039">D = Phosphonate Ester; 2-ethylhexyl bis (2-ethylhexyl) phosphonate ester from Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0040">E = Phosphate Ester; Tris (2-ethylhexyl) phosphate ester from Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="19"/>-->
F = Fatty acids, unsaturated; linoleic and linolenic acids; Linseed Oil .</p><p num="p0041">G = Fatty acids, unsaturated; eleostearic acid; Tung Oil.</p><p num="p0042">H = Phosphonate Ester; octyl phosphonic acid ester from Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0043">I = PEG Esters; PEG-30 castor oil (ricinoleic + oleic + palmitic.) ; Alkamuls EL-620 from Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0044">J = Sorbitan Esters; sorbitan monooleate; Alkamuls SMO from Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0045">K = Sulfosuccinate Ester; dioctyl sodium sulfosuccinate; OT-100 from Cytec Industries of Charlotte, NC .</p><p num="p0046">L = Sorbitan Ester; sorbitan monolaurate; Alkamuls SML from Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0047">M = Sorbitan Ester Ethoxylated; sorbitan trioleate; Alkamuls STO From Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0048">N = Aromatic Ethoxylate; dodecyl phenol ethoxylates; Igepal RC-630 From Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0049">0 = Aromatic Ethoxylate; nonylphenol ethoxylates; Igepal CO-210 From Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0050">P = Aromatic Ethoxylate; nonylphenol ethoxylates; Igepal CO-630 From Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0051">Q = Alcohol Ethoxylate; mixed linear alcohol ethoxylates; Rhodasurf LA-3 from Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0052">R = Alcohol Ethoxylate; mixed linear alcohol ethoxylates; Rhodasurf LA-12 from Rhodia HPCII of Cranberry, NJ.</p><p num="p0053">In the following examples, set out in Table 10, ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene (GUR 4170 from Ticona LLC, Summit, NJ) , filler (silica, HiSil from PPG of Pittsburgh, PA) , processing oil (naphthelenic oil from Calumet Co. of Pamaton, LA) , and 
<!-- EPO <DP n="20"/>-->
lubricant (as identified in the table) were mixed together and extruded from a Brabender extruder (BW Brabender Co . of South Hackensack, NJ) . In the control, 5.42 grams of UHMWPE was mixed with 14.65 g filler and 30.56 g oil. In the other examples, 5.42 grams of UHMWPE was mixed with 14.65 filler, 29.06 g oil and 1.50 g lubricant. This procedure is used to predict the lubricant's efficacy by observing fusion time and terminal torque. The fusion time is a measure of when the polymer dissolves in the oil (phase inversion of the polymer) . The fusion time is typically the second peak on a plot of torque as a function of time. The fusion time typically occurs after a first peak which indicates wetting of the polymer by the oil. The terminal torque is measured after 10 minutes of mixing. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="21"/>--></p><p num="p0054">TABLE 10</p><p num="p0055"><img id="imgf000021_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="118" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000021_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="221"/><!-- EPO <DP n="22"/>--><img id="imgf000022_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="117" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000022_0001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/></p><p num="p0056">The present invention may be embodied in other forms without departing from the spirit and the essential attributes thereof, and, accordingly, reference should be made to the appended claims, rather than to the foregoing specification, as indicated the scope of the invention. . 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="23"/>--><claim-text/><claim-text>That which is claimed:</claim-text><claim-text>1. An article of manufacture comprising: an ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene (UHMWPE) mixed with a processing oil and a lubricant selected from the group consisting of fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, glycol esters, PEG esters, glycerol esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, mercaptan ethoxylates, modified ethoxylates, amide surfactants, phosphate esters, phosphonate esters, phosphite esters, alkyl sulfates, fatty acid ethers, alkyl ether sulfates, alkylaryl ether sulfates, sulfonates, naphthalene sulfonates, sulfosuccinates, sulfonated esters, sulfonated amides, alkyl ether carboxylates, alkylaryl ether carboxylates, quaternary amines, amino quaternary amines, ethoxylated amines, imidazoline derivatives, betaines, sultaines, aminopropionate, catechol derivatives, saturated fatty acids, unsaturated fatty acids, and combinations thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>2. The article of Claim 1 wherein said lubricants being selected from the group consisting of fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, PEG esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, phosphate esters, phosphonate esters, phosphite esters, and combinations thereof. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="24"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>3. The article of Claim 1 wherein said UHMWPE has a molecular weight greater than 2xlO<sup>δ</sup>.</claim-text><claim-text>4. The article of Claim 1 wherein said UHMWPE has a molecular weight greater than 5x10<sup>6</sup>.</claim-text><claim-text>5. The article of Claim 1 wherein article being a microporous membrane having a porosity greater than 30%.</claim-text><claim-text>6. A battery separator comprising a microporous membrane comprising the article of Claim 1.</claim-text><claim-text>7. The separator of Claim 6 wherein said battery being a lithium battery.</claim-text><claim-text>8. An article of manufacture comprising: an ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene (UHMWPE) mixed with a filler, a processing oil, and a lubricant selected from the group consisting of fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, glycol esters, PEG esters, glycerol esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, mercaptan ethoxylates, modified ethoxylates, amide surfactants, phosphate esters, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="25"/>-->
phosphonate esters, phosphite esters, alkyl sulfates, fatty acid ethers, alkyl ether sulfates, alkylaryl ether sulfates, sulfonates, naphthalene sulfonates, sulfosuccinates, sulfonated esters, sulfonated amides, alkyl ether carboxylates, alkylaryl ether carboxylates, quaternary amines, amino quaternary amines, ethoxylated amines, imidazoline derivatives, betaines, sultaines, aminopropionate, catechol derivatives, saturated fatty acids, unsaturated fatty acids, and combinations thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>9. The article of manufacture of Claim 8 wherein said lubricants being selected from the group consisting fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, PEG esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, phosphate esters, phosphonate esters, phosphite esters, and combinations thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>10. The article of manufacture of Claim 8 wherein a weight ratio of said ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene to said filler ranges from 1:1 to 1:5.</claim-text><claim-text>11. The article of manufacture of Claim 8 wherein said lubricant comprising up to 15% by weight. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="26"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>12. The article of manufacture of Claim 8 wherein said ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene has a molecular weight greater than 2xl0<sup>6</sup>.</claim-text><claim-text>13. A battery separator comprising a microporous membrane comprising the article of Claim 8.</claim-text><claim-text>14. The separator of Claim 13 wherein said battery being a lead acid battery.</claim-text><claim-text>15. A method of making an ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene (UHMWPE) article comprising the step of: mixing ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene, processing oil, and a lubricant selected from the group consisting of fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, glycol esters, PEG esters, glycerol esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, mercaptan ethoxylates, modified ethoxylates, amide surfactants, phosphate esters, phosphonate esters, phosphite esters, alkyl sulfates, fatty acid ethers, alkyl ether sulfates, alkylaryl ether sulfates, sulfonates, naphthalene sulfonates, sulfosuccinates, sulfonated esters, sulfonated amides, alkyl ether carboxylates, alkylaryl ether carboxylates, quaternary amines, amino quaternary amines, ethoxylated amines, imidazoline 
<!-- EPO <DP n="27"/>-->
derivatives, betaines, sultaines, aminopropionate, catechol derivatives, saturated fatty acids, unsaturated fatty acids, and combinations thereof, and extruding said mixture .</claim-text><claim-text>16. The method of Claim 15 further comprising the step of extracting processing oil from said extruded mixture.</claim-text><claim-text>17. The method of Claim 15 wherein extruding further comprising screw extrusion, Brabender extrusion, and blown film extrusion.</claim-text><claim-text>18. The method of Claim 15 wherein a weight ratio of the oil to the lubricant ranges from 3:1 to 1:3.</claim-text><claim-text>19. The method of Claim 15 wherein the UHMWPE comprises up to 80% by weight of the mixture.</claim-text><claim-text>20. The method of Claim 15 wherein the lubricant being selected from the group consisting of fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, PEG esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, phosphate esters, phosphonate esters, phosphite esters, and combinations thereof. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="28"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>21. A method of making an ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene (UHMWPE) article comprising the step of: mixing ultrahigh molecular weight polyethylene, filler, processing oil, and a lubricant selected from the group consisting of fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, glycol esters, PEG esters, glycerol esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, mercaptan ethoxylates, modified ethoxylates, amide surfactants, phosphate esters, phosphonate esters, phosphite esters, alkyl sulfates, fatty acid ethers, alkyl ether sulfates, alkylaryl ether sulfates, sulfonates, naphthalene sulfonates, sulfosuccinates, sulfonated esters, sulfonated amides, alkyl ether carboxylates, alkylaryl ether carboxylates, quaternary amines, amino quaternary amines, ethoxylated amines, imidazoline derivatives, betaines, sultaines, aminopropionate, catechol derivatives, saturated fatty acids, unsaturated fatty acids, and combinations thereof, and extruding said mixture .</claim-text><claim-text>22. The method of Claim 21 further comprising the step of extracting processing oil from said extruded mixture. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="29"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>23. The method of Claim 21 wherein extruding further comprising screw extrusion, Brabender extrusion, and blown film extrusion.</claim-text><claim-text>24. The method of Claim 21 wherein a weight ratio of the UHMWPE to the filler ranges from 1:1 to 1:5.</claim-text><claim-text>25. The method of Claim 21 wherein a weight ratio of the UHMWPE and filler to the oil ranges from 1:1 to 1:2.</claim-text><claim-text>26. The method of Claim 21 wherein the lubricant being selected from the group consisting of fatty acid esters, ethoxylated fatty acid esters, PEG esters, ethoxylated esters, sorbitol esters, ethoxylated sorbitol esters, aromatic ethoxylates, alcohol ethoxylates, phosphate esters, phosphonate esters, phosphite esters, and combinations thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>27. The method of Claim 21 wherein the lubricant comprises up to 15% by weight of the mixture. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>