<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1693046-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1693046" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="36293379" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20060823"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1693046-A1" status="new" fvid="24704697"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1693046</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20060823</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-06250900-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>06250900</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20060220</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-90644705-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>90644705</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20050221</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   6/00        20060101AFI20060524BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   6/00        20060101CLI20060524BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   6/02        20060101CLI20060524BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   6/083       20060101ALI20060524BHEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K   6/00B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K   6/083B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Säure-tolerante Dentalmasse</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Acid tolerant dental composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition dentaire qui tolère l'acide</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1479364-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1479364</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1502569-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1502569</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-20030134933-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20030134933</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-20040235981-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20040235981</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3991008-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3991008</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4567030-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4567030</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4569976-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4569976</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4775585-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4775585</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4792632-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4792632</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4911899-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4911899</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5609675-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5609675</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6353041-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6353041</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>KING: 'Incompatibility Profiles of All-In-One Adhesives. I. True vs Apparent Incompatibility' INTERNATIONAL ASSOCIATION FOR DENTAL RESEARCH 82ND GENERAL SESSION 10 March 2004,</text><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KERR CORP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KERR CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kerr Corporation</last-name><address><street>1717 West Collins Avenue</street><city>Orange, CA 92667</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>QIAN XUEJUN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>QIAN, XUEJUN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>QIAN, XUEJUN</last-name><address><street>10 Arcella Circle</street><city>Foothill Ranch, CA 92610</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Findlay, Alice Rosemary</last-name><address><street>Lloyd Wise Commonwealth House, 1-19 New Oxford Street</street><city>London WC1A 1LW</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="pa01">A dental composition compatible with acidic dental primers/adhesives, the dental composition comprising (A) 5% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated vinyl, acrylate, or methacrylate group; (B) 0.01% (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one compound of structure
<chemistry id="chema01" num="0001"><img id="ia01" orientation="unknown" wi="47" img-format="tif" img-content="chem" file="imga0001.tif" inline="no" he="30"/></chemistry>
where each of R1, R2, and R3 may be the same or different and is independently selected from H, alkyl, alkoxyl, aryl, acyl, allyl, pyridyl, -OH, alkenyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl, and heterocyclic structure containing O, S, or N; (C) 0.01% (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one hydroperoxide compound with at least one hydroperoxide groups attached to a tertiary carbon; (D) 5% (w/w) to 95% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler; (E) 0% (w/w) to 25% (w/w) of one or more components selected from a solvent, a photoinitiator, a stabilizer, and/or an antimicrobial agent.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="p0001">The invention is directed to dental compositions in general, and an acid tolerant dental composition in particular as well as kits containing the composition.</p><p num="p0002">Resin cement is increasingly being used as a dental luting material for cementing prosthetic devices to a tooth, due to its excellent mechanical properties and good optical properties. Resin cement has good translucency and good initial color-matching to a tooth's natural color. Cementing prosthetic devices such as veneers, inlays, onlays, crowns, bridges, and posts to a tooth using a resin cement involves the steps of (1) preparing the tooth (cutting and cleaning) to receive the prosthetic device; (2) optionally, etching the prepared tooth surface with an acidic etchant and rinsing to remove the etchant; (3) applying an acidic primer/adhesive to the tooth surface receiving the prosthetic device; (4) adhering the prosthetic device to the primer/adhesive coated tooth surface using a resin cement, and (5) hardening the dental cement. Adhesion of the prosthetic device depends on the extent of curing of the primer/adhesive and cement. When cementing metal-based or high opacity prosthetic devices, it is difficult for light to reach the adhesive and cement, so a photocure process cannot be used. Instead, a redox initiator system must be used for the cement to cure effectively in the dark without the need for light.</p><p num="p0003">Current resin cements use benzoyl peroxide (BPO) and a tertiary amine as the redox initiator system to initiate polymerization and cure the cement. The resin cement typically comprises a base paste containing the tertiary amine and a catalyst paste containing BPO. When the base and catalyst pastes are mixed, BPO and the tertiary amine form a redox pair generating free radicals and initiating polymerization of the methacrylate monomers, causing the cement to harden (cure).</p><p num="p0004">Most primer/adhesives, particularly self-etching primer/adhesive systems, are acidic. When a resin cement containing a BPO/tertiary amine initiator system is applied to a tooth coated with such an acidic primer/adhesive, the tertiary amine is quickly neutralized by the acidic primer/adhesive, thereby compromising its curing efficacy and resulting in poor adhesion at the primer/cement interface. The incompatibility of current resin cements with acidic primers/adhesives has been reported (King et al, Incompatibility Profiles of All-In-One Adhesives. I. True vs Apparent Incompatibility., International Association for Dental Research 82<sup>nd</sup> General Session, Abstract No. 23, March 10-13, 2004, Honolulu, Hawaii). This same<!-- EPO <DP n="2"> --> incompatibility also exists between a core buildup material and an acidic primer/adhesive.</p><p num="p0005">A redox initiator system that can tolerate the acidity of the primer/adhesive and that cures effectively at the interface between a cement and the acidic primer/adhesive is desirable. One such redox initiator system utilizes 1-(2-pyridyl)-2-thiourea and a tertiary hydroperoxide in a self-adhering dental composition (Qian U.S. Published Patent Application Serial No. 10/440,804). This composition was applied directly to the tooth without any pre-treatment (etching or priming) of the tooth surface, but the bond strength was low without a primer/adhesive.</p><p num="p0006">In one embodiment of the invention there is provided a two-part dental composition comprising (A) 5% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated group selected from the group consisting of vinyl, acrylate and methacrylate; (B) 0.01 % (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one compound of structure
<chemistry id="chem0001" num="0001"><img id="ib0001" orientation="unknown" wi="54" img-format="tif" img-content="chem" file="imgb0001.tif" inline="no" he="31"/></chemistry>
where each of R1, R2, and R3 may be the same or different and is independently selected from the group consisting of H, alkyl, alkoxyl, aryl, acyl, alyl, pyridyl, -OH, alkenyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl, and heterocyclic structure containing O, S, or N; (C) 0.01% (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one hydroperoxide compound with at least one hydroperoxide group attached to a tertiary carbon; (D) 5% (w/w) to 95% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler; and (E) 0% (w/w) to 25% (w/w) of at least one component selected from the group consisting of a solvent, a photoinitiator, a stabilizer, an antimicrobial agent, or combinations thereof, wherein component (B) is in a first part of the two-part composition, component (C) is in a second part of the two-part composition, and components (A), (D), and (E) are independently in either the first part and/or the second part of the composition. Each of R1, R2, and R3 of component (B) is independently selected from the group consisting of H, alkyl, phenyl, 2-pyridyl, 2-tetrahydrofufuryl, acetyl, and benzoyl. The hydroperoxide compound is selected from the group consisting of t-butyl hydroperoxide, t-amyl hydroperoxide, p-diisopropylbenzene hydroperoxide, cumene hydroperoxide, pinane<!-- EPO <DP n="3"> --> hydroperoxide, p-menthane hydroperoxide, 1,1,3,3-tetramethylbutyl hydroperoxide, and combinations thereof. The filler is selected from the group consisting of inorganic metal, salt, oxide, nitride, silicate glass, bariumaluminosilicate glass, bariumaluminoborosilicate glass, strontiumaluminosilicate glass, bariurnfluoroaluminosilicate glass, strontiumfluoroaluminosilicate glass, strontiumzincfluoroaluminosilicate glass, zincaluminosilicate glass, quartz, colloidal silica, precipitated silica, zirconia-silica, polymeric filler, polymerized composite filler with inorganic particles, and combinations thereof. In one embodiment, the concentration of the filler provides a radiopacity of the composition that is at least 100% of that of aluminum. The antimicrobial agent is selected from the group consisting of benzakonium chloride, triclosan, alkyl 4-hydroxybenzoate, zinc oxide, a silicate glass powder containing silver and/or zinc, a zeolite containing silver and/or zinc ion(s), and combinations thereof. Each part of the two-part composition is independently selected from the group consisting of a liquid, a powder, and a paste.</p><p num="p0007">Another embodiment of the invention provides a two-part paste/paste dental composition. The first paste comprises (A1) 10% (w/w) to 80% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated group selected from the group consisting of vinyl, acrylate, and methacrylate; (B) 0.01 % (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one compound of structure
<chemistry id="chem0002" num="0002"><img id="ib0002" orientation="unknown" wi="50" img-format="tif" img-content="chem" file="imgb0002.tif" inline="no" he="34"/></chemistry>
where each of R1, R2, and R3 may be the same or different and is independently selected from the group consisting of H, alkyl, alkoxyl, aryl, acyl, allyl, pyridyl, -OH, alkenyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl, and heterocyclic structure containing O S, or N; and (D1) 15% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler; and the second paste comprises (A2) 10% (w/w) to 80% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated group selected from the group consisting of vinyl, acrylate, and methacrylate; (C) 0.01% (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one hydroperoxide compound with at least one hydroperoxide group attached to a tertiary carbon; and (D2) 15% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler, wherein components (A1) and (A2) of the composition are the same or<!-- EPO <DP n="4"> --> different, and the dental composition optionally further comprises 0% (w/w) to 25% (w/w) of a component selected from the group consisting of a photoinitiator, a stabilizer, a solvent, an antimicrobial agent, and combinations thereof.</p><p num="p0008">Another embodiment of the invention provides a two-part powder/liquid dental composition. The liquid comprises (A) 20% (w/w) to 99.5% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated group selected from the group consisting of vinyl, acrylate, and methacrylate; and (C) 0.01% (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one hydroperoxide compound with at least one hydroperoxide group attached to a tertiary carbon; and the powder comprises (B) 0.01 % (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one compound of structure
<chemistry id="chem0003" num="0003"><img id="ib0003" orientation="unknown" wi="61" img-format="tif" img-content="chem" file="imgb0003.tif" inline="no" he="31"/></chemistry>
where each of R1, R2, and R3 may be the same or different and is independently selected from the group consisting of H, alkyl, alkoxyl, aryl, acyl, allyl, pyridyl, -OH, alkenyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl, and heterocyclic structure containing O, S, or N; (D) 50% (w/w) to 99.5% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler; and the dental composition optionally further comprises 0% (w/w) to 25% (w/w) of a component selected from the group consisting of a photoinitiator, a stabilizer, a solvent, an antimicrobial agent, and combinations thereof.</p><p num="p0009">Another embodiment of the invention provides a dental cementation or core buildup kit. The kit comprises (I) a primer/adhesive composition having a pH less than 4.5; and (II) a two-part dental cement or core buildup material composition comprising (A) 5% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated group selected from the group consisting of vinyl, acrylate, and methacrylate; (B) 0.01 % (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one compound of structure
<chemistry id="chem0004" num="0004"><img id="ib0004" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="chem" file="imgb0004.tif" inline="no" he="33"/></chemistry><!-- EPO <DP n="5"> -->
 where each of R1, R2, and R3 may be the same or different and is independently selected from the group consisting of H, alkyl, alkoxyl, aryl, acyl, allyl, pyridyl, -OH, alkenyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl, and heterocyclic structure containing O, S, or N; (C) 0.01 % (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one hydroperoxide compound with at least one hydroperoxide group attached to a tertiary carbon; (D) 5% (w/w) to 95% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler; (E) 0% (w/w) to 25% (w/w) of at least one component selected from the group consisting of a solvent, a photoinitiator, a stabilizer, an antimicrobial agent, and combinations thereof, wherein component (B) is in a first part of the two-part composition, component (C) is in a second part of the two-part composition, and components (A), (D), and (E) are independently in either the first part and/or the second part. The two-part dental cement or core buildup material composition may be provided in a prepackaged container such as a syringe, bottle, capsule, ampule, or jar. Each part of the two-part dental cement or core buildup material composition independently may be a paste, a powder, or a liquid. In one embodiment, the prepackaged container is a dual-syringe assembly with each syringe housing one part of the two-part composition. A static mixer is attached to the openings of the dual syringe to provide a homogeneous mixture upon dispensing the mixed composition. In one embodiment, the prepackaged container is a single-dose assembly with the two parts of the two-part composition not in contact with each other.</p><p num="p0010">There is disclosed a method for adhering a prosthetic device to a tooth. A primer/adhesive with a pH less than 4.5 is applied to a surface of a tooth prepared to receive the device. The prosthetic device is adhered using a dental cement, and the dental cement is hardened. The dental cement composition comprises (A) 5% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated group selected from the group consisting of vinyl, acrylate, and methacrylate; (B) 0.01 % (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one compound of structure
<chemistry id="chem0005" num="0005"><img id="ib0005" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="chem" file="imgb0005.tif" inline="no" he="33"/></chemistry><!-- EPO <DP n="6"> -->
 where each of R1, R2, and R3 may be the same or different and is independently selected from the group consisting of H, alkyl, alkoxyl, aryl, acyl, allyl, pyridyl, -OH, alkenyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl, and heterocyclic structure containing O, S, or N; (C) 0.01 % (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one hydroperoxide compound with at least one hydroperoxide group attached to a tertiary carbon; (D) 5% (w/w) to 95% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler; (E) 0% (w/w) to 25% (w/w) of at least one component selected from the group consisting of a solvent, a photoinitiator, a stabilizer, an antimicrobial agent, and combinations thereof, wherein component (B) is in a first part of the two-part composition, component (C) is in a second part of the two-part composition, and components (A), (D), and (E) are independently in either the first part and/or the second part. In the method, an acidic etchant many optionally be applied to the tooth surface and then rinsed off prior to the first step.</p><p num="p0011">There is also disclosed a method for providing a tooth with a dental composition comprising (A) 5% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated group selected from the group consisting of vinyl, acrylate, and methacrylate; (B) 0.01 % (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one compound of structure
<chemistry id="chem0006" num="0006"><img id="ib0006" orientation="unknown" wi="57" img-format="tif" img-content="chem" file="imgb0006.tif" inline="no" he="34"/></chemistry>
where each of R1, R2, and R3 may be the same or different and is independently selected from the group consisting of H, alkyl, alkoxyl, aryl, acyl, allyl, pyridyl, -OH, alkenyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl, and heterocyclic structure containing O, S, or N; (C) 0.01 % (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one hydroperoxide compound with at least one hydroperoxide group attached to a tertiary carbon; (D) 5% (w/w) to 95% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler; (E) 0% (w/w) to 25% (w/w) of at least one component selected from the group consisting of a solvent, a photoinitiator, a stabilizer, an antimicrobial agent, or combinations thereof; wherein component (B) is in a first part of the two-part composition, component (C) is in a second part of the two-part composition, and components (A), (D), and (E) are independently in either the first part and/or the second part, the components mixed substantially immediately before application to the tooth, is applied to a tooth prepared to receive the composition,<!-- EPO <DP n="7"> --> and the composition is then hardened. This method may be used to provide a permanent cement, a core buildup material, a filling material, a temporary cement, a temporary crown and/or bridge, a temporary inlay, a temporary onlay, an endodontic sealer, or an endodontic filling material to the tooth.</p><p num="p0012">A detailed description of preferred embodiments of the invention will now be provided.</p><p num="p0013">One embodiment of the invention is an acid tolerant dental composition compatible with acidic dental primers/adhesive. The composition is described as acid tolerant in that the initiator component does not degrade in the presence of acid, so that curing of the composition is not affected by the acidity of the primer/adhesive with which the composition comes in contact. The composition thus enhances adhesion of prosthetic devices applied to a primer/adhesive coated tooth.</p><p num="p0014">The composition comprises (A) 5% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated group, either vinyl, acrylate, or methacrylate; (B) 0.01% (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one compound of structure
<chemistry id="chem0007" num="0007"><img id="ib0007" orientation="unknown" wi="55" img-format="tif" img-content="chem" file="imgb0007.tif" inline="no" he="31"/></chemistry>
where each of R1, R2, and R3 may be the same or different and is independently selected from H, alkyl, alkoxyl, aryl, acyl, allyl, pyridyl, -OH, alkenyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl, and heterocyclic structure containing O, S, or N; (C) 0.01% (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one hydroperoxide compound with at least one of the hydroperoxide groups attached to a tertiary carbon; (D) 5% (w/w) to 95% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler; and (E) 0% (w/w) to 25% (w/w) of one, or a combination of, a solvent, a photoinitiator, a stabilizer, and/or an antimicrobial agent.</p><p num="p0015">Another embodiment comprises a dental cementation or core buildup kit with enhanced compatibility between an acidic primer/adhesive and the cement or core buildup material, therefore improving adhesion to the tooth. The kit includes (I) an acidic primer/adhesive composition having a pH less than 4.5; and (II) a cement or core buildup composition having components (A)-(E) as previously described.<!-- EPO <DP n="8"> --></p><p num="p0016">The composition may be used in a method for adhering a prosthetic device to a tooth to restore the function and/or appearance of a diseased tooth. A prosthetic device includes, but is not limited to, a dental crown, bridge, inlay, onlay, veneer, or post. The diseased tooth is prepared (e.g., cleaned, cut, trimmed, etc.) to receive the device. In some embodiments, an acidic etchant is applied to the surface of the tooth to which the device will be applied, and then the etchant is removed by rinsing the surface. A primer/adhesive with a pH less than 4.5 is applied to this surface, to which the prosthetic device is adhered using the cement composition having components (A)-(E) as previously described.</p><p num="p0017">The inventive dental cement or core buildup composition tolerates the acidic primer/adhesive already coated on the tooth surface. In one embodiment, the inventive composition enhances adhesion of a prosthetic device applied to the primer/adhesive coated tooth surface. In another embodiment, the inventive composition is a temporary cement, temporary crown and/or bridge, a temporary inlay, a temporary onlay, an endodontic sealer, and/or an endodontic filling material.</p><p num="p0018">For component (A), at least one polymerizable monomer can be used. Examples of the polymerizable monomer include, but are not limited to, the following: hydroxyethyl (meth)acrylate {(meth)acrylate = acrylate or methacrylate}, hydroxypropyl (meth)acrylate, hydroxybutyl (meth)acrylate, glycerol di(meth)acrylate, glycerol mono(meth)acrylate, methyl (meth)acrylate, ethyl (meth)acrylate, propyl (meth)acrylate, butyl (meth)acrylate, hexyl (meth)acrylate, octyl (meth)acrylate, lauryl (meth)acrylate, decyl (meth)acrylate, tridecyl (meth)acrylate; 2-ethoxyethyl (meth)acrylate, 2'-ethoxy-2-ethoxyethyl (meth)acrylate, ethyleneglycol di(meth)acrylate, diethyleneglycol di(meth)acrylate, triethyleneglycol di(meth)acrylate (TEGDMA), tetraethyleneglycol di(meth)acrylate, polyethyleneglycol mono-(meth)acrylate, polyethyleneglycol di-(meth)acrylate, polypropyleneglycol mono-(meth)acrylate, polypropyleneglycol di-(meth)acrylate, polytetramethyleneglycol mono-(meth)acrylate, polytetramethyleneglycol di-(meth)acrylate, hexanediol di(meth)acrylate, trimethylolpropane tri(meth)acrylate, ethoxylated trimethylolpropane tri(meth)acrylate, UDMA (reaction product of 2-hydroxyethyl methacrylate with 2,4,4 -trimethylhexane diisocyanate), 2,2-bis[4-(2-hydroxy-3-methacryloylpropoxy)-phenyl]-propane (Bis-GMA), ethoxylated bisphenol A dimethacrylate (EBPADMA-n where n = total number of moles of ethylene oxide in the molecule, as only one example, n = 2-20 units), tetrahydrofurfuryl (meth)acrylate,<!-- EPO <DP n="9"> --> or mixtures thereof. In one embodiment, polymerizable monomers containing hydroxyl functional groups are used. Examples of hydroxyl-containing polymerizable monomers include, but are not limited to, hydroxyethyl (meth)acrylate, hydroxypropyl (meth)acrylate, hydroxybutyl (meth)acrylate, glycerol di(meth)acrylate, glycerol mono(meth)acrylate, 2,2-bis[4-(2-hydroxy-3-methacryloylpropoxy)-phenyl]-propane (Bis-GMA). In one embodiment, polymerizable monomers containing at least one acidic group are used. The acidic group may be carboxylic acid, carboxylic acid anhydride, sulfonic acid, sulfinic acid, phosphoric acid, a phosphoric acid derivative, phosphonic acid, or a phosphonic acid derivative, with a derivative being a salt or ester of the respective acid. In one embodiment, the acidic group is phosphoric acid and its derivatives, and/or phosphonic acid and its derivatives. The concentration of total polymerizable monomers (A) is in the range of about 5% (w/w) to about 90% (w/w) of the composition. In one embodiment, the concentration of total polymerizable monomers (A) is in the range of about 15% (w/w) to about 80% (w/w) of the composition. In one embodiment, the concentration of total polymerizable monomers (A) is in the range of about 20% (w/w) to about 50% (w/w) of the composition.</p><p num="p0019">For component (B), at least one compound of the structure
<chemistry id="chem0008" num="0008"><img id="ib0008" orientation="unknown" wi="51" img-format="tif" img-content="chem" file="imgb0008.tif" inline="no" he="30"/></chemistry>
is incorporated, where each of R1, R2, and R3 may be the same or different and is independently selected from H, alkyl, alkoxyl, aryl, acyl, allyl, pyridyl, -OH, alkenyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl, and a heterocyclic structure containing O, S, or N. Examples of component (B) include, but are not limited to, 1-benzoyl-3-(2-pyridyl)-2-thiourea, 1-acetyl-3-(2-pyridyl)-2-thiourea, 1-phenyl-3-(2-pyridyl)-2-thiourea, 1-(2-pyridyl)-2-thiourea, 1,3-di-(2-pyridyl)-2-thiourea, 1,1-dimethyl-3-(2-pyridyl)-2-thiourea, 1,1,3-trimethyl-3-(2-pyridyl)-2-thiourea, and 1-(2-tetrahydrofufuryl)-3-(2-pyridyl)-2-thiourea. Each of R1, R2, and R3 can be up to C14 structures. The concentration of component (B) is in the range of about 0.01 % (w/w) to about 10% (w/w) of the composition. In one embodiment, the concentration of component (B) is in the range of about 0.05% (w/w) to about 2% (w/w) of the composition. In one embodiment, the<!-- EPO <DP n="10"> --> concentration of component (B) is in the range of about 0.10% (w/w) to about 1% (w/w) of the composition.</p><p num="p0020">For component (C), any hydroperoxide compound that has at least one hydroperoxide group attached to a tertiary carbon can be used. The hydroperoxide compound can contain more than one hydroperoxide group. Examples of tertiary hydroperoxide compounds include, but are not limited to, t-butyl hydroperoxide, t-amyl hydroperoxide, p-diisopropylbenzene hydroperoxide, cumene hydroperoxide, pinane hydroperoxide, p-menthane hydroperoxide, and 1,1,3,3-tetramethylbutyl hydroperoxide. The concentration of component (C) ranges from about 0.01 % (w/w) to about 10% (w/w) of the composition. In one embodiment, the concentration of component (C) ranges from about 0.1 % (w/w) to about 5% (w/w) of the composition.</p><p num="p0021">For component (D), at least one filler is incorporated into the composition. Fillers enhance mechanical properties of the composition, reduce polymerization shrinkage, improve rheological properties of the composition, and increase radiopacity of the composition for ease in detection of gaps or voids. Examples of fillers include, but are not limited to, inorganic metal, salt, oxide, nitride, silicate glass, aluminosilicate glass, aluminoborosilicate glass, fluoroaluminosilicate glass, quartz, colloidal silica, precipitated silica, zirconia-silica, polymeric filler, and/or polymerized composite fillers with inorganic particles. In one embodiment, inorganic fillers for increased x-ray contrast ability include metals, salts, oxides, silicate glass, aluminosilicate glass, aluminoborosilicate glass, and fluoroaluminosilicate glass containing elements of high atomic number such as Sr, Y, Zr, Ba, La, Hf, Zn, Bi, W, rare earth metals, and combinations of these. Examples include barium sulfate, silver, strontium fluoride, barium fluoride, ytterbium fluoride, ytrium fluoride, barium tungstate, zinc oxide, bismuth(III) oxide, bariumaluminosilicate, bariumaluminoborosilicate, strontiumaluminosilicate, bariumfluoroaluminosilicate, strontiumfluoroaluminosilicate, strontiumzincfluoroaluminosilicate, zincaluminosilicate, etc. Fumed silica, colloidal silica, or precipitated silica can also be incorporated to improve the dispersion of the filler, as well as the rheological and handling properties of the composition. Examples of colloidal silicas are Aerosil series such as OX-50, OX-130, and OX-200 silica sold by Degussa (Ridgefield Park, NJ), and Cab-O-Sil M5 and Cab-O-Sil TS-530 silica sold by Cabot Corp (Tuscola, IL). The filler also includes nanoparticles such as those obtained through a sol-gel process. Examples include those disclosed in U.S. Patent Nos. 4,567,030 and<!-- EPO <DP n="11"> --> 5,609,675, the disclosure of each expressly incorporated by reference herein in its entirety. Mixtures of different fillers can be used. For inorganic fillers, the surface of the filler may be treated or coated with a coupling agent, such as gamma-methacryloyloxypropyltrimethoxy-silane (MPTMS), that enhances the interfacial bonding between the filler and resin matrix and improves mechanical properties. In one embodiment, the mean particle size of the filler is less than 50 microns. In another embodiment, the mean particle size of the filler is less than 10 microns. The concentration of total filler(s) ranges from about 10% (w/w) to about 95% (w/w) of the composition. In one embodiment, the concentration of total filler(s) ranges from about 30% (w/w) to about 80% (w/w) of the composition. In one embodiment, the concentration of filler is sufficient to provide radiopacity of the composition to be equal to or greater than 100% of aluminum.</p><p num="p0022">For component (E), 0% (w/w) to 25% (w/w) of one or more of the following components may be present in the composition: a solvent (E1), a photoinitiator system (E2), a stabilizer (E3), and/or an antimicrobial agent (E4).</p><p num="p0023">In one embodiment, a solvent (E1) may be present at a concentration of 0% (w/w) to about 20% (w/w) of the composition. In another embodiment, a solvent may be present at a concentration of 0% (w/w) to about 10% (w/w) of the composition. Solvents that may be used include water, methanol, ethanol, isopropanol, acetone, methyl ethyl ketone, ethylene glycol, and/or glycerin.</p><p num="p0024">In one embodiment, a photoinitiator system (E2) may be present at a concentration of 0% (w/w) to about 10% (w/w) of the composition. In another embodiment, a photoinitiator system may be present at a concentration of 0% (w/w) to about 5% (w/w) of the composition. The inclusion of a photoinitiator system can render the composition dual-curable, i.e. both self-curable (in the absence of light) and photo-curable. Examples of photoinitiators include, but are not limited to, benzoin, benzoin ethers and esters, 2,2-diethoxy acetophenone, diketone compounds such as camphorquinone and 1-phenyl-1,2-propanedione, monoacylphosphine oxide, bisacylphosphine oxide as disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 4,792,632, which is expressly incorporated by reference herein in its entirety, diaryliodonium salt, triarylsulfonium salt, and a mixture of photoinitiators.

Additionally, an activator can be used together with a photoinitiator to enhance curing efficiency. Activators include tertiary amine and sulfinate compounds. Examples of activators include, but are not limited to, ethyl 4-(N,N-dimethylamino)<!-- EPO <DP n="12"> --> benzoate, 2-(ethylhexyl)-4-(N,N-dimethylamino) benzoate, N,N-dimethylaminoethyl methacrylate, N,N-dimethylaminophenethyl alcohol, sodium benzenesulfinate, and sodium toluenesulfinate. In one embodiment, a photoinitiator system includes the combination of camphoroquinone and a tertiary amine such as ethyl 4-(N,N-dimethylamino) benzoate, 2-(ethylhexyl)-4-(N,N-dimethylamino) benzoate, N,N-dimethylaminoethyl methacrylate, and N,N-dimethylaminophenethyl alcohol. In another embodiment, a photoinitiator system includes the combination of camphoroquinone and bisacylphosphine oxide or monoacylphosphine oxide.</p><p num="p0025">In one embodiment, a stabilizer (E3) is incorporated in the composition at a concentration of 0% (w/w) to about 5% (w/w) of the composition. In one embodiment, a stabilizer is incorporated in the composition at a concentration of 0% (w/w) to about 1% (w/w) of the composition. Stabilizers are polymerization inhibitors to improve the shelf stability of the composition. Examples of stabilizers include, but are not limited to, 2,6-di-(<i>tert</i>-butyl)-4-methylphenol (BHT) and 4-methoxyphenol (MEHQ).</p><p num="p0026">In one embodiment, an antimicrobial agent (E4) may be present at a concentration of 0% (w/w) to about 20% (w/w) of the composition. In one embodiment, an antimicrobial agent may be present at a concentration of 0% (w/w) to about 5% (w/w) of the composition. Examples of antimicrobial agents include, but are not limited to, benzalkonium chloride, iodoform, eugenol, zinc oxide, triclosan, alkyl 4-hydroxybenzoate, silicate glass powder containing silver and/or zinc, and zeolite powder containing silver and/or zinc ion(s). Useful antibacterial zeolites and their preparation are disclosed in U.S. Patent Nos. 4,911,899 and 4,775,585, each of which is expressly incorporated by reference herein in its entirety.</p><p num="p0027">Any combination of components (E1), (E2), (E3) and (E4) can be incorporated into the inventive composition.</p><p num="p0028">In addition to the previously described components, other components may also be included in various embodiments of the inventive composition. As one example, a component that absorbs ultraviolet light (UV absorber) may be added to improve the color stability of the composition upon exposure to UV light. An example of a UV absorber is 2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone ("UV-9"). As another example, a flavoring agent or fragrance may be added to impart a pleasant taste and/or smell.<!-- EPO <DP n="13"> --></p><p num="p0029">Components (B) and (C) form a redox initiator system that initiates polymerization and hardening of the composition when components (B) and (C) are homogeneously mixed together. The composition can be conveniently packaged into two parts with one part containing component (B) and the other part containing component (C). Components (A), (D), and (E) can be incorporated into either or both parts. The two parts are homogeneously mixed just prior to application of the composition to the tooth. The composition can be a two-part self-cure composition (i.e. curing without the activation of light), or a two-part dual-cure composition (both self-cure and photo-cure) when a photoinitiator is also included. When the two parts are mixed and self-cured (without photo-curing), the mixed composition sets (or hardens) within about 20 minutes. In embodiments, the mixed composition sets within 15 minutes, or within 10 minutes, from the start of mixing. Each part of the two-part composition is independently selected from a liquid, a paste, or a powder.

In one embodiment, both parts are in paste forms. In another embodiment, one part is in a liquid form, and the other part is in a powder form. In one embodiment, one part is in a paste form and the other part is in a powder form. In one embodiment, one part is in a paste form and the other part is in a liquid form. One embodiment is a two-part paste/paste composition with the first paste containing components (A) (which may be designated A1), (B), (D) (which may be designated D1), and optionally one or more E1-E4 components; and the second paste containing components (A) (which may be designated A2), (C), (D) (which may be designated D2), and optionally one or more E1-E4 components. Each of the two parts contains 10% (w/w) to 80% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one vinyl, acrylate, or methacrylate as an ethylenically unsaturated group, and each part contains 15% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of a finely divided filler. One embodiment is a two-part powder/liquid composition with the liquid part comprising (A) 20% (w/w) to 99.5% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated vinyl, acrylate, or methacrylate group; and (C) 0.01 % (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one hydroperoxide compound with at least one hydroperoxide group attached to a tertiary carbon; and the powder part comprising (B) 0.01 % (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one compound of structure<!-- EPO <DP n="14"> --><chemistry id="chem0009" num="0009"><img id="ib0009" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="chem" file="imgb0009.tif" inline="no" he="35"/></chemistry>
where each of R1, R2, and R3 may be the same or different and is independently selected from the group consisting of H, alkyl, alkoxyl, aryl, acyl, allyl, pyridyl, -OH, alkenyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl, and heterocyclic structure containing O, S, or N; and (D) 50% (w/w) to 99.5% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler; the composition optionally further comprising 0% (w/w) to 25% (w/w) of a component selected from the group consisting of a photoinitiator, a stabilizer, a solvent, and/or an antimicrobial agent.</p><p num="p0030">The inventive composition can be used as a permanent dental cement, a provisional dental cement, a core buildup material, a dental filling material, a provisional crown and/or bridge material, or an endodontic sealing and/or filling material. The inventive composition improves compatibility with an acidic primer/adhesive.</p><p num="p0031">The invention also includes a dental cementation or core buildup kit comprising the dental cement or core buildup composition comprising components (A), (B), (C), (D), and (E), and an acidic primer/adhesive composition having a pH less than 4.5. The kit may include directions for use. The dental cement or core buildup composition has enhanced compatibility with the acidic primer/adhesive composition so that an improvement in adhesion to a tooth can be realized.</p><p num="p0032">The dental cement or core-buildup composition in the above-described kit has two parts. The two-part composition can be a paste/paste two-part composition, a powder/liquid two-part composition, a liquid/paste two-part composition, or a powder/paste two-part composition. The two-part composition can be provided in prepackaged container(s) such as a syringe, bottle, capsule, ampule, or jar. In one embodiment, the prepackaged container is a dual-syringe assembly. For the dual-syringe assembly, each syringe has an opening and a static mixer is attached to the openings to provide a homogeneous mixture upon dispensing the mixed composition from an exit of the mixer. In another embodiment, the prepackaged container is a single-dose assembly. The above described dual-syringe assembly may be a single-dose assembly. The single-dose assembly may be a capsule that houses a<!-- EPO <DP n="15"> --> two-part powder/liquid composition, and the content of the capsule can be conveniently mixed by a mechanical mixing device. An example of mechanical mixing device is an amalgamator. The single-dose package may be a blister package that houses a two-part paste/paste composition.</p><p num="p0033">In the above-described kit, the primer/adhesive composition has a pH less than 4.5. In embodiments, the pH is less than 4.0, or less than 3.5, or less than 3.0. The pH value is measured with pH paper. The primer/adhesive composition comprises a minimum of (a) an acidic compound, (b) a polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated acrylate, methacrylate, or vinyl group, and (c) a solvent of one or more of acetone, ethanol, methanol, water, and/or methyl ethyl ketone. The acidic compound (a) has one or more acidic moieties selected from nitric acid, carboxylic acid, carboxylic acid anhydride, phosphonic acid or its derivative(s), phosphoric acid or its derivative(s), sulfonic acid, and sulfinic acid. In one embodiment, the acidic compound (a) is a polymerizable monomer having at least one acidic moiety and at least one ethylenically unsaturated acrylate, methacrylate, or vinyl group. In one embodiment, the polymerizable monomer (b) is a hydroxyl-containing polymerizable monomer, examples of which include, but are not limited to, hydroxyethyl (meth)acrylate, hydroxypropyl (meth)acrylate, hydroxybutyl (meth)acrylate, glycerol di(meth)acrylate, glycerol mono(meth)acrylate, and/or 2,2-bis[4-(2-hydroxy-3-methacryloylpropoxy)-phenyl]-propane (Bis-GMA).

The primer/adhesive composition also contains one or more components selected from a polymerization initiator system, a stabilizer, a finely divided filler, or an antimicrobial agent. The polymerization initiator may be a redox initiator system, a photoinitiator system, or a combination of a redox initiator system and a photoinitiator system.</p><p num="p0034">The primer/adhesive composition may be a single-part system where all components are combined. The primer/adhesive composition may be divided into two or more parts. The primer/adhesive composition may be packaged in a plastic bottle(s) or in a single-dose container(s). In a multi-part configuration, the different parts may be applied sequentially to a prepared tooth surface. Alternatively, all parts may be combined and homogeneously mixed before being applied to a prepared tooth surface.</p><p num="p0035">In another embodiment, the dental cementation or core buildup kit optionally further comprises an acidic etchant, a silane primer, and/or a metal primer.<!-- EPO <DP n="16"> --> An acidic etchant may be a phosphoric acid, maleic acid, or citric acid etchant used to etch the tooth structure (dentin or enamel). An acidic etchant may also be a hydrofluoric acid etchant used to etch the ceramic substrate of a prosthetic device.

A silane primer may be used to prime the ceramic substrate of a prosthetic device to enhance adhesion. A metal primer may be used to prime the metal alloy substrate of a prosthetic device to enhance adhesion.</p><p num="p0036">The composition or kit may be used in a method of adhering a prosthetic device to a tooth to restore the function and/or appearance of a diseased tooth. The prosthetic device includes a dental crown, bridge, inlay, onlay, veneer, or post. A diseased tooth may be prepared (e.g., cleaned, trimmed, cut, etc.) to receive the prosthetic device. Optionally, an acidic etchant may be applied to a tooth and then removed (e.g., by rinsing the etchant off). A primer/adhesive with a pH less than 4.5 is applied to the tooth surface receiving the prosthetic device, and the prosthetic device is adhered to the primer/adhesive coated tooth surface using the inventive dental cement composition. The cement composition is then hardened. In one embodiment, the primer/adhesive has a pH less than 4.0. In one embodiment, the primer/adhesive has a pH less than 3.5. In one embodiment, the primer/adhesive has a pH less than 3.0. The method results in enhanced adhesion of the prosthetic device due to the acid tolerant nature of the dental cement composition, resulting in enhanced compatibility with the acidic primer/adhesive.</p><p num="p0037">The two-part paste/paste, powder/liquid, or paste/liquid composition may be used as a provisional or temporary dental material. The duration of a provisional or temporary material is typically less than three months before a permanent dental restorative material is placed. The temporary dental material may be a temporary cement, a temporary crown and/or bridge, a temporary inlay, or a temporary onlay. The composition may also be used as an endodontic sealer and/or endodontic filling material. In a method using the two-part composition as a provisional dental material or as an endodontic material, the two-part composition (components (A), (B), (C), (D) and (E)) is prepared. The tooth is prepared. The two parts of the two-part composition are mixed just prior to application, then the mixed composition is applied to the tooth and the composition is hardened. In this embodiment for provisional or endodontic application, one type of polymerizable monomer is an elastomeric (meth)acrylate oligomer. The elastomeric (meth)acrylate oligomer may be an elastomeric urethane (meth)acrylate oligomer and/or an elastomeric<!-- EPO <DP n="17"> --> polyalkyleneglycol (meth)acrylate oligomer. Those elastomeric oligomers are disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 6,353,041.</p><p num="p0038">The composition or kit may be used as a core buildup material to build up a tooth structure, or replace missing dentition, to receive a crown. The method involves the steps of (1) preparing the tooth to receive the core buildup material (e.g., cutting and cleaning); (2) optionally, etching the prepared tooth with an acid etchant and rinsing to remove the etchant; (3) applying a acidic primer/adhesive to coat the tooth surface to receive the core buildup material; (4) placing the core buildup material onto the primer/adhesive coated tooth surface; and (5) hardening the core-buildup material.</p><p num="p0039">The following examples are illustrative of the invention.</p><heading>Flexural Strength (FS)</heading><p num="p0040">FS was measured from the same flexural test according to an ISO 4049 standard. The specimens were prepared by condensing the mixed paste into a stainless-steel mold with a dimension of 2 mm x 2 mm x 25 mm, and then either self-cured or photo-cured from both sides. The cured disk was removed from the mold and conditioned in 37°C water for 24 hours before subjecting to mechanical testing on an Instron Universal Tester (Model 4202) in 3-point bending mode with a crosshead speed of 0.5 mm/minute. The peak load at which the specimen breaks is used to calculate the FS, expressed in MPa unit. Six specimens were tested for each formula.</p><heading>Abbreviations</heading><p num="p0041">The following abbreviations for materials are used in all examples.
<dl id="dl0001" compact="compact"><dt>Barium Glass:</dt><dd>bariumaluminoborosilicate filler that has a mean particle size of one micron and surface treated with MPTMS</dd><dt>BHT:</dt><dd>2,6-di-(<i>tert-</i>butyl)-4-methylphenol</dd><dt>Bis-GMA:</dt><dd>2,2-bis[4-(2-hydroxy-3-methacryloylpropoxy)-phenyl]-propane</dd><dt>CHPO:</dt><dd>cumene hydroperoxide</dd><dt>CQ:</dt><dd>camphoroquinone</dd><dt>EDMAB:</dt><dd>ethyl 4-(N,N-dimethylamino) benzoate</dd><dt>ETM PTA:</dt><dd>ethoxylated trimethylolpropane triacrylate with 3 moles of ethylene oxide<!-- EPO <DP n="18"> --></dd><dt>GDM:</dt><dd>glyceryldimethacrylate</dd><dt>GDM-P:</dt><dd>glyceryldimethacrylate phosphate</dd><dt>HEMA:</dt><dd>hydroxyethyl methacrylate</dd><dt>MEHQ:</dt><dd>4-methoxyphenol</dd><dt>MPTMS:</dt><dd>γ-methacryloyloxypropyltrimethoxysilane</dd><dt>ODMAB:</dt><dd>2-(ethylhexyl)-4-(N,N-dimethylamino) benzoate</dd><dt>PTU:</dt><dd>1-(2-pyridyl)-2-thiourea</dd><dt>Sr/Zn FAS Glass:</dt><dd>strontiumzincfluoroaluminosilicate glass that has a mean particle size of four microns and surface treated with MPTMS</dd><dt>ST-OX-50:</dt><dd>fumed silica OX-50 surface treated with MPTMS</dd><dt>TMBHPO:</dt><dd>1,1,3,3-tetramethylbutyl hydroperoxide</dd><dt>TS-530:</dt><dd>surface treated fumed silica or colloidal silica sold by Cabot Corp.</dd><dt>UDMA:</dt><dd>reaction product of 2-hydroxyethyl methacrylate with 2,4,4-trimethylhexane diisocyanate</dd> </dl></p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="p0042">In making the pastes in this and the following examples, all the monomers and any ingredients soluble in the resin mixture were first mixed together to make a homogeneous liquid mixture, and then the fillers (TS-530, ST-OX-50, Sr/Zn FAS glass, or barium glass) were blended into the liquid mixture to make the paste.</p><p num="p0043">An acid tolerant cement was made using the following composition.<!-- EPO <DP n="19"> --><tables id="tabl0001" num="0001"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" rowsep="0" colsep="0"><colspec colwidth="24mm" colnum="1" colsep="0" colname="col1"/><colspec colwidth="13mm" colnum="2" colsep="0" colname="col2"/><thead><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"><b>Base</b> </entry> <entry nameend="col2" char="." align="char" namest="col2" valign="top"/></row> </thead><tbody><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">BisGMA</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">17.10</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">GDM</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">8.55</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">HEMA</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">5.13</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">ETMPTA</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">3.41</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">CQ</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">0.21</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">MEHQ</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">0.007</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">ODMAB</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">0.41</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">PTU</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">0.68</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">TS-530</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">3.00</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">ST-OX-50</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">3.34</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Barium Glass</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">58.16</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" char="." align="char" namest="col2" valign="top"/></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables id="tabl0002" num="0002"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="26mm" colnum="1" colname="col1"/><colspec colwidth="15mm" colnum="2" colname="col2"/><thead><row><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"><b>Catalyst</b></entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" colsep="0" valign="top">BisGMA</entry><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2" colsep="0" valign="top">9.70</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" colsep="0" valign="top">GDM</entry><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2" colsep="0" valign="top">9.70</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" colsep="0" valign="top">HEMA</entry><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2"  colsep="0" valign="top">4.84</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1"  colsep="0"  valign="top">GDM-P</entry><entry nameend="col2"  rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2" colsep="0" valign="top">4.84</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" colsep="0" valign="top">ETMPTA</entry><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2" colsep="0" valign="top">3.24</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" colsep="0" valign="top">BHT</entry><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2" colsep="0" valign="top">0.05</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" colsep="0" valign="top">TMBHPO</entry><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2" colsep="0" valign="top">0.29</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" colsep="0" valign="top">CHPO</entry><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2" colsep="0" valign="top">0.58</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" colsep="0" valign="top">Water</entry><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2" colsep="0" valign="top">2.26</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" colsep="0" valign="top">TS-530</entry><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2" colsep="0" valign="top">3.00</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" colsep="0" valign="top">ST-OX-50</entry><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2" colsep="0" valign="top">3.34</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" rowsep="0" align="left" namest="col1" colsep="0" valign="top">Barium Glass</entry><entry nameend="col2" rowsep="0" align="center" namest="col2" colsep="0" valign="top">58.16</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="p0044">When the base paste and catalyst paste were mixed at 1:4 ratio, the mixed material hardened (or set) after 4 minutes and 20 seconds. The self-cured (dark-cured) material had a flexural strength of 80.7 MPa, and a radiopacitiy that was 170% of aluminum.<!-- EPO <DP n="20"> --></p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="p0045">An adhesion test to a dentin substrate was conducted on a commercial Panavia® F2.0 cementation system (Kuraray America, Inc., New York NY). The Panavia® F2.0 cementation kit comprised two self-etching Primers (Primer A and Primer B) and a resin cement. Primer A and Primer B were packaged in two separate plastic bottles. The cement consisted of two pastes (base and catalyst pastes) packaged in two separate individual syringes.</p><p num="p0046">The bonding strength was conducted as follows: The dentin surface was polished with wet 600 grit SiC paper. The primers were mixed at 1:1 ratio and the mixed primer was applied to dentin using a brush (separate acid etching was not necessary because the primers were self-etching). The pH of the mixed primers was 2.7 measured using pH paper. The primer was left on the dentin for 30 seconds and then the solvent was evaporated using compressed air for 2-3 seconds. A plastic mold with an inner diameter of 2.38 mm was securely placed over the primed tooth surface. The cement was dispensed from the syringes and homogeneously mixed. The mixed cement was condensed inside the mold and intimately bonded to the primer. The cement was self-cured (or dark-cured) for 24 hours. The bond strength was tested on an Instron mechanical tester using shear force. A bond strength of 11.7 MPa was obtained.</p><p num="p0047">The above bond strength test was repeated using the self-etching primers of Panavia® F2.0 and acid tolerant cement of Example 1 replacing the cement of Panavia® F2.0. The base paste and catalyst pastes of Example 1 were mixed in 1:4 (base paste: catalyst paste) ratio. A bond strength of 23.3 MPa was obtained. The enhanced bond strength over that obtained with Panavia® F2.0 primers and cement demonstrated the acid tolerant nature of the cement of Example 1 and enhanced compatibility between the acidic primers of Panavia® F2.0 and the cement of Example 1.</p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="p0048">An adhesion test to a dentin substrate was conducted on another commercial cementation system, Multilink® (Ivoclar Vivadent Inc., Amherst, NY). The Multilink® cementation kit comprised two self-etching Primers (Primer A and Primer B) and a resin cement. Primer A and Primer B were packaged in two<!-- EPO <DP n="21"> --> separate plastic bottles. The cement consisted of two pastes (base and catalyst pastes) packaged in separate barrels of a dual-barrel assembly. The bonding strength was conducted in the same manner as described in Example 2. The primers were mixed at 1:1 ratio and the mixed primer was applied to dentin using a brush (the pH of the mixed primers was 2.5 measured using pH paper). The primer was left on dentin for 15 seconds and then the solvent was evaporated using compressed air for 2-3 seconds. A plastic mold with an inner diameter of 2.38 mm was securely placed over the primed tooth surface. The cement was dispensed from the dual-barrel assembly and homogeneously mixed. The mixed cement was condensed inside the mold and intimately bonded to the primer. The cement was self-cured (or dark-cured) for 24 hours. The bond strength was tested on an Instron mechanical tester using shear force. A bond strength of 17.8 MPa was obtained.</p><p num="p0049">The above described bond strength test was repeated using the self-etching primers of Multilink® and the acid tolerant cement of Example 1 replacing the cement of Multilink® . The base paste and catalyst pastes of Example 1 were mixed in 1:4 (base paste: catalyst paste) ratio. A bond strength of 23.4 MPa was obtained. The enhanced bond strength over that obtained with Multilink® primers and cement demonstrated the acid tolerant nature of the cement of Example 1 and enhanced compatibility between the acidic primers of Multilink® and the cement of Example 1.</p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="p0050">An acid tolerant cement was made using the following composition:
<tables id="tabl0003" num="0003"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" rowsep="0" colsep="0"><colspec colwidth="28mm" colnum="1" colsep="0" colname="col1"/><colspec colwidth="13mm" colnum="2" colsep="0" colname="col2"/><thead><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"><b>Base</b></entry><entry nameend="col2" char="." align="char" namest="col2" valign="top"/></row></thead><tbody><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">UDMA</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">21.35</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">GDM</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">4.27</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">HEMA</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">2.85</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">CQ</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">0.142</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">MEHQ</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">0.014</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">EDMAB</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">0.285</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">PTU</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">0.59</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">TS-530</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">3.00</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">ST-OX-50</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">4.72</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Sr/Zn FAS Glass</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">62.78</entry></row></tbody></tgroup><!-- EPO <DP n="22"> --><tgroup cols="2" rowsep="0" colsep="0"><colspec colwidth="28mm" colnum="1" colsep="0" colname="col1"/><colspec colwidth="13mm" colnum="2" colsep="0" colname="col2"/><thead><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"><b>Catalyst</b></entry><entry nameend="col2" char="." align="char" namest="col2" valign="top"/></row></thead><tbody><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">BisGMA</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">5.56</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">GDM</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">7.29</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">HEMA</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">2.78</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">ETMPTA</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">3.47</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">GDM-P</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">12.16</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">BHT</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">0.05</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">TMBHPO</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">0.63</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">CHPO</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">0.63</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Water</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">2.43</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">TS-530</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">3.00</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">ST-OX-50</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">1.60</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Barium Glass</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="center" namest="col2" valign="top">60.40</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="p0051">When the base paste and catalyst paste were mixed at 1:4 ratio, the mixed material hardened (or set) after 4 minutes and 30 seconds. The self-cured (dark-cured) material had a flexural strength of 83.0 MPa, and a radiopacitiy that was 200% of aluminum.</p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="p0052">A commercial dental primer, OptiBond® Primer (Kerr Corporation, Orange, CA), was used for an adhesion test in combination with a commercial resin cement Nexus 2™ Dual-Syringe (Kerr Corporation, Orange, CA) or the acid tolerant resin cement composition of Example 4. OptiBond® Primer was a single primer (one-bottle) system and had a pH of 1.9. Resin cement Nexus 2™ Dual-Syringe utilized benzoyl peroxide/tertiary amine as its redox initiator system. The base and catalyst pastes of Nexus 2™ Dual-Syringe were packaged in the separate barrels of a dual-barrel assembly (1:1 ratio). The bonding strength was conducted as follows: the dentin surface was polished with wet 600 grit SiC paper, etched with a 37% Phosphoric Acid Gel Etchant (Kerr Corporation, Orange, CA) for 15 seconds. The surface was then rinsed with water and briefly dried with compressed air. OptiBond® Primer was applied to the etched tooth surface with agitation using a brush for 30 seconds and then the solvent was evaporated using compressed air for 3-5 seconds.<!-- EPO <DP n="23"> --> A plastic mold with an inner diameter of 2.38 mm was securely placed over the primed tooth surface. The Nexus 2™ Dual-Syringe resin cement was dispensed from the dual-barrel assembly fitted with a static mixer. The mixed cement was condensed inside the mold and intimately bonded to the primer. The cement was self-cured (or dark-cured) for 24 hours. The bond strength was tested on an Instron mechanical tester using shear force. A bond strength of 10.4 MPa was obtained.</p><p num="p0053">The above bond strength test was repeated using the OptiBond® Primer and acid tolerant cement of Example 4 replacing the resin cement Nexus 2™ Dual-Syringe. The base paste and catalyst pastes of Example 4 were mixed in 1:4 (base paste: catalyst paste) ratio. A bond strength of 26.0 MPa was obtained. The enhanced bond strength over that obtained with OptiBond® Primer + Nexus 2™ Dual-Syringe resin cement demonstrated the acid tolerant nature of the cement composition of Example 4 and enhanced compatibility between the acidic OptiBond® Primer and the cement composition of Example 4. An example of a dental cementation kit would include Phosphoric Acid Gel Etchant in this example, OptiBond® Primer in this example, and the acid-tolerant cement composition of Example 4.</p><p num="p0054">The above examples demonstrate the usefulness of the acid-tolerant resin cement in enhancing adhesion of acidic primer/adhesives to a tooth substrate due to improved compatibility between the resin cement and an acidic primer/adhesive.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="c-en-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>A two-part dental composition comprising
<claim-text>(A) 5% (w/w) to 99.5% (w/w) of at least one polymerizable monomer having at least one ethylenically unsaturated group selected from the group consisting of vinyl, acrylate and methacrylate;</claim-text><claim-text>(B) 0.01% (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one compound of structure
<chemistry id="chem0010" num="0010"><img id="ib0010" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="chem" file="imgb0010.tif" inline="no" he="31"/></chemistry>
where each of R1, R2, and R3 may be the same or different and is independently selected from the group consisting of H, alkyl, alkoxyl, aryl, acyl, alyl, pyridyl, -OH, alkenyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl, and heterocyclic structure containing O, S, or N;</claim-text><claim-text>(C) 0.01% (w/w) to 10% (w/w) of at least one hydroperoxide compound with at least one hydroperoxide group attached to a tertiary carbon;</claim-text><claim-text>(D) 5% (w/w) to 99.5% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler; and</claim-text><claim-text>(E) 0% (w/w) to 25% (w/w) of at least one component selected from the group consisting of a solvent, a photoinitiator, a stabilizer, an antimicrobial agent, and combinations thereof, wherein component (B) is in a first part of the two-part composition, component (C) is in a second part of the two-part composition, and components (A), (D), and (E) are independently in either the first part and/or the second part.</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>The dental composition of claim 1 wherein component (A) comprises 5% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of said at least one polymerizable monomer and component (D) comprises 5% (w/w) to 95% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>The dental composition of either claim 1 or claim 2 wherein each part of the two-part composition is independently selected from the group consisting of a liquid, a powder, and a paste.<!-- EPO <DP n="25"> --></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>The dental composition of claim 2 wherein the composition is a paste/paste composition comprising a first paste comprising component (A1) which comprises 10% (w/w) to 80% (w/w) of said at least one polymerizable monomer, component (B) and component (D1) which comprises 15% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler, and a second paste comprising component (A2) which comprises 10% (w/w) to 80% (w/w) of said at least one polymerizable monomer, component (C) and component (D2) which comprises 15% (w/w) to 90% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler, wherein components (A1) and (A2) of the composition are the same or different.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0005" num="0005"><claim-text>The dental composition of claim 1 wherein the composition is a powder/liquid composition comprising a liquid comprising component (A) which comprises 20% (w/w) to 99.5% (w/w) of said at least one polymerizable monomer and component (C), and a powder comprising component (B) and component (D) which comprises 50% (w/w) to 99.5% (w/w) of at least one finely divided filler.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0006" num="0006"><claim-text>The composition of any preceding claim wherein said at least one polymerizable monomer contains a functional group selected from the group consisting of a hydroxyl group, an acid group, and combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0007" num="0007"><claim-text>The composition of claim 6 wherein the hydroxyl-containing polymerizable monomer is selected from the group consisting of hydroxyethyl (meth)acrylate, hydroxypropyl (meth)acrylate, glycerol di(meth)acrylate, glycerol mono(meth)acrylate, 2,2-bis[4-(2-hydroxy-3-methacryloylpropoxy)-phenyl]-propane (Bis-GMA), and combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0008" num="0008"><claim-text>The composition of claim 6 wherein the acid group is selected from the group consisting of carboxylic acid, carboxylic acid anhydride, sulfonic acid, sulfinic acid, phosphoric acid, phosphoric acid derivative, phosphonic acid, and phosphonic acid derivative.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0009" num="0009"><claim-text>The composition of any one of claims 1 to 5 wherein said at least one polymerizable monomer is an elastomeric (meth)acrylate oligomer selected from the group consisting of elastomeric urethane (meth)acrylate oligomer and elastomeric polyalkyleneglycol (meth)acrylate oligomer.<!-- EPO <DP n="26"> --></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0010" num="0010"><claim-text>The dental composition of any preceding claim wherein each of R1, R2, and R3 of component (B) is independently selected from the group consisting of H, alkyl, phenyl, 2-pyridyl, 2-tetrahydrofufuryl, acetyl, and benzoyl.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0011" num="0011"><claim-text>The dental composition of any preceding claim wherein the hydroperoxide compound is selected from the group consisting of t-butyl hydroperoxide, t-amyl hydroperoxide, p-diisopropylbenzene hydroperoxide, cumene hydroperoxide, pinane hydroperoxide, p-menthane hydroperoxide, 1,1,3,3-tetramethylbutyl hydroperoxide, and combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0012" num="0012"><claim-text>The dental composition of any preceding claim wherein the filler is selected from the group consisting of inorganic metal, salt, oxide, nitride, silicate glass, bariumaluminosilicate glass, bariumaluminoborosilicate glass, strontiumaluminosilicate glass, bariumfluoroaluminosilicate glass, strontiumfluoroaluminosilicate glass, strontiumzincfluoroaluminosilicate glass, zincaluminosilicate glass, quartz, colloidal silica, precipitated silica, zirconia-silica, polymeric filler, polymerized composite filler with inorganic particles, and combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0013" num="0013"><claim-text>The dental composition of any preceding claim wherein the concentration of the filler provides a radiopacity of the composition that is at least 100% of aluminum.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0014" num="0014"><claim-text>The dental composition of any preceding claim wherein component (E) comprises an antimicrobial agent selected from the group consisting of benzakonium chloride, triclosan, alkyl 4-hydroxybenzoate, zinc oxide, a silicate glass powder containing silver and/or zinc, a zeolite containing silver and/or zinc ion(s), and combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0015" num="0015"><claim-text>The composition of any preceding claim wherein component (E) comprises a solvent selected from the group consisting of water, acetone, methanol, ethanol, isopropanol, methyl ethyl ketone, ethylene glycol, glycerin, and combinations thereof.<!-- EPO <DP n="27"> --></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0016" num="0016"><claim-text>A dental cementation or core buildup kit comprising
<claim-text>(I) a primer/adhesive composition having a pH less than 4.5, and</claim-text><claim-text>(II) a two-part dental composition of any preceding claim.</claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0017" num="0017"><claim-text>The kit of claim 16 wherein the two-part composition is provided in at least one prepackaged container.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0018" num="0018"><claim-text>The kit of claim 17 wherein the prepackaged container is selected from the group consisting of a syringe, a bottle, a capsule, an ampule, and a jar.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0019" num="0019"><claim-text>The kit of claim 17 wherein the prepackaged container is a dual-syringe assembly with each syringe of the dual-syringe assembly housing one part of the two-part composition.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0020" num="0020"><claim-text>The kit of claim 19 wherein each syringe in the dual syringe assembly has an opening and a static mixer is attached to the openings.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0021" num="0021"><claim-text>The kit of claim 17 wherein the prepackaged container is a single-dose assembly with the two parts of the two-part composition not in contact with each other.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0022" num="0022"><claim-text>The kit of any one of claims 16 to 21 wherein the primer/adhesive composition has a pH less than 3.0.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0023" num="0023"><claim-text>The kit of any one of claims 16 to 22 wherein the primer/adhesive composition comprises a polymerizable monomer containing at least one acidic functional group and at least one ethylenically unsaturated group, a solvent, and optionally one or more components selected from the group consisting of a polymerizable monomer containing at least one ethylenically unsaturated group without an acid functional group, a polymerization initiator, a finely divided filler, a stabilizer, and combinations thereof, wherein the ethylenically unsaturated group is selected from the group consisting of vinyl, acrylate, and methacrylate.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0024" num="0024"><claim-text>The kit of claim 23 wherein the acidic functional group is selected from the group consisting of carboxylic acid, carboxylic acid anhydride, sulfonic acid, sulfinic<!-- EPO <DP n="28"> --> acid, phosphoric acid, phosphoric acid derivative, phosphonic acid, and phosphonic acid derivative.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0025" num="0025"><claim-text>The kit of either claim 23 or claim 24 wherein the polymerization initiator is selected from the group consisting of a photoinitiator, a redox initiator, and combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0026" num="0026"><claim-text>The kit of any one of claims 16 to 25 further comprising a component selected from the group consisting of an acid etchant, a silane primer, a metal primer, and combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>