<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1120120-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1120120" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26554584" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010801"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1120120-A1" status="new" fvid="23192723"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1120120</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010801</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99944874-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99944874</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990928</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-28237898-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>28237898</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981005</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-29594798-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>29594798</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981019</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-9905298-W" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>9905298</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>19990928</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   9/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   9/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   9/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   9/20        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/4985      20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/4985      20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/502       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/502       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/517       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/517       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/519       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/519       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K  31/4985</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K  31/502</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K  31/517</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K  31/519</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K   9/00M18B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K   9/20P</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">TABLETEN DIE SICH UNMITTELBAR IN DER MUNDHÖHLE AUFLÖSEN</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">TABLETS IMMEDIATELY DISINTEGRATING IN THE ORAL CAVITY</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">COMPRIMES SE DELITANT IMMEDIATEMENT DANS LA CAVITE BUCCALE</invention-title><citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>See references of WO     0020033A1</text><sources><source name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>EISAI CO LTD</last-name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>EISAI CO., LTD.</last-name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Eisai Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>4-6-10, Koishikawa, Bunkyo-ku</street><city>Tokyo 112-8088</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>FURITSU HISAO</last-name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>KATO AKIRA</last-name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>OHWAKI TAKAYUKI</last-name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>YASUI MASANOBU</last-name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>FURITSU, HISAO</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>KATO, AKIRA</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>OHWAKI, TAKAYUKI</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>YASUI, MASANOBU</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>FURITSU, HISAO</last-name><address><street>Sunhills Yamanoi 503 1-6-2, Kasuga</street><city>Tsukuba-shi, Ibaraki 305-0821</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KATO, AKIRA</last-name><address><street>5-2-27, Matsushiro</street><city>Tsukuba-shi, Ibaraki 305-0035</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OHWAKI, TAKAYUKI</last-name><address><street>12-20, Aza Narumigo, Ohaza Haguro</street><city>Inuyama-shi, Aichi 484-0894</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>YASUI, MASANOBU</last-name><address><street>Dream Hanamizuki 1-212 5-13-8, Kamishibachonishi</street><city>Fukaya-shi Saitama 366-0052</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name><address><street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street><city>81925 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><pct-or-regional-filing-data ucid="JP-9905298-W" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>JP</country><doc-number>9905298</doc-number><kind>W</kind></document-id></pct-or-regional-filing-data><pct-or-regional-publishing-data ucid="WO-2000020033-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000020033</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000413</date></document-id></pct-or-regional-publishing-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country> <country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country> <country>GR</country> <country>IE</country> <country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention provides an intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet containing a phosphodiesterase
inhibitor having an effect of improving the erectile
dysfunction and a method for manufacturing the tablet. The
present invention also provides an intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet containing a slightly soluble
pharmaceutical agent having an improved solubility and a method
for manufacturing the tablet. That is, it is an intraoral
quickly disintegrating tablet containing a cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor and a saccharide, and a method for
manufacturing the tablet. Further, it is a method for
manufacturing an intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet,
which comprises dissolving a slightly soluble pharmaceutical
agent in an organic solvent or an aqueous organic solvent
together with a surfactant and/or a water-soluble polymer,
coating the solution on a filler or granulating it with a filler
to obtain molded products, mixing a saccharide with them, adding
an organic solvent, water or an aqueous organic solvent thereto,
followed by kneading, and subjecting it to a compression-molding.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="84" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="66"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>Technical Field</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to an intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet containing a phosphodiesterase
inhibitor having an effect of improving the erectile
dysfunction and to a method for manufacturing the tablet.</p><p num="0002">The present invention also relates to an intraoral
quickly disintegrating tablet containing a slightly soluble
pharmaceutical agent such as a phosphodiesterase inhibitor
having an improved solubility and to a method for manufacturing
the tablet.</p><heading>Prior Art</heading><p num="0003">It is reported in JP-B 9-503996 that pyrazonopyrimidinone
compounds having an inhibitory action to a cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase type V are useful for the therapy of erectile
dysfunction by means of oral administration. Further, 5-[2-ethoxy-5-(4-methyl-1-piperazinylsulfonyl)-phenyl]-1-methyl-3-n-propyl-1,6-dihydro-7H-pyrazolo[4,3-d]pyrimidin-7-one
(general name: sildenafil) belonging to the same
classification and being represented by the formula (I) surely
shows duration of its pharmaceutical effect at least for two
hours when it is orally administered (<i>British J</i>. <i>Urology,</i> 78, 
257-261, 1996.) and, therefore, there is a high possibility that
they are used for a highly practical drug therapy for erectile
dysfunction as a substitute for an injection therapy of
papaverine hydrochloride or prostaglandin E1 into corpus
cavernosum penis which has been carried out in an urological
field. In addition, with regard to a compound having an
inhibitory action to a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase type V,
there is disclosed a pyrazolopyrimidinone derivative
represented by the formula (II) {1,3-dimethyl-6-(2-propoxy-5-methanesulfonamidophenyl)-1,5-dihydropyrazolo[3,4-d]-pyrimidin-4-one}
in JP-A 7-70128 while, in WO 97/03675, there
are mentioned a compound represented by the formula (IV)
{(6R,12aR)-2,3,6,7,12,12a-hexahydro-2-methyl-6-(3,4-methylenedioxyphenyl)-pyrazino[2',1':6,1]pyrido[3,4-b]-indol-1,4-dione)}
and a compound represented by the formula (V)
{(3S,6R,12aR)-2,3,6,7,12,12a-hexahydro-2,3-dimethyl-6-(3,4-methylenedioxyphenyl)-pyrazino[2',1':6,1]pyrido[3,4-b]indol-1,4-dione}.</p><p num="0004">Further, in WO 93/07124, there is mentioned a compound
represented by the formula (III) {2-(4-carboxypiperidino)-4-(3,4-methylenedioxybenzyl)amino-6-chloroquinazoline}.
Furthermore, the compounds of a fused pyridazine type
represented by the formula (VI) mentioned in JP-A 10-114657 have
an inhibitory action to a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase type V
and are useful as therapeutic agents for erectile dysfunction.</p><p num="0005">It has been said that the number of the latent patients 
of erectile dysfunction are about 3,000,000 in Japan and are
about 20,000,000 in U. S. A. It has been also reported that,
while the number of the patients of erectile dysfunction in U.
S. A. are only 2-7% of the male population of younger than 50
years age, the rate increases together with aging and 15% of
males of fifties and a little over 30% of males of sixties are
suffering from this disease. Most of them are derived from
organic disorder and, taking the advent of an aging society in
near future into consideration, it may be concluded that oral
preparations of cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitors will
play a very big role in improving the quality of life (QOL) of
the patients suffering from erectile dysfunction.</p><p num="0006">However, when the conventional oral preparations
containing a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor are
administered, there is a possibility that, for example,
administration of tablets is difficult or that powdery or
granular agent adheres in the mouth or comes into artificial
teeth whereby a part of the preparation is dropped out since
aged people have a low swallowing ability.</p><p num="0007">When a consideration is made on the standpoint of the aged
people as such, there is a very high demand for "therapeutic
preparations for erectile dysfunction which can be easily taken,
easily swollen and easily handled" which is able to be "one of
the means whereby control of the carnal desire which is the
fundamental desire of human being can be embodied". Even in
ordinary and healthy adults, therapeutic preparations for 
erectile dysfunction which can be taken at any place without
water greatly contribute to their QOL.</p><p num="0008">On the other hand, intraoral quickly disintegrating
tablets have been known as the tablets which are quickly
disintegrated in the mouth and, since they can be easily taken
without water, they are recently receiving public attention as
a dosage form which is suitable for the people having
insufficient swallowing functions such as aged people and small
children.</p><p num="0009">It has been known that the intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablets can be prepared, for example, by the use
of wet powder. With regard to a method where wet powder is dried
without a tableting step whereupon the intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablets are prepared, there is disclosed for
example in JP-A 5-511543 for "a solid preparation which is
quickly disintegrated in the mouth comprising an active
ingredient, a saccharide selected from lactose and/or mannitol
and agar".</p><p num="0010">On the other hand, with regard to an intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet prepared by a compression-molding of wet
powder filled in a molding machine, there are disclosed, for
example, "a method for the manufacture of an intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet where a mixture containing a
pharmaceutical ingredient, a saccharide and water which is in
an amount of moisturizing the particle surface of the saccharide
is made into a tablet" in JP-A 5-271054; "an intraoral quickly 
disintegrating tablet comprising a pharmaceutical agent, a
saccharide, a sugar alcohol and a water-soluble polymer and
being prepared by moisturizing and molding" in JP-A 9-48726;
and "a wet-process tablet where a pharmaceutical agent is mixed
with a saccharide, a filler, etc., kneaded after addition of
water and/or organic solvent, filled in a mold and subjected
to a compression-molding and a method for manufacturing the
same" in JP-A 6-218028. Further, with regard to a method for
the molding of an intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet,
there is disclosed in JP-A 8-19589 for an invention concerning
"a method for the manufacture of a tablet where wet powder is
filled in a hole for molding the tablet and at least one side
of the wet powder in the hole is made into a shape of a tablet
by means of a metal mold for molding with a film for prevention
of adhesion and an apparatus for manufacturing the tablet".</p><p num="0011">However, there has been no report yet for a preparation
containing a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor and being
able to greatly contribute in such a QOL improvement and for
a method of manufacturing such a preparation.</p><p num="0012">Incidentally, in the case of a slightly soluble
pharmaceutical agent, it is not preferred to directly apply the
intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet using the above-mentioned
known means and the method for manufacturing the
tablet. That is because the low solubility of the slightly
soluble pharmaceutical agent delays the time for reaching the
effective blood level by oral administration and long time is 
required for achieving the pharmaceutical effect and also
because there is a risk that a sufficient pharmaceutical effect
is not achieved due to a low bioavailability.</p><p num="0013">In general, one of the most important factors among
various factors affecting the absorption of a pharmaceutical
agent via digestive tracts is its solubility and, especially
in the case of a slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent, it is
quite often that its dissolving rate determines the rate of
absorption. Various methods have been known for promoting the
solubility of a pharmaceutical agent and they may be roughly
classified into the following three. Thus, (1) to increase the
surface area of the pharmaceutical particles; (2) to use
amorphous or metastable crystals; and (3) to utilize various
types of salt or to add a solubilizer. As to the specific means
therefor, making the pharmaceutical agent into fine powder,
formation of a solvate and adsorption on the surface of a carrier
have been known for (1); selection of crystal polymorphism,
mixing/pulverization and preparation of a solid dispersion have
been known for (2); and preparation of an acidic salt or an
alkaline salt, addition of various pH buffers and/or
surfactants, etc. have been known for (3) and they are disclosed,
for example, in JP-A 59-14446 and JP-A 58-183615.</p><p num="0014">However, there has been no report yet for an intraoral
quickly disintegrating tablet containing a slightly soluble
pharmaceutical agent having an improved solubility as such and
for a method of manufacturing the tablet. One of the reasons 
therefor is that it is difficult for satisfying all of the
requirements for improving the solubility of the slightly
soluble pharmaceutical agent, for a quick disintegration in the
mouth and for ensuring a good touch on the tongue upon
disintegration. Many of the pharmaceutical ingredients acting
as a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor are the compounds
having a relatively low solubility and are within a category
of the slightly soluble pharmaceutical agents. Especially in
the weakly acidic to neutral regions which are the pH of the
stomach of the persons of anacidity and the pH ranging from
duodenum to small intestine which are the main sites for
absorption of the pharmaceutical agent, the solubility
significantly lowers. Solubilities at 37°C in the first
disintegration test solution (pH 1.2) and the second
disintegration test solution (pH 6.8) according to the Japanese
Pharmacopoeia are 2.52 mg/ml and 0.11 mg/ml, respectively for
sildenafil (citrate); 0.13 mg/ml and 0.0063 mg/ml, respectively,
for 4-(3-chloro-4-methoxybenzyl)amino-6-cyano-1-(4-hydroxypiperidino)-phthalazine
hydrochloride which is
represented by the formula (IX) among the phthalazine compounds
of the formula (VI); and 0.028 mg/ml and 0.0012 mg/ml,
respectively, for 4-(3-chloro-4-methoxyphenethyl)-amino-6-cyano-1-(4-hydroxypiperidino)phthalazine
hydrochloride
represented by the formula (X).</p><p num="0015">It is worried about that the slight solubility of the
cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor agent as such may result 
in a delay of the time reaching the effective blood level, a
lowering of the bioavailability and an expansion of the
dispersion thereof.</p><p num="0016">Accordingly, in a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor
having such a low solubility, it is desired that the solubility
of the effective ingredient in the intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet is improved so that the time for reaching
the effective blood level is made shorter and that the
absorption is improved so that the bioavailability is improved.</p><heading>Disclosure of the Invention</heading><p num="0017">With regard to a preparation containing a cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor, there has been a brisk demand for
the development of an oral preparation which is able to
contribute in the QOL of the patients suffering from erectile
dysfunction or, in other words, an oral preparation which can
be easily taken by aged people and can be taken without water
even by adults having a swallowing ability and a method for
manufacturing the preparation.</p><p num="0018">To be more specific, there has been a demand for the
development of an intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet
containing a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor having
quick disintegrating property and solubility in the mouth and
also having a strength for retaining its shape during
preservation and a method of manufacturing the tablet.</p><p num="0019">There has been also a demand for the development of an 
intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet containing a slightly
soluble pharmaceutical agent having quick disintegrating
property and solubility in the mouth, showing a good touch on
the tongue upon disintegration in the mouth and having a
strength for retaining its shape during preservation and a
method of manufacturing the tablet. Thus, it is expected that
the solubility of the pharmaceutical ingredient in the
intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet is improved whereby the
time for reaching the effective blood level is made short, the
time until expressing the pharmaceutical effect is made short
and absorption is improved so that the bioavailability is
improved.</p><p num="0020">However, although there are many aged people among the
patients suffering from erectile dysfunction and there have
been so many demands for an intraoral quickly disintegrating
tablet containing a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor and
to a method for manufacturing the tablet, such tablet and method
have not been developed yet. Such a situation is the same for
an intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet containing a
slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent with an improved
solubility and a method for manufacturing the tablet as well.</p><p num="0021">Under such circumstances, the present inventors have
carried out an intensive study for investigating an intraoral
quickly disintegrating tablet with an excellent disintegrating
property containing a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor
and a saccharide and a method for manufacturing the tablet and 
also for an intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet with an
excellent solubility containing a slightly soluble
pharmaceutical agent and a saccharide and a method for
manufacturing the tablet. As a result, it has been found that
the aimed object can be achieved by the constitutions as
mentioned below whereupon the present invention has been
accomplished.</p><p num="0022">The present invention is an intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet containing a cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor and a saccharide.</p><p num="0023">Further, the present invention is an intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet containing a cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor, a saccharide and a binder.</p><p num="0024">Furthermore, the present invention is an intraoral
quickly disintegrating tablet where a cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor and a saccharide are mixed, kneaded
with an organic solvent, water or an aqueous organic solvent
and subjected to a compression-molding and also a method for
manufacturing the tablet.</p><p num="0025">Still further, the present invention is an intraoral
quickly disintegrating tablet where a cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor and a saccharide are mixed, kneaded
with an organic solvent, water or an aqueous organic solvent,
filled in a mold and subjected to a compression-molding with
a film and also a method for manufacturing the tablet.</p><p num="0026">The cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor covers both 
that which is slightly soluble and that which is not slightly
soluble.</p><p num="0027">Still furthermore, the present invention is a method for
the manufacture of an intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet
where a slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent is dissolved in
an organic solvent or an aqueous organic solvent together with
a surfactant and/or a water-soluble polymer, then a saccharide
is mixed with a molded product prepared by a coating of a filler
or by a granulation together with a filler, an organic solvent,
water or an aqueous organic solvent is added thereto and the
mixture is kneaded and subjected to a compression-molding.
Here, the term "molded product" means granules, fine granules,
powder or the like and the molded product may be manufactured
using, for example, a fluidized bed granulator, a tumbling
granulator, an extrusion granulator or a spray-drying
granulator.</p><p num="0028">Further, the present invention is a method for the
manufacture of an intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet where
a surfactant and/or a water-soluble polymer are/is added to a
slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent followed by mixing, an
organic solvent, water or an aqueous organic solvent is added
thereto and the mixture is kneaded and subjected to a
compression-molding.</p><p num="0029">The term "slightly soluble" means that the substance is
slightly soluble in water, saliva, gastric juice, intestinal
juice, etc., and that can be measured by common tests. </p><p num="0030">Here, the surfactant and/or the water-soluble polymer
play(s) a role of improving the solubility whereby wetting of
the slightly soluble pharmaceutical ingredient <i>per se</i> with
water is improved. A method for improving the solubility of
the pharmaceutical agent in accordance with the present
invention is not only able to improve the solubility of the
intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet containing the
slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent and to ensure its quick
disintegration in the mouth but also able to ensure the good
touch on the tongue during the disintegration in the mouth.</p><p num="0031">During the course of the compression-molding in the
present invention, it is preferred for keeping the good molding
property of the tablet that the powder kneaded with an organic
solvent, water or an aqueous organic solvent is filled in a mold
and subjected to a compression-molding with a film.</p><p num="0032">Furthermore, the present invention is an intraoral
quickly disintegrating tablet with an improved solubility
containing a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor which is
a slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent and also is a method
for manufacturing the tablet.</p><p num="0033">Examples of the slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent in
the present invention are nifedipine, phenytoin,
nitrofurantoin, benoxaprofen, griseofulvin, sulfathiazole,
tacrolimus, piroxicam, carbamazepine, phenacetin and cyclic
GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor although the present invention
is not limited thereto. </p><p num="0034">Examples of the cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor
in the present invention are pyrazonopyrimidinone compounds
(JP-B 9-50396) represented by 5-[2-ethoxy-5-(4-methyl-1-piperazinylsulfonyl)phenyl]-1-methyl-3-n-propyl-1,6-dihydro-7H-pyrazolo[4,3-d]pyrimidin-7-one
(general name:
sildenafil) of the formula (I); pyrazolopyrimidinone compounds
represented by 1,3-dimethyl-6-(2-propoxy-5-methanesulfonamidophenyl)-1,5-dihydropyrazolo[3,4-d]pyrimidin-4-one
of the formula (II) (JP-A 7-70128);
(6R,12aR)-2,3,6,7,12,12a-hexahydro-2-methyl-6-(3,4-methylenedioxyphenyl)-pyrazino[2',1':6,1]-pyrido[3,4-b]indol-1,4-dione)
represented by the formula (IV) and
(3S,6R,12aR)-2,3,6,7,12,12a-hexahydro-2,3-dimethyl-6-(3,4-methylenedioxyphenyl)-pyrazino[2',1':6,1]pyrido[3,4-b]-indol-1,4-dione
represented by the formula (V) (WO 97/03675);
2-(4-carboxypiperidino)-4-(3,4-methylenedioxybenzyl)amino-6-chloroquinazoline
represented by the formula (III) (WO
93/07124); a fused pyridazine compound represented by the
formula (VI); and a pharmacologically acceptable salt thereof.</p><p num="0035">Examples of the compound shown by the formula (VI) are
4-(3-chloro-4-methoxybenzyl)amino-6-cyano-1-(4-hydroxypiperidino)phthalazine
hydrochloride represented by
the formula (IX) (JP-A 8-225541), 4-(3-chloro-4-methoxyphenethyl)amino-6-cyano-1-(4-hydroxypiperidino)phthalazine
hydrochloride represented by the formula (X),
4-[(3-chloro-4-methoxybenzyl)amino]-1-(2-hydroxy-7-azaspiro[3,5]-non-7-yl)-6-phthalazine 
carbonitrile
hydrochloride represented by the formula (XI), 1-(2-hydroxy-7-azaspiro[3,5]non-7-yl)-4-[(4-methoxy-3-methylbenzyl)amino]-6-phthalazine
carbonitrile hydrochloride
represented by the formula (XII), 1-[4-fluoro-4-(hydroxymethyl)piperidino]-4-[(4-methoxy-3-methylbenzyl)amino]-6-phthalazine
carbonitrile hydrochloride
shown by the formula (XIII), 4-[(3-chloro-4-methoxyphenethyl)amino]-1-(2-hydroxy-7-azaspiro[3,5]non-7-yl)-6-phthalazine
carbonitrile hydrochloride represented by
the formula (XIV) and 4-[(3-chloro-4-methoxybenzyl)amino]-1-(3-oxo-2-oxa-8-azaspiro[4,5]dece-8-yl)-6-phthalazine
carbonitrile represented by the formula (XV).</p><p num="0036">However, the cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor of
the present invention is not limited to those compounds only.</p><p num="0037">Usually, the compounding ratio of the cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor or the slightly soluble
pharmaceutical agent in the present invention to 1 part by
weight of the tablet is 0.0001-0.4 part by weight, preferably
0.005-0.3 part by weight or, more preferably, 0.01-0.25 part
by weight.</p><p num="0038">An average particle diameter of the cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor or the slightly soluble
pharmaceutical agent <i>per se</i> is 1-100 µm, preferably 5-70 µm and
more preferably, 5-50 µm.</p><p num="0039">With regard to the saccharide in the present invention, 
any saccharide may be used so far as it is soluble in water and
is stable and its examples are mannitol, sucrose, lactose,
trehalose, xylitol, erythritol, glucose, starch and dextrin.
In the present invention, each of them may be used solely or
two or more thereof may be used jointly.</p><p num="0040">The compounding ratio of the saccharide in the present
invention varies depending upon the type of the cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor or the slightly soluble
pharmaceutical agent but, usually, it is 2-50 parts by weight,
preferably 3-40 parts by weight or, more preferably, 4-30 parts
by weight to 1 part by weight of the cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase
inhibitor or the slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent.</p><p num="0041">An average particle size of the saccharide is 1-100 µ
m, preferably 5-70 µm or, more preferably, 5-50 µm.</p><p num="0042">The intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet of the
present invention may be compounded with a binder if necessary.</p><p num="0043">Examples of the binder are polyvinylpyrrolidone,
Macrogol, hydroxypropyl methylcellulose, methylcellulose,
hydroxypropyl cellulose, hydroxypropyl methylcellulose
phthalate, hydroxypropyl methylcellulose acetate succinate,
carboxymethycellulose sodium, cellulose acetate phthalate,
gum arabic, gelatin, methacrylic acid copolymer, carboxyvinyl
polymer, polyvinyl alcohol, alpha-starch and pullulan. In the
present invention, each of them may be used solely or two or
more thereof may be used jointly and the use of
polyvinylpyrrolidone is particularly preferred. </p><p num="0044">The compounding ratio of the binder in the present
invention to 1 part by weight of the tablet is usually 0.001-0.1
part by weight or, preferably, 0.005-0.05 part by weight, and
that may be appropriately increased or decreased so as to give
desired disintegrating degree and hardness. Incidentally, the
binder may be added in its powdery form to a mixture of the cyclic
GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor and the saccharide or may be
added after dissolving in the organic solvent, pure water or
the aqueous organic solvent.</p><p num="0045">The intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet according to
the present invention is a tablet which is quickly disintegrated
in the mouth after administration and is able to be easily taken
even without water. In addition to the above-mentioned
saccharide and binder, the intraoral quickly disintegrating
tablet may be compounded with conventionally used filler,
lubricant, disintegrating agent, sweetener and/or coloring
agent if necessary.</p><p num="0046">The intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet may be
prepared in such a manner that a saccharide and a binder are
mixed with a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor, then
conventionally used filler, lubricant, sweetener, coloring
agent, disintegrating agent, etc. are added thereto if
necessary, kneaded with an organic solvent, water or an aqueous
organic solvent, filled in a mold and subjected to a
compression-molding. The kneading and granulating operations
carried out by adding such auxiliary agents for making the 
preparation and by adding such a solvent may be conducted using
the conventionally used apparatus. For example, a fluidized
bed granulator, a tumbling granulator, an extrusion granulator
or a spray-drying drier may be used.</p><p num="0047">Examples of the filler are crystalline cellulose,
ethylcellulose, dextrin, various kinds of cyclodextrin (α-cyclodextrin,
β-cyclodextrin and γ-cyclodextrin) as well as
derivatives thereof and pullulan.</p><p num="0048">Examples of the lubricant are magnesium stearate, calcium
stearate, stearic acid and talc; examples of the sweetener are
aspartame, dipotassium glycyrrhizinate, white sugar, licorice,
saccharin and sodium saccharinate; and examples of the coloring
agent are yellow iron sesquioxide, yellow iron oxide, Yellow
#4 dye for food, Yellow #5 dye for food, (Yellow #4 dye for food
aluminum lake), red iron oxide, iron sesquioxide, Red #2 dye
for food, Red #3 dye for food and Red #102 dye for food. In
the present invention, each of them may be used solely or two
or more thereof may be used jointly.</p><p num="0049">Examples of the disintegrating agent are light silicic
anhydride, crystalline cellulose, cross povidone, lowly
substituted hydroxypropyl cellulose, cross carmellose sodium,
calcium silicate, magnesium metasilicate aluminate,
carboxymethyl cellulose, carboxymethyl cellulose calcium,
hydroxypropyl starch, carboxymethyl starch sodium, partially
α-starch and sodium alginate. In the present invention, each
of them may be used solely or two or more thereof may be used 
jointly.</p><p num="0050">In the present invention, an intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet may be manufactured in such a manner that
a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor is mixed with a
saccharide, a binder is further added thereto if necessary, the
mixture is kneaded with an organic solvent, water or an aqueous
organic solvent and the resulting wet powder is made into a form
of a tablet followed by drying.</p><p num="0051">In the present invention, an intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet may be manufactured in such a manner that
1) a slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent is dissolved in an
organic solvent together with a surfactant and/or a water-soluble
polymer, coated on a filler or granulated together with
a filler, a saccharide is mixed with the resulting granules,
fine granules or powder or that 2) a slightly soluble
pharmaceutical agent is mixed with a saccharide and a surfactant
and/or a water-soluble polymer, then a binder, a disintegrating
agent, a lubricant, a sweetener or a coloring agent is added
thereto if necessary and the mixture is kneaded with an organic
solvent, water or an aqueous organic solvent and, after that,
any of the above-mentioned mixture is filled in a mold followed
by subjecting to a compression molding.</p><p num="0052">Examples of the surfactant used here are sodium lauryl
sulfate, sorbitan fatty acid ester, polyethylene glycol fatty
acid ester, polyoxyethylene sorbitan fatty acid ester,
polyoxyethylene alkyl ether, polyoxyethylene polyoxypropylene 
alkyl ether, polyoxyethylene polyoxypropylene block copolymer,
polyoxyethylene alkyl phenyl ether, polyoxyethylene castor oil,
polyoxyethylene hydrogenated castor oil, polyoxyethylene
sorbitol fatty acid ester and polyoxyethylene glycerol fatty
acid ester. In the present invention, each of them may be used
solely or two or more thereof may be used jointly.</p><p num="0053">The compounding ratio of the surfactant in the present
invention to 1 part by weight of the slightly soluble
pharmaceutical agent is usually 0.0005-0.1 part by weight,
preferably 0.001-0.08 parts by weight or, more preferably,
0.001-0.05 parts by weight.</p><p num="0054">Examples of the water-soluble polymer are hydroxypropyl
methylcellulose, methylcellulose, hydroxypropyl cellulose,
hydroxypropyl methylcellulose phthalate, hydroxypropyl
methylcellulose acetate succinate, carboxymethyl cellulose
sodium, cellulose acetate phthalate, gum arabic, agar, gelatin,
sodium alginate, polyvinylpyrrolidone, aminoalkyl
methacrylate copolymer, methacrylic acid copolymer,
carboxyvinyl polymer, polyvinyl alcohol and Macrogol and, in
the present invention, each of them may be used solely or two
or more thereof may be used jointly.</p><p num="0055">The compounding ratio of the slightly soluble
pharmaceutical agent to the water soluble polymer in the present
invention is usually 0.001-0.6 parts by weight or, preferably,
0.005-0.1 part by weight of the water-soluble polymer to 1 part
by weight of the slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent. </p><p num="0056">Further, the concentration of the water soluble polymer
in the solution of the water soluble polymer is usually 0.1-40%
by weight or, preferably, 1-20% by weight.</p><p num="0057">The solution of the water soluble polymer may be any of
an aqueous solution, an organic solvent solution and an aqueous
organic solvent solution containing the above-mentioned water
soluble polymer.</p><p num="0058">The solvent which is used for the kneading stage in the
manufacturing process for the intraoral quickly disintegrating
tablet may be any of an organic solvent, pure water and an aqueous
organic solvent. Examples of the organic solvent or of that
used for the aqueous organic solvent are ethanol, methanol,
propanol and isopropanol and, preferably, ethanol. In the
present invention, one of them may be used solely or two or more
of them may be used jointly. The preferred compounding ratio
of the organic solvent in the aqueous organic solvent is usually
0.05-0.99 parts by weight, more preferably 0.2-0.98 parts by
weight or, further preferably, 0.25-0.98 parts by weight to 1
part by weight of the aqueous organic solvent.</p><p num="0059">In the molding of the wet powder, a lubricant may be
applied, if necessary, on upper and lower sides of the kneaded
mixture filled therein whereby an adhesion during the
compressing step can be prevented but, for the manufacture in
a more efficient and easier manner, it is preferred to use a
tablet manufacturing apparatus which is disclosed in JP-A
8-19589. Thus, a wet powder is filled in a mold for the tablet 
molding of the tablet manufacturing apparatus and at least one
surface of the wet powder in the mold is molded via an
adhesion-preventing film whereby an adhesion of the wet powder
to the metal mold for molding can be prevented and a quickly
disintegrating tablets are able to be manufactured in an
efficient manner.</p><p num="0060">The pressure applied upon the compression-molding of the
wet powder after kneading the mixture or upon tableting via an
adhesion-preventing film after filling in a mold in the present
invention is usually 2-150 kg/cm<sup>2</sup>, preferably 2-100 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> or,
more preferably, 3-50 kg/cm<sup>2</sup>.</p><p num="0061">The drying temperature after the compression-molding or
the tableting in the present invention is usually 15-80°C,
preferably 20-75°C or, more preferably, 30-70°C.</p><p num="0062">The tablet hardness of the intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet prepared by the manufacturing method in
accordance with the present invention is usually 1-15 kg/cm<sup>2</sup>,
preferably 1.5-10 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> or, more preferably, 2-6 kg/cm<sup>2</sup>. Time
for disintegration in the mouth of the intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet is usually 0.05-3 minute(s), preferably
0.05-1 minute or, more preferably, 0.1-0.5 minute.</p><p num="0063">The water content in the wet powder which is kneaded in
the present invention is 0.01-25% by weight, preferably 0.1-20%
by weight or, more preferably, 0.1-15% by weight of the kneaded
mixture.</p><p num="0064">The intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet according to 
the present invention may, for example, be manufactured as
follows. Thus, 75 g of sildenafil having the formula (I) which
is a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor and 340.8 g of
mannitol were well mixed in a mixer. To this mixture was added
an aqueous ethanol solution where 4.2 g of polyvinylpyrrolidone
K 30 were dissolved in 58.8 g of a 55% ethanol solution followed
by kneading for about 3 minutes. After that, the kneaded
mixture was subjected to a compression-molding using, for
example, a tablet manufacturing apparatus disclosed in JP-A
8-19589 by filling in a mold via a film with a pestle having
a diameter of 9.5 mm with a compressing pressure of 35 kg/cm<sup>2</sup>.
The molded product was dried in a drier of 50°C for about 2 hours
to manufacture intraoral quickly disintegrating tablets where
each tablet (280 mg) contains 50 mg of sildenafil.</p><p num="0065">Alternatively, 1.5 g of 4-(3-chloro-4-methoxybenzyl)amino-6-cyano-1-(4-hydroxypiperazino)phthalazine
hydrochloride having the formula (IX) which is a
slightly soluble cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor and
0.015 g of sodium lauryl sulfate were dissolved in 100 g of a
70% ethanol solution heated at 70°C. After that, 40.08 g of
mannitol were added thereto and the mixture was well mixed in
a mixer, followed by drying to give a powder. To this powder
is added an aqueous ethanol solution where 0.42 g of
polyvinylpyrrolidone K30 is dissolved in 5.88 g of a 55% ethanol
solution, and the mixture is kneaded for about 1 minute. Then
the kneaded mixture is subjected to a compression-molding using 
a compression tester (Shimadzu Autograph) with a compressing
pressure of 35 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> using a pestle having a diameter of 9.5
mm. The molded product is dried in a drier of 50°C for about
2 hours to manufacture the tablets where each tablet (280 mg)
contains 10 mg of the phthalazine compound having the formula
(IX).</p><p num="0066">In accordance with the present invention, it is possible
to manufacture an intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet which
contains a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor having an
improving effect for erectile dysfunction and has quick
disintegrating property, solubility and appropriate strength
in the mouth.</p><p num="0067">In accordance with the present invention, it is also
possible to manufacture an intraoral quickly disintegrating
tablet containing a slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent,
being characterized in a quick dissolving in the mouth and
having an appropriate strength.</p><p num="0068">Examples of the such effects will be shown as hereunder.</p><heading>Brief Description of the Drawings</heading><p num="0069">Fig. 1 is a graph showing the changes of the eluting rate
in the first solution as regulated by the Japanese Pharmacopoeia
concerning the phthalazine compound per se having the formula
(IX) and the intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet containing
the phthalazine compound.</p><p num="0070">Fig. 2 is a graph showing the changes of the eluting rate 
in the second solution as regulated by the Japanese
Pharmacopoeia concerning the phthalazine compound <i>per se</i> having
the formula (IX) and the intraoral quickly disintegrating
tablet containing the phthalazine compound.</p><p num="0071">Fig. 3 is a graph showing the changes of the eluting rate
in pure water concerning the phthalazine compound <i>per se</i> having
the formula (IX) and the intraoral quickly disintegrating
tablet containing the phthalazine compound.</p><p num="0072">Fig. 4 is a graph showing the changes of the eluting rate
in pure water concerning the intraoral quickly disintegrating
tablet containing the phthalazine compound having the formula
(X) and the tablet which is prepared by the conventional
manufacturing method.</p><heading>Experimental Examples</heading><heading>1) Good physical property of the tablets concerning the present
invention</heading><p num="0073">In a mixer, 1.5 g of a phthalazine compound having the
formula (IX) {4-(3-chloro-4-methoxybenzyl)amino-6-cyano-1-(4-hydroxypiperidino)-phthalazine
hydrochloride} and 40.08 g
of mannitol were well mixed, an aqueous ethanol solution where
0.42 g of polyvinylpyrrolidone K 30 was dissolved in 5.88 g of
a 55% ethanol solution was added and the mixture was kneaded
for about 1 minute. The kneaded mixture was molded using a
compression tester (Shimadzu Autograph) with a compressing
pressure of 50 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> using a pestle having a diameter of 9.5 
mm which was previously covered with a small amount of magnesium
stearate. The molded product was dried in a drier of 60°C for
about 3 hours to manufacture the tablets where each tablet (280
mg) contained 10 mg of the phthalazine compound having the
formula (IX).</p><p num="0074">When the physical property of the tablets was evaluated,
the tablet hardness was 5.59 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> (mean value of five tablets)
and the disintegrating time of the tablet was within 15 seconds
and, therefore, it is apparent that the tablets have a good
physical property as intraoral quickly disintegrating tablets.</p><p num="0075">Each one of the above tablets was subjected to an eluting
test in each 900 ml of the first liquid (pH 1.2), the second
liquid (pH 6.8) and pure water as regulated by the
Disintegration Test Method of the Japanese Pharmacopoeia
according to a puddle method (50 r.p.m.) of the Disintegration
Test Method of the Japanese Pharmacopoeia using 10 mg of the
phthalazine compound <i>per se</i> having the formula (IX) as a control.
Incidentally, the eluted amount of the phthalazine compound
having the formula (IX) was measured by means of a high-performance
liquid chromatography using an ultraviolet
absorptiometer (measured wave length=215 nm). Results of the
eluting test are shown in Figs. 1-3.</p><p num="0076">From Figs. 1-3, it is apparent that the intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet containing a cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor according to the present invention
shows quicker and better eluting characteristic as compared 
with the sole use of the agent <i>per se</i>.</p><heading>2) Good solubility of the tablet according to the present
invention containing a slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent</heading><p num="0077">4-(3-Chloro-4-methoxyphenethyl)amino-6-cyano-1-(4-hydroxypiperidino)phthalazine
hydrochloride having the
formula (X) has a very slight solubility and its absorption <i>in
vivo</i> is worried about.</p><p num="0078">Therefore, a pharmaceutical preparation where the
solubility of the phthalazine compound having the formula (X)
was improved was manufactured.</p><p num="0079">Thus, 16 g of the phthalazine compound having the formula
(X) and 1.6 g of sodium lauryl sulfate were dissolved in 1000
g of a 55% ethanol solution heated at 60°C (step A) . Separately,
a mixture of 198.4 g of mannitol and 8 g of light silicic
anhydride was subjected to a disintegration mixing using a
sample mill (step B). Then the mixed powder obtained in the
step B was subjected to a fluidized bed granulation using the
solution obtained in the step A to prepare granules, fine
granules or powder. Incidentally, temperatures of the sucking
and exhausting air during the fluidized bed granulation were
set at 70°C and 50°C, respectively.</p><p num="0080">After that, 21 g of the granules, fine granules or powder
containing the phthalazine compound having the formula (X)
were/was well mixed with 20.6 g of mannitol in a mixer, an aqueous
ethanol solution where 0.42 g of polyvinylpyrrolidone K 30 was
dissolved in 5.88 g of a 25% ethanol solution was added and the 
mixture was kneaded for about 1 minute. The kneaded mixture
was molded using a compression tester (Shimadzu Autograph) with
a compressing pressure of 28.5 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> using a pestle having a
diameter of 9.5 mm which was previously covered with a small
amount of magnesium stearate.</p><p num="0081">The molded product was dried in a drier of 60°C for about
3 hours to manufacture the tablets where each tablet (280 mg)
contained 10 mg of the phthalazine compound having the formula
(X).</p><p num="0082">When the physical property of the tablets was evaluated,
the tablet hardness was 5.53 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> (mean value of six tablets)
and the disintegrating time of the tablet was 18.2 seconds (mean
value of six tablets) and, therefore, it is apparent that the
tablets have a good physical property as intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablets.</p><p num="0083">One of the above tablets was subjected to an eluting test
in 900 ml of the first solution (pH 1.2) as regulated by the
Disintegration Test Method of the Japanese Pharmacopoeia using
a tablet containing 10 mg of the phthalazine compound <i>per se</i>
having the formula (X) as a control and the eluting rate was
evaluated using an ultraviolet absorptiometer (measured wave
length=240nm). Result of the eluting test is shown in Fig. 4.</p><p num="0084">Incidentally, the preparation which was prepared by the
conventional manufacturing method and used as a control was
prepared according to the following method.</p><p num="0085">Thus, 10 g of the phthalazine compound having the formula 
(X), 85.3 g of lactose and 20 g of corn starch were mixed and
subjected to a granulation by a tumbling granulator together
with a gradual addition of a 7% aqueous solution of
polyvinylpyrrolidone K 30 where 7 g of polyvinylpyrrolidone K
30 were dissolved whereupon a granulated product was obtained.
This granulated product was dried at 60°C for 20 hours and sieved
through a sieve of 24 mesh where 122g of a sieved product was
obtained, 7 g of cross carmellose sodium and 0.7 g of magnesium
stearate were added thereto and the mixture was made into
tablets using a pelletizer by a pestle having a diameter of 7
mm with a compressing pressure of 600 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> to manufacture the
conventional tablets where each tablet (130 mg) contained 10
mg of the phthalazine compound having the formula (X).</p><p num="0086">As shown in Fig. 4, the intraoral quickly disintegrating
tablet containing the phthalazine compound having the formula
(X) showed a significantly quicker eluting characteristic as
compared with the preparation which was prepared by the
conventional manufacturing method. In general, preparations
having a good solubility show little dispersion in an absorbing
property and, in addition, a higher bioavailability is often
achieved. It is apparent that the intraoral quickly
disintegrating tablet in accordance with the present invention
shows a better solubility than the preparation which was
prepared by the conventional manufacturing methods.</p><heading>Examples</heading><p num="0087">The present invention will now be further illustrated by
way of the following Examples although the present invention
is not limited thereto.</p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0088">In a mixer, 50 g of sildenafil which is a cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor having a formula (III) and 228 g
of mannitol were well mixed. To this mixture was added an
aqueous ethanol solution where 2 g of polyvinylpyrrolidone K
30 was dissolved in 15 g of a 5% ethanol solution, followed by
kneading for about 3 minutes. The resulting kneaded wet powder
was subjected to a compression-molding by a method mentioned
in JP-A 8-19589 (the kneaded mixture was filled in a mold for
the tablet molding of the pelletizer and at least one surface
of the wet powder in the above-mentioned mold was molded into
a tablet by a metal mold for the molding via an adhesion
preventing film), to manufacture tablets where each tablet
contained 50 mg of sildenafil.</p><p num="0089">Hardness of the tablet was about 5 kg/cm<sup>2</sup> and the
disintegrating time thereof in pure water was within 15 seconds.</p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0090">To 280 g of the kneaded mixture obtained in Example 1 were
added 1.4 g of a lowly-substituted hydroxypropyl cellulose and
0.1 g of magnesium stearate, followed by mixing. The mixture
was subjected to tableting by the same method as in Example 1,
to give tablets where each tablet contained 50 mg of sildenafil.</p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="0091">In a mixer, 10 g of a phthalazine compound having the
formula (IX) {4-(3-chloro-4-methoxybenzyl)-amino-6-cyano-1-(4-hydroxypiperidino)phthalazine
hydrochloride}, 267 g of
mannitol and 3 g of polyvinylpyrrolidone K 30 were well mixed.
To this mixture were added 40 g of 25% ethanol, followed by
kneading for about 1 minute. The resulting kneaded mixture was
subjected to the same operation as in Example 1 via an adhesion
preventing film, to manufacture tablets where each tablet
contained 10 mg of the phthalazine compound having the formula
(IX).</p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0092">Into 6000 g of a 25% ethanol solution heated at 50°C were
dissolved 100 g of the phthalazine compound having the formula
(X) and 15 g of polyoxyethylene hydrogenated castor oil (step
A). Separately, a mixture of 1240 g of mannitol and 100 g of
light silicic anhydride was disintegrated and mixed using a
hammer mill (step B). Next, the mixed powder obtained in the
step B was subjected to a tumbling granulation using a solution
prepared in the step A to prepare granules, fine granules or
powder. In a mixer, 147 g of the granules, the fine granules
or the powder prepared as such and 130 g of mannitol were well
mixed, a 55% ethanol solution where 3 g of hydroxypropyl
methylcellulose were dissolved therein was added and the
mixture was kneaded for about 3 minutes. The kneaded mixture
was molded by a means mentioned in JP-A 8-19589 (the kneaded
mixture was filled in a mold for the tablet molding of the 
pelletizer and at least one surface of the wet powder in the
above-mentioned mold was molded into a tablet by a metal mold
for the molding via an adhesion preventing film) using a pestle
having a diameter of 9.5 mm and with a compressing pressure of
45 kg/cm<sup>2</sup>.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet
comprising a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor and a
saccharide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The tablet as claimed in claim 1, which further
comprises a binder.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method for manufacturing the tablet defined in claim
1, which comprises mixing a cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase
inhibitor with a saccharide, kneading the mixture with an
organic solvent, water or an aqueous organic solvent and
subjecting it to a compression-molding.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method as claimed in claim 3, which comprises
filling the kneaded mixture in a mold and subjecting it to a
compression-molding with a film.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An intraoral quickly disintegrating tablet
comprising a difficultly soluble pharmaceutical agent and a
saccharide and further comprising at least one selected from
surfactant and a water-soluble polymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method for manufacturing the tablet as claimed in
claim 5, which comprises dissolving a difficultly soluble
pharmaceutical agent in an organic solvent or an aqueous organic
solvent together with at least one selected from a surfactant
and a water-soluble polymer, coating the solution on a filler
or granulating it with a filler to obtain molded products,
mixing a saccharide with them, adding an organic solvent, water
or an aqueous organic solvent thereto, followed by kneading,
and subjecting it to a compression-molding.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method for manufacturing the tablet as claimed in
claim 5, which comprises adding at least one selected from a
surfactant and a water-soluble polymer and a saccharide to a
difficultly soluble pharmaceutical agent, followed by mixing,
adding an organic solvent, water or an aqueous organic solvent
thereto, followed by kneading, and subjecting it to a
compression-molding.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing as claimed in claim 6,
wherein the molded products are granules, fine granules or
powder.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing as claimed in claim 6,
in which the granulation-molding is carried out, using a
fluidized bed granulator, a tumbling granulator, an extrusion
granulator or a spray-drying granulator.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing as claimed in claim 6
or 7, which comprises filling the powder kneaded with the
organic solvent, water or the aqueous organic solvent in a mold
and subjecting it to compression-molding with a film in the
compression-molding stage.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The tablet as claimed in claim 5, wherein the
slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent is a cyclic GMP
phosphodiesterase inhibitor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing as claimed in claim 6
or 7, wherein the slightly soluble pharmaceutical agent is a
cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The tablets as claimed in any of claims 1, 2 and 11,
wherein the cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor is 5-[2-ethoxy-5-(4-methyl-1-piperazinylsulfonyl)phenyl]-1-methyl-3-n-propyl-1,6-dihydro-7H-pyrazolo[4,3-d]pyrimidin-7-one
represented by the formula (I), 1,3-dimethyl-6-(2-propoxy-5-methanesulfonamidophenyl)-1,5-dihydropyrazolo[3,4-d]pyrimidin-4-one
represented by the formula (II), 2-(4-carboxypiperidino)-4-(3,4-methylenedioxybenzyl)amino-6-chloroquinazoline
represented by the formula (III),
(6R,12aR)-2,3,6,7,12,12a-hexahydro-2-methyl-6-(3,4-methylenedioxyphenyl)-pyrazino[2',1':6,1]pyrido[3,4-b]-indol-1,4-dione
represented by the formula (IV),
(3S,6R,12aR)-2,3,6,7,12,12a-hexahydro-2,3-dimethyl-6-(3,4-methylenedioxyphenyl)-pyrazino[2',1':6,1]pyrido[3,4-b]-indol-1,4-dione
shown by the formula (V) or a pharmacologically
acceptable salt thereof.
</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The tablet as claimed in any of claims 1, 2 and 11,
wherein the cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase inhibitor is a
compound represented by the following formula (VI) or a
pharmacologically acceptable salt thereof, i.e. a fused
pyridazine compound represented by the following formula or a
pharmacologically acceptable salt thereof.

in the formula, the ring C is an unsaturated 5- or 6-membered
ring which may have a hetero atom; n is 0 or an integer of 1-4;
R1 is a halogen atom, an optionally substituted lower alkyl group,
an optionally substituted lower alkoxy group, an optionally
substituted cycloalkyl group, nitro group, cyano group, a group
represented by the formula -NR2R3 (in the formula, R2 and R3 are
the same as or different from each other and each is hydrogen
atom, an optionally substituted lower alkyl group, an acyl group,
an optionally substituted arylalkyl group or an optionally
substituted heteroarylalkyl group. R2 and R3 may form a ring
together with a nitrogen atom bonded thereto. The ring may
further have a substituent), a group represented by the formula
-O-R9 (in the formula, R9 is hydrogen atom, an optionally
substituted lower alkyl group, an acyl group, an optionally
substituted arylalkyl group or an optionally substituted
heteroarylalkyl group), a group represented by the formula
-S-R10 (in the formula, R10 is hydrogen atom, an optionally
substituted lower alkyl group, an acyl group, an optionally
substituted arylalkyl group or an optionally substituted
heteroarylalkyl group), a group represented by the formula
(VII):

(in the formula (VII), R11 is hydrogen atom, a lower alkyl group
or amino group; and m is 0 or an integer of 1-2) or an optionally
protected carboxyl group, and when n is 2-4, R1 may independently
have the above-mentioned substituent; A is hydrogen atom, a
halogen atom, a group represented by the formula -NR4R5 (in the
formula, R4 and R5 are the same as or different from each other
and each is hydrogen atom, an optionally substituted lower alkyl
group, an acyl group, an optionally substituted arylalkyl group
or an optionally substituted heteroarylalkyl group, or R4 and
R5 may form a ring together with a nitrogen atom bonded thereto.
The ring may further have a substituent), an optionally
substituted aryl group, an optionally substituted heteroaryl
group, an optionally substituted arylalkyl group or an
optionally substituted heteroarylalkyl group; X is a group
represented by the formula -NR6- (in the formula, R6 is hydrogen
atom, an optionally substituted lower alkyl group, an
optionally substituted arylalkyl group or an optionally
substituted heteroarylalkyl group) or a group represented by
the formula -N=; Y is a group represented by -CO- or a group
represented by the formula -C (B) = (in the formula, B is hydrogen
atom, a halogen atom, a formula represented by the formula -NR7R8
(in the formula, R7 and R8 may be the same as or different from
each other and each is hydrogen atom, an optionally substituted
lower alkyl group, an acyl group, an optionally substituted
arylalkyl group or an optionally substituted heteroarylalkyl
group. R7 and R8 may form a ring together with a nitrogen atom
bonded thereto. The ring may further have a substituent), a
group represented by the formula -O-R12 (in the formula, R12 is
hydrogen atom, an optionally substituted lower alkyl group, an
acyl group, an optionally substituted arylalkyl group or an
optionally substituted heteroarylalkyl group), a group
represented by the formula -S-R13 (in the formula, R13 is hydrogen
atom, an optionally substituted lower alkyl group, an acyl group,
an optionally substituted arylalkyl group or an optionally
substituted heteroarylalkyl group), an optionally substituted
aryl group, an optionally substituted heteroaryl group, an
optionally substituted arylalkyl group or an optionally
substituted heteroarylalkyl group); and the formula (VIII) ------
means a double or single bond, provided that when the ring C
is a benzene ring, the case where n is 0 is excluded.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The tablet as claimed in claim 14, wherein the
compound represented by the formula (VI) is
<claim-text><claim-text>4-(3-chloro-4-methoxybenzyl)amino-6-cyano-1-(4-hydroxypiperidino)phthalazine
hydrochloride represented by
the formula (IX),</claim-text><claim-text>4-(3-chloro-4-methoxyphenethyl)amino-6-cyano-1-(4-hydroxypiperidino)phthalazine
hydrochloride represented by
the formula (X),</claim-text><claim-text>4-[(3-chloro-4-methoxybenzyl)amino]-1-(2-hydroxy-7-azaspiro[3,5]non-7-yl)-6-phthalazine
carbonitrile
hydrochloride represented by the formula (XI),</claim-text><claim-text>1-(2-hydroxy-7-azaspiro[3,5]non-7-yl)-4-[(4-methoxy-3-methylbenzyl)amino]-6-phthalazine
carbonitrile
hydrochloride represented by the formula (XII),</claim-text><claim-text>1-[4-fluoro-4-(hydroxymethyl)piperidino]-4-[(4-methoxy-3-methylbenzyl)amino]-6-phthalazine
carbonitrile
hydrochloride represented by the formula (XIII),</claim-text><claim-text>4-[(3-chloro-4-methoxyphenethyl)amino]-1-(2-hydroxy-7-azaspiro[3,5]non-7-yl)-6-phthalazine
carbonitrile
hydrochloride shown by the formula (XIV) or</claim-text><claim-text>4-[(3-chloro-4-methoxybenzyl)amino]-1-(3-oxo-2-oxa-8-azaspiro[4,5]decen-8-yl)-6-phthalazine
carbonitrile
represented by the formula (XV).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The tablet as claimed in any of claims 1, 2 and 5,
wherein the saccharide is at least one selected from mannitol,
sucrose, lactose, trehalose, xylitol, erythritol, glucose,
starch and dextrin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing as claimed in any of
claims 3, 4 and 12, wherein the cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase
inhibitor is 5-[2-ethoxy-5-(4-methyl-1-piperazinylsulfonyl)phenyl]-1-methyl-3-n-propyl-1,6-dihydro-7H-pyrazolo[4,3-d]pyrimidin-7-one
represented by the
formula (I), a compound represented by the formula (VI) or
pharmacologically acceptable salts thereof.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>