<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1333152-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1333152" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22041844" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030806"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1333152-A1" status="new" fvid="23822086"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1333152</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030806</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03250619-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03250619</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030131</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-6234202-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6234202</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020201</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/60        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/62        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/72        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/92        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/60L</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/62</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/72</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Eingekapselte Flüssigkeit zur Behandlung von Bohrlöchern</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Encapsulated liquid for well treatment</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Liquide encapsulé pour le traitement de puits</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="GB-2273484-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2273484</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5110486-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5110486</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5164099-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5164099</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5373901-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5373901</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5799734-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5799734</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6207620-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6207620</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERV INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERVICES, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Halliburton Energy Services, Inc.</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 1431</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73536</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BLAUCH MATTHEW E</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CASSIDY JUANITA M</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BLAUCH, MATTHEW E.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CASSIDY, JUANITA M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BLAUCH, MATTHEW E.</last-name><address><street>1125 Grand Boulevard</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73533</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CASSIDY, JUANITA M.</last-name><address><street>930 Woodside Drive</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73533</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Wain, Christopher Paul</last-name><address><street>A.A. Thornton &amp;amp; Co. 235 High Holborn</street><city>London WC1V 7LE</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states> </international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Liquid is encapsulated by first encapsulating a solid in a semipermeable membrane,
placing the capsule in a liquid which passes through the membrane into the capsule to
dissolve the solid, and then maintaining the capsule in a liquid until substantially all the solid
has been driven from the capsule, leaving liquid encapsulated therein. The capsules are
useful downhole for releasing their liquid contents for well treatment.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention relates to a method of encapsulating a liquid, and to use of the
encapsulated liquid for well treatment.</p> <p num="0002">Hydrocarbon production typically requires a variety of chemical treatments.
Normally injected downhole, the chemicals treat the producing formation or portions of the
well. When injecting chemicals in the liquid state, the operator must compensate for dilution
of the treatment chemicals by the carrier fluid. Further, certain well treatment chemicals,
such as acids, require the use of additional safety procedures to protect on-site personnel and
the environment.</p> <p num="0003">Various chemicals and drugs are commonly encapsulated as a means for controlling
the release of the encapsulated material. Current technology provides for the encapsulation
of solids, gels/colloids and frozen liquids. Free flowing liquids such as water or mineral
acids are not currently encapsulated in liquid form. Rather, encapsulation of free flowing
liquids generally requires absorption of the liquid on a solid prior to encapsulation.</p> <p num="0004">We have now devised a method of encapsulating free flowing fluids.</p><p num="0005">In one aspect, the invention provides a method of encapsulating a liquid, which
method comprises:
<sl><li>a) encapsulating a solid within a semi-permeable membrane to form a capsule;</li><li>b) placing said capsule in a first liquid capable of dissolving said solid whereby
said first liquid passes through said semi-permeable membrane and dissolves
said solid; and then either:</li><li>c) maintaining said capsule in said first liquid for a period of time sufficient to
permit concentration gradient driving forces to cause said liquid to displace
said solid from within said capsule such that substantially all of said solid is
removed from said capsule leaving said liquid in said capsule; or</li><li>d) maintaining said capsule in contact with a second liquid for a period of time
sufficient to permit concentration gradient driving forces to cause said second
liquid to displace substantially all of said solution of solid and first liquid from
within said capsule thereby producing a capsule containing primarily said
second liquid.</li></sl></p><p num="0006">The invention also includes a method treating the downhole region of a well, which
method comprises: placing an encapsulated liquid made by the method of the invention,
within the downhole region of a well; and releasing said liquid from the capsule.</p><p num="0007">The invention further includes a method of acid etching a fracture face located in a
subterranean production zone, which method comprises the steps of:
<sl><li>a) hydraulically fracturing a subterranean formation to produce a fractured
formation having at least one fracture face;</li><li>b) injecting capsules containing a liquid acid into said fractured formation while
maintaining hydraulic pressure on said fractured formation;</li><li>c) depositing said capsules in said fractured formation; and,</li><li>d) releasing said acid from said capsules thereby acid etching said fracture face.</li></sl></p><p num="0008">The present invention is particularly useful for acid etching a fractured production
zone. Following the fracturing of a production zone, well operators commonly acid etch the
fracture face to enhance hydrocarbon production rates. The acid etching process involves
injection of an acid downhole through the production pipe string into the fracture. Preferably,
the acid penetrates the entire length of the fracture. Once in the fracture, the acid reacts with
the fracture rock face creating channels in the rock face. Following the release of pressure on
the fractured zone, the resulting channels provide a flow path thereby increasing the flow of
hydrocarbons from the production zone to the borehole.</p><p num="0009">In accordance with the invention, the acid used in the etching process can be delivered
in a safe, environmentally friendly and undiluted manner to the exact location where acid
etching is desired. The invention achieves other advantages as well. For example, in prior
art practices, the acid detrimentally impacts the pipe string and casing. Repeated acid
treatments may require a "work over" or recompletion of the well to replace those portions of
the pipe string damaged by the acid. Encapsulating the acid in accordance with the
invention permits injection of the acid without exposing the pipe string to the corrosive
effects of the acid. Further, for example, the encapsulated acid can be delivered deeply into
the fracture prior to release.</p><p num="0010">The well treatment process of the invention also improves the performance and
economics of other well treatment chemicals. For example, encapsulation permits the
controlled release of well treatment chemicals at a desired downhole location. Therefore,
where the operator previously used a large quantity of chemicals to compensate for dilution 
or reaction during transport, the operator may now reduce the quantity of chemicals used.
Thus, as an added benefit, the operator will conserve resources, save money and reduce the
risk associated with handling chemicals at the well site.</p><p num="0011">The present invention provides a method of encapsulating a liquid within a semi-permeable
membrane. The method first encapsulates solid material within a semi-permeable
membrane to form a capsule. The capsule is placed in a liquid capable of passing through the
membrane and dissolving the solid. The solid is allowed to dissolve in said liquid. The
capsule remains in the liquid for a period of time sufficient to permit concentration gradient
driving forces to displace substantially all dissolved solid from within the capsule. The
resulting capsule contains primarily the liquid.</p><p num="0012">The present invention also provides an alternative method for encapsulating a liquid
within a semi-permeable membrane. This method encapsulates a solid within a semi-permeable
membrane to form a capsule. The capsule is placed in a first liquid capable of
passing through the membrane and dissolving the solid. Subsequently, the capsule containing
a solution of solid and first liquid is placed in contact with a second liquid. The concentration
and/or volume of the second liquid contacting the capsule, in comparison to the volume of the
solution within the capsule, creates an environment in which concentration gradient driving
forces will remove substantially all of the solution of first liquid and solid from the capsule.
As a result, the capsule contains primarily the second liquid.</p><p num="0013">The present invention also provides a method for treating a downhole region of a well
with well treatment chemicals or additives. The method encapsulates a solid within a semi-permeable
membrane to form a capsule. The capsule is placed in a liquid capable of passing
through the semi-permeable membrane and dissolving the solid. The solid is allowed to
dissolve in said liquid. The capsule remains in the liquid for a period of time sufficient to
permit concentration gradient driving forces to displace substantially all dissolved solid from
within the capsule. The resulting capsule contains primarily the liquid. The liquid containing
capsule is placed downhole at a preselected point. Following positioning, the encapsulated
liquid is released.</p><p num="0014">Additionally, the present invention provides an alternative method for treating the
downhole region of a well. This method encapsulates a solid within a semi-permeable
membrane to form a capsule. The capsule is placed in a first liquid capable of passing
through the membrane and dissolving the solid. Subsequently, the capsule containing a 
solution of solid and first liquid is placed in contact with a second liquid. The concentration
and/or volume of the second liquid contacting the capsule, in comparison to the volume of the
solution within the capsule, creates an environment in which concentration gradient driving
forces will remove substantially all of the solution of first liquid and solid from the capsule.
As a result, the capsule contains primarily the second liquid. Following placement at the
desired location, the second liquid is released from the capsules.</p><p num="0015">Further, the present invention provides a method for acid etching a fracture face
located in a subterranean production zone. The method provides for hydraulically fracturing
a subterranean formation to produce a fractured formation having at least one fracture face.
After fracturing the formation, capsules of liquid acid are injected into the fractured
formation while hydraulic pressure is maintained on the formation. Typically, a carrier fluid
is used to transport the capsules downhole to the fractured formation. After the capsules are
deposited in the fractured formation, hydraulic pressure is released from the formation. The
drop in hydraulic pressure allows the formation to close on and crush the capsules thereby
releasing the liquid acid. The acid subsequently reacts with and etches the fracture face.</p><p num="0016">In order that the invention may be more fully understood, reference will be made to
the accompanying drawings, wherein</p><p num="0017">Fig. 1 is an FTIR scan of unused Golpanol PAP and a scan of the fluid obtained from
the capsules of Example 3.</p><p num="0018">Fig. 2 is an infrared analysis of the fluid obtained from the capsules of Example 4.</p><p num="0019">As used herein, the term "downhole region" includes the subsurface portion of the
well bore, any subsurface production zones and the hardware associated with operating the
well. The term "free flowing liquid" generally describes a substance in a liquid phase,
capable of passing through a semi-permeable membrane. Examples of free flowing liquids
include acids and water. The term "liquid" includes single component liquids as well as
multi-component solutions.</p><p num="0020">The present invention provides methods for encapsulating free flowing fluids within a
semi-permeable membrane. In general, this aspect of the invention provides a method for
encapsulating fluids capable of passing through a semi-permeable membrane. A non-exclusive
list of liquids suitable for encapsulation, according to the invention, includes:
water, hydrochloric acid, sulfuric acid, phosphoric acid, nitric acid, formic acid, acetic acid,
sulfamic acids, citric acid, glycolic acid, maleic acid, fumeric acid, alcohols, thiols, 
polyphosphonic acid, polyphosphonate, scale inhibitors, corrosion inhibitors, fertilizers,
pharmaceuticals, detergents, cement retarders and accelerators, food additives, pesticides,
dyes, pigments, paints, pheromones, dimethyl formamide, acetone, acetonitrile, ethers,
perfumes, cross-linking agents and polymerization initiators.</p><p num="0021">Semi-permeable membranes suitable for use in the current invention may be formed
from materials including but not limited to: partially to fully hydrogenated vegetable oil,
such as tristearin, latex, gelatins, carageenans, polyethylene, polypropylene, polyisobutylene,
a copolymer of vinyl chloride and vinylidene chloride, a copolymer of vinylidene chloride
and an ester of an unsaturated carboxylic acid or a copolymer of ethylene and an unsaturated
carboxylic acid.</p><p num="0022">The methods of the current invention use a solid encapsulated within a semi-permeable
membrane as a starting material. A non-limiting list of solids suitable for use in
the invention include: mineral salts such as sodium chloride and potassium chloride, calcium
chloride, metal sulfates, metal nitrates, such as calcium nitrate and calcium sulfate, citric acid,
powdered metals such as copper and aluminum, organic salts such as metal salts of
carboxylic acids, citrates or formates, alcohols such as ethoxylated alcohols, mono-, di- and
polysaccharides, sodium hydroxide, and ammonium bi-fluoride.</p><p num="0023">Processes for encapsulating solids are well known. For example, encapsulated solids
suitable for use in the current invention are readily available from the Balchem Corporation,
P.O. Box 175, Slate Hill, NY 10973 (Balchem). Currently, Balchem markets encapsulated
citric acid under the brand name CAP-SHURE®. Balchem markets several forms of CAP-SHURE®
which are suitable for use in the current invention. Three versions currently
available are CAP-SHURE® CITRIC ACID C-165-85, CAP-SHURE® CITRIC ACID C-165-63
and CAP-SHURE® CITRIC ACID C-150-50. Each product has a semi-permeable
membrane formed from partially hydrogenated vegetable oil. The semi-permeable
membrane has a melting point ranging from 59°C to 70°C. In the C-165-85 product, the
membrane comprises 13-17% by weight of the total capsule. The C-165-63 product has a
membrane comprising 35-39% by weight of the total capsule and in the C-150-50, the
membrane comprises 48-52% by weight of the total capsule. The C-165-85 has a particle
size wherein no more than 2% of the particles are retained on a #20 mesh screen (USSS).
The C-165-63 has a particle size wherein no more than 2% of the particles are retained on a
#16 mesh screen (USSS). The C-150-50 has a particle size wherein no more than 2% of the 
particles are retained on a #10 mesh screen (USSS). Therefore, in each instance about 98%
of the particles passed through the respective screen. Other encapsulated solids marketed by
Balchem suitable for use in the current invention include sodium chloride and fumeric acid,
marketed under the trade name Bakeshure FT.</p><p num="0024">Halliburton Company also markets encapsulated solids suitable for use as a starting
material in the current invention including encapsulated solids marketed in association with
the trade names "Optiflo II," "Optiflo III," "Optiflo HTE" and "Optiflo LT."</p><p num="0025">The process steps, materials and parameters necessary to provide the desired
encapsulated liquid are as follows:</p><heading>A. Solid/Liquid Exchange</heading><p num="0026">One method for encapsulating a liquid according to the current invention comprises
the steps of: 1) placing an encapsulated solid in the liquid to be encapsulated; 2) allowing the
liquid to penetrate the semi-permeable membrane and subsequently dissolve the solid; and, 3)
maintaining sufficient volume and concentration of the liquid to establish the concentration
gradient necessary to drive substantially all of the solid from the interior of the capsule to the
exterior. This method yields a capsule containing substantially only the liquid. Preferably,
the final concentration of the liquid within the capsule will be greater than 50% of the
concentration of the liquid used during the exchange process. For example, if a 30% HCl
solution is used to dissolve the solid, then the capsule will contain a solution of at least 15%
HCl.</p><p num="0027">The substantially complete transfer of solid from the interior to the exterior of the
capsule is a result of concentration gradient driving forces. The principal of "concentration
gradient driving forces" describes the transfer of atoms, ions and molecules across a semi-permeable
membrane due to diffusion from a concentrated region to a substantially dilute
region. This phenomenon is based on Fick's first law of diffusion described by the formula:
<i>J</i> = <i>-X</i>(<i>∂C</i>/<i>∂x</i>). In the formula, J is the movement or flux of a substance in the direction that
eliminates the concentration gradient (<i>∂C</i>/<i>∂x</i>). The rate of the movement is proportional to
the magnitude, <i>X</i>, of its gradient. Gradient diffusion can be described by osmosis or dialysis,
depending on the size of the diffusing substance and the membrane pore size. Temperature,
concentration gradient, diffusion constants, membrane thickness and membrane area will
affect permeation and diffusion rates. In the current invention, the preferred volume of liquid
on the exterior of the capsule is sufficiently large so as to dissolve and draw substantially all 
of the solids to the exterior of the capsule. If necessary to achieve complete exchange,
multiple changes of the batch solution, large liquid to capsule volumes or continuous
replacement of the desired liquid will move the exchange toward completion.</p><p num="0028">The time period and temperature necessary for each of the steps in the current
invention will vary depending upon the solubility of the encapsulated solid, the porosity of
the semi-permeable membrane, the concentration of the liquid and the temperature. In
general, the temperature for carrying out the exchange may range from about room
temperature to slightly lower than the melting point of the semi-permeable membrane. The
time period necessary for the exchange can be calculated based on the temperature, the pore
size of the membrane and the solubility parameter of the solid in the liquid.</p><p num="0029">In this embodiment of the current invention, the encapsulated solid must be soluble in
the liquid to be encapsulated. Additionally, the encapsulating material must have a pore size
sufficient to permit penetration by the liquid and transfer of the dissolved solid to the exterior
of the capsule. Further, the concentration and/or volume of the liquid must be sufficient to
permit concentration gradient driving forces to drive substantially all solid material to the
exterior of the capsule. Finally, the temperature and time period necessary to complete the
exchange of solid material for the liquid will vary depending on the composition of the solid
material, the concentration and volume of the liquid and the pore size of the encapsulating
material. One skilled in the art will have the requisite understanding of solubility parameters
and semi-permeable membranes necessary to readily establish these operating parameters.</p><heading>Example 1 - Single Step Encapsulation of a Mineral Acid</heading><p num="0030">This example demonstrates the single step, solid/liquid exchange process for
encapsulating a mineral acid. The process requires a solid, soluble in the desired mineral
acid, as the encapsulated solid. In this case, an encapsulated citric acid marketed by
Balchem under the trade name CAP-SHURE® provides an adequate starting material.</p><p num="0031">Twenty-two grams of CAP-SHURE® 165-85 and 75 grams of reagent grade
hydrochloric acid ("HCl") (approximately 37.8%) were combined in a glass jar. Added to
this mixture was 0.1 ml of Sperse-All-M dispersant available from the Halliburton Company.
Following mixing, nearly all of the encapsulated citric acid material remained at the bottom
of the jar. A few capsules floated after mixing; however, these capsules were likely
damaged. After 16 days at room temperature, the majority of the capsules remained at the
bottom of the jar. The capsules were filtered, rinsed with water and then rinsed with acetone. 
After drying, an attempt was made to squeeze the acid out of the capsules by applying
mechanical force. Although the capsules were wet, insufficient liquid was produced for
analysis. Therefore, individual capsules were placed on a calcite spar surface and crushed.
Following crushing, production of CO<sub>2</sub> and fizzing were noted indicating the presence of
acid. However, the lack of buoyancy indicates that the capsules were not likely filled with
acid.</p><p num="0032">This Example demonstrates that the HCl will penetrate the encapsulating material and
dissolve the citric acid. The concentration and/or volume of the hydrochloric acid contacting
the encapsulated solid created an environment in which the concentration gradient favored
elimination of the citric acid from the interior of the capsule.</p><heading>Example 2 - Heating Improves the Exchange Efficiency in Single Step Exchange
Process</heading><p num="0033">This Example demonstrates the improved exchange efficiency achieved by heating
the capsules during the exchange process.</p><p num="0034">19.6 grams of CAP-SHURE® C165-85, 0.1 ml of Sperse-All-M surfactant and 87.6
grams of HCl (reagent grade 36.63%) were combined in a glass jar. The resulting mixture
was heated for three days at 52°C (125°F). At the end of three days, approximately 50% of
the capsules were floating. The floating capsules were decanted, isolated using a büchner
funnel, washed with distilled water, washed with acetone and allowed to air dry. After
drying, the capsules were placed in a 5 cc glass syringe and the liquid was mechanically
forced out of the capsules by crushing. The final concentration of HCl removed from the
capsules was 23.85%. Thus, the capsules contained 65% of the HCl present in the initial HCl
solution.</p><p num="0035">This Example demonstrates that heating the capsules enhances the dissolution of the
citric acid in the HCl and improves the exchange rate. Although the concentration of HCl
within the capsule has been reduced, the concentration is sufficient for downhole applications
such as acid etching of a fracture face.</p><heading>Example 3 - Single Step Encapsulation of a Corrosion Inhibitor</heading><p num="0036">Twenty-one grams of CAP-SHURE® C 165-85 and 38.4 grams of a propargyl alcohol
propoxylated, were combined in a glass jar. Propargyl alcohol propoxylated (CAS number
7732-18-5) is a corrosion inhibitor available from BASF under the trade name Golpanol PAP.
Initially, the capsules remained at the bottom of the jar. After standing at room temperature 
for 17 days, the buoyant capsules were isolated using a büchner funnel, washed with acetone
and dried. The dried capsules were placed in a 5 cc glass syringe and crushed with the
plunger. After crushing, a light yellow fluid was collected and analyzed using FTIR analysis.
For comparison, an unused Golpanol PAP sample (dark yellow) was also analyzed using
FTIR analysis. Fig. 1, Scan A is the scan generated by the unused sample of Golpanol PAP
and Fig. 1, Scan B is the scan generated by the fluid obtained from the capsules. A
comparison of the FTIR scans indicates that fluid obtained from the capsules is Golpanol
PAP. The extra peaks found at approximately 2070 and 1727 cm <sup>-1</sup> in Scan B are possibly
due to encapsulant.</p><p num="0037">Thus, the current invention provides a suitable mechanism for encapsulating organic
compounds useful as corrosion inhibitors.</p><p num="0038">While the foregoing examples describe the encapsulation of a mineral acid and a
corrosion inhibitor, the inventive process will work equally well with any solid/liquid system
in which the solid is soluble in the liquid and in which the solution of dissolved solid in the
desired liquid will pass through the semi-permeable membrane. For example, citric acid is
also soluble in a solution of phosphonic acids or esters such as polyphosphonic acid or
polyphosphonate, common well treatment chemicals used to prevent the precipitation of scale
on the interior walls of a pipe string. Therefore, the foregoing method will be able to produce
capsules containing polyphosphonic acid or polyphosphonate. The variables of temperature
and treatment time will vary depending on the encapsulated solid, the desired liquid and the
pore size of the encapsulating material; however, one familiar with the dissolution rates of the
solid in the liquid will readily determine the proper operating conditions with only minimal
experimentation.</p><heading>B. Solid/Liquid Exchange &amp; Liquid/Liquid Exchange</heading><p num="0039">An alternative embodiment of the current invention comprises the steps of: 1) placing
an encapsulated solid in a first liquid capable of dissolving the solid; 2) allowing the first
liquid to dissolve the solid; 3) placing the capsules containing the solution of first liquid and
solid in a second liquid; and 4) maintaining sufficient volume and/or concentration of the
liquid to establish the concentration gradient necessary to drive substantially all of the solid
from the interior of the capsule to the exterior. The resulting product is a capsule containing
substantially only the second liquid. </p><p num="0040">In this process, the initial liquid can be, for example, water, hydrochloric acid, sulfuric
acid, phosphoric acid, nitric acid, formic acid, acetic acid, sulfamic acids, citric acid, glycolic
acid, maleic acid, fumeric acid, corrosion inhibitors, scale inhibitors, fertilizers,
pharmaceuticals, detergents, cement retarders and accelerators, food additives, pesticides,
dyes, pigments, paints, pheromones and perfumes.</p><p num="0041">The second liquid used in step 3) will vary depending on the initial fluid. In general,
the second liquid may include, for example: water, hydrochloric acid, sulfuric acid,
phosphoric acid, nitric acid, formic acid, acetic acid, sulfamic acids, citric acid, glycolic acid,
maleic acid, fumeric acid, alcohols, thiols, polyphosphonic acid, polyphosphonate, scale
inhibitors, corrosion inhibitors, fertilizers, pharmaceuticals, detergents, cement retarders and
accelerators, food additives, pesticides, dyes, pigments, paints, pheromones, dimethyl
formamide, acetone, acetonitrile, ethers, perfumes, cross-linking agents and polymerization
initiators. The term polymerization initiators includes, but is not limited to peroxides such as
benzoyl peroxide, Lewis acids and nitriles compounds. Cross-linking agents includes
compounds such as titanates, borates and zirconates as commonly used in the art.</p><p num="0042">In accordance with this embodiment, step 2) can be stopped prior to removing
substantially all solid from the capsule. Preferably, step 2) proceeds at least until the
resulting solution reaches equilibrium between the solid and the first liquid. The capsule
containing a solution of the first liquid and dissolved solid will be transferred to the second
liquid. However, if an undesirable reaction may occur between the second liquid and the
solid, step 2) may be allowed to progress to the point where concentration gradient driving
forces have removed substantially all of the solid from the capsule.</p><p num="0043">As in the solid/liquid exchange described in connection with the first embodiment set
forth above, the time period and temperature necessary for each of the above steps will vary
depending upon the solubility of the encapsulated solid, the porosity of the semi-permeable
membrane, the concentration of the liquid, the temperature and the concentration of the
second liquid. In general, the temperature for carrying out the exchange may range from
about room temperature to slightly lower than the melting point of the semi-permeable
membrane. For the solid/liquid exchange, the requisite time period can be calculated based
on the temperature, the pore size of the membrane and the solubility parameter of the solid in
the liquid. The time period necessary for the liquid/liquid exchange can be calculated based
on the temperature, pore size, diffusion rate, concentration gradient and the partition 
coefficients of the two liquids. Further, if necessary to achieve complete exchange, multiple
changes of the batch solution, large liquid to capsule volumes or continuous replacement of
desired liquid will move the exchange toward completion.</p><p num="0044">One advantage of this particular embodiment of the invention is the ability to
encapsulate a liquid incapable of dissolving the encapsulated solid. In such instances, the
first liquid is chosen for its ability to dissolve the solid and its miscibility with the second
liquid. When using water as the first liquid, this process also permits recovery and recycling
of the solid from the first liquid. Another advantage of the liquid/liquid exchange process is
the ability to decouple the first exchange step from the second exchange step in time and
space. Another advantage of the liquid/liquid process is a reduction in overall time to provide
the desired encapsulated liquid as compared to the single liquid process.</p><heading>Example 4 - Two Step Exchange of Citric Acid for Methanol</heading><p num="0045">Citric acid has a low solubility constant in methanol. Therefore, a solid/liquid
exchange of methanol for citric acid will take an inordinate amount of time and may not
result in complete exchange of methanol for citric acid. To obtain encapsulated methanol, the
preferred method will be the solid/liquid &amp; liquid/liquid exchange process of the current
invention. As is well known, citric acid is very soluble in water and methanol is miscible
with water. Therefore, the solid/liquid &amp; liquid/liquid exchange method of the current
invention will provide a mechanism for encapsulating methanol in a reasonable period of
time.</p><p num="0046">Capsules containing citric acid (CAP-SHURE® C 165-85) were initially immersed in
water at room temperature for a period of time sufficient to completely exchange the citric
acid for water. Approximately 10 ml of water filled capsules, by volume, were placed in a
250 ml graduated cylinder containing methanol. The level of methanol was brought up to the
250 ml mark in the graduated cylinder. A layer of presumably defective capsules rose to the
surface of the methanol. The majority of the capsules remained at the bottom of the cylinder.
Over the next 24 hours, the graduated cylinder was periodically inverted. After
approximately 24 hours, some of the capsules were decanted and isolated using a büchner
funnel. The separated capsules were rinsed with acetone and air-dried. The fluid removed
from the capsules was analyzed using infrared analysis. The resulting scan, provided in Fig.
2, correlates well with reagent grade methanol except for some additional water peaks. These
peaks likely resulted from trace concentrations of water remaining in the capsules. </p><heading>Example 5 - Two Step Exchange of Citric Acid for Hydrochloric Acid</heading><p num="0047">The following is an example of the solid/liquid exchange &amp; liquid/liquid exchange
process for producing a capsule containing HCl.</p><p num="0048">Solid citric acid encapsulated in hydrogenated vegetable oil was obtained from
Balchem. A sufficient quantity of capsules was placed in tap water to form a slurry. The
slurry was maintained for several days until reaching equilibrium as evidenced by the
capsules having a density less than that of the aqueous phase. Heating the slurry accelerated
the equilibration process; however, the heating step may be omitted. The resulting water
containing capsules were transferred to a solution of concentrated HCl (31.45%). The
capsules were maintained in the concentrated HCl for 24 hours. Upon removal from the HCl,
the capsules were washed with deionized water and dried. When ruptured on a calcite spar
surface, the released fluid was observed to react with the calcite spar thereby demonstrating
the encapsulation of the HCl. As a control, capsules obtained from the water slurry prior to
transfer to the HCl were also ruptured to release the contained fluid on the calcite spar
surface. The fluid released from these capsules did not react with the calcite spar.</p><heading>II. Methods of Chemically Treating a Downhole Region of a Well</heading><p num="0049">The present invention also provides improved methods for chemically treating a
downhole region of a well. A non-exclusive list of common well treatment chemicals and
additives includes: acid etching agents, scale inhibitors, corrosion inhibitors, biocides,
paraffin and asphaltene inhibitors, H<sub>2</sub>S scavengers, oxygen scavengers, demulsifiers, clay
stabilizers; surfactants, acidizing agents and mixtures thereof. The controlled downhole
release of these chemicals will significantly improve their functionality.</p><p num="0050">The process of chemically treating a well according to the current invention entails
encapsulating the desired well treatment chemicals according to one of the methods described
in the preceding section of this disclosure. Following encapsulation, the capsules of well
treatment chemicals are blended into a carrier fluid capable of transporting the capsules to a
desired location downhole. Carrier fluids suitable for use in the current invention include
fracturing fluids as well as acidizing fluids, gelled or non-gelled fluids, gravel pack fluids,
completion fluids and work over fluids. The methods currently used for blending solids and
slurries at the wellhead will provide satisfactory blending of the capsules and the carrier fluid.
For example, devices such as slurry processors and blenders are suitable for blending the
capsules into a carrier fluid. Blending will typically be achieved by feeding the capsules to 
the blender or processor by means of an auger feed or from a liquid storage tank containing a
slurry of capsules. If desired, capsules may be suspended in either a gel carrier or an inert
fluid designed to prevent settling. To ensure a consistent concentration of capsules
throughout the gel or inert fluid, the specific gravity of the gel or inert fluid should
approximate the specific gravity of the capsules. Alternatively, the capsules may also be
suspended via mechanical agitation in a pre-blender familiar to those skilled in the art of
hydraulic fracturing.</p><p num="0051">In practice, a slurry processor or blender uses a gallinger pump for the suction end.
The capsules enter the gallinger pump via either the auger system or holding tank. Upon
blending with the fracturing gel or other fluid, the final slurry enters the low pressure suction
side of the high pressure pump grid and exits via high pressure discharge lines connected to
the wellhead assembly.</p><p num="0052">United States Pat No. 5,799,734, incorporated herein by reference, discloses a method
for preparing a slurry containing particulate matter such as resin coated sand, glass bead,
ceramic particles and the like. The method disclosed by the '734 patent will also provide a
satisfactory means for preparing a slurry of encapsulated liquid.</p><p num="0053">After blending into a carrier fluid, the capsules are injected downhole to a desired
location in the well. Those skilled in the art of well treatment are familiar with the techniques
used for injecting particulates and chemicals into the desired portion of a well. For example,
a typical fracturing process first positions a spacer in the pipe string just below the fractured
formation. After positioning of the spacer, fracturing fluid is pumped at fracturing rates into
the target formation. The spacer acts to initiate the fracture by focusing fluid pressure on the
desired formation. Following fracturing of the formation, acid etching of the fracture
typically takes place. Thus, a carrier fluid containing the acid filled capsules would then be
initiated to the well. During injection of the acid containing capsules, the hydraulic fracture
will likely continue to grow. Preferably, the capsules will travel the length of the fracture.
Leak off of the non-acid carrier fluid into the rock fractures and pores concentrates the
capsules where they are needed for pinpoint reaction. In this manner, the reaction occurs
where it is most needed.</p><p num="0054">In the acid etching process, release of the encapsulated acid occurs after positioning
the capsules at the desired location. Acids suitable for encapsulation and acid etching include
but are not limited to hydrochloric acid, nitric acid, sulfuric acid and mixtures thereof. 
Typically, in the case of acid etching, release of the acid from the capsules occurs when
hydraulic pressure is removed from the fracture. Upon removal of hydraulic pressure from
the fracture, the fracture will close and crush the capsules. The released acid reacts with the
fracture face forming channels. These channels provide the passages necessary to increase
the production of hydrocarbons from the producing formation.</p><p num="0055">Isolation of the encapsulated fluid from the carrier fluid and the downhole
environment by the inventive encapsulation process provides several advantages. For
example, using encapsulated well treatment chemicals permits blending of normally
incompatible compounds in the carrier fluid. Thus, the present invention permits the
transport of an acid compound to a downhole environment by a carrier fluid having a neutral
or basic pH without detrimentally impacting either the carrier fluid or the acid. Further, the
present invention provides a mechanism for carrying out a chemical reaction in the downhole
environment between two liquid compounds. Specifically, one or more of the compounds
can be separately encapsulated and placed in the carrier fluid. Following placement of the
liquids downhole, the liquids are then released from the capsules and allowed to react.</p><p num="0056">Additionally, the inventive method provides a means for transporting the well
treatment chemicals to the desired location without dilution by the carrier fluid. As an added
benefit, when transporting corrosive chemicals such as mineral acids, the carrier fluid will
behave as a non-acid. Viscosity enhancing agents and/or other additives may be added to the
carrier fluid without reducing the concentration of the well treatment chemicals or additives.
As an added benefit, when transporting corrosive chemicals such as mineral acids, the carrier
fluid will behave as a non-acid. Thus, the current invention enhances the economic usage of
the specific target chemical or acid.</p><p num="0057">A non-limiting list of mechanisms suitable for releasing the encapsulated fluid
includes: a change in pH, crushing, rupture, dissolution of the semi-permeable membrane,
diffusion and/or thermal melting of the encapsulating membrane. For example, acid etching
of a fracture face typically follows formation fracturing. Preferably, the acid containing
capsules will be injected into the formation with the fracturing fluid. This process places the
acid in direct contact with the fracture face. Upon removal of hydraulic pressure from the
fracture, the fracture will close and crush the capsules. The released acid reacts with the
fracture face forming channels. These channels provide the passages necessary to increase
the production of hydrocarbons from the producing formation. When thermal release of the 
fluid is desired, a fracture cool down model is prepared to design or predict thermal cool
down effects and effective depth of transport prior to achieving thermal release of the liquid.
In a diffusive release mode, plots of the fraction release vs. time provide the release rates
needed to calculate pump rate, pump time or shut-in period to achieve the desired liquid
release point.</p><heading>Example 6 - Acid Etching a Well Fracture with Encapsulated Acid</heading><p num="0058">The method of injecting an acid containing capsule and acid etching a well fracture
will be discussed to exemplify the current invention. While the following discussion focuses
on acid etching, the method of injecting well treatment chemicals and additives is not limited
to the injection of an acid.</p><p num="0059">Acid etching a well fracture according to the current invention requires an acid
encapsulated within a semi-permeable membrane. The previously described processes will
produce capsules containing a suitable acid such as HCl.</p><p num="0060">The encapsulation of HCl according to the methods described herein may take place
either at the well location or off-site. In either case, following encapsulation, the operator
blends the encapsulated HCl with the desired carrier fluid prior to injection downhole. If
desired, surfactants may be added to aid in dispersing and carrying the capsules.
Alternatively foamed or gelled fluids may also be used to transport capsules.</p><p num="0061">Due to the isolation of the HCl from the carrier fluid, additional components may be
added, as necessary, to ensure complete transport of the HCl through the length of the
fracture to be acid etched. For example, addition of viscosity enhancers will increase the
viscosity of the carrier fluid and will improve pumpability. Improved pumpability will
promote transport of the capsules to the end of the fracture. Alternatively, the carrier fluid
may also double as the fracturing fluid. In either case, despite the high concentration of acid
dispersed therein, the carrier fluid will act as a non-acid and will generally have a pH
between about 4 and about 11.5.</p><p num="0062">Following transport to the desired downhole location, the operator releases the HCl by
any of several methods including but not limited to: releasing pressure on the fracture
causing it to close and crush the capsule; dissolution of the semi-permeable membrane by
other downhole chemicals; dissolution or rupture of the membrane due to a change in pH;
changing the downhole static pressure leading to rupture of the membrane; diffusion; and/or, 
melting of the encapsulating membrane. Upon release, the acid will react with the fracture
face to create additional channels and passages for oil production.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method OF encapsulating a liquid, which method comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) encapsulating a solid within a semi-permeable membrane to form a capsule;</claim-text><claim-text>b) placing said capsule in a first liquid capable of dissolving said solid whereby
said first liquid passes through said semi-permeable membrane and dissolves
said solid; and then either:</claim-text><claim-text>c) maintaining said capsule in said first liquid for a period of time sufficient to
permit concentration gradient driving forces to cause said liquid to displace
said solid from within said capsule such that substantially all of said solid is
removed from said capsule leaving said liquid in said capsule; or</claim-text><claim-text>d) maintaining said capsule in contact with a second liquid for a period of time
sufficient to permit concentration gradient driving forces to cause said second
liquid to displace substantially all of said solution of solid and first liquid from
within said capsule thereby producing a capsule containing primarily said
second liquid.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1, wherein said semi-permeable membrane is formed
from a compound selected from vegetable oil, partially and fully hydrogenated vegetable oil,
latex, gelatins, carageenans, homopolymer or copolymer of ethylene, propylene, isobutylene,
vinyl chloride, and vinylidene chloride.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1 or 2, wherein said semi-permeable membrane is
formed from a polymer selected from tristearin, polyethylene, polypropylene,
polyisobutylene, a copolymer of vinyl chloride and vinylidene chloride, a copolymer of
vinylidene chloride and an ester of an unsaturated carboxylic acid or a copolymer of ethylene
and an unsaturated carboxylic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1, 2 or 3, wherein said solid is selected from organic
acids, inorganic acids, alcohols, powdered metals, ethoxylated alcohols, mono-saccharides,
disaccharides, sodium hydroxide, ammonium bi-fluoride, salts of organic acids and salts of
mineral acids.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A method according to claim 4, wherein said solid is citric acid, potassium chloride,
ammonium bi-fluoride or sodium chloride.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method according to any of claims 1 to 5, wherein said first liquid is selected
from water, hydrochloric acid, sulfuric acid, phosphoric acid, nitric acid, formic acid, acetic
acid, sulfamic acids, citric acid, glycolic acid, maleic acid, fumaric acid, alcohols, thiols,
polyphosphonic acid, polyphosphonate, scale inhibitors, corrosion inhibitors, fertilizers,
pharmaceuticals, detergents, cement retarders and accelerators, biocides, paraffin inhibitors,
asphaltene inhibitors, hydrogen sulfide scavengers, oxygen scavengers, demulsifiers, clay
stabilizers, surfactants, food additives, pesticides, dyes, pigments, paints, pheromones,
dimethyl formamide, acetone, acetonitrile, ethers, perfumes, cross-linking agents,
polymerization initiators and any mixture of two or more thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1, wherein said solid is water-soluble.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1 to 7, wherein said second liquid is selected
from water, hydrochloric acid, sulfuric acid, phosphoric acid, nitric acid, formic acid, acetic
acid, sulfamic acids, citric acid, glycolic acid, maleic acid, fumeric acid, alcohols, thiols,
polyphosphonic acid, polyphosphonate, scale inhibitors, corrosion inhibitors, fertilizers,
pharmaceuticals, detergents, cement retarders and accelerators, food additives, pesticides,
dyes, pigments, paints, pheromones, dimethyl formamide, acetone, acetonitrile, ethers,
perfumes, cross-linking agents and polymerization initiators and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method according to claim 8, wherein said first liquid is water and said second
liquid is hydrochloric acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1 to 9, wherein said solid and said first liquid
reach a state of equilibrium in step (b) before step (c) is carried out.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A method according to any preceding claim, wherein said first liquid replaces
substantially all of said solid in step (b) before step (c) is carried out.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A method for treating the downhole region of a well, which method comprises:
placing an encapsulated liquid made by the method of any of claims 1 to 11, within the
downhole region of a well; and releasing said liquid from the capsule.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A method according to claim 12, wherein said liquid is released from said capsule by
crushing said capsule, rupturing said capsule, dissolving said capsule, diffusion of said liquid
out of said capsule, or melting of the encapsulating membrane.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A method according to claim 12, wherein said liquid is released from said capsule by
crushing said capsule between the faces of a fractured production zone.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A method according to claim 12 or 13, wherein said capsule is placed within a well
fracture.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A method of acid etching a fracture face located in a subterranean production zone,
which method comprises the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) hydraulically fracturing a subterranean formation to produce a fractured
formation having at least one fracture face;</claim-text><claim-text>b) injecting capsules containing a liquid acid into said fractured formation while
maintaining hydraulic pressure on said fractured formation;</claim-text><claim-text>c) depositing said capsules in said fractured formation; and,</claim-text><claim-text>d) releasing said acid from said capsules thereby acid etching said fracture face.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A method according to claim 16, wherein said step of releasing said acid is carried out
by removing hydraulic pressure from said fractured formation thereby allowing said fractured
formation to close and crush said capsules.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A method according to claim 16 or 17, wherein said acid is hydrochloric acid, sulfuric
acid, nitric acid or any mixture of two or more thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A process according to claim 16, 17 or 18, further comprising the step of blending
said capsules in a carrier fluid having approximately the same specific gravity as said
capsules prior to injecting said capsules into said fractured formation.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>A process according to claim 19, wherein said carrier fluid has a pH from 4 to 11.5,
and/or said carrier fluid has a pH of from 7 to 11.5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>A process according to any of claims 16 to 20, wherein said capsules have been made
by a method as claimed in any of claims 1 to 11.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>