<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1069095-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1069095" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="23400444" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010117"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1069095-A1" status="new" fvid="23020122"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1069095</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010117</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00305886-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00305886</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000712</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-35617599-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>35617599</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990716</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C06B  21/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C06B  21/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C06B  45/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C06B  45/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C06D   5/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C06D   5/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C06B  21/00F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C06B  45/10</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Feststoffraketentreibsatz</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Solid rocket propellant</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Charge propulsive solide pour fusée</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-19520548-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>19520548</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0266973-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0266973</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4098627-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4098627</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4775432-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4775432</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5240523-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5240523</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>UNITED TECHNOLOGIES CORP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>UNITED TECHNOLOGIES CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>UNITED TECHNOLOGIES CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>United Technologies Building, 1 Financial Plaza</street><city>Hartford, CT 06101</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>JONES MARVIN LUTHER</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TZENG DONALD DONGJAW</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>JONES, MARVIN LUTHER</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TZENG, DONALD DONGJAW</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>JONES, MARVIN LUTHER</last-name><address><street>425 South Street</street><city>Hollister, California 95023</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TZENG, DONALD DONGJAW</last-name><address><street>1195 Morrill Avenue</street><city>San Jose, California 95132</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Leckey, David Herbert</last-name><address><street>Frank B. Dehn &amp;amp; Co., European Patent Attorneys, 179 Queen Victoria Street</street><city>London EC4V 4EL</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A solid rocket propellant includes a hydroxy-terminated caprolactone ether binder
and an oxidizer. The propellant may be disposed of by contacting it with an
aqueous solution of 12 N NaOH or 6 N HCl at a temperature of about 140°F (60°C)
for about 24 hours to decompose the binder. Solids remaining in the solution after
the binder decomposes are removed.</p> </abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention is directed to a solid rocket propellant.</p><p num="0002">Solid rocket propellants typically comprise an oxidizer, a fuel, a variety of
additives, and a binder that holds the propellant together. Typical oxidizers include
ammonium nitrate, ammonium dinitramide, ammonium perchlorate, potassium
perchlorate, and other compounds known in the art. Typical fuels include aluminum
powder, boron, and beryllium. Typical binders include nitrocellulose, hydroxy
terminated polybutadiene, butadiene terpolymer, polybutadiene-acrylic acid-acrylonitrile,
carboxyl terminated polybutyldiene, polyesters, polyethylene glycol,
poly tetramethylene glycol and other compounds known in the art. Typical additives
include plasticizers such as n-butyl nitratoethyl nitramine, trimethylolethane trinitrate
and isodecyl pelargonate, dioctyl adipate; burning rate modifiers such as iron oxide
and carbon; combustion stabilizers such as zirconium oxide; anti-oxidants such as
n-methyl nitroaniline and 2,2'-Methylene-Bis-(4-Methyl-6-Tert-Butylphenol)
(available as AO-2246 from American Cyanamid Company, Parsippany, NJ); curing
agents such as dimeryl diisocyante, isophorone diisocyanate, and Desmodur® N-100
(available from Bayer Corporation, Pittsburgh, PA); curing catalysts such as
triphenyl bismuth and dibutyltin dilaurate; and acoustic suppressants such as silicon
carbide.</p><p num="0003">Solid rocket propellants can be tailored to specific applications by varying
their formulations. Although preliminary work on new formulations can be done in
a laboratory with small quantities, testing and large scale demonstrations are
typically required before a new formulation is accepted for military or commercial
use. As a result, propellant development programs often generate considerable
excess inventory of propellant. Production programs also generate excess
inventory or off specification material. Finally, excess propellant is generated
when rocket motors are periodically remanufactured to replace aging propellant 
with fresh propellant. In all cases, the excess inventory or off-specification
material must be disposed of safely. Historically, open air incineration was the
preferred disposal method. Increasingly, however, open air incineration is
becoming environmentally unacceptable. Therefore, what is needed in the
industry is a solid rocket propellant that can be disposed of with environmentally
acceptable techniques.</p><p num="0004">The present invention is directed towards a solid rocket propellant that can
be disposed of with environmentally acceptable techniques. As a side benefit,
main components of the propellant can be recovered for reuse.</p> <p num="0005">In accordance with one aspect of the invention there is provided a rocket
motor propellant that includes a hydroxy-terminated caprolactone ether binder.</p> <p num="0006">Another aspect of the invention includes a method of disposing of a solid
rocket propellant. A solid rocket propellant that includes a hydroxy-terminated
caprolactone ether binder and one or more solid compounds disposed in the binder
is contacted with a solution capable of hydrolyzing the binder to form hydrolyzed
caprolactone and poly(tetramethylene ether). Solids remaining in the solution after
the binder hydrolyzes are removed.</p> <p num="0007">These and other features and advantages of the present invention will
become more apparent from the following description.</p><p num="0008">The present invention provides in its various embodiments a full range of
solid rocket propellant formulations, including minimum smoke propellants, reduced
smoke propellants, and metalized propellants. The common element in all aspects
of the present invention is the use of a hydroxy-terminated caprolactone ether
(HTCE) polymer as a binder to hold the solid constituents of the propellant of the
present invention together. As a result, the propellant of the present invention
comprises at least one solid compound, for example an oxidizer, dispersed in an
HTCE binder. For purposes of this application, HTCE is a linear block co-polymer of 
caprolactone and tetramethylene ether. Preferably, HTCE will have a molecular
weight of about 2000 units to about 4200 units. At typical HTCE may have an OH
value of about 56 mg KOH/g, an acid value of less than about 0.1 mg KOH/g, and
a melting range of about 86°F (30°C) to about 95°F (35°C). The preferred HTCE
is a waxy solid at room temperature and is a liquid at typical propellant processing
temperatures of 120°F (48.9°C) to 140°F (60°C). HTCE is commercially available
from Solvay Interox, Inc. (Houston TX) as part of Solvay's CAPA® line of
polycaprolactones. The HTCE binder may make up about 4 weight % to about 10
weight % of the propellant of the present invention.</p><p num="0009">Minimum smoke propellants of the present invention include an HTCE binder
and a chlorine-free oxidizer. Suitable chlorine-free oxidizers include ammonium
nitrate (AN), ammonium dinitramide (ADN), nitramines such as cyclotrimethylene
trinitramine (RDX) and cyclotetramethylene tetranitramine (HMX), and other
chlorine-free oxidizers known in the art. A minimum smoke propellant may comprise
about 45 weight % to about 75 weight % of the oxidizer. If desired, the propellant
also may include one or more nitrate ester plasticizers such as n-butyl nitratoethyl
nitramine (BuNENA), trimethylol ethane trinitrate (TMETN), triethylene glycol
dinitrate (TEGDN), and other nitrate ester plasticizers known in the art for additional
energy. Plasticizers may make up about 6 weight % to about 18 weight % the
minimum smoke propellant. Minimum smoke propellants of the present invention
may have a theoretical specific impulse of more than 230 lb<sub>f</sub> sec/lb<sub>m</sub> (2255 N
sec/kg) with an AN oxidizer and more than 260 lb<sub>f</sub> sec/lb<sub>m</sub> (2550 N sec/kg) with an
ADN oxidizer. Such propellants may be useful in tactical applications where a
visible exhaust is undesirable because it would expose a rocket's firing position.</p><p num="0010">Reduced smoke propellants of the present invention include an HTCE binder
and a chlorinated oxidizer. Suitable chlorinated oxidizers include ammonium
perchlorate (AP), which may make up about 65 weight % to about 86 weight % of a
reduced smoke propellant. If desired, the propellant also may include one or more
energetic plasticizers such as BuNENA, TMETN, and TEGDN or fuel plasticizers 
such as dioctyl adipate (DOA) or isodecyl pelargonate (IDP). Plasticizers may make
up about 5 weight % to about 12 weight % of the reduced smoke propellant.
Reduced smoke propellants of the present invention may have a theoretical specific
impulse of more than 244 lb<sub>f</sub> sec/lb<sub>m</sub> (2393 N sec/kg) with an AP oxidizer. Such
propellants may be useful in tactical applications, such a air-to-air applications,
where a small amount of visible exhaust is tolerable as long as the exhaust does
not obscure an operator's field of view.</p><p num="0011">Metalized propellants of the present invention include an HTCE binder, metal
fuel, and an oxidizer. Suitable metal fuels include aluminum, boron, and other metal
fuels known in the art. The preferred metal fuel is aluminum. The metal fuel may
make up about 15 weight % to about 24 weight % of the metalized propellant.
Suitable oxidizers include AP, AN, ADN, HMX, RDX, and other oxidizers known in
the art. The oxidizer may make up about 45 weight % to about 75 weight % of the
metalized propellant. If desired, the propellant also may include one or more
energetic plasticizers, such as TMETN or TDGDN, or fuel plasticizers, such as DOA
or IDP. Plasticizers may make up about 5 weight % to about 12 weight % of
metalized propellants of the present invention. Metalized propellants of the present
invention may have a theoretical specific impulse of more 263 lb<sub>f</sub> sec/lb<sub>m</sub> (2579 N
sec/kg) with AP oxidizer and 268 lb<sub>f</sub> sec/lb<sub>m</sub> (2628 N sec/kg) with ADN or HMX
oxidizer. Such propellants may be useful in applications for which high energy
content is desirable and for which visible exhaust is not a problem.</p><p num="0012">The HTCE binder of the present invention can be cured with a variety of
curing agents including di-functional isocyanates such as isophorene diisocyante
(IPDI), dimeryl diisocyanate (DDI), bis-(4,isocyanatocyclohexyl) methane
(Desmodur®-W, available from Bayer Corporation, Pittsburgh, PA), and other di-functional
isocyanates; and poly-functional isocyanates such as aliphatic
isocyanates made by the homo-polymerization of hexamethylene diisocyanate,
including Desmodur® N-100 and Desmodur® N-3200 (both available from Bayer
Corporation), and other poly-functional isocyanates. The curing agent may make up 
as much as about 2.75 weight % of the propellant. A cross-linker may be desirable
when di-functional isocyanates are use as curing agents. Preferable cross-linkers
include tri-functional and tetra-functional hydroxy terminated caprolactones, such as
CAPA® 310 and CAPA® 316 (available from Solvay Interox, Inc.). The cross-linker
may make up as much as about 2.0 weight % of the propellant of the present
invention. A cure catalyst such as triphenyl bismuth (TPB), dibutyltin dilaurate
(DBTDL), or similar cure catalysts may be used to speed the cure reaction. Typical
amounts of TPB in the propellant range from about 0.01 weight % to about 0.05
weight %. Typical amounts of DBTDL range from about 1 PPM by weight to about 6
PPM by weight. HTCE may be cured under conditions typically used in the industry.
For example, HTCE may be cured at temperatures of about 120°F (49°C) to about
140°F (60°C) for times ranging from 3 days to 2 weeks.</p><p num="0013">The propellant of the present invention also may include stabilizers, acoustic
suppressants, burner rate modifiers, and other additives. For example, propellants
of the present invention may include up to about 0.5 weight % of one or more
stabilizers, such as N-methyl-<i>p</i>-nitroanaline (NMNA), 2-nitro diphenylamine (NDPA),
or other stabilizers known in the art, to extend their useful lives. Stabilizers may be
particularly useful in propellants that contain nitrate ester plasticizers. The
propellants also may include up to about 0.5 weight % of an acoustic suppressants
such as silicon carbide or zirconium carbide. Burn rate modifiers, such as carbon
black and/or lead compounds including lead citrate, may be included in the
propellant of the present invention in amounts up to about 0.2 weight %. Iron oxide
can be used as a burning rate modifier in formulations without energetic nitrate
ester plasticizers in amounts up to about 2 weight %.</p><p num="0014">By varying the formulation, burn rates for the propellant of the present
invention may be tailored for numerous applications. Burning rates have been
observed as low as 0.18 in/sec (0.46 cm/sec) and as high as 0.34 in/sec (0.86
cm/sec) at 1000 psi (6895 kPa) for formulations without any burning rate modifiers.
Pressure exponents were between 0.3 and 0.4. The ranges of burning rates and 
pressure exponents may be expanded by using various additives and curing
catalysts discussed above. It should be possible to formulate metalized propellants
with iron oxide burning rate catalyst that have burning rates as high as 0.75 in/sec
(1.91 cm/sec) at 1000 psi (6895 kPa).</p><p num="0015">The mechanical properties of the HTCE binder, such as modulus, tensile
strength, and elongation, also may be tailored for particular applications. For
example, the modulus may be varied from about 300 psi (2068 kPa) to about 700
psi (4826 kPa), the tensile strength may be varied from about 75 psi (517 kPa) to
about 150 psi (1034 kPa), and the elongation may be varied from about 30% to
about 150% of the propellant of the present invention. One way to adjust the
mechanical properties of the binder is to vary the isocyanate/hydroxyl (NCO/OH)
equivalent ratio. For example, the NCO/OH equivalent ratio may be varied from
about 0.95 to about 1.20. Another method is to add about 0.1 weight % to about 2.0
weight % of a tri-functional or tetra-functional hydroxyl-terminated caprolactone to
the formulation as a cross-linker in the propellant. The cross-linker promotes cross-linking
within the HTCE co-polymer structure. Suitable cross-linkers include tri-functional
and tetra-functional hydroxy terminated caprolactones, such as CAPA®
310 and CAPA® 316 (available from Solvay Interox, Inc.).</p><p num="0016">Once a specific formulation is chosen, the ingredients are mixed in an
explosion proof mixing vessel according to industry practices to create an uncured
propellant. The uncured propellant may be loaded into a rocket casing or other
container by known casting techniques and cured under suitable conditions. For
example, the propellant of the present invention may be cured at temperatures of
about 120°F (49°C) to about 140°F (60°C). It may take about 3 days to about 14
days to cure a batch of propellant of the present invention. Samples of the cured
propellant may then be tested to confirm the properties. The final product would
then be ready to deliver to the customer.</p><p num="0017">Over time, quantities of propellant that require disposal may be accumulated
as a result of off-specification mixing, excess production, natural degradation of the 
propellant, obsolescent propellant or missiles being removed from service, and
similar events. In the past, such propellant was typically disposed of by open air
incineration. Propellants of the present invention, however, may be disposed of by
hydrolyzing the HTCE binders in the propellant. The ester linkage in the
caprolactone in the HTCE binder provides the site for hydrolysis. The polyether
linkage in the HTCE binders increase the hydrophilicity of the cured binder toward
aqueous acidic and/or basic solutions. Thus, the polyether linkage is more resistant
to hydrolysis than the ester linkage.</p><p num="0018">To dispose of propellant of the present invention by hydrolysis, the propellant
may be reduced in size to facilitate handing and increase surface area for the
reaction. While no particular size reduction is required, preferably the propellant will
be reduced to pieces of no more than about 0.5 inch (1.3 cm) in any dimension.
The propellant is then mixed with a solution capable of hydrolyzing HTCE. For
example, HTCE may be hydrolized in an acidic aqueous solution of 6 N HCl
(hydrochloric acid) or a basic aqueous solution of 12 N NaOH (sodium hydroxide).
One skilled in the art will recognize that solutions with different compositions and
concentrations would work as well. Preferable, the hydrolysis will be conducted at
an elevated temperature, for example about 140°F (60°C), for a sufficient time to
completely hydrolyze the HTCE. Agitation can speed the hydrolysis reaction. By
selecting appropriate conditions, hydrolysis can be completed within about 24
hours. As a result of the hydrolysis reaction, the HTCE binder will decompose into
water soluble, environmentally benign compounds such as hydrolyzed
caprolactone, typically ω-hydroxyl caproic acid, and poly(tetramethylene ether) that
may be recycled. Solids that were in the propellant, for example the oxidizer and
other solids, may be recovered and recycled for use in other propellants. Aluminum
may be recovered as aluminum oxide. The ability to recover and reuse the solids,
which may make up 85 weight % or more of the propellant, greatly reduces the
environmental impact of disposing of propellants of the present invention. The 
residue of hydrolysis that cannot be recycled may be disposed of in a suitable
landfill without any environmental harm.</p><p num="0019">The following examples demonstrates the present invention without limiting
the invention's broad scope.</p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0020">To demonstrate the present invention, several propellants were formulated
using a HTCE binder. The table shows the compositions, mechanical properties,
and where available burning rate and pressure exponent data.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Propellant A Metalized</entry><entry align="center">Propellant B Metalized</entry><entry align="center">Propellant C Reduced Smoke</entry></row><row><entry align="left">HTCE binder (MW = 2000)</entry><entry align="center">8.80</entry><entry align="center">4.21</entry><entry align="center">6.21</entry></row><row><entry align="left">CAPA® 316 cross-linking agent</entry><entry align="center">0.18</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry><entry align="center">1.04</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diocytal adipate (DOA) plasticizer</entry><entry align="center">4.84</entry></row><row><entry align="left">n-butyl nitratoethyl nitramine (BuNENA) plasticizer</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">15.54</entry><entry align="center">10.65</entry></row><row><entry align="left">n-methyl nitroanaline (NMNA) stabilizer</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">triphenyl bismuth (TPB) cure catalyst</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">silicon carbine (SiC) acoustic suppressant</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">carbon (C) black burning rate modifier</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">dimeryl diisocyante (DDI) curing agent</entry><entry align="center">3.13</entry><entry align="center">2.50</entry><entry align="center">3.40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">ammonium perchlorate (AP) oxidizer</entry><entry align="center">63.00</entry><entry align="center">56.00</entry><entry align="center">77.20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">aluminum (Al) fuel</entry><entry align="center">20.00</entry><entry align="center">20.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">modulus, psi (kPa)</entry><entry align="center">623 (4295)</entry><entry align="center">100 (689)</entry><entry align="center">383 (2641)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">tensile strength, psi (kPa)</entry><entry align="center">92 (634)</entry><entry align="center">29 (200)</entry><entry align="center">45 (310)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">elongation, failure %</entry><entry align="center">65</entry><entry align="center">43</entry><entry align="center">20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">burning rate, in/sec @1000 psi (cm/sec @ 6895 kPa)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.28 (0.71)</entry><entry align="center">0.26 (0.66)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">pressure exponent</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.39</entry><entry align="center">0.36</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0021">A 2.0-gram sample of cured HTCE gum stock was cut into small pieces of no
more than 0.5 inch (1.3 cm) in any dimension. The cut pieces were placed in a
beaker containing 50-ml of 12 N NaOH aqueous solution. The solution was stirred
with a magnetic stirrer and heated on a hot plate. The reaction temperature was
kept at 60°C. At the end of reaction, about 24 hours, all solid gum stock dissolved
and some oil droplet suspension was visible. These results indicate that the HTCE
binder may be hydrolyzed as part of a method of disposing of a propellant of the
present invention.</p><p num="0022">The invention is not limited to the particular embodiments shown and
described herein. Various changes and modifications may be made without
departing from the spirit or scope of the claimed invention.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A rocket motor propellant comprising a hydroxy-terminated caprolactone ether
binder and an oxidizer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The propellant of claim 1, wherein the hydroxy-terminated caprolactone ether is
a linear block co-polymer of caprolactone and tetramethylene ether.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The propellant of claim 1 or claim 2, wherein the hydroxy-terminated
caprolactone ether has a molecular weight of about 2000 to about 4200 units.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The propellant of any one of claims 1 to 3, wherein the oxidizer comprises
ammonium nitrate, ammonium dinitramide, cyclotrimethylene trinitramide,
cyclotetramethylene tetranitramine or ammonium perchlorate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The propellant of any one of claims 1 to 4, further comprising a plasticizer that
comprises n-butyl nitratoethyl nitramine, trimethylol ethane trinitrate,
triethyleneglycol dinitrate, dioctyl adipate or isodecyl pelargonate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The propellant of any one of claims 1 to 5, further comprising an aluminum or
boron metal fuel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The propellant of any one of claims 1 to 3, wherein the oxidizer comprises
ammonium nitrate, ammonium dinitramide, cyclotrimethylene trinitramide, or
cyclotetramethylene tetranitramine and further comprises a plasticizer that
comprises n-butyl nitratoethyl nitramine, trimethylol ethane trinitrate, or
triethyleneglycol dinitrate, wherein the propellant comprises about 4 weight % to
about 10 weight % HTCE binder, about 45 weight % to about 75 weight %
oxidizer, and about 6 weight % to about 18 weight % plasticizer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The propellant of any one of claims 1 to 3, wherein the oxidizer comprises
ammonium perchlorate and further comprises a plasticizer that comprises n-butyl
nitratoethyl nitramine, trimethylol ethane trinitrate, triethyleneglycol
dinitrate, dioctyl adipate, or isodecyl pelargonate wherein the propellant
comprises about 4 weight % to about 10 weight % HTCE binder, about 65
weight % to about 86 weight % oxidizer, and about 5 weight % to about 12
weight % plasticizer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The propellant of any one of claims 1 to 3, wherein the oxidizer comprises
ammonium perchlorate, ammonium nitrate, ammonium dinitramide,
cyclotrimethylene trinitramide, or cyclotetramethylene tetranitramine and further
comprises an aluminum or boron metal fuel and a plasticizer that comprises
trimethylol ethane trinitrate, triethyleneglycol dinitrate, dioctyl adipate, or isodecyl
pelargonate wherein the propellant comprises about 4 weight % to about 10
weight % HTCE binder, about 45 weight % to about 75 weight % oxidizer, about
15 weight % to about 24 weight % metal fuel and about 5 weight % to about 12
weight % plasticizer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A method of disposing of a solid rocket propellant, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) contacting a propellant that comprises a hydroxy-terminated
caprolactone ether binder and at least one or more solid compounds
dispersed in the binder with a solution capable of hydrolyzing the
binder to form hydrolyzed caprolactone and poly(tetramethylene
ether), and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) removing solids remaining in the solution after the binder hydrolyzes.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The method of claim 10, wherein the solids are recovered and recycled.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The method of claim 10 or claim 11, wherein the hydrolyzed caprolactone and
the poly(tetramethylene ether) binder ingredients are recovered and recycled.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The method of any one of claims 10 to 12, wherein the propellant is as claimed
in any one of claims 1 to 9.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>