<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1256338-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1256338" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="25299560" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021113"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1256338-A2" status="new" fvid="23581671"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1256338</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20021113</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01121128-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01121128</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010904</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-84701701-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>84701701</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010501</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   9/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   9/16        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   9/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   9/20        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K   9/16P4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K   9/20P</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61K9:16H2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61K9:16H6B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61K9:20H2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61K9:20H6B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung von Formulierungen zur Direkttablettierung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">A process for the preparation of direct tabletting formulations and aids</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour la préparation de formulations pour la compression directe</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-4072535-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4072535</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4757090-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4757090</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4800086-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4800086</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5006345-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5006345</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5667807-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5667807</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6083430-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6083430</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>SHEKUNOV B Y ET AL: "Crystallization processes in pharmaceutical technology and drug delivery design" JOURNAL OF CRYSTAL GROWTH, NORTH-HOLLAND PUBLISHING CO. AMSTERDAM, NL, vol. 211, no. 1-4, April 2000 (2000-04), pages 122-130, XP004193361 ISSN: 0022-0248</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WEI MING PHARMACEUTICAL MFG CO</name><address><country>TW</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WEI MING PHARMACEUTICAL MFG. CO. LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WEI MING PHARMACEUTICAL MFG. CO. LTD.</last-name><address><street>3 Lane 98 Chilin Road</street><city>Taipei, Taiwan R.O.C.</city><country>TW</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TA-SHUONG YEH</name><address><country>TW</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YEH DANIEL HUNGTING</name><address><country>TW</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YEH DANIEL HUNTING</name><address><country>TW</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YEH TA-SHUONG</name><address><country>TW</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YEH, DANIEL HUNGTING</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YEH, TA-SHUONG</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TA-SHUONG, YEH</last-name><address><street>No. 3, Lane 98, Chilin Road</street><city>Taipei, Taiwan R.O.C.</city><country>TW</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>YEH, DANIEL HUNTING</last-name><address><street>No. 3, Lane 98, Chilin Road</street><city>Taipei, Taiwan R.O.C.</city><country>TW</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Lichti, Heiner, Dipl.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>Patentanwälte, Dipl.-Ing. Heiner Lichti, Dipl.-Phys. Dr. rer. nat. Jost Lempert, Dipl.-Ing. Hartmut Lasch, Postfach 41 07 60</street><city>76207 Karlsruhe</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A thermal adhesion granulation process for preparing direct tabletting formulations or aids is
disclosed. The process comprises the step of subjecting all or part of a mixture comprising:
<sl><li>A) from about 5 to about 99% by weight of one or more diluent excipients and/or from
0 to about 99% by weight of a pharmaceutically active ingredient;</li><li>B) from about 1 to about 95% by weight of a binder excipient;

optionally with,</li><li>C) from 0 to about 10% by weight of a disintegrant excipient;</li></sl>
to heating at a temperature in the range of from about 30 to about 130 °C under the condition
of low moisture or low content of a pharmaceutically-acceptable organic solvent in a closed
system under mixing by tumble rotation until the formation of granules.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><heading><i>Field of the Invention</i></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a novel granulation process for the preparation of direct
tabletting formulations for pharmaceutically-active ingredients, or direct pharmaceutical
tabletting aids using pharmaceutical excipients. In particular, this novel granulation process is
performed under the condition of low moisture content or low content of a
pharmaceutically-acceptable solvent by subjecting a mixture containing one or more diluents
and/or active ingredients; a binder; and optionally a disintegrant, to heating in a closed system
under mixing by tumble rotation.</p><p num="0002">The invention furthermore relates to tablets, capsules, or pellets, which comprise such direct
tabletting formulations or tabletting aids, and to processes for producing the tablets, capsules,
or pellets comprising the direct tabletting formulations or tabletting aids according to the
present invention.</p><heading><i>Description of the Related Art</i></heading><p num="0003">The modern tabletting process often involves the compression of direct tabletting aids
(excipients), along with active substances, into a tablet under pressure. Direct tabletting aids
are required to have not only good flow properties and binding capacity but also a high uptake
capacity for active substances, which are generally difficult to compress. This is also true for
developing a directly compressible formulation for any pharmaceutically active ingredients.
Optimally, the resulting tablets are generally intended to have low friability and high fracture
resistance. Some of these requirements are contradictory. For example, high tablet fracture
resistance is associated with the presence of many points of contact between the diluent (filler)
or pharmaceutically active ingredient and binder inside the tablet, which is usually achieved
with the use of diluent and binder in the form of fine particles. However, fine-particle 
substances in turn have poor flow properties, limiting their suitability for use in high-speed
processes. Attempts have been made over the years to improve or modify the diluents (or
pharmaceutically active ingredient) and binders so that these contradictory properties are
substantially eliminated while retaining the beneficial characteristics.</p><p num="0004">Direct tabletting aids of this type, which are also referred to as "multipurpose excipients", are,
as a rule, preparations which are produced via specific processes, consist of a plurality of
components and are also mentioned as co-processed materials in the literature. For example, a
combination of α-lactose monohydrate and powdered cellulose is disclosed for direct
tabletting in DE-C 3 506 276. Although this composition has a high binding capacity, it has no
disintegration-promoting properties, especially when the compressive forces are relatively high.
Another combination of α-lactose monohydrate and polyvinyl pyrrolidone as binder, and
crosslinked, insoluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone to promote disintegration, disclosed in DE-A 35
05 433 (USP 5,006,345), has excellent flow properties and results, without further addition of
a disintegrant, in rapidly disintegrating tablets. However, this direct tabletting aid is less
suitable for high-dose active substances whose compressibility is poor, because its uptake
capacity for active substances to form tablets with sufficient mechanical stability is limited.</p><p num="0005">US 5,840,769 described a direct tabletting aid using microcrystalline cellulose (MCC) as diluent,
soluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone (PVP) as binder, and crospovidone as disintegrant. It was taught
that this product can be prepared by conventional wet granulation methods such as mixer
granulation, Shugi granulation, extrusion, perforated plate granulation, or preferably, fluidized
bed granulation. Wet Granulation of excipients (diluents or disintegrants) or pharmaceutically
active ingredients, using a binder, such as PVP, dissolved in water and/or organic solvents, is a
common practice. However, despite its widespread usage, wet granulation is a process with
certain fundamental drawbacks.</p><p num="0006">The technique of wet granulation is often employed in the pharmaceutical industry to improve
the properties of a tabletting mixture. Wet granulation involves the addition of a binder
solution to aggregate smaller particles into larger granules for the improvement of powder
flowability. Due to the even distribution of the binder on the surface of the diluent or active
ingredient, thereby increasing the points of contact, binding efficiency of the resulting
granules is often increased and results in greater tablet strength. Granulation also serves to
reduce dust in the tabletting mixture and improve workplace conditions during the automated
tabletting processes. Another benefit of wet granulation is that it helps to facilitate the
uniform blending of components in a tabletting mixture.</p><p num="0007">Wet granulation requires a large amount of liquid to be added, which necessitates tanks and
handling equipments. Since the liquid used in wet granulation must subsequently be removed, 
a drying step is also needed, thereby requiring drying equipment and further complicating the
manufacturing process, as well as significantly increasing the energy, cost and production time
of the overall process. Furthermore, the use of large amounts of volatile organic solvent as
granulating fluid may be harmful to the operator as well as the environment. Special
precaution and equipments are necessary to avoid explosions and protect workers from
exposure to these solvents.</p><p num="0008">Another disadvantage of wet granulation is that, in certain instances, the presence of excessive
moisture can negatively affect the ingredients in the tabletting formulation. For example, as
discussed in USP 6,103,219, it is known that the exposure of microcrystalline cellulose to
moisture in the wet granulation process severely reduces the compressibility of this excipient,
mainly due to softening of the cellulose fibers. This loss of tabletting strength dictates that a
larger amount of the MCC may be needed to obtain an acceptably compressed final product,
especially when a high dose of active ingredients is sought. The additional amount of MCC
required not only adds cost to the preparation, but more importantly, increases the size and
bulk of the resulting tablet, making it more difficult to swallow. The loss of compressibility of
microcrystalline cellulose caused by wet granulation has long been considered a problem in the
art for which there has been no satisfactory solution.</p><p num="0009">The literature is flooded with various examples for the use of PVP (or other binders) in wet
granulation (e.g., WO 93/09763; WO 00/06125; USP 4,968,509; USP 5,200,193; USP
5,462,747). By in large, wet granulation with a large amount of aqueous or alcoholic solution
to dissolve the binder is still the most popular way to prepare granules for tabletting or to
manufacture matrix-forming material for sustained-release dosage forms. Considering the
drawbacks of wet granulation, it would be desirable to obtain an alternative granulation
process which improves the flowability, while retaining or improving other tabletting features,
such as tablet hardness, of a direct tabletting formulation or aid, without the extensive use of
granulation liquid as employed in wet granulation.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0010">Thus, the object of the present invention is to develop an alternative granulation process
which utilizes considerably less water or solvent than the traditional wet granulation method. </p><p num="0011">Another object of the present invention is to utilize the granulation process for providing
direct tabletting formulations with good flow properties and binding capacity to form tablets
of low friability and adequate hardness.</p><p num="0012">A further object of the present invention is to utilize the granulation process for producing
direct tabletting aids which, while having good flow properties and binding capacity to form
tablets of low friability and adequate hardness, have a high uptake capacity for active
substances whose tablettability is poor.</p><p num="0013">An additional object of the present invention is to utilize the granulation process for providing
direct tabletting formulations or aids which, while having good flow properties and binding
capacity to form tablets of low friability and adequate hardness, have an adequate
disintegration activity for active substances.</p><p num="0014">Further objects and advantages of this invention will become apparent from a consideration
of the ensuing discussions and examples.</p><p num="0015">As a result of various investigations carried out to find a novel method achieving the purpose,
the present inventors found that when a finely-divided powder of binder is mixed with diluent
excipients such as cellulose powder, microcrystalline cellulose, lactose, starch, dibasic calcium
phosphate, or active substances, such as acetaminophen or ascorbic acid, and subjected to
heating in a closed system with a low moisture content or low content of a
pharmaceutically-acceptable solvent, while mixed by tumble rotation, it was possible to obtain
direct tabletting formulations or aids with favorable properties not observed in the starting
materials.</p><p num="0016">Thus, the present invention provides a novel method to prepare a direct tabletting
formulations or aids using a finely-divided powder of binder to granulate excipients or active
substances in a closed system with a low moisture content or low content of a
pharmaceutically-acceptable solvent while being subjected to heating and mixing by tumble
rotation.</p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0017">The present invention, termed "thermal adhesion granulation" (TAG), is a novel granulation
method and will be described in detail below. </p><p num="0018">The present invention provides a granulation process for preparing direct tabletting
formulations containing pharmaceutically-active ingredients, or direct tabletting aids (i.e., aids
which contain no active substances), by subjecting the mixture of A) and B) in the following to
heating at a temperature range of from about 30 to about 130 °C, preferably from about 40 to
about 110 °C, and in particular from about 60 to about 105 °C, under the condition of from
about 0.1 to about 20% initial moisture content and/or from about 0.1 to about 20% initial
content of a pharmaceutically-acceptable organic solvent, in a closed system under mixing by
tumble rotation until the formation of granules:
<sl><li>A) from about 5 to about 99% by weight, preferably from about 10 to about 90% by weight,
of one or more diluent (filler) excipients suitable for tabletting, and/or from 0 to about
99% by weight, preferably from about 10 to about 90% by weight, of a
pharmaceutically-active ingredient;</li><li>B) from about 1 to about 95% by weight, preferably from about 5 to about 50% by weight, of
a binder excipient;

and optionally,</li><li>C) from 0 to about 10% by weight of disintegrant excipient, which can be added to the above
mixture of A) and B) before or after granulation.</li></sl></p><p num="0019">The granulation of a mixture of components A), B) and optionally C), according to the
present invention, must be conducted in a dosed system with initial moisture content of the
mixtures in the range of from about 0.1 to about 20%, preferably in a range of from about 2 to
about 15%, and more preferably from about 4 to about 10%, as determined by a moisture
balance (e.g., Ohaus, Japan). Alternatively, granulation may be accomplished with a
pharmaceutically-acceptable organic solvent (e.g., ethanol) at an initial solvent content of the
mixtures in the range of from about 0.1 to about 20%, preferably in a range of from about 0.1
to about 10%, and more preferably from about 0.5 to about 5%.</p><p num="0020">"Tumble rotation" is defined as rotation of a container about an inner horizontal axis,
whereby the powder mixture mass inside the container is made to slide, roll, flow, fall or
otherwise move along the inner wall of the container.</p><p num="0021">The diluent excipient(s) in component A) may be selected from powdered cellulose,
microcrystalline cellulose, lactose, starch, dibasic calcium phosphate, tribasic calcium
phosphate, mannitol, sorbitol, sucrose, dextrose, cellulose acetate, hydroxypropyl
methylcellulose, and others, or a combination thereof, preferably powdered cellulose,
microcrystalline cellulose, lactose, starch, and dibasic calcium phosphate. In a preferred 
embodiment of the present invention, the microcrystalline used is grade 101, wherein about
90% of the particles are in the range from about 1 µm to about 125µm, and the average
particle size is from about 10µm to about 70µm.</p><p num="0022">The pharmaceutically-active ingredient in component A) may be selected from acetaminophen,
ascorbic acid, nifedipine, ibuprofen, aspirin, and others, or a combination thereof, preferably
acetaminophen and ascorbic acid.</p><p num="0023">Although stable tablets can usually be obtained with diluent excipient such as powdered
cellulose, microcrystalline cellulose, lactose, starch, and dibasic calcium phosphate, even with
low compressive forces, the flow properties of these fine powders are generally poor due to
the relatively small particle sizes. Granulation with binders improves the flow properties due
to the increase in particle size taking place during granulation.</p><p num="0024">For component B), the binder excipient may be selected from soluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone
(PVP), hydroxypropylcellulose (HPC), hydroxypropyl methylcellulose (HPMC),
low-substituted hydroxypropylcellulose (L-HPC), sodium carboxymethylcellulose, methyl
cellulose, ethyl cellulose, sugar, and others, or a combination thereof, preferably polyvinyl
pyrrolidone and hydroxypropylcellulose. Further, the binder excipient may contain from 0 to
about 10% (by weight with respect to the binder) of one or more anticaking agents, such as
dibasic calcium phosphate anhydrous, silicon dioxide, or calcium silicate, preferably dibasic
calcium phosphate anhydrous.</p><p num="0025">For component C), disintegrating agents such as crospovidone (PVP-CL), sodium starch
glycolate (SSG), reticulated (crosslinked) carboxymethylcellulose (CMC-CL), low-substituted
hydroxypropylcellulose (L-HPC), and others, or a combination thereof, may be mixed with the
mixture during granulation (intragranular) or after granulation (extragranular) to further
facilitate the disintegration of the resulting tablets or capsules.</p><p num="0026">Soluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone (PVP), used in the present invention as a preferred binder in one
embodiment of the thermal adhesion granulation process, is a finely-divided powder applied
extensively in the pharmaceutical industry as a tabletting binder, either for wet granulation or
direct compression. Generally, the polyvinyl pyrrolidones have a K value of from about 12 to
about 120. Particularly preferred polyvinyl pyrrolidones according to the invention have a K
value of from about 20 to about 95, in particular from about 25 to about 35. For the definition
of the K value, reference may be made to the povidone monograph in USP 24/NF19 (2000).</p><p num="0027">Thermal adhesion granulation is essentially a dry process in which the binder is dry-blended
into the mixture, rather than added as a solution. To optimize the binding efficiency, it is
desirable to use a finely-divided binder powder to maximize the contact points between the 
binder and the diluent or active ingredients. Certain binders, such as PVP, are highly
hygroscopic and become sticky and tacky with the absorption of moisture. Caking of
fine-particle PVP during storage, as a result of absorbing moisture from the atmosphere, is a
common occurrence. To help promote and maintain the uniform distribution of the binder as
a fine powder (component B) when mixed with the diluents and/or active ingredients
(component A), the binder used in this invention can be first mixed with from 0 to about 10%,
preferably from about 0.01 to about 10%, more preferably from about 2 to about 4% (by
weight with respect to binder), of an anticaking agent. In applying the anticaking agent, the
binder and the anticaking agent should be blended together, pulverized to a fine powder in a
blender, then passed through a 200-mesh sieve. This binder/anticaking agent mixture can
then be used for granulation with component A and optionally component C.</p><p num="0028">The low water or solvent requirement for TAG stems from the fact that the granulation is
conducted in a closed system. Because vapors generated from heating (from the added wetting
solution plus any inherent moisture of the powder mass) are prevented from escaping from
the system, granulation fluid usage is maximized and the granulation can be accomplished with
a minimal addition of moisture or solvent. It is believed that the heating of the powder mass
may also result in the transfer of certain inherent moisture in the diluents to the binder. A
preferred embodiment of TAG is that the heat distribution on the surface of the granulation
vessel should be, in some manner, slightly non-uniform, such that when the powder mass is
heated, the evolved water or solvent vapor can condense on a portion of the inner surface of
the vessel which is comparatively cooler. Since binders, e.g., PVP, are generally highly
hygroscopic, any moisture present in the system, especially in the form of condensation, is
scavenged by the binder, which then becomes sticky and tacky with the absorption of moisture
and heat. Because the binder was uniformly predispersed among the diluents/active
ingredients as a fine powder prior to granulation, the increasing adhesiveness of the binder
results in the cohesion of neighboring particles and ultimately the formation of granules as the
powder mass is mixed within the dosed vessel. The optimal temperature range for TAG is
system-specific, and depends on factors such as the type and amount of diluents, binder and
granulation fluid used. For example, when an organic solvent rather than water is used as the
granulation fluid, a lower temperature may be necessary.</p><p num="0029">Compared with the known techniques of mixing and tabletting active substances with
powdered cellulose, microcrystalline cellulose, crosslinked polyvinyl pyrrolidone and
water-soluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone, as described in, for example, EP-A 273 209 or USP
5,840,769, a tabletting process using the direct tabletting aid according to the invention is
distinguished by being a significantly simplified production process with relatively low energy
requirement, minimal pollution potential and a wide range of applicability with regard to the
excipients, binders and active substance employed. These advantages can be attributed mainly 
to the low amount or water or organic solvent required by the present invention as granulation
fluids to produce granules which are comparable or superior in performance compared to
granules derived from existing technologies.</p><p num="0030">The present invention, "thermal adhesion granulation," differs from the traditional wet
granulation approach in several important aspects:
<sl><li>1) In thermal adhesion granulation, a low amount of moisture is added to the tabletting
mixture already containing diluent excipients and binder, whereas in wet granulation the
binder is generally dissolved in the granulation fluid then mixed with the diluent excipients.</li><li>2) Thermal adhesion granulation resembles a "dry" process in that the granulation fluid
requirement (water or organic solvent) of thermal adhesion granulation is significantly less
than that in wet granulation.</li><li>3) With the exception of the drying step, wet granulation is typically conducted at the
ambient temperature, whereas in thermal adhesion granulation the tabletting mixture is
heated to promote the formation of granules.</li><li>4) In wet granulation, the mixing requirement is typically accomplished by either directly
stirring the powder/fluid mixture or mass with a blade, arm, propeller, chopper, or other
types of mechanical stirring means (e.g., shear granulation using a planetary mixer, high
speed mixer/granulator), or suspending the powder in a hot stream of air while spraying
with a binder solution (fluidized bed granulators). In the former, granules are formed by
sieving the wet mass, while in the latter, granules are formed by coating the particles with
the binder solution. In thermal adhesion granulation, granules are formed during mixing
of the moist powder under continuous tumble rotation, as the heated powder mass flows
within the container and agglomerates with the aid of the binder.</li><li>5) Wet granulation involves significant post-granulation steps of drying and milling to form
the desired granules. These steps are unnecessary in the present invention due to the low
amount of moisture introduced to the tabletting mixture.</li><li>6) Conventional granulation methods are typically conducted in open systems. The present
invention of thermal adhesion granulation is conducted in a dosed system.</li></sl></p><p num="0031">An advantage of being able to conduct granulation in a dosed system is that system conditions
may be manipulated to a high degree of specificity, depending on the reactor configuration.
For example, in a mixer capable of heating and vacuum drying, the headspace gas may either
be withdrawn to a complete or partial vacuum, or purged and replaced with inert or
nonreactive gases (e.g., nitrogen or helium). Although heat is applied, granulation in a system 
devoid of oxygen can lead to greater drug stability as well as decreased likelihood of solvent
explosion. In the same reactor, a post-granulation vacuum drying step could also be applied
for efficient solvent recovery.</p><p num="0032">Another major advantage of granulating pharmaceutical products in a closed system is that it
helps to minimize the generation of dust during powder processing. This technique serves to
contain fine-powder active ingredients whose spread or loss from the system is not desirable
due to their cost or biological activity. Just as applicable, the TAG process may be utilized in
other industries such as nutraceutical, food, or animal feed, among others.</p><p num="0033">The application of TAG may be further extended to the granulation of other industrial or
agricultural products - such as fertilizer or pesticide powders, granules or pellets - for which
granulation in a dosed system may help to reduce the generation of toxic or hazardous dust.</p><p num="0034">The present invention is also related to a powder mixture of soluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone
containing from about 0.01 to about 10% (by weight with respect to the polyvinyl pyrrolidone)
of dibasic calcium phosphate anhydrous.</p><p num="0035">The present invention is further related to a direct tabletting formulation or aid comprising:
<sl><li>i) from about 5 to about 99% by weight of powder cellulose, microcrystalline cellulose,
lactose, starch, or dibasic calcium phosphate;</li><li>ii) from 0 to about 99% by weight of acetaminophen or ascorbic acid;</li><li>iii) from about 1 to about 95% by weight of a soluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone which
contains from about 0.01 to about 10% (by weight with respect to the polyvinyl
pyrrolidone) of dibasic calcium phosphate anhydrous; and</li><li>iv) from 0 to about 10% by weight of crospovidone, sodium starch glycolate,
reticulated carboxymethylcellulose, or low-substituted hydroxypropylcellulose.</li></sl></p><p num="0036">The present invention furthermore relates to tablets, capsules, or pellets, which comprise the
direct tabletting formulations or tabletting aids disclosed in the present invention, and to
processes for producing such said tablets, capsules, or pellets.</p><p num="0037">The present invention is specifically described below in the following examples. These
examples are intended to be illustrative only and are not intended to limit the scope of the
present invention. </p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0038">The diluent (filler) excipients used in the examples of this invention comprise of
microcrystalline cellulose grade 101 (MCC 101), lactose (lactose anhydrous, Borculo), starch
(starch 1500, Colorcon), and dibasic calcium phosphate anhydrous (DCP, Fujicalin SG, Fuji
Chemical). These diluents were selected because they represent some of the more frequently
utilized tabletting diluents. The use of these diluents is to demonstrate the wide range of
application of the present invention and should not be interpreted as a limitation of the scope
of the present invention. The basic physical and tabletting properties of these diluents, as well
as those of Ludipress® (consisting of 93% by weight of lactose, 3.5% by weight of
Kollidon® 30 and 3.5% by weight of Kollidon® CL, BASF) and with Avicel® PH 200, a
microcrystalline cellulose (FMC Corporation), are listed in Table 1. In all examples of this
invention, dibasic calcium phosphate anhydrous (Fujicalin, Fuji Chemical, Japan) was added to
the binder in an amount of about 3% (by weight with respect to the binder) as an anticaking
agent. Thus, it should be noted that the percentages of binders expressed in the subsequent
examples are nominal percentages (i.e., they also include a small amount of dibasic calcium
phosphate anhydrous).</p><p num="0039">To determine the powder characteristics of the excipients, granules and direct tabletting aids
described within this invention, the following parameters were measured: mean particle size
(through sieve analysis using 37µm to 800µm size sieves), powder repose angle, powder bulk
density, and powder tapped density (A.B.D. Fine Particle Characteristics Measuring Instrument,
Tsutsui, Japan). The ease of powder flow is represented by both the repose angle and the
Carr's index, calculated as follows:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center"><st32:italic>Carr's index (%)= (tapped density - bulk density</st32:italic>)/<st32:italic>tapped density x 100%</st32:italic></st32:df>
where lower values of the repose angle and the Carr's index represent better powder flow. To
characterize tablets made using the excipients, granules and direct tabletting aids described
within this invention, tablets (11.3 mm discoid, 0.5 g) were produced under a compression
pressure of 49 MPa (500Kg) using the Sankyo Pio-Tech SK-02 Tablettability Tester (Japan).
Tablet hardness (tensile strength measured diametrically) was tested on the same instrument.
Tablet friability and disintegration time were tested on an Aikho (Japan) AE-20 Roche
Friabilator (20 rpm; 5 min; n=10) and a Shin Gwon (Taiwan) SK-0004 tablet disintegration
tester (n=6), respectively. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Properties</entry><entry align="center">MCC 101</entry><entry align="center">Lactose</entry><entry align="center">Starch</entry><entry align="center">DCP</entry><entry align="center">Ludipress®</entry><entry align="center">Avicel® PH 200</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mean Size (µm)</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">80</entry><entry align="center">113</entry><entry align="center">170</entry><entry align="center">180</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Angle of Repose (deg.) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">54.33 ± 1.53</entry><entry align="center">40.33 ± 0.58</entry><entry align="center">40.68 ±0.58</entry><entry align="center">41.33 ± 0.58</entry><entry align="center">35.67 ± 0.58</entry><entry align="center">46.00 ± 1.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bulk Density (g/ml) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.256 ± 0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.635 ± 0.006</entry><entry align="center">0.623 ± 0.007</entry><entry align="center">0.387 ± 0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.527 ± 0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.324 ± 0.001</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tapped Density (g/ml) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.397 ± 0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.811 ± 0.011</entry><entry align="center">0.784 ± 0.006</entry><entry align="center">0.455 ± 0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.600 ± 0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.411 ± 0.001</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carr's Index (%) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">35.58 ± 0.71</entry><entry align="center">21.63 ± 0.34</entry><entry align="center">20.56 ± 0.21</entry><entry align="center">14.94 ± 0.14</entry><entry align="center">12.20 ± 0.53</entry><entry align="center">21.04 ± 0.35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Strength (MPa) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">2.677 ± 0.493</entry><entry align="center">NT <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.191 ± 0.017</entry><entry align="center">NT <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.302 ± 0.043</entry><entry align="center">3.154 ± 0.373</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Friability (%)</entry><entry align="center">0.20</entry><entry align="center">NT <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">1.03</entry><entry align="center">NT <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">2.99</entry><entry align="center">0.20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Disintegration (sec)</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">NT <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">&lt;420</entry><entry align="center">NT <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">&lt;40</entry><entry align="center">&lt;440<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 1</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of the direct tabletting aids with different diluent excipients</u></heading><p num="0040">The direct tabletting aids were produced by the method disclosed, which outlines the general
technique of the thermal adhesion granulation process. For this, water-soluble polyvinyl
pyrrolidone (Kollidon® 30, BASF) with a K value of about 30 (hereafter referred to as PVP
K30), containing within it about 3% dibasic calcium phosphate anhydrous, was mixed either
with microcrystalline cellulose grade 101 (Granule A), lactose (Granule B), starch (Granule C),
or dibasic calcium phosphate (Granule D) at a PVP ratio of 10% by weight with respect to the
total mixture. The binder/diluent mixture was next moisturized with an additional 5% water
(by weight of the total mixture) via a fine spray and blended briefly. The mixture was next
placed in a prewarmed glass bottle, sealed close, and then subjected to heating by infrared lamp
at 90 - 105°C while mixed under tumble rotation (the bottle is subjected to a rolling motion
about a horizontal axis) for 3 to 20 min. until the formation of granules. During the
granulation, the bottle was also briefly shaken periodically for the powder mass to contact any
accumulated vapor condensation on the inner surface of the bottle. The resulting granules
were then screened immediately through a size 24 mesh (800 µm). The resulting granules may
be used directly upon cooling, or, in certain cases if so desired, may be dried further by the 
infrared lamp or by other means as necessary. This granulation process produced granule
compositions with the properties listed in Table 2A. It can be seen that, referring to Table 1,
Granules A-D exhibited significant improvements in particle size, density, flowability, tablet
strength, and disintegration time when compared with their respective parent materials
(diluents). In addition to the diluents used in Granules A-D, the TAG process could also be
applied to the granulation of other diluents, or different grades of MCC, lactose, starch, or
DCP. For example, yet larger granules could be obtained with the use of a microcrystalline
cellulose of a larger size grade as the parent material (e.g., grade 102 with a mean particle size
of 90 µm).
<tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center">% Composition</entry><entry align="center">Granule A</entry><entry align="center">Granule B</entry><entry align="center">Granule C</entry><entry align="center">Granule D</entry><entry align="center">Granule E</entry><entry align="center">Granule F</entry><entry align="center">Granule G</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MCC 101</entry><entry align="center">90.0</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">95.0</entry><entry align="center">90.0</entry><entry align="center">85.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lactose</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">90.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Starch</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">90.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">DCP</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">90.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PVP K30</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">5.0</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Added Moisture (%)</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mean Size (µm)</entry><entry align="center">212.4</entry><entry align="center">326.0</entry><entry align="center">515.2</entry><entry align="center">200.7</entry><entry align="center">123.0</entry><entry align="center">239.9</entry><entry align="center">419.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Angle of Repose (deg.) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">42.67 ±0.58</entry><entry align="center">35.00 ±1.00</entry><entry align="center">38.33 ±0.58</entry><entry align="center">32.00 ±0.00</entry><entry align="center">49.33 ±1.53</entry><entry align="center">43.00 ±1.00</entry><entry align="center">41.33 ±1.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bulk Density (g/ml) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.205 ±0.003</entry><entry align="center">0.524 ±0.004</entry><entry align="center">0.443 ±0.003</entry><entry align="center">0.454 ±0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.216 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.213 ±0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.223 ±0.004</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tapped Density (g/ml) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.255 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.561 ±0.005</entry><entry align="center">0.458 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.505 ±0.003</entry><entry align="center">0.291 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.253 ±0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.245 ±0.004</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carr's Index (%) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">19.69 ±0.88</entry><entry align="center">6.52 ±0.08</entry><entry align="center">3.17 ±0.69</entry><entry align="center">10.08 ±0.86</entry><entry align="center">25.58 ±0.23</entry><entry align="center">15.59 ±0.29</entry><entry align="center">9.11 ±0.74</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Strength (MPa) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">3.077 ± 0.329</entry><entry align="center">2.234 ± 0.802</entry><entry align="center">1.077 ± 0.161</entry><entry align="center">1.162 ± 0.124</entry><entry align="center">3.324 ± 0.469</entry><entry align="center">3.125 ± 0.205</entry><entry align="center">3.529 ± 0.264</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Friability (%)</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0.60</entry><entry align="center">0.81</entry><entry align="center">1.42</entry><entry align="center">0.20</entry><entry align="center">0.40</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Disintegration (sec)</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&lt;375</entry><entry align="center">&lt;190</entry><entry align="center">&lt;180</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 2</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of the direct tabletting aids with PVP at different percentages</u></heading><p num="0041">The direct tabletting aids were produced in accordance with the general method disclosed in
Example 1. For this example, PVP K30 at different percentages [5% (Granule E), 10%
(Granule F), and 15% (Granule G)] was mixed with microcrystalline cellulose grade 101 and
then was subjected to the thermal adhesion granulation process. The moisture added to the
mixtures was about 5%. This process resulted in the granule compositions compiled in Table
2A. It can be seen that granule size, and accordingly flowability, increased with additional
amount of PVP used for the mixture. Differences in the tabletting tensile strengths of the
three granules were not statistically significant.</p><heading>Example 3</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of the direct tabletting aids with PVP at a larger percentage</u></heading><p num="0042">The direct tabletting aids were produced in accordance with the general method disclosed in
Example 1. For this example, PVP K30 at a percentage of 50% was mixed either with
microcrystalline cellulose grade 101 (Granule H), lactose (Granule I), starch (Granule J), or
dibasic calcium phosphate (Granule K) and then was subjected to the thermal adhesion
granulation process. The moisture added to the mixtures was about 5%. This process resulted
in the granule compositions compiled in Table 2B. It can be seen that the use of PVP K30 at
a percentage of 50% led to a decrease in particle size as compared to Granules A, B, C and D
which were made at a PVP K30 content of 10%.</p><heading>Example 4</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of the direct tabletting aids with PVP at different moisture content</u></heading><p num="0043">The direct tabletting aids were produced in accordance with the general method disclosed in
Example 1. For this example, PVP K30 at a fixed ratio (10%) was mixed with microcrystalline
cellulose at different levels of moisture added to the mixture [about 5% (Granule L), about
10% (Granule M), about 15% (Granule N)] and then was subjected to the thermal adhesion
granulation process. This process resulted in the granule compositions compiled in Table 2B.
It can be seen that, of the three moisture levels tested, 5% moisture addition produced the 
largest particle size and best flowability. It can also be seen that increased water content
actually led to decreased granule formation and that the present invention, in a significant
departure from conventional wet granulation processes, was implemented optimally under low
moisture content. Furthermore, the close similarity of the properties of Granule A, F, and L,
which were compositionally identical, served to verify the repeatability of the thermal
adhesion granulation process.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center">% Composition</entry><entry align="center">Granule H</entry><entry align="center">Granule I</entry><entry align="center">Granule J</entry><entry align="center">Granule K</entry><entry align="center">Granule L</entry><entry align="center">Granule M</entry><entry align="center">Granule N</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MCC 101</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">90.0</entry><entry align="center">90.0</entry><entry align="center">90.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lactose</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">50.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Starch</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">50.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">DCP</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">50.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PVP K30</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Added Moisture (%)</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mean Size (µm)</entry><entry align="center">162.6</entry><entry align="center">204.7</entry><entry align="center">151.4</entry><entry align="center">195.1</entry><entry align="center">196.1</entry><entry align="center">156.6</entry><entry align="center">144.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Angle of Repose (deg.) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">49.00 ±1.00</entry><entry align="center">44.33 ±3.51</entry><entry align="center">38.67 ±1.16</entry><entry align="center">38.33 ±0.58</entry><entry align="center">44.67 ±0.58</entry><entry align="center">50.00 ±1.00</entry><entry align="center">56.33 ±0.58</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bulk Density (g/ml) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.296 ±0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.430 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.425 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.415 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.209 ±0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.234 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.239 ±0.002</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tapped Density (g/ml) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.385 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.523 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.531 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.495 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.258 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.301 ±0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.294 ±0.001</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carr's Index (%) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">23.08 ±0.56</entry><entry align="center">17.82 ±0.07</entry><entry align="center">19.97 ±0.21</entry><entry align="center">16.12 ±0.17</entry><entry align="center">19.17 ±0.58</entry><entry align="center">22.31 ±0.17</entry><entry align="center">18.61 ±0.23</entry> </row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Strength (MPa) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">6.931 ± 0.941</entry><entry align="center">6.470 ± 1.087</entry><entry align="center">4.362 ± 0.907</entry> <entry align="center">1.284 ± 0.322</entry> <entry align="center">3.277 ± 0.398</entry> <entry align="center">2.761 ± 0.212</entry><entry align="center">3.197 ± 0.292</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Friability (%)</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0.20</entry><entry align="center">0.20</entry><entry align="center">0.40</entry><entry align="center">0.20</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Disintegration (sec)</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 5</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of the direct tabletting aids by different methods in terms of binder, wetting
solution, and system condition</u></heading><p num="0044">The production of the direct tabletting aids by different methods in terms of binder, wetting
solution, and system condition was demonstrated in this example. The general method of
thermal adhesion granulation was followed in this example, with the changes as specified
below. Microcrystalline cellulose grade 101, at 90%, was used in all granules. The
compositions and properties of the granules, as well as Granule A from Example 1, can be
found in Table 3. Granule A' was compositionally similar to Granule A with the exception that
it contained 3.5% crospovidone as an intragranular disintegrant, i.e., the crospovidone was
blended with the MCC and the PVP K30 prior to thermal adhesion granulation. For Granule
Q, PVP K30 at a percentage of 10% was mixed with microcrystalline cellulose. A low amount
of ethanol (about 1.5%) was used as the wetting solution rather than water, as used in previous
examples. When granulating with ethanol, a heating temperature of 70 - 90°C was applied. It
can be seen that ethanol could be applied as the wetting solution for thermal adhesion
granulation, albeit smaller granules were formed when compared with water-wetted granules
(Granule A). For Granule R, hydroxypropylcellulose (HPC, Klucel® EXF, Aqualon) at 10%
was mixed with microcrystalline cellulose. Ethanol (about 1.5%) was again used as the wetting
solution. It can be seen that the use of HPC produced favorable granules, demonstrating the
applicability of the thermal adhesion granulation process to produce tabletting mixtures
containing other binders.</p><p num="0045">As a demonstration of the closed-system requirement for thermal adhesion granulation, two
granulation series (Group T, about 5% water added; Group U, about 1.5% ethanol added),
both containing 10% PVP K30 and 90% MCC 101, were attempted in open systems with the
glass bottle uncapped. Comparing the mean particle sizes of Group T and U to their closed
system counterparts (Granule A and Q, respectively), it can be seen that thermal adhesion
granulation according to the present invention could not be achieved in an open system. This
result demonstrates that TAG is not simply a variation of wet granulation performed at a lower
moisture level. The failure of Group T and U to form granules also serves to differentiate the
present invention from moisture-activated dry granulation (MADG) techniques. The strict
requirement for thermal adhesion granulation process to be conducted in a closed system
highlights the uniqueness and novelty of the present invention, since conventional granulation
processes are routinely carried out in an open system. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="2">Closed system</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">Open</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">system</entry></row><row><entry align="center">% Composition</entry><entry align="center">Granule A</entry><entry align="center">Granule A'</entry><entry align="center">Granule Q</entry><entry align="center">Granule R</entry><entry align="center">Group T</entry><entry align="center">Group U</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MCC 101</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">86.85</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">90</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PVP K30</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">9.65</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">HPC</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Disintegrant (crospovidone)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">3.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Method of wetting</entry><entry align="center">5% water</entry><entry align="center">5% water</entry><entry align="center">1.5% ethanol</entry><entry align="center">1.5% ethanol</entry><entry align="center">5% water</entry><entry align="center">1.5% ethanol</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mean Size (µm)</entry><entry align="center">212.4</entry><entry align="center">139.8</entry><entry align="center">76.5</entry><entry align="center">98.3</entry><entry align="center">56.3</entry><entry align="center">53.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Angle of Repose (deg.) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">42.67 ± 0.58</entry><entry align="center">45.33 ± 0.58</entry><entry align="center">47.67 ± 0.58</entry><entry align="center">51.00 ± 1.00</entry><entry align="center">47.67 ± 0.58</entry><entry align="center">49.67 ± 0.58</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bulk Density (g/ml) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.205 ± 0.003</entry><entry align="center">0.199 ± 0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.231 ± 0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.216 ± 0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.250 ± 0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.292 ± 0.003</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tapped Density (g/ml) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.255 ± 0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.241 ± 0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.320 ± 0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.287 ± 0.001</entry><entry align="center">0.329 ± 0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.400 ± 0.004</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carr's Index (%) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">19.69 ±0.88</entry><entry align="center">17.41 ±0.43</entry><entry align="center">27.77 ±0.18</entry><entry align="center">24.70 ±0.23</entry><entry align="center">23.88 ±0.28</entry><entry align="center">27.01 ±0.26</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Strength (MPa) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">3.077 ± 0.329</entry><entry align="center">3.787 ± 0.192</entry><entry align="center">2.457 ± 0.168</entry><entry align="center">2.535 ± 0.150</entry><entry align="center">1.846 ± 0.457</entry><entry align="center">2.139 ± 0.388</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Friability (%)</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">1.02</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0.40</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Disintegration (sec)</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&lt;180</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 6</heading><heading><u style="single">Granulation of active substance for direct compression tabletting</u></heading><p num="0046">The direct tabletting formulation with only active ingredient and no diluent present is
produced by the method disclosed. For this, PVP K30 was mixed with acetaminophen (fine
powder, BASF) either with disintegrant (Granule O) or without disintegrant (Granule P) and
then was subjected to the thermal adhesion granulation process. The moisture added to the
mixtures was about 5%. This method resulted in the granule compositions compiled in Table
4. Prior to granulation, acetaminophen existed as a fine powder (&lt;400mesh, 37µm) which has 
extremely poor flowability and cannot be tabletted at all at 500 kg (49 MPa). It can be seen that
the TAG process produced acetaminophen granules with significantly improved size and
flowability, as well as good tablet strength and disintegration properties.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center">% Composition</entry><entry align="center">Granule O</entry><entry align="center">Granule P</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PVP K30</entry><entry align="center">9.65</entry><entry align="center">10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Disintegrant (crospovidone)</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">86.85</entry><entry align="center">90</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mean Size (µm)</entry><entry align="center">177.2</entry><entry align="center">165.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Angle of Repose (deg.) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">48.00 ± 1.00</entry><entry align="center">53.00 ± 1.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bulk Density (g/ml)<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.247 ± 0.003</entry><entry align="center">0.283 ± 0.002</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tapped Density (g/ml)<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.303 ± 0.002</entry><entry align="center">0.319 ± 0.002</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carr's Index (%)<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">18.36 ± 0.52</entry><entry align="center">11.42 ± 0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Strength (MPa) <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0.481 ± 0.057</entry><entry align="center">0.808 ± 0.094</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Friability (%)</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry><entry align="center">1.38</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Disintegration (sec)</entry><entry align="center">&lt;35</entry><entry align="center">&lt;55<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 7</heading><heading><u style="single">Use of the direct tabletting aids for tabletting with active substance</u></heading><p num="0047">The tabletting mixtures described in this example were produced by screening an active
substance (ascorbic acid, a hydrophilic drug, in Test 1, and acetaminophen, a hydrophobic
drug, in Test 2) through a No. 24 screen (800 µm) and loosely mixing it with the direct
tabletting aid produced by the thermal adhesion granulation process as described in Example 1.
The powder mixture was mixed for 10 minutes before being used for direct tabletting. Tables
5 and 6 show the tabletting results for formulations using the granules according to the
invention (Granules A, B, C and D), compared with formulations using Ludipress®
(consisting of 93% by weight of lactose, 3.5% by weight of Kollidon® 30 and 3.5% by weight
of Kollidon® CL) and Avicel® PH 200, a microcrystalline cellulose. </p><p num="0048">For the MCC-based products, it can be seen that ascorbic acid and acetaminophen
formulations using Granule A were at least comparable to those using Avicel® PH200 in
terms of tablet strength, disintegration time and friability (Tables 5 and 6). However, Granule
A exhibited better flowability over Avicel® PH200 (see Tables 1 and 2A). For the
lactose-based products, it can be seen that formulations containing Granule B were superior to
formulations containing Ludipress® in all regards.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Tabletting test 1 (with ascorbic acid)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ascorbic acid crystals</entry><entry align="right">40.0 % by wt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Direct tabletting aid</entry><entry align="right">56.5 % by wt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Disintegrant (crospovidone)</entry><entry align="right">3.5 % by wt</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Direct Tabletting Aid</entry><entry align="center">Tensile Strength [MPa] (mean±SD; n=10)</entry><entry align="center">Disintegration time [sec]</entry><entry align="center">Friability [%]</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granule A</entry><entry align="center">1.296 ± 0.112</entry><entry align="center">&lt;20</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granule B</entry><entry align="center">0.532 ± 0.135</entry><entry align="center">&lt;20</entry><entry align="center">1.21</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granule C</entry><entry align="center">0.369 ± 0.037</entry><entry align="center">&lt;150</entry><entry align="center">1.95</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granule D</entry><entry align="center">0.240 ± 0.038</entry><entry align="center">&lt;45</entry><entry align="center">5.49</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Avicel® PH 200 (Comp.)</entry><entry align="center">1.325 ± 0.120</entry><entry align="center">&lt;20</entry><entry align="center">0.41</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ludipress® (Comp.)</entry><entry align="center">0.183 ± 0.043</entry><entry align="center">&lt;40</entry><entry align="center">10.85</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Tabletting test 2 (with acetaminophen)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Acetaminophen powder</entry><entry align="right">30.0 % by wt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Direct tabletting aid</entry><entry align="right">66.5 % by wt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Disintegrants (crospovidone)</entry><entry align="right">3.5 % by wt</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Direct Tabletting Aid</entry><entry align="center">Tensile Strength [MPa] (mean±SD; n=10)</entry><entry align="center">Disintegration time [sec]</entry><entry align="center">Friability [%]</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granule A</entry><entry align="center">1.287 ± 0.115</entry><entry align="center">&lt;26</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granule B</entry><entry align="center">0.457 ± 0.090</entry><entry align="center">&lt;37</entry><entry align="center">1.62</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granule C</entry><entry align="center">0.258 ± 0.025</entry><entry align="center">&lt;205</entry><entry align="center">1.03</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granule D</entry><entry align="center">0.321 ± 0.050</entry><entry align="center">&lt;45</entry><entry align="center">4.45</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Avicel® PH 200 (Comp.)</entry><entry align="center">0.826 ± 0.058</entry><entry align="center">&lt;17</entry><entry align="center">0.81</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ludipress® (Comp.)</entry><entry align="center">0.173 ± 0.045</entry><entry align="center">&lt;60</entry><entry align="center">5.98</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 8</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of a direct tabletting formulation containing active substance using thermal
adhesion granulation</u></heading><p num="0049">In the preceding example, the active ingredient and the disintegrant were added extragranularly,
i.e., they were blended with the direct tabletting aid produced by TAG, then the mixture was
directly compressed into a tablet. The TAG process can also be utilized to granulate all
components into a direct tabletting formulation, such that the resulting granules can be
directly tabletted without further additions or modifications. In this example, a mixture of the
following formula, which is compositionally identical to the Granule A series in Table 6, was
subjected to thermal adhesion granulation (with about 5% moisture added), then directly
compressed into tablets.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Acetaminophen powder</entry><entry align="center">30.0 % by wt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MCC 101</entry><entry align="center">59.85 % by wt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PVP K30</entry><entry align="center">6.65 % by wt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Disintegrants (crospovidone)</entry><entry align="center">3.5 % by wt</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0050">The resulting tablets had the following properties: Tensile Strength = 1.088 ± 0.167 MPa;
Disintegration time &lt; 10 sec.; Friability = 0%. These values are comparable to that shown in
Table 6 for tablets produced with Granule A, wherein the active substance and disintegrant
were added extragranularly.</p><heading>Example 9</heading><heading><u style="single">Determination of the active substance uptake capacity for the direct tabletting formulations</u></heading><p num="0051">The active substance uptake capacity (loading capacity) of Granule A was compared to that of
Ludipress®. Acetaminophen was again used as the sample active substance at increasing levels.
The tabletting mixture was produced as described in Example 8 (i.e., 3.5% extragranular
crospovidone as disintegrant + acetaminophen in a percentage as indicated in Table 7 +
Ludipress® or Granule A for the remaining balance). The tabletting results are listed in Table
7. It can be seen that Granule A exhibited excellent uptake capacity. <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Tensile Strength [MPa] (mean±SD;n=10)</entry><entry align="center">Disintegration time Disintegration time [sec]</entry><entry align="center">Friability rnabuity [%]</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ludipress®</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   No active substance</entry><entry align="center">0.302 ± 0.043</entry><entry align="center">&lt;50</entry><entry align="center">2.99</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   10% Acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">0.318 ± 0.070</entry><entry align="center">&lt;55</entry><entry align="center">4.06</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   20% Acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">0.251 ± 0.066</entry><entry align="center">&lt;60</entry><entry align="center">4.52</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   30% Acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">0.226 ± 0.055</entry><entry align="center">&lt;45</entry><entry align="center">3.88</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   40% Acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">0.198 ± 0.035</entry><entry align="center">&lt;45</entry><entry align="center">8.39</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granules A</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   No active substance</entry><entry align="center">3.355 ± 0.376</entry><entry align="center">&lt;60</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   10% Acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">2.736 ± 0.343</entry><entry align="center">&lt;45</entry><entry align="center">0.40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   20% Acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">2.010 ± 0.319</entry><entry align="center">&lt;30</entry><entry align="center">0.40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   30% Acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">1.379 ± 0.108</entry><entry align="center">&lt;20</entry><entry align="center">1.41</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   40% Acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">0.909 ± 0.098</entry><entry align="center">&lt;20</entry><entry align="center">1.84</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   50% Acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">0.529 ± 0.046</entry><entry align="center">&lt;40</entry><entry align="center">2.67</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 10</heading><heading><u style="single">The use of alternative disintegrants in conjunction with the direct tabletting formulations</u></heading><p num="0052">Other commonly utilized tabletting disintegrants, such as sodium starch glycolate (SSG),
reticulated carboxymethylcellulose (croscarmellose, crosslinked CMC) and low-substituted
hydroxypropylcellulose (L-HPC) could be substituted for crospovidone in Examples 5 to 9 to
produce tablets with results comparable to that of crospovidone. The optimal concentration
range of SSG is from about 4 to about 8% by weight of the total mixture, while croscarmellose
and L-HPC should be used at a level from about 3 to about 6%. The disintegrant may be
added entirely intragranularly (before granulation), entirely extragranularly (after granulation),
or split between intragranule and the running powder. The advantage of the third approach is
that the extragranule disintegrant first acts to break up the tablet into granules, thereby
increasing the surface area available for the intragranular disintegrants to break up the granules. </p><heading>Comparative Example</heading><heading><u style="single">Comparison of tabletting properties of TAG granules to that of a physical mixture of
microcrystalline cellulose grade 101, PVP K30 and 3.5% crospovidone</u></heading><p num="0053">In this comparison, 3.5% crospovidone was added to Granule A (formed by TAG as described
in Example 1) extragranularly such that the combination was compositionally identical to the
physical mixture. Additional crospovidone was not added to Granule A' and Ludipress® since
these tabletting aids already contain the disintegrant. The results of the comparisons are listed
in Table 8. The physical mixture of MCC/PVP K30/crospovidone was not suitable for
tabletting because the flow properties were extremely poor (angle of repose = 54.67 deg.; BD
= 0.293 g/ml; TD = 0.427 g/ml; Carr's Index = 31.27 %), especially when compared to that of
Granule A (angle of repose = 42.67 deg.; BD = 0.205 g/ml; TD = 0.255 g/ml; Carr's Index =
19.69 %) which had superior flowability as a result of TAG. The standard deviation for the
tensile strength of tablets made with the physical mixture was also larger, as compared to that
of those made from TAG granules. Further, despite the addition of crospovidone to aid
disintegration, the disintegration time of the resulting tablets from the physical mixture
containing acetaminophen was much greater than 15 minutes. By comparison, the
extragranular addition of crospovidone to granule A resulted in considerably faster
disintegration. The slightly longer disintegration time associated with Granule A' compared
with Granule A is typical of the phenomenon commonly observed in formulation wherein the
use of intragranular disintegrant results in longer disintegration time compared with
extragranular disintegrant, due to the ability of extragranular disintegrants to break up the
tablet first into the individual granules. These comparisons serve to prove that the
improvements in overall tabletting properties of granule A over that of MCC 101, or in other
granules over the starting diluent excipient, is not due simply to the addition of PVP as a
binder. The thermal adhesion granulation process described by the present invention is a
necessary process to improve the flow properties of the diluent excipients without
compromising tablet strength, resistance to fracture, and ease of disintegration. <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Tensile Strength [MPa] (mean±SD; n=10)</entry><entry align="center">Disintegration time [sec]</entry><entry align="center">Friability [%]</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Physical mixture without active substance</entry><entry align="center">3,754 ± 0.588</entry><entry align="center">&lt;150</entry><entry align="center">0.20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Physical mixture + 30% acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">1.495 ± 0.195</entry><entry align="center">&gt;900</entry><entry align="center">0.81</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granules A without active substance</entry><entry align="center">3.355 ± 0.376</entry><entry align="center">&lt;60</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granules A + 30% acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">1.379 ± 0.108</entry><entry align="center">&lt;20</entry><entry align="center">1.41</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granule A' without active substance</entry><entry align="center">3.787 ± 0.192</entry><entry align="center">&lt;180</entry><entry align="center">0.20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Granule A' + 30% acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">1.548 ± 0.123</entry><entry align="center">&lt;40</entry><entry align="center">0.40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ludipress® without active substance</entry><entry align="center">0.302 ± 0.043</entry><entry align="center">&lt;50</entry><entry align="center">2.99</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ludipress® + 30% acetaminophen</entry><entry align="center">0.226 ± 0.055</entry><entry align="center">&lt;35</entry><entry align="center">3.88</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>CONCLUSIONS, RAMIFICATIONS AND SCOPE</heading><p num="0054">From the above examples and discussions, those skilled in the art can appreciate that the
present invention is a simple yet effective and novel means to prepare direct tabletting
formulations and aids. Thermal adhesion granulation can be applied to a wide range of
diluents, binders and active ingredients, and can utilize both aqueous and organic granulation
fluids. The process is an attractive alternative to wet granulation and offers the following
advantages:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>Due to the significantly lower amount of water utilized, TAG does not decrease the
compressibility of MCC, a problem often encountered in wet granulation.</li><li>The low amount of granulating fluids utilized, and the potential for granulation in a
controlled oxygen-free headspace environment (due to granulation in a closed system),
translate to greater drug stability.</li><li>The time consuming steps of wet sieving, followed by drying and milling of the granules,
are eliminated in TAG.</li><li>The low amount of granulating fluids utilized simplifies the manufacturing process and
reduces production time. This translates into greater production volume and reduced
production costs.</li><li>Occupational safety and environmental protection are increased, due to the low solvent
requirement of TAG and its ability to accomplish granulate in a confined closed system.</li></ul></p><p num="0055">While the above descriptions and examples contain many specificities, these should not be
construed as limitations on the scope of the invention, but rather as an exemplification of one
preferred embodiment thereof. Many other variations of TAG are possible. For example, the
diluents may be mixed at different ratios, either before or after thermal adhesion granulation,
to form tabletting aids with a combination of properties. One such combination is a blend of
MCC and lactose to form a tabletting aid with water-insoluble and -soluble portions. Yet
another possibility is the addition of other tabletting excipients, such as color, flavoring, and
glidants (e.g., silicon dioxide or calcium silicate), before or after thermal adhesion granulation.
As well, the thermal adhesion granulation process could be applied to suit the particular
granulation needs of a variety of industries other than the pharmaceutical industry.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A thermal adhesion granulation process for preparing direct tabletting formulations or
aids, comprising the step of subjecting all or part of a mixture comprising.
<claim-text><claim-text>A) from about 5 to about 99% by weight of one or more diluent excipients and/or from
0 to about 99% by weight of a pharmaceutically-active ingredient;</claim-text><claim-text>B) from about 1 to about 95% by weight of a binder excipient; and
optionally with,</claim-text><claim-text>C) from 0 to about 10% by weight of a disintegrant excipient;</claim-text></claim-text>
to heating at a temperature range of from about 30 to about 130°C under the condition
of from about 0.1 to about 20% initial moisture content and/or from about 0.1 to about
20% initial content of a pharmaceutically-acceptable organic solvent in a closed system
under mixing by tumble rotation until the formation of granules.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the temperature range is from about 40 to about
110°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the temperature range is from about 60 to about
105°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the initial moisture content is from about 2 to
about 15%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the initial moisture content is from about 4 to
about 10%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the initial organic solvent content is from about
0.1 to about 10%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, where the initial organic solvent content is from about
0.5 to about 5%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the diluent excipient is powdered cellulose,
microcrystalline cellulose, lactose, starch, or dibasic calcium phosphate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the pharmaceutically-active ingredient is
acetaminophen or ascorbic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the binder excipient is soluble polyvinyl
pyrrolidone or hydroxypropylcellulose.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the disintegrant excipient is crospovidone,
sodium starch glycolate, reticulated carboxymethylcellulose, or low-substituted
hydroxypropylcellulose.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the diluent excipient is microcrystalline
cellulose.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 12, wherein the microcrystalline cellulose is of a type in
which about 90% of the particles are in the range from about 1 µm to about 125µm, and
the average particle size is from about 10µm to about 70µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the binder excipient is soluble polyvinyl
pyrrolidone.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 14, wherein the soluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone has a K value
of from about 12 to about 120.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 14, wherein the soluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone has a K value
of from about 20 to about 95.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A process as defined in daim 14, wherein the soluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone has a K value
of from about 25 to about 35.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 1, wherein the binder excipient further contains from 0 to
about 10% (by weight with respect to the binder) of an anticaking agent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 18, wherein the binder excipient contains from about 0.01
to about 10% (by weight with respect to the binder) of an anticaking agent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 18, wherein the binder excipient contains from about 2 to
about 4% (by weight with respect to the binder) of an anticaking agent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>A process as defined in claim 18, wherein the anticaking agent is dibasic calcium
phosphate anhydrous.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>A product of thermal adhesion granulation process for preparing direct tabletting
formulations or aids as defined in claim 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>A powder mixture of soluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone containing from about 0.01 to about
10% (by weight with respect to the polyvinyl pyrrolidone) of dibasic calcium phosphate
anhydrous.</claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>A direct tabletting formulation or aid comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>i) from about 5 to about 99% by weight of powder cellulose, microcrystalline cellulose,
lactose, starch, or dibasic calcium phosphate;</claim-text><claim-text>ii) from 0 to about 99% by weight of acetaminophen or ascorbic acid;</claim-text><claim-text>iii) from about 1 to about 95% by weight of a soluble polyvinyl pyrrolidone which
contains from about 0.01 to about 10% (by weight with respect to the polyvinyl
pyrrolidone) of dibasic calcium phosphate anhydrous; and</claim-text><claim-text>iv) from 0 to about 10% by weight of crospovidone, sodium starch glycolate, reticulated
carboxymethylcellulose, or low-substituted hydroxypropylcellulose.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="25"><claim-text>A tablet, which comprises a product as defined in claim 22, a powder mixture as defined
in claim 23, or a tabletting formulation or aid as defined in claim 24.</claim-text></claim><claim num="26"><claim-text>A capsule, which comprises a product as defined in claim 22, a powder mixture as
defined in claim 23, or a tabletting formulation or aid as defined in claim 24.</claim-text></claim><claim num="27"><claim-text>A pellet, which comprises a product as defined in claim 22, a powder mixture as defined
in claim 23, or a tabletting formulation or aid as defined in claim 24.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>