<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1400492-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1400492" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="28675086" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040324"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1400492-A2" status="new" fvid="24011195"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1400492</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20040324</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03254687-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03254687</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030728</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-22768202-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>22768202</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020826</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  17/02        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  17/02        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B03D   1/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B03D   1/14        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   1/00        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   1/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   1/38        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   1/38        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   9/00        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   9/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   9/02        20060101A I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   9/02        20060101C I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01D  17/02B+/02D+/02F+/02F4+/02H</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B03D   1/14C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C02F   1/38</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M02F1:00R2D2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M02F101:32</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M02F9:00+1/38+1/28</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren und Vorrichtung zur Entfernung von Kohlenwasserstoffen aus Wasser durch Flotation mit Luft</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method and apparatus for removing hydrocarbons from water by air flotation</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Méthode et dispositif d'élimination d'hydrocarbures présents dans des eaux par flottation à air</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-10201916-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>10201916</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0695719-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0695719</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4094783-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4094783</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6398966-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6398966</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999000169-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999000169</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>AMCOL INTERNATIONAL CORP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AMCOL INTERNATIONAL CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>AMCOL INTERNATIONAL CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>1 North Arlington, 1500 West Shore Drive</street><city>Chicago, Illinois 60004</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DARLINGTON JR JERALD W</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>JUST GERARD A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OCCHIPINTI JOHN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SMITH JEFFREY J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DARLINGTON, JR, JERALD W.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>JUST, GERARD A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OCCHIPINTI, JOHN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SMITH, JEFFREY J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DARLINGTON, JR, JERALD W.</last-name><address><street>20613 Beth Court, Marengo</street><city>Illinois 60152</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>JUST, GERARD A.</last-name><address><street>2500 Noccalula Road</street><city>Gadsen, Alabama 35904</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OCCHIPINTI, JOHN</last-name><address><street>5511 Langhorne Court</street><city>Katy, Texas 77450</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SMITH, JEFFREY J.</last-name><address><street>219 Olivier Street</street> <city>New Orleans, Louisiana 71004</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor> </inventors> <agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>W.P. Thompson &amp;amp; Co.</last-name> <address><street>Coopers Building, Church Street</street><city>Liverpool L1 3AB</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>GB</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An improved production water treatment system and method are
disclosed. The treatment apparatus includes a vertically oriented vessel (11) with
tangentially disposed injection nozzles including one or more water input inlets
(P<sub>1</sub>,P<sub>2</sub>) for the introduction of production water and one or
more recycle fluid/sparge gas inlets (R<sub>1</sub>,R<sub>2</sub>,R<sub>3</sub>,R<sub>4</sub>)
for the introduction of recycled water from the vessel (11) and a sparge gas. The tangential
orientation of the injection nozzles creates a cyclonic flow within the vessel for
improved sparge gas bubble/hydrocarbon contact. A hydrocarbon-rich layer migrates
to the top surface (14) of the liquid in the vessel (11) where it is removed about a center axis of
the vessel (11). The resulting hydrocarbon-lean production water has a sufficiently low
hydrocarbon content that it is eligible for more intensive processing, such as with
organophillic clay cartridges.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="76" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="82"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b><u style="single">Technical Field</u></b></heading><p num="0001">An apparatus and method for separating hydrocarbons and other
organic materials from water, such as acidflow back water, completion fluid water,
produced water and rain water collected from off-shore oil drilling and production
platforms, are disclosed. More specifically, an apparatus is disclosed for pre-treating
these production waters generated on off-shore oil drilling and production platforms
by injecting the production water in an enclosed vessel and generating a cyclonic flow
within the vessel. Recycled water from the vessel and a sparge gas are also
tangentially injected into the vessel to further encourage the cyclonic flow. The gas
and hydrocarbon-rich water migrate towards the top surface of the liquid in the vessel
and towards the axial center of the vessel where the hydrocarbon-rich water is purged.
Hydrocarbon-lean water is then purged from a bottom section of the vessel and
discharged or processed further.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Background of the Related Art</u></b></heading><p num="0002">During crude oil production, a significant amount of water is co-produced
with the oil. This "produced water" is contaminated with residual or
hydrocarbons and therefore is a substantial waste stream. For example, it is estimated
that 380 million tons of produced water was generated in the North Sea during the
2001 production year. While new operational fields produce relatively minor
amounts of water, <i>e.g</i>., 10-20% percent of the total production (<i>i.e</i>., water and oil), as
an oil field ages, the produced water volume increases to 80-90% of the total
production. These huge volumes of produced water must be treated before they are
returned to the sea because they contain significant amounts of hydrocarbon
contaminants.</p><p num="0003">Currently, off-shore production facilities treat the hydrocarbon-contaminated
production water by adding oil coalescing and water clarifying chemical
agents to assist in a mechanical separation of the hydrocarbons from the water.
However, this technology results in the discharge of production water to the ocean
which still contains hydrocarbons in the range of 20-40 ppm and additional trace 
impurities such as benzene related compounds, phenols, alkyl phenols and
polyaromatic hydrocarbons in concentrations ranging from 100 to 10,000 ppb. While
a 20-40 ppm hydrocarbon content meets current regulations, it is been found that the
discharge of production water with the above-noted trace impurities can adversely
affect marine life.</p><p num="0004">Often, large amounts of natural gas are produced with crude oil. To
separate the gas from the oil and the oil from the water, three phase separators have
been developed. In a three phase separator, the gas is first separated from the oil and
water and the oil layer is physically separated from the water and sent to a dehydrator
to remove residual water. The water phase, which includes a small fraction of
residual oil, enters a water skimmer to skim the free oil off of the top of the water
layer. After skimming, the water layer, which still contains a substantial amount of
hydrocarbons, enters a horizontal induced gas floatation separator. These horizontal
induced gas floatation (HIGF) separators can produce a water phase with a
hydrocarbon content of 20-40 ppm.</p><p num="0005">HIGF separators work by bubbling a gas through the production water
which results in hydrocarbon droplets floating to the surface. Typically, the gas used
is natural gas produced at the well. Nitrogen or other inert gases may be used as well.
Each HIGF separator includes a number of cells, each with its own gas diffuser to
maximize the natural gas bubble/hydrocarbon droplet contact. While the HIGF
separators are commonly used, they suffer from numerous drawbacks.</p><p num="0006">At the outset, HIGF separators are extremely large. Their length can
reach 60 feet which represents a tremendous amount of deck space, which is at a
premium on an off-shore oil platform. Many older platforms, where space is limited,
cannot be outfitted with such separators. It will be noted that all currently available
"horizontal" induced gas floatation separators have a length or width substantially
greater than their height.</p><p num="0007">Further, HIGF separators to date have not been able to reduce
hydrocarbon concentration below an approximately 20 ppm threshold level. While
this level meets current regulatory standards, it falls short of the proposed standards
for the North Sea which may take effect as early as 2005. </p><p num="0008">HIGF separators are also susceptible to wave motion experienced by
modem platforms. Specifically, modem deep water platforms are not permanently
anchored to the sea floor but, instead, are tethered and move with currents. Thus,
these floating platforms will sway and roll with wave motion. This rolling causes the
water inside the HIGF separators to form waves, which makes skimming
hydrocarbons from the water surface difficult and often ineffective. Further, intense
wave motion will cause some units to shut down thereby creating disruptions in
platform production because of a lack of storage capacity for untreated production
water.</p><p num="0009">Also, because of their large size, in the event the production water
output exceeds expectations, operators are unable to expand capacity by adding
additional HIGF separators because of a lack of available floor space. As a result,
either the operator must reduce production or discharge produced water with a
hydrocarbon content greater than the regulatory limit.</p><p num="0010">Further, the flow rate of production water from a well can vary greatly
and HIGF separators operate more efficiently in a steady state condition and the
efficiencies of these systems is compromised with varying input flows. Still further,
HIGF separators are limited in their ability to treat water with higher hydrocarbon
concentrations, <i>i.e</i>. greater than 300 ppm. Concentrations exceeding 300 ppm
generally exceed the separators ability to achieve acceptable hydrocarbon removal.
HIGF separators are also designed to remove dispersed oil or hydrocarbon droplets.
Their ability to remove partially soluble components such as alkyl phenols and
polyaromatic hydrocarbons is extremely limited as these components are relatively
soluble in water and do not respond to gas/bubble contact. As noted above, these
compounds are extremely harmful to marine life.</p><p num="0011">One substitute for HIGF separators has been suggested in the form of a
vertical vortex separator. One example is disclosed in WO 99/00169. The disclosed
apparatus relies upon creating a vortex in a cylindrical vessel for purposes of
separating oil from water. However, this apparatus is suitable only for preliminary
separation of oil from production water and does not reduce the hydrocarbon content
in the production water to a level acceptable for discharge or more intensive treatment
such as filtering with organophillic clays. </p><p num="0012">The treatment of production water with organophilic clays is also
known and is disclosed by commonly owned U.S. Patent Nos. 5,935,444, 6,398,966
and 6,398,951, all of which are incorporated herewith. The production water is
typically introduced into a contained vessel which contains a plurality of cartridges
containing the organophilic clay. The production water flows through the packed
cartridge beds of organophilic clay and the hydrocarbon contaminants are adsorbed
onto the clay particles. The process is very efficient, resulting in extremely low
hydrocarbon content of the treated production water.</p><p num="0013">However, it has been found that when the hydrocarbon content of the
production water inputted into an organophilic clay containing vessel exceeds 100
ppm, the available adsorbing sites on the clay are readily used up and the cartridges
must be replaced frequently, thereby increasing costs and creating time delays. The
vortex creating apparatus of WO 99/00169 is not suitable as a sole pre-treatment of
production water upstream of an organophilic clay filtering apparatus.</p><p num="0014">Therefore, there is a two-fold need for improved methods of treating
production water, especially on off-shore oil platforms. First, an improved method
and apparatus is required which avoids the disadvantages of the HIGF separators
described above. Further, there is a need for an improved hydrocarbon/water
separation method and apparatus which can be used as an effective pretreatment prior
to additional treatment of the water with organophilic clay cartridges.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Summary of the Disclosure</u></b></heading><p num="0015">An improved apparatus for separating hydrocarbons from water is
disclosed. The apparatus comprises a vessel having a height and a diameter. The
height of the vessel is greater than the diameter of the vessel thereby providing it with
a "vertical" configuration which is preferred by off-shore oil platform operators. The
vessel further comprises an enclosed top and bottom with a vertical cylindrical section
extending therebetween.</p><p num="0016">At least one input inlet is provided that extends through the vertical
cylindrical section. The input inlet is connected to a supply of input liquid, <i>i</i>.<i>e</i>.,
untreated production water. The input inlet is directed "tangentially" or at an angle of
less than or equal to 45° with respect to a tangent of the vertical cylindrical section so
that the input inlet can encourage or generate a cyclonic flow within the vessel. </p><p num="0017">The apparatus further includes at least one recycle fluid/sparge gas
inlet that extends through the vertical cylindrical section of the vessel as well. The
recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet is connected to a recycled pump which, in turn, is
connected to the vessel by a recycle line. The recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet is also
connected to a source of sparge gas. Similar to the input inlet, the recycle fluid/sparge
gas inlet is also directed "tangentially" or at an angle of less than or equal to 45° with
respect to a tangent of the vertical cylindrical section for generating or encouraging
cyclonic flow within the vessel.</p><p num="0018">The apparatus also includes a hydrocarbon-lean water outlet. The
apparatus further includes an upwardly directed collection bucket disposed along an
axial center of the vessel. The collection bucket is also connected to a hydrocarbon-rich
outlet line. The vessel is also equipped with a sparge gas outlet line.</p><p num="0019">In a refinement, the apparatus further includes an upwardly directed
recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet. This upwardly directed recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet is
also connected to the recycle pump and the supply of sparge gas and is directed
upwardly to generate or encourage upward flow within the vessel.</p><p num="0020">In another refinement, the at least one input inlet comprises two input
inlets disposed diametrically opposite the vessel from one another. The two input
inlets are also disposed at a common vertical height.</p><p num="0021">Further, three input inlets may be provided which are equidistantly
spaced around the vessel, or at approximately 120° intervals around the vessel.
Again, a common vertical height is preferred.</p><p num="0022">In another refinement, the at least one recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet
further comprises two recycle fluid/sparge gas inlets disposed diametrically opposite
the vessel from one another and having common vertical height. Preferably, three
recycle fluid/sparge gas inlets are provided, equidistantly spaced around the vessel at
a common vertical height. In still a further refinement, the common vertical height of
the recycle fluid/sparge gas inlets is disposed below the common vertical height of the
input inlets.</p><p num="0023">In still another refinement, the input inlets are disposed approximately
one foot below the surface of the circulating cyclonic flow within the vessel. The 
recycle fluid/sparge gas inlets are disposed below the input inlets, and preferably at or
about a mid-point of the vessel.</p><p num="0024">In another refinement, a ratio of the vessel to the diameter of the vessel
ranges from about 5:1 to about 1.5:1, more preferably about 2.5.</p><p num="0025">Further, as noted above, to meet increasing demanding environmental
concerns, the hydrocarbon-lean water outlet may be connected to a secondary
treatment vessel containing organophilic media for adsorbing any residual
hydrocarbons that remain in the pre-treated production water.</p><p num="0026">A method for reducing hydrocarbon content in a stream of production
water is also disclosed. The method comprises tangentially injecting the production
water into a cylindrical vessel to encourage cyclonic flow within the vessel,
tangentially injecting the flow of recycled water from the vessel and sparge gas into
the vessel at a level below a point where the production water is injected and to
further encourage cyclonic flow within the vessel, allowing the sparge gas and
hydrocarbon-rich water to migrate to a top surface of the circulating liquid within the
vessel, purging the hydrocarbon-rich water at a top surface of the circulating liquid
and along a central axis of the vessel, and purging hydrocarbon-lean water from a
lower point in the vessel below where the flow of recycled water and sparge gas are
injected into the vessel.</p><p num="0027">In a refinement, the method also includes maintaining a positive gage
pressure within the vessel with additional sparge gas or an inner gas. In another
refinement, the sparge gas is natural gas co-produced with the production water to be
treated.</p><p num="0028">An improved system for treating production waters is also disclosed.
The improved system includes a vertically-oriented pre-treatment vessel where the
production water is mixed with a sparge gas, such as co-produced natural gas, and a
hydrocarbon-rich layer is skimmed off the top surface while a hydrocarbon-lean layer
is removed through a lower portion of the pre-treatment vessel. The hydrocarbon-lean
water is then transmitted to a secondary treatment vessel where it is contacted
with an organophillic clay.</p><heading>Brief Description of the Drawings</heading><p num="0029">The invention is illustrated, by way of example, more or less
diagrammatically in the accompanying drawings wherein:
<sl><li>FIG. 1 is a schematic illustration of a production water treatment
system made in accordance with this disclosure;</li><li>FIG. 2A is a partial perspective view of the vessel illustrated in FIG. 1
showing the relative placement of the production water input nozzles and recycle
fluid/sparge gas input nozzles;</li><li>FIG. 2B is a top sectional view of the vessel illustrated in FIG. 1,
particularly illustrating the preferred placement of the production water input nozzles
and recycle fluid/sparge gas input nozzles;</li><li>FIG. 2C illustrates the tangential angle of the input nozzles relative to
the vessel wall;</li><li>FIG. 3 is a perspective view of the bucket, baffle and partial view of
the hydrocarbon-rich outlet line;</li><li>FIG. 4 is a schematic illustration of the apparatus of FIG. 1 connected
to a secondary treatment vessel containing an organophilic clay filter system; and</li><li>FIG. 5 illustrates, graphically, the hydrocarbon concentration reduction
achieved by an apparatus made in accordance with this disclosure.</li></sl></p><p num="0030">It will be understood that the drawings are not necessarily to scale in
that the embodiments are illustrated using graphic symbols, diagrammatic
representations and fragmentary views. In certain instances, details which are not
necessary for an understanding of the disclosed apparatuses and methods or which
render other details difficult to perceive may have been omitted. It should be
understood, of course, that this disclosure is not necessarily limited to the particular
embodiments illustrated herein.</p><heading>Detailed Description of the Present and Preferred Embodiments</heading><p num="0031">Turning to FIG. 1, an improved apparatus 10 is disclosed which has a
vertical orientation and can provide a superior substitute for the currently employed
HIGF separators. The apparatus 10 includes a vessel 11 which has a height to width 
ratio ranging from about 5.0 to about 1.5, preferably about 2.5. One suitable size for
the vessel 11 is a height of 10 feet and a width or diameter of 4 feet.</p><p num="0032">Production water is introduced into the vessel through one or more
input inlets indicated at P<sub>1</sub>, P<sub>2</sub> in FIGS. 1 and 2A-2C. It will be noted that the number
of production water input inlets can vary in anywhere from 1 to 3 or 4 and that the use
of two production water input inlets P<sub>1</sub>, P<sub>2</sub> as shown in FIGS. 1 and 2A-2C is an
example, albeit a preferred example. Referring to FIGS. 2A-C, it will be noted that
the production water input inlets P<sub>1</sub>, P<sub>2</sub> are directed "tangentially" with respect to the
vessel 11. That is, the nozzles P<sub>1</sub>, P<sub>2</sub> are directed at a positive angle with respect to a
tangent to the cylindrical section of the vessel 11 as shown in FIG. 2C. Specifically,
any nozzle such as P<sub>1</sub>, P<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub> or R<sub>3</sub> will pass through the vessel 11 as shown at an
angle  with respect to a tangent T taken at the entry point of the nozzle. The angle 
can vary, but should preferably be less than or equal to 45° so that the injected fluid
encourages a cyclonic flow within the vessel 11 for enhance mixing of sparge gas and
production liquid as discussed below.</p><p num="0033">Returning to FIGS. 2B, the production water input inlets P<sub>1</sub>, P<sub>2</sub>, are
preferably disposed diametrically opposite the vessel 11 from each other as shown in
FIG. 2B. If three production water input inlets are utilized, then it would be preferred
that these inlets be equidistantly spaced around the vessel 11 or 120° apart from one
another. It will be also noted that the height of the production water input inlets P<sub>1</sub>,
P<sub>2</sub>, are about the same and are disclosed towards the top 12 of the vessel 11 as
opposed to the bottom 13. The production water input inlets P<sub>1</sub>, P<sub>2</sub>, is preferably
disposed about a foot below the surface 14 of the liquid circulated in the vessel 11.</p><p num="0034">In addition to the production water input inlets P<sub>1</sub>, P<sub>2</sub>, one or more
recycled fluid/sparge gas inlet nozzles are utilized, three of which are shown at R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>,
R<sub>3</sub> in FIGS. 1 and 2. If three of these inlets are utilized, the nozzle should be
equidistantly spaced around the vessel wall 15 as shown in FIG. 2B. Water is
withdrawn from the vessel 11 through the recycle line 16 where it is drawn into a
pump 17 and mixed with sparge gas via the line 19 which recycles sparge gas from
the vessel 11 and introduces the sparge gas through the eductors 20 where the sparge
gas is mixed with the liquid being delivered by the recycle pump 17. The recycle
fluid/sparge gas mixture is then injected into the vessel 11 by way of the nozzles R<sub>1</sub>, 
R<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>3</sub> and R<sub>4</sub>. Again, the number of recycle water/sparge gas nozzles R can vary and
can range from as few as one to more than the three that are shown.</p><p num="0035">In addition to the tangentially disposed recycle fluid/sparge gas nozzles
R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>3</sub> shown in FIGS. 2A-2B, an additional nozzle is shown at R<sub>4</sub> which is
directed upwardly and disposed towards the bottom 13 of the vessel 11. This
upwardly directed recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet R<sub>4</sub> promotes upward flow within the
vessel 11 in addition to the cyclonic flow provided by the nozzles P<sub>1-2</sub>, R<sub>1-3</sub>.</p><p num="0036">The inventors have found that the combination of the cyclonic flow
produced by the nozzles P<sub>1-2</sub>, R<sub>1-3</sub> and the turbulent upward flow provided by the
nozzle R<sub>4</sub> in addition to the injection of sparge gas using the eductors 20, which
would normally be co-produced natural gas, provides for improved mixing of the
sparge gas with the produced water, improved contact between the gas bubbles and
the hydrocarbon contained in the produced water and therefore better separation that
HIGF separators and previously available vortex separators.</p><p num="0037">Due to the improved mixing of the sparge gas bubbles and production
water, hydrocarbon-rich production water migrates to the surface 14 of the liquid
contained in the vessel and further migrates towards an axial center of the vessel 11.
The hydrocarbon-rich water is then collected at the bucket shown at 23 which is
connected to a hydrocarbon-rich outlet line 24.</p><p num="0038">In contrast, hydrocarbon-lean water is removed through the lower
outlet 26 where it may be discharged or, in the alternative, as shown in FIG. 4,
treatment may be continued in one or more vessels shown at 28. It has been found
that additional treatment with organophillic clay is preferred. Further, the apparatus
10 is a preferred pre-treatment prior to additional treatment with organophillic clay.
Specifically, as shown graphically in FIG. 5, the apparatus 10 is capable of reducing
the hydrocarbon content in production water that is greater than 200 ppm to a value of
less than 50 ppm. As noted above, when production water is fed into an organophillic
clay treatment system that has a hydrocarbon content of greater than 100 ppm, the
organophillic clay cartridges tend to foul quickly and require frequent replacement
which is time consuming and costly. Thus, the disclosed apparatus, which can easily
reduce the hydrocarbon content to a less than 50 ppm, is a preferred pre-treatment for
systems that incorporate organophillic clay technology. </p><p num="0039">Flow through the hydrocarbon-lean outlet 26 is controlled by the valve
36 which is controlled by a liquid level controller 37.</p><p num="0040">The vessel 10 should be operated at a positive gage pressure,
preferably ranging from 5 to 10 psig. The pressure may be maintained with a gas
source 29 which may be sparge gas or an inert gas. The gas applied 29 is connected
to the vessel by way of the line 31 and control valve 34. Control valve 35 is used to
bleed excess pressure. A convenient sparge gas is, of course, co-produced natural
gas.</p><p num="0041">An apparatus with the general nozzle configuration illustrated in FIGS.
2A-2C was tested and the experimental results are presented in FIG. 5. The vessel
pressure was maintained between 6 and 10 psig and at a temperature of about 145°F.
The produced water flow rate through the apparatus ranged from 2 to 3 barrels per
minute (BPM). A standard production water treatment chemical, 6022Y, was also
added.</p><p num="0042">Further, referring to FIGS. 1 and 3, it has been found that the
performance of the apparatus 10 is improved with the use of a baffle 31 which aides
in skimming the hydrocarbon-rich water off the top surface 14 and directing it
towards the slot 33 of the bucket 23. Standard wire-type baffles 31 may be employed.
Preferably, the baffle 31 is parabolically shaped to compliment the contour of the
surface 14 of the cyclonically flowing fluid in the vessel 11.</p><p num="0043">It will finally be noted that use of the apparatus 10 in conjunction with
organophillic clay technology as represented in U.S. Patent Nos. 5,935,444, 6,398,966
and 6,398,951 is expected to have a substantial benefit to the environment.
Specifically, it has been found that benzene related compounds, phenols, alkyl
phenols and polyaromatic hydrocarbons, even in trace amounts ranging from 100 to
10,000 ppb, present a substantial threat to marine life, including many species of male
fish. Utilizing the apparatus 10 as disclosed herein in combination with organophillic
clay technology can all but eliminate the discharge of these trace impurities back to
the ocean.</p><p num="0044">While only certain embodiments have been set forth, alternative
embodiments and various modifications will be apparent from the above description 
to those skilled in the art. These and other alternatives are considered equivalents
within the spirit and scope of this disclosure.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An apparatus (10) for separating hydrocarbons from water, the
apparatus (10) comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a vessel (11) having a height and a diameter, the height being greater than
the diameter, the vessel (11) further comprising an enclosed top (12) and bottom
(13) with a vertical cylindrical section (15) extending therebetween,</claim-text><claim-text>at least one input inlet (P1, P2) extending through the vertical cylindrical
section (15) of the vessel (11), the input inlet (P1, P2) connected to a supply of
hydrocarbon-rich input liquid to be treated, the input inlet (P1, P2) being directed
at an angle of less than or equal to 45° with respect to a tangent (T) of the vertical
cylindrical section (15) for generating a cyclonic flow within the vessel (11),</claim-text><claim-text>at least one recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet (R1, R2, R3) extending through
the vertical cylindrical section (15) of the vessel (11) the recycle fluid/sparge gas
inlet (R1, R2, R3) connected to a recycle pump (17) and source of sparge gas ( 19),
the recycle pump (17) connected to the vessel (11) by a recycle line (16), the
recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet (R1, R2, R3) being directed at an angle of less than or
equal to 45° with respect to a tangent of the vertical cylindrical section (15) for
generating a cyclonic flow within the vessel (11),</claim-text><claim-text>a hydrocarbon-lean water outlet (26),</claim-text><claim-text>an upwardly directed collection bucket (23) disposed along an axial center
of the vessel (11), the collection bucket (23) connected to a hydrocarbon-rich
outlet line (24),</claim-text><claim-text>a sparge gas input/outlet line (31 ).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>An apparatus (10) as claimed in claim 1, further comprising an
upwardly directed recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet (R4), the upwardly directed
recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet (R4) connected to the recycle pump (17) and the
supply of sparge gas (19), the upwardly directed recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet (R4)
generating an upward flow within the vessel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 1 or 2, wherein the at least one input
inlet comprises two input inlets (P1, P2) disposed diametrically opposite the vessel
from one another.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in any one of claims 1 to 3, wherein the at
least one recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet (R1, R2, R3) comprises three recycle
fluid/sparge gas inlets (R1, R2, R3) equidistantly spaced around the vessel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein
the at least one input inlet (R1, R2, R3) is disposed vertically above the at least one
recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet (R4).</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 2 or any one of claims 3 to 5 when
dependant upon claim 2, wherein the at least one input inlet (P1, P2) is disposed
vertically above the at least one recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet (R1, R2, R3) and the
upwardly directed recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet (R4).</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein a
ratio of the height of the vessel (11) to the diameter of the vessel (11) ranges from
about 5:1 to about 1.5:1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 7, wherein the ratio is about 2.5:1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein
the collection bucket (23) is connected to a radially outwardly extending baffle
(31 ) for skimming hydrocarbons off of a surface of the liquid in the vessel (11).</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 9, wherein the baffle (31 ) is
parabolically shaped.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein
the hydrocarbon-lean water outlet line (26) is connected to a secondary treatment
vessel (28) containing an organophilic media providing intimate contact with the
hydrocarbon-lean water and adsorption of hydrocarbon contaminant in the
hydrocarbon-lean water on the media.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, further
comprising an eductor (20) disposed between the at least one recycle fluid/sparge
gas inlet (R1, R2, R3) and the source of sparge gas (19)for introducing sparge gas
into the recycled fluid downstream of the recycle pump (17).</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>An apparatus as claimed in claim 12, wherein the source of sparge gas
(19) comprises sparge gas recycled from the vessel (11) as well as a separate
supply of sparge gas (29) connected to the sparge gas input/outlet line (31 ) for
pressurizing the vessel (11).</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A method for reducing hydrocarbon content in a stream of production
water, the method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>tangentially injecting the production water into a cylindrical vessel (11) to
encourage cyclonic flow within the vessel (11),</claim-text><claim-text>tangentially injecting a flow of recycled water from the vessel (11) and
sparge gas into the vessel (11) at a level (R1, R2, R3, R4) below a point (P1, P2)
where the production water is injected and to further encourage cyclonic flow
within the vessel (11),</claim-text><claim-text>allowing the sparge gas and hydrocarbon-rich water to migrate to a top
surface (14) of liquid in the vessel (11),</claim-text><claim-text>purging the hydrocarbon-rich water at the top surface (14) and along a
central axis of the vessel (11),</claim-text><claim-text>purging the hydrocarbon-lean water from a lower point (26) in the vessel
(11) below where the flow of recycled water and sparge gas are injected (R1, R2,
R3, R4) into the vessel.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A method as claimed in claim 14, further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>maintaining a positive gauge pressure within the vessel (11) with
additional sparge gas or an inert gas.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A method as claimed in claim 14 or 15, further comprising purging
sparge gas from a top portion (12) of the vessel (11) in the event the pressure
exceeds a desired positive gauge pressure.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of claims 14 to 16, further
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>introducing the hydrocarbon-lean water into a secondary treatment vessel
(28) containing an organophilic media, and</claim-text><claim-text>allowing intimate contact with the hydrocarbon-lean water and adsorption
of hydrocarbon contaminant in the hydrocarbon-lean water on the media.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A system for separating hydrocarbons from water, the system
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first pre-treatment vessel (11), the first pre-treatment vessel comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>a height and a diameter, the height being greater than the diameter,
the pre-treatment vessel further comprising an enclosed top (12) and bottom (13)
with a vertical cylindrical section (15) extending therebetween,</claim-text><claim-text>at least one input inlet (P1, P2) extending through the vertical
cylindrical section (15) of the pre-treatment vessel (11), the input inlet (P1, P2)
connected to a supply of hydrocarbon-rich input liquid to be treated,</claim-text><claim-text>at least one recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet (R1, R2, R3) extending
through the vertical cylindrical section (15) of the pre-treatment vessel (11), the
recycle fluid/sparge gas inlet (R1, R2, R3) connected to a recycle pump (17) and a
source of sparge gas (19), the recycle pump (17) connected to the pre-treatment
vessel (11) by a recycle line (16),</claim-text><claim-text>a hydrocarbon-lean water outlet (26),</claim-text><claim-text>an upwardly directed collection bucket (23) disposed along an axial
center of the pre-treatment vessel (11), the collection bucket (23) connected to a
hydrocarbon-rich outlet line (24),</claim-text><claim-text>a sparge gas inlet/outlet line (31 ),</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>the hydrocarbon-lean water outlet (26) connected to a secondary treatment
vessel (28) containing an organophilic media.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>