<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1167475-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1167475" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="24378796" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020102"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1167475-A2" status="new" fvid="23329362"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1167475</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20020102</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01112359-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01112359</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010521</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-59442200-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>59442200</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000615</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   5/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   5/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  17/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  17/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 133/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 133/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 133/14        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 133/14        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 133/24        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 133/26        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  17/00D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  17/00J6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D   5/02K4</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Wässrige Beschichtungszusammensetzung mit verbesserter Transparenz</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Aqueous coating compositions having improved transparency</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition de revêtement aqueuse avec transparence améliorée</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0174628-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0174628</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0777707-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0777707</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="FR-2766107-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>FR</country><doc-number>2766107</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DU PONT</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>E.I. DUPONT DE NEMOURS AND COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>E.I. DUPONT DE NEMOURS AND COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1007 Market Street</street><city>Wilmington, Delaware 19898</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KIRSHENBAUM KENNETH S</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MC INTYRE PATRICK F</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VISSCHER KARYLN B</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KIRSHENBAUM, KENNETH S.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MC INTYRE, PATRICK F.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VISSCHER, KARYLN B.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KIRSHENBAUM, KENNETH S.</last-name><address><street>4160 Wendell Road</street><city>West Bloomfield, MI 48323</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MC INTYRE, PATRICK F.</last-name><address><street>1019 Radley Drive</street><city>West Chester, Pennsylvania 19382</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VISSCHER, KARYLN B.</last-name><address><street>2903 Hamilton Drive</street><city>Voorhees, New Jersey 08043</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Abitz, Walter, Dr.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>Patentanwälte Abitz &amp;amp; Partner Postfach 86 01 09</street><city>81628 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>BE</country><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An aqueous coating composition having improved transparency and
reduced haze containing:
<sl><li>(a) an aqueous carrier medium;</li><li>(b) transparent iron oxide pigment particles stabilized by</li><li>(c) a mixture of acrylic copolymer pigment dispersants of
<sl><li>(i) an acrylic copolymer dispersant having a hydrophilic
stabilizing segment and a hydrophobic adsorbing segment having
acid groups attached thereto; and</li><li>(ii) an acrylic copolymer dispersant having a hydrophilic
stabilizing segment and a hydrophobic adsorbing segment having
phosphate groups attached thereto; and</li><li>(iii) an acrylic copolymer dispersant having a hydrophilic
stabilizing segment and a hydrophobic adsorbing segment having
alkyl amino groups and preferably benzyl groups attached thereto;</li></sl></li><li>(d) a film forming polymeric binder; and</li><li>(e) a crosslinking agent for the binder.</li></sl></p><p>Pigment dispersions of the forgoing acrylic copolymer dispersant
combination and process for forming the dispersions also are part of this invention.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></b></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to an aqueous coating composition and in
particular to an aqueous coating composition containing a transparent iron oxide
pigment dispersion formed with a synergistic mixture of acrylic copolymer
pigment dispersants that has improved transparency and reduced haze.</p><p num="0002">The use of transparent iron oxide pigments in coating compositions
used in particular for exterior finishes for automobiles and trucks to provide the
finish with high transparency, glamour and aesthetic quality is well known. High
film transparency is particularly important for automotive coatings containing
metallic flake pigments, such as aluminum flake, as it is needed to impart high
metallic luster to the finish. To obtain films of high transparency, the pigment
particles must be fully deflocculated and uniformly dispersed in the coating
composition. Pigment dispersions stabilized with copolymer dispersants are
generally used to disperse and maintain, in a dispersed state, transparent iron
oxide pigments in coating compositions. Copolymer dispersants used to form
such pigment dispersions are well known in the art and typically include random,
block and graft copolymers that have a pigment adsorbing segment that is
attracted to the pigment surface and a stabilizing segment that extends into the
surrounding solvent medium to provide entropic or steric stabilization of the
pigment particles against flocculation and keep the pigments dispersed.</p><p num="0003">There are relatively few problems with the addition of transparent
iron oxide pigment dispersions to solvent based coating compositions, but in
waterborne compositions, stabilization of transparent iron oxide pigments is a
difficult task. In typical aqueous coating compositions, other particulate materials
such as latex, other pigments, electrolytes, etc. compete for the iron oxide surface
and have a tendency to displace the dispersing resin from the pigment surfaces,
which causes the pigments to flocculate or cluster together and jeopardizes the
pigment stability necessary to obtain high transparency and low haze in the final
coating.</p><p num="0004">The stabilization of transparent iron oxide in waterborne systems
therefore depends, at least in part, on the ability to have the dispersing polymer 
favorably associated with the pigment surface. The existing polymeric dispersing
resins used to stabilize transparent iron oxide pigments in aqueous coatings
compositions do not adequately meet this criteria. Such resins, which include
acrylic copolymers having a hydrophobic adsorbing segment containing acid
groups for enhanced interaction with the pigment surface and a hydrophilic
stabilizing segment for aqueous solubility, as for example, as taught in U.S. Patent
5,231,131 to Chu et al issued July 27, 1993, incorporated by reference herein,
produce stable aqueous transparent iron oxide pigment dispersions that have very
good shelf life, but when the dispersions are added to aqueous coating
compositions, they tend to undergo pigment flocculation and phase separation due
to competing effects described above which result in poor paint stability, high
haze, high viscosity, and ultimately coatings having diminished transparency and
color strength.</p><p num="0005">Phosphated acrylic copolymer dispersants are also known in the art,
as for example, as taught in U.S. Patent 5,502,113 to Antonelli et al issued Mar.
26, 1996 and U.S. Patent 5,530,070 to Antonelli et al issued Jun. 25, 1996, both
incorporated by reference herein, and have been used to form aqueous pigment
dispersions and coating compositions containing metallic flake, e.g., aluminum
flake, pigment. Although these dispersants are effective in stabilizing metallic
flake pigments in waterborne systems, they are not sufficient when used alone in
stabilizing transparent iron oxide pigments.</p><p num="0006">Therefore, there is a need to improve the performance of aqueous
coating compositions containing transparent iron oxide pigments, and in particular
to find new pigment dispersions for use therein containing dispersing resins that
have greater affinity for the transparent iron oxide pigment surface and provide
more effective pigment stabilization, and ultimately improve the transparency of
coatings formed therefrom and come close to the performance of solvent borne
systems.</p><p num="0007">The present invention teaches a method of using a phosphated acrylic
copolymer dispersant, as an auxiliary dispersant, in combination with a tradidonal
transparent iron oxide dispersant to improve the transparency of aqueous coating
compositions containing transparent iron oxide pigments. The present invention
also teaches a method of using the auxiliary phosphated dispersant as an
anchoring polymer which provides anchoring sites for copolymer dispersants with 
alkyl amino groups to provide a venue for stronger adsorption of polymeric
dispersants to the pigment surface and greater coating transparency.</p><heading><b><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></b></heading><p num="0008">The present invention relates to an improved aqueous coating
composition containing
<sl><li>(a) an aqueous carrier medium:</li><li>(b) transparent iron oxide pigment particles stabilized by</li><li>(c) a synergistic mixture of acrylic copolymer dispersants
consisting essentially of
<sl><li>(i) an acrylic copolymer dispersant having a
hydrophilic stabilizing segment and acid groups in a
hydrophobic pigment adsorbing segment</li><li>(ii) an acrylic copolymer dispersant having a
hydrophilic stabilizing segment and phosphate groups in a
hydrophobic pigment adsorbing segment and</li><li>(iii) optional acrylic copolymer having a hydrophilic
stabilizing segment and alkyl amino groups in a
hydrophobic pigment adsorbing segment;</li></sl>
wherein the pigment and dispersants are present in a dispersant
(i) to pigment weight ratio, D/P, of about 0.1/1 to 1/1, a
dispersant (ii) to pigment weight ratio, D/P, of about 0.05/1 to
0.33/1, and a dispersant (iii) to pigment weight ratio, D/P, if
present, of about 0.05/1 to 0.2/1;</li><li>(d) a film forming polymeric binder; and</li><li>(e) a crosslinking agent for the binder.</li></sl></p><p num="0009">Pigment dispersions of the forgoing acrylic copolymer combination
and process for forming the dispersions also are part of this invention.</p><heading><b><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></b></heading><p num="0010">The novel coating composition of this invention is an aqueous based
composition containing 10-70% by weight of film forming polymeric components
which include a film forming polymeric binder, a crosslinking agent, and a
mixture of specified copolymer dispersants and a corresponding amount of 30-90% 
by weight of an aqueous carrier which is primarily water. The composition
also contains transparent iron oxide pigments. The pigments are introduced in the
coating composition in the form of an aqueous pigment dispersion that utilizes the
specified mixture of dispersants in a specified amount to stabilize and keep the
pigments deflocculated over long periods of time in the dispersion and most
notably herein after being added to the coating composition. As a result, the novel
coating composition is stable and non-flocculated or agglomerated and has
excellent transparency.</p><p num="0011">Not to be held to any particularly theory, it is thought that the
phosphated acrylic copolymer dispersant used in the composition has greater
affinity for the iron oxide surface and when it is employed as an auxiliary
dispersant alongside a traditional transparent iron oxide dispersant, it improves the
overall dispersion stability of transparent iron oxide pigments in aqueous coatings
without the negative side effects normally associated with use of phosphated
dispersants, such as unwanted increases in dispersion viscosity. By virtue of its
strong adsorption to the iron oxide surface, it is thought the phosphated acrylic
copolymer also provides anchoring sites for additional copolymer dispersants with
alkyl amino functional groups that bond with functional groups on the anchoring
phosphated polymer. This synergism provides a venue for stronger adsorption of
polymeric dispersants to the pigment surface which results in further stabilization
of the aqueous coating.</p><p num="0012">Another advantage of this invention is that the copolymer dispersants
used in the composition are generally compatible with each other and also with a
variety of polymeric filth forming binders that are conventionally used in
waterborne coating compositions and in particular, compatible with acrylic
polymers that are used in the waterborne coatings. Upon curing of the coating
composition, the copolymer dispersants also preferably contain functional groups,
such as hydroxyl groups, that react with other film forming components of the
coating composition and become a part of the film and do not cause deterioration
of the film upon weathering as may occur if it were an unreacted component of
the film. The dispersant combination also enables good water-to-solvent borne
paint matching as well as better esthetics in color styling.</p><p num="0013">The coating composition of this invention contains a film forming
binder, typically an acrylic polymer and a curing agent, such as a blocked
polyisocyanate or an alkylated melamine. These materials provide excellent 
coating properties desirable for automotive finishes. Waterborne basecoats of
conventional basecoat/clearcoat finishes currently used on automobiles and trucks
containing a transparent iron oxide pigment dispersion that utilizes the
combination of dispersants specified herein have significantly improved
transparency and significantly less haze in comparison to basecoats that utilize the
conventional transparent iron oxide copolymer dispersants.</p><p num="0014">More specifically, the dispersant mixture selected for use herein
consists essentially of i) at least one acrylic copolymer dispersant having acid
groups in the hydrophobic adsorbing portion, ii) at least one acrylic copolymer
dispersant containing phosphate groups in the hydrophobic adsorbing portion; and
optionally iii) at least one adjunct acrylic copolymer dispersant containing alkyl
amino groups preferably along with aryl groups in the hydrophobic portion.</p><p num="0015">The acrylic copolymer dispersants used herein are water-dispersible
in nature. Accordingly, they each include at least one hydrophobic pigment
adsorbing segment that interacts with the pigment surface and at least one
hydrophilic stabilizing segment that is soluble in the aqueous carrier medium.
Not to be held to any particular theory, it is thought that adsorbing segments
function, in part, to attach the copolymer dispersant to the pigment surface, while
stabilizing segments function, in part, to provide steric stabilization of the pigment
particle against flocculation and keep the pigments dispersed in aqueous medium.</p><p num="0016">The location of the adsorbing segment and the stabilizing segment in
each of the acrylic copolymers may vary depending upon the structure of the
acrylic copolymer dispersant. Acrylic polymer dispersants of the present
invention may be random, block or graft copolymers. A block copolymer used in
the present invention may have an AB, ABA, or ABC structure, for example. At
least one of the blocks, A, B or C must be an adsorbing segment. At least one of
the blocks, A, B or C must be a stabilizing segment. A block copolymer used
herein may also include an additional third segment. Graft copolymer dispersants
used herein have a backbone segment and at least one side chain segment,
preferably a macromonomer, grafted onto the backbone. Either a backbone
segment or a side chain segment must be an adsorbing segment. Either a
backbone segment or a side chain segment must be a stabilizing segment.
Preferably a backbone segment is an adsorbing segment and a side chain segment
is a stabilizing segment. Random copolymer dispersants used herein have both 
adsorbing segments and stabilizing segments randomly placed in a polymer
dispersant chain.</p><p num="0017">The adsorbing segment of each of the forgoing dispersants is
hydrophobic relative to the stabilizing segment and is mainly composed of
polymerized ethylenically unsaturated hydrophobic monomers, such as alkyl
(meth)acrylates, cycloaliphatic (meth)acrylates, and aryl (meth)acrylates as are
listed hereinafter. The term (meth)acrylate refers to both the acrylate and
methacrylate esters. The adsorbing segment preferably further contains about 1-20%
by weight, preferably 1-10% by weight, based on the total weight of the
copolymer, of polymerized non-hydrophobic ethylenically unsaturated monomers
that either have attached thereto an acid, phosphate, or alkyl amino anchoring
group depending on which of the forgoing dispersants is desired.</p><p num="0018">Examples of monomers that can be used to introduce acid
functionality in an adsorbing segment include ethylenically unsaturated carboxylic
acids such as acrylic acid and methacrylic acid. Other carboxylic acids that can
be used include itaconic acid, maleic acid, and the like. Ethylenically unsaturated
sulfonic, sulfinic, phosphoric or phosphonic acid and esters thereof also can be
used such as styrene sulfonic acid, 2-acrylamido-2-propane sulfonic acid, vinyl
phosphonic acid and its esters, and the like. Monomers containing acid
functionality are selected, in part, on their theoretical ability to bind to iron oxide
pigments which have basic groups on the surface. The iron oxide surface is
complex. Usually there are a wide range of functional groups on the surface in
addition to basic groups.</p><p num="0019">Phosphate groups can be introduced in an adsorbing segment by
copolymerizing ethylenically unsaturated glycidyl containing monomers, such as
glycidyl acrylate or glycidyl methacrylate, into the adsorbing segment to provide
reactive glycidyl groups and subsequently reacting the glycidyl groups with
phosphoric acid or phosphorous pentoxide to provide the copolymer with pendant
phosphate groups. Monomers having phosphate functionality are selected, in part,
on their theoretical ability to irreversibly bind to transparent iron oxide pigments
in aqueous environments.</p><p num="0020">Examples of monomers that can be used to introduce alkyl amino
functionality in an adsorbing segment include alkyl amino alkyl methacrylate
monomers having 1 to 4 carbon atoms in the alkyl group such as 
dimethylaminoethyl methacrylate, diethylaminoethyl methacrylate,
dipropylaminoethyl methacrylate, dibutylaminoethyl methacrylate.</p><p num="0021">Also, it is not necessary that the anchoring groups mentioned above
all be incorporated in the hydrophobic part of the copolymer but can be
incorporated in the hydrophilic part as well.</p><p num="0022">Examples of hydrophobic monomers that can be used to form the rest
of the adsorbing segment include alkyl (meth)acrylates having 1-12 carbon atoms
in the alkyl group, such as methyl acrylate, ethyl acrylate, propyl acrylate,
isopropyl acrylate, butyl acrylate, pentyl acrylate, hexyl acrylate, 2-ethylhexyl
acrylate, isopropyl acrylate, butyl acrylate, pentyl acrylate, hexyl acrylate, 2-ethylhexyl
acrylate, nonyl acrylate, lauryl acrylate, methyl methacrylate, ethyl
methacrylate, propyl methacrylate, isopropyl methacrylate, butyl methacrylate,
pentyl methacrylate, hexyl methacrylate, 2-ethylhexyl methacrylate, nonyl
methacrylate, lauryl methacrylate, and the like, and any mixtures thereof.
Cycloaliphatic (meth)acrylates can also be used such as trimethylcyclohexyl
methacrylate, isobutylcyclohexyl methacrylate, and the like. Aryl (meth)acrylates
can also be used such as benzyl (meth)acrylate, napthyl (meth)acrylate, phenoxy
(meth)acrylate, and the like. Mixtures of any of the above may also be used.
Other polymerizable monomers that can be used are styrene, alpha methyl
styrene, methacrylamide and methacrylonitrile.</p><p num="0023">The hydrophilic stabilizing segment of each dispersant used herein is
soluble in the selected aqueous carrier medium. It is composed mainly of
polymerized ethylenically unsaturated hydrophilic monomers. Acid containing
monomers, such as acrylic acid and methacrylic acid and 2-acrylamido-2-propane
sulfonic acid, can be used. Some useful examples of acid containing monomers
include the acids listed hereinabove. Non-ionic hydrophilic monomers can also
be used to form the stabilizing segment such as monoethylenically unsaturated
poly(alkylene glycol) monomers such as poly(ethylene glycol) mono
(meth)acrylate (weight average molecular weight of 200-4000, preferably 200-2000),
and the like. In addition to the forgoing monomers, up to 40% by weight,
based on the weight of the stabilizing segment, of other commonly used
hydrophobic monomers can be copolymerized into the stabilizing portion
provided they are used at a concentration that will not drastically change the
solubility properties of the stabilizing portion in the selected aqueous processing 
medium. Some useful examples include the alkyl(meth)acrylates listed
hereinabove.</p><p num="0024">Either or both the stabilizing or adsorbing segment, preferably the
stabilizing segment, of each dispersant used herein also may contain up to 30% by
weight, based on the weight of the copolymer, of ethylenically unsaturated
hydrophilic monomers that have functional groups that will react with the film
forming components present in the coating composition which in turn enable the
dispersant to become a permanent part of the network structure. Suitable
monomers include hydrophilic hydroxyl alkyl (meth)acrylate monomers having 1
to 4 carbon atoms in the alkyl group, such as hydroxy ethyl acrylate, hydroxy
ethyl methacrylate, and the like.</p><p num="0025">The acrylic copolymer dispersants used herein have a number average
molecular weight of about 4,000 to about 25,000 (preferably about 5,000 to about
20,000). The adsorbing segment typically has a number average molecular
weight of about 2,000 to about 10,000 (preferably about 4,000 to about 7,000).
The stabilizing segment typically has a number average molecular weight of about
2,000 to about 15,000 (preferably about 4,000 to about 7,000). All molecular
weights referred herein are determined by GPC (gel permeation chromatography)
using a polystyrene standard. The adsorbing segment typically comprises about
20-80% by weight of the polymer, and correspondingly the stabilizing segment
typically comprises about 80-20% by weight of the polymer.</p><p num="0026">The forgoing dispersants may be prepared by a variety of well known
solution polymerization techniques devised for a particular structure, such as by
the GTP (Group Transfer Polymerization) method reported in U.S. Patent
4,656,226; by the standard anionic or the free radical polymerization method
reported in U.S. Patent 4,656,226; or by the SCT (Special Chain Transfer) method
reported in U.S. Patent 5,231,131, all incorporated herein by reference. The GTP
method is traditionally used to form block copolymers. Using this method, it is
generally recommended to block any acid or hydroxyl containing monomers to
prevent side reactions during polymerization. Following polymerization, the acid
and hydroxyl groups are unblocked by a reaction with alcohol or water. The SCT
method is traditionally used to form the macromonomer portion of a graft
copolymer. Macromonomers can also be supplied by other means. Standard
anionic polymerization is oftentimes used to form random copolymers. </p><p num="0027">After each of the forgoing copolymers is formed, typically an amine
or inorganic base such as ammonium hydroxide are added to the copolymers to
neutralize unreacted or residual acid constituents and make the copolymers more
easily dispersible in aqueous medium. Primary and secondary amines can be
used. One preferred amine is 2-amino methyl propanol. These above
neutralization agents are typically added during the pigment dispersion process
described below.</p><p num="0028">To form a pigment dispersion, transparent iron oxide pigment is
added to the specified copolymers in the customary water-soluble organic solvent
or blend, followed by the addition of an amine or an inorganic base to neutralize
the copolymers, and then water is added to form an aqueous dispersion.
Conventional mixing is used to form the dispersion, such as high speed mixing,
ball milling, sand grinding, attritor grinding, or two or three roll milling. Mixing
is generally carried out for about 5-150 minutes to form a dispersion having a low
shear viscosity of about 100-1,000 centipoise and preferably about 100-500
centipoise at 5 and 100 rpm measured on a Brookfield Viscometer at ambient
temperatures.</p><p num="0029">The pigment dispersion so formed contains about 10-30% by weight
of pigment and dispersant and correspondingly about 90-70% by weight of an
aqueous carrier and has an overall dispersant to pigment weight ratio, (D/P), of
about 0.1/1 to 1/1. The acid containing dispersant (i) to pigment weight ratio,
D/P is about 0.25/1 to 0.75 to 1 and preferably about 0.33/1 to 0.5/1. The
phosphate containing dispersant (ii) to pigment ratio, D/P is about 0.05/1 to 0.45/1
and is preferably about 0.5/1 to 0.15/1. The alkyl amino containing dispersant
(iii) to pigment ratio, D/P if present, is about 0.05/1 to 0.5/1 and is preferably
0.05/1 to 0.15/1. The overall dispersant to pigment ratio, D/P is the sum total of
D/P contribution from each dispersant. Film properties indicate overall D/P are
optimal in range of 0.4/1 up to 0.7/1 and preferentially 0.6/1.</p><p num="0030">Any of the conventional transparent iron oxide pigment of various
colors can be used to form the pigment dispersion, for example "AC-1005" (red)
from Johnson-Matthey and "L-1916" (yellow) from BASF. Such pigments are
typically 0.1 microns or less. Use of transoxide pigments in aqueous systems
containing aluminum flake can induce hydrogen gassing. The transoxide pigment
competes for phosphated passivator resins on the aluminum pigment surface. Use 
of phosphated dispersing resin in this invention, in dispersion formulation,
mitigates this effect.</p><p num="0031">Under some circumstances, it may be desirable to form pigment
dispersions by using the dispersant mixture that do not contain transparent iron
oxide pigments but contain pigments used in paints in particular waterborne paints
that have affinity to phosphate groups in the dispersant molecule, such as opaque
iron oxide of various colors and other metallic oxides like titanium dioxide, zinc
oxide, and the like.</p><p num="0032">The coatings compositions of this invention contain in addition to the
pigment dispersion a binder preferably of an acrylic-based polymer and a
crosslinking agent such as a melamine crosslinking agent, a polyisocyanate
crosslinking agent or a blocked polyisocyanate crosslinking agent in an aqueous
medium. The acrylic copolymers form stable solutions or dispersions. These
coating compositions also contain about 10-70%, more typically 15-50% by
weight of binder, and about 30-90%, more typically 50-85% by weight, of the
liquid carrier which is water alone or a mixture of mainly water and customary
water-soluble organic solvent or blend. Suitable coating compositions are
prepared by blending other useful components in accordance with normal paint
formulation techniques.</p><p num="0033">The acrylic based polymer binders typically are polymers of alkyl
(meth)acrylates having 1-12 carbon atoms in the alkyl group, hydroxy alkyl
(meth) acrylates having 1-4 carbon atoms in the alkyl group and methacrylic or
acrylic acid and have a number average molecular weight of 5,000-30,000 and are
neutralized with ammonium hydroxide or an amine to form aqueous solutions or
dispersions. The aforementioned alkyl (meth)acrylates, hydroxy alkyl
(meth)acrylates can be used to formulate these polymers.</p><p num="0034">To form a coating composition which will crosslink under elevated
baking temperatures of about 60-180°C for about 5-60 minutes, about 10 to 50%,
preferably 15 to 30% by weight, based on the weight of the binder, of an alkylated
melamine formaldehyde crosslinking agent having 1-4 carbon atoms in the
alkylated group is preferred.</p><p num="0035">These crosslinking agents are generally partially or fully alkylated
melamine formaldehyde compounds and may be monomeric or polymeric as
described above. Blocked polyisocyanates can also be used as crosslinking
agents. 
Coating compositions containing a melamine crosslinking agent can contain about
0.1 to 1.0% by weight, based on the weight of a binder, of a strong acid catalyst or
a salt thereof to lower curing temperatures and time. Aromatic sulfonic acids such
as para toluene sulfonic acid or its ammonium salt are preferred catalysts. Other
catalysts that can be used are dodecyl benzene sulfonic acid, phosphoric acid and
amine or ammonium salts of these acids.</p><p num="0036">Other film forming polymers can also be used in these coating
compositions such as acrylourethanes, polyesters and polyester urethanes,
polyethers and polyether urethanes that are compatible. A polyisocyanate may be
used as a crosslinking agent to provide a coating composition that will cure at
ambient temperatures.</p><p num="0037">In addition, coating composition of the present invention may contain
a variety of other optional ingredients, including pigments, fillers, plasticizers,
antioxidants, surfactants and flow control agents.</p><p num="0038">To improve weatherability of a finish of the novel coating
compositions, an ultraviolet light stabilizer or a combination of ultraviolet light
stabilizers can be added in the amount of about 0.1-5% by weight, based on the
weight of the binder. The stabilizer may be added for example to the pigment
dispersion or may be added directly to the coating composition. Such stabilizers
include ultraviolet light absorbers, screeners, quenchers, and specific hindered
amine light stabilizers. Also, an anitoxidant can be added, in the amount of 0.1
-5% by weight, based on the weight of the binder.</p><p num="0039">Typical ultraviolet light stabilizers that are useful include
benzophenones, triazoles, triazines, benzoates, hindered amines and mixtures
thereof. Specific examples of ultraviolet stabilizers are disclosed in U.S. Patent
4,591,533, the entire disclosure of which is incorporated herein by reference.</p><p num="0040">Such coating composition may also include conventional formulation
additives such as flow control agents, for example, "Resiflow" S
(polybutylacrylate), BYK 320 and 325 (high molecular weight polyacrylates);
rheology control agents, such as fumed silica and thickeners such as the
Acrylsol® copolymers from Rohm &amp; Haas.</p><p num="0041">Apart from transparent iron oxide pigments, the coating composition
of this invention can also include any of the other conventional pigments used in
paints in particular waterborne paints such as metallic flakes like aluminum flake,
bronze, nickel stainless steel flakes and the like, pearlescent flakes like coated 
mica flakes such as mica flakes coated with titanium dioxide and the like, as well
as carbon black, filler pigments such as talc, china clay, barytes, carbonates,
silicates, metallic oxides such as titanium dioxide, opaque iron oxides of various
colors, and zinc oxide; carbon black, and a wide variety of organic pigments such
as quinacridones, phthalocyanines, perylenes, azo pigments, indanthrones,
carbazoles such as carbazole violet, isoindolinones, isoindolones, thioindigo reds,
benzimidazolinones, and the like. Metallic flakes like aluminum flake is
preferred. These pigments may be provided in aqueous dispersions stabilized by
conventional dispersants and not necessarily by the combination listed
hereinabove.</p><p num="0042">The coating compositions of the present invention may be utilized as
a monocoat or in a pigmented colorcoat or basecoat over which a clearcoat is
applied to provide a colorcoat/clearcoat finish.</p> <p num="0043">Coating compositions of this invention have excellent adhesion to a
variety of metallic or non-metallic substrates, such as previously painted
substrates, primed substrates, cold rolled steel, phosphatized steel, and steel
coated with conventional electrodeposition primers. These coating compositions
can be used to coat plastic substrates such as polyester reinforced fiberglass,
reaction injection-molded urethanes and partially crystalline polyamides. In
particular, base coat or color coat composition of this invention, provide improved
transparency and reduced haze and improved paint stability, which properties are
very important property for coatings used on automobiles and trucks.</p><p num="0044">Coating compositions of this invention can be applied by
conventional techniques such as spraying, electrostatic spraying, dipping,
brushing, flowcoating and the like. The preferred techniques are spraying and
electrostatic spraying. In OEM applications, the composition typically is baked at
100-150°C for about 15-30 minutes to form a coating about 0.1-3.0 mils thick.
When the composition is used as a clearcoat, it is applied over the color coat that
may be dried to a tack-free state and cured or preferably flash dried for a short
period before the clearcoat is applied. The color coat/clearcoat finish is then baked
as mentioned above to provide a dried and cured finish. The present invention is
also applicable to non-baking refinish systems, as will be readily appreciated by
those skilled in the art.</p><p num="0045">It is customary to apply a clear topcoat over a basecoat by means of a
"wet-on-wet" application, i.e., the topcoat is applied to the basecoat without 
curing or completely drying the basecoat. The coated substrate is then heated for a
predetermined time period to allow simultaneous curing of the base and clear
coats.</p><p num="0046">The following Examples illustrate the invention. All parts, ratios and
percentages are on a weight basis unless otherwise indicated. All molecular
weights disclosed herein are determined by GPC (gel permeation
chromatography) using a polystyrene standard.</p><heading><b><u style="single">EXAMPLES</u> </b> </heading> <p num="0047">Polymer dispersants were prepared and formulated into a pigment
dispersion and the pigment dispersion was formulated into a transparent coating
composition.</p><heading><u style="single">Polymer Dispersant 1</u></heading><p num="0048">Polymer Dispersant 1 is an example of a random acrylic copolymer
containing acid functionality in the pigment adsorbing segment composed of
methyl methacrylate (MMA), butyl acrylate (BA), acrylic acid (AA), 2-hydroxy
ethyl methacrylate (HEMA) and 2-acrylamido-2-methyl propane sulfonic acid
(AMPS) in a weight ratio of 37.5/50.2/5.1/5.1/2.1 having a number average
molecular weight of 20,000 and a polydispersity of 2. This polymer was made
using a standard anionic polymerization process as described in U.S. Patent
4,656,226, herein incorporated by reference. The polymer solution was
neutralized with 2-amino methyl propanol and diluted with deionized water and
isopropanol to a solids content of 50% prior to use.</p><heading><u style="single">Polymer Dispersant 2</u></heading><p num="0049">Polymer Dispersant 2 is an example of a phosphated graft copolymer
containing phosphate functionality in the pigment adsorbing backbone segment
and prepared using a standard free radical polymerization approach. The resulting
phosphated graft copolymer had the following composition:

   [60] NBA/MA/GMA-Phosphated (45.5/45.5/9)//[40] Bisomer 20W</p><p num="0050">The phosphate polymer was prepared using the macromonomer,
Bisomer 20W as the stabilizing arms of the graft copolymer. This material is a
macromonomer of poly(ethyleneglycol monomethacrylate) which is purchased
from ISC. It is nonionic with a molecular weight, Mw of 2000 and provides the
water soluble functionality to the polymer. The Bisomer 20W macromonomer 
along with other constituents are reacted in a vessel to form the macro branched
graft copolymer.</p><p num="0051">The graft copolymer was formed by charging a reactor equipped with
a stirrer, thermocouple, condenser and nitrogen blanket and heating to reflux. To
the reactor the backbone monomers of n-butyl acrylate (NBA), glycidyl
methacrylate (GMA), methyl acrylate (MA) and the Bisomer 20W
macromonomer were added with isopropanol as the solvent. The polymerization
reaction was initiated by feeding the initiator 2,2'-azobis(2,4-dimethylvaleronitrile)
(Vazo® 52 from DuPont Co., Wilmington, DE) which was
dissolved in a solution of methyl ethyl ketone and isopropanol. The phosphating
was accomplished by an esterification of the epoxy groups on glycidyl
methacrylate with phosphoric acid, H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>.</p><p num="0052">The resulting phosphate acrylic graft copolymer reached 99%
conversion. Its solids was 45 % in a solution of water/isopropanol. The
molecular weight of the polymer was obtained using GPC. The polymer was
methylated prior to injection into the column. The GPC indicated a number
average molecular weight of 4,577 and a polydispersity of 2.64.</p><heading><u style="single">Polymer Dispersant 3</u></heading><p num="0053">Polymer Dispersant 3 is an example of an AB block copolymer
containing benzyl functionality and alkyl amino functionality in the adsorbing
segment and prepared using the GTP method</p><p num="0054">The AB block copolymer was prepared by charging to a 5-liter flask
equipped with an agitator, condenser, heating mantle, nitrogen inlet, thermocouple
and an addition port, 1,600 g of tetrahydrofuran and 3.8 g of p-xylene, followed
by 0.6 mL of a 1.0 M solution of a catalyst, tetrabutylammonium m-chlorobenzoate
in acetonitrile. 32.5 g of a 0.140 M solution of an initiator, 1,1-bis(trimethylsiloxy)-2-methylpropene,
were injected into the flask. Feed I,
consisting of 0.6 mL of a 1.0 M solution of tetrabutylammonium m-chlorobenzoate
in acetonitrile, was started and added over 200 minutes. Feed II,
consisting of 265.0 g (1.67 mol) of trimethylsilyl methacrylate, 298.0 g (2.10 mol)
of butyl methacrylate, 140.0 g (1.40 mol) of methyl methacrylate, and 141.0 g
(0.70 mol) of trimethylsiloxyethyl methacrylate, was started at 0.0 minutes and
added over a 45 minute period. One hundred minutes after Feed II was completed,
over 99% of the monomers had reacted. Feed III, consisting of 616.0 g (3.46 mol) 
of benzyl methacrylate, and 154.0 g (0.98 mol) of dimethylaminoethyl
methacrylate, was started and added over 30 minutes. After 400 minutes, 150 g
methanol was added to the resulting reaction mixture to quench the reaction and
deblock the hydroxy and acid monomers and solvent distillation was started.
During the first stage of distillation, 400.0 g of solvent were removed. 100 g of
methanol were added and an additional 200.0 g of solvent were distilled off.</p><p num="0055">The resulting polymer solution had a solids content of 50% and the
polymer had the following composition: benzyl methacrylate (BZMA) /
dimethylaminoethyl methacrylate (DMEAMA) // BMA / MMA / hydroxyethyl
methacrylate (HEMA) / methacrylic acid (MAA) in a monomer ratio of
25/7//15/10/5/12. The polymer had a number average molecular weight of 9,400
and a polydispersity of 1.1. The polymer solution was diluted with a 1:1 mixture
of deionized water and isopropyl alcohol to a solids content of 30% prior to use.</p><heading><u style="single">Evaluation of Pigment Dispersion Properties</u></heading><p num="0056">The pigment dispersion samples were prepared by the following
procedure. Laboratory grinds were performed using standard 01 attritors which
are described in <u style="single">Paint Flow and Pigment Dispersion</u> by Temple C. Patton, pages
439-441, Wiley Interscience Publication, 1979. Each grind was loaded with 400
grams of the experimental dispersion and milling was accomplished with 850
grams of 0.8-1.0 mm high density zirconia media. Each attritor was milled for a
total of 24 hours at 500 rpm spindle agitation to ensure that adequate milling was
achieved.</p><p num="0057">Included in the experimental design was one control. The control was
a dispersion made with the existing transparent iron oxide dispersant (Polymer
Dispersant 1), which gave a basepoint for existing technology. The remaining
experiments determined the optimal level of phosphate dispersant which gave
improved dispersion and paint performance.</p><p num="0058">The red and yellow transparent iron oxide ("transoxide") dispersion
formulations, (Ex), each had the following compositions: <tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">CEx.1</entry><entry align="center">Ex.2</entry><entry align="center">Ex.3</entry><entry align="center">Ex.4</entry><entry align="center">Ex.5</entry><entry align="center">Ex.6</entry><entry align="center">Ex.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Deionized Water</entry><entry align="center">69.45</entry><entry align="center">66.95</entry><entry align="center">64.45</entry><entry align="center">59.45</entry><entry align="center">54.45</entry><entry align="center">59.45</entry><entry align="center">64.45</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Transoxide pigment</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer Dispersant 1</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">12.50</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer Dispersant 2</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">2.50</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">15.00</entry><entry align="center">12.50</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer Dispersant 3</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Defoamer</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Aminomethylpropanol</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables>
The dispersion CEx.1 is the control.

The dispersion, Ex.2 was made only for Yellow transoxide pigment, BASF L-1916.
The Red transoxide used was Johnson Matthey AC-1005. The resin solids
for Polymer Dispersant 1 is 50%, for Polymer Dispersant 2 is 45% and for
Polymer Dispersant 3 is 30%. The amount of each dispersant applied to the
pigment is reported as D/P which is the dispersant to pigment weight ratio.</p><heading><u style="single">Results</u></heading><p num="0059">The experimental results are given in Tables 1, 2, 3 and 4. A
dispersion pigment loading of 15.00% was used to provided adequate screening
between 01 attritor grinds. In analyzing each grind and comparing versus control,
the key product characteristics used included: (i) dispersion viscosity, (ii)
dispersion haze and transparency, and (iii) the paint letdown haze/transparency
and stability.</p><p num="0060">The desired attributes of the dispersion include: (i) high pigment
loading, (ii) low viscosity, and (iii) low haze and high transparency. The
dispersion viscosity is measured using a standard Brookfield Viscometer at low
shear, 5 rpm and higher shear, 100 rpm . The haze and transparency of the
dispersion are measured using a drawdown on Mylar and reading the panel using
the Hunter Colorquest Instrument.</p><p num="0061">A good dispersion is a necessary but not sufficient condition for
making good paint. A good dispersion must also work well and produce the
desired aesthetics when used in an aqueous paint system. To make this 
assessment, each dispersion sample was letdown into a balanced clear paint
formulation. The balanced clear, BC-1, used had the following composition:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Balanced Clear, BC-1</entry><entry align="center">Weight Percent</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Acrylic Latex (32.7% solids in an aqueous medium of polymer of allyl methacrylate/methyl methacrylate/methacryilc acid/hydroxy ethyl acrylate/butyl acrylate)</entry><entry align="center">58.40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">15.90</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Aminomethylpropanol</entry><entry align="center">0.32</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyester Solution (89% solids in butoxyethanol of a polyester of neopentyl glycol/trimethyl porpane/1,6 hexanediol/ isophthalic acid/phthalic anhydride/ adipic acid/ 1,12 dodecane dioic acid)</entry><entry align="center">5.96</entry></row><row><entry align="left">"Cymel" 301 (methylated melamine crosslinking agent from Cytec Industries)</entry><entry align="center">6.05</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Agitan 281 (defoamer)</entry><entry align="center">1.10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mineral Spirits</entry><entry align="center">6.60</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Butoxyethanol</entry><entry align="center">1.66</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hexoxyethanol</entry><entry align="center">2.94</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Nacure XP-221 (aromatic sulfonic acid catalyst)</entry><entry align="center">0.12</entry></row><row><entry align="left">ASE-60 (acrylic emulsion polymer thickener)</entry><entry align="center">0.95</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0062">The paint evaluations were performed by adding 6 g of the dispersion
to 20 grams of balanced clear, BC-1, mixing thoroughly, and drawing the paint
onto Mylar film with a #20 WWR, (Wire Wound Rod). After the film is dried, a
Clearcoat was applied over the film with a #20 WWR. The sample was oven
cured at 250°F for 30 minutes. After cooling, the haze and transparency was read
using the Hunter ColorQuest. The procedure for dispersion letdown and
haze/transparency measurement are described more fully in DuPont Co.,
Wilmington, DE, Procedure, TM-0501A. </p><heading><u style="single">Yellow Transoxide Results</u></heading><p num="0063">The results for the yellow transoxide pigment, BASF L-1916 are
shown in Table 1. The paint letdown haze in BC-1 as a function of the percent
phosphate resin in the dispersion shows that the haze of the Control which
contains no phosphate resin, has the highest letdown haze (14.43%). The grinds
Ex.2 through Ex.5 with standard transoxide dispersant at D/P = 0.50 with
additional phosphate resin ranging from D/P = 0.075 up through D/P = 0.45 show
that sample 2 with D/P = 0.075 phosphate resin gave the lowest haze with the
haze increasing slightly as the level of phosphate resin is increased. The results
also show that the dispersion viscosity increases rapidly as phosphate resin level is
increased. Based on the results, a loading of phosphate resin, polymer dispersant
2, at D/P between 0.075 and 0.15 in the dispersion appears to be optimal based on
letdown haze and dispersion viscosity.</p><heading><u style="single">Red Transoxide Results</u></heading><p num="0064">A similar set of dispersion grinds was performed for the red
transoxide pigment, Johnson Matthey, AC-1005. These results also show the
same trend of increasing dispersion viscosity with increasing phosphate level.
The dispersions were letdown into BC-1</p><p num="0065">The results in Table 2 show that CEx. 1, the Control, which contains
no phosphate resin had the highest letdown haze. The letdown haze showed the
same slow increase with increasing phosphate level. The dispersion viscosity
shows the same rapid increase with phosphate level as well. A grind was not
made with a phosphate resin level less than 5.0%. Further optimization grinds
may be required to establish the optimal level required which may be less than
5.0%.</p><p num="0066">In addition to reducing the letdown haze another key product
characteristic is the viscosity and transparency stability of the letdown. This is
also an important consideration because the paint may sit for several weeks or
months before a customer may actually use the paint. Therefore, the conditions of
paint stability look at increasing viscosity of the letdown due to phase separation
or increasing haze due to flocculation over time. Since this is also a key product
characteristic, the yellow and red transoxide letdowns were examined and
remeasured for haze at 1 and 3 week intervals. The results in Table 3 and 4 show 
that there was no significant haze increase with any sample which indicates good
paint stability.</p><heading><u style="single">Three Dispersant System</u></heading><p num="0067">One last experiment was performed in which a three dispersant
system was evaluated for both the red and yellow transoxide pigments. Use of the
phosphated comb (graft) improved performance in paint but there was a
noticeable increase in dispersion viscosity. At elevated viscosities dispersion
milling becomes difficult and yield loss due to clingage is high. The use of
polymer dispersant 3 at D/P of 0.1, showed additional transparency benefit and
unexpected improvement in reducing dispersion viscosity and rheology. Optimal
dispersion viscosity for milling large batches in high throughput mills is about 100
to 500 centipoise at 5 and 100 rpm on a Brookfield Viscometer. These last
experiments which are reported in Table 1 and Table 2 for the yellow and red
transoxide, respectively examine a three dispersant combination. In the dispersion
formulations the existing transoxide dispersant, polymer dispersant 1, was
reduced from D/P of 0.50 to 0.33. The phosphated comb, polymer dispersant 2,
was held at 0.15 and a third, polymer dispersant 3 which is a benzyl and amine
functional polymer was introduced at D/P of 0.10 loading as well. The results in
Tables 1 and 2 indicate that these dispersion formulations not only have the
lowest haze in dispersion and letdown but also has a lower dispersion viscosity.
These results indicate transoxide pigment surfaces are complex and achieving
optimal stabilization using conventional wet milling processes is not easy.</p><p num="0068">The results demonstrate that phosphated graft copolymer dispersing
resin improved the stabilization of both red and yellow transoxide pigments for
aqueous paint systems. The dispersion formulation work shows that the pigment
loading can be significant which should help address the color styling issue. The
letdown and paint stability data also show that using the phosphate resin as an
anchor resin on the pigment surface with a codispersant such as dispersant 3,
which bonds with the anchor resin significantly improved transoxide performance
in aqueous paint systems.</p><p num="0069">Various modifications, alterations, additions or substitutions of he
components if the compositions of this invention will be apparent to those skilled
in the art without departing from the spirit and scope of this invention. This 
invention is not limited by the illustrative embodiments set forth herein, but rather
is defined by the following claims. <img id="img-00210001" orientation="unknown" wi="75" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00210001.tif" inline="no" he="224"/><img id="img-00220001" orientation="unknown" wi="69" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00220001.tif" inline="no" he="219"/><img id="img-00230001" orientation="unknown" wi="71" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00230001.tif" inline="no" he="229"/><img id="img-00240001" orientation="unknown" wi="71" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00240001.tif" inline="no" he="216"/></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An aqueous coating composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) an aqueous carrier medium:</claim-text><claim-text>(b) transparent iron pigment particles stabilized by</claim-text><claim-text>(c) a mixture of pigment dispersants consisting essentially of
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) at least one acrylic copolymer dispersant having a hydrophilic
stabilizing segment and acid groups in a hydrophobic adsorbing
segment;</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) at least one acrylic copolymer dispersant having a hydrophilic
stabilizing segment and phosphate groups in a hydrophobic
adsorbing segment; and</claim-text><claim-text>(iii) optionally at least one acrylic copolymer dispersant having a
hydrophilic stabilizing segment and alkyl amino groups in a
hydrophobic adsorbing segment;</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>(d) a film forming polymeric binder; and</claim-text><claim-text>(e) a crosslinking agent for the binder.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The coating composition of claim 1 wherein the pigment and
dispersants are present in a
<claim-text><claim-text>dispersant to pigment, D/P (i) weight ratio of 0.1/1 to 1/1;</claim-text><claim-text>dispersant to pigment, D/P (ii) weight ratio of 0.05/1 to 0.33/1; and</claim-text><claim-text>dispersant to pigment, D/P(iii) weight ratio of 0.05/1 to 0.20/1.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The coating composition of claim 1 wherein the acrylic copolymer
dispersants have a number average molecular weight of about 4,000-25,000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The coating composition of claim 1 wherein the composition also
contains aluminum flake pigment.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The coating composition of claim 1 wherein the acrylic copolymer
dispersants contain hydroxyl groups in their stabilizing segment that on curing
will react with the crosslinking agent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The coating composition of claim 1 wherein the phosphated
dispersant comprises an acrylic graft copolymer having a polymeric backbone and
macromonomer side chains attached to the backbone, wherein the backbone is a
hydrophobic polymer consisting essentially of polymerized alkyl (meth)acrylate
monomers having 1-12 carbon atoms in the alkyl group and glycidyl
(meth)acrylate monomers, with the glycidyl groups being reacted with phosphoric
acid or phosphorous pentoxide, and the side chains consist essentially of
hydrophilic poly(ethylene glycol) mono(meth)acrylate macromonomers attached
to the backbone.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The coating composition of claim 6 wherein the acid containing
dispersant comprises a random acrylic copolymer consisting essentially of
polymerized alkyl (meth)acrylate monomers having 1-12 carbon atoms in the
alkyl group, acrylic acid or methacrylic acid, hydroxy alkyl (meth)acrylate
monomers having 1-4 carbon atoms in the alkyl group, and a 2-acrylamido-2-methyl
propane sulfonic acid monomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The coating composition of claim 7 wherein the alkyl amino
containing dispersant comprises an acrylic AB block copolymer wherein the
hydrophobic A segment consists essentially of benzyl (meth)acrylate monomers
and alkyl amino (meth)acrylate monomers having 1-4 carbon atoms in the alkyl
group and the hydrophilic B segment consists essentially of polymerized alkyl
(meth)acrylate monomers having 1-12 carbon atoms in the alkyl group, acrylic
acid or methacrylic acid, and hydroxy alkyl (meth)acrylate monomers having 1-4
carbon atoms in the alkyl group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The coating composition of claim 1 wherein the crosslinking agent
comprises an alkylated melamine crosslinking agent and the film forming
polymeric binder is an acrylic polymer comprising an alkyl (meth)acrylate having
1-12 carbon atoms in the alkyl group, hydroxyl alkyl (meth)acrylate having 1-4
carbon atoms in the alkyl group and acrylic acid or methacrylic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An aqueous pigment dispersion comprising pigment and a mixture of
copolymer dispersants consisting essentially of at least one acrylic copolymer
dispersant having a hydrophilic stabilizing segment and acid groups in a
hydrophobic adsorbing segment and at least one acrylic copolymer dispersant
having a hydrophilic stabilizing segment and phosphate groups in a hydrophobic
adsorbing segment and optionally at least one acrylic copolymer dispersant having
a hydrophilic stabilizing segment and alkyl amino groups in a hydrophobic
adsorbing segment.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The dispersion of claim 1 wherein the pigment comprises transparent
iron oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A substrate coated with a dried and cured layer of the composition of
claim 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The substrate of claim 11 having superimposed thereon a clear layer
of a coating composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A process for preparing the dispersion of claim 11 in which the
dispersants are mixed together in water or in a water and water-soluble solvent
blend, followed by addition of amine or inorganic base to neutralize the residual
or unreacted acid groups of the dispersants, and then dispersing transparent iron
oxide pigment in the dispersion to form a pigment dispersion.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>