<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1308198-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1308198" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="19149170" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030507"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1308198-A1" status="new" fvid="23751557"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1308198</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030507</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02020950-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02020950</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020919</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2001333972-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2001333972</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011031</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  53/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  53/14        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  53/46        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  53/64        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10J   3/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10J   3/02        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10J   3/46        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10J   3/46        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10K   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10K   1/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10K   1/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10K   1/12        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10K   1/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01D  53/14</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01D  53/64</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10K   1/08B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10K   1/10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10K   1/16</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01D257:602</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren und Vorrichtung zur Entfernung von Quecksilber</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Mercury removal method and system</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé et dispositif pour l'élimination de mercure</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-3661509-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3661509</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4044098-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4044098</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4500327-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4500327</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4591490-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4591490</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4863489-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4863489</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4895708-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4895708</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000069991-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000069991</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI HEAVY IND LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI HEAVY INDUSTRIES, LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Mitsubishi Heavy Industries, Ltd.</last-name><address><street>5-1, Marunouchi 2-chome, Chiyoda-ku</street><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HARADA MASAHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HONJO SHINTARO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ISHIDA KAZUO</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NAGANO HAJIME</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OKINO SUSUMU</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SUSAKI MAKOTO</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HARADA, MASAHIRO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HONJO, SHINTARO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ISHIDA, KAZUO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NAGANO, HAJIME</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OKINO, SUSUMU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SUSAKI, MAKOTO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HARADA, MASAHIRO</last-name><address><street>Mitsubishi Heavy Ind.,Ltd., 5-1 Marunouchi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Honjo, Shintaro, c/o Hiroshima Res. &amp;amp; Dev. Center</last-name><address><street>Mitsubishi H. Ind., 6-22,Kan-on-shin-machi 4-chome</street><city>Nishi-ku, Hiroshima, Hiroshima-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ISHIDA, KAZUO</last-name><address><street>Mitsubishi Heavy Ind.,Ltd., 5-1,Marunouchi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NAGANO, HAJIME</last-name><address><street>Mitsubishi Heavy Ind.,Ltd., 5-1,Marunouchi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OKINO, SUSUMU</last-name><address><street>Mitsubishi Heavy Ind.,Ltd., 5-1,Marunouchi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SUSAKI, MAKOTO</last-name><address><street>Mitsubishi Heavy Ind.,Ltd., 5-1,Marunouchi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Henkel, Feiler, Hänzel &amp;amp; Partner</last-name><address><street>Möhlstrasse 37</street><city>81675 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents> </parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>IT</country> </ep-contracting-states> </designated-states> </international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention provides a mercury removal method which
can effectively remove very small amounts of mercury
components present in a gas during wet gas purification such
as coal or heavy oil gasification gas purification and
petroleum refining. A mercury removal method for the removal
of mercury present in a gas, the method comprising the steps
of bringing a gas containing at least mercury and not less
than 10 ppm of hydrogen sulfide into gas-liquid contact with
an absorbing fluid under pressurized conditions so as to
cause mercury to pass into the absorbing fluid; flashing the
mercury-containing absorbing fluid under lower-pressure
conditions to separate it into gaseous components and liquid
components; and removing the mercury contained in the
separated gaseous components by adsorption to an adsorbent.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="133" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="83"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b><u style="single">Field of the Invention</u></b></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to a mercury removal method and
system for use in wet gas purification. More particularly,
it relates to a mercury removal method which can effectively
remove very small amounts of mercury components present in a
gas during wet gas purification such as coal or heavy oil
gasification gas purification and petroleum refining.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Background of the Invention</u></b></heading><p num="0002">Exhaust gas from coal-fired thermal electric power
plants contains mercury originating from coal. This mercury
cannot be completely removed in a conventional flue gas
treatment system (including an electrostatic precipitator, a
wet flue gas desulfurizer and the like), and some of it is
discharged therefrom. Since mercury is a trace component and
has a very high vapor pressure and, in particular, metallic
mercury has the property of being insoluble in water, it is
difficult to remove mercury by recovering it with a dust
collector or by washing the gas with a scrubber.</p><p num="0003">A large amount of mercury is discharged from
conventional waste disposal by incineration or the like, but
the scale of disposal is relatively small and produces a
small volume of gas. Accordingly, such mercury has 
frequently been treated, for example, by adsorption using
activated carbon. While treating methods involving
adsorption by activated carbon are effective methods for the
removal of such mercury, they are not suitable for practical
use in the treatment of a large volume of gas because an
enormous consumption cost is required.</p><p num="0004">Consequently, a mercury removal method has been proposed
in which an oxidizing agent is sprayed, for example, in a
mist eliminator (M/E) installed downstream of a flue gas
desulfurizer. Since it is difficult to use activated carbon
in thermal electric power plants for the above-described
reason, this method provides a more convenient means for
removing mercury by spraying an oxidizing agent in a mist
eliminator.</p><p num="0005">Moreover, a process has been proposed in which metallic
Hg is oxidized to HgCl<sub>2</sub> on a catalyst such as a denitration
catalyst and this HgCl<sub>2</sub> is removed in a flue gas desulfurizer.</p><p num="0006">Mercury exists chiefly in two forms: metallic mercury
(Hg) of zero valence and mercury chloride (HgCl<sub>2</sub>). While
metallic mercury is hardly soluble in water, mercury chloride
is relatively soluble in water. Thus, mercury in the form of
mercury chloride can be removed by means of a desulfurizer.
Accordingly, metallic mercury of zero valence can be removed
by oxidizing it to mercury chloride with the aid of an
oxidizing agent. </p><p num="0007">In this process, therefore, a chlorinating agent such as
Cl<sub>2</sub> or HCl is added and sprayed just before a denitration
catalyst within a denitrator, so that metallic mercury is
oxidized on the denitration catalyst.</p><p num="0008">In ordinary exhaust gases, all mercury is not present in
the form of metallic mercury. A certain proportion thereof
is present in the form of mercury chloride because coal has a
high chlorine content, and this mercury component can be
removed. Accordingly, a chlorinating agent may be used for
the remaining metallic mercury.</p><p num="0009">However, examination of the mercury contained, for
example, in coal or heavy oil gasification gas has revealed
that almost all mercury is present as metallic mercury under
a reducing atmosphere and little is dissolved in water.
Accordingly, if an oxidizing agent is sprayed under an
atmosphere of a reducing gas during wet gas purification, the
oxidizing agent will be wasted owing to the presence of
various reducing substances and cannot be expected to produce
any beneficial effect.</p><p num="0010">Moreover, if a chlorinating agent is continuously
sprayed to induce a reaction on the catalyst, a gasification
gas having a high ammonia content and a high pressure
undergoes the reaction of ammonia with HCl, resulting in the
precipitation of ammonium chloride (NH<sub>4</sub>Cl). This ammonium
chloride may cause a problem in that it is likely to 
accumulate in such units as GGHs and block them up.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u></b></heading><p num="0011">In view of the above-described problems, the present
inventors made intensive investigations in order to develop a
mercury removal method which can remove mercury, as a trace
component in gases, effectively and efficiently, which can
reduce the mercury removal cost resulting from the operation
of the system, and which requires a simplified procedure and
system and can hence be carried out easily.</p><p num="0012">As a result, the present inventors have now found that
the coexistence of H<sub>2</sub>S in a gasification gas causes metallic
mercury to pass into water and that the so-collected is
released into the gaseous phase when the water is exposed to
a lower pressure (or flashed). That is, in the case of wet
gas purification, the coexistence of hydrogen sulfide in the
water washing step permits Hg to pass into the absorbing
fluid and be removed thereby, and the Hg captured in the
water washing step can be released into the gaseous phase by
returning the Hg-containing waste water from the elevated
pressure to atmospheric pressure. Thus, it has also been
found that the above-described problems can be solved by
removing mercury according to a method utilizing such
phenomena. The present invention has been completed from
this point of view. </p><p num="0013">Specifically, the present invention provides a mercury
removal method for the removal of mercury components present
in a gas during wet gas purification, the method comprising a
water washing step for bringing a gas containing mercury
components into contact with an absorbing fluid under
pressurized conditions including the presence of not less
than 10 ppm and preferably not less than 100 ppm of hydrogen
sulfide so as to cause mercury components to pass from the
gas into the absorbing fluid; a flashing step subsequent to
the water washing step, for spraying the discharged absorbing
fluid under a lower pressure to separate it into gaseous
components and waste water; and an adsorption removal step
for passing the gaseous components through a mercury remover
provided with an adsorbent to remove mercury components
therefrom by adsorption. In this mercury removal method, it
is preferable to dissolve mercury components in the absorbing
fluid, for example, under an elevated pressure of 0.2 to 5.0
MPa and in the coexistence of about 500 ppm to 10% of
hydrogen sulfide, and remove the flashed mercury components
by adsorption to activated carbon used as the adsorbent.
Preferably, the activated carbon has an S component deposited
thereon.</p><p num="0014">The present invention also provides a mercury removal
system for the removal of mercury present in a gas during wet
gas purification, the system comprising a water washing tower 
in which a gas containing both mercury components and
hydrogen sulfide is introduced thereinto and an absorbing
tower is circulated through the tower under pressurized
conditions so as to cause mercury components to pass into the
absorbing fluid; a flash drum in which the absorbing fluid
discharged from the water washing tower is sprayed under a
lower pressure to separate it into gaseous components and
waste water; and a mercury remover provided with an adsorbent
in which the mercury components present in the gaseous
components are removed by adsorption. Typically, the
aforesaid water washing tower comprises a gas cooling tower
and a gas cleaning tower. In this system having a flash drum
and a mercury remover installed on the downstream side of the
water washing tower, about 50 to 95% of the mercury present
in the formed gas introduced into the system can be removed.</p><p num="0015">The present invention also provides the above-described
system that further comprises a hydrogen sulfide absorption
tower in which the water-washed gas fed from the aforesaid
water washing tower introduced thereinto and an absorbing
fluid containing an amine compound is used to remove hydrogen
sulfide by absorption into the absorbing fluid; a second
flash drum in which the absorbing fluid discharged from the
hydrogen sulfide absorption tower is sprayed under a lower
pressure to separate it into gaseous components and an
absorbing fluid to be fed to a regeneration tower; and a 
mercury remover provided with an adsorbent in which the
mercury components present in the gaseous components
delivered from the second flash drum are removed by
adsorption. In this system having a flash drum and a mercury
remover installed on the downstream side of the hydrogen
sulfide absorption tower, about 50 to 95% of the mercury
present in the water-washed gas introduced into the hydrogen
sulfide absorption tower can be removed.</p><p num="0016">In the present invention, Hg can be removed by the
coexistence of hydrogen sulfide in the water washing tower of
the system. That is, if the gas being treated is a system
involving the coexistence of hydrogen sulfide, Hg passes into
the water present in the water washing tower and can hence be
removed from the gas. As a result, Hg is contained in waste
water discharged from the water washing tower.</p><p num="0017">When the collected Hg-containing waste water is returned
from the elevated pressure to atmospheric pressure, Hg is
released into the gaseous phase. Specifically, Hg is
dispersed into the gaseous phase by passing the waste water
through a flash drum.</p><p num="0018">Since hydrogen sulfide is usually present in a
gasification gas subjected to gas purification, Hg present in
the gas passes into an absorbing fluid within a water washing
tower. After this absorbing fluid is passed through a flash
drum to recover gaseous components, Hg can be adsorbed and 
captured by passing the gaseous components through an
adsorbent. The present invention comprises a system in which
Hg-containing gaseous components separated by flashing is
passed through an adsorbent to remove mercury therefrom by
means of the adsorbent. Thus, as compared with the case in
which the whole gasification gas is directly treated with an
adsorbent prior to its introduction into the system, Hg can
be removed by treating a much smaller volume of gas, and the
operating cost required for treatment with an adsorbent can
be markedly reduced.</p><p num="0019">Thus, the present invention makes it possible to remove
mercury, as a trace component in gases, effectively and
efficiently and also to reduce the mercury removal cost
resulting from the operation of the system.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Brief Description of the Drawings</u></b></heading><p num="0020"><sl><li>FIG. 1 is a diagram illustrating an outline of a system
suitable for carrying out the wet gas purification process of
the present invention.</li><li>FIG. 2 is a diagram schematically showing the
construction of the purification system used in Example 1.</li><li>FIG. 3 is a diagram schematically showing the
construction of the purification system used in Example 2.</li><li>FIG. 4 is a diagram schematically showing the
construction of the purification system used in Example 3.</li></sl></p><p num="0021">The reference numerals shown in these figures are
defined as follows: 1 Gas cooling tower; 2 Gas cleaning
tower; 3 Flash drum; 4 Mercury remover; 5 Hydrogen sulfide
absorption tower; 6 Absorption fluid regeneration tower; 7
Circulating pump; 8 Flash drum; 9 Absorbing fluid heat
exchanger; 10 Gasification furnace; 11 Cyclone; 12 Filter; 13
COS converter; 14 Gas-gas heat exchanger; 15 Mercury remover;
20,21 Flash drum.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Detailed Description of the Invention</u></b></heading><p num="0022">A specific embodiment of the wet gas purification
process in accordance with the present invention will be
described hereinbelow with reference to the accompanying
drawings.</p><p num="0023">FIG. 1 schematically illustrates an exemplary system in
accordance with this embodiment which is suitable for
carrying out the mercury removal method of the present
invention during wet gas purification. In the system of this
embodiment, the water washing step comprises a cooling step
and a cleaning step. The cooling step is carried out in a
gas cooling tower 1, and the cleaning step is carried out in
a gas cleaning tower 2. Water used to absorb the ammonia
component present in the gas is introduced, for example, into
gas cleaning tower 2. These two water washing towers serve
to remove ammonia present in the gas by absorption into an 
absorbing fluid. The water introduced into gas cleaning
tower 2 is circulated by means of a pump 7 and acts as an
absorbing fluid for absorbing ammonia. A portion thereof is
fed to gas cooling tower 1 installed on the upstream side
with respect to the direction of gas flow, and is also
circulated through the tower by means of a pump 7. The
present invention may also be practiced in an embodiment in
which the cooling and cleaning steps are carried out in a
single water washing tower. Alternatively, sulfuric acid may
be added to the absorbing fluid within gas cooling tower 1.</p><p num="0024">In the above-described water washing step for the
removal of ammonia, when mercury components are contained in
the introduced gas and not less than 10 ppm of hydrogen
sulfide is also contained therein, the mercury components
pass into the absorbing fluid under pressurized conditions in
the water washing towers (i.e., the cooling tower and the
cleaning tower). Since the passage of mercury components
into the absorbing fluid is influenced by temperature, the
degree of mercury removal from the gas is enhanced as the
temperature of the fluid becomes lower. Accordingly, it is
believed that the degree of mercury removal is influenced by
the temperatures of gas cooling tower 1 and gas cleaning
tower 2, and the degree of mercury removal is enhanced as the
temperature of gas cleaning tower 2 installed on the
downstream side becomes lower. From the viewpoint of mercury 
removal, it is preferable to operate gas cleaning tower 2
usually at 50 °C or below and preferably at 40 °C or below.</p><p num="0025">Next, the mercury-containing absorbing fluid discharged
from the above-described water washing step is transferred to
a flashing step using a flash drum 3, in which it is sprayed
under a lower pressure. Thus, the absorbing fluid is
separated into gaseous components and waste water.</p><p num="0026">In such purification treatment systems, the waste water
discharged from the water washing step generally has a high
pressure and hence contains various gases dissolved therein.
In order to treat such waste water, it is common practice to
depressurize the waste water in flash drum 3 and thereby
release it from the elevated pressure. Thus, the gases
dissolved therein are once flashed and released into the
gaseous phase. Then, the remaining solution is subjected to
a waste water treatment.</p><p num="0027">Where an ordinary formed gas is treated, the flashed gas
components are burned in a combustion furnace or discharged
into the atmosphere. However, where the gas being treated
according to the present invention is a mercury-containing
gas, these gas components include mercury. The reason for
this is believed that, when the absorbing fluid into which
mercury has passed in the water washing step is sprayed under
a lower pressure, the mercury, together with other gases, is
suspended or dispersed in the gaseous phase. </p><p num="0028">Accordingly, the gaseous components separated in the
aforesaid flash drum 3 are passed through a mercury remover 4
provided with an adsorbent (e.g., activated carbon). In this
mercury remover 4, mercury components present in the gas are
removed by adsorption to activated carbon used as the
adsorbent. The exhaust gas from which mercury has been
removed by passage through mercury remover 4 is then fed to
an off-gas combustion furnace.</p><p num="0029">On the other hand, the mercury removal system of this
embodiment as illustrated in FIG. 1 also serves to remove
mercury components from the water-washed gas transferred from
the aforesaid water washing towers to a hydrogen sulfide
absorption tower.</p><p num="0030">In the above-described water washing step for the
removal of ammonia, a certain proportion of mercury
components pass from the mercury-containing gas into the
absorbing fluid. However, some mercury components still
remain in the water-washed gas and transferred to a further
stage of the wet gas purification system. On the downstream
side of the water washing step, there is provided a hydrogen
sulfide removal step for removing hydrogen sulfide present in
the gas. In this step, mercury components present in the gas
are also removed. The hydrogen sulfide removal step includes
an H<sub>2</sub>S absorption tower 5 and an absorbing fluid regeneration
tower 6. The water-washed gas transferred from the water 
washing step is introduced into hydrogen sulfide absorption
tower 5.</p><p num="0031">The main purpose of hydrogen sulfide absorption tower 5
is to remove hydrogen sulfide by absorption into an absorbing
fluid containing an amine. According to this embodiment, in
this hydrogen sulfide absorption tower 5, mercury components
are allowed to pass from the mercury- and hydrogen sulfide-containing
gas into the absorbing fluid under pressurized
conditions (water washing step). Thus, the amine-containing
absorbing fluid also contains mercury components.
Accordingly, the absorbing fluid discharged from hydrogen
sulfide absorption tower 5 is introduced into a second flash
drum 8, in which it is sprayed under a lower pressure and
separated into gaseous components and an absorbing fluid to
be fed to the regeneration tower.</p><p num="0032">Subsequently, in the embodiment, the gaseous components
separated in the aforesaid flash drum 8 are passed through
mercury remover 4 provided with activated carbon, similarly
to the gaseous components from the aforesaid flash drum 8.
In this mercury remover 4, mercury components present in the
gas are removed by adsorption to activated carbon. The
exhaust gas from which mercury has been removed by passage
through mercury remover 4 is then fed to an off-gas
combustion furnace.</p><p num="0033">The gaseous components separated in flash drum 8 may be 
transferred to a second mercury remover installed separately
from mercury remover 4 and treated by adsorption to activated
carbon.</p><p num="0034">In addition to activated carbon, the adsorbent may
comprise a chelate resin, elemental sulfur or a sulfur
compound supported on a carrier comprising at least one
compound selected from the group consisting of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, TiO<sub>2</sub> and
SiO<sub>2</sub>, or zeolite.</p><p num="0035">While several embodiments of the present invention have
been described, it is to be understood that the present
invention is not limited to the above-described embodiments,
but various changes and modifications may be made without
departing from the spirit and scope of the invention. The
present invention is further illustrated by the following
examples. However, these examples are not to be construed to
limit the scope of the invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0036">FIG. 2 illustrates an outline of a wet gas purification
system used in this example.</p><p num="0037">In a gasification furnace 10, coal fed thereto was
converted to a gasification gas, which was passed through a
cyclone 11 installed downstream thereof and then through a
filter 12, and fed to a COS converter 13. The feed rate of
coal was 10 kg/h. Subsequently, the formed gas passed
through a gas-gas heat exchanger 14 and then introduced into 
a wet gas purification process. The pressure of the formed
gas was 0.9 MPa and the flow rate thereof was 22.4 m<sup>3</sup>N/h(d).
Prior to the water washing step, the formed gas had an H<sub>2</sub>S
concentration of 800 to 1,000 ppm and a temperature (T<sub>1</sub>) of
about 200 °C.</p><p num="0038">The water washing step includes two towers: a gas
cooling tower 1 installed on the upstream side and a gas
cleaning tower 2 installed on the downstream side as viewed
from the direction of gas flow. The gas temperature (T<sub>2</sub>) at
the outlet of gas cooling tower 1 was 80 °C, the flow rate of
the fluid circulated through gas cooling tower 1 was 60 l/h,
and the flow rate of waste waster from gas cooling tower 1
was 1.9 l/h. Moreover, the gas temperature (T<sub>3</sub>) at the
outlet of gas cleaning tower 2 was 40 °C, and the flow rate
of the fluid circulated through gas cleaning tower 2 was 100
l/h.</p><p num="0039">The mercury-containing absorbing fluid discharged from
the water washing step was sprayed in a flash drum 20. The
separated gaseous components were introduced into a mercury
remover 4, where mercury was removed from the gas. The
amount of the gas flashed from waste water was 30 lN/h.</p><p num="0040">On the other hand, the gas freed of ammonia in the water
washing step was fed to a hydrogen sulfide absorption tower 5.
The gas temperature (T<sub>4</sub>) at the outlet of H<sub>2</sub>S absorption 
tower 5 was 40 °C, and the flow rate of the fluid circulated
through H<sub>2</sub>S absorption tower 5 was 30 l/h.</p><p num="0041">With respect to the above-described system of FIG. 2, Hg
concentrations were measured at various positions S1 to S6 in
the system. The results thus obtained are shown in Table 1
below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b><u style="single">Item</u></b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at gas cooling tower inlet, S1 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">0.0056</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at gas cleaning tower outlet, S2 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">0.0014</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at H<sub>2</sub>S absorption tower outlet, S3 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">0.0004</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration in waste water from gas cooling tower, S4 (mg/l)</entry><entry align="center">0.001</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration in flashed gas from waste water, S5 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at Hg adsorption remover outlet, S6 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.01</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0042">The difference between concentrations S1 and S2 given in
Table 1 (i.e., S1-S2) is the amount of mercury which was
removed by the water washing step. Moreover, when the
gaseous components separated by flashing waste water were
passed through mercury remover 4, the mercury concentration
was reduced from 3.0 mg/m<sup>3</sup>N (S5) to less than 0.01 mg/m<sup>3</sup>N
(S6). It has been confirmed by these results that mercury
passes into the waste water discharged from the water washing
step and mercury components can be effectively removed from 
the gaseous components separated by flashing the waste water.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0043">FIG. 3 illustrates an outline of a wet gas purification
system used in this example.</p><p num="0044">In addition to the system of Example 1, this example
includes an additional step in which the mercury (Hg) removed
into the absorbing fluid in hydrogen sulfide absorption tower
5 was introduced into a flash drum 21 to release it into the
gaseous phase and then removed by means of a mercury remover
15 using activated carbon or the like. The conditions
concerning the formed gas and the flow rates and temperatures
employed in the water washing step were the same as those
described in Example 1. The amount of the gas separated by
flashing the H<sub>2</sub>S absorbing gas in flash drum 21 was 50 lN/h.</p><p num="0045">With respect to the above-described system of FIG. 3, Hg
concentrations were measured at various positions S1 to S9 in
the system. The results thus obtained are shown in Table 2
below. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b><u style="single">Item</u></b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at gas cooling tower inlet, S1 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">0.0056</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at gas cleaning tower outlet, S2 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">0.0014</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at H<sub>2</sub>S absorption tower outlet, S3 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">0.0004</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration in waste water from gas cooling tower, S4 (mg/l)</entry><entry align="center">0.001</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration in flashed gas from waste water, S5 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at Hg adsorption remover outlet, S6 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration in H<sub>2</sub>S absorbing fluid, S7 (mg/l)</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.005</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration in flashed gas from H<sub>2</sub>S absorbing fluid, S8 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">0.45</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at Hg adsorption remover outlet, S9 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.01</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0046">The difference between concentrations S2 and S3 given in
Table 2 (i.e., S2-S3) is the amount of mercury which was
removed by washing with the absorbing fluid within the
hydrogen sulfide absorption tower. Moreover, when the
gaseous components separated by flashing the absorbing fluid
were passed through mercury remover 15, the mercury
concentration was reduced from 0.45 mg/m<sup>3</sup>N (S8) to less than
0.01 mg/m<sup>3</sup>N (S9). It has been confirmed by these results
that, also in the hydrogen sulfide absorption step subsequent
to the water washing step, mercury passes into the absorbing
fluid and mercury components can be effectively removed from
the gaseous components separated by flashing the absorbing
fluid. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><p num="0047">FIG. 4 illustrates an outline of a wet gas purification
system used in this example.</p><p num="0048">In addition to the system of Example 2, this example
includes an additional step in which the exhaust gas having
passed through gas-gas heat exchanger 14, which was directly
discharged in Example 2, was passed through heat exchangers
and then burned in a combustor. In this example, the feed
rate of coal was 1,000 kg/h, the flow rate of the formed gas
was 3,500 m<sup>3</sup>N/h, the H<sub>2</sub>S concentration in the formed gas was
800 to 1,000 ppm, the gas temperature (T<sub>2</sub>) at the outlet of
gas cooling tower 1 was 40 °C, the flow rate of the fluid
circulated through gas cooling tower 1 was 8.4 tons/h, the
flow rate of waste waster from gas cooling tower 1 was 0.4
ton/h, the amount of the flashed gas produced from waste
water in flash drum 20 was 0.2 m<sup>3</sup>N/h, the gas temperature
(T<sub>3</sub>) at the outlet of gas cleaning tower 2 was 40 °C, the
flow rate of the fluid circulated through gas cleaning tower
2 was 10 tons/h, the gas temperature (T<sub>4</sub>) at the outlet of
H<sub>2</sub>S absorption tower 5 was 40 °C, the flow rate of the fluid
circulated through H<sub>2</sub>S absorption tower 5 was 3.6 tons/h, and
the amount of the flashed gas produced from the H<sub>2</sub>S absorbing
fluid was 1.6 m<sup>3</sup>N/h. Other conditions were the same as in
Example 2. </p><p num="0049">With respect to the above-described system of FIG. 4, Hg
concentrations were measured at various positions S1 to S9 in
the system. The results thus obtained are shown in Table 3
below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b><u style="single">Item</u></b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at gas cooling tower inlet, S1 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">0.005</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at gas cleaning tower outlet, S2 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">0.0013</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at H<sub>2</sub>S absorption tower outlet, S3 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">0.0003</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration in waste water from gas cooling tower, S4 (mg/l)</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.005</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration in flashed gas from waste water, S5 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">63</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at Hg adsorption remover outlet, S6 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration in H<sub>2</sub>S absorbing fluid, S7 (mg/l)</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.005</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration in flashed gas from H<sub>2</sub>S absorbing fluid, S8 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">2.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hg concentration at Hg adsorption remover outlet, S9 (mg/m<sup>3</sup>N)</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.01</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0050">It has been confirmed by these results that, even when a
large volume of formed gas is subjected to wet gas
purification, the mercury removal method of the present
invention can reduce the Hg concentration in exhaust gas to
less than 0.01 mg/m<sup>3</sup>N at all of positions S6 to S9.</p><p num="0051">According to the mercury removal method of the present
invention, the volume of gas being treated can be markedly
decreased by treating flashed gas, and the operating cost 
required for the treatment can also be reduced, as compared
with the case in which the formed gas is directly treated.
Moreover, since no energy supply to the mercury removal (or
absorption) step and the Hg flashing step is required for the
purpose of mercury removal, Hg can be positively removed
without modifying an ordinary purification system
substantially.</p><p num="0052">Furthermore, the adsorbent for the adsorption of Hg can
be used at low temperatures (400 °C or below) and only a
small amount of adsorbent is required because of its high
rate of Hg removal. In addition, since a gas once dissolved
in water is treated with activated carbon, hydrocarbons and
other substances capable of inhibiting Hg adsorption are not
present therein.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A mercury removal method for the removal of mercury
present in a gas, said method comprising the steps of
bringing a gas containing at least not less than 10 ppm of
hydrogen sulfide and mercury into gas-liquid contact with an
absorbing fluid under pressurized conditions so as to cause
mercury to pass into the absorbing fluid; flashing the
mercury-containing absorbing fluid under lower-pressure
conditions to separate it into gaseous components and liquid
components; and removing the mercury contained in the
separated gaseous components by adsorption to an adsorbent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A mercury removal method as claimed in claim 1
which comprises the steps of bringing a gas containing at
least not less than 10 ppm of hydrogen sulfide and mercury
into gas-liquid contact with an absorbing fluid under
pressurized conditions so as to cause mercury to pass into
the absorbing fluid; bringing the gas freed partially of
mercury into gas-liquid contact with an absorbing fluid
containing an amine compound so as to cause hydrogen sulfide
and mercury present in the gas to be absorbed into the
absorbing fluid; flashing each of the absorbing fluids under
a lower pressure to separate it into a mercury-containing gas
and a liquid; and removing mercury from the mercury-containing
gases by adsorption to an adsorbent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A mercury removal method as claimed in claim 1 or 2
wherein the gas containing at least not less than 10 ppm of
hydrogen sulfide and mercury is coal gasification gas or
heavy oil gasification gas.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A mercury removal method as claimed in any of
claims 1 to 3 wherein the adsorbent for adsorbing mercury
comprises a chelate resin, elemental sulfur or a sulfur
compound supported on a carrier comprising at least one
compound selected from the group consisting of Al2O3, TiO2 and
SiO2, activated carbon or zeolite.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A mercury removal method for the removal of mercury
components present in a gas during wet gas purification, said
method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a water washing step for bringing a gas containing
mercury components into contact with an absorbing fluid under
pressurized conditions including the presence of not less
than 10 ppm of hydrogen sulfide so as to cause mercury
components to pass from the gas into the absorbing fluid;</claim-text><claim-text>a flashing step subsequent to the water washing step,
for spraying the discharged absorbing fluid under a lower
pressure to separate it into gaseous components and waste
water; and</claim-text><claim-text>an adsorption removal step for passing the gaseous
components through a mercury remover provided with an
adsorbent to remove mercury components therefrom by
adsorption.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A mercury removal method as claimed in claim 5
wherein the adsorbent comprises a chelate resin, elemental
sulfur or a sulfur compound supported on a carrier comprising
at least one compound selected from the group consisting of
Al2O3, TiO2 and SiO2, activated carbon or zeolite.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A mercury removal system for the removal of mercury
present in a gas during wet gas purification, said system
comprising a water washing tower in which a gas containing
both mercury components and hydrogen sulfide is introduced
thereinto and an absorbing tower is circulated through the
tower under pressurized conditions so as to cause mercury
components to pass into the absorbing fluid; a flash drum in
which the absorbing fluid discharged from the water washing
tower is sprayed under a lower pressure to separate it into
gaseous components and waste water; and a mercury remover
provided with an adsorbent in which the mercury components
present in the gaseous components are removed by adsorption.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A mercury removal system as claimed in claim 7,
said system further comprising a hydrogen sulfide absorption
tower in which the water-washed gas fed from the water
washing tower introduced thereinto and an absorbing fluid
containing an amine compound is used to remove hydrogen
sulfide by absorption into the absorbing fluid; a second
flash drum in which the absorbing fluid discharged from the
hydrogen sulfide absorption tower is sprayed under a lower
pressure to separate it into gaseous components and an
absorbing fluid to be fed to a regeneration tower; and a
mercury remover provided with an adsorbent in which the
mercury components present in the gaseous components
delivered from the second flash drum are removed by
adsorption.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A mercury removal system as claimed in claim 7 or 8
wherein the adsorbent comprises a chelate resin, elemental
sulfur or a sulfur compound supported on a carrier comprising
at least one compound selected from the group consisting of
Al2O3, TiO2 and SiO2, activated carbon or zeolite.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>