<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1300244-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1300244" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25518353" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030409"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1300244-A1" status="new" fvid="23727751"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1300244</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030409</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02078941-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02078941</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020923</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-97141401-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>97141401</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011005</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01F  17/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01F  17/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/175       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/175       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01F  17/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/175C2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/175C3A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/175C8</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Tintenzusammensetzung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Ink composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition d'encre</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0784085-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0784085</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-10114875-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>10114875</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4361843-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4361843</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4400215-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4400215</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5683500-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5683500</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000059620-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000059620</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 1998, no. 10, 31 August 1998 (1998-08-31) &amp; JP 10 114875 A (TOSHIBA CORP;FUJI SHIKISO KK), 6 May 1998 (1998-05-06)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>EASTMAN KODAK CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>EASTMAN KODAK COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>EASTMAN KODAK COMPANY</last-name><address><street>343 State Street</street><city>Rochester, New York 14650</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BLEASE JAMES WEST</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WHITLOCK LEE RONALD</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BLEASE, JAMES WEST</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WHITLOCK, LEE RONALD</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BLEASE, JAMES WEST</last-name><address><street>343 State Street</street><city>Rochester, New York 14650-2201</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WHITLOCK, LEE RONALD</last-name><address><street>343 State Street</street><city>Rochester, New York 14650-2201</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Haile, Helen Cynthia</last-name><address><street>Kodak Limited Patent, W92-3A, Headstone Drive</street><city>Harrow, Middlesex HA1 4TY</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An ink composition and an ink cartridge having the ink
composition are provided. The ink composition includes a colorant and an
aqueous carrier, the ink composition having a dissolved gas content of less than 3
ppm as measured on the basis of the amount of dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C and
a static surface tension at 25°C of greater than 34 dynes/cm. The ink cartridge
(16) includes an ink container filled (70) with a liquid ink, the liquid ink having a
dissolved gas content of less than 3 ppm as measured on the basis of the amount
of dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C and a static surface tension at 25°C of greater
than 34 dynes/cm. The ink container can be a collapsible bag.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="100"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to ink jet printing and, more
particularly, to ink compositions used in ink jet printing.</p><p num="0002">Ink jet printing is a non-impact method for producing images by
the deposition of ink droplets in a pixel-by-pixel manner to an image-recording
element in response to digital signals. There are various methods which may be
utilized to control the deposition of ink droplets on the image-recording element
to yield the desired image. In one process, known as continuous ink jet, a
continuous stream of droplets is charged and deflected in an imagewise manner
onto the surface of the image-recording element, while unimaged droplets are
caught and returned to an ink sump. In another process, known as drop-on-demand
ink jet, individual ink droplets are projected as needed onto the image-recording
element to form the desired image. Common methods of controlling
the projection of ink droplets in drop-on-demand printing include piezoelectric
transducers and thermal bubble formation.</p><p num="0003">The inks used in the various ink jet printers can be classified as
either dye-based or pigment-based. A dye is a colorant, which is dissolved in the
carrier medium. A pigment is a colorant that is insoluble in the carrier medium,
but is dispersed or suspended in the form of small particles, often stabilized
against flocculation and settling by the use of dispersing agents. The carrier
medium can be a liquid or a solid at room temperature in both cases. Commonly
used carrier media include water, mixtures of water and organic co-solvents and
high boiling organic solvents, such as hydrocarbons, esters, ketones, etc.</p><p num="0004">A requirement in wide format ink jet printers is the delivery of at
least 500 ml of ink through a printhead before nozzles begin to fail to fire ink
droplets. In order to achieve this, the ink composition is required to have desired
physical characteristics including viscosity, surface tension and amount of
dissolved gas. The optimized property levels are largely dependent on the printer
design and printhead architecture. </p><p num="0005">During the ink delivery from an ink cartridge to a printer head,
minute air bubbles present in the ink or within the ink cartridge gives flow
resistance to the ink. In addition, when the ink head is repeatedly pressurized and
depressurized during ink ejection, dissolved gases (e.g. dissolved oxygen and
dissolved nitrogen) present in the ink tend to stagnate in the ink head causing the
printhead to misfire during droplet ejection resulting in reduced printhead
reliability. This is particularly true in piezoelectric print heads. Additionally,
changes in both ink viscosity and surface tension can cause unreliable droplet
ejection or droplet splashing which leads to reduced image quality. Typically,
inks having a low surface tension (typically less than 40 mN/m) tend to have a
faster drying time when compared to inks having a high surface tension (typically
greater than 40 mN/m). However, inks having a high surface tension typically
produce images of higher image quality as compared to the images produced by
inks having lower surface tension.</p><p num="0006">U.S. Patent 5,683,500, which issued to Kawasumi et al. on
November 4, 1997, optimizes an ink composition used in a writing instrument so
as to reduced writing defects including uneven ink density and skips in a drawn
line. U.S. Patent 5,833,744, which issued to Breton et al. on November 10, 1998,
optimizes an ink composition by adding a paper specific surfactant having a paper
pulp debonding agent. U.S. Patent 6,288,156 B1, which issued to Higashiyama et
al. on May 8, 2001, optimizes an ink composition for use over a range of
temperatures.</p><p num="0007">An object of the present invention is to optimize the above
described physical properties of an ink composition so that desired quantities of
ink can be delivered by a printhead to a receiver reliability and consistently over
time.</p><p num="0008">According to one feature of the present invention, an ink
composition has a colorant and an aqueous carrier, wherein the ink composition
has a dissolved gas content of less than 3 ppm as measured on the basis of the 
amount of dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C and a static surface tension at 25°C of
greater than 34 dynes/cm.</p><p num="0009">According to another feature of the present invention, an ink
cartridge has an ink container filled with a liquid ink, the liquid ink having a
dissolved gas content of less than 3 ppm as measured on the basis of the amount
of dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C and a static surface tension at 25°C of greater
than 34 dynes/cm.</p><p num="0010">According to another feature of the present invention, an ink
cartridge has a housing having a front side wall, a back side wall opposite the
front side wall, a pair of opposed left and right side walls separating the front and
the back side walls, and a bottom wall, the walls defining an internal cavity within
the housing. An ink container is located within the internal cavity and filled with
a liquid ink, the liquid ink having a dissolved gas content of less than 3 ppm as
measured on the basis of the amount of dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C and a static
surface tension at 25°C of greater than 34 dynes/cm.</p><p num="0011">According to another feature of the present invention, a method of
filling an ink cartridge providing a housing having a front side wall, a back side
wall opposite the front side wall, a pair of opposed left and right side walls
separating the front and the back side walls, and a bottom wall, the walls defining
an internal cavity within the housing; providing an ink container; positioning the
ink container within the internal cavity; and filling the ink container with a liquid
ink having a dissolved gas content of less than 3 ppm as measured on the basis of
the amount of dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C and a static surface tension at 25°C of
greater than 34 dynes/cm.
<sl><li>FIG. 1A is a perspective view of an inkjet printer;</li><li>FIG. 1B is a perspective view showing an inkjet printhead used in
the printer of FIG. 1A;</li><li>FIG.1C is a plan view illustrating the nozzle plate for the printhead
of FIG. 1B;</li><li>FIG. 2 is a perspective view of an ink cartridge receiver assembly 
used in the printer of FIG. 1;</li><li>FIG. 3 is a top plan view of the ink cartridge receiver assembly of
FIG. 2;</li><li>FIG. 4 is another perspective view of the ink cartridge receiver
assembly used in the printer of FIG. 1;</li><li>FIG. 5 is a perspective view of an ink cartridge;</li><li>FIG. 6 shows a bottom view of the ink cartridge;</li><li>FIGS. 7 and 8 show ink cartridge alignment features engaging with
the separators in the ink cartridge receiver assembly;</li><li>FIGS. 9A and 9B show how the color identifier keyway and color
identifier key tab interface when the ink cartridge is placed in the receiver
assembly;</li><li>FIG. 10 is an exploded view showing an ink bag, fitment and the
septum and ink withdrawal needle which needle forms part of a receptacle in the
cartridge receiver assembly;</li><li>FIG. 11 is a schematic of a cross-section of the ink cartridge
illustrating support by the internal surfaces of the ink cartridge of the filled ink
bag;</li><li>FIG. 12A and FIG. 12B are front side elevational views of the ink
bag that is to be positioned in the cartridge and showing respectively the ink bag
in a fully stretched condition and the ink bag when it is not stretched; and</li><li>FIG. 13 is a perspective view of the ink bag.</li></sl></p><p num="0012">The present description will be directed in particular to elements
forming part of, or cooperating more directly with, apparatus and methods in
accordance with the present invention. It is to be understood that elements not
specifically shown or described may take various forms well known to those
skilled in the art.</p><p num="0013">In order to meet the above described ink delivery performance
requirements, improve image quality, and improve printer performance, the
inventors of the present invention have discovered that it is desirable to reduce the 
amount of dissolved gas present in an ink composition and maintain the surface
tension of the ink composition above a predetermined level. As such, an ink
composition of the present invention comprises a colorant and an aqueous carrier,
wherein a dissolved gas content of the ink composition is less than 3 ppm as
measured on the basis of the amount of dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C and a static
surface tension of the ink composition at 25°C is greater than 34 dynes/cm.
Additionally, ink compositions of this type are particular suited for use in an ink
cartridge having an ink container positioned therein, as described below.</p><p num="0014">The colorant can be a water-soluble dye, a pigment, or any other
type of colorant provided the colorant can form a color in a water based ink
composition. Additionally, the colorant can have chromatic color or achromatic
color. As referred to in this description and as defined in <u style="single">Measuring Color,</u> by
R.W.G. Hunt, published by Ellis Horwood Limited (1991), the term chromatic
color denotes any color exhibiting hue (these colors are distinct from those colors
commonly referred to as white, gray, black, neutral, and colorless) while the term
achromatic color denotes any color devoid of hue (commonly referred to as
white, gray, black, neutral, and colorless colors).</p><p num="0015">Any water-soluble dye, or combination of dyes, commonly used in
an ink composition having an aqueous carrier can be used in this invention, such
as reactive dyes, direct dyes, anionic dyes, acid dyes, food dyes and the like, for
example, those described in U.S. Patent 5,973,026. Additionally, the water-soluble
dye can be a cationic dye or an anionic dye. Examples of cationic dyes
include azo dyes, such as quaternized pyrazoleazoaniline dyes, triarylmethane
dyes, azine dyes, phthalocyanine dyes, oxazine dyes, thiazine dyes, etc.
Examples of anionic dyes include metal-complex dyes, such as transition metal
complexes of 8-heterocyclylazo-5-hydroxyquinoline; azo dyes, such as C.I.
Direct Yellow 132; phthalocyanine dyes such as C.I. Direct Blue 199;
anthraquinone dyes, or anthrapyridone dyes; etc. The exact choice of dye will
depend upon the specific application and performance requirements such as color
reproduction and image stability. </p><p num="0016">Any known pigment, or combination of pigments, commonly used
in an ink composition having an aqueous carrier can be used in the invention. For
example those pigments disclosed in U.S. Patents 5,026,427; 5,086,698;
5,141,556; 5,160,370; and 5,169,436. The exact choice of pigments will depend
upon the specific application and performance requirements such as color
reproduction and image stability. Pigments suitable for use in the present
invention include, for example, azo pigments, monoazo pigments, disazo
pigments, azo pigment lakes, β-Naphthol pigments, Naphthol AS pigments,
benzimidazolone pigments, disazo condensation pigments, metal complex
pigments, isoindolinone and isoindoline pigments, polycyclic pigments,
phthalocyanine pigments, quinacridone pigments, perylene and perinone
pigments, thioindigo pigments, anthrapyrimidone pigments, flavanthrone
pigments, anthanthrone pigments, dioxazine pigments, triarylcarbonium
pigments, quinophthalone pigments, diketopyrrolo pyrrole pigments, titanium
oxide, iron oxide, and carbon black. Typical examples of pigments which may be
used include Color Index (C. I.) Pigment Yellow 1, 2, 3, 5, 6, 10, 12, 13, 14, 16,
17, 62, 65, 73, 74, 75, 81, 83, 87, 90, 93, 94, 95, 97, 98, 99, 100, 101, 104, 106,
108, 109, 110, 111, 113, 114, 116, 117, 120, 121, 123, 124, 126, 127, 128, 129,
130, 133, 136, 138, 139, 147, 148, 150, 151, 152, 153, 154, 155, 165, 166, 167,
168, 169, 170, 171, 172, 173, 174, 175, 176, 177, 179, 180, 181, 182, 183, 184,
185, 187, 188, 190, 191, 192, 193, 194; C. I. Pigment Orange 1, 2, 5, 6, 13, 15,
16, 17, 17:1, 19, 22, 24, 31, 34, 36, 38, 40, 43, 44, 46, 48, 49, 51, 59, 60, 61, 62,
64, 65, 66, 67, 68, 69; C. I. Pigment Red 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13,
14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 21, 22, 23, 31, 32, 38, 48:1, 48:2, 48:3, 48:4, 49:1, 49:2, 49:3,
50:1, 51, 52:1, 52:2, 53:1, 57:1, 60:1, 63:1, 66, 67, 68, 81, 95, 112, 114, 119,
122, 136, 144, 146, 147, 148, 149, 150, 151, 164, 166, 168, 169, 170, 171, 172,
175, 176, 177, 178, 179, 181, 184, 185, 187, 188, 190, 192, 194, 200, 202, 204,
206, 207, 210, 211, 212, 213, 214, 216, 220, 222, 237, 238, 239, 240, 242, 243,
245, 247, 248, 251, 252, 253, 254, 255, 256, 258, 261, 264; C.I. Pigment Violet
1, 2, 3, 5:1, 13, 19, 23, 25, 27, 29, 31, 32, 37, 39, 42, 44, 50; C.I. Pigment Blue 1, 
2, 9, 10, 14, 15:1, 15:2, 15:3, 15:4, 15:6, 15, 16, 18, 19, 24:1, 25, 56, 60, 61, 62,
63, 64, 66; C.I. Pigment Green 1, 2, 4, 7, 8, 10, 36, 45; C.I. Pigment Black 1, 7,
20, 31, 32, and C.I. Pigment Brown 1, 5, 22, 23, 25, 38, 41, 42. In a preferred
embodiment of the invention, the pigment is C.I. Pigment Blue 15:3, C.I.
Pigment Red 122, C.I. Pigment Yellow 155, C.I. Pigment Yellow 74,
bis(phthalocyanylalumino)tetraphenyldisiloxane or C.I. Pigment Black 7.</p><p num="0017">If a pigment is used as the colorant, a pigment dispersant can be
added to the ink composition. Pigment dispersants include water-soluble resins,
surface active agents, and the like. Examples of water-soluble resins include
natural resins, semi-synthetic resins, synthetic resins, etc. Examples of synthetic
resins include alkali-water-soluble resins such as polyacrylic acid resins,
polymaleic acid resins, styrene-acrylic acid copolymers and styrene-maleic acid
copolymers, water-soluble styrene resins, polyvinyl pyrrolidone, polyvinyl
alcohol, water-soluble urethane resins, etc. Examples of surface-active agents
include anionic surface-active agents, cationic surface-active agents, nonionic
surface-active agents, ampholytic surface-active agents, etc.</p><p num="0018">Typically, the aqueous carrier for the ink composition is water or a
mixture of water and at least one water miscible co-solvent. Selection of a
suitable mixture depends on requirements of the specific application, such as
desired surface tension and viscosity, the selected pigment or dye, drying time of
the ink jet ink, and the type of paper onto which the ink will be printed.
Representative examples of water-miscible co-solvents that may be selected
include (1) alcohols, such as methyl alcohol, ethyl alcohol, n-propyl alcohol,
isopropyl alcohol, n-butyl alcohol, sec-butyl alcohol, t-butyl alcohol, iso-butyl
alcohol, furfuryl alcohol, and tetrahydrofurfuryl alcohol; (2) ketones or
ketoalcohols such as acetone, methyl ethyl ketone and diacetone alcohol; (3)
ethers, such as tetrahydrofuran and dioxane; (4) esters, such as ethyl acetate, ethyl
lactate, ethylene carbonate and propylene carbonate; (5) polyhydric alcohols, such
as ethylene glycol, diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol, tetraethylene glycol,
propylene glycol, polyethylene glycol, glycerol, 2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol 1,2, 
6-hexanetriol and thioglycol; (6) lower alkyl mono- or di-ethers derived from
alkylene glycols, such as ethylene glycol mono-methyl (or -ethyl) ether,
diethylene glycol mono-methyl (or -ethyl) ether, diethylene glycol mono-butyl
(or -ethyl) ether, propylene glycol mono-methyl (or -ethyl) ether, poly(ethylene
glycol) butyl ether, triethylene glycol mono-methyl (or -ethyl) ether and
diethylene glycol di-methyl (or -ethyl) ether; (7) nitrogen containing cyclic
compounds, such as pyrrolidone, N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone, and 1,3-dimethyl-2-imidazolidinone;
and (8) sulfur-containing compounds such as dimethyl
sulfoxide, 2,2'-thiodiethanol, and tetramethylene sulfone.</p><p num="0019">Typically, the amount of aqueous carrier employed is in the range
of approximately 70 to 98 weight %, preferably approximately 90 to 98 weight
%, based on the total weight of the ink. A mixture of water and a polyhydric
alcohol, such as diethylene glycol, is useful as an aqueous carrier. In a preferred
embodiment, the inks contain from 5 to 60 weight % of water miscible organic
solvent. Percentages are based on the total weight of the aqueous carrier.</p><p num="0020">Water-miscible organic solvents may also be added to the ink
composition in order to help the ink penetrate the receiving substrate, especially
when the substrate is a highly sized paper. Examples of such solvents include
alcohols, such as methyl alcohol, ethyl alcohol, n-propyl alcohol, isopropyl
alcohol, n-butyl alcohol, sec-butyl alcohol, t-butyl alcohol, iso-butyl alcohol,
furfuryl alcohol, and tetrahydrofurfuryl alcohol; ketones or ketoalcohols such as
acetone, methyl ethyl ketone and diacetone alcohol; ethers, such as
tetrahydrofuran and dioxane; and esters, such as, ethyl lactate, ethylene carbonate
and propylene carbonate.</p><p num="0021">Other additives which may optionally be present in the ink jet ink
compositions include thickeners, conductivity enhancing agents, anti-kogation
agents, drying agents, waterfast agents, dye solubilizers, chelating agents, binders,
light stabilizers, viscosifiers, buffering agents, anti-mold agents, anti-curl agents,
stabilizers and defoamers. Additionally, the ink compositions can include a 
humectant, a surfactant, a penetrant, a biocide, etc. as is required depending on the
application.</p><p num="0022">A humectant is usually employed in the ink jet compositions of the
invention to help prevent the ink from drying out or crusting in the orifices of the
printhead. Examples of humectants which can be used include polyhydric
alcohols, such as ethylene glycol, diethylene glycol(DEG), triethylene glycol,
propylene glycol, tetraethylene glycol, polyethylene glycol, glycerol, 2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol,
2-ethyl-2-hydroxymethyl-1,3-propanediol(EHMP), 1,5
pentanediol, 1,2-hexanediol, 1,2,6-hexanetriol and thioglycol; lower alkyl mono-
or di-ethers derived from alkylene glycols, such as ethylene glycol mono-methyl
or mono-ethyl ether, diethylene glycol mono-methyl or mono-ethyl ether,
propylene glycol mono-methyl or mono-ethyl ether, triethylene glycol mono-methyl,
mono-ethyl or mono-butyl ether (TEGMBE), diethylene glycol di-methyl
or di-ethyl ether, poly(ethylene glycol) monobutyl ether (PEGMBE), and
diethylene glycol monobutylether(DEGMBE); nitrogen-containing compounds,
such as urea, 2-pyrrolidinone, N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinone, and 1,3-dimethyl-2-imidazolidinone;
and sulfur-containing compounds such as dimethyl sulfoxide
and tetramethylene sulfone, etc..</p><p num="0023">Preferred humectants for the inks of the invention include DEG,
glycerol, DEGMBE, TEGMBE, 1,2-hexanediol, 1,5-pentanediol, urea, 2-pyrrolidinone,
EHMP and mixtures thereof. Preferably, the humectant employed
in each ink in an amount of from 5 to 60 weight percent.</p><p num="0024">Surfactants may be added to the ink to adjust the surface tension to
an appropriate level. The surfactants may be anionic, cationic, amphoteric or
nonionic and used at levels of 0.01 to 1% of the ink composition. Preferred
surfactants include Surfynol® 465 (available from Air Products Corp.) and
Tergitol® 15-S-5 (available from Union Carbide).</p><p num="0025">A penetrant (0-10% by weight) may also be added to the ink
composition employed in the process of the invention to help the ink penetrate the
receiving substrate, especially when the substrate is a highly sized paper. A 
preferred penetrant for the inks of the present invention is n-propanol at a final
concentration of 1-6% by weight.</p><p num="0026">A biocide may be added to the ink composition employed in the
invention to suppress the growth of microorganisms such as molds, fungi, etc. in
aqueous inks. A preferred biocide for the ink composition employed in the
present invention is Proxel® GXL (Avecia Corp.) at a final concentration of
0.0001-0.5 wt.%.</p><p num="0027">The pH of the aqueous ink compositions employed in the
invention may be adjusted by the addition of organic or inorganic acids or bases.
Useful inks may have a preferred pH of from 2 to 10, depending upon the type of
dye being used. Typical inorganic acids include hydrochloric, phosphoric and
sulfuric acids. Typical organic acids include methanesulfonic, acetic and lactic
acids. Typical inorganic bases include alkali metal hydroxides and carbonates.
Typical organic bases include ammonia, triethanolamine (TEA) and
tetramethylethlenediamine.</p><p num="0028">A typical ink composition employed in the invention may
comprise, for example, the following components by weight: colorant (0.05-20%),
water (20-95%), a humectant (5-70%), water miscible co-solvents (2-20%),
surfactant (0.1-10%), biocide (0.05-5%) and pH control agents (0.1-10%).
Examples of ink compositions made in accordance with the present invention
include the following.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1">Example Ink Formulations</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ink</entry><entry align="left">Dye(s)</entry><entry align="left">Wt.% Dye(s)</entry><entry align="left">Wt.% glycerol</entry><entry align="left">Wt.% DEG</entry><entry align="left">Wt.% PEG MBE</entry><entry align="left">t.% TEA</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex. 1 Cyan</entry><entry align="left">Avecia Projet Fast Cyan 2</entry><entry align="center">3.6</entry><entry align="center">9.5</entry><entry align="center">12.5</entry><entry align="center">7.0</entry><entry align="center">0.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex. 2 Magenta</entry><entry align="left">Nippon Kayaku JPD-EK1,

Sensient Reactive Red 31</entry><entry align="center">3.00

0.86</entry><entry align="center">9.0</entry><entry align="center">11.5</entry><entry align="center">7.5</entry><entry align="center">0.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex. 3 Yellow</entry><entry align="left">Avecia Projet Yellow 1G</entry><entry align="center">4.0</entry><entry align="center">15.5</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">9.0</entry><entry align="center">0.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex. 4 Black</entry><entry align="left">Clariant Duasyn KRL-SF</entry><entry align="center">5.0</entry><entry align="center">8.0</entry><entry align="center">11.25</entry><entry align="center">8.5 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex. 5 Light Cyan</entry><entry align="left">Avecia Projet Fast Cyan 2</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry><entry align="center">11.75</entry><entry align="center">13.5</entry><entry align="center">7.0</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex. 6 Light Magenta</entry><entry align="left">Nippon Kayaku JPD-EK1,

Sensient Reactive Red 31</entry><entry align="center">0.9 0.24</entry><entry align="center">11.3</entry><entry align="center">13.5</entry><entry align="center">7.5</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex. 7 Cyan</entry><entry align="left">Avecia Projet Fast Cyan 2</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">5.5</entry><entry align="center">5.5</entry><entry align="center">11.0</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex. 8 Cyan</entry><entry align="left">Avecia Projet Fast Cyan 2</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">9.5</entry><entry align="center">9.5</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex.9 Cyan</entry><entry align="left">Avecia Projet Fast Cyan 2</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">15.5</entry><entry align="center">15.5</entry><entry align="center">11.0</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex. 10 Cyan</entry><entry align="left">Avecia Projet Fast Cyan 2</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">19.5</entry><entry align="center">19.5</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Comparative Examples</heading> <p num="0029">Comparative examples 1 through 6 correspond to Examples 1
through 6 having a dissolved gas content of the ink composition was greater than
3 ppm as measured on the basis of the amount of dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Com. Ex. 7</entry><entry nameend="5" align="left" namest="2">Epson Cyan Ink T410

(for the Epson Stylus Pro 9000 Printer)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Com. Ex. 8</entry><entry nameend="5" align="left" namest="2">Epson Cyan Ink T502

(for the Epson Stylus Pro 10000 Printer)</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">Inks</entry> <entry align="left">Dye(s)</entry><entry align="left">Wt.%

Dye(s)</entry><entry align="left">Wt.% 2-pyrrolidinone</entry><entry align="left">Wt.%

1,2-hexanediol</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Com. Ex. 9 Black</entry><entry align="left">Clariant Duasyn KRL-SF</entry><entry align="center">12.0</entry><entry align="center">12.0</entry><entry align="center">6.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Testing Procedures</u></heading><p num="0030">Ink viscosity can be measured by any suitable means known in the
art. For the ink compositions of the invention and the comparative examples, a
temperature controlled capillary viscometer was used. The viscometer employs an
electronic balance to collect the ink that leaves the capillary tube so that a mass
flow rate at steady state can be determined. The capillary tube is made from glass 
and has a diameter of 0.1 centimeter and is temperature controlled by a water
jacket. All ink measurements were made at 25 °C.</p><p num="0031">Ink viscosity is calculated from the Poiseuille equation shown
below.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">µ = <st32:frac align="centre">ρ<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup> g(h + L)πD<st32:sup pos="post">4</st32:sup><st32:over>128Lq</st32:over></st32:frac></st32:df>
In the equation, µ is the ink viscosity, g is the gravitational constant, <i>h</i> is the
height of the liquid sample above the capillary tube, <i>L</i> is the length of the
capillary tube, <i>D</i> is the diameter of the capillary tube, ρ is the density of the ink to
be tested and <i>q</i> is the average mass flow rate of the ink.</p><p num="0032">Measurement of dissolved gas (O<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>) in the ink compositions
of the invention can be accomplished using a gas chromatography method
described in Table 1 and accompanying text set forth below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Material</entry><entry align="left">Inks (dye and pigment)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Test(s)</entry><entry align="left">O<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> (ug/g Ink)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Column</entry><entry align="left">J &amp; W Scientific Molesieve (30m x 0.53mm x 25.0 um)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Instrument</entry><entry align="left">Agilent 6890 GC with manual Purge and Trap device</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Temperature Gradient</entry><entry align="left">Initial Temperature (°C): 30, Initial Time (min): 5.5; Rate (°C/min): 15, Temperature (°C): 60; Rate (°C/min): 30, Final Temperature (°C): 250; Final Time (min): 4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Purge and Trap (liquid N<sub>2</sub>)</entry><entry align="left">Purge Time (min): 5.5, Trap Time (min): 5.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Detector Temperature (°C)</entry><entry align="left">300 °C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gases</entry><entry align="left">Carrier: Helium, Pressure (psi): 12 psi, Split flow (ml/min): 60 (empty purge vessel), Makeup (ml/min): 7 (constant), Reference (ml/min): 20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Detector</entry><entry align="left">Thermal Conductivity (TCD)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Integrator</entry><entry align="left">Agilent ChemStation (Version A.06.01)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0033">Standard Preparation: Inject 10, 20, 30, and 50 uL of Air into Purge vessel
(through septum) using a gas tight syringe. Quantification is based on a method of external
standards. Background air (O<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>) is determined by placing a section of the column in 
liquid N<sub>2</sub> for 5.5 min. O<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> areas in the background are then subtracted from that of
the standards and samples.</p><p num="0034">Sample Preparation: Pierce septum of ink bag with the needle of a 2 mL
VICI Pressure Lok syringe, withdraw 0.5 mL ink, and then discard ink. Re-pierce septum
and draw 1.3 mL of ink into the syringe. Lock in the sample by pushing the red button
until it stops against the front sleeve. Remove needle from syringe tip and attach syringe
to Purge vessel. Open purge and syringe valves and push 0.3 mL of sample (until 1.0 mL
mark) into the purge vessel, then close valves. This step removes the air present between
the syringe and the purge vessel. Wait approximately 1 min after air elutes from the
column and then insert a section of the column into a dewar of liquid N<sub>2</sub>. Immediately
open purge and syringe valves and add remaining sample (1.0 mL) to the purge vessel.
Purge/trap time is 5.5 mL. After 5.5 min, remove column from the dewar of liquid N<sub>2</sub>.
Switch purge valve to "blow out" sample after the completion of the chromatographic run.
Component O<sub>2</sub> can be identified based on the retention time of approximately 6.5 minutes
while component N<sub>2</sub> can be identified based on the retention time of approximately 6.8
minutes.</p><p num="0035">Alternatively, measurement of dissolved oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>) in the ink
compositions of the invention can be accomplished using a dissolved oxygen (DO) meter
described in Table 2 and accompanying text set forth below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Material</entry><entry align="left">Inkjet Inks</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Test</entry><entry align="left">Dissolved Oxygen Concentration, O<sub>2</sub>, PPM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Instrument</entry><entry align="left">Mettler-Teledo Model 4100 Meter equipped with oxygen sensing electrode Model 6100. Available from Mettler-Toledo Process Analytical, Inc, Woburn MA.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Calibration</entry><entry align="left">Room air and high purity Helium</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample</entry><entry align="left">Ink cartridge</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0036">Calibration Procedure: Single point calibration of Model 4100 DO meter is
done according to the recommended procedure of suspending the DO probe in air and
adjusting the digital read out to 8.5 PPM 02. A two-point calibration is the run using the
same procedure with an added step of adjusting the zero PPM 02 concentration while
suspending the DO probe in a stream of high purity He. </p><p num="0037">Sample Preparation: The degassed ink sample is contained in a flexible
plastic laminate pouch housed in a sealed plastic cartridge. The plastic cartridge is cut
opened sufficiently to expose one end of the plastic pouch. The pouch is then cut open
only sufficiently to allow insertion of the metal DO probe.</p><p num="0038">Sample Measurement Procedure: With an occasional very gentle stirring
action using the probe itself inside the pouch, a steady-state DO reading is taken after
approx. 10-20 minutes.</p><p num="0039">Alternative Sample Measurement Procedure: The ink can be drained from
cartridge for measurement by insertion of a needle into the pouch through its septum or
pouch wall. The needle is attached to a short section of flexible tubing which in turn is
attached to a "T" housing available from Mettler-Toledo (Model no. 724DO2). The "T"
housing holds the DO probe in such a way as to allow the ink to flow past the tip without
contacting the ambient atmosphere. After approx. 30-50 ml of ink has flowed through the
"T" housing an accurate and reproducible O2 measurement can be taken.</p><p num="0040">Static surface tension of the ink can be measured by any suitable
means known in the art. For the ink compositions of the invention and the
comparative examples, a temperature controlled surface tension apparatus
employing the Wilhemy plate method was used. Such an apparatus is the K 10 ST
Digital Tensiometer manufactured by Kruss GmBH. All inks were measured at 25
°C. Ink surface tension is calculated from the equation shown below.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">σ = <st32:frac align="centre">P<st32:sub pos="post">w</st32:sub><st32:over>1<st32:sub pos="post">b</st32:sub> cos </st32:over></st32:frac></st32:df>
In the equation, σ is the static surface tension, <i>P</i><sub>w</sub> is the measured force, <i>l</i><sub>b</sub> is the
wetting length (40 mm for the Kruss tensionmeter) and  is the contact angle
between the plate and the ink. The viscometer automatically determines the static
surface tension of the sample ink when operated according to the manufacturer's
procedure. </p><heading><u style="single">Results</u></heading><p num="0041">Ink compositions having various dissolved gas levels, surface
tensions, and viscosities were tested by firing the ink compositions through a
BROTHER piezoelectric type drop on demand ink jet printhead. A successful test
result occurred when 67 pL ink droplets of the ink composition were continuously
fired through the printhead at a rate of 7,500 drops/second for at least 5 minutes
without nozzle failure or ink droplet misdirection. The results are described in the
table below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Ink comp.</entry><entry align="center">Package Types</entry><entry align="center">Dissolved Oxygen ppm</entry><entry align="center">Viscosity @ 25°C cp</entry><entry align="center">Surface tension dynes/cm</entry><entry align="center">Test Results</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. 1</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">&lt; 3</entry><entry align="center">2.9</entry><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="left">OK</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. 2</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">&lt; 3</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry><entry align="center">39</entry><entry align="left">OK</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. 3</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">&lt; 3</entry><entry align="center">2.9</entry><entry align="center">39</entry><entry align="left">OK</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex.4</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">&lt; 3</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry><entry align="center">39</entry><entry align="left">OK</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. 5</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">&lt; 3</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry><entry align="center">39</entry><entry align="left">OK</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. 6</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">&lt; 3</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry><entry align="center">39</entry><entry align="left">OK</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. 7</entry><entry align="center">N/A</entry><entry align="center">&lt; 3</entry><entry align="center">2.3</entry><entry align="center">36</entry><entry align="left">OK</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. 8</entry><entry align="center">N/A</entry><entry align="center">&lt; 3</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="left">OK</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. 9</entry><entry align="center">N/A</entry><entry align="center">&lt; 3</entry><entry align="center">4.4</entry><entry align="center">36</entry><entry align="left">OK</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. 10</entry><entry align="center">N/A</entry><entry align="center">&lt; 3</entry><entry align="center">4.2</entry><entry align="center">43</entry><entry align="left">OK</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Com Ex. 1</entry><entry align="center">BAg</entry><entry align="center">&gt;3</entry><entry align="center">2.9</entry><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="left">Failed</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Com Ex. 2</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">&gt;3</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry><entry align="center">39</entry><entry align="left">Failed</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Com Ex. 3</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">&gt;3</entry><entry align="center">2.9</entry><entry align="center">39</entry><entry align="left">Failed</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Com Ex. 4</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">&gt;3</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry><entry align="center">39</entry><entry align="left">Failed</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Com Ex. 5</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">&gt;3</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry><entry align="center">39</entry><entry align="left">Failed</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Com Ex. 6</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">&gt;3</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry><entry align="center">39</entry><entry align="left">Failed</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Com Ex. 7</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">0.4-0.6</entry><entry align="center">3.3</entry><entry align="center">33</entry><entry align="left">Failed</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Com Ex. 8</entry><entry align="center">Bag</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">3.1</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="left">Failed</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Com Ex. 9</entry><entry align="center">N/A</entry><entry align="center">&lt; 3</entry><entry align="center">2.4</entry><entry align="center">34</entry><entry align="left">Failed</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0042">The ink compositions have physical properties compatible with a
wide range of ink ejecting conditions, i.e., driving voltages and pulse widths for
thermal ink jet printing devices, driving frequencies of the piezo element for
either a drop-on-demand device or a continuous device, and the shape and size of
the nozzle. </p><p num="0043">The viscosity of the ink compositions of the present invention is
controlled to fall in a range from 2.0 to 10 cps and preferably from 2.5 to 3.5 cps.
When the viscosity is lower than 2.0 cps, poor droplet ejection occurs resulting in
multiple randomly sized dots in irregular locations on the printed media. When
the viscosity is higher than 10 cps, the printhead's ability to eject a droplet is
reduced increasing the possibility of permanent nozzle clogging.</p><p num="0044">The surface tension of the ink compositions of the present
invention is greater than 34, preferably from 34 mN/m to 45 mN/m, and more
preferably from 36 to 40 mN/m. When the surface tension is lower than the above
described range, the printhead failed to fire continuously for at least 5 minutes.
Although a preferred embodiment has a surface tension range of from 36 to less
than 40 mN/m, the surface tension can be higher than 40 mN/m. However, when
the surface tension exceeds 40 mN/m, the droplet's ability to penetrate the
receiver can be reduced and the overall drying time of the image can be increased.</p><p num="0045">The amount of dissolved gas of the ink jet ink of the present
invention is controlled to be no greater than 3.0ppm as measured on the basis of
the amount of dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C and preferably no greater than
1.0ppm. When the amount of dissolved gas is higher than the above described
range, the printhead failed to fire continuously for at least 5 minutes.</p><p num="0046">Referring to FIGS. 1A-C, an embodiment of a printer 10 that is
adapted to accept a plurality of the ink cartridges, each cartridge having an ink
composition described above as a main ink supply. The printer includes a
carriage 11 that supports an ink jet print head for movement during printing. The
ink jet print head is mounted on a print head module 25 (FIG. 1B) which in turn
is mounted to the carriage 11. The carriage 11, is coupled through a timing belt
13 with a drive motor (not shown), is reproducibly movable along the width of a
recording medium 12 (in the directions of arrows A and B in the Fig. 1A), while
being guided by a guide member 15. The ink jet print head 31 receives ink from
the ink tank or cartridge 16 through an ink supply tube 17. An intermediate supply
of ink may be provided between the ink cartridge and printhead, and thus the ink 
cartridge may be considered a bulk supply of the ink of a particular color for the
printer. A sheet transport roller 18, when driven by a drive motor (not shown),
transports the recording medium 12 in the direction (of arrow C in the FIG. 1A)
perpendicular to the moving direction of the carriage 11.</p><p num="0047">A Raster Image Processor controls image manipulation and the
resultant image file is delivered to the printer via a remotely located computer
through a communications port. On board memory stores the image file while the
printer is in operation.</p><p num="0048">FIGS. 1B and 1C show an embodiment of a piezoelectric print
head module or assembly 25. However, the ink cartridge may be used with other
drop-on-demand print heads such as thermal inkjet print heads and continuous
inkjet print heads. Reference numeral 36 designates a nozzle plate having nozzle
openings 37 formed therein. Numeral 38 indicates an ink supply port through
which ink flows from the ink cartridges 16 via the ink supply tube 17. The firing
rate of the print head 31 can be switched between 7.5 kHz and 15 kHz depending
on the selection of image resolution and print quality. The carriage velocity is
fixed in all print modes.</p><p num="0049">With reference to FIGS. 2-6 there is shown a printer main ink
supply 19 that includes a plurality of different color ink containing ink cartridges
16 and ink cartridge receiver assembly 20 that includes individual cartridge
receiving receptacles for receiving each cartridge. Six ink cartridges 16 are
positioned in the assembly housing of the ink cartridge receiver assembly such
that they are each separated by a divider wall or spacer wall 23 that forms a part
of the receiver assembly. The ink cartridge 16 is comprised of a housing 50 with
a non-symmetrical curvaceous profile 51, integrated hand hold features or handle
53, cartridge alignment features 52, ink cartridge color identifier or color or ink
type discrimination structure 60, and a memory chip assembly 55. An ink bag 70
is also supported within the cartridge and contains ink of a particular color.
Typically, the ink color used may be cyan, magenta, yellow and black. Different
shades of one or more of these colors may also be provided. Thus, for example, 
there may be provided cartridges with different shades of cyan. A spot color may
also be provided, thus providing an option for use of a very particular color.</p><p num="0050">The cartridge housing includes an ink receiving cavity, and the
housing is defined by a front side wall 90, a back side wall 91 opposite the front
side wall, a left side wall 94 and a right side wall 93, the left side wall and the
right side wall each respectively establishing a spacing between the front side wall
and the back side wall. A bottom wall 95 is also provided from which ink is
removed from the ink cartridge. The front side wall and the back side wall are
curved so that an outer surface of one has a generally convex curvature and the
outer surface of the other has a concave curvature. A plurality of alignment
recesses or features 52 are formed on the surfaces of the cartridge housing. A first
alignment recess 52 is formed on the outer surface of the front side wall and a pair
of alignment recesses 52 are formed on the outer surface of the back side wall.
The three alignment recesses are formed adjacent to the bottom wall and the first
alignment recess is located substantially midway between the pair of alignment
recesses in the width -wise direction of the ink receiving cavity. It will be noted
from the figures that the recesses 52 are each relatively elongated in the direction
of the height of the cartridge and this is advantageous since the cartridge is
inserted with the bottom of the cartridge moving towards the bottom of the ink
cartridge receiving receptacle. Therefore, the elongation of the recesses are in the
direction of insertion of the cartridges into a respective receptacle. The walls of
the ink cartridge are relatively rigid to provide a rigid cartridge structure.</p><p num="0051">A plurality of identical spacer walls spaced equally from each other
in the assembly housing also have cartridge alignment structures 24 thereon ( see
also FIGS. 6 and 7). Each spacer wall 23 has a curvature to receive a cartridge
having a generally complementary curvature to the curvature of the spacer wall.
Adjacent spacer walls 23 define a cartridge receiving receptacle and have facing
surfaces wherein the location of alignment structures 24 are not identical since the
alignment recesses on the front and back surfaces of the cartridge are not
identical. </p><p num="0052">The curvaceous profile 51 of the cartridge 16 is comprised of
various radii and appears in a wave shape. This shape can be other non-rectangular
shapes such that when nested with other cartridges the orientation of
insertion is uni-directional. The provision of a curved shape to the ink cartridge
provides a visual aid in describing the proper orientation of the ink cartridge
before insertion. The general shape of the cartridge and that of the cartridge
receiving receptacle forming a part of the cartridge receiver assembly prevents the
cartridge from being inserted incorrectly. This permits electrical contacts forming
a part of the memory chip assembly to be aligned with electrical contact members
21 (Fig. 4) in the receptacles of the cartridge receiver assembly 20. The
curvaceous profile 51 also stabilizes the ink cartridge when in storage by
providing nesting action as cartridges are stacked one on top of the other.</p><p num="0053">The ink cartridge housing (FIG. 5, 6) includes integral alignment
features 52 that are molded into the plastic cartridge that mate or cooperate with
location structures or features formed in the receptacles of the ink cartridge
receiver assembly 19 (FIG. 3). The opening of each receptacle is significantly
larger than the ink cartridge allowing for easy insertion. The ink cartridge's
alignment features 52 engage with mating location features 24 on the divider or
spacer walls 23 (FIG. 7) as the ink cartridge 16 is being inserted into the proper
receptacle of the ink cartridge receiver assembly 19. Engagement of these
features occurs before the receptacle's ink color identifier key and needle
approach the cartridge fitment 71 and septum 72 (FIG. 10). These features align
the ink cartridge 16 such that the hollow needle 74 aligns with and pierces the
septum 72. The cartridge alignment features 52 also align the ink cartridge such
that the electrical contact members 21 (FIG. 4) of each cartridge receiving
receptacle are positioned to engage the counterpart electrical contacts 58 of
memory chip assembly 55 (FIGS. 13A and 13B) on the ink cartridge 16. It is
important to note that the divider walls 23, the ink cartridge housing 50 (FIG. 5)
and color identifier (color or ink type discrimination structure) 60 are the same
parts used repeatedly in the ink cartridge assembly 20. The difference from one 
color cartridge to the next is the orientation difference of the color identifier 60 in
concert with the orientation difference of the color identifier key tab 67 (see FIGs.
9A and 9B) from one cartridge receiving receptacle to another cartridge receiving
receptacle. This design therefore minimizes the manufacturing cost of the ink
cartridge assembly 20 by using a minimum number of unique components.</p><p num="0054">With reference to FIGS. 10, 19A and 19B, and 13 illustrate details
regarding the construction of the ink bag 70 that is located within the cartridge.
The fitment 71 is thermally sealed to the bag material. The flexible ink bag
material is composed of three layers with adhesive between each layer. Each
layer has a specific purpose by providing either compatibility with the ink, low
water vapor and gas permeability, or abrasion resistance. The inside layer, in
contact with the ink, is either a linear low density or low density polyethylene.
The fitment is made from either a low-density or a high-density polyethylene
thereby promoting good adhesion of it to the bag during the thermal welding
process. The middle layer is aluminum foil providing low water vapor and gas
permeability, and the outer layer is either nylon or polyethylene terepthalate
having high strength and abrasion resistance. The septum 72 is inserted into the
circular opening of the fitment 71. The inside diameter of the circular opening of
the fitment is smaller than the outside diameter of the septum creating a slight
compression of the septum once inserted into the fitment. Once assembled, the
bag, fitment and septum must allow for an efficient filling and evacuation process.
A feature to the function of the ink bag is the taper angle 73 illustrated in FIG. 10.</p><p num="0055">It is important to minimize the amount of trapped air remaining in
the bag once filled with ink. If air remains in the bag it will dissolve into the ink
between the time of manufacture and usage. Dissolved gases in the ink will come
out of solution during the firing process of the piezoelectric print head and form
air bubbles. Air bubbles, being compressible, will prevent the nozzles from
expelling a drop of ink onto the print media 12. The taper angle 73 helps expedite
the evacuation of air in the bag during the filling process and allow for a majority
of the ink to drain from the bag during usage. </p><p num="0056">During the filling process the bag is evacuated of air before ink is
injected into it. When the ink bag is full the remaining air, now near the fitment
and septum, is evacuated. If the taper angle is not present the air tends to become
trapped in the corners of the bag and can not be evacuated. The angle allows the
remaining air to move to the fitment and thereby allows for its removal. The
taper angle 73, which is formed from the area of the bag near the fitment and
tapers to a vertical side edge of the bag should be between 5 and 45 degrees. In
the preferred embodiment a taper angle of 15 degrees is provided.</p><p num="0057">Another contributor to the performance of the ink bag is the
relationship between the cartridge housing size and shape and the size and shape
of the bag 70. When the ink bag is full of ink (see FIG. 11), and contained within
the ink cartridge housing 50, the ink bag is constrained by four interior sides of
the ink cartridge housing 50. Therefore the capacity of the ink bag within the ink
cartridge housing is driven by the optimization of the size of the ink cartridge
housing 50. Key to this optimization is the aspect ratio of the ink cartridge
housing size, which in turn drives the size of the ink bag 70.</p><p num="0058">The method utilized in the assembly of the ink cartridge is
benefited by the design. The advantage of sizing the ink bag and cartridge
housing according to the relationships stated above allows for the assembly of the
ink bag to the cartridge housing before the ink filling process is initiated. The
process of assembly includes evacuating the ink bag of air, laying the first half of
the cartridge housing on its side, placing color identification components around
the fitment of the ink bag, and inserting the ink bag into the first housing using
two sided tape. The insertion of the bag is made such that the empty ink bag is
conformed to the profile of the first housing half, taped in place using double-sided
tape, and then covered with the second housing half. The first and second
housings halves are then ultrasonically welded together. The ultrasonic welding
process providing a low cost assembly method although other known methods
may be used.</p><p num="0059">Once the housing assembly is welded, the ink bag is filled with a 
known amount of ink (for example, 1100mL) while lying on its side and by
placing a needle through the septum and pumping ink through the needle and into
the ink bag. The cartridge assembly is then turned vertically such that the fitment
and septum are facing up. The cartridge may be bumped to cause air in the ink to
rise to the top of the bag. The remaining air and approximately 50mL of ink are
then removed from the bag by applying a vacuum through the needle. At this
point the ink bag is fully constrained by the housing and the surface of bag is in
intimate contact with the four inside surfaces of the housing assembly as
illustrated in the horizontal sectional view shown in FIG. 11. This prevents the
bag from shifting during transport. If shifting were to occur then the bag surface
could potentially abrade and rupture resulting in ink leakage. If the ink bag was
filled prior to the ultrasonic welding process it may also become abraded from the
welding process and subsequently rupture. The method of assembly and the
configuration of the housing in concert with the ink bag together result in a low
cost ink cartridge assembly. As may be noted from FIG. 11 at the section shown
there is a uniform internal cartridge cavity thickness spacing between
corresponding points on the respective internal surfaces of the front and back side
walls even though the front and back sides are curved as are their internal
surfaces. The front and backsides are curved complementary; for example one is
generally concave in curvature and the other is generally convex in curvature, but
internally they maintain a generally uniform spacing between corresponding
points on the internal surfaces at least along a certain section through the
cartridge.</p><p num="0060">The ink compositions are degassed prior to filling. During the
degassing process, ink is pumped to a degassing unit and cycled until the ink
reaches a desired gas level. Once reaching the desired gas level, the ink is ready
for the filling process. The degassing unit may incorporate known mechanisms for
removing dissolved gases from an ink. These include, but are not limited to,
physical processes such as boiling and evacuation, and chemical processes such as
incorporating gas absorbents in the inks. Furthermore, additional heating, 
vibration, and evacuation methods can also be incorporated. These include, for
example, the use of microwave energy as described in U. S. Patent 5,341,162 and
U. S. Patent 6,089,702; the use of ultrasonic wave generator as described in U. S.
Patent 3, 904, 392 and U.S. patent 5, 373,212; and the use of a gas-permeable
hollow fiber membrane as described in EP 1052011A1 and JP 05-317605 A2; a
commercially available Liquid-Cel membrane cartridge manufactured by Celgard
KK. Alternatively, other degassing processes can be used.</p><p num="0061">Although it is preferable to incorporate a collapsible bag in the ink
cartridge, non-collapsible bags, or rigid ink containers can also be used provided
the level of dissolved gas in the ink composition remains substantial constant.
Additionally, printers using cartridges having ink bags that are sealed and not
vented to the atmosphere but instead collapse as the ink is used have advantages
over printers using other types of ink cartridges, for example, cartridges that vent
to the atmosphere or incorporate additional components (e.g. an ink absorbing
sponge) into the ink cartridge. Using an ink cartridge having a collapsible bag
allows the low level of dissolved gas in the ink composition to be maintained
during printing. This can be contrasted with an ink cartridge that vents to the
atmosphere which allows the level of dissolved gas in the ink composition to
increase over time once the ink cartridge is connected to the printer. This, in turn,
can lead to degraded ink performance during printing. Additionally, if additional
components are incorporated into the ink cartridge, small pieces or particles of the
incorporated component can break away causing contamination of the ink. This
may eventually cause nozzles to become clogged, degrading the quality of the
image produced.</p><p num="0062">The invention has been described in detail with particular reference
to certain preferred embodiments thereof, but it will be understood that variations
and modifications can be effected within the scope of the invention.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An ink cartridge comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a housing having a front side wall (90), a back side wall (91)
opposite the front side wall, a pair of opposed left (94) and right (93) side walls
separating the front and the back side walls, and a bottom wall, the walls defining
an internal cavity within the housing;</claim-text><claim-text>an ink container (70) located within the internal cavity and filled
with a liquid ink, the liquid ink having a dissolved gas content of less than 3 ppm
as measured on the basis of the amount of dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C and a
static surface tension at 25°C of greater than 34 dynes/cm.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The ink cartridge according to Claim 1, wherein the ink
container is a collapsible bag.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The ink cartridge according to Claim 1, wherein the
dissolved gas content is less than 1.0 ppm as measured on the basis of the amount
of dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The ink cartridge according to Claim 1, wherein the surface
tension is between 36 to less than 40 dynes/cm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The ink cartridge according to Claim 1, wherein the liquid
ink has a viscosity at 25°C greater than 2.5 cp.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The ink cartridge according to Claim 5, wherein the
viscosity at 25°C is between 2.5 and 3.5 cp.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method of filling an ink cartridge comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing a housing having a front side wall, a back side wall
opposite the front side wall, a pair of opposed left and right side walls separating
the front and the back side walls, and a bottom wall, the walls defining an internal
cavity within the housing;</claim-text><claim-text>providing an ink container;</claim-text><claim-text>positioning the ink container within the internal cavity; and</claim-text><claim-text>filling the ink container with a liquid ink having a dissolved gas
content of less than 3 ppm as measured on the basis of the amount of dissolved
oxygen gas at 20°C and a static surface tension at 25°C of greater than 34
dynes/cm.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method according to Claim 7, wherein the container is
a collapsible bag.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method according to Claim 7, wherein the dissolved
gas content is less than 1.0 ppm as measured on the basis of the amount of
dissolved oxygen gas at 20°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method according to Claim 7, wherein the surface
tension is between 36 to less than 40 dynes/cm.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>