<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1258507-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1258507" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26615154" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021120"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1258507-A1" status="new" fvid="23614795"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1258507</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20021120</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02291190-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02291190</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020513</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2001145803-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2001145803</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010516</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2001326197-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2001326197</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011024</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/01        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/5419      20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/04        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   3/22</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/01</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/5419</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L83:04</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Halogenfreie flammhemmende Harzzusammensetzung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Flame-retardant resin composition free from halogen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition de résine ignifuge exempte d'halogenes</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1059330-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1059330</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1164164-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1164164</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1188794-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1188794</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-2000248126-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000248126</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4288360-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4288360</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4695597-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4695597</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5296534-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5296534</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 2000, no. 12, 3 January 2001 (2001-01-03) -&amp; JP 2000 248126 A (FUJIKURA LTD), 12 September 2000 (2000-09-12)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SHINETSU CHEMICAL CO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SHIN-ETSU CHEMICAL CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SHIN-ETSU CHEMICAL CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>6-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>IHARA TOSHIAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TANAKA MASAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>IHARA, TOSHIAKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TANAKA, MASAKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Ihara, Toshiaki c/o Shin-Etsu Chemical Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>1-10, Oaza Hitomi, Matsuida-machi</street><city>Usui-gun, Gunma-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Tanaka, Masaki c/o Shin-Etsu Chemical Co., Ltd.</last-name> <address><street>6-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome, Chiyoda-ku</street><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook> </inventor> </inventors> <agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Peaucelle, Chantal</last-name><address><street>Cabinet Armengaud Aine 3, avenue Bugeaud</street><city>75116 Paris</city><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The invention discloses a flame-retardant thermoplastic resin
composition without containing any halogen compounds as a flame-retardant
agent but still exhibiting excellent flame retardancy. The
resin composition comprises: (a) a thermoplastic resin kneadable or
moldable at a temperature lower than 250 °C such as polyethylene; (b)
magnesium hydroxide as the principal flame retardant agent; (c) an
organopolysiloxane compound of a specified viscosity; and (d) a reactive
catalytic compound which is a radical-generating compound having
an incipient thermal decomposition temperature higher than 250 °C
such as 2,3-dimethyl-2,3-diphenylbutane. Alternatively, the catalytic
compound as the component (d) can be a combination of a noble
metal, e.g., platinum, compound and a vinyl group-containing organosiloxane
compound.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a novel flame-retardant
resin composition free from halogen or, more particularly, relates to a
novel flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition without containing
any halogen compounds but still having excellent mechanical
properties and safety against pollution of environments as well as sufficiently
high flame retardancy even by compounding a decreased
amount of non-halogen flame-retardant agent such as metal hydroxides.</p><p num="0002">As is well known, one of the most serious problems in thermoplastic
resins is the inflammability of the articles shaped or molded
therefrom, which sometimes prohibit use of the resin in certain applications
requiring high flame retardancy of the resin articles. While
various technological proposals and attempts have been made heretofore
to impart flame retardancy to thermoplastic resins, a most conventional
way in this regard is to prepare a flame-retardant thermoplastic
resin composition by compounding the resin with flame-retardant
agents including a halogen-based compound, e.g., bromine
compounds, and antimony oxide in combination. While halogen-based
flame-retardant agents can impart excellent flame-retardancy to the
resin composition by way of their radical-trapping activity and evolution
of nonflammable gases, such halogen-containing gases are generally
very toxic against human body and the damage in a fire hazard is
sometimes multiplied by a large volume of such toxic gases evolved 
from thermoplastic resin articles containing a halogen-based flame-retardant
agent. Accordingly, it is eagerly desired to develop a flame-retardant
thermoplastic resin composition without formulation of a
halogen-based flame-retardant agent.</p><p num="0003">A proposal recently made in this regard for polyolefin-based
resin compositions, which are widely employed as an insulating material
or sheath of electric wires and cables, is for the use of a metal hydroxide
such as magnesium hydroxide as a non-halogen flame-retardant
agent. Metal hydroxides are mostly advantageous as a
flame-retardant agent in respect of their low toxicity and small volumes
of smoke evolution by combustion along with little corrosiveness. The
flame-retardant effect on the matrix resin thereby is exhibited by
means of the water of crystallization released from the resin articles
under combustion. The effect of flame retardancy exhibited by this
mechanism, however, cannot be high enough and the oxygen consumption
index, referred to as the OI hereinafter, can rarely exceed 25
even in a resin composition containing 100 parts by weight of a metal
hydroxide powder per 100 parts by weight of the polyolefin resin.</p><p num="0004">An alternative proposal is made in Japanese Patents Nos.
2825500, 3019225 and 3072746, according to which the flame retardancy
of a polyolefin resin composition can be improved without adversely
affecting the mechanical properties of the resin articles by the
use of a metal hydroxide powder after a surface treatment with a special
surface treatment agent as the flame-retardant agent. Japanese
Patent Publication 7-119324, Japanese Patent Nos. 3051211 and
3063759 and Japanese Patent Kokai 8-295784 further disclose a
flame-retardant resin composition which is prepared by compounding 
a polyolefin resin with a specific metal hydroxide and a specific organopolysiloxane
compound in combination. Each of these methods is in
fact effective to improve the flame retardancy of the resin composition
prepared according to the proposed formulation so that the amount of
the metal hydroxide can be substantially decreased without affecting
the mechanical properties of the resin articles prepared from the resin
composition. The effectiveness of these methods, however, is still not
high enough so that debut of a flame-retardant thermoplastic resin
composition having excellent flame retardancy without a decrease in
the mechanical properties is eagerly desired.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0005">The present invention accordingly has an object to provide a
novel and improved flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition
capable of exhibiting excellent flame retardancy without a decrease in
the mechanical properties of the resin articles shaped from the resin
composition, which is obtained without compounding any halogen-containing
compounds as a flame-retardant agent.</p><p num="0006">Thus, the flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition
provided by the present invention is a uniform blend which comprises:
<sl><li>(a) 100 parts by weight of a thermoplastic resin kneadable or moldable,
i.e. plastically deformable, at a temperature lower than 250 °C;</li><li>(b) from 50 to 300 parts by weight of a metal hydroxide powder;</li><li>(c) from 0.1 to 30 parts by weight of an organopolysiloxane compound
free from aliphatic unsaturation; and</li><li>(d) a catalytically effective amount of a reactive catalyst compound,
of which, in particular, the metal hydroxide as the component (b) is, 
preferably, magnesium hydroxide, the organopolysiloxane compound
as the component (c), preferably, has gum-like consistency with a viscosity
of at least 40 mm<sup>2</sup>/s at 25 °C and the reactive catalyst compound
as the component (d) is, preferably, (d1) a radical-generating
compound having an incipient thermal decomposition temperature of
250 °C or higher such as 2,3-dimethyl-2,3-diphenyl butane or (d2) a
combination of a noble metal compound and a vinyl group-containing
organosiloxane compound having flowability with a relatively low viscosity.</li></sl></p><p num="0007">In particular, the reactive catalytic compound as the component
(d1) is a complex compound of a noble metal compound, which is
preferably a platinum compound, with a vinyl siloxane compound. The
catalytically effective amount of the component (d1) is from 0.01 to 10
parts by weight, when it is a radical-generating compound, and, when
it is a noble metal complex compound, from 0.000001 to 0.1 part by
weigh, calculated as the noble metal element, per 100 parts by weight
of the component (a).</p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading><p num="0008">As is described above, the essential ingredients comprised
in the inventive flame-retardant resin composition are the components
(a), (b), (c) and (d), of which the component (a) is a thermoplastic
resin having specified physical properties to serve as the base ingredient
of the composition. Examples of the thermoplastic resins as the
component (a), from which the flame-retardant resin composition of
the present invention can be prepared, include a variety of olefin-based 
polymeric resins and thermoplastic synthetic elastomers. The
olefin-based polymeric resin is exemplified by low-density polyethylenes,
high-density polyethylenes, straight-chain low-density polyethylenes,
ultralow-density polyethylenes, ultrahigh molecular-weight polyethylenes,
polypropylenes, polystyrenes, saponification products of
ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymers, i.e. ethylene/vinyl alcohol copolymers,
ethylene/ethyl (meth)acrylate copolymers, ethylene/methyl
(meth)acrylate copolymers, ethylene/acrylamide copolymers, ethylene/(meth)acrylic
acid copolymers, ethylene/glycidyl (meth)acrylate
copolymers and ethylene/maleic anhydride copolymers as well as ionomers
and the thermoplastic synthetic elastomer is exemplified by
ethylene/propylene copolymeric rubbers, butyl rubbers, SBRs, NBRs,
acrylic rubbers and silicone rubbers, though not particularly limitative
thereto. These thermoplastic resins and elastomers can be used as
the component (a) either singly or as a combination of two kinds or
more according to need.</p><p num="0009">It is essential that the above described thermoplastic resins
are kneadable or moldable at a temperature lower than 250 °C in consideration
of the conventional molding process of these resins undertaken
at a temperature of 250 °C or below. This is because, since the
radical-generating compound as the component (d1) has an incipient
thermal decomposition temperature of 250 °C or higher, this component
can easily and uniformly be dispersed in the resin composition
without causing thermal decomposition when the compounding work is
conducted at 250 °C or below where the thermoplastic resin is in a
softened state. The component (d) dispersed uniformly in the resin 
composition together with the organopolysiloxane compound as the
component (c) synergistically exhibits a strong effect of flame retardancy
only when the resin article is under combustion although the
exact mechanism of this synergistic effect is not well understood at
present. A presumable mechanism in this regard is that, when the
resin article containing the components (c) and (d) in combination is
brought into fire, the organopolysiloxane first migrates toward the surface
layer of the article to form a surface layer rich in the content of
the organopolysiloxane to prevent exudation of the molten resin onto
the surface while the radical-generating compound contained in the
body of the article serves to promote crosslinking of the resin which is
a condition beneficial for the effect of flame retardancy.</p><p num="0010">It is a quite novel and unexpected discovery not reported in
any prior art documents that a resin article shaped from a thermoplastic
resin composition compounded with a metal hydroxide, an organopolysiloxane
compound and a radical-generating compound as the
components (a), (b), (c) and (d), respectively, may exhibit a strong
flame-retardant effect. When the radical-generating compound has a
thermal decomposition temperature lower than 250 °C as is the case
in most organic peroxide compounds, the radical-generating compound
exhibits an activity to promote crosslinking of the resin already
during the compounding work of the resin composition to decrease
mobility of the organopolysiloxane within the body of the article without
contribution to the effect of flame-retardancy if not to mention the disadvantage
due to premature hardening of the resin composition during
the compounding works as well as the adverse influences caused by
the residual amount of the organic peroxide or decomposition debris 
thereof.</p><p num="0011">The component (b) compounded in the inventive flame-retardant
resin composition is a powder of a metal hydroxide to serve
as a flame-retardant agent, which is preferably magnesium hydroxide
although a variety of metal hydroxides including aluminum hydroxide
can meet the purpose. As compared with magnesium hydroxide, aluminum
hydroxide has a disadvantage because, since aluminum hydroxide
releases vapor of the adsorbed water at about 250 °C in a
peak vigorousness, the resin composition compounded at around this
temperature sometimes contains voids due to the water vapor. The
compounding amount of the metal hydroxide as the component (b) is
in the range from 50 to 300 parts by weight or, preferably, from 50 to
150 parts by weight per 100 parts by weight of the thermoplastic resin
as the component (a) although an amount thereof up to 300 parts by
weight has no particular disadvantages. This is in great contrast to the
formulation of conventional flame-retardant resin compositions compounded
with a metal hydroxide in which the amount of the metal hydroxide
must always be at least 50 parts by weight per 100 parts by
weight of the thermoplastic resin.</p><p num="0012">The metal hydroxide powder as the component (b) is not
particularly limitative relative to the granulometric properties of the
particles provided that the metal hydroxide powder has good dispersibility
in the matrix of the thermoplastic resin as the component (a).
In this regard, it is sometimes advantageous that the powder of the
metal hydroxide prior to compounding is subjected to a surface treatment
with a compound selected from the group consisting of saturated
or unsaturated fatty acids, silane coupling agents and organopolysiloxane 
compounds having a reactive functional group in the molecule.
Surface treatment of a magnesium hydroxide powder with a fatty acid
is particularly preferable in respect of good improvement on the flame
retardancy presumably due to increased mobility of the organopolysiloxane
compound as the component (c) when the resin article is under
combustion.</p><p num="0013">The component (c) compounded in the inventive flame-retardant
resin composition is an organopolysiloxane compound which
preferably has a viscosity of 1000000 mm<sup>2</sup>/s or higher or, more preferably,
gum-like consistency at 25 °C. It is also preferable that the organopolysiloxane
compound as the component (c) is a dimethylpolysiloxane
having a straightly linear molecular structure. It is more preferable
that the organopolysiloxane compound as the component (c)
has an average absolute molecular weight of at least 3000 calculated
by making reference to known polystyrene resins. When the average
molecular weight of the component (c) is too low, a decrease is
caused in the mechanical properties of the articles shaped from the
resin composition.</p><p num="0014">The amount of the organopolysiloxane compound as the
component (c) compounded with the thermoplastic resin as the component
(a) is in the range from 0.1 to 30 parts by weight or, preferably,
from 0.1 to 10 parts by weight per 100 parts by weight of the component
(a). It is preferable that the organopolysiloxane as the component
(c) compounded in the above mentioned amount is free from aliphatic
unsaturation without containing any unsaturated groups such as vinyl
groups bonded to the silicon atoms as in the case of a dimethylpolysiloxane.
This is in contrast to the unsaturation-functional or vinyl 
group-containing organopolysiloxane as a part of the component (d2)
in combination with a noble metal compound to promote the activity of
the noble metal compound. The high-polymeric dimethylpolysiloxane
as the component (c) has a viscosity of, preferably, at least 1000000
mm<sup>2</sup>/s at 25 °C while the unsaturation-functional organopolysiloxane
as a part of the component (d2) has a viscosity in the range from 40 to
1000000 mm<sup>2</sup>/s at 25°C.</p><p num="0015">The component (d) compounded with the above described
components (a) to (c) is a reactive catalytic compound which is typically,
on one hand, (d1) a radical-generating compound having an incipient
thermal decomposition temperature of 250 °C or higher.
Though not particularly limitative, the component (d1) of this class is
preferably 2,3-dimethyl-2,3-diphenyl butane. Advantageously, this
compound is not a dangerous material under regulation of Japanese
Fire Service Act and has no toxicity against human body so that no
problems are caused not only in the compounding works of the inventive
composition but also relative to the residual content of the compound
in the shaped articles of the inventive resin composition.</p><p num="0016">The compounding amount of the radical-generating compound
as a class of the component (d1) in the inventive resin composition
can be a catalytically effective amount or, preferably, is an
amount in the range from 0.01 to 10 parts by weight per 100 parts by
weight of the thermoplastic resin as the component (a). When the
amount of the component (d1) is too small, the desired effect of flame
retardancy on the resin composition may eventually be not obtained
while, when the amount thereof is too large, a disadvantageous phenomenon 
of blooming is sometimes caused with appearance of a
white powder on the surface of the articles shaped from the flame-retardant
resin composition.</p><p num="0017">Though optional, the above described radical-generating
compound as the component (d1) can be compounded in the resin
composition as a combination with a crosslinking aid compound such
as triallyl isocyanurate, N,N'-<i>m</i>-phenylene bismaleimide, 1,1,1-trimethylolpropane
triacrylate, diethyleneglycol dimethacrylate and divinyl
benzene. The compounding amount of this crosslinking aid is
preferably in the range from 0.01 to 20 parts by weight per 100 parts
by weight of the thermoplastic resin as the component (a). When the
amount thereof is too small, the effects of desired improvement on the
flame retardancy and mechanical properties of the shaped articles of
the resin composition cannot be high enough while increase of the
amount to exceed the above mentioned upper limit has no particular
additional advantages.</p><p num="0018">In addition to the above described essential ingredients, i.e.
components (a) to (d), it is optional that the flame-retardant thermoplastic
resin composition of the invention is compounded with various
kinds of known additives including antioxidants, ultraviolet absorbers,
stabilizers, photostabilizers, lubricants, fillers and others each in a limited
amount.</p><p num="0019">Examples of the above mentioned antioxidants usable in the
inventive resin composition include 2,6-di-<i>tert</i>-butyl-4-methyl phenol,
n-octadecyl-3-(3',5'-di-<i>tert</i>-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl) propionate, tetrakis-[methylene-3-(3,5-di-<i>tert</i>-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)
propionato]methane,
tris(3,5-di-<i>tert</i>-butyl-4-hydroxybenzyl) isocyanurate, 4,4'-butylidene bis-(3-methyl-6-<i>tert</i>-butyl 
phenol), triethyleneglycol bis[3-(3-<i>tert</i>-butyl-4-hydroxy-5-methylphenyl)
propionate], 3,9-bis{2-[3-<i>tert</i>-butyl-4-hydroxy-5-methylphenyl]propionyloxy]-1,1-dimethylethyl}-2,4,8,10-tetraoxaspiro[5,5]undecane,
4,4-thiobis(2-<i>tert</i>-butyl-5-methylphenol), 2,2-methylenebis(6-<i>tert</i>-butyl
methylphenol), 4,4-methylenebis(2,6-di-<i>tert</i>-butylphenol),
1,3,5-trimethyl-2,4,6-tris(3,5-di-<i>tert</i>-butyl-4-hydroxybenzyl)-benzene,
tris(nonylphenyl) phosphite, tris(2,4-di-<i>tert</i>-butylphenyl)
phosphite, distearylpentaerithritol phosphite, bis(2,4-di-<i>tert</i>-butylphenyl)pentaerithritol
phosphite, bis(2,6-di-<i>tert</i>-butyl-4-methyl-phenyl)-pentaerithritol
phosphite, 2,2-methylenebis(4,6-di-<i>tert</i>-butylphenyl octyl
phosphite, tetrakis(2,4-di-<i>tert</i>-butylphenyl)-4,4'-biphenylene diphosphite,
dilauryl 3,3'-thio dipropionate, dimyristyl 3,3'-thio dipropionate,
pentaerithritol tetrakis(3-laurylthiopropionate), 2,5,7,8-tetramethyl-2-(4,8,12-trimethyldecyl)coumaron-2-ol,
5,7-di-<i>tert</i>-butyl-3-(3,4-dimethyl-phenyl)-3H-benzofuran-2-on,
2-[1-(2-hydroxy-3,5-di-<i>tert</i>-pentylphenyl)-ethyl]-4,6-dipentylphenyl
acrylate and 2-<i>tert</i>-butyl-6-(3-<i>tert</i>-butyl-2-hydroxy-5-methylbenzyl)-4-methylphenyl
acrylate.</p><p num="0020">Examples of the stabilizers mentioned above as an optional
additive include various kinds of metal soaps such as lithium stearate,
magnesium stearate, calcium laurate, calcium ricinolate, calcium stearate,
barium laurate, barium ricinolate, barium stearate, zinc laurate,
zinc ricinolate and zinc stearate, various kinds of laurate-, maleate- or
mercapto-based organic tin compounds, various kinds of lead compounds
such as lead stearate and tribasic lead sulfate, epoxy compounds
such as epoxidated vegetable oils, phosphite compounds
such as alkylaryl phosphites and trialkyl phosphites, β-diketone compounds
such as dibenzoylmethane and dehydroacetic acid and polyol 
compounds such as sorbitol, mannitol and pentaerithritol as well as
hydrotalcites and zeolites.</p><p num="0021">Examples of the ultraviolet absorbers as a further optional
additive include benzotriazole compounds, benzophenone compounds,
salicylate compounds, cyanoacrylate compounds, oxalic acid anilides
and hindered amine compounds.</p><p num="0022">While the component (c) in the inventive resin composition
is an organopolysiloxane which is preferably a high-polymeric dimethylpolysiloxane,
the inventive resin composition may contain, as is
mentioned before, an unsaturation-functional or vinyl group-containing
organopolysiloxane compound, which serves as a part of the component
(d2) of an alternative type jointly in combination with a noble
metal compound, in a limited amount.</p><p num="0023">The amount of the unsaturation-functional organopolysiloxane
as a part of the component (d2) is in the range from 0.001 to 9
parts by weight or, preferably, from 0.5 to 3 parts by weight per 100
parts by weight of the component (a). When the amount of this ingredient
is too small, a decrease is caused in the flame retardancy of the
resin article molded from the resin composition due to a low density of
crosslinks to be formed by the reaction of the unsaturated functional
groups when the resin article is brought under flame while, when the
amount thereof is too large, distribution uniformity of the ingredients
may be decreased since the vinyl group-containing organopolysiloxane
is usually an oily liquid. It is preferable that the weight proportion
of the vinyl group-containing organopolysiloxane as a part of the component
(d2) relative to the total amount of the component (c) and the
vinyl group-containing organopolysiloxane as the component (d2) is in 
the range from 1 to 30% by weight. When this proportion of the two
types of the organopolysiloxanes is too low, deficiency in the density
of the crosslinks is resulted when the resin article is brought under
flame while, when this proportion is too high, a decrease is resulted in
the distribution uniformity of the ingredients.</p><p num="0024">The unsaturation-functional organopolysiloxane as a part of
the component (d2) should have a viscosity not exceeding 1000000
mm<sup>2</sup>/s at 25 °C. When the viscosity is too high, the migration velocity
of the organopolysiloxane toward the surface layer of the shaped article
is disadvantageously decreased along with a problem of premature
crosslink formation in the course of the compounding works of the
composition or the molding works of the shaped articles resulting in a
decreased value of oxygen consumption index. The content of the
unsaturated functional groups in the unsaturation-functional organopolysiloxane
as a part of the component (d2) should be at lease 2% by
moles relative to the total molar content of functional groups. When
this molar proportion is too low, the value of oxygen consumption index
is decreased due to insufficient density of crosslinks not to give a
fully cured film of the resin composition. The types of the functional
groups bonded to the silicon atoms of the organopolysiloxane other
than the unsaturation-functional groups are not particularly limitative.</p><p num="0025">When the inventive resin composition contains, in addition
to the component (c), a vinyl group-containing organopolysiloxane as
a part of the component (d2), the other part of the component (d2)
compounded in combination therewith is a noble metal compound selected
from platinum, palladium and rhodium compounds or, preferably,
a platinum compound. The noble metal compound is compounded 
preferably in the form of a complex compound with the vinyl group-containing
organopolysiloxane in order to obtain a more improved effect
of flame retardancy of the articles shaped from the inventive resin
composition with an increase in the oxygen consumption index (OI) by
compounding the resin composition with a small amount of the noble
metal compound. The compounding amount of the noble metal compound
in the inventive resin composition is in the range from 0.000001
to 0.1 part by weight, calculated as the noble metal element <i>per se,</i>
per 100 parts by weight of the component (a). When the compounded
amount of the noble metal compound is too small, the desired improvement
of the flame retardancy can hardly be obtained while, when
the amount thereof is too large, a disadvantage due to coloring may
be caused in the resin composition in addition to the economical disadvantage
due to expensiveness of noble metal compounds in general.</p><p num="0026">The mechanism leading to the unexpectedly excellent flame
retardancy exhibited by the inventive thermoplastic resin composition
is not fully understood at present. A presumable mechanism therefor
would be as follows.</p><p num="0027">When the resin composition or a shaped article thereof is
brought under burning, migration of the organopolysiloxane ingredient
proceeds in the first place. It would be a reasonable assumption that
the unsaturation-functional organopolysiloxane compound as a part of
the component (d2) causes migration at the earliest stage since this
ingredient is an oily organopolysiloxane, of which the functional unsaturated
groups, e.g., vinyl groups, are subject to a crosslinking reaction
when the increasing temperature has reached 250 °C or higher. 
Accordingly, a coating film of the crosslinked organopolysiloxane is
formed on the surface of the burning article. This crosslinked coating
layer exhibits the effect of flame retardancy by itself and serves to hold
the flame retardant layer formed below from the silica derived from the
dimethylpolysiloxane and the magnesium hydroxide powder which exhibits
an effect of flame retardancy by disturbing flow-out of the molten
thermoplastic resin as the principal combustion source to the surface
layer.</p><p num="0028">In the compounding work for the preparation of the inventive
flame-retardant resin composition, the various ingredients including a
thermoplastic resin, a metal hydroxide powder, an organopolysiloxane
and a reactive catalytic compound together with other optional additives
can be directly blended together in a double-screw extruder machine,
single-screw extruder machine, Banbury mixer or pressurizable
kneader under heating. It is preferable, however, in respect of the
uniformity of dispersion of the compounded ingredients that a master
blend is prepared in advance by omitting the metal hydroxide or by
omitting the thermoplastic resin from the overall formulation and the
master blend is subsequently blended with the metal hydroxide or the
thermoplastic resin.</p><p num="0029">In the following, the flame-retardant thermoplastic resin
composition free from halogen according to the present invention is
illustrated in more detail by way of Examples and Comparative Examples,
which, however, never limit the scope of the invention in any way.
In the following description, the term of "parts" always refers to "parts
by weight". </p><heading>Example 1.</heading><p num="0030">A thermoplastic resin composition was prepared by uniformly
blending 100 parts of an ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymeric
resin having a Vicat softening temperature of 57 °C (Evaflex 460, a
product by Mitsui Du Pont Polychemical Co.), referred to as the EVA
hereinafter, 100 parts of a magnesium hydroxide powder surface-treated
with a fatty acid (Kisma 5B, a product by Kyowa Chemical Co.),
referred to as the Kisma hereinafter, 8 parts of a dimethylpolysiloxane
gum having a straightly linear molecular structure with an average
molecular weight of 500000 (a product by Shin-Etsu Chemical Co.),
referred to as the silicone gum hereinafter, and a combination of 2
parts of a methylvinyl silicone oil having a viscosity of 700 mm<sup>2</sup>/s at
25 °C (a product by Shin-Etsu Chemical Co.) and 0.2 part of an organic
solution of a platinum complex compound containing 2% by
weight of a platinum compound calculated as the platinum element
(Cat-PL-1, a product by Shin-Etsu Chemical Co.) in a blending machine
(Laboplasto Mixer manufactured by Toyo Seiki Co.) rotating at
30 rpm for 10 minutes at 140 °C.</p><p num="0031">The thus compounded thermoplastic resin composition was
compression-molded by compressing for 1 minute under a pressure of
10 kgf/cm<sup>2</sup> into a 2.5 mm thick plate and 0.8 to 1.0 mm thick sheets.
The 2.5 mm thick plate was subjected to the measurement of the oxygen
consumption index (OI) and the 0.8 to 1.0 mm thick sheets were
subjected to the measurements of the tensile strength (TS) and ultimate
elongation (El). The results are shown in Table 1 below. The OI
value was measured according to JIS K7201 and the mechanical 
properties were measured according to JIS K7113 by using the No. 2
test specimens.</p><heading>Example 2.</heading><p num="0032">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Example 1 except that, in the formulation of the resin composition,
the amounts of the Kisma was increased from 100 parts to 140 parts.
The results of measurements are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>Example 3.</heading><p num="0033">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Example 1 except that, in the formulation of the resin composition,
the amounts of the silicone gum was decreased from 8 parts to 7 parts
and the amount of the methylvinyl silicone oil used in combination with
0.2 part of the platinum catalyst solution was increased from 2 parts to
3 parts. The results of measurements are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>Example 4.</heading><p num="0034">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Example 1 except that, in the formulation of the resin composition,
the amount of the silicone gum was increased from 8 parts to 10 parts
and the combination of the methylvinyl silicone oil and the platinum
catalyst solution was replaced with 0.08 part of 2,3-dimethyl-2,3-diphenyl
butane, of which the incipient thermal decomposition temperature
was 257 °C (Nofmer BC, a product by Nippon Oil &amp; Fat Co.).
The results of measurements are shown in Table 1. </p><heading>Example 5.</heading><p num="0035">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Example 4 except that, in the formulation of the resin composition,
the amount of the Nofmer BC was increased from 0.08 part to 0.2 part.
The results of measurements are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 1.</heading><p num="0036">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Example 1 except that the composition was prepared from 100
parts of the same EVA resin and 150 parts of the Kisma alone with
omission of the other ingredients. The results of measurements are
shown in Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 2.</heading><p num="0037">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Example 4 excepting for omission of Nofmer BC in the formulation
of the resin composition. The results of measurements are shown in
Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 3.</heading><p num="0038">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Comparative Example 2 except that, in the formulation of the resin
composition, the silicone gum was replaced with the same amount of
the same methylvinyl silicone oil as used in Example 1. The results of
measurements are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 4</heading><p num="0039">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Example 5 except that, in the formulation of the resin composition,
0.2 part of Nofmer BC was replaced with the same amount of the
same platinum catalyst solution as used in Example 1. The results of
measurements are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 5.</heading><p num="0040">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Example 1 except that, in the formulation of the resin composition,
the silicone gum was omitted and the amount of the methylvinyl silicone
oil was increased from 2 parts to 10 parts 1. The results of
measurements are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 6.</heading><p num="0041">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Example 1 except that, in the formulation of the resin composition, 2
parts of the methylvinyl silicone oil were replaced with the same
amount of a high-polymeric methylvinyl silicone gum having a viscosity
of 11500000 mm<sup>2</sup>/s at 25 °C, of which the content of the vinyl groups
was 10% by moles based on the total amount of the methyl and vinyl
groups. The results of measurements are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 7.</heading><p num="0042">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Example 1 except that, in the formulation of the resin composition,
the silicone gum was replaced with the same amount of a dimethyl 
silicone oil having a viscosity of 5000 mm<sup>2</sup>/s at 25 °C (KF96, a product
by Shin-Etsu Chemical Co.). The results of measurements are shown
in Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 8.</heading><p num="0043">The experimental procedure was substantially the same as
in Example 1 except that, in the formulation of the resin composition,
the amount of the silicone gum was decreased from 8 parts to 6 parts
and the amount of the methylvinyl silicone oil combined with the platinum
catalyst solution was increased from 2 parts to 4 parts. The results
of measurements are shown in Table 1. <img id="img-00210001" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00210001.tif" inline="no" he="152"/></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen which comprises, as a uniform blend:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) 100 parts by weight of a thermoplastic resin kneadable or moldable
at a temperature lower than 250 °C;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) from 50 to 300 parts by weight of a metal hydroxide powder;</claim-text><claim-text>(c) from 0.1 to 30 parts by weight of an organopolysiloxane compound
free from aliphatic unsaturation; and</claim-text><claim-text>(d) a reactive catalytic compound in a catalytically effective amount.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 1 in which the organopolysiloxane compound
as the component (c) has a viscosity of at least 1000000 mm2/s
at 25 °C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 1 in which the organopolysiloxane compound
as the component (c) has a straightly linear molecular structure.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 1 in which the reactive catalytic compound
as the component (d) is (d1) a radical-generating compound
having an incipient thermal decomposition temperature of 250 °C or
higher.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 4 in which the radical-generating compound
as the component (d1) is 2,3-dimethyl-2,3-diphenylbutane.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 1 in which the amount of the metal hydroxide
powder as the component (b) is in the range from 50 to 150
parts by weight per 100 parts by weight of the component (a).</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 1 in which the amount of the organopolysiloxane
compound as the component (c) is in the range from 0.1 to
30 parts by weight per 100 parts by weight of the component (a).</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 4 in which the amount of the radical-generating
compound as the component (d) is in the range from 0.01
to 10 parts by weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 1 in which the reactive catalytic compound
as the component (d) is (d2) a combination of a noble metal
compound and a vinyl group-containing organosiloxane compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 9 in which the amount of the vinyl group-containing
organosiloxane compound as a part of the component (d2)
is in the range from 0.001 to 9 parts by weight per 100 parts by weight
of the component (a).</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 9 in which the amount of the vinyl group-containing
organopolysiloxane compound as a part of the component
(d2) is in the range from 1 to 30% by weight based on the total amount
of the component (c) and the vinyl group-containing organopolysiloxane
compound as a part of the component (d2).</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 9 in which the amount of the noble metal
compound as a part of the component (d2) is in the range from
0.000001 to 0.1 part by weight, calculated as the noble metal element,
per 100 parts by weight of the component (a).</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 9 in which the vinyl group-containing organosiloxane
compound as a part of the component (d2) has a viscosity
not exceeding 1000000 mm2/s at 25 °C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 9 in which the content of the vinyl groups
in the vinyl group-containing organosiloxane compound as a part of
the component (d2) is at least 2% by moles based on the total amount
of the organic groups bonded to the silicon atoms thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 9 in which the noble metal compound as a
part of the component (d2) is a compound of a noble metal selected
from the group consisting of platinum, palladium and rhodium.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 1 in which the thermoplastic resin as the
component (a) is a homopolymer or copolymer of a monomeric olefin
compound or a combination thereof with at least one non-olefinic
polymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 1 in which the metal hydroxide powder as
the component (b) is a magnesium hydroxide powder.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 1 in which the metal hydroxide powder as
the component (b) consists of particles surface-treated with a surface
treatment agent selected from the group consisting of saturated fatty
acids, unsaturated fatty acids, silane coupling agents and organopolysiloxane
compounds having reactive functional groups.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 15 in which the noble metal compound as
a part of the component (d2) is a platinum compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The flame-retardant thermoplastic resin composition free from
halogen as claimed in claim 19 in which the amount of the platinum
compound as a part of the component (d2) is in the range from
0.000001 to 0.1 part by weight, calculated as platinum element, per
100 parts by weight of the component (a).</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>