<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1308487-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1308487" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="21697117" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030507"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1308487-A1" status="new" fvid="23750996"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1308487</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030507</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02257170-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02257170</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021016</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-164501-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>164501</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011030</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Ausblutkontrolle zwischen schwarzen und farbigen Tinten</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new"  lang="EN">Methods of controlling bleed between black and color dye based inks</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédés de contrôle de bavure entre des encres noires et des encres colorées pendant l'impression</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0649888-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0649888</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0872344-A2"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0872344</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1029903-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1029903</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HEWLETT PACKARD CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HEWLETT-PACKARD COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hewlett-Packard Company</last-name><address><street>3000 Hanover Street</street><city>Palo Alto, CA 94304</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>REHMAN ZIA</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>REHMAN, ZIA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>REHMAN, ZIA</last-name><address><street>3010 NE Glacier Way</street><city>Corvallis, OR 97330</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Jackson, Richard Eric</last-name><address><street>Carpmaels &amp;amp; Ransford, 43 Bloomsbury Square</street><city>London WC1A 2RA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention is drawn to ink-jet ink
compositions, systems, and methods for black and color
printing with substantially reduced black to color bleed.
Specifically, by utilizing black dyes together with at
least one long chain diol in a glycol ether, black ink-jet
inks can be printed in contact with color ink-jet
inks with substantially reduced black to color bleed.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">The present invention is drawn to ink-jet ink
systems and methods for black and color printing with
substantially reduced black to color bleed.</p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0002">In recent years, computer printer technology has
evolved to a point where very high resolution images can
be transferred to various types of media, including
paper. One particular type of printing involves the
placement of small drops of a fluid ink onto a media
surface in response to a digital signal. Typically, the
fluid ink is placed or jetted onto the surface without
physical contact between the printing device and the
surface.</p><p num="0003">Properties that are desirable for black ink-jet ink
compositions, to effectively compete with other imaging
technology include neutral black color, neutral gray
scale, and good optical density, and when printed with
color inks, substantially reduced black to color bleed.
Thus, with respect to black ink-jet inks, there is a
challenge that exists related to maintaining light
fastness, optical density, color neutrality, gray scale
quality, and pen performance, while at the same time 
reducing black to color bleed when printed in conjunction
other color dye-based inks. Thus, many have focused on
the color ink-jet inks, rather than the black ink-jet
inks, for reducing black to color bleed.</p><p num="0004">Several prior bleed control solutions have been
implemented from reactive and non-reactive inks. For
reactive pigment-containing black inks, black to color
bleed control has been achieved by using salts in the
color inks, such as, CaNO<sub>3</sub> and MgNO<sub>3</sub> to crash the pigment
based black inks on the paper, thus forming a barrier
that prevents bleed. Low pH color inks have also been
used to crash the pigment based black inks.</p><p num="0005">For non-reactive dye-containing black inks, the
available technique is to use surfactants in the black
ink to control black to color bleed. The use of
surfactants in the black ink has its drawbacks, in that
the optical density of the black for the same amount of
dye is reduced considerably by the use of surfactants.
The spreading effect of surfactants also have a negative
effect on print quality.</p><p num="0006">Illustrative of the art related to reducing bleed of
ink-jet inks include the following. In U.S. Patent No.
5,106,416, 5,116,409 and 5,133,803, it is disclosed that
surfactants are effectively used to reduce bleed in dye-based
ink formulations</p><p num="0007">Based upon the state of the prior art, improvement
in the area of preventing bleed is desired.

Specifically, it would be desirable to provide
compositions, systems, and methods for reducing black to
color bleed, without the necessity of including
undesirable additives in the ink-jet ink formulations.
Such compositions, systems, and methods are disclosed
herein. </p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0008">The present invention is drawn to compositions,
systems, and methods for printing with reduced black to
color bleed. Specifically, a method for printing black
and color images with reduced black to color bleed is
disclosed comprising the steps of providing a dye-based
color ink-jet ink; providing a dye-based black ink-jet
ink comprising at least one long chain alcohol in a
glycol ether; jetting the dye-based color ink-jet ink
onto a substrate; and jetting the dye-based black ink-jet
ink onto the substrate, such that the dye-based color
ink-jet ink contacts the dye-based black ink-jet ink at
an interface, and substantially no color to black bleed
occurs at the interface.</p><p num="0009">Additionally, a system for color printing with
reduced black to color bleed is disclosed comprising an
ink-jet pen containing a dye-based color ink-jet ink,
wherein the ink-jet pen is capable of printing the color
ink-jet ink onto a substrate; and an ink-jet pen
containing a dye-based black ink-jet ink, wherein the
black ink-jet ink comprises at least one long chain
alcohol in a glycol ether;, and wherein the ink-jet pen
is capable of printing its contents on the substrate such
that the black ink-jet ink contacts the color ink-jet
ink. When the color ink-jet ink contacts the black ink-jet
ink on the substrate at an interface, substantially
no black to color bleed is present.</p><p num="0010">Further, a printed image on a substrate having
reduced black to color bleed is disclosed. This printed
image comprises a black ink-jet ink comprising at least
one long chain alcohol in a glycol ether, printed in
contact with a dye-based color ink-jet ink having
substantially no bleed control treatment additives
present. </p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0011">Before the present invention is disclosed and
described, it is to be understood that this invention is
not limited to the particular process steps and materials
disclosed herein because such process steps and materials
may vary somewhat. It is also to be understood that the
terminology used herein is used for the purpose of
describing particular embodiments only. The terms are
not intended to be limiting because the scope of the
present invention is intended to be limited only by the
appended claims and equivalents thereof.</p><p num="0012">It must be noted that, as used in this specification
and the appended claims, the singular forms "a," "an,"
and "the" include plural referents unless the content
clearly dictates otherwise.</p><p num="0013">"Black to color bleed" or "bleed" is defined as the
undesirable intermixing of two or more ink-jet inks at a
color-black interface, reducing the sharpness of the
image. Bleed is particularly known to occur on fibrous
papers, though it can occur on any substrate.</p><p num="0014">"Bleed control agents" or "additives" include any
organic or inorganic substance added to ink-jet ink
formulations in order to reduce bleed between colors or
between black and a color on a substrate.</p><p num="0015">"Dye-based color inks" or "dye-based ink-jet inks"
used in the context of the present invention are
essentially soluble.</p><p num="0016">Bleed control between non-reactive black and color
inks has been achieved through a new technique. A
combination of long chain alcohol, such as dodecanol or
1,2 decanediol, and a glycol ether improves black to
color bleed without using large amounts of surfactants as
penetrants. This allows bleed control without 
sacrificing optical density of the black inks. The
optical density suffers when bleed control surfactants
are used.</p><p num="0017">The present invention enables a work group printer,
which typically requires high optical density and good
print quality output, to utilize a color ink-jet ink and
a black ink-jet ink neither of which contains bleed
control surfactants. In the case of black ink-jet ink,
these additives have a significant negative effect on
optical density. Furthermore, the spreading effect of
surfactants has a generally negative effect on print
quality in both black and color ink-jet ink. Thus, the
present invention provides very good black to color bleed
control without the use of these traditional additives.</p><p num="0018">With this in mind, the present invention is
specifically drawn to compositions and methods for
printing color images with reduced black to color bleed.</p><p num="0019">The inventor in the present application has
discovered that by combining higher alcohols that are
sparingly soluble in water with glycol ethers that
dissolve the alcohols, a solution is created which is
soluble in water.</p><p num="0020">When this solution is added to the dye-based black
and color inks, black to color bleed is controlled
without the negative effects of surfactants, which
include reduced optical density in dye-based black ink
and decreased print quality in both black and color dye-based
ink.</p><p num="0021">This prevention of black to color bleed comes about
as follows: The ejected drop hits the paper. Ink paper
interaction causes the sparingly soluble alcohols to
separate from the bulk ink and go to the interface
between the dye-based black and the dye-based color inks. 
The alcohols therefore prevent black to color bleed by
this separating out and moving to the interface.</p><p num="0022">A method of the present invention comprises the
steps of providing a dye-based color ink-jet ink
comprising at least one long chain alcohol in a glycol
ether; providing a dye-based black ink-jet ink comprising
at least one long chain diol in a alcohol ether; jetting
the dye-based color ink-jet ink onto a substrate; and
jetting the dye-based black ink-jet ink onto the
substrate. When these steps are followed such that the
dye-based color ink-jet ink contacts the dye-based black
ink at an interface, substantially no color to black
bleed occurs at the interface.</p><p num="0023">Additionally, a system for color printing with
reduced black to color bleed is disclosed comprising a
first ink-jet pen containing a dye-based color ink-jet
ink comprising at least one long chain alcohol in a
glycol ether; that is capable of printing the color ink-jet
ink onto a substrate. Next, a second ink-jet pen
containing a dye-based black ink-jet ink is present
comprising at least one long chain alcohol in a glycol
ether. The second ink-jet pen should be configured such
that the black ink-jet ink can contact the color ink-jet
ink once printed on the substrate. Thus, when the color
ink-jet ink contacts the black ink-jet ink on the
substrate, substantially no black to color bleed is
occurs at a black-color interface.</p><p num="0024">Next, a printed image on a substrate is disclosed
having reduced black to color bleed. The printed image
comprises a dye-based black ink-jet ink comprising at
least one long chain diol in a glycol ether. The dye
based black ink-jet ink is printed in contact with, a
dye-based color ink-jet ink comprising at least one long
chain alcohol in a glycol ether. Even without 
traditional bleed control agents in the color ink-jet
ink, by using the black ink-jet inks disclosed herein,
substantially no black to color bleed occurs.</p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0025">The following examples illustrate various
formulations for preparing the ink-jet ink compositions
used in the present invention, as well as provide data
showing the effectiveness of the ink-jet inks disclosed
herein. The following examples should not be considered
as limitations of the present invention, but should
merely teach how to make the best known ink-jet ink
formulations based upon current experimental data.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0026">Black inks were tested having the following formulas
given in Table 1. All percentages of ingredients given
are in weight percentages. The vehicle of the ink was
made to ensure that all the ingredients dissolve by
mixing on rollers. The pH of the vehicle was adjusted
before the black dye was added. The black dye was added.
The pH of the vehicle was adjusted again as necessary
after the dye was added to the vehicle. The final inks
were mixed on rollers.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">#</entry><entry align="center">Formula Ingredients (Wt %)</entry><entry align="left">Formula #79</entry><entry align="left">Formula # 80-91</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2-Pyrrolidinone</entry><entry align="left">8.5</entry><entry align="left">8.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">1,5-Pentanediol</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="left">7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">Different Ethers (See Below)</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">See Below</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">Cocobetaine</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry></row> <row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">Trizma Base</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.2 </entry></row> <row><entry align="center">6</entry> <entry align="center">Proxel GXL</entry> <entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">Neutralization with NaOH or HNO<sub>3</sub> to pH</entry><entry align="left">8.5</entry><entry align="left">8.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">Dye = K1334 Abs. @ 1/10K</entry><entry align="left">0.18</entry><entry align="left">0.18</entry></row><row><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">H<sub>2</sub>O</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">Total</entry><entry align="left">100 gms</entry><entry align="left">100gms</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0027">The following table shows the effects on black to color
bleed when different ethers are added to the ink
formulation of Example 1 as compared to a control black
ink without ether.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><u style="single">Ingredient #3</u><u style="single">(Ethers)</u></entry><entry align="left"><u style="single">Formula #</u></entry><entry align="left"><u style="single">% Evaluated</u></entry><entry align="left"><u style="single">Range</u></entry><entry align="left"><u style="single">Improved Bleed Rel to #79</u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Triethylene Glycol mono Butyl Ether</entry><entry align="left">80</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">0.25 to 15</entry><entry align="left">38.10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Triethylene Glycol mono Methyl Ether</entry><entry align="left">81</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">0.25 to 15</entry><entry align="left">0.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Propylene Glycol mono Propyl Ether</entry><entry align="left">82</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">0.25 to 18</entry><entry align="left">0.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Propylene Glycol mono Butyl Ether</entry><entry align="left">83</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">0.25 to 12</entry><entry align="left">23.81</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dipropylene Glycol Butyl Ether</entry><entry align="left">85</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">0.25 to 12</entry><entry align="left">28.57</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diethylene Glycol mono Butyl Ether Acetate</entry><entry align="left">87</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">0.25 to 12</entry><entry align="left">0.00 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diethylene Glycol mono Ethyl Ether</entry><entry align="left">88</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">0.25 to 12</entry><entry align="left">0.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diethylene Glycol mono Propyl Ether</entry><entry align="left">89</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">0.25 to 12</entry><entry align="left">0.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dipropylene Glycol Methyl Ether</entry><entry align="left">90</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">0.25 to 15</entry><entry align="left">42.86</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diethylene Glycol Dimethyl Ether</entry><entry align="left">91</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">0.25 to 15</entry><entry align="left">0.00</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><p num="0028">The bleed improvements shown in Example 2 were further
improved when one or more of the following alcohols were
added in the ranges given: 1,2 decanediol (0.1 to 3 wt%;
dodecanol (0.1 to 0.5 wt%); octanediol (0.1 to 0.5 wt%;
and Neopentyl Alcohol (0.1 to 0 wt%).</p><p num="0029">While the invention has been described with
reference to certain preferred embodiments, those skilled
in the art will appreciate that various modifications,
changes, omissions, and substitutions can be made without
departing from the spirit of the invention. It is
therefore intended that the invention be limited only by
the scope of the appended claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for printing black and color images with
reduced black to color bleed comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) providing a dye-based color ink-jet ink;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) providing a dye-based black ink-jet ink
comprising at least one long chain alcohol in a glycol
ether;</claim-text><claim-text>(c) jetting the dye-based color ink-jet ink onto a
substrate; and</claim-text><claim-text>(d) jetting the dye-based black ink-jet ink onto the
substrate,</claim-text></claim-text>
   such that the dye-based color ink-jet ink contacts
the dye-based black ink at an interface, and
substantially no color to black bleed occurs at the
interface.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method as in claim 1 wherein the glycol ether is
at least one of triethylene glycol mono butyl ether,
triethylene glycol mono methyl ether, propylene glycol
mono propyl ether, propylene glycol mono butyl ether,
dipropylene glycol butyl ether, diethylene glycol mono
butyl ether acetate, diethylene glycol mono ethyl ether,
diethylene glycol mono propyl ether, dipropylene glycol
methyl ether, and diethylene glycol dimethyl ether.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method as in claim 1 wherein the glycol ether is
present in the dye-based black ink-jet ink in a range
from 0.1 to 15 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A method as in claim 1 wherein the at least one long
chain alcohol is at least one of dodecanol, 1,2-decanediol,
octanediol and neopentyl alcohol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A method as in claim 4 wherein the 1,2-decanediol is
present in the dye-based black ink-jet ink in a range
from 0.1 to 3 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method as in claim 4 wherein the dodecanol is
present in the dye-based black ink-jet ink in a range
from 0.1 to 0.5 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method as in claim 4 wherein the octanediol is
present in the dye-based black ink-jet ink in a range
from 0.1 to 0.5 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A method as in claim 4 wherein the neopentyl alcohol
is present in the dye-based black ink-jet ink in a range
from 0.1 to 0.5 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method as in claim 1 wherein the at least one long
chain alcohol is dissolved in a glycol ether to form a
solution and the solution is dissolved in the dye-based
black ink-jet ink.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A system for black and color printing with reduced
black to color bleed comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) an ink-jet pen containing a dye-based color ink-jet
ink, said ink-jet pen capable of printing the color
ink-jet ink onto a substrate; and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) an ink-jet pen containing a dye-based black ink-jet
ink, said black ink-jet ink comprising at least one
long chain alcohol in a glycol ether, said ink-jet pen
being capable of printing on the substrate such that the
black ink-jet ink contacts the color ink-jet ink at an
interface;</claim-text></claim-text>
   such that when said color ink-jet ink contacts said
black ink-jet ink on said substrate, substantially no
black to color bleed is present at the interface.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A system as in claim 10 wherein the glycol ether is
at least one of triethylene glycol mono butyl ether,
triethylene glycol mono methyl ether, propylene glycol
mono propyl ether, propylene glycol mono butyl ether,
dipropylene glycol butyl ether, diethylene glycol mono
butyl ether acetate, diethylene glycol mono ethyl ether,
diethylene glycol mono propyl ether, dipropylene glycol
methyl ether, and diethylene glycol dimethyl ether.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A system as in claim 10 wherein the glycol ether is
present in the dye-based black ink-jet ink in a range
from 0.1 to 15 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A system as in claim 10 wherein the at least one
long chain alcohol is at least one of dodecanol, 1,2-decanediol,
octanediol and neopentyl alcohol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A system as in claim 13 wherein the 1,2-decanediol is
present in the dye-based black ink-jet ink in a range
from 0.1 to 3 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A system as in claim 13 wherein the dodecanol is
present in the dye-based black ink-jet ink in a range
from 0.1 to 0.5 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A system as in claim 13 wherein the octanediol is
present in the dye-based black ink-jet ink in a range
from 0.1 to 0.5 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A system as in claim 13 wherein the neopentyl alcohol
is present in the dye-based black ink-jet ink in a range
from 0.1 to 0.5 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A system as in claim 10 wherein the at least one
long chain alcohol is dissolved in a glycol ether to form
a solution and the solution is dissolved in both the dye-based
black ink-jet ink and the dye-based colored ink-jet
ink.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A printed image on a substrate having reduced black
to color bleed comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) a dye-based black ink-jet ink comprising at
least one long chain alcohol in a glycol ether;
printed on a substrate in contact with,</claim-text><claim-text>b) a dye-based color ink-jet ink.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>A printed image as in claim 19 wherein the glycol
ether is at least one of triethylene glycol mono butyl
ether, triethylene glycol mono methyl ether, propylene
glycol mono propyl ether, propylene glycol mono butyl
ether, dipropylene glycol butyl ether, diethylene glycol
mono butyl ether acetate, diethylene glycol mono ethyl
ether, diethylene glycol mono propyl ether, dipropylene
glycol methyl ether, and diethylene glycol dimethyl
ether;
   and wherein the at least one long chain alcohol is
at least one of dodecanol, 1,2-decanediol,octanediol and
neopentyl alcohol.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>