<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2002030926-A1" country="WO" doc-number="2002030926" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="8173902" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20020418"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2002030926-A1" status="new" fvid="77695769"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2002030926</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020418</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="GB-0104497-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>0104497</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20011009</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-00402845-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00402845</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001013</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>C07D 407/12</main-classification><further-classification>C07D 407/14</further-classification><further-classification>A61K  31/495</further-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/517       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/517       20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/5375      20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/5377      20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/541       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/541       20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  35/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  35/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 405/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 405/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 405/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 417/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 417/14        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07D 405/12+307+239</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07D 405/14+307+249+239</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07D405:12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07D405:14</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">QUINAZOLINE DERIVATIVES</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">DÉRIVÉS DE QUINAZOLINE</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0602851-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0602851</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0795556-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0795556</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5747498-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5747498</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5770599-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5770599</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5814630-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5814630</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999006396-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999006396</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>MYERS, MICHAEL R. ET AL: "The preparation and SAR of 4-(anilino), 4-(phenoxy), and 4-(thiophenoxy)-quinazolines: inhibitors of p56lck and EGF-R tyrosine kinase activity" BIOORG. MED. CHEM. LETT. (1997), 7(4), 417-420 , XP004136037</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ASTRAZENECA AB</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ASTRAZENECA UK LTD</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LAMBERT CHRISTINE MARIE PAUL</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PLE PATRICK</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ASTRAZENECA AB</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ASTRAZENECA UK LIMITED</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LAMBERT, CHRISTINE, MARIE-PAUL</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PLE, PATRICK</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LAMBERT CHRISTINE MARIE-PAUL</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PLE PATRICK</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LAMBERT, CHRISTINE, MARIE-PAUL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PLE, PATRICK</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The invention concerns quinazoline derivatives of Formula (I) wherein each of m, R&lt;1&gt;, n, R&lt;2&gt; and R&lt;3&gt; have any of the meanings defined in the description; process for their preparation, pharmaceutical compositions them and their use in the manufacture of a medicament for use as an anti-invasive agent in the containment and/or treatment of solid tumour disease.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>L'invention concerne des dérivés de quinazoline de formule (I) dans laquelle m, R&lt;1&gt;, n, R&lt;2&gt; et R&lt;3&gt; sont tels que définis dans la description. L'invention concerne également des procédés de préparation des dérivés, des compositions pharmaceutiques les contenant et leur utilisation dans la fabrication d'un médicament à utiliser comme agent anti-invasif dans la maîtrise et/ou le traitement d'une maladie à tumeur solide.</p></abstract><description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="2"/>--><p num="p0001"> OUINAZOLINE DERIVATIVES</p><p num="p0002">The invention concerns certain novel quinazoline derivatives, or pharmaceutically-acceptable salts thereof, which possess anti-tumour activity and are accordingly useful in methods of treatment of the human or animal body. The invention also concerns processes for the manufacture of said quinazoline derivatives, to pharmaceutical compositions containing them and to their use in therapeutic methods, for example in the manufacture of medicaments for use in the prevention or treatment of solid tumour disease in a warm-blooded animal such as man. Many of the current treatment regimes for cell proliferation diseases such as psoriasis and cancer utilise compounds which inhibit DNA synthesis. Such compounds are toxic to cells generally but their toxic effect on rapidly dividing cells such as tumour cells can be beneficial. Alternative approaches to anti-tumour agents which act by mechanisms other than the inhibition of DNA synthesis have the potential to display enhanced selectivity of action. In recent years it has been discovered that a cell may become cancerous by virtue of the transformation of a portion of its DNA into an oncogene i.e. a gene which, on activation, leads to the formation of malignant tumour cells (Bradshaw, Mutagenesis, 1986, 1, 91). Several such oncogenes give rise to the production of peptides which are receptors for growth factors. Activation of the growth factor receptor complex subsequently leads to an increase in cell proliferation. It is known, for example, that several oncogenes encode tyrosine kinase enzymes and that certain growth factor receptors are also tyrosine kinase enzymes (Yarden et al., Ann. Rev. Biochem., 1988, 57, 443; Larsen et al, Ann. Reports in Med. Chem., 1989, Chpt. 13). The first group of tyrosine kinases to be identified arose from such viral oncogenes, for example pp60<sup>v"Src</sup> tyrosine kinase (otherwise known as v-Src), and the corresponding tyrosine kinases in normal cells, for example pp60<sup>c"Src</sup> tyrosine kinase (otherwise known as c-Src).</p><p num="p0003">Receptor tyrosine kinases are important in the transmission of biochemical signals which initiate cell replication. They are large enzymes which span the cell membrane and possess an extracellular binding domain for growth factors such as epidermal growth factor (EGF) and an intracellular portion which functions as a kinase to phosphorylate tyrosine amino acids in proteins and hence to influence cell proliferation. Various classes of receptor tyrosine kinases are known (Wilks, Advances in Cancer Research, 1993, 60, 43-73) based on 
<!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>-->
families of growth factors which bind to different receptor tyrosine kinases. The classification includes Class I receptor tyrosine kinases comprising the EGF family of receptor tyrosine kinases such as the EGF, TGFoc, Neu and erbB receptors, Class π receptor tyrosine kinases comprising the insulin family of receptor tyrosine kinases such as the insulin and IGFI receptors and insulin-related receptor (IRR) and Class HI receptor tyrosine kinases comprising the platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF) family of receptor tyrosine kinases such as the PDGFα, PDGFβ and colony-stimulating factor 1 (CSF1) receptors.</p><p num="p0004">It is also known that certain tyrosine kinases belong to the class of non-receptor tyrosine kinases which are located intracellularly and are involved in the transmission of biochemical signals such as those that influence tumour cell motility, dissemination and invasiveness and subsequently metastatic tumour growth (Ullrich et al., Cell, 1990, 61, 203- 212, Bolen et al, FASEB J.. 1992, 6, 3403-3409, Brickell et al, Critical Reviews in Oncogenesis, 1992, 3, 401-406, Bohlen et al, Oncogene, 1993, 8, 2025-2031, Courtaeidge et al, Se in. Cancer Biol., 1994, 5, 239-246, Lauffenburger et al, Ceg, 1996, 84, 359-369, Hanks et al, BioEssays, 1996, 19, 137-145, Parsons et al, Current Opinion in Cell Biology, 1997, 9, 187-192, Brown et al, Biochimica et Biophvsica Acta, 1996, 1287, 121-149 and Schlaepfer et al, Progress in Biophysics and Molecular Biology. 1999, 71, 435-478). Various classes of non-receptor tyrosine kinases are known including the Src family such as the Src, Lyn and Yes tyrosine kinases, the Abl family such as Abl and Arg and the Jak family such as Jak 1 and Tyk 2.</p><p num="p0005">It is known that the Src family of non-receptor tyrosine kinases are highly regulated in normal cells and in the absence of extracellular stimuli are maintained in an inactive conformation. However, some Src family members, for example c-Src tyrosine kinase, is frequently significantly activated (when compared to normal cell levels) in common human cancers such as gastrointestinal cancer, for example colon, rectal and stomach cancer</p><p num="p0006">(Cartwright et al, Proc. Nafl. Acad. Sci. USA, 1990, 87, 558-562 and Mao et al, Oncogene, 1997, 15, 3083-3090), and breast cancer (Muthuswa y et al, Oncogene, 1995, 11, 1801- 1810). The Src family of non-receptor tyrosine kinases has also been located in other common human cancers such as non-small cell lung cancers (NSCLCs) including adenocarcinomas and squamous cell cancer of the lung (Mazurenko et al. European Journal of Cancer, 1992, 28, 372-7), bladder cancer (Fanning et al, Cancer Research, 1992, 52, 1457- 62), oesophageal cancer (Jankowski et al, Gut, 1992, 33, 1033-8), cancer of the prostate, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
ovarian cancer (Wiener et al, Clin. Cancer Research, 1999, 5, 2164-70) and pancreatic cancer (Lutz et al, Biochem. and Biophys. Res. Comm., 1998, 243, 503-8). As further human tumour tissues are tested for the Src family of non-receptor tyrosine kinases it is expected that its widespread prevalence will be established. It is further known that the predominant role of c-Src non-receptor tyrosine kinase is to regulate the assembly of focal adhesion complexes through interaction with a number of cytoplasmic proteins including, for example, focal adhesion kinase and paxillin. In addition c-Src is coupled to signalling pathways that regulate the actin cytoskeleton which facilitates cell motility. Likewise, important roles are played by the c-Src, c-Yes and c-Fyn non-receptor tyrosine kinases in integrin mediated signalling and in disrupting cadherin-dependent cell-cell junctions (Owens et al, Molecular Biology of the Cell, 2000, 11, 51-64 and Klinghoffer et al, EMBO Journal, 1999, 18, 2459-2471). Cellular motility is necessarily required for a localised tumour to progress through the stages of dissemination into the blood stream, invasion of other tissues and initiation of metastatic tumour growth. For example, colon tumour progression from localised to disseminated, invasive metastatic disease has been correlated with c-Src non-receptor tyrosine kinase activity (Brunton et al, Oncogene, 1997, 14, 283-293, Fincham et al, EMBO J, 1998, 17, 81-92 and Nerbeek et al, Exp. Cell Research, 1999, 248, 531-537).</p><p num="p0007">Accordingly it has been recognised that an inhibitor of such non-receptor tyrosine kinases should be of value as a selective inhibitor of the motility of tumour cells and as a selective inhibitor of the dissemination and invasiveness of mammalian cancer cells leading to inhibition of metastatic tumour growth. In particular an inhibitor of such non-receptor tyrosine kinases should be of value as an anti-invasive agent for use in the containment and/or treatment of solid tumour disease. We have now found that surprisingly certain quinazoline derivatives possess potent anti-tumour activity. Without wishing to imply that the compounds disclosed in the present invention possess pharmacological activity only by virtue of an effect on a single biological process, it is believed that the compounds provide an anti-tumour effect by way of inhibition of one or more of the non-receptor tyrosine-specific protein kinases that are involved in the signal transduction steps which lead to the invasiveness and migratory ability of metastasising tumour cells. In particular, it is believed that the compounds of the present invention provide 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
an anti-tumour effect by way of inhibition of the Src family of non-receptor tyrosine kinases, for example by inhibition of one or more of c-Src, c-Yes and c-Fyn.</p><p num="p0008">It is also known that c-Src non-receptor tyrosine kinase enzyme is involved in the control of osteoclast-driven bone resorption (Soriano et al, Cell, 1991, 64, 693-702; Boyce et al, J. Clin. Invest., 1992, 90, 1622-1627; Yoneda et al, J. Clin. Invest., 1993, 91, 2791-2795 and Missbach et al , Bone, 1999, 24 , 437-49). An inhibitor of c-Src non-receptor tyrosine kinase is therefore of value in the prevention and treatment of bone diseases such as osteoporosis, Paget's disease, metastatic disease in bone and tumour-induced hypercalcaemia. The compounds of the present invention are also useful in inhibiting the uncontrolled cellular proliferation which arises from various non-malignant diseases such as inflammatory diseases (for example rheumatoid arthritis and inflammatory bowel disease), fibrotic diseases (for example hepatic cirrhosis and lung fibrosis), glomerulonephritis, multiple sclerosis, psoriasis, hypersensitivity reactions of the skin, blood vessel diseases (for example atherosclerosis and restenosis), allergic asthma, insulin-dependent diabetes, diabetic retinopathy and diabetic nephropathy.</p><p num="p0009">Generally the compounds of the present invention possess potent inhibitory activity against the Src family of non-receptor tyrosine kinases, for example by inhibition of c-Src and/or c-Yes, whilst possessing less potent inhibitory activity against other tyrosine kinase enzymes such as the receptor tyrosine kinases, for example EGF receptor tyrosine kinase and/or VEGF receptor tyrosine kinase. Furthermore, certain compounds of the present invention possess substantially better potency against the Src family of non-receptor tyrosine kinases, for example c-Src and/or c-Yes, than against VEGF receptor tyrosine kinase. Such compounds possess sufficient potency against the Src family of non-receptor tyrosine kinases, for example c-Src and/or c-Yes, that they may be used in an amount sufficient to inhibit, for example, c-Src and/or c-Yes whilst demonstrating little activity against VEGF receptor tyrosine kinase.</p><p num="p0010">According to one aspect of the invention there is provided a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>--><img id="imgf000006_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="77" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000006_0001.tif" inline="no" he="41"/></p><p num="p0011">wherein m is 0, 1, 2 or 3; each R<sup>1</sup> group, which may be the same or different, is selected from halogeno, trifluoromethyl, cyano, isocyano, nitro, hydroxy, mercapto, amino, formyl, carboxy, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl, (l-6C)alkoxy, (2-6C)aIkenyloxy, (2-6C)alkynyloxy, (l-6C)alkylthio, (l-6C)alkylsulphinyl, (l-6C)alkylsulphonyl, (l-6C)alkylamino, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino, (l-6C)alkoxycarbonyl, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyloxy, (2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-(2-6C)alkanoylamino, (3-6C)alkenoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl- (3-6C)alkenoylamino, (3-6C)alkynoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-(3-6C)alkynoylamino,</p><p num="p0012">N-(l-6C)alkylsulphamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]sulphamoyl, (l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino and N-(l-6C)alkyl-(l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino, or from a group of the formula : cxx<sup>1</sup>- wherein X<sup>1</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, S, SO, SO<sub>2</sub>, N(R<sup>4</sup>), CO, CH(OR<sup>4</sup>), CON(R<sup>4</sup>), N(R<sup>4</sup>)CO, SO<sub>2</sub>N(R<sup>4</sup>), N(R<sup>4</sup>)SO<sub>2</sub>, OC(R<sup>4</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, SC(R<sup>4</sup>)<sub>2</sub> and N(R<sup>4</sup>)C(R<sup>4</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, wherein R<sup>4</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>1</sup> is aryl, aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkyl- (l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkenyl, (3-7C)cycloalkenyl-(l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl, heteroaryl- (l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl, or (R^<sub>m</sub> is (l-3C)alkylenedioxy, and wherein adjacent carbon atoms in any (2-6C)alkylene chain within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent are optionally separated by the insertion into the chain of a group selected from O, S, SO, SO<sub>2</sub>, N(R<sup>5</sup>), CO, CH(OR<sup>5</sup>), CON(R<sup>5</sup>), N(R<sup>5</sup>)CO, SO<sub>2</sub>N(R<sup>5</sup>), N(R<sup>5</sup>)SO<sub>2</sub>, CH=CH and C≡C wherein R<sup>5</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl or, when the inserted group is N(R<sup>5</sup>), R<sup>5</sup> may also be (2-6C)alkanoyl, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub>=CH- or HC≡C- group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears at the terminal CH = or HC≡ position a substituent selected from halogeno, carboxy, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkoxycarbonyl, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
amino-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkylamino-(l-6C)alkyl and di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino-(l-6C)alkyl or from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0013">Q<sup>2</sup>-X<sup>2</sup>- wherein X is a direct bond or is selected from CO and N(R )CO, wherein R is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>2</sup> is aryl, aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl, heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears on each said CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group one or more halogeno or (l-6C)alkyl substituents or a substituent selected from hydroxy, cyano, amino, carboxy, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkoxy, (l-6C)alkylthio, (l-6C)alkylsulphinyl, (l-6C)alkylsulphonyl, (l-6C)alkylamino, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino, (l-6C)alkoxycarbonyl, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyloxy, (2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl- (2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkylsulphamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]sulphamoyl, (l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino and N-(l-6C)alkyl-(l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino, or from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0014">-X<sup>3</sup>-Q<sup>3</sup> wherein X<sup>3</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, S, SO, SO<sub>2</sub>, N(R<sup>7</sup>), CO, CH(OR<sup>7</sup>), CON(R<sup>7</sup>), N(R<sup>7</sup>)CO, SO<sub>2</sub>N(R<sup>7</sup>), N(R<sup>7</sup>)SO<sub>2</sub>, C(R<sup>7</sup>)<sub>2</sub>O, C(R<sup>7</sup>)<sub>2</sub>S and N(R<sup>7</sup>)C(R<sup>7</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, wherein R<sup>7</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>3</sup> is aryl, aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkyl- (l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkenyl, (3-7C)cycloalkenyl-(l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl, heteroaryl- (l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl, and wherein any aryl, heteroaryl or heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1, 2 or 3 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from halogeno, trifluoromethyl, cyano, nitro, hydroxy, amino, carboxy, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl, (l-6C)alkoxy, (2-6C)alkenyloxy, (2-6C)alkynyloxy, (l-6C)alkylthio, (l-6C)alkylsulρhinyl, (l-6C)alkylsulρhonyl, (l-6C)alkylamino, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino, (l-6C)alkoxycarbonyl, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyloxy, (2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-(2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkylsulphamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]sulphamoyl, (l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino and N-(l-6C)alkyl- (l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino, or from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0015">-X<sup>4</sup>-R<sup>8</sup><!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>-->
wherein X<sup>4</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O and N(R<sup>9</sup>), wherein R<sup>9</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and R<sup>8</sup> is halogeno-(l-6C)alkyl, hydroxy-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkoxy-(l-6C)alkyl, cyano-(l-6C)alkyl, amino-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkylamino-(l-6C)alkyl, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino- (l-6C)alkyl, (2-6C)alkanoylamino-(l-6C)alkyl or (l-6C)alkoxycarbonylamino-(l-6C)alkyl, or from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0016">-X<sup>5</sup>-Q<sup>4</sup> wherein X<sup>5</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, N(R<sup>10</sup>) and CO, wherein R<sup>10</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>4</sup> is aryl, aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl, heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl which optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from halogeno, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl and (l-6C)alkoxy, and wherein any heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo or thioxo substituents;</p><p num="p0017">R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl; n is O, 1, 2 or 3; and</p><p num="p0018">R<sup>3</sup> is halogeno, trifluoromethyl, cyano, nitro, hydroxy, amino, carboxy, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl, (l-6C)alkoxy, (2-6C)alkenyloxy, (2-6C)alkynyloxy, (l-6C)alkylthio, (l-6C)alkylsulphinyl, (l-6C)alkylsulphonyl, (l-6C)alkylamino, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino, (l-6C)alkoxycarbonyl, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyloxy, (2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-(2-6C)alkanoylamino, (3-6C)alkenoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl- (3-6C)alkenoylamino, (3-6C)alkynoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-(3-6C)alkynoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkylsulphamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]sulphamoyl, (l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino and N-(l-6C)alkyl-(l-6C)alkanesulρhonylamino, or from a group of the formula : -X<sup>6</sup>-R<sup>π</sup> wherein X<sup>6</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O and N(R<sup>12</sup>), wherein R<sup>12</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, andR<sup>11</sup> is halogeno-(l-6C)alkyl, hydroxy-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkoxy-(l-6C)alkyl, cyano-(l-6C)alkyl, amino-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkylamino-(l-6C)alkyl or di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino-(l-6C)alkyl, or from a group of the formula : -X<sup>7</sup>-Q<sup>5</sup> wherein X<sup>7</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, S, SO, SO<sub>2</sub>, N(R<sup>13</sup>), CO, CH(OR<sup>13</sup>), CON(R<sup>13</sup>), N(R<sup>13</sup>)CO, SO<sub>2</sub>N(R<sup>13</sup>), N(R<sup>13</sup>)SO<sub>2</sub>, C(R<sup>13</sup>)<sub>2</sub>O, C(R<sup>13</sup>)<sub>2</sub>S and N(R<sup>13</sup>)C(R<sup>13</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>-->
wherein R<sup>13</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>5</sup> is aryl, aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl, heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl which optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from halogeno, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl and (l-6C)alkoxy, and any heterocyclyl group within Q<sup>5</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo or thioxo substituents, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof.</p><p num="p0019">In this specification the generic term "alkyl" includes both straight-chain and branched-chain alkyl groups such as propyl, isopropyl and tert-butyl, and also (3-7C)cycloalkyl groups such as cyclopropyl, cyclobutyl, cyclopentyl, cyclohexyl and cycloheptyl. However references to individual alkyl groups such as "propyl" are specific for the straight-chain version only, references to individual branched-chain alkyl groups such as "isopropyl" are specific for the branched-chain version only and references to individual cycloalkyl groups such as "cyclopentyl" are specific for that 5-membered ring only. An analogous convention applies to other generic terms, for example (l-6C)alkoxy includes methoxy, ethoxy, cyclopropyloxy and cyclopentyloxy, (l-6C)alkylamino includes methylamino, ethylamino, cyclobutylamino and cyclohexylamino, and di-[(l-6Calkyl]amino includes dimethylamino, diethylamino, N-cyclobutyl-N-methylamino and N-cyclohexyl- N-ethylamino.</p><p num="p0020">It is to be understood that, insofar as certain of the compounds of Formula I defined above may exist in optically active or racemic forms by virtue of one or more asymmetric carbon atoms, the invention includes in its definition any such optically active or racemic form which possesses the above-mentioned activity. The synthesis of optically active forms may be carried out by standard techniques of organic chemistry well known in the art, for example by synthesis from optically active starting materials or by resolution of a racemic form. Similarly, the above-mentioned activity may be evaluated using the standard laboratory techniques referred to hereinafter.</p><p num="p0021">Suitable values for the generic radicals referred to above include those set out below. A suitable value for any one of the 'Q' groups (Q<sup>1</sup> to Q<sup>5</sup>) when it is aryl or for the aryl group within a 'Q' group is, for example, phenyl or naphthyl, preferably phenyl. A suitable value for any one of the 'Q' groups (Q<sup>1</sup> or Q<sup>3</sup>) when it is</p><p num="p0022">(3-7C)cycloalkyl or for the (3-7C)cycloalkyl group within a 'Q' group is, for example, cyclopropyl, cyclobutyl, cyclopentyl, cyclohexyl, cycloheptyl or bicyclo[2.2.1]heptyl and a 
<!-- EPO <DP n="10"/>-->
suitable value for any one of the 'Q' groups (Q<sup>1</sup> or Q<sup>3</sup>) when it is (3-7C)cycloalkenyl or for the (3-7C)cycloalkenyl group within a 'Q' group is, for example, cyclobutenyl, cyclopentenyl, cyclohexenyl or cycloheptenyl.</p><p num="p0023">A suitable value for any one of the 'Q' groups (Q<sup>1</sup> to Q<sup>5</sup>) when it is heteroaryl or for the heteroaryl group within a 'Q' group is, for example, an aromatic 5- or 6-membered monocyclic ring or a 9- or 10-membered bicyclic ring with up to five ring heteroatoms selected from oxygen, nitrogen and sulphur, for example furyl, pyrrolyl, thienyl, oxazolyl, isoxazolyl, imidazolyl, pyrazolyl, thiazolyl, isothiazolyl, oxadiazolyl, thiadiazolyl, triazolyl, tetrazolyl, pyridyl, pyridazinyl, pyrimidinyl, pyrazinyl, 1,3,5-triazenyl, benzofuranyl, indolyl, benzothienyl, benzoxazolyl, benzimidazolyl, benzothiazolyl, indazolyl, benzofurazanyl, quinolyl, isoquinolyl, quinazolinyl, quinoxalinyl, cinnolinyl or naphthyridinyl.</p><p num="p0024">A suitable value for any one of the 'Q' groups (Q<sup>1</sup> to Q<sup>5</sup>) when it is heterocyclyl or for the heterocyclyl group within a 'Q' group is, for example, a non-aromatic saturated or partially saturated 3 to 10 membered monocyclic or bicyclic ring with up to five heteroatoms selected from oxygen, nitrogen and sulphur, for example oxiranyl, oxetanyl, tetrahydrofuranyl, tetrahydropyranyl, oxepanyl, pyrrolinyl, pyrrolidinyl, morpholinyl, tetrahydro-l,4-thiazinyl, l,l-dioxotetrahydro-l,4-thiazinyl, piperidinyl, homopiperidinyl, piperazinyl, homopiperazinyl, dihydropyridinyl, tetrahydropyridinyl, dihydropyrimidinyl or tetrahydropyrimidinyl, preferably tetrahydrofuranyl, tetrahydropyranyl, pyrrolidinyl, morpholinyl, l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazinyl, piperidinyl or piperazinyl. A suitable value for such a group which bears 1 or 2 oxo or thioxo substituents is, for example, 2-oxopyrrolidinyl, 2-thioxopyrrolidinyl, 2-oxoimidazolidinyl, 2-thioxoimidazolidinyl, 2-oxopiperidinyl, 2,5-dioxopyrrolidinyl, 2,5-dioxoimidazolidinyl or 2,6-dioxopiperidinyl. A suitable value for a 'Q' group when it is heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl is, for example, heteroarylmethyl, 2-heteroarylethyl and 3-heteroarylρropyl. The invention comprises corresponding suitable values for 'Q' groups when, for example, rather than a heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl group, an aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkyl-(l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkenyl-(l-6C)alkyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl group is present.</p><p num="p0025">In structural Formula I there is a hydrogen atom at each of the 2- and 5-positions on the quinazoline ring. It is to be understood thereby that the R<sup>1</sup> substituents may only be located at the 6-, 7- or 8-positions on the quinazoline ring i.e. that the 2- and 5-positions remain unsubstituted. It is further to be understood that the R<sup>3</sup> group that may be present on 
<!-- EPO <DP n="11"/>-->
the benzofuran ring within structural Formula I may be located on the phenyl ring or on the carbon atoms within the furyl ring.</p><p num="p0026">Suitable values for any of the 'R' groups (R<sup>1</sup> to R<sup>13</sup>) or for various groups within an R<sup>1</sup> or R substituent include :- for halogeno fluoro, chloro, bromo and iodo; for (l-6C)alkyl: methyl, ethyl, propyl, isopropyl and tert-butyl; for (2-8C)alkenyl: vinyl, isopropenyl, allyl and but-2-enyl; for (2-8C)alkynyl: ethynyl, 2-propynyl and but-2-ynyl; for (l-6C)alkoxy: methoxy, ethoxy, propoxy, isopropoxy and butoxy; for (2-6C)alkenyloxy: vinyloxy and allyloxy; for (2-6C)alkynyloxy: ethynyloxy and 2-propynyloxy; for (l-6C)alkylthio: methylthio, ethylthio and propylthio; for (l-6C)alkylsulphinyl: methylsulphinyl and ethylsulphinyl; for (l-6C)alkylsulphonyl: methylsulphonyl and ethylsulphonyl; for (l-6C)alkylamino: methylamino, ethylamino, propylamino, isopropylamino and butylamino; for di-[(l-6C)alkyl] amino: dimethylamino, diethylamino, N-ethyl-</p><p num="p0027">N-methylamino and diisopropylamino; for (l-6C)alkoxycarbonyl: methoxycarbonyl, ethoxycarbonyl, propoxycarbonyl and tert-butoxycarbonyl; or N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl: N-methylcarbamoyl, N-ethylcarbamoyl and</p><p num="p0028">N-propylcarbamoyl; or N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl: N,N-dimethylcarbamoyl, N-ethyl-</p><p num="p0029">N-methylcarbamoyl and N,N-diethylcarbamoyl; or (2-6C)alkanoyl: acetyl and propionyl; or (2-6C)alkanoyloxy: acetoxy and propionyloxy; or (2-6C)alkanoylamino: acetamido and propionamido; or N-(l-6C)alkyl-(2-6C)alkanoylamino: N-methylacetamido and N-methylpropionamido; or N-(l-6C)alkylsulphamoyl: N-methylsulphamoyl and N-ethylsulphamoyl; or N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]sulphamoyl: N,N-dimethylsulphamoyl; or (l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino: methanesulphonylamino and ethanesulphonylamino; 
<!-- EPO <DP n="12"/>-->
for N-(l-6C)alkyl-(l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino: N-methylmethanesulphonylamino and</p><p num="p0030">N-methylethanesulphonylamino ; for (3-6C)alkenoylamino: acrylamido, methacrylamido and crotonamido; for N-(l-6C)alkyl-(3-6C)alkenoylamino: N-methylacrylamido and N-methylcrotonamido; for (3-6C)alkynoylamino: propiolamido; for N-(l-6C)alkyl-(3-6C)alkynoylamino: N-methylpropiolamido; for amino-(l-6C)alkyl: aminomethyl, 2-aminoethyl, 1-aminoethyl and 3-aminopropyl; for (l-6C)alkylamino-(l-6C)alkyl: methylaminomethyl, ethylaminomethyl, 1-methylaminoethyl, 2-methylaminoethyl,</p><p num="p0031">2-ethylaminoethyl and 3-methylaminopropyl; for di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino-(l-6C)alkyl: dimethylaminomethyl, diethylaminomethyl,</p><p num="p0032">1-dimethylaminoethyl, 2-dimethylaminoethyl and 3-dimethylaminopropyl; for halogeno-(l-6C)alkyl: chloromethyl, 2-chloroethyl, 1-chloroethyl and 3-chloropropyl; for hydroxy-(l-6C)alkyl: hydroxymethyl, 2-hydroxyethyl, 1-hydroxyethyl and 3-hydroxypropyl; for (l-6C)alkoxy-(l-6C)alkyl: methoxymethyl, ethoxymethyl, 1-methoxyethyl, 2-methoxyethyl, 2-ethoxyethyl and</p><p num="p0033">3-methoxypropyl; for cyano-(l-6C)alkyl: cyanomethyl, 2-cyanoethyl, 1-cyanoethyl and 3-cyanopropyl; for (2-6C)alkanoylamino-(l-6C)alkyl: acetamidomethyl, propionamidomethyl and 2-acetamidoethyl; and for (l-6C)alkoxycarbonylamino-(l-6C)alkyl: methoxycarbonylaminomethyl, ethoxycarbonylaminomethyl, tert-butoxycarbonylaminomethyl and 2-methoxycarbonylaminoethyl. A suitable value for (R^<sub>m</sub> when it is a (l-3C)alkylenedioxy group is, for example, methylenedioxy or ethylenedioxy and the oxygen atoms thereof occupy adjacent ring positions. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="13"/>-->
 When, as defined hereinbefore, an R<sup>1</sup> group forms a group of the formula Q^X<sup>1</sup>- and, for example, X<sup>1</sup> is a OC(R<sup>4</sup>)<sub>2</sub> linking group, it is the carbon atom, not the oxygen atom, of the OC(R<sup>4</sup>)<sub>2</sub> linking group which is attached to the quinazoline ring and the oxygen atom is attached to the Q<sup>1</sup> group. Similarly, when, for example a CH<sub>3</sub> group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent bears a group of the formula -X<sup>3</sup>-Q<sup>3</sup> and, for example, X<sup>3</sup> is a C(R<sup>7</sup>)<sub>2</sub>O linldng group, it is the carbon atom, not the oxygen atom, of the C(R<sup>7</sup>)<sub>2</sub>O linking group which is attached to the CH<sub>3</sub> group and the oxygen atom is linked to the Q<sup>3</sup> group. A similar convention applies to the attachment of the groups of the formulae Q<sup>2</sup>-X<sup>2</sup>- and -X<sup>7</sup>-Q<sup>5</sup>.</p><p num="p0034">As defined hereinbefore, adjacent carbon atoms in any (2-6C)alkylene chain within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent may be optionally separated by the insertion into the chain of a group such as O, CON(R<sup>5</sup>) or C≡C. For example, insertion of a C≡C group into the ethylene chain within a 2-morpholinoethoxy group gives rise to a 4-morpholinobut-2-ynyloxy group and, for example, insertion of a CONH group into the ethylene chain within a 3-methoxypropoxy group gives rise to, for example, a 2-(2-methoxyacetamido)ethoxy group. When, as defined hereinbefore, any CH<sub>2</sub>=CH- or HC≡C- group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears at the terminal CH<sub>2</sub>= or HC≡ position a substituent such as a group of the formula Q<sup>2_</sup>X<sup>2</sup>- wherein X<sup>2</sup> is, for example, NHCO and Q<sup>2</sup> is a heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl group, suitable R<sup>1</sup> substituents so formed include, for example, N-[heterocyclyl- (l-6C)alkyl]carbamoylvinyl groups such as N-(2-pyrrolidin-l-ylethyl)carbamoylvinyl or N-[heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoylethynyl groups such as N-(2-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylethyl)carbamoylethynyl .</p><p num="p0035">When, as defined hereinbefore, any CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears on each said CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group one or more halogeno or (l-6C)alkyl substituents, there are suitably 1 or 2 halogeno or (l-6C)alkyl substituents present on each said CH<sub>2</sub> group and there are suitably 1, 2 or 3 such substituents present on each said CH<sub>3</sub> group. When, as defined hereinbefore, any CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears on each said CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group a substituent as defined hereinbefore, suitable R<sup>1</sup> substituents so formed include, for example, hydroxy-substituted heterocyclyl- (l-6C)alkoxy groups such as 2-hydroxy-3-piperidinoρropoxy and 2-hydroxy- 3-morpholinopropoxy, hydroxy-substituted amino-(2-6C)alkoxy groups such as 3-amino- 2-hydroxypropoxy, hydroxy-substituted (l-6C)alkylamino-(2-6C)alkoxy groups such as 2-hydroxy-3-methylaminopropoxy, hydroxy-substituted di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino-(2-6C)alkoxy 
<!-- EPO <DP n="14"/>-->
groups such as 3-dimethylamino-2-hydroxypropoxy, hydroxy-substituted heterocyclyl- (l-6C)alkylamino groups such as 2-hydroxy-3-piperidinopropylamino and 2-hydroxy- 3-mo holinopropylamino, hydroxy-substituted amino-(2-6C)alkylamino groups such as 3-amino-2-hydroxypropylamino, hydroxy-substituted (l-6C)alkylamino-(2-6C)alkylamino groups such as 2-hydroxy-3-methylaminopropylamino, hydroxy-substituted di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino-(2-6C)alkylamino groups such as 3-dimethylamino- 2-hydroxypropylamino, hydroxy-substituted (l-6C)alkoxy groups such as 2-hydroxyethoxy, (l-6C)alkoxy-substituted (l-6C)alkoxy groups such as 2-methoxyethoxy and 3-ethoxypropoxy, (l-6C)alkylsulphonyl-substituted (l-6C)alkoxy groups such as 2-methylsulphonylethoxy and heterocyclyl-substituted (l-6C)alkylamino-(l-6C)alkyl groups such as 2-morpholinoethylaminomethyl, 2-piperazin-l-ylethylaminomethyl and 3-morpholinopropylaminomethyl.</p><p num="p0036">A suitable pharmaceutically-acceptable salt of a compound of the Formula I is, for example, an acid-addition salt of a compound of the Formula I, for example an acid-addition salt with an inorganic or organic acid such as hydrochloric, hydrobromic, sulphuric, trifluoroacetic, citric or maleic acid; or, for example, a salt of a compound of the Formula I which is sufficiently acidic, for example an alkali or alkaline earth metal salt such as a calcium or magnesium salt, or an ammonium salt, or a salt with an organic base such as methylamine, dimethylamine, trimethylamine, piperidine, morpholine or tris-(2-hydroxyethyl)amine.</p><p num="p0037">Particular novel compounds of the invention include, for example, quinazoline derivatives of the Formula I, or pharmaceutically-acceptable salts thereof, wherein, unless otherwise stated, each of m, R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup>, n and R<sup>3</sup> has any of the meanings defined hereinbefore or in paragraphs (a) to (h) hereinafter :- (a) m is 1 or 2, and each R<sup>1</sup> group, which may be the same or different, is selected from halogeno, trifluoromethyl, hydroxy, amino, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl, (l-6C)alkoxy, (l-6C)alkylamino, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, (2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-(2-6C)alkanoylamino, (3-6C)alkenoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl- (3-6C)alkenoylamino, (3-6C)alkynoylamino and N-(l-6C)alkyl-(3-6C)alkynoylamino, or from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0038">Q^X<sup>1</sup> - 
<!-- EPO <DP n="15"/>-->
wherein X<sup>1</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, N(R<sup>4</sup>), CON(R<sup>4</sup>), N(R<sup>4</sup>)CO and OC(R<sup>4</sup>)<sub>2</sub> wherein R<sup>4</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>1</sup> is aryl, aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, cycloalkyl- (l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl, heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl, and wherem adjacent carbon atoms in any (2-6C)alkylene chain within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent are optionally separated by the insertion into the chain of a group selected from O, N(R<sup>5</sup>), CON(R<sup>5</sup>), N(R<sup>5</sup>)CO, CH=CH and C≡C wherein R<sup>5</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, or, when the inserted group is N(R<sup>5</sup>), R<sup>5</sup> may also be (2-6C)alkanoyl, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub>=CH- or HC≡C- group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears at the terminal CH<sub>2</sub>= or HC≡ position a substituent selected from carbamoyl, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, amino-(l-6C)alkyl,</p><p num="p0039">(l-6C)alkylamino-(l-6C)alkyl and di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino-(l-6C)alkyl or from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0040">Q<sup>2</sup>-X<sup>2</sup>- wherein X<sup>2</sup> is a direct bond or is CO or N(R<sup>6</sup>)CO, wherein R<sup>6</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>2</sup> is heteroaryl, heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears on each said CH<sub>2</sub> or CH group a substituent selected from hydroxy, amino, (l-6C)alkoxy, (l-6C)alkylsulphonyl, (l-6C)alkylamino, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino, (2-6C)alkanoyloxy, (2-6C)alkanoylamino and N-(l-6C)alkyl-(2-6C)alkanoylamino, or from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0041">-X<sup>3</sup>-Q<sup>3</sup> wherein X<sup>3</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, N(R<sup>6</sup>), CON(R<sup>7</sup>), N(R<sup>7</sup>)CO and C(R<sup>7</sup>)<sub>2</sub>O, wherein R<sup>7</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>3</sup> is heteroaryl, heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl, and wherein any aryl, heteroaryl or heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1, 2 or 3 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from halogeno, trifluoromethyl, hydroxy, amino, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkoxy, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl and N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, or optionally bears 1 substituent selected from a group of the formula : -X<sup>4</sup>-R<sup>8</sup> wherein X<sup>4</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O and N(R<sup>9</sup>), wherein R<sup>9</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and R<sup>8</sup> is hydroxy-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkoxy-(l-6C)alkyl, cyano-(l-6C)alkyl, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="16"/>-->
amino-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkylamino-(l-6C)alkyl, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino-(l-6C)alkyl, (2-6C)alkanoylamino-(l-6C)alkyl or (l-6C)alkoxycarbonylamino-(l-6C)alkyl, and from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0042">-X<sup>5</sup>-Q<sup>4</sup> wherem X<sup>5</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, N(R<sup>10</sup>) and CO, wherein R<sup>10</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>4</sup> is heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl which optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from halogeno, (l-6C)alkyl and (l-6C)alkoxy, and wherein any heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo substituents;</p><p num="p0043">(b) m is 1 or 2, and each R<sup>1</sup> group, which may be the same or different, is selected from fluoro, chloro, trifluoromethyl, hydroxy, amino, carbamoyl, methyl, ethyl, propyl, butyl, vinyl, ethynyl, methoxy, ethoxy, propoxy, isopropoxy, butoxy, methylamino, ethylamino, propylamino, dimethylamino, diethylamino, dipropylamino, N-methylcarbamoyl, N,N-dimethylcarbamoyl, acetamido, propionamido, acrylamido and propiolamido, or from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0044">Q^X<sup>1</sup> - wherein X<sup>1</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, NH, CONH, NHCO and OCH<sub>2</sub> and Q<sup>1</sup> is phenyl, benzyl, cyclopropylmethyl, 2-thienyl, 1-imidazolyl, 1,2,3-triazol-l-yl, 1,2,4-triazol-l-yl, 2-, 3- or 4-pyridyl, 2-imidazol-l-ylethyl, 3-imidazol-l-ylpropyl, 2-(l,2,3-triazolyl)ethyl, 3-(l,2,3-triazolyl)proρyl, 2-(l,2,4-triazolyl)ethyl, 3-(l,2,4-triazolyl)propyl, 2-, 3- or 4-pyridylmethyl, 2-(2-, 3- or 4-pyridyl)ethyl, 3-(2-, 3- or 4-pyridyl)propyl, 1-, 2- or 3-pyrrolidinyl, morpholino, 1,1-dioxotetrahydro- 4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl, piperidino, piperidin-3-yl, piperidin-4-yl, 1-, 3- or 4-homopiperidinyl, piperazin-1-yl, homopiperazin-1-yl, 1-, 2- or 3-pyrrolidinylmethyl, morpholinomethyl, piperidinomethyl, 3- or 4-piperidinylmethyl, 1-, 3- or 4-homopiperidinylmethyl, 2-pyrrolidin-l-ylethyl, 3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropyl, pyrrolidin-2-ylmethyl, 2-pyrrolidin-2-ylethyl, 3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropyl, 4-pyrrolidin-l-ylbutyl, 2-morpholinoethyl, 3-morpholinopropyl, 4-morpholinobutyl, 2-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl)ethyl, 3-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro- 4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl)propyl, 2-piperidinoethyl, 3-piperidinopropyl, 4-piperidinobutyl,</p><p num="p0045">2-piperidin-3-ylethyl, 3-piperidin-3-ylpropyl, 2-piperidin-4-ylethyl, 3-piperidin-4-ylpropyl, 2-homopiperidin-l-ylethyl, 3-homopiperidin-l-ylpropyl, 2-piperazin-l-ylethyl, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="17"/>-->
3-piperazin-l-ylpropyl, 4-piperazin-l-ylbutyl, 2-homopiperazin-l-ylethyl or</p><p num="p0046">3 -homopiperazin- 1 -ylpropyl, and wherein adjacent carbon atoms in any (2-6C)alkylene chain within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent are optionally separated by the insertion into the chain of a group selected from O, NH, CONH, NHCO, CH=CH and C≡C, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub>=CH- or HC≡C- group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears at the terminal CH<sub>2</sub>= or HC≡ position a substituent selected from carbamoyl,</p><p num="p0047">N-methylcarbamoyl, N-ethylcarbamoyl, N-propylcarbamoyl, N,N-dimethylcarbamoyl, aminomethyl, 2-aminoethyl, 3-aminopropyl, 4-aminobutyl, methylaminomethyl, 2-methylaminoethyl, 3-methylaminopropyl, 4-methylaminobutyl, dimethylaminomethyl,</p><p num="p0048">2-dimethylaminoethyl, 3-dimethylaminopropyl or 4-dimethylaminobutyl, or from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0049">Q<sup>2</sup>-X<sup>2</sup>- wherein X<sup>2</sup> is a direct bond or is CO, NHCO or N(Me)CO and Q<sup>2</sup> is pyridyl, pyridylmethyl, 2-pyridylethyl, pyrrolidin-1-yl, pyrrolidin-2-yl, morpholino, piperidino, piperidin-3-yl, piperidin-4-yl, piperazin-1-yl, pyrrolidin-1-ylmethyl, 2-pyrrolidin-l-ylethyl,</p><p num="p0050">3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropyl, 4-pyrrolidin-l-ylbutyl, pyrrolidin-2-ylmethyl, 2-pyrrolidin-2-ylethyl,</p><p num="p0051">3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropyl, morpholinomethyl, 2-morpholinoethyl, 3-morpholinopropyl,</p><p num="p0052">4-morpholinobutyl, piperidinomethyl, 2-piperidinoethyl, 3-piperidinopropyl, 4-piperidinobutyl, piperidin-3-ylmethyl, 2-piperidin-3-ylethyl, piperidin-4-ylmethyl,</p><p num="p0053">2-piperidin-4-ylethyl, piperazin-1-ylmethyl, 2-piperazin-l-ylethyl, 3-piperazin-l-ylpropyl or</p><p num="p0054">4-piperazin-l-ylbutyl, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears on each said CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group a substituent selected from hydroxy, amino, methoxy, methylsulphonyl, methylamino, dimethylamino, diisopropylamino, N-ethyl-N-methylamino,</p><p num="p0055">N-isopropyl-N-methylamino, N-methyl-N-propylamino, acetoxy, acetamido and</p><p num="p0056">N-methylacetamido or from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0057">-X<sup>3</sup>-Q<sup>3</sup> wherein X<sup>3</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, NH, CONH, NHCO and CH<sub>2</sub>O and Q<sup>3</sup> is pyridyl, pyridylmethyl, pyrrolidin-1-yl, pyrrolidin-2-yl, morpholino, piperidino, piperidin-3-yl, piperidin-4-yl, piperazin-1-yl, 2-pyrrolidin-l-ylethyl, 3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropyl, pyrrolidin-</p><p num="p0058">2-ylmethyl, 2-pyrrolidin-2-ylethyl, 3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropyl, 2-morpholinoethyl, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="18"/>-->
3-morpholinopropyl, 2-piperidinoethyl, 3-piperidinopropyl, piperidin-3-ylmethyl, 2-piperidin- 3-ylethyl, piperidin-4-ylmethyl, 2-piperidin-4-ylethyl, 2-piperazin-l-ylethyl or 3-piperazin- 1-ylρropyl, and wherein any aryl, heteroaryl or heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1, 2 or 3 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from fluoro, chloro, trifluoromethyl, hydroxy, amino, carbamoyl, methyl, ethyl, methoxy, N-methylcarbamoyl and N,N-dimethylcarbamoyl, or optionally bears 1 substituent selected from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0059">-X<sup>4</sup>-R<sup>8</sup> wherein X<sup>4</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O and NH and R<sup>8</sup> is 2-hydroxyethyl, 3-hydroxypropyl, 2-methoxyethyl, 3-methoxypropyl, cyanomethyl, aminomethyl, 2-aminoethyl, 3-aminopropyl, methylaminomethyl, 2-methylaminoethyl, 3-methylaminopropyl, 2-ethylaminoethyl, 3-ethylaminopropyl, dimethylaminomethyl, 2-dimethylaminoethyl, 3-dimethylaminopropyl, acetamidomethyl, methoxycarbonylaminomethyl, ethoxycarbonylaminomethyl or tert-butoxycarbonvlaminomethyl, and from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0060">-X<sup>5</sup>-Q<sup>4</sup> wherein X<sup>5</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, NH and CO and Q<sup>4</sup> is pyrrolidin-1-ylmethyl, 2-pyrrolidin-l-ylethyl, 3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropyl, morpholinomethyl, 2-morpholinoethyl, 3-morpholinopropyl, piperidinomethyl, 2-piperidinoethyl,</p><p num="p0061">3-piperidinopropyl, piperazin-1-ylmethyl, 2-piperazin-l-ylethyl or 3-piperazin-l-ylpropyl, each of which optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from fluoro, chloro, methyl and methoxy, and wherein any heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo substituents;</p><p num="p0062">(c) m is 1 or 2 and each R<sup>1</sup> group, which may be the same or different, is located at the 6- and/or 7-positions and is selected from hydroxy, amino, methyl, ethyl, propyl, butyl, vinyl, ethynyl, methoxy, ethoxy, propoxy, isopropoxy, butoxy, methylamino, ethylamino, dimethylamino, diethylamino, acetamido, propionamido, cyclopentyloxy, cyclohexyloxy, phenoxy, benzyloxy, tetrahydrofuran-3-yloxy, tetrahydropyran-3-yloxy, tetrahydropyran-4-yloxy, cyclopropylmethoxy, 2-imidazol- 1 -ylethoxy, 3-imidazol-l-ylpropoxy, 2-(l,2,3-triazol-l-yl)ethoxy, 3-(l,2,3-triazol-l-yl)propoxy, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="19"/>-->
2-(l ,2,4-triazol- 1 -yl)ethoxy, 3-(l ,2,4-triazol- 1 -yl)propoxy, pyrid-2-ylmethoxy, pyrid-3-ylmethoxy, pyrid-4-ylmethoxy, 2-pyrid-2-ylethoxy, 2-pyrid-3-ylethoxy, 2-pyrid-4-ylethoxy, 3-pyrid-2-ylpropoxy, 3-pyrid-3-ylpropoxy, 3-pyrid-4-ylpropoxy, pyrrolidin-1-yl, morpholino, piperidino, piperazin-1-yl, 2-pyrrolidin- 1-ylethoxy, 3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy, 4-pyrrolidin-l-ylbutoxy, pyrrolidin-3 -yloxy, pyrrolidin-2-ylmethoxy, 2-pyrrolidin-2-ylethoxy, 3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropoxy, 2-morpholinoethoxy, 3-morpholinopropoxy, 4-morpholinobutoxy, 2-( 1 , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin-4-yl)ethoxy, 3-(l , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin-4- yl)propoxy, 2-piperidinoethoxy, 3-piperidinopropoxy, 4-piperidinobutoxy, piperidin-3-yloxy, piperidin-4-yloxy, piperidin-3-ylmethoxy, piperidin-4-ylmethoxy, 2-piperidin-3-ylethoxy, 3-piperidin-3-ylpropoxy, 2-piperidin-4-ylethoxy, 3-piperidin-4-ylpropoxy, 2-homoρiperidin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3 -homopiperidin- 1 -ylpropoxy, 2-piperazin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3-piperazin- 1 -ylpropoxy, 4-piperazin- 1 -ylbutoxy, 2-homopiperazin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3-homopiperazin- 1 -ylpropoxy, 2-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylethylamino, 3-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylpropylamino, 4-pyrrolidin-l-ylbutylamino, pyrrolidin-3 -ylamino, pyrrolidin-2-ylmethylamino, 2-pyrrolidin- 2-ylethylamino, 3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropylamino, 2-morpholinoethylamino, 3-morpholinopropylamino, 4-morpholinobutylamino, 2-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin- 4-yl)ethylamino, 3-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl)propylamino, 2-piperidinoethylamino, 3-piperidinopropylamino, 4-piperidinobutylamino, piperidin-3-ylamino, piperidin-4-ylamino, piperidin-3-ylmethylamino,</p><p num="p0063">2-piperidin-3-ylethylamino, piperidin-4-ylmethylamino, 2-piperidin-4-ylethylamino, 2-homopiρeridin-l-ylethylamino, 3-homopiperidin-l-ylpropylamino, 2-piperazin-l-ylethylamino, 3-piperazin- 1-ylpropylamino, 4-piperazin- 1-ylbutylamino, 2-homopiperazin- 1 -ylethylamino or 3-homopiperazin-l-ylpropylamino, and wherein adjacent carbon atoms in any (2-6C)alkylene chain within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent are optionally separated by the insertion into the chain of a group selected from O, NH, CH=CH and C≡C, and when R<sup>1</sup> is a vinyl or ethynyl group, the R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears at the terminal CH<sub>2</sub>= or HC≡ position a substituent selected from N-(2-dimethylaminoethyl)carbamoyl, N-(3-dimethylaminopropyl)carbamoyl, methylaminomethyl, 2-methylaminoethyl, 3-methylaminopropyl, 4-methylaminobutyl, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="20"/>-->
dimethylaminomethyl, 2-dimethylaminoethyl, 3-dimethylaminopropyl and 4-dimethylaminobutyl, or from a group of the formula :</p><p num="p0064">Q<sup>2</sup>-X<sup>2</sup>- wherein X<sup>2</sup> is a direct bond or is NHCO or N(Me)CO and Q<sup>2</sup> is imidazolylmethyl, 2-imidazolylethyl, 3-imidazolylpropyl, pyridylmethyl, 2-pyridylethyl, 3-pyridylpropyl, pyrrolidin-1-ylmethyl, 2-pyrrolidin-l-ylethyl, 3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropyl, 4-pyrrolidin-l-ylbutyl, pyrrolidin-2-ylmethyl, 2-pyrrolidin-2-ylethyl, 3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropyl, morpholinomethyl, 2-morpholinoethyl, 3-morpholinopropyl, 4-morpholinobutyl, piperidinomethyl, 2-piperidinoethyl, 3-piperidinopropyl, 4-piperidinobutyl, piperidin-3-ylmethyl, 2-piperidin-3-ylethyl, piperidin-4-ylmethyl, 2-piperidin-4-ylethyl, piperazin-1-ylmethyl, 2-piperazin-l-ylethyl, 3-piperazin-l-ylpropyl or 4-piperazin-l-ylbutyl, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears on each said CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group a substituent selected from hydroxy, amino, methoxy, methylsulphonyl, methylamino, dimethylamino, diisopropylamino, N-ethyl-N-methylamino, N-isopropyl-N-methylamino, N-methyl-N-propylamino, acetoxy, acetamido and N-methylacetamido, and wherein any phenyl, imidazolyl, triazolyl, pyridyl or heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from fluoro, chloro, trifluoromethyl, hydroxy, amino, carbamoyl, methyl, ethyl, N-methylcarbamoyl, N,N-dimethylcarbamoyl and methoxy, and a pyrrolidin-2-yl, piperidin-3-yl, piperidin-4-yl, piperazin-1-yl or homopiperazin-1-yl group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent is optionally N-substituted with 2-methoxyethyl, 3-methoxypropyl, cyanomethyl, 2-aminoethyl, 3-aminopropyl, 2-methylaminoethyl, 3-methylaminopropyl, 2-dimethylaminoethyl, 3-dimethylaminopropyl, 2-pyrrolidin-l-ylethyl, 3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropyl, 2-morpholinoethyl, 3-morpholinopropyl, 2-piperidinoethyl, 3-piperidinopropyl, 2-piperazin-l-ylethyl or 3-piperazin-l-ylpropyl, the last 8 of which substituents each optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from fluoro, chloro, methyl and methoxy, and wherem any heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo substituents;</p><p num="p0065">(d) m is 1 and the R<sup>1</sup> group is located at the 6- or 7-position and is selected from hydroxy, amino, methyl, ethyl, propyl, butyl, methoxy, ethoxy, propoxy, isopropoxy, butoxy, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="21"/>-->
methylamino, ethylamino, dimethylamino, diethylamino, acetamido, propionamido, benzyloxy, 2-imidazol-l -ylethoxy, 2-(l,2,3-triazol-l-yl)ethoxy, 2-(l,2,4-triazol-l-yl)ethoxy, 2-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylpropoxy, 4-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylbutoxy, pyrrolidin-3-yloxy, pyrrolidin-2-ylmethoxy, 2-pyrrolidin-2-ylethoxy, 3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropoxy, 2-morpholinoethoxy, 3-morpholinopropoxy, 4-morpholinobutoxy, 2-( 1 , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin-4-yl)ethoxy , 3 -( 1 , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin- 4-yl)propoxy, 2-piperidinoethoxy, 3-piperidinopropoxy, 4-piperidinobutoxy, piperidin-3-yloxy, piperidin-4-yloxy, piperidin-3-ylmethoxy, 2-piperidin-3-ylethoxy, piperidin-4-ylmethoxy, 2-piperidin-4-ylethoxy, 2-homopiperidin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3-homopiperidin-l -ylpropoxy, 2-piperazin-l -ylethoxy, 3 -piperazin-1 -ylpropoxy, 2-homopiperazih-l -ylethoxy or 3-homopiperazin-l -ylpropoxy, and wherein adjacent carbon atoms in any (2-6C)alkylene chain within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent are optionally separated by the insertion into the chain of a group selected from O, NH, CH=CH and C≡C, and wherein any CH or CH<sub>3</sub> group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears on each said CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group a substituent selected from hydroxy, amino, methoxy, methylsulphonyl, methylamino, dimethylamino, diisopropylamino, N-ethyl-N-methylamino, N-isopropyl-N-methylamino and acetoxy, and wherein any heteroaryl or heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from fluoro, chloro, trifluoromethyl, hydroxy, amino, methyl, ethyl and methoxy, and wherein any heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo substituents; (e) R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen; (f) n is 1 or 2 and the R groups, which may be the same or different, are located at the 5- and/or 6-positions of the benzofuran ring and are selected from halogeno, trifluoromethyl, cyano, hydroxy, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl and (l-6C)alkoxy; (g) n is 1 or 2 and the R groups, which may be the same or different, are located at the 5- and/or 6-positions of the benzofuran ring and are selected from fluoro, chloro, bromo, iodo, trifluoromethyl, cyano, hydroxy, methyl, ethyl, vinyl, allyl, isopropenyl, ethynyl, 1-propynyl, 2-propynyl, methoxy and ethoxy; and (h) n is 0. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="22"/>-->
 A preferred compound of the invention is a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I wherein : m is 1 or 2 and each R<sup>1</sup> group, which may be the same or different, is located at the 6- and/or 7-positions and is selected from hydroxy, amino, methyl, ethyl, propyl, butyl, methoxy, ethoxy, propoxy, isopropoxy, butoxy, methylamino, ethylamino, dimethylamino, diethylamino, acetamido, propionamido, 2-imidazol-l -ylethoxy, 2-(l,2,4-triazol-l-yl)ethoxy, 2-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylpropoxy, 4-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylbutoxy, pyrrolidin-3-yloxy, pyrrolidin-2-ylmethoxy, 2-pyrrolidin-2 -ylethoxy, 3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropoxy, 2-morpholinoethoxy, 3-morpholinopropoxy, 4-morpholinobutoxy, 2-( 1 , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin-4-yl)ethoxy, 3 -( 1 , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin- 4-yl)propoxy, 2-piperidinoethoxy, 3-piperidinopropoxy, 4-piperidinobutoxy, piperidin-3-yloxy, piperidin-4-yloxy, piperidin-3-ylmethoxy, piperidin-4-ylmethoxy, 2-piperidin-3 -ylethoxy, 3 -piperidin-3 -ylpropoxy, 2-piperidin-4-ylethoxy , 3-piperidin-4-ylpropoxy, 2-homopiperidin-l -ylethoxy, 3-homopiperidin-l-ylpropoxy, 2-piperazin-l -ylethoxy, 3-piperazin-l-ylpropoxy, 4-piperazin- 1 -ylbutoxy, 2-homopiperazin- 1 -ylethoxy and 3 -homopiperazin-1 -ylpropoxy, and wherein adjacent carbon atoms in any (2-6C)alkylene chain within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent are optionally separated by the insertion into the chain of a group selected from O, NH, CH=CH and C≡C, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears on each said CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group a substituent selected from hydroxy, amino, methoxy, methylsulphonyl, methylamino, dimethylamino, diethylamino, N-ethyl-N-methylamino, N-isopropyl-N-methylamino, N-methyl-N-propylamino and acetoxy; and wherein any heteroaryl or heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from fluoro, chloro, trifluoromethyl, hydroxy, amino, carbamoyl, methyl, ethyl, methoxy, N-methylcarbamoyl and N,N-dimethylcarbamoyl and a pyrrolidin-2-yl, piperidin-3-yl, piperidin-4-yl, piperazin-1-yl or homopiperazin-1 -yl group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent is optionally N-substituted with 2-methoxyethyl, 3-methoxypropyl, cyanomethyl, 2-aminoethyl, 3-aminopropyl, 2-methylaminoethyl, 3-methylaminopropyl, 2-dimethylaminoethyl,</p><p num="p0066">3-dimethylaminopropyl, 2-pyrrolidin-l-ylethyl, 3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropyl, 2-morpholinoethyl, 3-morpholinopropyl, 2-piperidinoethyl, 3-piperidinopropyl, 2-piperazin-l-ylethyl or 
<!-- EPO <DP n="23"/>-->
3-piperazin-l-ylpropyl, the last 8 of which substituents each optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from fluoro, chloro, methyl and methoxy, and wherein any heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo substituents;</p><p num="p0067">R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen; n is 0 or 1 and the R<sup>3</sup> group, if present, is located at the 5- or 6-position of the benzofuran ring and is selected from fluoro, chloro, trifluoromethyl, cyano, hydroxy, methyl, ethyl, vinyl, allyl, ethynyl, methoxy and ethoxy; or a pharmaceutically-acceptable acid-addition salt thereof.</p><p num="p0068">A further preferred compound of the invention is a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I wherein : m is 2 and the first R<sup>1</sup> group is located at the 6-position and is selected from hydroxy, methoxy, ethoxy and propoxy, and the second R<sup>1</sup> group is located at the 7-position and is selected from 2-dimethylaminoethoxy, 3-dimethylaminopropoxy, 4-dimethylaminobutoxy, 2-diethylaminoethoxy, 3-diethylaminopropoxy, 4-diethylaminobutoxy, 2-diisopropylaminoethoxy, 3-diisopropylaminopropoxy, 4-diisopropylaminobutoxy, 2-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)ethoxy, 3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy, 4-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)butoxy, 2-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3 -pyrrolidin- 1 -ylpropoxy, 4-pyrrolidin-l -ylbutoxy, pyrrolidin-3-yloxy, N-methylpyrrolidin-3-yloxy, pyrrolidin-2-ylmethoxy, 2-pyrrolidin-2-ylethoxy, 3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropoxy, 2-morpholinoethoxy, 3-morpholinopropoxy, 4-morpholinobutoxy,</p><p num="p0069">2-(l , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin-4-yl)ethoxy, 3-(l , l-dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin- 4-yl)propoxy, 2-piperidinoethoxy, 3-piperidinopropoxy, 4-piperidinobutoxy, piperidin-3-yloxy, N-methylpiperidin-3-yloxy, piperidin-4-yloxy, N-methylpiperidin-4-yloxy, piperidin-3 -ylmethoxy, N-methylpiperidin-3 -ylmethoxy , piperidin-4-ylmethoxy, N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy, 2-piperidin-3 -ylethoxy, 2-(N-methylpiperidin-3-yl)ethoxy, 3-piperidin-3-ylpropoxy, 3-(N-methylpiperidin-3-yl)propoxy, 2-piperidin-4-ylethoxy, 2-(N-methylpiperidin-4-yl)ethoxy, 3 -piperidin-4-ylpropoxy, 3-(N-methylpiperidin-4-yl)propoxy, 2-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)ethoxy, 3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy, 4-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)butoxy, 2-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin- 1 -yl)ethoxy, 3 -(4-cyanomethylpiperazin- 1 -yl)propoxy, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="24"/>-->
4-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin-l-yl)butoxy, 2-[2-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)ethoxy]ethoxy,</p><p num="p0070">2-methylsulphonylethoxy and 3-methylsulphonylpropoxy, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> group within the second R<sup>1</sup> group that is attached to two carbon atoms optionally bears a hydroxy group or acetoxy group on said CH<sub>2</sub> group, and wherein any heterocyclyl group within the second R<sup>1</sup> group optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo substituents;</p><p num="p0071">R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen; and n is 0 or n is 1 and the R<sup>3</sup> group is located at the 5- or 6-position of the benzofuran ring and is selected from fluoro, chloro, trifluoromethyl, cyano, methyl, ethyl, ethynyl, methoxy and ethoxy; or a pharmaceutically-acceptable acid-addition salt thereof.</p><p num="p0072">A further preferred compound of the invention is a quinazoline derivative of the</p><p num="p0073">Formula I wherein : m is 2 and the first R<sup>1</sup> group is located at the 6-position and is selected from hydroxy, methoxy, ethoxy and propoxy, and the second R<sup>1</sup> group is located at the 7-position and is selected from 2-dimethylaminoethoxy, 3-dimethylaminopropoxy, 2-diethylaminoethoxy,</p><p num="p0074">3-diethylaminopropoxy, 2-diisopropylaminoethoxy, 3-diisopropylaminopropoxy,</p><p num="p0075">2-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)ethoxy, 3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy,</p><p num="p0076">2-(N-isobutyl-N-methylamino)ethoxy, 3-(N-isobutyl-N-methylamino)propoxy, 2-(N-allyl-N-methylamino)ethoxy, 3-(N-allyl-N-methylamino)propoxy,</p><p num="p0077">2-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3 -pyrrolidin- 1 -ylpropoxy, 2-pyrrolidin-2-ylethoxy,</p><p num="p0078">3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropoxy, 2-morpholinoethoxy, 3-morpholinopropoxy,</p><p num="p0079">2-( 1 , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin-4-yl)ethoxy, 3 -( 1 , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin-</p><p num="p0080">4-yl)propoxy, 2-piperidinoethoxy, 3-piperidinopropoxy, piperidin-3 -ylmethoxy, N-methylρiperidin-3 -ylmethoxy, piperidin-4-ylmethoxy, N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy,</p><p num="p0081">2-piperidin-3 -ylethoxy, 2-(N-methylpiperidin-3-yl)ethoxy, 3-piperidin-3-ylpropoxy,</p><p num="p0082">3-(N-methylpiperidin-3-yl)propoxy, 2-piperidin-4-ylethoxy,</p><p num="p0083">2-(N-methylpiperidin-4-yl)ethoxy, 3 -piperidin-4-ylpropoxy ,</p><p num="p0084">3-(N-methylpiperidin-4-yl)propoxy, 3-homopiperidinopropoxy, 2-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)ethoxy, 3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy,</p><p num="p0085">2-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin-l-yl)ethoxy and 3-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="25"/>-->
 and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> group within the second R<sup>1</sup> group that is attached to two carbon atoms optionally bears a hydroxy group or acetoxy group on said CH<sub>2</sub> group,</p><p num="p0086">R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen; and n is 0 or n is 1 or 2 and an R<sup>3</sup> group, if present, is located at the 5- or 6-position of the benzofuran ring and is selected from fluoro, chloro, bromo, trifluoromethyl, cyano, methyl, ethyl, ethynyl, methoxy and ethoxy; or a pharmaceutically-acceptable acid-addition salt thereof.</p><p num="p0087">A further preferred compound of the invention is a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I wherein :</p><p num="p0088">1 1 m is 2 and the first R group is a 6-methoxy group and the second R group is located at the 7-position and is selected from 3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy, 3-(N-isobutyl-N-methylamino)propoxy, 3 -pyrrolidin-l -ylpropoxy, 3-morpholinopropoxy, 3-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl)propoxy, 3-piperidinopropoxy, piperidin-4-ylmethoxy, N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy, 3-homopiperidinopropoxy, 2-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)ethoxy,</p><p num="p0089">3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy and 3-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> group within the second R<sup>1</sup> group that is attached to two carbon atoms optionally bears a hydroxy or acetoxy group on said CH<sub>2</sub> group; R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen; and n is 0 or n is 1 and the R<sup>3</sup> group is located at the 5-position of the benzofuran ring and is selected from fluoro and chloro; or a pharmaceutically-acceptable acid-addition salt thereof. A further preferred compound of the invention is a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I wherein : m is 2 and the first R<sup>1</sup> group is a 6-methoxy group and the second R<sup>1</sup> group is located at the 7-position and is selected from 3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy, 3-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylpropoxy, 3 -morpholinopropoxy , 3 -( 1 , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin- 4-yl)propoxy, 3-piperidinopropoxy, N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy, 2-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)ethoxy, 3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy, 3-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy and 2-[2-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)ethoxy]ethoxy, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> group within the second R<sup>1</sup> group that is attached to two carbon atoms optionally bears a hydroxy group on said CH<sub>2</sub> group; 
<!-- EPO <DP n="26"/>-->
 R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen; and n is O; or a pharmaceutically-acceptable acid-addition salt thereof.</p><p num="p0090">A particular preferred compound of the invention is, for example, a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I selected from:-</p><p num="p0091">4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-6-methoxy-7-(3-morpholinopropoxy)quinazoline,</p><p num="p0092">4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7-[3-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl)propoxy]-</p><p num="p0093">6-methoxyquinazoline,</p><p num="p0094">4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-6-methoxy-7-(3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)quinazoline, 4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-6-methoxy-7-[3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]quinazoline,</p><p num="p0095">4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-6-methoxy-7-(3-piperidinopropoxy)quinazoline,</p><p num="p0096">4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-6-methoxy-7-(N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy)quinazoline,</p><p num="p0097">4-(5-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylamino)-6-methoxy-7-(3-morpholinopropoxy)quinazoline,</p><p num="p0098">7-(2-acetoxy-3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)-4-(3-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylamino)- 6-methoxyquinazoline,</p> <p num="p0099">7-[2-acetoxy-3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy]-4-(3-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylarnino)-</p><p num="p0100">6-methoxyquinazoline,</p><p num="p0101">7-[2-acetoxy-3-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]-4-(3-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylamino)-</p><p num="p0102">6-methoxyquinazoline, 7-(2-acetoxy-3-piperidinopropoxy)-4-(3-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylamino)-6-methoxyquinazoline,</p><p num="p0103">7-(2-acetoxy-3-morpholinopropoxy)-4-(3-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylamino)-</p> <p num="p0104">6-methoxyquinazoline,</p> <p num="p0105">4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7-(2-hydroxy-3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)-6-methoxyquinazoline,</p> <p num="p0106">4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7-[2-hydroxy-3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy]- 6-methoxyquinazoline,</p><p num="p0107">4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7- [3 -(4-cyanomethylpiperazin- 1 -yl)-2-hydroxypropoxy] -</p><p num="p0108">6-methoxyquinazoline,</p><p num="p0109">4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7-(2-hydroxy-3-piperidinopropoxy)-6-methoxyquinazoline and</p><p num="p0110">4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7-(2-hydroxy-3-morpholinopropoxy)-6-methoxyquinazoline; or a pharmaceutically-acceptable acid-addition salt thereof.</p><p num="p0111">A quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, may be prepared by any process known to be applicable to the preparation of 
<!-- EPO <DP n="27"/>-->
chemically-related compounds. Such processes, when used to prepare a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I are provided as a further feature of the invention and are illustrated</p><p num="p0112">1 by the following representative process variants in which, unless otherwise stated, m, R , R , n and R<sup>3</sup> have any of the meanings defined hereinbefore. Necessary starting materials may be obtained by standard procedures of organic chemistry. The preparation of such starting materials is described in conjunction with the following representative process variants and within the accompanying Examples. Alternatively necessary starting materials are obtainable by analogous procedures to those illustrated which are within the ordinary skill of an organic chemist. (a) The reaction of a quinazoline of the Formula π</p><p num="p0113"><img id="imgf000027_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="49" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000027_0001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/></p><p num="p0114">II wherein L is a displaceable group and m and R<sup>1</sup> have any of the meanings defined hereinbefore except that any functional group is protected if necessary, with an aniline of the</p><p num="p0115">Formula DI</p><p num="p0116"><img id="imgf000027_0002" orientation="portrait" wi="62" img-format="tif"  img-content="drawing" file="imgf000027_0002.tif" inline="no" he="24"/></p><p num="p0117">9 " wherein R , n and R have any of the meanings defined hereinbefore except that any functional group is protected if necessary, whereafter any protecting group that is present is removed by conventional means.</p><p num="p0118">The reaction may conveniently be carried out in the presence of a suitable acid or in the presence of a suitable base. A suitable acid is, for example, an inorganic acid such as, for example, hydrogen chloride or hydrogen bromide. A suitable base is, for example, an organic amine base such as, for example, pyridine, 2,6-lutidine, collidine, 4-dimethylaminopyridine, triethylamine, morpholine, N-methylmorpholine or diazabicyclo[5.4.0]undec-7-ene, or, for example, an alkali or alkaline earth metal carbonate or hydroxide, for example sodium carbonate, potassium carbonate, calcium carbonate, sodium hydroxide or potassium hydroxide, or, for example, an alkali metal hydride, for example sodium hydride , or, for 
<!-- EPO <DP n="28"/>-->
example, an alkali metal amide, for example sodium amide or sodium 1 , 1 , 1 ,3 ,3 ,3-hexamethyldisilazidehydride.</p><p num="p0119">A suitable displaceable group L is, for example, a halogeno, alkoxy, aryloxy or sulphonyloxy group, for example a chloro, bromo, methoxy, phenoxy, pentafluorophenoxy, methanesulphonyloxy or toluene-4-sulphonyloxy group. The reaction is conveniently carried out in the presence of a suitable inert solvent or diluent, for example an alcohol or ester such as methanol, ethanol, isopropanol or ethyl acetate, a halogenated solvent such as methylene chloride, chloroform or carbon tetrachloride, an ether such as tetrahydrofuran or 1,4-dioxan, an aromatic solvent such as toluene, or a dipolar aprotic solvent such as N,N-dimethylformamide, N,N-dimethylacetamide, N-methylpyrrolidin-2-one or dimethylsulphoxide. The reaction is conveniently carried out at a temperature in the range, for example, 10 to 250°C, preferably in the range 40 to 120°C.</p><p num="p0120">Typically, the quinazoline of the Formula II may be reacted with an aniline of the Formula HI in the presence of a protic solvent such as isopropanol, conveniently in the presence of an acid, for example hydrogen chloride gas in diethyl ether, and at a temperature in the range , for example, 25 to 150°C, preferably at or near the reflux temperature of the reaction solvent.</p><p num="p0121">The quinazoline derivative of the Formula I may be obtained from this process in the form of the free base or alternatively it may be obtained in the form of a salt with the acid of the formula H-L wherein L has the meaning defined hereinbefore. When it is desired to obtain the free base from the salt, the salt may be treated with a suitable base, for example, an organic amine base such as, for example, pyridine, 2,6-lutidine, collidine, 4-dimethylaminopyridine, triethylamine, morpholine, N-methylmorpholine or diazabicyclo[5.4.0]undec-7-ene, or, for example, an alkali or alkaline earth metal carbonate or hydroxide, for example sodium carbonate, potassium carbonate, calcium carbonate, sodium hydroxide or potassium hydroxide.</p><p num="p0122">Protecting groups may in general be chosen from any of the groups described in the literature or known to the skilled chemist as appropriate for the protection of the group in question and may be introduced by conventional methods. Protecting groups may be removed by any convenient method as described in the literature or known to the skilled chemist as appropriate for the removal of the protecting group in question, such methods being chosen so 
<!-- EPO <DP n="29"/>-->
as to effect removal of the protecting group with minimum disturbance of groups elsewhere in the molecule.</p><p num="p0123">Specific examples of protecting groups are given below for the sake of convenience, in which "lower", as in, for example, lower alkyl, signifies that the group to which it is applied preferably has 1-4 carbon atoms. It will be understood that these examples are not exhaustive. Where specific examples of methods for the removal of protecting groups are given below these are similarly not exhaustive. The use of protecting groups and methods of deprotection not specifically mentioned are, of course, within the scope of the invention.</p><p num="p0124">A carboxy protecting group may be the residue of an ester-forming aliphatic or arylaliphatic alcohol or of an ester-forming silanol (the said alcohol or silanol preferably containing 1-20 carbon atoms). Examples of carboxy protecting groups include straight or branched chain (l-12C)alkyl groups (for example isopropyl, and tert-butyl); lower alkoxy- lower alkyl groups (for example methoxymethyl, ethoxymethyl and isobutoxymethyl); lower acyloxy-lower alkyl groups, (for example acetoxymethyl, propionyloxymethyl, butyryloxymethyl and pivaloyloxymethyl); lower alkoxycarbonyloxy-lower alkyl groups (for example 1-methoxycarbonyloxyethyl and 1-ethoxycarbonyloxyethyl); aryl-lower alkyl groups (for example benzyl, 4-methoxybenzyl, 2-nitrobenzyl, 4-nitrobenzyl, benzhydryl and phthalidyl); tri(lower alkyl)silyl groups (for example trimethylsilyl and tert-butyldimethylsilyl); tri(lower alkyl)silyl-lower alkyl groups (for example trimethylsilylethyl); and (2-6C)alkenyl groups (for example allyl). Methods particularly appropriate for the removal of carboxyl protecting groups include for example acid-, base-, metal- or enzymically-catalysed cleavage.</p><p num="p0125">Examples of hydroxy protecting groups include lower alkyl groups (for example tert-butyl), lower alkenyl groups (for example allyl); lower alkanoyl groups (for example acetyl); lower alkoxycarbonyl groups (for example tert-butoxycarbonyl); lower alkenyloxycarbonyl groups (for example allyloxycarbonyl); aryl-lower alkoxycarbonyl groups (for example benzyloxycarbonyl, 4-methoxybenzyloxycarbonyl, 2-nitrobenzyloxycarbonyl and 4-nitrobenzyloxycarbonyl); tri(lower alkyl)silyl (for example trimethylsilyl and tert-butyldimethylsilyl) and aryl-lower alkyl (for example benzyl) groups. Examples of amino protecting groups include formyl, aryl-lower alkyl groups (for example benzyl and substituted benzyl, 4-methoxybenzyl, 2r-nitrobenzyl and 2,4-dimethoxybenzyl, and triphenylmethyl); di-4-anisylmethyl and furylmethyl groups; lower 
<!-- EPO <DP n="30"/>-->
alkoxycarbonyl (for example tert-butoxycarbonyl); lower alkenyloxycarbonyl (for example allyloxycarbonyl); aryl-lower alkoxycarbonyl groups (for example benzyloxycarbonyl, 4-methoxybenzyloxycarbonyl, 2-nitrobenzyloxycarbonyl and 4-nitrobenzyloxycarbonyl); trialkylsilyl (for example trimethylsilyl and tert-butyldimethylsilyl) ; alkylidene (for example methylidene) and benzylidene and substituted benzylidene groups.</p><p num="p0126">Methods appropriate for removal of hydroxy and amino protecting groups include, for example, acid-, base-, metal- or enzymically-catalysed hydrolysis for groups such as 2-nitrobenzyloxycarbonyl, hydrogenation for groups such as benzyl and photolytically for groups such as 2-nitrobenzyloxycarbonyl. The reader is referred to Advanced Organic Chemistry, 4th Edition, by J. March, published by John Wiley &amp; Sons 1992, for general guidance on reaction conditions and reagents and to Protective Groups in Organic Synthesis, 2<sup>nd</sup> Edition, by T. Green et al, also published by John Wiley &amp; Son, for general guidance on protecting groups.</p><p num="p0127">Quinazoline starting materials of the Formula U may be obtained by conventional procedures. For example, a 3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one of Formula IN</p><p num="p0128"><img id="imgf000030_0001" orientation="portrait"  wi="52"  img-format="tif"  img-content="drawing" file="imgf000030_0001.tif" inline="no" he="26"/></p><p num="p0129">IV wherein m and R<sup>1</sup> have any of the meanings defined hereinbefore except that any functional group is protected if necessary, may be reacted with a halogenating agent such as thionyl chloride, phosphoryl chloride or a mixture of carbon tetrachloride and triphenylphosphine whereafter any protecting group that is present is removed by conventional means. The 4-chloroquinazoline so obtained may be converted, if required, into a 4-pentafluorophenoxyquinazoline by reaction with pentafluorophenol in the presence of a suitable base such as potassium carbonate and in the presence of a suitable solvent such as N,N-dimethylformamide. 4-Aminobenzofuran starting materials of the Formula IE may be obtained by conventional procedures as illustrated in the Examples.</p><p num="p0130">(b) For the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein at least one R<sup>1</sup> group is a group of the formula 
<!-- EPO <DP n="31"/>-->
wherein Q<sup>1</sup> is an aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkyl-(l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkenyl- (l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl group and X<sup>1</sup> is an oxygen atom, the coupling, conveniently in the presence of a suitable dehydrating agent, of a quinazoline of the Formula N</p><p num="p0131"><img id="imgf000031_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="74" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000031_0001.tif" inline="no" he="40"/></p><p num="p0132">V wherein m, R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup>, n and R<sup>3</sup> have any of the meanings defined hereinbefore except that any functional group is protected if necessary, with an appropriate alcohol wherein any functional group is protected if necessary whereafter any protecting group that is present is removed by conventional means.</p><p num="p0133">A suitable dehydrating agent is, for example, a carbodiimide reagent such as dicyclohexylcarbodiimide or l-(3-dimethylaminopropyl)-3-ethylcarbodiimide or a mixture of an azo compound such as diethyl or di-tert-butyl azodicarboxylate and a phosphine such as triphenylphosphine. The reaction is conveniently carried out in the presence of a suitable inert solvent or diluent, for example a halogenated solvent such as methylene chloride, chloroform or carbon tetrachloride and at a temperature in the range, for example, 10 to 150°C, preferably at or near ambient temperature.</p><p num="p0134">The reaction is conveniently carried out in the presence of a suitable inert solvent or diluent, for example a halogenated solvent such as methylene chloride, chloroform or carbon tetrachloride and at a temperature in the range, for example, 10 to 150°C, preferably at or near ambient temperature.</p><p num="p0135">(c) For the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein an R<sup>1</sup> group contains a primary or secondary amino group, the cleavage of the corresponding compound of the Formula I wherein the R<sup>1</sup> group contains a protected primary or secondary amino group. Suitable protecting groups for an amino group are, for example, any of the protecting groups disclosed hereinbefore for an amino group. Suitable methods for the cleavage of such 
<!-- EPO <DP n="32"/>-->
amino protecting groups are also disclosed hereinbefore. In particular, a suitable protecting group is a lower alkoxycarbonyl group such as a tert-butoxycarbonyl group which may be cleaved under conventional reaction conditions such as under acid-catalysed hydrolysis, for example in the presence of trifluoroacetic acid. (d) For the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein an R<sup>1</sup> group contains a (l-6C)alkoxy or substituted (l-6C)alkoxy group or a (l-6C)alkylamino or substituted (l-6C)alkylamino group, the alkylation, conveniently in the presence of a suitable base as defined hereinbefore, of a quinazoline derivative of the formula I wherein the R<sup>1</sup> group contains a hydroxy group or a primary or secondary amino group as appropriate. A suitable alkylating agent is, for example, any agent known in the art for the alkylation of hydroxy to alkoxy or substituted alkoxy, or for the alkylation of amino to alkylamino or substituted alkylamino, for example an alkyl or substituted alkyl halide, for example a (l-6C)alkyl chloride, bromide or iodide or a substituted (l-6C)alkyl chloride, bromide or iodide, conveniently in the presence of a suitable base as defined hereinbefore, in a suitable inert solvent or diluent as defined hereinbefore and at a temperature in the range, for example, 10 to 140°C, conveniently at or near ambient temperature.</p><p num="p0136">Conveniently for the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein R<sup>1</sup> contains a (l-6C)alkylamino or substituted (l-6C)alkylamino group, a reductive amination reaction may be employed. For example, for the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein R<sup>1</sup> contains a N-methyl group, the corresponding compound containing a N-H group may be reacted with formaldehyde in the presence of a suitable reducing agent. A suitable reducing agent is, for example, a hydride reducing agent, for example an alkali metal aluminium hydride such as lithium aluminium hydride or, preferably, an alkali metal borohydride such as sodium borohydride, sodium cyanoborohydri.de, sodium triethylborohydride, sodium trimethoxyborohydride and sodium triacetoxyborohydride. The reaction is conveniently performed in a suitable inert solvent or diluent, for example tetrahydrofuran and diethyl ether for the more powerful reducing agents such as lithium aluminium hydride, and, for example, methylene chloride or a protic solvent such as methanol and ethanol for the less powerful reducing agents such as sodium triacetoxyborohydride and sodium cyanoborohydride. The reaction is performed at a temperature in the range, for example, 10 to 80°C, conveniently at or near ambient temperature, (e) For the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein R<sup>1</sup> is an 
<!-- EPO <DP n="33"/>-->
amino-hydroxy-disubstituted (l-6C)alkoxy group (such as 2-hydroxy-3-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylpropoxy or 3-[N-allyl-N-methylamino]-2-hydroxypropoxy), the reaction of a compound of the Formula I wherein the R<sup>1</sup> group contains an epoxy-substituted (l-6C)alkoxy group with a heterocyclyl compound or an appropriate amine. The reaction is conveniently carried out in the presence of a suitable inert diluent or carrier as defined hereinbefore and at a temperature in the range 10 to 150°C, preferably at or near ambient temperature.</p><p num="p0137">(f) For the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein an R<sup>1</sup> group contains a hydroxy group, the cleavage of the corresponding compound of the Formula I wherein the R<sup>1</sup> group contains a protected hydroxy group.</p><p num="p0138">Suitable protecting groups for a hydroxy group are, for example, any of the protecting groups disclosed hereinbefore. Suitable methods for the cleavage of such hydroxy protecting groups are also disclosed hereinbefore. In particular, a suitable protecting group is a lower alkanoyl group such as an acetyl group which may be cleaved under conventional reaction conditions such as under base-catalysed conditions, for example in the presence of ammonia. When a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt of a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I is required, for example an acid-addition salt, it may be obtained by, for example, reaction of said quinazoline derivative with a suitable acid using a conventional procedure.</p><p num="p0139">Biological Assays</p><p num="p0140">The following assays can be used to measure the effects of the compounds of the present invention as c-Src tyrosine kinase inhibitors, as inhibitors in vitro of the proliferation of c-Src transfected fibroblast cells, as inhibitors in vitro of the migration of A549 human lung tumour cells and as inhibitors in vivo of the growth in nude mice of xenografts of A549 tissue.</p><p num="p0141">(a) In Vitro Enzyme Assay</p><p num="p0142">The ability of test compounds to inhibit the phosphorylation of a tyrosine containing polypeptide substrate by the enzyme c-Src kinase was assessed using a conventional Elisa assay. A substrate solution [lOOμl of a 20μg ml solution of the polyamino acid</p><p num="p0143">Poly(Glu, Tyr) 4:1 (Sigma Catalogue No. P0275) in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) containing 0.2mg/ml of sodium azide] was added to each well of a number of Nunc 96-well 
<!-- EPO <DP n="34"/>-->
immunoplates (Catalogue No. 439454) and the plates were sealed and stored at 4°C for 16 hours. The excess of substrate solution was discarded, and aliquots of Bovine Serum Albumin (BSA; 150μl of a 5% solution in PBS) were transferred into each substrate-coated assay well and incubated for 1 hour at ambient temperature to block non specific binding. The assay plate wells were washed in turn with PBS containing 0.05% v/v Tween 20 (PBST) and with Hepes pH7.4 buffer (50mM, 300μl/well) before being blotted dry.</p><p num="p0144">Each test compound was dissolved in dimethyl sulphoxide and diluted with distilled water to give a series of dilutions (from lOOμM to O.OOlμM). Portions (25μl) of each dilution of test compound were transferred to wells in the washed assay plates. "Total" control wells contained diluted DMSO instead of compound. Aliquots (25 μl) of an aqueous magnesium chloride solution (80mM) containing adenosine-5'-triphosphate (ATP; 40μM) was added to all test wells except the "blank" control wells which contained magnesium chloride without ATP.</p><p num="p0145">Active human c-Src kinase (recombinant enzyme expressed in Sf9 insect cells; obtained from Upstate Biotechnology Inc. product 14-117) was diluted immediately prior to use by a factor of 1: 10,000 with an enzyme diluent which comprised lOOmM Hepes pH7.4 buffer, 0.2mM sodium orthovanadate, 2mM dithiothreitol and 0.02% BSA. To start the reactions, aliquots (50μl) of freshly diluted enzyme were added to each well and the plates were incubated at ambient temperature for 20 minutes. The supernatant liquid in each well was discarded and the wells were washed twice with PBST. Mouse IgG anti-phosphotyrosine antibody (Upstate Biotechnology Inc. product 05-321; lOOμl) was diluted by a factor of 1:6000 with PBST containing 0.5% w/v BSA and added to each well. The plates were incubated for 1 hour at ambient temperature. The supernatant liquid was discarded and each well was washed with PBST (x4). Horse radish peroxidase (HRP)-linked sheep anti-mouse Ig antibody (Amersham Catalogue No. NXA 931 ; lOOμl) was diluted by a factor of 1 :500 with PBST containing 0.5% w/v BSA and added to each well. The plates were incubated for 1 hour at ambient temperature. The supernatant liquid was discarded and the wells were washed with PBST (x4).</p><p num="p0146">A PCSB capsule (Sigma Catalogue No. P4922) was dissolved in distilled water (100ml) to provide phosphate-citrate pH5 buffer (50mM) containing 0.03% sodium perborate. An aliquot (50ml) of this buffer was mixed with a 50mg tablet of 2,2'-azinobis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulphonic acid) (ABTS; Boehringer Catalogue 
<!-- EPO <DP n="35"/>-->
No. 1204 521). Aliquots (lOOμl) of the resultant solution were added to each well. The plates were incubated for 20 to 60 minutes at ambient temperature until the optical density value of the "total" control wells, measured at 405nm using a plate reading spectrophotometer, was approximately 1.0. "Blank" (no ATP) and "total" (no compound) control values were used to determine the dilution range of test compound which gave 50% inhibition of enzyme activity, (b) In Vitro c-Src transfected NTH 3T3 (c-src 3T3 Fibroblast Proliferation Assay</p><p num="p0147">This assay determined the ability of a test compound to inhibit the proliferation of National Institute of Health (NIH) mouse 3T3 fibroblast cells that had been stably-transfected with an activating mutant (Y530F) of human c-Src. Using a similar procedure to that described by Shalloway et al, Cell, 1987, 49, 65-73,</p><p num="p0148">NIH 3T3 cells were transfected with an activating mutant (Y530F) of human c-Src. The resultant c-Src 3T3 cells were typically seeded at 1.5 x 10<sup>4</sup> cells per well into 96-well tissue- culture-treated clear assay plates (Costar) each containing an assay medium comprising Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM; Sigma) plus 0.5% foetal calf serum (FCS), 2mM glutamine, 100 units/ml penicillin and O.lmg/ml streptomycin in 0.9% aqueous sodium chloride solution. The plates were incubated overnight at 37°Cin a humidified (7.5% CO<sub>2</sub> : 95%o air) incubator.</p><p num="p0149">Test compounds were solubilised in DMSO to form a lOmM stock solution. Aliquots of the stock solution were diluted with the DMEM medium described above and added to appropriate wells. Serial dilutions were made to give a range of test concentrations. Control wells to which test compound was not added were included on each plate. The plates were incubated overnight at 37°Cin a humidified (7.5% CO<sub>2</sub> : 95% air) incubator.</p><p num="p0150">BrdU labelling reagent (Boehringer Mannheim Catalogue No. 647 229) was diluted by a factor of 1: 100 in DMEM medium containing 0.5% FCS and aliquots (20μl) were added to each well to give a final concentration of lOμM). The plates were incubated at 37°C for 2 hours. The medium was decanted. A denaturating solution (FixDenat solution, Boehringer Mannheim Catalogue No. 647 229; 50μl) was added to each well and the plates were placed on a plate shaker at ambient temperature for 45 minutes. The supernatant was decanted and the wells were washed with PBS (200μl per well). Anti-BrdU-Peroxidase solution (Boehringer Mannheim Catalogue No. 647 229) was diluted by a factor of 1 : 100 in PBS containing 1% BSA and 0.025% dried skimmed milk (Marvel (registered trade mark), Premier Beverages, Stafford, GB) and an aliquot (lOOμl) of the resultant solution was added to each 
<!-- EPO <DP n="36"/>-->
well. The plates were placed on a plate shaker at ambient temperature for 90 minutes. The wells were washed with PBS (x5) to ensure removal of non bound antibody conjugate. The plates were blotted dry and tetramethylbenzidine substrate solution (Boehringer Mannheim Catalogue No. 647 229; lOOμl) was added to each well. The plates were gently agitated on a plate shaker while the colour developed during a 10 to 20 minute period. The absorbance of the wells was measured at 690nm. The extent of inhibition of cellular proliferation at a range of concentrations of each test compound was determined and an anti-proliferative IC<sub>50</sub> value was derived, (c) In Vitro Microdroplet Migration Assay This assay determines the ability of a test compound to inhibit the migration of adherent mammalian cell lines, for example the human tumour cell line A549.</p><p num="p0151">RPMI medium(Sigma) containing 10% FCS, 1% L-glutamine and 0.3% agarose (Difco Catalogue No. 0142-01) was warmed to 37°C in a water bath. A stock 2% aqueous agar solution was autoclaved and stored at 42°C. An aliquot (1.5 ml) of the agar solution was added to RPMI medium (10 ml) immediately prior to its use. A549 cells (Accession No. ATCC CCL185) were suspended at a concentration of 2 x 10<sup>7</sup> cells/ml in the medium and maintained at a temperature of 37°C.</p><p num="p0152">A droplet (2μl) of the cell/agarose mixture was transferred by pipette into the centre of each well of a number of 96-well, flat bottomed non-tissue-culture-treated microtitre plate (Bibby Sterilin Catalogue No. 642000). The plates were placed briefly on ice to speed the gelling of the agarose-containing droplets. Aliquots (90μl) of medium which had been cooled to 4°C were transferred into each well, taking care not to disturb the microdroplets. Test compounds were diluted from a lOmM stock solution in DMSO using RPMI medium as described above. Aliquots (lOμl) of the diluted test compounds were transferred to the wells, again taking care not to disturb the microdroplets. The plates were incubated at 37°C in a humidified (7.5% CO<sub>2</sub> : 95% air) incubator for about 48 hours.</p><p num="p0153">Migration was assessed visually and the distance of migration was measured back to the edge of the agar droplet. A migratory inhibitory IC<sub>50</sub> was derived by plotting the mean migration measurement against test compound concentration. (d) In Vivo A549 Xenograft Growth Assay</p><p num="p0154">This test measures the ability of compounds to inhibit the growth of the A549 human carcinoma grown as a tumour in athymic nude mice (Alderley Park nu/nu strain). A total of 
<!-- EPO <DP n="37"/>-->
about 5 x 10<sup>6</sup> A549 cells in matrigel (Beckton Dickinson Catalogue No. 40234) were injected subcutaneously into the left flank of each test mouse and the resultant tumours were allowed to grow for about 14 days. Tumour size was measured twice weekly using callipers and a theoretical volume was calculated. Animals were selected to provide control and treatment groups of approximately equal average tumour volume. Test compounds were prepared as a ball-milled suspension in 1% polysorbate vehicle and dosed orally once daily for a period of about 28 days. The effect on tumour growth was assessed.</p><p num="p0155">Although the pharmacological properties of the compounds of the Formula I vary with structural change as expected, in general activity possessed by compounds of the Formula I, may be demonstrated at the following concentrations or doses in one or more of the above tests (a), (b), (c) and (d):-</p><p num="p0156">Test (a):- IC<sub>50</sub> in the range, for example, 0.001 - 10 μM;</p><p num="p0157">Test (b):- IC<sub>50</sub> in the range, for example, 0.01 - 20 μM;</p><p num="p0158">Test (c):- activity in the range, for example, 0.1-25 μM; Test (d):- activity in the range, for example, 1-200 mg/kg/day;.</p><p num="p0159">No physiologically-unacceptable toxicity was observed in Test (d) at the effective dose for compounds tested of the present invention. Accordingly no untoward toxicological effects are expected when a compound of Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined hereinbefore is administered at the dosage ranges defined hereinafter. According to a further aspect of the invention there is provided a pharmaceutical composition which comprises a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined hereinbefore in association with a pharmaceutically-acceptable diluent or carrier.</p><p num="p0160">The compositions of the invention may be in a form suitable for oral use (for example as tablets, lozenges, hard or soft capsules, aqueous or oily suspensions, emulsions, dispersible powders or granules, syrups or elixirs), for topical use (for example as creams, ointments, gels, or aqueous or oily solutions or suspensions), for administration by inhalation (for example as a finely divided powder or a liquid aerosol), for administration by insufflation (for example as a finely divided powder) or for parenteral administration (for example as a sterile aqueous or oily solution for intravenous, subcutaneous, intramuscular or intramuscular dosing or as a suppository for rectal dosing).</p><p num="p0161">The compositions of the invention may be obtained by conventional procedures using 
<!-- EPO <DP n="38"/>-->
conventional pharmaceutical excipients, well known in the art. Thus, compositions intended for oral use may contain, for example, one or more colouring, sweetening, flavouring and/or preservative agents.</p><p num="p0162">The amount of active ingredient that is combined with one or more excipients to produce a single dosage form will necessarily vary depending upon the host treated and the particular route of administration. For example, a formulation intended for oral administration to humans will generally contain, for example, from 0.5 mg to 0.5 g of active agent (more suitably from 0.5 to 100 mg, for example from 1 to 30 mg) compounded with an appropriate and convenient amount of excipients which may vary from about 5 to about 98 percent by weight of the total composition.</p><p num="p0163">The size of the dose for therapeutic or prophylactic purposes of a compound of the Formula I will naturally vary according to the nature and severity of the conditions, the age and sex of the animal or patient and the route of administration, according to well known principles of medicine. In using a compound of the Formula I for therapeutic or prophylactic purposes it will generally be administered so that a daily dose in the range, for example, 0.1 mg/kg to 75 mg/kg body weight is received, given if required in divided doses. In general lower doses will be administered when a parenteral route is employed. Thus, for example, for intravenous administration, a dose in the range, for example, 0.1 mg/kg to 30 mg/kg body weight will generally be used. Similarly, for administration by inhalation, a dose in the range, for example, 0.05 mg/kg to 25 mg/kg body weight will be used. Oral administration is however preferred, particularly in tablet form. Typically, unit dosage forms will contain about 0.5 mg to 0.5 g of a compound of this invention.</p><p num="p0164">According to a further aspect of the invention there is provided a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined hereinbefore for use in a method of treatment of the human or animal body by therapy.</p><p num="p0165">As stated above, it is known that the predominant role of c-Src non-receptor tyrosine kinase is to regulate cell motility which is necessarily required for a localised tumour to progress through the stages of dissemination into the blood stream, invasion of other tissues and initiation of metastatic tumour growth. We have found that the quinazoline derivatives of the present invention possess potent anti-tumour activity which it is believed is obtained by way of inhibition of one or more of the non-receptor tyrosine-specific protein kinases such as 
<!-- EPO <DP n="39"/>-->
c-Src kinase that are involved in the signal transduction steps which lead to the invasiveness and migratory ability of metastasising tumour cells.</p><p num="p0166">Accordingly the quinazoline derivatives of the present invention are of value as anti- tumour agents, in particular as selective inhibitors of the motility, dissemination and invasiveness of mammalian cancer cells leading to inhibition of metastatic tumour growth. Particularly, the quinazoline derivatives of the present invention are of value as anti-invasive agents in the containment and/or treatment of solid tumour disease. Particularly, the compounds of the present invention are expected to be useful in the prevention or treatment of those tumours which are sensitive to inhibition of one or more of the multiple non-receptor tyrosine kinases such as c-Src kinase that are involved in the signal transduction steps which lead to the invasiveness and migratory ability of metastasising tumour cells. Further, the compounds of the present invention are expected to be useful in the prevention or treatment of those tumours which are mediated alone or in part by inhibition of the enzyme c-Src, i.e. the compounds may be used to produce a c-Src enzyme inhibitory effect in a warm-blooded animal in need of such treatment. Specifically, the compounds of the present invention are expected to be useful in the prevention or treatment of solid tumour disease.</p><p num="p0167">Thus according to this aspect of the invention there is provided the use of a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined hereinbefore in the manufacture of a medicament for use as an anti-invasive agent in the containment and/or treatment of solid tumour disease.</p><p num="p0168">According to a further feature of this aspect of the invention there is provided a method for producing an anti-invasive effect by the containment and/or treatment of solid tumour disease in a warm-blooded animal, such as man, in need of such treatment which comprises administering to said animal an effective amount of a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined hereinbefore. According to a further aspect of the invention there is provided the use of a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined hereinbefore in the manufacture of a medicament for use in the prevention or treatment of solid tumour disease in a warm-blooded animal such as man. According to a further feature of this aspect of the invention there is provided a method for the prevention or treatment of solid tumour disease in a warm-blooded animal, such as man, in need of such treatment which comprises administering to said animal an 
<!-- EPO <DP n="40"/>-->
effective amount of a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined hereinbefore.</p><p num="p0169">According to a further aspect of the invention there is provided the use of a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined hereinbefore in the manufacture of a medicament for use in the prevention or treatment of those tumours which are sensitive to inhibition of non-receptor tyrosine kinases such as c-Src kinase that are involved in the signal transduction steps which lead to the invasiveness and migratory ability of metastasising tumour cells.</p><p num="p0170">According to a further feature of this aspect of the invention there is provided a method for the prevention or treatment of those tumours which are sensitive to inhibition of non-receptor tyrosine kinases such as c-Src kinase that are involved in the signal transduction steps which lead to the invasiveness and migratory ability of metastasising tumour cells which comprises administering to said animal an effective amount of a quinazoline derivative of the</p><p num="p0171">Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined hereinbefore. According to a further aspect of the invention there is provided the use of a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined hereinbefore in the manufacture of a medicament for use in providing a c-Src kinase inhibitory effect.</p><p num="p0172">According to a further feature of this aspect of the invention there is provided a method for providing a c-Src kinase inhibitory effect which comprises administering to said animal an effective amount of a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined hereinbefore.</p><p num="p0173">The anti-invasive treatment defined hereinbefore may be applied as a sole therapy or may involve, in addition to the quinazoline derivative of the invention, conventional surgery or radiotherapy or chemotherapy. Such chemotherapy may include one or more of the following categories of anti-tumour agents :-</p><p num="p0174">(i) other anti-invasion agents (for example metalloproteinase inhibitors like marimastat and inhibitors of urokinase plasminogen activator receptor function);</p><p num="p0175">(ii) antiproliferative/antineoplastic drugs and combinations thereof, as used in medical oncology, such as alkylating agents (for example cis-platin, carboplatin, cyclophosphamide, nitrogen mustard, melphalan, chlorambucil, busulphan and nitrosoureas); antimetabolites (for example antifolates such as fluoropyrimidines like 5-fluorouracil and tegafur, raltitrexed, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="41"/>-->
methotrexate, cytosine arabinoside and hydroxyurea, or, for example, one of the preferred antimetabolites disclosed in European Patent Application No. 562734 such as (2S)-2-{o-fluoro-p_-[N-{2,7-dimethyl-4-oxo-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-6-ylmethyl)- N-(prop-2-ynyl)amino]benzamido}-4-(tetrazol-5-yl)butyric acid); antitumour antibiotics (for example anthracyclines like adriamycin, bleomycin, doxorubicin, daunomycin, epirubicin, idarubicin, mitomycin-C, dactinomycin and mithramycin); antimitotic agents (for example vinca alkaloids like vincristine, vinblastine, vindesine and vinorelbine and taxoids like taxol and taxotere); and topoisomerase inhibitors (for example epipodophyllotoxins like etoposide and teniposide, amsacrine, topotecan and camptothecin); (iii) cytostatic agents such as antioestrogens (for example tamoxifen, toremifene, raloxifene, droloxifene and iodoxyfene), antiandrogens (for example bicalutamide, flutamide, nilutamide and cyproterone acetate), LHRH antagonists or LHRH agonists (for example goserelin, leuprorelin and buserelin), progestogens (for example megestrol acetate), aromatase inhibitors (for example as anastrozole, letrazole, vorazole and exemestane) and inhibitors of 5 -reductase such as finasteride;</p><p num="p0176">(iv) inhibitors of growth factor function, for example such inhibitors include growth factor antibodies, growth factor receptor antibodies, tyrosine kinase inhibitors and serine/threonine kinase inhibitors, for example inhibitors of the epidermal growth factor family (for example the EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitors N-(3-chloro-4-fluorophenyl)-7-methoxy- 6-(3-morpholinopropoxy)quinazolin-4-amine (ZD1839), N-(3-ethynylphenyl)-</p><p num="p0177">6,7-bis(2-methoxyethoxy)quinazolin-4-amine (CP 358774) and 6-acrylamido-N-(3-chloro- 4-fluorophenyl)-7-(3-morpholinopropoxy)quinazolin-4-amine (CI 1033)), for example inhibitors of the platelet-derived growth factor family and for example inhibitors of the hepatocyte growth factor family; and (v) antiangiogenic agents such as those which inhibit vascular endothelial growth factor such as the compounds disclosed in International Patent Applications WO 97/22596, WO 97/30035, WO 97/32856 and WO 98/13354 and those that work by other mechanisms (for example linomide, inhibitors of integrin αvβ3 function and angiostatin).</p><p num="p0178">Such conjoint treatment may be achieved by way of the simultaneous, sequential or separate dosing of the individual components of the treatment. Such combination products employ the compounds of this invention within the dosage range described hereinbefore and the other pharmaceutically-active agent within its approved dosage range. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="42"/>-->
 According to this aspect of the invention there is provided a pharmaceutical product comprising a quinazoline derivative of the formula I as defined hereinbefore and an additional anti-tumour agent as defined hereinbefore for the conjoint treatment of cancer.</p><p num="p0179">Although the compounds of the Formula I are primarily of value as therapeutic agents for use in warm-blooded animals (including man), they are also useful whenever it is required to inhibit the effects of c-Src. Thus, they are useful as pharmacological standards for use in the development of new biological tests and in the search for new pharmacological agents.</p><p num="p0180">The invention will now be illustrated in the following Examples in which, generally :</p><p num="p0181">(i) operations were carried out at ambient temperature, i.e. in the range 17 to 25 °C and under an atmosphere of an inert gas such as argon unless otherwise stated;</p><p num="p0182">(ii) evaporations were carried out by rotary evaporation in vacuo and work-up procedures were carried out after removal of residual solids by filtration;</p><p num="p0183">(iii) column chromatography (by the flash procedure) and medium pressure liquid chromatography (MPLC) were performed on Merck Kieselgel silica (Art. 9385) or Merck Lichroprep RP-18 (Art. 9303) reversed-phase silica obtained from E. Merck, Darmstadt, Germany or high pressure liquid chromatography (HPLC) was performed on C18 reverse phase silica, for example on a Dynamax C-18 60 A preparative reversed-phase column;</p><p num="p0184">(iv) yields, where present, are not necessarily the maximum attainable;</p><p num="p0185">(v) in general, the end-products of the Formula I have satisfactory microanalyses and their structures were confirmed by nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) and/or mass spectral techniques; fast-atom bombardment (FAB) mass spectral data were obtained using a Platform spectrometer and, where appropriate, either positive ion data or negative ion data were collected; NMR chemical shift values were measured on the delta scale [proton magnetic resonance spectra were determined using a Jeol JNM EX 400 spectrometer operating at a field strength of 400MHz, Varian Gemini 2000 spectrometer operating at a field strength of 300MHz or a Bruker AM300 spectrometer operating at a field strength of 300MHz]; the following abbreviations have been used: s, singlet; d, doublet; t, triplet; q, quartet; m, multiplet; br, broad;</p><p num="p0186">(vi) intermediates were not generally fully characterised and purity was assessed by thin layer chromatographic, HPLC, infra-red (IR) and/or NMR analysis;</p><p num="p0187">(vii) melting points are uncorrected and were determined using a Mettler SP62 automatic melting point apparatus or an oil-bath apparatus; melting points for the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="43"/>-->
end-products of the Formula I were determined after crystallisation from a conventional organic solvent such as ethanol, methanol, acetone, ether or hexane, alone or in admixture; (viii) the following abbreviations have been used:-</p><p num="p0188">DMF N,N-dimethylformamide DMSO dimethylsulphoxide</p><p num="p0189">THF tetrahydrofuran 
<!-- EPO <DP n="44"/>--></p><p num="p0190">Example 1 4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-6-methoxy-7-[3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]quinazoline</p><p num="p0191">A mixture of 4-chloro-6-methoxy-7-[3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]quinazoline (0.1 g), 4-aminobenzofuran (0.057 g), isopropanol (4 ml) and a solution of hydrogen chloride in isopropanol (6M, 0.06 ml) was stirred and heated to 85°C for 3 hours. The resultant mixture was cooled to ambient temperature and the precipitate was isolated by filtration, washed in turn with a 1:1 mixture of diethyl ether and isopropanol and with diethyl ether and dried under vacuum. There was thus obtained the title compound (0.14 g) as a dihydrochloride salt; NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>COOD) 2.35 (m, 2H), 2.9 (s, 3H), 3.3-4.0 (broad m, 10H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.35 (m, 2H), 6.9 (s, IH), 7.4 (m, 2H), 7.45 (t, IH), 7.65 (d, IH), 8.05 (d, IH), 8.3 (s, IH), 8.8 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>+</sup> 448.</p><p num="p0192">The 4-aminobenzofuran used as a starting material was prepared as follows :- Allyl bromide (12.5 ml) and sodium iodide (1 g) were added in turn to a stirred mixture of methyl 3-hydroxybenzoate (20 g), potassium carbonate (22 g) and acetone (200 ml) and the resultant mixture was stirred at ambient temperature for 16 hours. The mixture was filtered and the solvent was evaporated. The residue was partitioned between methylene chloride and water. The organic phase was dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated and the residue was purified by column chromatography using increasingly polar mixtures of petroleum ether (b.p. 60-80°C) and ethyl acetate as eluent. There was thus obtained methyl 3-allyloxybenzoate as an oil (21.8 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 3.85 (s, 3H), 4.65 (d, 2H), 5.30 (m, IH), 5.45 (m, IH), 6.05 (m, IH), 7.25 (m, IH), 7.45 (m, 2H), 7.55 (d, IH).</p><p num="p0193">The methyl 3-allyloxybenzoate so obtained was heated to 200°C for 0.7 hours and then to 230°C for 1 hour. The reaction product, comprising a mixture of methyl 2-allyl- 3-hydroxybenzoate and methyl 4-allyl-3-hydroxybenzoate, was cooled to ambient temperature and partitioned between diethyl ether and IN aqueous potassium hydroxide solution. The aqueous phase was allowed to stand for 30 minutes whereupon the methyl 4-allyl- 3-hydroxybenzoate was hydrolysed to 4-allyl-3-hydroxybenzoic acid. The aqueous phase was then acidified to pHl by the addition of 6N aqueous hydrochloric acid and extracted with diethyl ether. The organic extract was washed with 10% aqueous potassium carbonate solution, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. There was thus obtained methyl 2-allyl-3-hydroxybenzoate (10.7 g) as an oil; Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>+</sup> 192. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="45"/>-->
 Using analogous procedures to those described in J. Med. Chem., 1995, 38, 3102- 3103, methyl 2-allyl-3-hydroxybenzoate was converted in three steps via methyl 2-hydroxy- 2,3-dihydrobenzofuran-4-carboxylate and methyl benzofuran-4-carboxylate into benzofuran- 4-carboxylic acid. A mixture of benzofuran-4-carboxylic acid (0.5 g), diphenylphosphoryl azide (1.2 ml), triethylamine (0.79 ml) and tert-butanol (1.5 ml) were stirred and heated to reflux for 18 hours. The mixture was cooled to ambient temperature and partitioned between ethyl acetate and water. The organic phase was washed in turn with water and brine, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography using methylene chloride as eluent. There was thus obtained tert-butyl benzofuran-4- carbamate (0.8 g) as an oil; Mass Spectrum: M4-Na<sup>+</sup> 256.</p><p num="p0194">Trifluoroacetic acid (2.5 ml) was added to a solution of tert-butyl benzofuran- 4-carbamate (0.65 g) and methylene chloride (20 ml) which had been cooled to 0°C and the mixture was stirred for lhour. The mixture was allowed to warm to ambient temperature and stirring was continued for 1.5 hours. The mixture was evaporated and the residue was partitioned between ethyl acetate and water. The organic phase was dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The resultant oil was purified by column chromatography using a 4:1 mixture of methylene chloride and petroleum ether (p.p. 60-80°C) as eluent. There was thus obtained 4-aminobenzofuran (0.35 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 5.5 (br s, 2H), 6.35 (d, IH), 6.7 (d, IH), 6.95 (d, IH), 7.0 (d, IH), 7.7 (d, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+lX 133.</p><p num="p0195">The 4-chloro-6-methoxy-7-[3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]quinazoline used as a starting material was prepared as follows :-</p><p num="p0196">3-(4-Methylpiperazin-l-yl)propyl 4-toluenesulphonate was prepared as follows :-</p><p num="p0197">A mixture of 3-bromopropanol (20 ml), N-methylpiperazine (29 ml), potassium carbonate (83 g) and ethanol (200 ml)was stirred and heated to reflux for 20 hours. The mixture was cooled to ambient temperature and filtered. The filtrate was evaporated and the residue was triturated under diethyl ether. The resultant mixture was filtered and the filtrate was evaporated. The residue was purified by distillation at about 60-70°C under about 0.2 mm Hg to give l-(3-hydroxypropyl)-4-methylpiperazine (17 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.72 (m, 2H), 2.3 (s, 3H), 2.2-2.8 (m, 8H), 2.6 (t, 2H), 3.8 (t, 2H), 5.3 (br s, IH).</p><p num="p0198">4-Toluenesulphonyl chloride (3.2 g) was added to a stirred mixture of l-(3-hydroxypropyl)-4-methylpiperazine (2.4 g), triethylamine (4.6 ml) and methylene 
<!-- EPO <DP n="46"/>-->
chloride (60 ml) and the resultant mixture was stirred at ambient temperature for 2 hours. The solution was washed in turn with a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution and with water and filtered through phase separating paper. The organic filtrate was evaporated to give 3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propyl 4-toluenesulphonate as an oil which crystallised on standing (3.7 g); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>+</sup> 313.</p><p num="p0199">The trifluoroacetic acid salt of 4-(4-chloro-2-fluorophenoxy)-7-hydroxy- 6-methoxyquinazoline was prepared as follows :-</p><p num="p0200">A mixture of 2-amino-4-benzyloxy-5-methoxybenzamide (J. Med. Chem., 1977, 20, 146-149; 10 g), (3-dimethylamino-2-azaprop-2-en-l-ylidene)dimethylammonium chloride (Gold's reagent, 7.4 g) and dioxane (100 ml) was stirred and heated to reflux for 24 hours. Sodium acetate (3.02 g) and acetic acid (1.65 ml) were added and the reaction mixture was heated for a further 3 hours. The mixture was evaporated and water was added to the residue. The resultant solid was collected by filtration, washed with water and dried. The material was recrystallised from acetic acid to give 7-benzyloxy-6-methoxy-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (8.7 g).</p><p num="p0201">After repetition of the reaction so described, a mixture of 7-benzyloxy-6-methoxy- 3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (20.3 g), thionyl chloride (440 ml) and DMF (1.75 ml) was heated to reflux for 4 hours. The thionyl chloride was evaporated under vacuum and the residue was azeotroped with toluene three times to give 7-benzyloxy-4-chloro- 6-methoxyquinazoline.</p><p num="p0202">A mixture of the 7-benzyloxy-4-chloro-6-methoxyquinazoline so obtained, potassium carbonate (50 g) and 4-chloro-2-fluorophenol (8.8 ml) and DMF (500 ml) was stirred and heated to 100°C for 5 hours. The mixture was allowed to cool to ambient temperature, poured into water (2 L) and stirred at ambient temperature for a few minutes. The resultant solid was isolated and washed with water. The solid was dissolved in methylene chloride and the solution was filtered and treated with decolourising charcoal. The resultant solution was filtered and evaporated to give a solid which was triturated under diethyl ether. There was thus obtained 7-benzyloxy-4-(4-chloro-2-fluorophenoxy)-6-methoxyquinazoline (23.2 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 3.98 (s, 3H), 5.34 (s, 2H), 7.42 (m, 9H), 7.69 (m, IH), 8.55 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0203">A mixture of the material so obtained and trifluoroacetic acid (15 ml) was heated to reflux for 3 hours. The reaction mixture was allowed to cool, toluene was added and the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="47"/>-->
mixture was evaporated. The residue was triturated under diethyl ether and then under acetone. The resultant precipitate was isolated and dried to give 4-(4-chloro- 2-fluorophenoxy)-7-hydroxy-6-methoxyquinazoline trifluoroacetate salt (21.8 g) which was used without further purification. Thereafter, a mixture of the trifluoroacetic acid salt of 4-(4-chloro-2-fluorophenoxy)-</p><p num="p0204">7-hydroxy-6-methoxyquinazoline (3.2 g), 3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propyl 4-toluenesulphonate (3.0 g), potassium carbonate (6.1 g) and DMF (60 ml) was stirred at 90°C for 5 hours. The resultant mixture was cooled to ambient temperature, poured into water (700 ml) and extracted with ethyl acetate (5 times). The combined extracts were washed in turn with water, a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution, water and brine. The ethyl acetate solution was dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 100: 8:1 mixture of methylene chloride, methanol and a concentrated aqueous ammonium hydroxide solution (0.880 g/ml) as eluent. The material so obtained was triturated under diethyl ether. There was thus obtained 4-(4-chloro-2-fluorophenoxy)-6-methoxy-7-[3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]quinazoline (1.64 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 1.95 (m, 2H), 2.14 (s, 3H), 2.35 (m, 8H), 2.44 (t, 2H), 3.96 (s, 3H), 4.22 (t, 2H), 7.38 (s, IH), 7.4 (m, IH), 7.54 (m, 2H), 7.68 (m, IH), 8.55 (s, IH). After repetition of the previous reaction, a mixture of 4-(4-chloro-2-fluorophenoxy)- 6-methoxy-7-[3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]quinazoline (2.6 g) and 2N aqueous hydrochloric acid solution (45 ml) was stirred and heated to 95°C for 2 hours. The mixture was cooled to ambient temperature and basified by the addition of solid sodium bicarbonate The mixture was evaporated and the residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 50: 8:1 mixture of methylene chloride, methanol and a concentrated aqueous ammonium hydroxide solution (0.880 g/ml) as eluent. There was thus obtained 6-methoxy- 7-[3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (1.8 g,); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>+</sup> 333.</p><p num="p0205">After repetition of the previous reaction, a mixture of 6-methoxy- 7-[3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (2.15 g), thionyl chloride (25 ml) and DMF (0.18 ml) was stirred and heated to reflux for 2 hours. The thionyl chloride was evaporated under vacuum and the residue azeotroped twice with toluene. The residue was taken up in water, basified by the addition of a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution and extracted with methylene chloride (4 times). The combined extracts were 
<!-- EPO <DP n="48"/>-->
washed in turn with water and brine and filtered through phase separating paper. The filtrate was evaporated under vacuum and the residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 100: 8:1 mixture of methylene chloride, methanol and a concentrated aqueous ammonium hydroxide solution (0.880 g/ml) as eluent. The solid so obtained was triturated under acetone, filtered and dried to give 4-chloro-6-methoxy-7-[3-(4-methylpiperazin- l-yl)propoxy] quinazoline (1.2 g); Mass Spectrum: M-tTT<sup>1"</sup> 351.</p><p num="p0206">Example 2</p><p num="p0207">Using an analogous procedure to that described in Example 1, the appropriate 4-chloroquinazoline was reacted with the appropriate 4-aminobenzofuran to give the compounds described in Table I. Unless otherwise stated, each compound described in Table I was obtained as a dihydrochloride salt.</p><p num="p0208">Table I</p><p num="p0209"><img id="imgf000048_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="66" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000048_0001.tif" inline="no" he="40"/></p><p num="p0210"><img id="imgf000048_0002" orientation="portrait" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000048_0002.tif" inline="no" he="95"/><!-- EPO <DP n="49"/>-->
Notes</p><p num="p0211">[1] The product gave the following characterising data; NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 1.9 (m, 2H), 2.05 (m, 2H), 2.3 (m, 2H), 3.1 (m, 2H), 3.35 (m, 2H), 3.65 (m, 2H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.35 (t, 2H), 6.9 (d, IH), 7.4 (m, 2H), 7.45 (t, IH), 7.65 (d, IH), 8.05 (d, IH), 8.25 (s, IH), 8.8 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>+</sup> 419.</p><p num="p0212">The 4-chloro-6-methoxy-7-(3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)quinazoline used as a starting material was prepared as follows :-</p><p num="p0213">A mixture of 4-hydroxy-3-methoxybenzoic acid (8.4 g), 3-(pyrrolidin-l-yl)propyl chloride (J. Amer. Chem. Soc, 1955, 77, 2272; 14.75 g), potassium carbonate (13.8 g), potassium iodide (1.66 g) and DMF (150 ml) was stirred and heated to 100°C for 3 hours. The mixture was allowed to cool to ambient temperature, filtered and the filtrate was evaporated. The residue was dissolved in ethanol (75 ml), 2N aqueous sodium hydroxide solution (75 ml) was added and the mixture was heated to 90°C for 2 hours. The mixture was concentrated by evaporation and acidified by the addition of concentrated aqueous hydrochloric acid. The resultant mixture was washed with diethyl ether and then purified by column chromatography using a Diaion (trade mark of Mitsubishi) HP20SS resin column, eluting with water and then with a gradient of methanol (0 to 25%) in dilute hydrochloric acid (pH2.2). The methanol was removed by evaporation and the aqueous residue was freeze dried to give 3-methoxy-4-(3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)benzoic acid hydrochloride (12.2 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOdg and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 2.2 (m, 2H), 3.15 (t, 2H), 3.3 (t, 2H), 3.5 (d, 2H), 3.7 (t, 2H), 3.82 (s, 3H), 4.05 (d, 2H), 4.15 (t, 2H), 7.07 (d, IH), 7.48 (s, IH), 7.59 (d, IH).</p><p num="p0214">The material so obtained was dissolved in trifluoroacetic acid (40 ml) and the solution was cooled to 0°C. Fuming nitric acid (2.4 ml) was added slowly. The cooling bath was removed and the reaction mixture was stirred at ambient temperature for 1 hour. The mixture was evaporated and a mixture of ice and water was added to the residue. The mixture was evaporated. The solid residue was dissolved in dilute hydrochloric acid (pH2.2) and purified by column chromatography using a Diaion HP20SS resin column using a gradient of methanol (0 to 50%) in water. Concentration of the fractions by evaporation gave a precipitate which was collected and dried under vacuum over phosphorus pentoxide. There was thus obtained 5-methoxy-2-nitro-4-(3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)benzoic acid hydrochloride (12.1 g, 90%); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 1.8-1.9 (m, 2H), 2.0-2.1 (m, 2H), 2.1-2.2 (m, 2H), 
<!-- EPO <DP n="50"/>-->
3.0-3.1 (m, 2H), 3.3 (t, 2H), 3.6-3.7 (m, 2H), 3.95 (s, 3H), 4.25 (t, 2H), 7.35 (s, IH), 7.62 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0215">A mixture of a portion (9.63 g) of the material so obtained, thionyl chloride (20 ml) and DMF (0.05 ml) was heated to 45°C for 1.5 hours. The excess thionyl chloride was evaporated using the evaporation of added toluene (x2) to remove the last traces. The resultant solid was suspended in a mixture of THF (250 ml) and methylene chloride (100ml) and ammonia was bubbled though the mixture for 30 minutes. The resultant mixture was stirred for a further 1.5 hours at ambient temperature. The volatiles were removed by evaporation and the residue was dissolved in water and purified by column chromatography using a Diaion HP20SS resin column eluting with a gradient of methanol (0 to 5%) in water. The solvent was removed by evaporation from the fractions containing product. The residue was dissolved in a minimum of methanol and the solution was diluted with diethyl ether. The resultant precipitate was collected by filtration, washed with diethyl ether and dried under vacuum to give 5-methoxy-2-nitro-4-(3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)benzamide (7.23 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 1.85-1.95 (m, 2H), 2-2.1 (m, 2H), 2.15-2.25 (m, 2H), 3.0-3.1 (m, 2H), 3.31 (t, 2H), 3.62 (t, 2H), 3.93 (s, 3H), 4.2 (t, 2H), 7.16 (s, IH), 7.6 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0216">A mixture of a portion (1.5 g) of the material so obtained, concentrated aqueous hydrochloric acid (5 ml) and methanol (20 ml) was warmed to 50°C to give a solution. Iron powder (1.3 g) was added in portions and the reaction mixture was heated to reflux for 1 hour. The mixture was allowed to cool to ambient temperature. Insoluble material was removed by filtration through diatomaceous earth and the filtrate was evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography using a Diaion HP20SS resin column, eluting with water and then with dilute aqueous hydrochloric acid (pH2). The fractions containing product were concentrated by evaporation and the resultant precipitate was collected by filtration and dried under vacuum over phosphorus pentoxide. There was thus obtained 2-amino-5-methoxy- 4-(3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)benzamide hydrochloride (1.44 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 1.9 (br s, 2H), 2.05 (br s, 2H), 2.2 (br s, 2H), 3.05 (br s, 2H), 3.3 (t, 2H), 3.61 (br s, 2H), 3.8 (s, 3H), 4.11 (t, 2H), 7.05 (s, IH), 7.53 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0217">After repetition of the previous reaction, a mixture of 2-amino-5-methoxy- 4-(3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)benzamide hydrochloride (5.92 g), Gold's reagent (3.5 g) and dioxane (50 ml) was heated to reflux for 5 hours. Acetic acid (0.7 ml) and sodium acetate (1.33 g) were added and the reaction mixture was heated to reflux for a further 5 hours. The 
<!-- EPO <DP n="51"/>-->
mixture was allowed to cool to ambient temperature and evaporated. The residue was dissolved in water, adjusted to pH8 with 2N aqueous sodium hydroxide solution and purified on a Diaion HP20SS resin column eluting with methanol (gradient 0-50 %) in water. The fractions containing product were concentrated by evaporation and then freeze dried to give 6-methoxy-7-(3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (4.55 g); NMR</p><p num="p0218">Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 1.9 (m, 2H), 2.0-2.1 (m, 2H), 2.2-2.3 (m, 2H), 3.05 (m, 2H), 3.34 (t, 2H), 3.6-3.7 (br s, 2H), 3.94 (s, 3H), 4.27 (t, 2H), 7.31 (s, IH), 7.55 (s, IH), 9.02 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0219">A mixture of a portion (1.7 g) of the material so obtained, thionyl chloride (25 ml) and DMF (0.2 ml) was heated at reflux for 3 hours. Excess thionyl chloride was removed by evaporation and by azeotroping with toluene (x2). The residue was suspended in diethyl ether and washed with a 10% aqueous solution of sodium bicarbonate. The organic layer was dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated to give 4-chloro-6-methoxy-7-(3-pyrrolidin-l- ylpropoxy)quinazoline (1.94 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.8 (br s, 4H), 2.17 (m, 2H), 2.6 (br s, 4H), 2.7 (t, 2H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.3 (t, 2H), 7.35 (s, IH), 7.38 (s, IH), 8.86 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0220">[2] The product gave the following characterising data; NMR Spectrum: (DMSOde and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 2.35 (m, 2H), 3.5 (t, 2H), 3.7 (m, 4H), 3.85 (m, 4H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.35 (t, 2H), 6.9 (d, IH), 7.4 (m, 2H), 7.45 (t, IH), 7.65 (d, IH), 8.05 (d, IH), 8.25 (s, IH), 8.8 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+ϊ 483. The 4-chloro-7- [3 -(1,1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin-4-yl)propoxy] -</p><p num="p0221">6-methoxyquinazoline used as a starting material was prepared as follows :- 3-(l,l-Dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl)propan-l-ol (4.2 g) and l,r-(azodicarbonyl)dipiperidine (11.7 g) were added in turn to a mixture of 4-(4-chloro- 2-fluorophenoxy)-7-hydroxy-6-methoxyquinazoline (5.0 g), tributylphosphine (11.1 ml) and methylene chloride (150 ml). The resultant mixture was stirred at ambient temperature overnight. The mixture was diluted with diethyl ether (300 ml) and the precipitate was removed by filtration. The filtrate was evaporated and the residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 19:1 mixture of methylene chloride and methanol as eluent. The material so obtained was triturated under ethyl acetate and dried to give 4-(4-chloro-2-fluorophenoxy)-7- [3 -( 1 , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin-4-yl)propoxy] - 6-methoxyquinazoline (5.4 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOde) 1.86 (m, 2H), 2.65 (t, 2H), 2.92 
<!-- EPO <DP n="52"/>-->
 (m, 4H), 3.08 (m, 4H), 3.97 (s, 3H), 4.26 (t, 2H), 7.4 (m, IH), 7.42 (s, IH), 7.56 (m, 2H), 7.68 (m, IH), 8.54 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0222">A mixture of a portion (3.5 g) of the material so obtained and a 2N aqueous hydrochloric acid solution (56 ml) was stirred and heated to 95°C for 2 hours. The reaction 5 mixture was cooled to ambient temperature and treated with solid sodium bicarbonate to give a thick paste which was diluted with water and filtered. The solid was transferred to a flask and azeotroped with toluene twice to give a dry solid. The solid was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 19:1 mixture of methylene chloride and methanol as eluent. There was thus obtained 7-[3-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl)propoxy]-6-methoxy-</p><p num="p0223">10 3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (2.26 g) as a white solid; Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>"</sup> 368.</p><p num="p0224">After repetition of the previous reaction, a mixture of 7-[3-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro- 4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl)propoxy]-6-methoxy-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (4.2 g), thionyl chloride (45 ml) and DMF (0.1 ml) was heated to reflux for 2.5 hours. The residue was diluted with toluene and was evaporated under vacuum. The residue was taken up in water</p><p num="p0225">15 and basified to pH8 with a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution. The mixture was extracted with methylene chloride and the organic layer was washed in turn with water and brine. The organic solution was filtered through phase separating paper and evaporated to give an orange solid which was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 19:1 mixture of methylene chloride and methanol as eluent. The resultant solid was triturated</p><p num="p0226">20 under diethyl ether and dried to give 4-chloro-7-[3-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin- 4-yl)propoxy]-6-rnethoxyquinazoline (2.27 g); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>1"</sup> 386.</p><p num="p0227">The 3-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl)propan-l-ol used as an intermediate was obtained as follows :-</p><p num="p0228">A mixture of 3-aminopropan-l-ol (0.65 ml) and divinyl sulphone (1 g) was heated to</p><p num="p0229">25 110°C for 45 minutes. The mixture was allowed to cool to ambient temperature and was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 19:1 mixture of methylene chloride and methanol as eluent. There was thus obtained 3-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin-4- yl)propan-l-ol (0.8 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.7-1.8 (m, 2H), 2.73 (t, 2H), 3.06 (br s, 8H), 3.25 (s, IH), 3.78 (t, 2H); Mass Spectrum: M+H" 194.</p><p num="p0230">30 [3] The product gave the following characterising data; NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>COOD) 2.35 (m, 2H), 3.15 (t, 2H), 3.35 (t, 2H), 3.5 (d, 2H), 3.8 (t, 2H), 4.0 (m, 2H), 4.05 
<!-- EPO <DP n="53"/>-->
(s, 3H), 4.35 (t, 2H), 6.9 (s, IH), 7.4 (m, 3H), 7.65 (d, IH), 8.05 (d, IH), 8.35 (s, IH), 8.8 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>1"</sup> 435.</p><p num="p0231">The 4-chloro-6-methoxy-7-(3-morpholinopropoxy)quinazoline used as a starting material was prepared as follows :- A mixture of 7-benzyloxy-6-methoxy-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (35 g), thionyl chloride (440 ml) and DMF (1.75 ml) was heated to reflux for 4 hours. The thionyl chloride was evaporated under vacuum and the residue was azeotroped with toluene three times. The residue was dissolved in N-methylpyrrolidin-2-one (250 ml) to give a solution of 7-benzyloxy-4-chloro-6-methoxyquinazoline. Phenol (29.05 g) was dissolved in N-methylpyrrolidin-2-one (210 ml) and sodium hydride (60% dispersion in mineral oil; 11.025 g) was added in portions with cooling. The resultant mixture was stirred at ambient temperature for 3 hours. The resultant viscous suspension was diluted with N-methylpyrrolidin-2-one (180 ml) and stirred overnight. The above-mentioned solution of 7-benzyloxy-4-chloro-6-methoxyquinazoline was added and the resultant suspension was stirred and heated to 100°C for 2.5 hours. The mixture was allowed to cool to ambient temperature and poured into water (1.5 L) with vigorous stirring. The precipitate was collected by filtration, washed with water and dried under vacuum. The material so obtained was dissolved in methylene chloride and the solution was washed with brine and filtered through phase separating paper. The solution was evaporated under vacuum and the resultant residue was triturated under diethyl ether. There was thus obtained</p><p num="p0232">7-benzyloxy-6-methoxy-4-phenoxyquinazoline (87.8 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 4.09 (s, 3H), 5.34 (s, 2H), 7.42 (m, 12H), 7.63 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0233">A mixture of a portion (36.95 g) of the material so obtained and trifluoroacetic acid (420 ml) was heated to reflux for 3 hours. The reaction mixture was allowed to cool and evaporated under vacuum. The residue was stirred mechanically under water, basified by the addition of a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution and stirred overnight. The water was decanted and the residual solid was suspended in acetone. After stirring, the white solid was collected by filtration, washed with acetone and dried to give 7-hydroxy-6-methoxy- 4-phenoxyquinazoline (26.61 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 3.97 (s, 3H), 7.22 (s, IH), 7.3 (m, 3H), 7.47 (t, 2H), 7.56 (s, IH), 8.47 (s, IH), 10.7 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0234">A mixture of 7-hydroxy-6-methoxy-4-phenoxyquinazoline (25.27 g), 3-morpholinopropyl chloride (18.48 g), potassium carbonate (39.1 g) and DMF (750 ml) was 
<!-- EPO <DP n="54"/>-->
stirred and heated to 90°C for 3 hours. The mixture was allowed to cool to ambient temperature and filtered. The filtrate was evaporated and the residue was triturated under ethyl acetate. There was thus obtained 6-methoxy-7-(3-morpholinopropoxy)- 4-phenoxyquinazoline (31.4 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 1.97 (m, 2H), 2.39 (t, 4H), 2.47 (t, 2H), 3.58 (t, 4H), 3.95 (s, 3H), 4.23 (t, 2H), 7.31 (m, 3H), 7.36 (s, IH), 7.49 (t, 2H), 7.55 (s, IH), 8.52 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0235">A mixture of the material so obtained and 6N aqueous hydrochloric acid solution (800 ml) was stirred and heated to reflux for 1.5 hours. The reaction mixture was decanted and concentrated to a volume of 250 ml. The mixture was basified to pH9 by the addition of a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution and extracted with methylene chloride (4x400 ml). The combined extracts were filtered through phase separating paper and the filtrate was evaporated. The resultant solid was triturated under ethyl acetate to give 6-methoxy-7-(3-morpholinoρropoxy)-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (23.9 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 1.91 (m, 2H), 2.34 (t, 4H), 2.42 (t, 2H), 3.56 (t, 4H), 3.85 (s, 3H), 4.12 (t, 2H), 7.11 (s, IH), 7.42 (s, IH), 7.96 (s, IH), 12.01 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0236">A mixture of the material so obtained, thionyl chloride (210 ml) and DMF (1.8 ml) was heated to reflux for 1.5 hours. The thionyl chloride was removed by evaporation under vacuum and the residue was azeotroped with toluene three times. The residue was taken up in water and basified to pH8 by the addition of a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution. The resultant aqueous layer was extracted with methylene chloride (4x400 ml). The combined extracts were washed with water and with brine and dried over magnesium sulphate. The solution was filtered and evaporated. The resultant solid was triturated under ethyl acetate to give 4-chloro-6-methoxy-7-(3-morpholinopropoxy)quinazoline (17.39 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 2.1-2.16 (m, 2H), 2.48 (br s, 4H), 2.57 (t, 2H), 3.73 (t, 4H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.29 (t, 2H), 7.36 (s, IH), 7.39 (s, IH), 8.86 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0237">The 3-morpholinopropyl chloride used as a reagent was obtained as follows :- A mixture of morpholine (52.2 ml), l-bromo-3-chloropropane (30 ml) and toluene (180 ml) was heated to 70°C for 3 hours. The solid was removed by filtration and the filtrate was evaporated under vacuum. The resultant oil was decanted from the additional solid which was deposited and the oil was purified by vacuum distillation to yield 3-morpholinopropyl chloride (37.91 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 1.85 (m, 2H), 2.3 (t, 4H), 2.38 (t, 2H), 3.53 (t, 4H), 3.65 (t, 2H). 
<!-- EPO <DP n="55"/>-->
[4] The product gave the following characterising data; NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd-5 and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 1.6 (m, 2H), 2.05 (m, 2H), 2.15 (m, IH), 2.8 (s, 3H), 3.05 (t, 2H), 3.5 (d, 2H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.15 (d, 2H), 6.9 (s, IH), 7.4 ( , 2H), 7.45 (t, IH), 7.7 (d, IH), 8.05 (d, IH), 8.2 (s, IH), 8.8 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H" 419. The 4-chloro-7-(N-methylpiperidin-l-ylmethoxy)-6-methoxyquinazoline used as a starting material was prepared as follows :-</p><p num="p0238">A solution of di-tert-butyl dicarbonate (41.7 g) in ethyl acetate (75 ml) was added dropwise to a stirred solution of ethyl piperidine-4-carboxylate (30 g) in ethyl acetate (150 ml) which had been cooled to 0 to 5 °C in an ice-bath. The resultant mixture was stirred at ambient temperature for 48 hours. The mixture was poured into water (300 ml). The organic layer was separated, washed in turn with water (200 ml), 0.1N aqueous hydrochloric acid solution (200 ml), a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution (200 ml) and brine (200 ml), dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. There was thus obtained ethyl N-tert-butoxycarbonylpiperidine-4-carboxylate (48 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.25 (t, 3H), 1.45 (s, 9H), 1.55-1.7 (m, 2H), 1.8-2.0 (d, 2H), 2.35-2.5 (m, IH), 2.7-2.95 (t, 2H), 3.9-4.1 (br s, 2H), 4.15 (q, 2H).</p><p num="p0239">A solution of the material so obtained in THF (180 ml) was cooled at 0°C and lithium aluminium hydride (1M solution in THF; 133 ml) was added dropwise. The mixture was stirred at 0°C for 2 hours. Water (30 ml) and 2N aqueous sodium hydroxide solution (10 ml) were added in turn and the mixture was stirred for 15 minutes. The resultant mixture was filtered through diatomaceous earth and the solids were washed with ethyl acetate. The filtrate was washed in turn with water and with brine, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. There was thus obtained N-tert-butoxycarbonyl-4-hydroxymethylpiperidine (36.3 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.05-1.2 (m, 2H), 1.35-1.55 (m, 10H), 1.6-1.8 (m, 2H), 2.6-2.8 (t, 2H), 3.4-3.6 (t, 2H), 4.0-4.2 (br s, 2H). l,4-Diazabicyclo[2.2.2]octane (42.4 g) was added to a solution of N-tert-butoxycarbonyl-4-hydroxymethylpiperidine (52.5 g) in tert-butyl methyl ether (525 ml) and the mixture was stirred at ambient temperature for 15 minutes. The mixture was then cooled in an ice-bath to 5°C and a solution of 4-toluenesulphonyl chloride (62.8 g) in tert-butyl methyl ether (525 ml) was added dropwise over 2 hours while maintaining the reaction temperature at approximately 0°C. The resultant mixture was allowed to warm to ambient temperature and was stirred for 1 hour. Petroleum ether (b.p. 60-80°C, 1L) was 
<!-- EPO <DP n="56"/>-->
added and the precipitate was removed by filtration. The filtrate was evaporated to give a solid residue which was dissolved in diethyl ether. The organic solution was washed in turn with 0.5N aqueous hydrochloric acid solution, water, a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution and brine, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. There was thus obtained N-tert-butoxycarbonyl-4-(4-toluenesulphonyloxymethyl)piperidine (76.7 g), NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.0-1.2 (m, 2H), 1.45 (s, 9H), 1.65 (d, 2H), 1.75-1.9 (m, 2H), 2.45 (s, 3H), 2.55-2.75 ( , 2H), 3.85 (d, IH), 4.0-4.2 (br s, 2H), 7.35 (d, 2H), 7.8 (d, 2H).</p><p num="p0240">A portion (40 g) of the material so obtained was added to a suspension of ethyl 4-hydroxy-3-methoxybenzoate (19.6 g) and potassium carbonate (28 g) in DMF (200 ml) and the resultant mixture was stirred and heated to 95°C for 2.5 hours. The mixture was cooled to ambient temperature and partitioned between water and a mixture of ethyl acetate and diethyl ether. The organic layer was washed in turn with water and brine, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The resulting oil was crystallised from petroleum ether (b.p. 60-80°C) and the suspension was stored overnight at 5°C. The resultant solid was collected by filtration, washed with petroleum ether and dried under vacuum. There was thus obtained ethyl 4-(N-tert-butoxycarbonylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy)-3-methoxybenzoate (35 g), m.p. 81-83°C; NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.2-1.35 (m, 2H), 1.4 (t, 3H), 1.48 (s, 9H), 1.8-1.9 (d, 2H), 2.0-2.15 (m, 2H), 2.75 (t, 2H), 3.9 (d, 2H), 3.95 (s, 3H), 4.05-4.25 (br s, 2H), 4.35 (q, 2H), 6.85 (d, IH), 7.55 (s, IH), 7.65 (d, IH). The material so obtained was dissolved in formic acid (35 ml), formaldehyde (12M,</p><p num="p0241">37% in water, 35 ml) was added and the mixture was stirred and heated to 95°C for 3 hours. The resultant mixture was evaporated. The residue was dissolved in methylene chloride and hydrogen chloride (3M solution in diethyl ether; 40 ml) was added. The mixture was diluted with diethyl ether and the mixture was triturated until a solid was formed. The solid was collected, washed with diethyl ether and dried under vacuum overnight at 50°C. There was thus obtained ethyl 3-methoxy-4-(N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy)benzoate (30.6 g), NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 1.29 (t, 3H), 1.5-1.7 (m, 2H), 1.95 (d, 2H), 2.0-2.15 (br s, IH), 2.72 (s, 3H), 2.9-3.1 (m, 2H), 3.35-3.5 (br s, 2H), 3.85 (s, 3H), 3.9-4.05 (br s, 2H), 4.3 (q, 2H), 7.1 (d, lH), 7.48 (s, lH), 7.6 (d, lH). The material so obtained was dissolved in methylene chloride (75 ml) and the solution was cooled in an ice-bath to 0-5°C. Trifluoroacetic acid (37.5 ml) was added followed by the dropwise addition over 15 minutes of a solution of fuming nitric acid (24M; 7.42 ml) in 
<!-- EPO <DP n="57"/>-->
methylene chloride (15 ml). The resultant solution was allowed to warm to ambient temperature and was stirred for 2 hours. Volatile materials were evaporated. The residue was dissolved in methylene chloride (50 ml) and the solution was cooled in an ice-bath to 0-5°C. Diethyl ether was added and the resultant precipitate was collected and dried under vacuum at 50°C. The solid was dissolved in methylene chloride (500 ml) and hydrogen chloride (3M solution in diethyl ether; 30 ml) was added followed by diethyl ether (500 ml). The resultant solid was collected and dried under vacuum at 50°C. There was thus obtained ethyl 5-methoxy-4-(N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy)-2-nitrobenzoate (28.4 g), NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd&lt; 1.3 (t, 3H), 1.45-1.65 (m, 2H), 1.75-2.1 (m, 3H), 2.75 (s, 3H), 2.9-3.05 (m, 2H), 3.4-3.5 (d, 2H), 3.95 (s, 3H), 4.05 (d, 2H), 4.3 (q, 2H), 7.32 (s, IH), 7.66 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0242">A mixture of a portion (3.89 g) of the material so obtained, 10% platinum-on-activated carbon (50% wet, 0.389 g) and methanol (80 ml) was stirred under 1.8 atmospheres pressure of hydrogen until uptake of hydrogen ceased. The mixture was filtered and the filtrate was evaporated. The residue was dissolved in water (30 ml) and basified to pHIO by the addition of a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution. The mixture was diluted with a 1:1 mixture of ethyl acetate and diethyl ether and the organic layer was separated. The aqueous layer was further extracted with a 1:1 mixture of ethyl acetate and diethyl ether and the organic extracts were combined, washed in turn with water and brine, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was triturated under a mixture of petroleum ether (b.p. 60-80°C) and diethyl ether. The solid so obtained was isolated, washed with petroleum ether and dried under vacuum at 60°C. There was thus obtained ethyl 2-amino-5-methoxy- 4-(N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy)benzoate (2.58 g), m.p. 111-112°C; NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.35 (t, 3H), 1.4-1.5 (m, 2H), 1.85 (m, 3H), 1.95 (t, 2H), 2.29 (s, 3H), 2.9 (d, 2H), 3.8 (s, 3H), 3.85 (d, 2H), 4.3 (q, 2H), 5.55 (br s, 2H), 6.13 (s, IH), 7.33 (s, IH). A mixture of ethyl 2-amino-5-methoxy-4-(N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy)benzoate</p><p num="p0243">(16.1 g), formamidine acetic acid salt (5.2 g) and 2-methoxyethanol (160 ml) was stirred and heated at 115°C for 2 hours. Further formamidine acetic acid salt (10.4 g) was added in portions every 30 minutes during 4 hours and heating was continued for 30 minutes after the last addition. The resultant mixture was evaporated. The solid residue was stirred under a mixture of methylene chloride (50 ml) and ethanol (100 ml). The precipitate was removed by filtration and the filtrate was concentrated to a final volume of 100 ml. The resultant suspension was cooled to 5°C. The solid so obtained was collected, washed with cold ethanol 
<!-- EPO <DP n="58"/>-->
and with diethyl ether and dried under vacuum at 60°C. There was thus obtained 6-methoxy- 7-(N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy)-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (12.7 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOds) 1.25-1.4 (m, 2H), 1.75 (d, 2H), 1.9 (t, IH), 1.9 (s, 3H), 2.16 (s, 2H), 2.8 (d, 2H), 3.9 (s, 3H), 4.0 (d, 2H), 7.11 (s, IH), 7.44 (s, IH), 7.97 (s, IH). A mixture of a portion (2.8 g) of the material so obtained, thionyl chloride (28 ml) and</p><p num="p0244">DMF (0.28 ml) was heated to reflux for 1 hour. The mixture was evaporated and the precipitate was triturated under diethyl ether. The resultant solid was isolated and washed with diethyl ether. The solid was then dissolved in methylene chloride and the solution was washed with a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution. The organic layer was washed in turn with water and brine, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. There was thus obtained 4-chloro-6-methoxy-7-(N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy)quinazoline (2.9 g,), NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 1.3-1.5 (m, 2H), 1.75-1.9 (m, 4H), 2.0 (t, IH), 2.25 (s, 3H), 2.85 (d, 2H), 4.02 (s, 3H), 4.12 (d, 2H), 7.41 (s, IH), 7.46 (s, IH), 8.9 (s, IH). [5] The product gave the following characterising data; NMR Spectrum: (DMSOdg and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 2.45 (m, 2H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.25 (t, 2H), 4.65 (t, 2H), 6.9 (s, IH), 7.3 (s, IH), 7.4 (d, IH), 7.45 (t, IH), 7.65 (d, IH), 7.8 (s, IH), 8.05 (d, IH), 8.25 (m, 2H), 8.8 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H÷ 417.</p><p num="p0245">The 4-chloro-7-(3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)-6-methoxyquinazoline used as a starting material was prepared as follows :- Sodium hydride (60% dispersion in mineral oil, 1.44 g) was added portionwise during</p><p num="p0246">20 minutes to a solution of 7-benzyloxy-6-methoxy-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (8.46 g) in DMF (70 ml) and the mixture was stirred for 1.5 hours. Chloromethyl pivalate (5.65 g) was added dropwise and the mixture was stirred at ambient temperature for 2 hours. The mixture was diluted with ethyl acetate (100 ml) and poured onto a mixture of ice and water (400 ml) containing 2N aqueous hydrochloric acid (4 ml). The organic layer was separated and the aqueous layer was extracted with ethyl acetate. The organic extract was washed with a saturated aqueous sodium chloride solution, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was triturated under a mixture of petroleum ether (b.p. 60-80°C) and diethyl ether. The solid so obtained was isolated and dried under vacuum to give 7-benzyloxy-6-methoxy- 3-pivaloyloxymethyl-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (10 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 1.11 (s, 9H), 3.89 (s, 3H), 5.3 (s, 2H), 5.9 (s, 2H), 7.27 (s, IH), 7.35 (m, IH), 7.47 (t, 2H), 7.49 (d, 2H), 7.51 (s, IH), 8.34 (s, IH). 
<!-- EPO <DP n="59"/>-->
 A mixture of a portion (7 g) of the material so obtained, 10% palladium-on-charcoal catalyst (0.7 g), ethyl acetate (250 ml), DMF (50 ml), methanol (50 ml) and acetic acid (0.7 ml) was stirred under an atmosphere pressure of hydrogen for 40 minutes. The catalyst was removed by filtration and the filtrate was evaporated. The residue was triturated under diethyl ether. The solid so obtained was isolated and dried under vacuum to give 7-hydroxy- 6-methoxy-3-pivaloyloxymethyl-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (4.36 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 1.1 (s, 9H), 3.89 (s, 3H), 5.89 (s, 2H), 7.0 (s, IH), 7.48 (s, IH), 8.5 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0247">A solution of diethyl azodicarboxylate (1.34 ml) in methylene chloride (10 ml) was added dropwise to a stirred mixture of 7-hydroxy-6-methoxy-3-pivaloyloxymethyl- 3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (2
<img id="imgf000059_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="68" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000059_0001.tif" inline="no" he="6"/>
 (0.91 g), triphenylphosphine (1.84 g) and methylene chloride (10 ml). The resultant mixture was stirred at ambient temperature for 3 hours. The solvent was evaporated and the residue was purified by column chromatography using increasingly polar solvent mixtures of methylene chloride and methanol as eluent There was thus obtained 6-methoxy-3-pivaloyloxymethyl- 7-[3-(l,2,3-triazol-l-yl)propoxy]-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (2.7 g); Mass Spectrum: M+H* 416.</p><p num="p0248">A saturated solution of ammonia in methanol (75 ml) was added to a solution of the 3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one so obtained in methanol (30 ml) and the reaction mixture was stirred at ambient temperature for 4 days. The precipitate was removed by filtration and the filtrate was evaporated. The residue was triturated under diethyl ether and dried under vacuum. There was thus obtained 6-methoxy-7-[3-(l,2,3-triazol-l-yl)propoxy]quinazolin- 4-one (1.8 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 2.35 (t, 2H), 3.9 (s, 3H), 4.15 (t, 2H), 4.6 (t, 2H), 7.15 (s, IH), 7.5 (s, IH), 7.75 (s, IH), 8.0 (s, IH), 8.2 (s, IH), Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>+</sup> 302. A mixture of the material so obtained, thionyl chloride (15 ml) and DMF (0.15 ml) was heated to reflux for 1 hour. The excess thionyl chloride was evaporated using the evaporation of added toluene to remove the last traces. Methylene chloride and water were added to the solid residue and the mixture was neutralised by the addition of solid sodium bicarbonate. Some of the desired product precipitated at this stage and was collected by filtration, washed with water and dried under vacuum. The organic phase was washed with water, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The two batches of solid were combined. There was thus obtained 4-chloro-6-mefhoxy-7-[3-(l,2,3-triazol- 
<!-- EPO <DP n="60"/>-->
l-yl)propoxy]quinazoline (1.6 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOde) 2.4 (t, 2H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.25 (t, 2H), 4.6 (t, 2H), 7.4 (s, IH), 7.45 (s, IH), 7.75 (s, IH), 8.2 (s, IH), 8.9 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0249">The N^ -hydroxypropy^-lAS-triazole used as a starting material was prepared as follows :- A mixture of 1,2,3-triazole (5 g), ethyl acrylate (7.8 ml) and pyridine (50 drops) was stirred and heated to 90°C for 4 hours. The mixture was cooled to ambient temperature and evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using increasingly polar mixtures of methylene chloride and diethyl ether as eluent. There was thus obtained ethyl 1,2,3-triazol-l-ylpropanoate (8.96 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.25 (t, 3H), 2.95 (t, 2H), 4.15 (q, 2H), 4.7 (t, 2H), 7.65 (s, IH), 7.7 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0250">A solution of the material so obtained in THF (50 ml) was added dropwise to a suspension of lithium aluminium hydride (3 g) in THF (250 ml) which had been cooled to 0°C. The mixture was stirred at 5°C for 1 hour and at ambient temperature for a further hour. The mixture was cooled to 0°C and 4N aqueous sodium hydroxide solution (30 ml) was added dropwise. The mixture was filtered and the filtrate was dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 47:3 mixture of methylene chloride and methanol as eluent. There was thus obtained ^-(S-hydroxypropy -l^^-triazole (6.2 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDCI<sub>3</sub>) 2.1-2.2 (m, 3H), 3.65 (m, 2H), 4.6 (t, 2H), 7.6 (s, IH), 7.72 (s, IH). [6] Pentan-2-ol was used in place of isopropanol as the reaction solvent and the reaction mixture was heated to 110°C for 5 hours. The product gave the following characterising data; NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>ό</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 2.35 (m, 2H), 3.15 (m, 2H), 3.35 (t, 2H), 3.55 (d, 2H), 3.7 (t, 2H), 4.05 (m, 5H), 4.35 (t, 2H), 6.95 (d, IH), 7.4 (s, IH), 7.6 (d, IH), 7.8 (d, IH), 8.15 (d, IH), 8.25 (s, IH), 8.8 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>1"</sup> 469. The 4-amino-5-chlorobenzofuran used as a starting material was prepared as follows :-</p><p num="p0251">A mixture of 4-chloro-3-nitrophenol (1 g), trifluoroacetic acid (9 ml) and hexa ethylenetetramine (0.8 g) was heated to 115°C for 1.5 hours. The reaction mixture was cooled to ambient temperature and partitioned between methylene chloride and a 4N hydrochloric acid solution. The organic phase was washed twice with brine, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using methylene chloride as eluent. There was thus obtained 3-chloro-6-hydroxy- 
<!-- EPO <DP n="61"/>-->
2-nitrobenzaldehyde (3 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOde) 7.25 (m, IH), 7.85 (m, IH), 10.25 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0252">A mixture of the material so obtained, diethyl bromomalonate (2.78 ml), potassium carbonate (3.1 g), tetrabutylammonium bromide (0.477 g) and toluene (50 ml) was stirred and heated to reflux in a Dean &amp; Stark apparatus for 20 hours. The mixture was cooled to ambient temperature, filtered and the filtrate was evaporated. The residue was dissolved in ethyl acetate and the solution was washed in turn with water and brine, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using methylene chloride as eluent. There was thus obtained ethyl 5-chloro-4-nitrobenzofuran- 2-carboxylate (3 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 3.35 (t, 3H), 4.45 (q, 2H), 7.85 (s, IH), 7.9 (d, IH), 8.2 (d, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>+</sup> 269.</p><p num="p0253">A mixture of the material so obtained, 2N aqueous potassium hydroxide solution (11.1 ml) and ethanol (17 ml) was stirred and heated to reflux for 1 hour. The ethanol was evaporated and the residue was dissolved in water. The solution was acidified to pH2 by the addition of 6N aqueous hydrochloric acid. The resultant precipitate was isolated, washed with water and dried under vacuum over phosphorus pentoxide to give 5-chloro-4-nitrobenzofuran- 2-carboxylic acid (2.65 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 7.25 (s, IH), 7.7 (d, IH), 8.05 (d, IH).</p><p num="p0254">A mixture of a portion (1.6 g) of the material so obtained, cupric (II) oxide (0.08 g) and quinoline (14 ml) was heated to 210°C for 30 minutes. Copper powder (0.02 g) was then added and the reaction mixture was heated to 230°C for a further 20 minutes. The mixture was cooled to ambient temperature and filtered. The filtrate was partitioned between diethyl ether and 2N aqueous hydrochloric acid. The organic phase was dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 17:3 mixture of petroleum ether (b.p. 60-80°C) and diethyl ether as eluent. There was thus obtained 5-chloro-4-nitrobenzofuran (0.36 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>), 7.2 (d, IH), 7.7 (d, IH), 8.05 (d, IH), 8.35 (d, IH).</p><p num="p0255">5-Chloro-4-nitrobenzofuran (0.1 g) was added portionwise to a stirred mixture of hydrazine hydrate (0.097 ml), Raney nickel (0.02 g) and methanol (7 ml) that had been warmed to 55-60°C. The reaction mixture was then heated to reflux for 30 minutes. The catalyst was removed by filtration and the filtrate was evaporated. The residue was partitioned between methylene chloride and water. The organic phase was dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using 
<!-- EPO <DP n="62"/>-->
a 3:2 mixture of petroleum ether (b.p. 60-80°C) and methylene chloride as eluent. There was thus obtained 4-amino-5-chlorobenzofuran (0.037 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 5.8 (br s, 2H), 6.8 (d, IH), 7.1 (d, IH), 7.15 (d, IH), 7.8 (d, IH).</p><p num="p0256">[7] The product gave the following characterising data; Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>1"</sup> 493. The 4-chloro-6-methoxy-7-(2-acetoxy-3-morpholinopropoxy)quinazoline used as a starting material was prepared as follows :-</p><p num="p0257">A mixture of 7-hydroxy-6-methoxy-3-pivaloyloxymethyl-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (40 g), 2,3-epoxypropyl bromide (16.8 ml), potassium carbonate (36 g) and DMF (400 ml) was stirred and heated to 70°C for 1.5 hours. The mixture was poured into an ice-water mixture (1.5 L) and the resultant precipitate was isolated, washed in turn with water and diethyl ether and dried under vacuum over phosphorus pentoxide. There was thus obtained 7-(2,3-epoxypropoxy)-6-methoxy-3-pivaloyloxymethyl-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (46.7 g).</p><p num="p0258">A mixture of a portion (8 g) of the material so obtained, morpholine (5.8 ml) and chloroform (120 ml) was heated to reflux for 16 hours. The mixture was evaporated and the residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 19: 1 mixture of methylene chloride and methanol as eluent. There was thus obtained 7-(2-hydroxy- 3-morpholinoρropoxy)-6-methoxy-3-pivaloyloxymethyl-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one as a foam (8.2 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.2 (s, 9H), 2.5 (m, 2H), 2.6 (m, 2H), 2.7 (m, 2H), 3.5 (br s, IH), 3.75 (m, 4H), 3.95 (s, 3H), 4.15 (m, 2H), 4.25 (m, IH), 5.95 (s, 2H), 7.15 (s, IH), 7.65 (s, IH), 8.2 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0259">A mixture of the material so obtained and a saturated methanolic ammonia solution was stirred at ambient temperature for 24 hours. The mixture was evaporated and the resultant solid was washed with diethyl ether and a 19:1 mixture of diethyl ether and methylene chloride. There was thus obtained 7-(2-hydroxy-3-morpholinopropoxy)-6-methoxy- 3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one (6.34 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 2.4 (m, 6H), 3.55 (m, 4H), 3.85 (s, 3H), 4.0 (m, 2H), 4.15 (m, IH), 4.95 (br s, IH), 7.15 (s, IH), 7.45 (s, IH), 7.95 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0260">A mixture of a portion (5.2 g) of the material so obtained, acetic anhydride (20 ml) and pyridine (1 ml) was stirred at ambient temperature for 30 minutes. The resultant mixture was poured into an ice-water mixture and stirred for 30 minutes. The mixture was then cooled in an ice-bath and a saturated solution of sodium bicarbonate was slowly added to adjust the pH to 9. The mixture was extracted with methylene chloride and the organic phase was washed 
<!-- EPO <DP n="63"/>-->
with water and with brine, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 93:7 mixture of methylene chloride and methanol as eluent. There was thus obtained 7-(2-acetoxy-3-morpholinopropoxy)-6-methoxy- 3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one as a solid (5 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 2.05 (s, 3H), 2.4 (m, 4H), 2.6 (m, 2H), 3.55 (m, 4H), 3.85 (s, 3H), 4.35 (m, 2H), 5.25 (m, IH), 7.2 (s, IH), 7.45 (s, IH), 8.0 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>+</sup> 378.</p><p num="p0261">A mixture of the material so obtained, thionyl chloride (60 ml) and DMF (0.5 ml) was heated to reflux for 1 hour. The mixture was evaporated, toluene was added and the mixture was evaporated. A mixture of ice and water was added to the residue and the mixture was basified to pH8.5 by the addition of a saturated aqueous sodium bicarbonate solution. The mixture was extracted with methylene chloride. The organic phase was washed with water and with brine, dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 97:3 mixture of methylene chloride and methanol as eluent. There was thus obtained 7-(2-acetoxy-3-morpholinopropoxy)-4-chloro- 6-methoxyquinazoline as a foam (4.56 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 2.1 (s, 3H), 2.55 (m, 4H), 2.7 (d, 2H), 3.7 (m, 4H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.35 (m, IH), 4.45 (m, IH), 5.45 (m, IH), 7.4 (d, 2H), 8.85 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>+</sup> 396 and 398.</p><p num="p0262">[8] The product gave the following characterising data; Mass Spectrum: M+H* 479. The 7- [2-acetoxy-3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy] -4-chloro- 6-methoxyquinazoline used as a starting material was prepared as follows :-</p><p num="p0263">Using an analogous procedure to that described in Note [7] immediately above, 7-(2,3-epoxypropyl)-6-methoxy-3-pivaloyloxymethyl-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one was treated with N-isopropyl-N-methylamine to give 7-[2-hydroxy-3-(N-isopropyl- N-methylamino)propoxy] -6-methoxy-3 -pi valoyloxymethyl-3 ,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one which, in turn, was converted into 7-[2-acetoxy-3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy]- 4-chloro-6-methoxyquinazoline; NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.0 (d, 6H), 2.1 (s, 3H), 2.3 (s, 3H), 2.6 (m, IH), 2.75 (m, IH), 2.85 (m, IH), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.35 (m, IH), 4.45 (m, IH), 5.35 (m, IH), 7.25 (s, IH), 7.4 (s, IH), 8.85 (s, IH); [9] The product gave the following characterising data; Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>1"</sup> 531. The 7-[2-acetoxy-3-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]-4-chloro-</p><p num="p0264">6-methoxyquinazoline used as a starting material was prepared as follows :- 
<!-- EPO <DP n="64"/>-->
 Using an analogous procedure to that described in Note [7] immediately above, 7-(2,3-epoxypropyl)-6-methoxy-3-pivaloyloxymethyl-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one was treated with l-(cyanomethyl)piperazine to give 7-[2-hydroxy-3-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin- 1 -yl)propoxy] -6-methoxy-3 -pi valoyloxymethyl-3 ,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one which was converted to 7-[2-acetoxy-3-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]-4-chloro-</p><p num="p0265">6-methoxyquinazoline; NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 2.1 (s, 3H), 2.65 (br s, 10H), 3.5 (s, 2H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.4 (m, 2H), 5.45 (m, IH), 7.25 (s, IH), 7.4 (s, IH), 8.85 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H* 434 and 436.</p><p num="p0266">The l-(cyanomethyl)piperazine was prepared as follows :- A mixture of 1 -(tert-butoxycarbonyl)piperazine (5 g), 2-chloroacetonitrile (1.9 ml), potassium carbonate (4 g) and DMF (20 ml) was stirred at ambient temperature for 16 hours. A saturated aqueous ammonium chloride solution was added and the mixture was extracted with ethyl acetate. The organic phase was dried over magnesium sulphate and evaporated. The residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using diethyl ether as eluent. There was thus obtained l-(tert-butoxycarbonyl)-4-cyanomethylpiperazine as a solid (5.7 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub>) 1.45 (s, 9H), 2.5 (m, 4H), 3.45 (m, 4H), 3.55 (s, 2H).</p><p num="p0267">A mixture of the material so obtained, trifluoroacetic acid (20 ml) and methylene chloride (25 ml) was stirred at ambient temperature for 4 hours. The mixture was evaporated, toluene was added and the mixture was evaporated again. The residue was purified by column chromatography on silica using a 9: 1 mixture of methylene chloride and methanol as eluent. There was thus obtained 1-cyanomethylpiperazine trifluoroacetate salt which was treated with solid sodium bicarbonate in a mixture of methylene chloride, ethyl acetate and methanol to give the free base form (2.9 g); NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub> and DMSOd<sub>6</sub>) 2.7 (m, 4H), 3.2 (m, 4H), 3.6 (s, 2H), 6.2 (br s, IH). [10] The product gave the following characterising data; Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>1"</sup> 477.</p><p num="p0268">The 7-(2-acetoxy-3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)-4-chloro-6-methoxyquinazoline used as a starting material was prepared as follows :-</p><p num="p0269">Using an analogous procedure to that described in Note [7] immediately above, 7-(2,3-epoxypropyl)-6-methoxy-3-pivaloyloxymethyl-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one was treated with pyrrolidine to give 7-(2-hydroxy-3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)-6-methoxy-</p><p num="p0270">3 -pi valoyloxymethyl-3, 4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one which was converted into 7-(2-acetoxy- 3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)-4-chloro-6-methoxyquinazoline; NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub> + 
<!-- EPO <DP n="65"/>-->
CD<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 2.05 (s, 4H), 2.15 (s, 3H), 3.45 (br s, 4H), 3.65 (m, 2H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.4 (d, 2H),</p><p num="p0271">5.65 (m, IH), 7.4 (s, IH), 7.55 (s, IH), 8.9 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0272">[11] The product gave the following characterising data; Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>1"</sup> 491.</p><p num="p0273">The 7-(2-acetoxy-3-piperidinopropoxy)-4-chloro-6-methoxyquinazoline used as a starting material was prepared as follows :-</p><p num="p0274">Using an analogous procedure to that described in Note [7] immediately above, 7-(2,3-epoxypropyl)-6-methoxy-3-pivaloyloxymethyl-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one was treated with piperdine to give 7-(2-hydroxy-3-piperdinopropoxy)-6-methoxy- 3-pivaloyloxymethyl-3,4-dihydroquinazolin-4-one which was converted into 7-(2-acetoxy- 3-piperidinopropoxy)-4-chloro-6-methoxyquinazoline; NMR Spectrum: (CDC1<sub>3</sub> + CD<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D)</p><p num="p0275">1.6 (m, 2H), 1.9 (m, 4H), 2.1 (s, 3H), 3.2 (br s, 4H), 3.5 (m, 2H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.35 (m, 2H),</p><p num="p0276">5.7 (m, IH), 7.4 (s, IH), 7.5 (s, IH), 8.9 (s, IH).</p><p num="p0277">Example 3 4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7-(2-hydroxy-3-morpholinopropoxy)-6-methoxyquinazoline</p><p num="p0278">A mixture of 7-(2-acetoxy-3-morpholinopropoxy)-4-(4-benzofuranylamino)- 6-methoxyquinazoline dihydrochloride (0.14 g) and a saturated methanolic ammonia solution (3 ml) was stirred at ambient temperature overnight. The solvent was removed by evaporation and the mixture was dissolved in methylene chloride (3 ml) and adsorbed on the top of a pre-packed chromatography column containing 5 g of NH<sub>2</sub>-silica (Isolute sorbent from International Sorbent Technology Ltd, ref 9470-0100) and eluted with a 19:1 mixture of methylene chloride and methanol. The material so obtained was dissolved in methylene chloride (3 ml) and a 6M solution of hydrogen chloride in isopropanol (0.3 ml) was added with stirring. Diethyl ether (10 ml) was added and the resultant precipitate was collected, rinsed with diethyl ether and dried under vacuum. There was thus obtained the title compound (0.129 g); NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 3.15-3.48 (m, 4H), 4.56 (d, 2H), 3.76-3.94 (m, 2H), 3.94-4.06 (m, 2H), 4.06 (s, 3H), 4.26 (d, 2H), 4.53-4.61 (m, IH), 6.91 (d, IH), 7.4 (d, IH), 7.46 (m, IH), 7.51 (s, IH), 7.55 (s, IH), 8.03 (d, IH), 8.38 (s, IH), 8.8 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>1"</sup> 451. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="66"/>-->
Example 4</p><p num="p0279">Using an analogous procedure to that described in Example 3, the appropriate 7-(2-acetoxypropoxy)quinazoline was reacted with a saturated methanolic ammonia solution to give the compounds described in Table H Unless otherwise stated, each compound described in Table π was obtained as a dihydrochloride salt.</p><p num="p0280">Table II</p><p num="p0281"><img id="imgf000066_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="66" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000066_0001.tif" inline="no" he="40"/></p><p num="p0282"><img id="imgf000066_0002" orientation="portrait" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000066_0002.tif" inline="no" he="41"/></p><p num="p0283">Notes</p><p num="p0284">[1] The product gave the following characterising data; NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 1.22-1.36 (m, 6H), 2.81 (s, 3H), 3.11-3.5 (m, 2H), 3.56-3.74 (m, IH), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.21-4.32 (m, 2H), 4.4-4.5 (m, IH), 6.91 (m, IH), 7.4 (d, IH), 7.43-7.5 (m, 2H), 7.57 (d, IH), 8.04 (d, IH), 8.28 (s, IH), 8.81 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H* 437. [2] The product gave the following characterising data; NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 2.56-3.12 (m, 4H), 3.15-3.48 (m, 4H), 3.56-3.75 (m, 2H), 3.89 (s, 2H), 4.06 (s, 3H), 4.22-4.34 (m, 2H), 4.48-4.58 (m, IH), 6.91 (m, IH), 7.41 (d, IH), 7.44-7.5 (m, 2H), 7.67 (d, IH), 8.03 (d, IH), 8.33 (s, IH), 8.82 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>+</sup> 489. [3] The product gave the following characterising data; NMR Spectrum: (DMSOd<sub>6</sub> and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 1.85-1.98 (m, 2H), 2.0-2.11 (m, 2H), 3.1-3.21 (m, 2H), 3.35-3.43 (m, 2H), 3.59- 3.7 (m, 2H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.24 (d, 2H), 4.36-4.45 (m, IH), 6.9 (m, IH), 7.4 (d, IH), 7.43-7.5 (m, 2H), 7.67 (d, IH), 8.04 (d, IH), 8.3 (s, IH), 8.81 (s, IH). 
<!-- EPO <DP n="67"/>-->
[4] The product gave the following characterising data; NMR Spectrum: (DMSOdβ and CF<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub>D) 1.37-1.52 (m, IH), 1.66-1.78 (m, 2H), 1.79-1.94 (m, 3H), 2.93-3.13 (m, 2H), 3.21- 3.39 (m, 2H), 3.48-3.62 (m, 2H), 4.05 (s, 3H), 4.25 (d, 2H), 4.47-4.55 (m, IH), 6.9 (m, IH), 7.4 (d, IH), 7.45 (s, IH), 7.48 (d, IH), 7.67 (d, IH), 8.03 (m, IH), 8.28 (s, IH), 8.81 (s, IH); Mass Spectrum: M+H<sup>1"</sup> 449. 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="68"/>--><claim-text/><claim-text>CLAIMS</claim-text><claim-text>A quinazoline derivative of the Formula I</claim-text><claim-text><img id="imgf000068_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="77" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000068_0001.tif" inline="no" he="41"/></claim-text><claim-text>wherein m is 0, 1, 2 or 3; each R<sup>1</sup> group, which may be the same or different, is selected from halogeno, trifluoromethyl, cyano, isocyano, nitro, hydroxy, mercapto, amino, formyl, carboxy, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl, (l-6C)alkoxy, (2-6C)alkenyloxy, (2-6C)alkynyloxy, (l-6C)alkylthio, (l-6C)alkylsulphinyl, (l-6C)alkylsulphonyl, (l-6C)alkylamino, di-[(l-6C)alkyl] amino, (l-6C)alkoxycarbonyl, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyloxy, (2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-(2-6C)alkanoylamino, (3-6C)alkenoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl- (3-6C)alkenoylamino, (3-6C)alkynoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-(3-6C)alkynoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkylsulphamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]sulphamoyl, (l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino and N-(l-6C)alkyl-(l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino, or from a group of the formula :</claim-text><claim-text>Q^X<sup>1</sup> - wherein X<sup>1</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, S, SO, SO<sub>2</sub>, N(R<sup>4</sup>), CO, CH(OR<sup>4</sup>), CON(R<sup>4</sup>), N(R<sup>4</sup>)CO, SO<sub>2</sub>N(R<sup>4</sup>), N(R<sup>4</sup>)SO<sub>2</sub>, OC(R<sup>4</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, SC(R<sup>4</sup>)<sub>2</sub> and N(R<sup>4</sup>)C(R<sup>4</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, wherein R<sup>4</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>1</sup> is aryl, aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkyl- (l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkenyl, (3-7C)cycloalkenyl-(l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl, heteroaryl- (l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl, or (R^<sub>m</sub> is (l-3C)alkylenedioxy, and wherein adjacent carbon atoms in any (2-6C)alkylene chain within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent are optionally separated by the insertion into the chain of a group selected from O, S, SO, SO<sub>2</sub>, N(R<sup>5</sup>), CO, CH(OR<sup>5</sup>), CON(R<sup>5</sup>), N(R<sup>5</sup>)CO, SO<sub>2</sub>N(R<sup>5</sup>), N(R<sup>5</sup>)SO<sub>2</sub>, CH=CH and C≡C wherein R<sup>5</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl or, when the inserted group is N(R<sup>5</sup>), R<sup>5</sup> may also be (2-6C)alkanoyl, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="69"/>-->
 and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub>=CH- or HC≡C- group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears at the terminal CH = or HC≡ position a substituent selected from halogeno, carboxy, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkoxycarbonyl, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, amino-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkylamino-(l-6C)alkyl and di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino-(l-6C)alkyl or from a group of the formula :</claim-text><claim-text>Q<sup>2</sup>-X<sup>2</sup>- wherein X<sup>2</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from CO and N(R<sup>6</sup>)CO, wherein R<sup>6</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>2</sup> is aryl, aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl, heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl, and wherein any CH or CH<sub>3</sub> group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears on each said CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group one or more halogeno or (l-6C)alkyl substituents or a substituent selected from hydroxy, cyano, amino, carboxy, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkoxy, (l-6C)alkylthio, (l-6C)alkylsulphinyl, (l-6C)alkylsulphonyl, (l-6C)alkylamino, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino, (l-6C)alkoxycarbonyl, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyloxy, (2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-</claim-text><claim-text>(2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkylsulphamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]sulphamoyl, (l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino and N-(l-6C)alkyl-(l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino, or from a group of the formula :</claim-text><claim-text>-X<sup>3</sup>-Q<sup>3</sup> wherein X<sup>3</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, S, SO, SO<sub>2</sub>, N(R<sup>7</sup>), CO, CH(OR<sup>7</sup>),</claim-text><claim-text>CON(R<sup>7</sup>), N(R<sup>7</sup>)CO, SO<sub>2</sub>N(R<sup>7</sup>), N(R<sup>7</sup>)SO<sub>2</sub>, C(R<sup>7</sup>)<sub>2</sub>O, C(R<sup>7</sup>)<sub>2</sub>S and N(R<sup>7</sup>)C(R<sup>7</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, wherein R<sup>7</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>3</sup> is aryl, aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkyl- (l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkenyl, (3-7C)cycloalkenyl-(l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl, heteroaryl- (l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl, and wherein any aryl, heteroaryl or heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1, 2 or 3 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from halogeno, trifluoromethyl, cyano, nitro, hydroxy, amino, carboxy, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl, (l-6C)alkoxy, (2-6C)alkenyloxy, (2-6C)alkynyloxy, (l-6C)alkylthio, (l-6C)alkylsulphinyl, (l-6C)alkylsulρhonyl, (l-6C)alkylamino, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino, (l-6C)alkoxycarbonyl, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl,</claim-text><claim-text>N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyloxy, (2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-(2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkylsulphamoyl, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="70"/>-->
N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]sulphamoyl, (l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino and N-(l-6C)alkyl- (l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino, or from a group of the formula :</claim-text><claim-text>-X<sup>4</sup>-R<sup>8</sup> wherein X<sup>4</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O and N(R<sup>9</sup>), wherein R<sup>9</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and R<sup>8</sup> is halogeno-(l-6C)alkyl, hydroxy-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkoxy-(l-6C)alkyl, cyano-(l-6C)alkyl, amino-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkylamino-(l-6C)alkyl, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino- (l-6C)alkyl, (2-6C)alkanoylamino-(l-6C)alkyl or (l-6C)alkoxycarbonylamino-(l-6C)alkyl, or from a group of the formula :</claim-text><claim-text>-X<sup>5</sup>-Q<sup>4</sup> wherein X<sup>5</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, N(R<sup>10</sup>) and CO, wherein R<sup>10</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>4</sup> is aryl, aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl, heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl which optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from halogeno, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl and (l-6C)alkoxy, and wherein any heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo or thioxo substituents;</claim-text><claim-text>R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl; n is O, 1, 2 or 3; and</claim-text><claim-text>R<sup>3</sup> is halogeno, trifluoromethyl, cyano, nitro, hydroxy, amino, carboxy, carbamoyl, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl, (l-6C)alkoxy, (2-6C)alkenyloxy, (2-6C)alkynyloxy, (l-6C)alkylthio, (l-6C)alkylsulphinyl, (l-6C)alkylsulphonyl, (l-6C)alkylamino, di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino, (l-6C)alkoxycarbonyl, N-(l-6C)alkylcarbamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]carbamoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyl, (2-6C)alkanoyloxy, (2-6C)alkanoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-(2-6C)alkanoylamino, (3-6C)alkenoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl- (3-6C)alkenoylamino, (3-6C)alkynoylamino, N-(l-6C)alkyl-(3-6C)alkynoylamino,</claim-text><claim-text>N-(l-6C)alkylsulphamoyl, N,N-di-[(l-6C)alkyl]sulphamoyl, (l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino and N-(l-6C)alkyl-(l-6C)alkanesulphonylamino, or from a group of the formula :</claim-text><claim-text>-X<sup>6</sup>-R<sup>π</sup> wherein X<sup>6</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O and N(R<sup>12</sup>), wherein R<sup>12</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and R<sup>11</sup> is halogeno-(l-6C)alkyl, hydroxy-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkoxy-(l-6C)alkyl, cyano-(l-6C)alkyl, amino-(l-6C)alkyl, (l-6C)alkylamino-(l-6C)alkyl or di-[(l-6C)alkyl]amino-(l-6C)alkyl, or from a group of the formula : 
<!-- EPO <DP n="71"/>-->
 -X<sup>7</sup>-Q<sup>5</sup> wherein X<sup>7</sup> is a direct bond or is selected from O, S, SO, SO<sub>2</sub>, N(R<sup>13</sup>), CO, CH(OR<sup>13</sup>), CON(R<sup>13</sup>), N(R<sup>13</sup>)CO, SO<sub>2</sub>N(R<sup>13</sup>), N(R<sup>13</sup>)SO<sub>2</sub>, C(R<sup>13</sup>)<sub>2</sub>O, C(R<sup>13</sup>)<sub>2</sub>S and N(R<sup>13</sup>)C(R<sup>13</sup>)<sub>2</sub>, wherein R<sup>13</sup> is hydrogen or (l-6C)alkyl, and Q<sup>5</sup> is aryl, aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl, heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl, heterocyclyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl which optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from halogeno, (l-6C)alkyl, (2-8C)alkenyl, (2-8C)alkynyl and (l-6C)alkoxy, and any heterocyclyl group within Q<sup>5</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo or thioxo substituents, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>2. A quinazoline derivative of the Formula I according to claim 1 wherein : m is 1 or 2 and each R<sup>1</sup> group, which may be the same or different, is located at the 6- and/or 7-positions and is selected from hydroxy, amino, methyl, ethyl, propyl, butyl, methoxy, ethoxy, propoxy, isopropoxy, butoxy, methylamino, ethylamino, dimethylamino, diethylamino, acetamido, propionamido, 2-imidazol-l -ylethoxy, 2-(l,2,4-triazol-l-yl)ethoxy, 2-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy, 4-pyrrolidin-l-ylbutoxy, pyrrolidin-3-yloxy, pyrrolidin-2-ylmethoxy, 2-pyrrolidin-2-ylethoxy,</claim-text><claim-text>3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropoxy, 2-morpholinoethoxy, 3-morpholinopropoxy, 4-morpholinobutoxy, 2-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl)ethoxy, 3-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin- 4-yl)propoxy, 2-piperidinoethoxy, 3-piperidinopropoxy, 4-piperidinobutoxy, piperidin-3-yloxy, piperidin-4-yloxy, piperidin-3 -ylmethoxy, piperidin-4-ylmethoxy, 2-piperidin-3-ylethoxy, 3-piperidin-3-ylpropoxy, 2-piperidin-4-ylethoxy, 3-piperidin-4-ylpropoxy, 2-homopiperidin-l -ylethoxy, 3-homopiperidin-l-ylpropoxy, 2-piperazin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3 -piperazin- 1 -ylpropoxy, 4-piperazin- 1 -ylbutoxy, 2-homopiperazin- 1 -ylethoxy and 3 -homopiperazin- 1 -ylpropoxy, and wherein adjacent carbon atoms in any (2-6C)alkylene chain within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent are optionally separated by the insertion into the chain of a group selected from O, NH, CH=CH and C≡C, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent optionally bears on each said CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>3</sub> group a substituent selected from hydroxy, amino, methoxy, methylsulphonyl, methylamino, dimethylamino, diethylamino, N-ethyl-N-methylamino, N-isopropyl-N-methylamino, N-methyl-N-propylamino and acetoxy; 
<!-- EPO <DP n="72"/>-->
 and wherein any heteroaryl or heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from fluoro, chloro, trifluoromethyl, hydroxy, amino, carbamoyl, methyl, ethyl, methoxy, N-methylcarbamoyl and N,N-dimethylcarbamoyl and a pyrrolidin-2-yl, piperidin-3-yl, piperidin-4-yl, piperazin-1-yl or homopiperazin-1 -yl group within a R<sup>1</sup> substituent is optionally N-substituted with 2-methoxyethyl, 3-methoxypropyl, cyanomethyl, 2-aminoethyl, 3-aminopropyl, 2-methylaminoethyl, 3-methylaminopropyl, 2-dimethylaminoethyl, 3-dimethylaminopropyl, 2-pyrrolidin-l-ylethyl, 3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropyl, 2-morpholinoethyl, 3-morpholinopropyl, 2-piperidinoethyl, 3-piperidinopropyl, 2-piperazin-l-ylethyl or 3-piperazin-l-ylpropyl, the last 8 of which substituents each optionally bears 1 or 2 substituents, which may be the same or different, selected from fluoro, chloro, methyl and methoxy, and wherein any heterocyclyl group within a substituent on R<sup>1</sup> optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo substituents; R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen; n is 0 or 1 and the R group, if present, is located at the 5- or 6-position of the benzofuran ring and is selected from fluoro, chloro, trifluoromethyl, cyano, hydroxy, methyl, ethyl, vinyl, allyl, ethynyl, methoxy and ethoxy; or a pharmaceutically-acceptable acid-addition salt thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>3. A quinazoline derivative of the Formula I according to claim 1 wherein : m is 2 and the first R<sup>1</sup> group is located at the 6-position and is selected from hydroxy, methoxy, ethoxy and propoxy, and the second R<sup>1</sup> group is located at the 7-position and is selected from 2-dimethylaminoethoxy, 3-dimethylaminopropoxy, 4-dimethylaminobutoxy, 2-diethylaminoethoxy, 3-diethylaminopropoxy, 4-diethylaminobutoxy,</claim-text><claim-text>2-diisopropylaminoethoxy, 3-diisopropylaminopropoxy, 4-diisopropylaminobutoxy, 2-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)ethoxy, 3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy, 4-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)butoxy, 2-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3 -pyrrolidin- 1 -ylpropoxy, 4-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylbutoxy, pyrrolidin-3 -yloxy, N-methylpyrrolidin-3-yloxy, pyrrolidin-2-ylmethoxy, 2-pyrrolidin-2-ylethoxy, 3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropoxy, 2-morpholinoethoxy, 3-morpholinopropoxy, 4-morpholinobutoxy, 2-(l , l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l ,4-thiazin-4-yl)ethoxy, 3-(l , l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l ,4-thiazin- 
<!-- EPO <DP n="73"/>-->
4-yl)propoxy, 2-piperidinoethoxy, 3-piperidinopropoxy, 4-piperidinobutoxy, piperidin-3-yloxy, N-methylpiperidin-3-yloxy, piperidin-4-yloxy, N-methylpiperidin-4-yloxy, piperidin-3-ylmethoxy, N-methylpiperidin-3 -ylmethoxy, piperidin-4-ylmethoxy, N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy, 2-piperidin-3-ylethoxy, 2-(N-methylpiperidin-3-yl)ethoxy, 3-piperidin-3-ylpropoxy, 3-(N-methylpiperidin-3-yl)propoxy, 2-piperidin-4-ylethoxy, 2-(N-methylpiperidin-4-yl)ethoxy, 3-piperidin-4-ylpropoxy, 3-(N-methylpiperidin-4-yl)propoxy, 2-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)ethoxy, 3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy, 4-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)butoxy, 2-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin- 1 -yl)ethoxy , 3 -(4-cyanomethylpiperazin- 1 -yl)propoxy, 4-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin- 1 -yl)butoxy , 2- [2-(4-methylpiperazin- 1 -yl)ethoxy] ethoxy, 2-methylsulphonylethoxy and 3-methylsulphonylpropoxy, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> group within the second R<sup>1</sup> group that is attached to two carbon atoms optionally bears a hydroxy group or acetoxy group on said CH<sub>2</sub> group, and wherein any heterocyclyl group within the second R group optionally bears 1 or 2 oxo substituents;</claim-text><claim-text>R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen; and n is 0 or n is 1 and the R<sup>3</sup> group is located at the 5- or 6-position of the benzofuran ring and is selected from fluoro, chloro, trifluoromethyl, cyano, methyl, ethyl, ethynyl, methoxy and ethoxy; or a pharmaceutically-acceptable acid-addition salt thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>4. A quinazoline derivative of the Formula I according to claim 1 wherein : m is 2 and the first R<sup>1</sup> group is located at the 6-position and is selected from hydroxy, methoxy, ethoxy and propoxy, and the second R<sup>1</sup> group is located at the 7-position and is selected from 2-dimethylaminoethoxy, 3-dimethylaminopropoxy, 2-diethylaminoethoxy, 3 -diethylaminopropoxy, 2-diisopropylaminoethoxy, 3 -diisopropylaminopropoxy , 2-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)ethoxy, 3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy, 2-(N-isobutyl-N-methylamino)ethoxy, 3-(N-isobutyl-N-methylamino)propoxy, 2-(N-allyl-N-methylamino)ethoxy, 3-(N-allyl-N-methylamino)propoxy, 2-pyrrolidin- 1 -ylethoxy, 3 -pyrrolidin-l -ylpropoxy, 2-pyrrolidin-2-ylethoxy, 3-pyrrolidin-2-ylpropoxy, 2-morpholinoethoxy, 3-morpholinopropoxy, 2-(l , l-dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin-4-yl)ethoxy, 3-(l , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin- 
<!-- EPO <DP n="74"/>-->
4-yl)propoxy, 2-piperidinoethoxy, 3-piperidinopropoxy, piperidin-3-ylmethoxy, N-methylpiperidin-3 -ylmethoxy, piperidin-4-ylmethoxy, N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy, 2-piperidin-3 -ylethoxy, 2-(N-methylpiperidin-3-yl)ethoxy, 3-piperidin-3-ylpropoxy, 3 -(N-methylpiperidin-3 -yl)propoxy, 2-piperidin-4-ylethoxy , 2-(N-methylpiperidin-4-yl)ethoxy, 3-piperidin-4-ylpropoxy, 3-(N-methylpiperidin-4-yl)propoxy, 3-homopiperidinopropoxy, 2-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)ethoxy, 3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy, 2-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin- 1 -yl)ethoxy and 3 -(4-cyanomethylpiperazin- 1 -yl)propoxy, and wherein any CH<sub>2</sub> group within the second R<sup>1</sup> group that is attached to two carbon atoms optionally bears a hydroxy group or acetoxy group on said CH<sub>2</sub> group,</claim-text><claim-text>R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen; and n is 0 or n is 1 or 2 and an R<sup>3</sup> group, if present, is located at the 5- or 6-position of the benzofuran ring and is selected from fluoro, chloro, bromo, trifluoromethyl, cyano, methyl, ethyl, ethynyl, methoxy and ethoxy; or a pharmaceutically-acceptable acid-addition salt thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>5. A quinazoline derivative of the Formula I according to claim 1 wherein : m is 2 and the first R<sup>1</sup> group is a 6-methoxy group and the second R<sup>1</sup> group is located at the 7-position and is selected from 3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy, 3-(N-isobutyl-N-methylamino)propoxy, 3 -pyrrolidin-l -ylpropoxy, 3-morpholinopropoxy, 3-(l,l-dioxotetrahydro-4H-l,4-thiazin-4-yl)propoxy, 3-piperidinopropoxy, piperidin-4-ylmethoxy, N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy, 3 -homopiperidinopropoxy, 2-(4-methylpiperazin- 1 -yl)ethoxy, 3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy and 3-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy, and wherein any CH group within the second R<sup>1</sup> group that is attached to two carbon atoms optionally bears a hydroxy or acetoxy group on said CH<sub>2</sub> group; R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen; and n is 0 or n is 1 and the R<sup>3</sup> group is located at the 5-position of the benzofuran ring and is selected from fluoro and chloro; or a pharmaceutically-acceptable acid-addition salt thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>6. A quinazoline derivative of the Formula I according to claim 1 selected from:- 
<!-- EPO <DP n="75"/>-->
4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-6-methoxy-7-(3-morpholinopropoxy)quinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>4-(4-benzof uranylamino)-7- [3 -( 1 , 1 -dioxotetrahydro-4H- 1 ,4-thiazin-4-yl)propoxy] -</claim-text><claim-text>6-methoxyquinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-6-methoxy-7-(3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)quinazoline, 4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-6-methoxy-7-[3-(4-methylpiperazin-l-yl)propoxy]quinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-6-methoxy-7-(3-piperidinopropoxy)quinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-6-methoxy-7-(N-methylpiperidin-4-ylmethoxy)quinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>4-(5-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylamino)-6-methoxy-7-(3-morpholinopropoxy)quinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>7-(2-acetoxy-3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)-4-(3-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylamino)- 6-methoxyquinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>7-[2-acetoxy-3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy]-4-(3-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylamino)-</claim-text><claim-text>6-methoxyquinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>7- [2-acetoxy-3-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin- 1 -yl)propoxy] -4-(3-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylamino)-</claim-text><claim-text>6-methoxyquinazoline, 7-(2-acetoxy-3-piperidinopropoxy)-4-(3-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylamino)-6-methoxyquinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>7-(2-acetoxy-3-morpholinopropoxy)-4-(3-chlorobenzofuran-4-ylamino)-</claim-text><claim-text>6-methoxyquinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7-(2-hydroxy-3-pyrrolidin-l-ylpropoxy)-6-methoxyquinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7-[2-hydroxy-3-(N-isopropyl-N-methylamino)propoxy]- 6-methoxyquinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7-[3-(4-cyanomethylpiperazin-l-yl)-2-hydroxypropoxy]-</claim-text><claim-text>6-methoxyquinazoline,</claim-text><claim-text>4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7-(2-hydroxy-3-piperidinopropoxy)-6-methoxyquinazoline and</claim-text><claim-text>4-(4-benzofuranylamino)-7-(2-hydroxy-3-morpholinopropoxy)-6-methoxyquinazoline; or a pharmaceutically-acceptable acid-addition salt thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>7. A process for the preparation of a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, according to claim 1 which comprises :-</claim-text><claim-text>(a) the reaction of a quinazoline of the Formula It 
<!-- EPO <DP n="76"/>--><img id="imgf000076_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="49" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000076_0001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/></claim-text><claim-text>II wherein L is a displaceable group and m and R<sup>1</sup> have any of the meanings defined in claim 1 except that any functional group is protected if necessary, with an aniline of the Formula IH</claim-text><claim-text><img id="imgf000076_0002" orientation="portrait" wi="62" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000076_0002.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
 wherein R<sup>2</sup>, n and R<sup>3</sup> have any of the meanings defined in claim 1 except that any functional group is protected if necessary, whereafter any protecting group that is present is removed by conventional means;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) for the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein at least one R<sup>1</sup> group is a group of the formula 
<img id="imgf000076_0003" orientation="portrait" wi="13" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000076_0003.tif" inline="no" he="6"/>
 wherein Q<sup>1</sup> is an aryl-(l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkyl-(l-6C)alkyl, (3-7C)cycloalkenyl- (l-6C)alkyl, heteroaryl-(l-6C)alkyl or heterocyclyl-(l-6C)alkyl group and X<sup>1</sup> is an oxygen atom, the coupling of a quinazoline of the Formula V</claim-text><claim-text><img id="imgf000076_0004" orientation="portrait" wi="74" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000076_0004.tif" inline="no" he="40"/></claim-text><claim-text>V wherein m, R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup>, n and R<sup>3</sup> have any of the meanings defined in claim 1 except that any functional group is protected if necessary, with an appropriate alcohol wherein any functional group is protected if necessary whereafter any protecting group that is present is removed by conventional means; 
<!-- EPO <DP n="77"/>-->
(c) for the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein an R<sup>1</sup> group contains a primary or secondary amino group, the cleavage of the corresponding compound of the Formula I wherein the R<sup>1</sup> group contains a protected primary or secondary amino group;</claim-text><claim-text>(d) for the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein an R<sup>1</sup> group contains a (l-6C)alkoxy or substituted (l-6C)alkoxy group or a (l-6C)alkylamino or substituted</claim-text><claim-text>(l-6C)alkylamino group, the alkylation of a quinazoline derivative of the formula I wherein the R<sup>1</sup> group contains a hydroxy group or a primary or secondary amino group as appropriate;</claim-text><claim-text>(e) for the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein R<sup>1</sup> is an amino-hydroxy-disubstituted (l-6C)alkoxy group, the reaction of a compound of the Formula I wherein the R<sup>1</sup> group contains an epoxy-substituted (l-6C)alkoxy group with a heterocyclyl compound or an appropriate amine; or</claim-text><claim-text>(f) for the production of those compounds of the Formula I wherein an R<sup>1</sup> group contains a hydroxy group, the cleavage of the corresponding compound of the Formula I wherein the R<sup>1</sup> group contains a protected hydroxy group; and when a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt of a quinazoline derivative of the</claim-text><claim-text>Formula I is required it may be obtained using a conventional procedure.</claim-text><claim-text>8. A pharmaceutical composition which comprises a quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined in claim 1 in association with a pharmaceutically-acceptable diluent or carrier.</claim-text><claim-text>9. A quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined in claim 1 for use in a method of treatment of the human or animal body by therapy.</claim-text><claim-text>10. The use quinazoline derivative of the Formula I, or a pharmaceutically-acceptable salt thereof, as defined in claim 1 in the manufacture of a medicament for use as an anti-invasive agent in the containment and/or treatment of solid tumour disease. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>