<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-0969046-A1" country="EP" doc-number="0969046" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22330769" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000105"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-0969046-A1" status="new" fvid="22724723"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0969046</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000105</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99112336-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99112336</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990628</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-11000898-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>11000898</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19980702</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/30        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/40        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   3/30+L67/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   3/40+L67/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  67/02+B2A1</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Polyesterzusammensetzung mit hoher Dichte</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">High density polyester composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition de polyestère à haute densité</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0423509-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0423509</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0676442-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0676442</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HNA HOLDINGS INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HNA HOLDINGS, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HNA Holdings, Inc.</last-name><address><street>30 Independence Boulevard</street><city>Warren, New Jersey 07060</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>IMES ROBERT H</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LU MENGSHI</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>IMES, ROBERT H.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LU, MENGSHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>IMES, ROBERT H.</last-name><address><street>462 Milcrip Road</street><city>Bridgewater, NJ</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>LU, MENGSHI</last-name><address><street>1275 Roack Avenue, Apt. FF4</street><city>North Plainfield, NJ</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Aulmich, Gerhard, Dr.</last-name><address><street>Ticona GmbH Patent and License Dept. Lyoner Str. 38</street><city>60528 Frankfurt am Main</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A highly filled, ceramic-like thermoplastic polyester resin molding
composition, characterized as containing a polyethylene terephthalate base resin, an
impact modifier system containing a copolymer and terpolymer, glass fibers, and a
mineral filler. Shaped articles prepared from the molding composition exhibit a
ceramic appearance and feel, glossy surface finish, improved impact strength, and
high specific gravity.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">Field of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to high density, improved impact strength polyester
molding compositions suitable for the preparation of shaped articles. Polyester resins
may be combined with an impact modifier system, and certain fillers to prepare the
molding composition exhibiting improved mechanical properties. Molded articles
prepared from polyester compositions exhibit excellent mechanical properties, enhanced
surface gloss, increased density, and improved impact strength. The compositions are
suitable for the preparation of shaped articles exhibiting ceramic-like properties, e.g.
gaming chips, ceramic insulators, tableware, billiard balls, and other applications wherein
a ceramic substitute is desirable.</p><heading><u style="single">Background of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0002">Polyester resins, particularly polybutylene terephthalate (PBT) and polyethylene
terephthalate (PET), are suitable for the preparation of molded articles because of its
partially crystalline structure. Molded articles prepared from PBT, as a base resin, and
various additives are known to exhibit good mechanical properties when subjected to
severe mechanical stress and extreme heat. PBT/PET blends have been combined with
other materials to improve the mechanical and chemical properties, i.e. molding
characteristics, impact strength, thermal stability, flame stability, warping and surface
appearance, for a host of applications. Generally, a plethora of materials have been 
blended with PBT and PET in an attempt to improve the properties of the blend without
detracting from the characteristic properties provided by the resin.</p><p num="0003">The use of glass fibers as a PET reinforcing material is generally discussed in U.S.
Patent No. 3,368,995 to Furakawa <i>et al</i>. The inclusion of barium sulfate to provide
highly filled PET/PBT blends is mentioned in U.S. Patent No. 5,149,734 to Fisher <i>et
al</i>., and U.S. Patent Nos. 5,214,088 and 5,395,875 to Allen <i>et al</i>. Japan Laid-Open
Patent No. 1-247454, published October 3, 1989 references an impact modifier
additive for polyester resin compositions, characterized as a mixture of a copolymer
of ethylene/ glycidyl(meth)acrylate and a copolymer of ethylene/(meth)acrylic acid.
Lu <i>et al</i>., U.S. Patent No. 4,341,758 teaches the addition of a nucleating agent to
polyester blends to provide smooth, glossy surfaces to molded articles prepared
therefrom. Kirsch <i>et al</i>., U.S. Patent No. 5,298,546 suggests a polyalkylene
terephthalate blend containing barium sulfate, reinforcing materials, and an elastomer-modifier
based on (meth)acrylates.</p><p num="0004">It is desirous to provide a PET resin composition that is suitable for the
preparation of shaped articles exhibiting a combination of high surface gloss,
improved impact strength, high density, and ceramic-like feel. The composition
should provide the benefits of a PET-filler material and be a suitable substitute for
ceramic materials.</p><heading><u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0005">The present invention is directed to a highly filled, ceramic-like thermoplastic
PET molding resin composition suitable for the preparation of shaped articles
exhibiting high surface gloss, improved impact strength, and a ceramic-like feel. The 
composition may be characterized as containing at least about 17.0 weight percent of
polyethylene terephthalate having an intrinsic viscosity of at least about 0.4 dl/g; at
least about 60 weight percent of barium sulfate; at least about 6.0 weight percent of a
glass filler; and an impact modifier system comprising at least about 0.5 weight
percent of a functionalized or unfunctionalized ethylene/glycidyl methacrylate/methyl
acrylate terpolymer; and at least about 3.5 weight percent of an ethylene/acrylic ester
copolymer, based on a total of 100 weight percent, wherein shaped articles prepared
from the composition exhibits a glossy surface, high impact strength and specific
gravity. The composition is suitable for the preparation of shaped articles possessing
PET qualities, a ceramic appearance and specific gravity, and is a suitable substitute
for ceramic materials.</p><heading><u style="single">Detailed Description of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0006">Particularly, the invention is directed to a highly filled, ceramic-like
thermoplastic PET resin composition, characterized as containing about 17.0 to about
24.0 weight percent of polyethylene terephthalate having an intrinsic viscosity of from
about 0.4 to about 1.5 dl/g; about 60 to about 70 weight percent of barium sulfate;
from about 6 to about 10 weight percent of a glass filler; and an impact modifier
system comprising from about 0.5 to about 2.0 weight percent of a functionalized or
unfunctionalized ethylene/glycidyl methacrylate/methyl acrylate terpolymer, and from
about 3.5 to about 6.0 weight percent of an ethylene/acrylic ester copolymer, based on
a total of 100 weight percent of the composition, wherein shaped articles prepared
from the composition exhibits a glossy surface, a specific gravity of from about 1.7 to
about 3.0, a Notched Izod of from about 0.7 to about 0.8 ft-lb/in, an Unnotched Izod
of from about 2.0 to about 2.7 ft-lb/in (both measured by ASTM D 256), and a
Gardner Impact from about 5.4 to about 6.2 in-lb (measured by ASTM D 5420). </p><p num="0007">One preferred embodiment of the invention is directed to a highly filled,
ceramic-like thermoplastic PET resin composition characterized as containing about
21.6 weight percent of polyethylene terephthalate having an intrinsic viscosity of
about 0.68 to about 0.86 dl/g; about 65 weight percent of barium sulfate; about 8.0
weight percent of a glass filler; and an impact modifier system comprising about 1.1
weight percent of an ethylene/glycidyl methacrylate/methyl acrylate terpolymer, and
about 4.3 weight percent of an ethylene/acrylic ester copolymer, based on a total of
100 weight percent of the composition, wherein shaped articles prepared from the
composition exhibits a glossy surface, a specific gravity of about 2.6, a Notched Izod
of about 0.72 ft-lb/in, an Unnotched Izod of about 2.4 ft-lb/in, and a Gardner Impact
about 5.8 in-lb. Yet another preferred embodiment provides a highly filled, ceramic-like
thermoplastic PET resin composition, comprising about 21.6 weight percent of
polyethylene terephthalate having an intrinsic viscosity of about 0.86 dl/g; about 65
weight percent of barium sulfate; about 8.0 weight percent of a glass filler; and an
impact modifier system comprising about 1.1 weight percent of an ethylene/glycidyl
methacrylate/methyl acrylate terpolymer, and about 4.3 weight percent of an
ethylene/acrylic ester copolymer, based on a total of 100 weight percent of the
composition, wherein shaped articles prepared from the composition exhibits a glossy
surface, a specific gravity of about 2.6, a Notched Izod of about 0.7 ft-lb/in, an
Unnotched Izod of about 2.7 ft-lb/in, and a Gardner Impact about 5.4 in-lb. </p><heading><u style="single">Polyethylene terephthalate</u></heading><p num="0008">Generally, a class of polyesters which may be useful to form the highly filled,
impact modified PET may be prepared in a conventional manner such as by direct
esterification of purified terephthalic acid and ethylene glycol or transesterification of
dimethyl terephthalate with ethylene glycol as described in U.S. Patent No. 2,465,319
to Whinfield <i>et al</i>. incorporated herein by reference thereto. Typically, polyethylene
terephthalate useful in the invention may contain at least about 97 percent of repeating
units of the general formula:
<img id="img-00050001" orientation="unknown" wi="95" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050001.tif" inline="no" he="30"/></p><p num="0009">With the remainder being minor amounts of ester-forming components, and ethylene
terephthalate wherein up to about 10 mole percent of the copolymer is prepared from
the monomer units of diethylene glycol; 1,3-propanediol; 1,4-butanediol;
polytetramethylene ether glycol; methyl propanediol; polyethylene glycol;
polypropylene glycol; 1,4-hydroxymethylcyclohexane and the like, substituted for the
glycol moiety in the preparation of the copolymer and/or isophthalic; bibenzoic;
naphthalene 1,4- or 2,6-dicarboxylic adipic; sebacic; decane-1,10-dicarboxylic acid,
and the like substituted for the acid moeity in the preparation of the copolymer.
Polyethylene terephthalate resins can be prepared in accordance with U.S. Patent No.
3,047,534 incorporated herein by reference thereto. The preferred PET, Impet® 100,
is an unfilled polyester manufactured and distributed by Ticona LLC of Summit, New
Jersey. Impet 100 may be identified as exhibiting physical properties as follows: 
density of 1.39 g/cm<sup>3</sup>; melt point of 252° C; L color (amorphous) of 80; b* color
(amorphous) of 3; and melt viscosity at 1000 sec<sup>-1</sup> at 280° C of 4560 poise.</p><p num="0010">Generally, the intrinsic viscosity of the polymeric material of the invention is
from about 0.4 to about 1.5 dl/g as measured in accordance with ASTM D 2857.
Typically, the intrinsic viscosity may be from about 0.6 to about 1.2 dl/g, and
preferably from about 0.68 to about 0.86 dl/g.</p><heading><u style="single">Impact Modifier System</u></heading><p num="0011">The impact modifier system of the invention is believed to provide the
composition with its impact resistant characteristics. Suitable impact modifiers may
be selected from copolymers of ethylene/acrylic ester, and terpolymers of
ethylene/acrylic ester/glycidyl methacrylate. Generally, the impact modifier system
may be incorporated into the resin composition in amounts of from about 4.0 to about
6.0 weight percent, based on a 100 total weight percent of the composition, at a ratio
of about 1:4 of terpolymer to copolymer. Typically, the impact modifier system may
be incorporated into the resin composition in amounts of from about 4.2 to about 4.6
weight percent, and preferably 4.4 weight percent. According to the preferred
embodiment of the invention, the impact modifier system may contain 1.1 weight
percent of the terpolymer and 4.3 weight percent of the copolymer.</p><p num="0012">The preferred terpolymer is marketed under the trade name Lotader® AX8900
and is distributed by Elf Atochem North America, Inc. of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
The preferred copolymer is marketed under the trade name Lotryl® 29MA03 and is
also distributed by Elf Atochem North America, Inc. of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. </p><p num="0013">Lotader® AX8900 (CAS #51541-08-3), identified as containing 26 weight
percent of methyl acrylate comonomer and 7.25 weight percent of glycidyl
methacrylate/methyl acrylate, exhibits a melt index (190° C, 2.16kg ASTM D 1238)
of 6.5, a melting point (DSC) of 149°F, a Vicat Softening Point (ASTM D 1525 -1kg)
of &lt;100, a tensile strength at break (ASTM D 638) of 810 psi, an elongation at break
(ASTM D 638) of 900, and a Hardness A (ASTM D 2240) of 70. Lotryl® 29MA03
(CAS #25103-74-6), a copolymer of ethylene/acrylic ester, identified as containing 27
to 31 percent of the ester (Elf Atochem (IR), exhibits a melt index (g/10mm)(ASTM
D 1238, ISO Standard 133) of 2 to 3.5, a melting point (DSC) of 61° C, and a Viscat
Softening Point (ASTM D 1525, ISO Standard 306) of &lt;40° C.</p><p num="0014">Generally, the impact modifier system may contain a combination of at least
about 1.0 weight percent of an ethylene/glycidyl methacrylate/methyl acrylate
terpolymer, and at least about 4.0 weight percent of an ethylene/acrylic ester
copolymer, based on 100 total weight percent of the composition. Typically, the
impact modifier system may contain from about 1.0 to about 1.3 weight percent of the
an ethylene/ glycidyl methacrylate/methyl acrylate terpolymer, and from about 4.0 to
about 4.5 weight percent of the ethylene/acrylic ester copolymer; and preferably,
about 1.1 weight percent of the ethylene/glycidyl methacrylate/methyl acrylate
terpolymer and ethylene/acrylic ester copolymer, based on 100 total weight percent of
the composition. The preferred total weight of the impact modifier system may be
about 5.4 weight percent of the two (2) above-identified components. </p><heading><u style="single">The Barium Sulfate</u></heading><p num="0015">Barium sulfate is believed to provide the molding composition of the
invention with its highly filled, high specific gravity characteristics and ceramic-like
properties. Generally, the barium sulfate, barytes, useful for the invention may be
present in an amount of at least about 60 weight percent, based on a total of 100
weight percent of the composition. Typically, the barium sulfate may be present in an
amount of from about 60 to about 70 weight percent, based on a total of 100 weight
percent of the composition, and preferably in an amount of about 65.0 weight percent.
Suitable barium sulfate particles may range in size of from about 0.5 to about 1.5 µm.
The preferred barium sulfate suitable for the invention is Barite 1090P marketed by
Polar Minerals of Mount Vernon, Indiana. Barite, barium sulfate, is known to exhibit
an average particle size of about 0.9 µm (about 5 µm top size).</p><heading><u style="single">The Fiberglass</u></heading><p num="0016">Glass fibers are believed to enhance the reinforcing properties of the present
invention. Glass fibers of the present invention will generally exhibit an average
standard diameter of from about 5 to about 30 microns. Typically, the glass fibers
will exhibit an average diameter of from about 10 to about 20 microns, and preferably
from about 12 to about 18 microns. For the purpose of the invention, it is
conventional to use filamentous glass in the form of chopped strands of from about
1.5 mm to about 10 mm in length; typically, from about 2 to about 8 mm and
preferably of about 4 mm in length. The aspect ration of the glass fibers (the avenge
length of the diameter of the fibers) of about 5. Generally, glass fibers may be present
in an amount of at least about 6.0 weight percent. Typically, the amount of glass
fibers in the molding composition may be from about 6.0 to about 10.0 weight 
percent, based on a total of 100 weight percent of the composition, and preferably, in
an amount of about 8.0 weight percent. A preferred glass fiber is marketed by
Owens-Coming Fiberglas Corporation of Toledo, Ohio under the trade name
Fiberglass OCF 183F-14C. Fiberglass OCF 183F-14C is characterized as an E-glass
composition exhibiting an average fiber diameter of about 14 microns containing an
amino silane coupling agent and a proprietary sizing agent.</p><heading><u style="single">Other Additives</u></heading><p num="0017">Other additives in effective amounts that do not distract from the novelty or
mechanical properties of the molding composition may be incorporated therein. The
additive pentaerythritol tetrastearate is a dispersing agent for the barium sulfate in the
base resin an will also function as an external lubricant or mold release agent.
Suitable antioxidants include phosphites, hindered phenols, secondary amines and the
like, which may be added in effective amounts to retard oxidative degradation. A
suitable antioxidant is tetrakis(methylene-3(3',5'-di-tert-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)
propionate)methane. Flame retardant agents and pigments may be added in effective
amounts. Suitable flame retardant agents for the invention are disclosed in U.S.
Patent Nos. 3,334,154; 4,020,124; and 4,785,592. External lubricants including fatty
acids, fatty esters, wax esters, glycerol esters, glycol esters, fatty alcohol esters, fatty
alcohols, fatty amides, metallic stearates, and waxes are not required components of
the invention but may be utilized as necessary as mold release agents. In addition
other components well known in the art such as pigments, ultraviolet stabilizers,
antistatic agents, etc. which do not detract from the invention may be added thereto. </p><p num="0018">Suitable uses for the highly filler thermoplastic resin molding composition
include all applications wherein it is desirous to provide a thermoplastic resin
substitute for ceramic materials. In additional to the mechanical properties offered by
PET, the inventive molding resin possesses improved impact strength and a high
specific gravity. The composition is suitable for the preparation of gaming chips,
electrical insulation pans, tableware and billiard balls.</p><p num="0019">The following examples are presented as specific illustrations of the claimed
invention. It should be understood, however, that the invention is not limited to the
specific details set forth in the examples.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0020">To prepare a blend of the highly filled, ceramic-like thermoplastic, polyester
resin (0.68 IV) composition, the following components were utilized:
<sl><li>a) 4.32 lbs. of Impet 100 (PET1511), 0.68 IV</li><li>b) 1.6 lbs. of Fiberglas OCF 183F-14C, 4mm length;</li><li>c) 13 lbs. of Barite 1090P;</li><li>d) 99.79 gm. of Lotader AX8900; and</li><li>e) 390.1 gm. of Lotryl 29 MA 03.</li></sl></p><p num="0021">The above ingredients were blended in dry form and then extruded in a 30 mm
Werner and Pfleiderer twin screw ZSK 30 extruder, heated and purged with PET
operated at an avenge temperature of about 260° C, a die temperature of about
267° C, screw speed of about 250 rpm, torque of about 38%, die pressure of about
235 psi, and vacuum of about 28 mm Hg. Thereafter, the extruded material was
pelletized and injection molded on a 22S Boy injection molder under the following
conditions: <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Barrel temperature</b>,</entry><entry align="center">(°C)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zone #1</entry><entry align="left">265</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zone #2</entry><entry align="left">270</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zone #3</entry><entry align="left">275</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>Mold Temp</b>,</entry> <entry align="center">(°C)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Field</entry><entry align="left">120</entry></row> <row><entry align="left">Movable</entry> <entry align="left">120</entry> </row><row><entry align="center"><b>Pressure</b>,</entry><entry align="center">(%)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Inject #1</entry><entry align="left">63</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>Speeds</b>,</entry><entry align="center">(%)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Screw</entry><entry align="left">50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Inject #1</entry><entry align="left">90</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>Time</b>,</entry><entry align="center">sec</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Inject #1</entry><entry align="left">9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cool</entry><entry align="left">19</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0022">The molded parts were ASTM D 638 Type 1 tensile bars, 2 in. disks and 5 in. flex
bars. The mechanical properties of the test specimens are listed in the Table
hereinafter. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0023">To prepare a blend of the highly filled, ceramic-like thermoplastic, polyester
resin (0.86 IV) composition, the following components were utilized:
<sl><li>a) 4.32 lbs. of PET 0.86 IV;</li><li>b) 1.6 lbs. of Fiberglas OCF 183F-14C, 4mm length;</li><li>c) 13 lbs. of Barite 1090P;</li><li>d) 99.79 gm. of Lotader AX8900; and</li><li>e) 390.1 gm. of Lotryl 29 MA 03.</li></sl></p><p num="0024">The components were blended, extruded and molded into tensile bars, disks, and flex
bars in accordance with the procedure of Example 1. Results of mechanical
properties of the test specimens are listed in the Table.</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Example 3</u></heading><p num="0025">To illustrate the benefits of the impact modifier system, a PET comparative
composition, 0.68 IV, was prepared in accordance with the procedure of Example 1;
titanium dioxide acts as a pigment additive. The components and amounts of the
composition are as follows:
<sl><li>a) 4.96 lbs. of Impet 100 (PET1511), 0.68 IV;</li><li>b) 1.6 lbs. of Fiberglas OCF 183F-14C, 4mm length;</li><li>c) 12.6 lbs. of Barite 1090P; and</li><li>d) 190.51 gm. of titanium dioxide (in 381.02 gm. of polybutylene
terephthalate (PBT) concentrate).</li></sl></p><p num="0026">The components were blended, extruded and molded into tensile bars, disks, and flex
bars in accordance with the procedure of Example 1. Results of mechanical
properties of the test specimens are listed in the Table.</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Example 4</u></heading><p num="0027">A second PET comparative composition, 0.86 IV, have no impact modifier
system therein was prepared in accordance with Example 1, the components are as
follows:
<sl><li>a) 4.96 lbs. of 0,86 IV;</li><li>b) 1.6 lbs. of Fiberglas OCF 183F-14C, 4mm length;</li><li>c) 12.6 lbs. of Barite 1090P; and</li><li>d) 190.51 gm. of titanium dioxide (in 381.02 gm. of PBT concentrate).</li></sl></p><p num="0028">These components were blended, extruded and molded into tensile bars, disks, and
flex bars in accordance with the procedure of Example 1. Results of mechanical
properties of the test specimens are listed in the Table. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Impact Modified PET Formulation (wt %)</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4">PET Based Formulation (wt %)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">Comp. 3</entry><entry align="center">Comp. 4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PBT 0.76 IV</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2.2</entry><entry align="center">2.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PET 0.68 IV</entry><entry align="center">21.6</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">24.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PET 0.86 IV</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">21.6</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">24.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glass Fiber</entry><entry align="center">8.0</entry><entry align="center">8.0</entry><entry align="center">8.0</entry><entry align="center">8.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">TiO<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lotader AX8900</entry><entry align="center">1.1</entry><entry align="center">1.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lotryl 29 MA 03</entry><entry align="center">4.3</entry><entry align="center">4.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">BaSO<sub>4</sub></entry><entry align="center">65.0</entry><entry align="center">65.0</entry><entry align="center">63.0</entry><entry align="center">63.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Specific Gravity</entry><entry align="center">2.6</entry><entry align="center">2.6</entry><entry align="center">2.6</entry><entry align="center">2.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Izod, Notched (ft-lb./in)</entry><entry align="center">0.7</entry><entry align="center">0.7</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Izod, Unnotched (ft-lb./in)</entry><entry align="center">2.4</entry><entry align="center">2.7</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">1.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Impact, Gardner (in-lb.)</entry><entry align="center">5.8</entry><entry align="center">5.4</entry><entry align="center">3.6</entry><entry align="center">3.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Surface Appearance</entry><entry align="center">Glossy</entry><entry align="center">Glossy</entry><entry align="center">Glossy</entry><entry align="center">Glossy</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0029">The results of the examples illustrate that shaped articles prepared from compositions
containing the impact modifier system, as compared to examples not containing the
system, exhibit improved Notched and Unnotched Izods, and Gardner Impacts.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A highly filled, ceramic-like thermoplastic polyester resin composition,
comprising at least about 17.0 weight percent of polyethylene terephthalate having
an intrinsic viscosity of at least about 0.4 dl/g; at least about 60 weight percent of
barium sulfate; at least about 6.0 weight percent of a glass filler; and an impact
modifier system comprising at least about 0.5 weight percent of a functional or
non-functional ethylene/glycidyl methacrylate/methyl acrylate terpolymer, and at
least about 3.5 weight percent of an ethylene/acrylic ester copolymer, based on a
total of 100 weight percent, wherein shaped articles prepared from the
composition exhibits a glossy surface, high impact strength and specific gravity.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 1, wherein the polyethylene terephthalate is
present in an amount from about 17.0 to about 24.0 weight percent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 2, wherein the intrinsic viscosity of the
polyethylene terephthalate is from about 0.4 to about 1.5 dl/g.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 3, wherein the intrinsic viscosity of the
polyethylene terephthalate is from about 0.68 to about 0.86 dl/g.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 4, wherein the barium sulfate is present in an
amount of from about 60 to about 70 weight percent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 5, wherein the glass fibers are present in an
amount of from about 6 to about 10 weight percent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 6, wherein the impact modifier system is
present in an amount of from about 4.0 to about 6.0 weight percent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 7, wherein the impact modifier system
comprises a terpolymer consisting of a functionalized or unfunctionalized
ethylene/glycidyl methacrylate/methyl acrylate, and a copolymer consisting of
ethylene/acrylic ester in a ratio of about 1 to 4, respectively.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 8, wherein the composition exhibits a
specific gravity of from about 1.7 to about 3.0, a Notched Izod of from about 0.7
to about 0.80 ft-lb/in, an Unnotched Izod of from about 2.0 to about 2.7 ft-lb/in,
and a Gardner Impact of from about 5.4 to about 6.2 in-lb.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A highly filled, ceramic-like thermoplastic polyester resin composition,
comprising about 21.6 weight percent of polyethylene terephthalate having an
intrinsic viscosity of from about 0.68 to about 0.86 dl/g; about 65 weight percent
of barium sulfate; about 8.0 weight percent of a glass filler; and an impact
modifier system comprising from about 0.5 to about 2.0 weight percent of a
functionalized or unfunctionalized ethylene/glycidyl methacrylate/methyl acrylate
terpolymer, and from about 3.5 to about 6.0 weight percent of an ethylene/acrylic
ester copolymer, based on a total of 100 weight percent, wherein shaped articles
prepared from the composition exhibit a glossy surface, a specific gravity of from
about 1.7 to about 2.6, a Notched Izod of from about 0.7 to about 0.8 ft-lb/in, an
Unnotched Izod of from about 2.0 to about 2.7 ft-lb/in, and a Gardner Impact from
about 5.4 to about 6.2 in-lb.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A highly filled, ceramic-like thermoplastic polyester resin composition,
comprising about 21.6 weight percent of polyethylene terephthalate having an
intrinsic viscosity of about 0.68 dl/g; about 65 weight percent of barium sulfate;
about 8.0 weight percent of a glass filler; and an impact modifier system
comprising from about 0.5 to about 2.0 weight percent of a functionalized or
unfunctionalized ethylene/glycidyl methacrylate/methyl acrylate terpolymer, and
from about 3.5 to about 6.0 weight percent of an ethylene/acrylic ester copolymer,
based on a total of 100 weight percent, wherein shaped articles prepared from the
composition exhibit a glossy surface, a specific gravity of about 2.6, a Notched
Izod of about 0.8 ft-lb/in, an Unnotched Izod of about 2.4 ft-lb/in, and a Gardner
Impact about 5.8 in-lb.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A highly filled, ceramic-like thermoplastic polyester resin composition,
comprising about 21.6 weight percent of polyethylene terephthalate having an
intrinsic viscosity of about 0.86 dl/g; about 65 weight percent of barium sulfate;
about 8.0 weight percent of a glass filler; and an impact modifier system
comprising about 1.1 weight percent of a functionalized or unfunctionalized
ethylene/glycidyl methacrylate/methyl acrylate terpolymer, and about 4.3 weight
percent of an ethylene/acrylic ester copolymer, based on a total of 100 weight
percent, wherein shaped articles prepared from the composition exhibit a glossy
surface, a specific gravity of about 2.6, a Notched Izod of about 0.7 ft-lb/in, an
Unnotched Izod of about 2.7 ft-lb/in, and a Gardner Impact about 5.4 in-lb.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A ceramic-like, glossy, high density shaped article exhibiting improved impact
strength prepared from the composition according to any one of Claims 9, 10, 11
and 12.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The shaped article according to Claim 13 selected from the group consisting of is
a gaming chip, ceramic insulator, tableware or billiard ball.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="155" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="242" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="239" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>