<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1050538-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1050538" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="23171947" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20001108"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1050538-A2" status="new" fvid="22977211"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1050538</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20001108</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00303708-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00303708</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000503</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-30341099-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>30341099</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990503</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07F  15/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07F  15/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07F  17/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07F  17/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   2/46        20060101C I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   2/50        20060101A I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/00        20060101C I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/80        20060101A I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/07        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 183/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 183/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 183/07        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 183/07        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07F  17/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  83/04+B4S+C12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D 183/04+B4S+C12</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new"  lang="DE">Photoaktive Platinverbindungen enthaltende durch Bestrahlung vernetzbare Silikonenzusammensetzungen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Irradiation-curable silicone compositions containing photo-active platinum (IV) compounds</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Compositions de silicones réticulables par irradiation contenant des composés de platine photoactifs</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-4600484-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4600484</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4916169-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4916169</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEN ELECTRIC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1 River Road</street><city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BUTTS MATTHEW DAVID</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BUTTS, MATTHEW DAVID</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BUTTS, MATTHEW DAVID</last-name><address><street>Hollandale Apartments 41B</street><city>Clifton Park, New York 12065</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Szary, Anne Catherine, Dr.</last-name><address><street>GE London Patent Operation, Essex House, 12-13 Essex Street</street><city>London WC2R 3AA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Cyclopentadienylplatinum (IV) compounds having C<sub>7-20</sub> aromatic radical
substitution on the cyclopentadienyl ring have been found to impart enhanced
cure speed and shelf-life stability to irradiation-curable silicone mixtures.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention is directed to photo-active cyclopentadienylplatinum
(IV) compounds, and to irradiation-curable silicone compositions containing
such compounds as photo-active platinum (IV) catalysts.</p><p num="0002">Drahnak, U.S. patent 4,600,484, is directed to a hydrosilylation process
involving the addition between silicon hydride compounds (i.e. compounds
containing the Si-H moiety) and compounds containing aliphatic unsaturation.
Drahnak discloses that his process is activated by actinic radiation. Drahnak
uses a platinum complex having the formula,
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">CpPt(R)<sub>3</sub>,</st32:che>
where Cp is cyclopentadienyl and R is a C<sub>1-18</sub> aliphatic organic radical.</p><p num="0003">The Drahnak catalyst consists of a cyclopentadienyl group, Cp, eta-bonded to
a platinum (IV) group, Pt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>, which is substituted with three sigma bonded
aliphatic radicals. It is also reported in U.S. patent 4,600,484, that the
cyclopentadienyl group Cp can be further modified with organosilyl groups.</p><p num="0004">Boardman et al., U.S. patent 4,916,169, shows a visible light-activated
hydrosilylation process for effecting the addition of a silicon hydride to
compounds containing aliphatic unsaturation. In accordance with the
hydrosilylation practice of Boardman et al., a polycyclic aromatic organic
compound, such as anthracene, is physically blended as a sensitizer with a
photo-active platinum compound, such as shown by formula (1). Based on
the theory of Boardman et al., the sensitizer effects a visible light energy
transfer to further enhance the photo-activation of the platinum compound.
While beneficial cure results are reported by Boardman et al., it has been 
found that the sensitizer is sometimes incompatible in the silicone curable
silicone mixture and/or a large amount of sensitizer is required to be effective.</p><p num="0005">It would be desirable therefore to provide additional procedures for improving
the efficiency of photo-activated platinum (IV) compounds as catalysts for
effecting the cure of irradiation-curable silicone compositions.</p><p num="0006">Further, it would be desirable to provide photo-active platinum compounds
comprising a cyclopentadienyl group chemically combined to a Pt (IV) group,
which did not require the separate blending of an incompatible organic
material, such as anthracene, into an irradiation-curable silicone mixture.</p><p num="0007">The present invention is based on the discovery that a
cyclopentadienylplatinum (IV) compound of formula (2), having a C<sub>7-20</sub>
aromatic organic radical attached to the cyclopentadienyl is more effective as
a hydrosilylation catalyst for effecting the cure of an irradiation-curable
silicone mixture, than is a mixture an aromatic organic compound, for
example, phenanthrene and a photo-active cyclopentadienylplatinum (IV)
compound, such as shown by formula (1), which is free of aromatic
substitution.</p><p num="0008">In one of its embodiments the present invention comprises platinum (IV)
compounds having the formula,
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">[(R<sup>1</sup>)<sub>a</sub>(R<sup>2</sup>)<sub>b</sub>Cp]Pt(R<sup>3</sup>)<sub>3</sub></st32:che>
where R<sup>1</sup> is a C<sub>7-20</sub> aromatic organic radical, R<sup>2</sup> and R<sup>3</sup> are each
independently a C<sub>1-22</sub> aliphatic organic radical, Cp is a cyclopentadienyl
radical, "a" is an integer equal to 1 to 3 inclusive, "b" is an integer equal to 0 to
3 inclusive, and the sum of a + b is equal to 1 to 4 inclusive. </p><p num="0009">In another of its embodiments the present invention comprises a method for
making platinum (IV) compounds of formula (2), comprising, effecting reaction
between a C<sub>7-20</sub> aromatic substituted cyclopentadienyl species having the
formula,
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">(R<sup>1</sup>)<sub>a</sub>(R<sup>2</sup>)<sub>b</sub>CpM,</st32:che>
and a platinum (IV) compound having the formula,
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">XPt(R<sup>3</sup>)<sub>3</sub></st32:che>
where R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup>, R<sup>3</sup>, Cp, "a" and "b" are as previously defined, M is a metallic
anion, such as lithium, and X is an anionic leaving group, such as triflate,
borate, phosphate, or halogen.</p><p num="0010">In still another of its embodiments the present invention comprises irradiation-curable
silicone compositions comprising,
<sl><li>(a) an alkenyl-substituted polydiorganosiloxane having alkenyl radicals
attached to silicon by carbon-silicon bonds, where the alkenyl radicals can be
in the terminal position, in the polymer backbone, or a combination thereof,</li><li>(b) a silicon hydride cross-linker, and,</li><li>(c) an amount of a photo-active cyclopentadienyl-platinum (IV) compound of
formula (2) which is sufficient to convert the irradiation-curable silicone
composition to a tack-free state when said composition is subjected to 240-400
nm light.</li></sl></p><p num="0011">In still another of its embodiments the present invention comprises a method
of coating a substrate with a cured tack-free silicone film, which comprises,
<sl><li>(1) applying onto the surface of the substrate to a thickness of about 0.5 to
about 5 mil, an irradiation-curable silicone composition comprising, <sl><li>(a) an alkenyl-substituted polydiorganosiloxane having alkenyl radicals
attached to silicon by carbon-silicon bonds, where the alkenyl radicals can be
in the terminal position, in the polymer backbone, or a combination thereof,</li><li>(b) a silicon hydride cross-linker, and,</li><li>(c) an amount of a photo-active cyclopentadienylplatinum (IV) compound of
formula (2) which is sufficient to convert the irradiation-curable silicone
composition to a tack-free state, and</li></sl></li><li>(2) irradiating the surface of the applied irradiation- curable silicone
composition with light in the range of 240-400 nm.</li></sl></p><p num="0012">In still other of its embodiments the present invention comprises substrates
coated with an irradiation-curable silicone composition and the corresponding
substrates coated with the subsequently cured silicone film comprising
platinum (IV) compounds included within formula (2), and any reaction
products thereof which may have been formed, for example, during
processing and irradiation-curing.</p><p num="0013">The photo-active cyclopentadienylplatinum (IV) compounds of the present
invention are shown by the following formula,
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">[(R<sup>1</sup>)<sub>a</sub>(R<sup>2</sup>)<sub>b</sub>Cp]Pt(R<sup>3</sup>)<sub>3</sub></st32:che>
where R<sup>1</sup> is a C<sub>7-20</sub> aromatic organic radical, R<sup>2</sup> is a C<sub>1-22</sub> aliphatic organic
radical, R<sup>3</sup> is a C<sub>1-22</sub> aliphatic organic radical or a C<sub>6-20</sub> aromatic organic
radical, Cp is a cyclopentadienyl radical, "a" is an integer equal to 1 to 3
inclusive, "b" is an integer equal to 0 to 3 inclusive, and the sum of a + b is
equal to 1 to 4 inclusive. In one embodiment the photo-active
cyclopentadienylplatinum (IV) compounds of formula (2) can be synthesized
by effecting reaction between a C<sub>7-20</sub> aromatic-substituted cyclopentadienyl
compound having the formula, <st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">(R<sup>1</sup>)<sub>a</sub>(R<sup>2</sup>)<sub>b</sub>CpM,</st32:che>
and a platinum (IV) compound having the formula,
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">XPt(R<sup>3</sup>)<sub>3</sub></st32:che>
where R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup>, R<sup>3</sup>, Cp, "a" and "b" are as previously defined, M is a metallic
anion, such as lithium, and X is an anionic leaving group, such as, but not
limited to, triflate, borate, phosphate, or halogen.</p><p num="0014">Among the C<sub>7-20</sub> aromatic organic radicals shown by R<sup>1</sup> of formula (2), there
are included tolyl, naphthyl, 2-benzoylnaphthalene, thioxanthone, 2-chlorothioxanthone,
2-isopropylthioxanthone, anthraquinone, 1-chloroanthraquinone,
acetophenone, benzophenone, 9,10-dimethylanthracene, 9,10-dichloroanthracene,
biphenyl, anthracenyl, phenanthryl and pyrenyl. Further,
the cyclopentadienyl compound can be substituted with an η<sup>5</sup>-fluorenyl group.
Preferred C<sub>7-20</sub> aromatic organic radicals are naphthyl, biphenyl, anthracenyl,
phenanthryl and pyrenyl.</p><p num="0015">Aliphatic organic radicals included within both R<sup>2</sup> and R<sup>3</sup> groups are C<sub>1-22</sub>
aliphatic moieties which can independently be the same or different, and
include, but are not limited to, methyl, ethyl, propyl, isopropyl, butyl, allyl, arylsubstituted
aliphatic moieties including benzyl and substituted benzyl, and
cycloaliphatic groups including cyclopentyl and cyclohexyl. Aromatic organic
radicals included within R<sup>3</sup> are C<sub>6-20</sub> aromatic moieties which can be the same
or different, and include, but are not limited to, phenyl, and substituted phenyl,
particularly alkyl-substituted phenyl. Mixtures of C<sub>1-22</sub> aliphatic moieties and
C<sub>6-20</sub> aromatic moieties for R<sup>3</sup> are also within the scope of the invention. In
preferred embodiments both R<sup>2</sup> and R<sup>3</sup> groups are independently C<sub>1-22</sub>
aliphatic moieties, more preferably independently C<sub>1-12</sub> aliphatic moieties, and
most preferably independently C<sub>1-6</sub> aliphatic moieties. In especially preferred
embodiments of the present invention R<sup>2</sup> and R<sup>3</sup> groups are methyl. </p><p num="0016">Illustrative examples of the compounds of formula (2), include, [(1'-naphthyl)-cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum; [(2'-naphthyl)-cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum; [1-methyl-3-(1'-naphthyl)-cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl platinum; [1-methyl-3-(2'-naphthyl)-cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum; [(4'-biphenyl)-cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum; [1-(4'-biphenyl )-3-methyl-cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum; [(9'-phenanthryl)-cyclopentadienyl]-trimethyl
platinum; [1-methyl-3-(9'-phenanthryl)-cyclopentadienyl]-trimethyl platinum; [1-(2'-anthracenyl)-3-methyl-cyclopentadienyl]-trimethyl
platinum; [(2'-anthracenyl
)-cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl platinum; [(1'-pyrenyl)-cyclopentadienyl]-trimethyl
platinum; and [1-methyl-3-(1'-pyrenyl)-cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum.</p><p num="0017">The irradiation-curable silicone compositions of the present invention can be
made by incorporating an effective amount of a photo-active platinum (IV)
compound included within formula (2) into an irradiation-curable silicone blend
comprising an alkenyl-substituted polydiorganosiloxane and a silicon hydride
cross-linker. An effective amount of the photo-active platinum (IV) compound
of formula (2) is an amount sufficient to provide from about 5 ppm to about
500 ppm of platinum, and preferably, about 10 to about 200 ppm based on the
weight of irradiation-curable silicone mixture.</p><p num="0018">If any of the components of the irradiation-curable silicone composition is a
solid or is extremely viscous, a solvent can be introduced into the composition
to facilitate uniform mixing of the composition components. Suitable solvents
include aromatic hydrocarbons, such as, but not limited to, xylene and
toluene, aliphatic hydrocarbons, such as, but not limited to, hexane and
mineral spirits, halogenated hydrocarbons, such as, but not limited to,
dichloromethane, chlorobenzene and trichlorobenzene, and ethers, such as,
but not limited to, tetrahydrofuran, methyltetrahydrofuran, and dioxane. From
about 0.01 to about 10 parts of solvent per part by weight of the irradiation-curable
silicone composition may be used. The resulting composition will
generally be sufficiently pure for its intended use. However, it may be 
desirable to remove the solvent, if one has been employed, by any convenient
means known in the art.</p><p num="0019">As used hereinafter, the expression "irradiation curable" refers to the ability to
convert an irradiation-curable silicone composition to a non-smear, tack-free
film, after it has been applied in a continuous, semi-continuous, or batch
manner onto a substrate, such as a paper substrate, a plastic substrate, or a
metal substrate, to a thickness of about 0.5 to about 5 mils.</p><p num="0020">Lamps which can be used to effect an irradiation cure preferably provide light
in the range of about 240 nanometers (nm) to about 400 nm, and most
preferably, about 240 nm to about 350 nm. Depending on lamp intensity,
which can vary over about 200 watts (W) to about 600 W, a continuous
application rate can vary over a line speed of about 50 feet per minute (ft/min)
to about 1500 ft/min.</p><p num="0021">While a variety of irradiation-curable coating compositions are included within
the scope of the present invention, a preferred variety of coating compositions
are useful in the paper coating art. Accordingly, the alkenyl-containing
polydiorganosiloxane, which preferably consists essentially of chemically
combined dimethylsiloxy units, can be a polydimethylsiloxane having vinyl
radicals attached to silicon. While vinyl radicals can be in the backbone or in
the terminal position, vinyl terminated polydimethylsiloxane is particularly
preferred. The vinylsiloxy unit content can be about 0.05 to about 3.5 mole
percent, and preferably, about 0.14 to about 2 mole percent based on total
siloxy units.</p><p num="0022">While dimethylsiloxy units are preferred, other diorganosiloxy units which can
be in the backbone include for example, methylphenylsiloxy units,
methyltrifluoropropylsiloxy units, and diphenylsiloxy units. </p> <p num="0023">The alkenyl-containing polydiorganosiloxane can have a viscosity of about
100 centipoise to about 10,000 centipoise at 25°C, and preferably about 150
centipoise to about 600 centipoise.</p><p num="0024">The silicon hydride cross-linker can be present in the irradiation-curable
coating composition at from about 0.1 part to about 10 parts by weight, based
on 100 parts by weight of the alkenyl-containing polydiorganosiloxane. The
silicon hydride cross-linker can have a viscosity of about 20 to about 1000
centipoise, and preferably about 30 to about 40 centipoise, and can have
about 0.04% to about 1.4% by weight of hydrogen attached to silicon.</p><p num="0025">Another embodiment of the present invention comprises a method of coating
a substrate with a cured tack-free silicone film, which comprises,
<sl><li>(1) applying onto the surface of the substrate to a thickness of about 0.5 to
about 5 mil, an irradiation-curable silicone composition comprising,
<sl><li>(a) an alkenyl-substituted polydiorganosiloxane having alkenyl radicals
attached to silicon by carbon-silicon bonds, where the alkenyl radicals can be
in the terminal positiorr, in the polymer backbone, or a combination thereof,</li><li>(b) a silicon hydride cross-linker, and,</li><li>(c) an amount of a photo-active cyclopentadienylplatinum (IV) compound of
formula (2) which is sufficient to convert the irradiation-curable silicone
composition to a tack-free state, and</li> </sl> </li> <li>(2) irradiating the surface of the applied irradiation- curable silicone
composition with light in the range of 240-400 nm.</li></sl></p><p num="0026">Still other embodiments of the present invention comprise substrates coated
with an irradiation-curable silicone composition and the corresponding
substrates coated with the subsequently cured silicone film comprising
platinum (IV) compounds included within formula (2), and any reaction
products thereof which may have been formed, for example, during 
processing and irradiation-curing. Suitable substrates which can be coated
with a curable silicone composition and subsequently cured silicone film
include, but are not limited to, cellulose-based substrates; such as paper,
preferably Glassine or super-calendered Kraft paper, and film substrates,
such as polyethylene, polypropylene, and polyester, such as Mylar, and
hybrid substrates, such as those comprising polyethylene-Kraft paper or
polypropylene-Kraft paper. Suitable substrates also include those which are
substantially non-porous, such as glass or metal.</p><p num="0027">In order that those skilled in the art will be better able to practice the invention,
the following examples are given by way of illustration and not by way of
limitation. All parts are by weight unless otherwise indicated.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 1.</heading><p num="0028">A cyclopentadienylplatinum (IV) compound, as shown by formula (2) was
synthesized by initially preparing, as follows, a C<sub>7-20</sub> aromatic-substituted
cyclopentadienyl compound within the scope of formula (3):</p><p num="0029">There was added 10 milliliters (mL) of dry tetrahydrofuran to a flame-dried
flask containing 1.4795 grams (g), (5.7537 millimoles [mmol]) of 9-bromophenanthrene
under argon. A pale yellow solution was formed with
stirring and it was cooled to -78°C in a dry ice/acetone bath. There was
slowly added dropwise to the yellow solution while it was stirred at -78°C,
12.8 mmol of sec-butyllithium lithium as a 1.185 M solution in cyclohexane. A
tan mixture was formed at the end of the addition.</p><p num="0030">After 12 minutes at -78°C, there was added dropwise to the tan mixture, 0.60
mL (6.06 mmol) of 3-methyl-2-cyclopentene-1-one (dried over molecular
sieves). After stirring at 30 minutes at -78°C, the mixture was allowed
to warm to room temperature slowly. One hour later, the tan mixture was
cooled to 0°C in an ice bath. </p><p num="0031">There was slowly added to the tan mixture, 14.4 mmol of a 2.88 M HCl
solution. Gas evolution resulted, and a precipitate formed. The reaction was
stirred at ambient temperature for 30 minutes; the volume was reduced under
reduced pressure to ∼ 4ml. A viscous orange oily material was obtained
which was extracted three times with diethyl ether. The combined ether
extracts were washed with distilled water and with aqueous sodium
bicarbonate. The resulting orange layer was dried over magnesium sulfate
and concentrated under vacuum to 1.37 g of a tacky orange solid.</p><p num="0032">Inside an argon-filled dry box, the above crude product was dissolved in 3 mL
of diethyl ether followed by 40 mL of hexane. There was added, 6.93 mmol of
n-butyllithium as a 1.54 M solution in hexane. The mixture was stirred for 1.5
hours, and filtered. There was obtained 742 milligrams (mg) of a tan product
after drying under reduced pressure. Based on method of preparation and
starting weight of 9-bromophenanthrene, there was obtained a 49% yield of
lithium 1-methyl-3-(9'-phenanthryl)cyclopentadienide.</p><p num="0033">The lithium1-methyl-3-(9'-phenanthryl)cyclopentadienide salt was then
reacted with trimethylplatinum iodide to form a compound within the scope of
formula (2) in accordance with the following procedure:</p><p num="0034">There was added dropwise under anhydrous conditions in the dark, a dry
tetrahydrofuran solution of 0.843 mole of lithium 1-methyl-3-(9'-phenanthryl)cyclopentadienide
to a vessel containing 0.765 mmol of stirring
trimethylplatinum iodide in tetrahydrofuran at 0°C under argon. The resulting
mixture was allowed to stir at room temperature for 75 minutes to form a
homogeneous deep orange solution. Volatile materials were separated under
reduced pressure to yield a viscous orange oil. The oil was extracted four
times with 10 mL of hexane in the dark. The combined extracts were reduced
under vacuum to 4mL. The resulting yellow product was subjected to -30°C
to form crystalline clumps. There was obtained 197 mg (52% yield) of product.
Based on method of preparation, NMR spectroscopy and mass spectrometry, 
the product was [1-methyl-3-(9'-phenanthryl)cyclo-pentadienyl]trimethylplatinum.</p><p num="0035">Following a substantially similar procedure, additional
cyclopentadienylplatinum (IV) compounds shown by formula (2) were
prepared, such as [1-methyl-3-(2'-naphthyl)-cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum, and [1-(4'-biphenyl)-3-methylcyclopentadienyl]trimethyl platinum.
The respective platinum compounds were recovered as yellow powders. The
naphthyl compound (271 my) was obtained in 47% yield and the biphenyl
compound (260 mg) was obtained in 42% yield.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 2.</heading><p num="0036">A hydrosilylation catalyst evaluation test was run to compare catalytic
effectiveness of [1-methyl-3-(9'-phenanthryl )-cyclopentadienyl]-trimethylplatinum
of Example 1, and a mixture of a commercially available
cyclopentadienylplatinum compound, such as CH<sub>3</sub>CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>, and
phenanthrene, as a sensitizer. In evaluating the catalysts, there was used a
silicone mixture based on materials obtained from GE Silicone Products
Division at Waterford, N.Y. The silicone mixture consisted of 10 parts of
SL6100, a vinyl-terminated polydimethylsiloxane having a viscosity of 200
centipoise, and 0.5 part of SL 6020, a siloxane hydride cross-linker having a
viscosity of 35 centipoise.</p><p num="0037">The respective irradiation-curable silicone mixtures were applied onto
Glassine® paper with a doctor blade and cured on an RPC UV processor,
PPG model 1202, which was fitted with 400-500 W mercury arc lamps. A line
speed of 100-200 ft/min was used.</p><p num="0038">Degree of cure of the coatings was determined by using a smear test and a
tape migration test. In the smear test, a 0.5 to 5 mil coating was applied,
followed by irradiation. The coating was then rubbed firmly and checked for
any smears. In the tape migration test, the adhesive surface of tape was 
pressed firmly onto a freshly cured coating. The adhesive surface of the tape
was then checked for surface migration by folding and self-contacting its
adhesive surface to manually determine whether any change occurred in
degree of adhesion.</p><p num="0039">Catalytic effectiveness was measured with respect to achieving a non-smear,
no migration cure of the silicone mixture using the respective catalysts.
Values such as ppm of Pt, line speed, and lamp intensity, needed to achieve
a satisfactory cure were measured.</p><p num="0040">In evaluating a mixture of CH<sub>3</sub>CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>, and phenanthrene as a sensitizer,
it was found that 1800 ppm is the optimum level of phenanthrene. At higher
levels, particularly 10,000 ppm or greater, phenanthrene was found to be
incompatible in the silicone mixture. It was found that a non-smear, no
migration cure at a line speed of 100 ft/min using a 400W lamp required 200
ppm of Pt and 1800 ppm of phenanthrene based on curable mixture.</p><p num="0041">On the other hand, a non-smear, no migration cure of the silicone mixture
was achieved with [1-methyl-3-(9'-phenanthryl)-cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum of Example 1 in the absence of phenanthrene, at a line speed of 200
ft/min with a 400W lamp, using only 100 ppm of Pt based on the weight of
curable mixture.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 3.</heading><p num="0042">A series of irradiation-curable silicone mixtures containing a
cyclopentadienyiplatinum (IV) compound of Example 1 were respectively
evaluated for shelf-life stability at room temperature in the substantial absence
of light.</p><p num="0043">The respective platinum compounds were introduced and mixed vigorously as
a toluene solution into a silicone mixture. There was employed sufficient
platinum compound to provide 100 ppm of platinum, based on the weight of
silicone mixture. The silicone mixture consisted of 95.2 parts of a vinylterminated 
polydimethylsiloxane having a viscosity of 200 centipoise at 25°C,
and 4.8 parts of a trimethylsiloxy-terminated polysiloxane consisting
essentially of a mixture of methylhydrogensiloxy units and dimethylsiloxy units
and having a viscosity of 35 centipoise at 25°C.</p><p num="0044">In the following table, "Bath Life", measured in the absence of light is the time
required for the curable silicone formulation to show a viscosity increase
sufficient to interfere with free flow when shaken. In addition, C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>7</sub> is a
naphthyl group, C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>9</sub> is a biphenyl group, and C<sub>14</sub>H<sub>9</sub> is a phenanthryl group:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Catalyst<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">Bath Life</entry></row><row><entry align="left">CH<sub>3</sub>CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub><!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">24-48 hours</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>7</sub> (CH<sub>3</sub>CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="left">96 hours</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>9</sub>(CH<sub>3</sub>)CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="left">144 hours</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>14</sub>H<sub>9</sub>(CH<sub>3</sub>)CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="left">120 hours<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0045">The "Bath Life" values show that the compositions of the present invention
have suitable shelf-life stability in the absence of light.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 4.</heading><p num="0046">Additional curable silicone formulations were prepared following the
procedure of Example 3, which were used to treat Kraft paper in the absence 
of light using a Meyer bar rod. The treated paper was then exposed to
fluorescent light.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Catalyst<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">Tack Free</entry></row><row><entry align="left">CH<sub>3</sub>CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="left">&gt; 24 hours</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>7</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="left">31 minutes<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>EXAMPLE 5.</heading><p num="0047">In accordance with the procedures of Example 3, additional curable silicone
formulations were prepared in the absence of light. Samples consisting of 2-3
mg formulations were added to aluminum pans. Information on cure speed
and extent of cure were determined using Photo Differential Scanning
Calorimetry using a Perkin-Elmer Photo-DSC system (DSCT + DPA7) with a
PEM500 multipower supply. The light source was a 200 watt Hg/Xe lamp. A
temperature of 30°C was maintained during the test procedure. The following
results were obtained:</p><heading>Photo-DSC Experiments</heading><p num="0048"><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Catalyst<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">ΔH(J/g)</entry><entry align="center">peak time (min)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">CH<sub>3</sub>CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">-16.7</entry><entry align="center">0.39</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>(CH<sub>3</sub>)CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">-27.7</entry><entry align="center">0.38</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>9</sub>(CH<sub>3</sub>)CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">-30.6</entry><entry align="center">0.26</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>7</sub>(CH<sub>3</sub>)CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">-34.0</entry><entry align="center">0.16</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>14</sub>H<sub>9</sub>(CH<sub>3</sub>)CpPt(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">-39.2</entry><entry align="center">0.19<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0049">The above results show that the cyclopentadienylplatinum compounds of the
present invention can be used to provide improved catalysts for the
irradiation-curable silicone coating compositions of the present inventions.</p><p num="0050">Although the above examples are directed to only a few of the very many
variables which can be used in the practice of the present invention, it should
be understood that the present invention is directed to the use of a much
broader variety of cyclopentadienyl- platinum (IV) compounds and the use of
such compounds as catalysts in a wide variety of irradiation-curable silicon
mixtures as set forth in the description preceding these examples.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>Platinum (IV) compounds having the formula,
[(R1)a(R2)bCp]Pt(R3)3.
where R1 is a C7-20 aromatic organic radical, R2 and R3 are each
independently a C1-22 aliphatic organic radical, Cp is a cyclopentadienyl
radical, "a" is an integer equal to 1 to 3 inclusive, "b" is an integer equal to 0 to
3 inclusive, and the sum of a + b is equal to 1 to 4 inclusive.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A platinum (IV) compound in accordance with claim 1, where R1 is
phenanthryl, naphthyl or biphenyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The compound [1-methyl-3-(9'-phenanthryl)cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The compound [1-methyl-3-(2'-naphthyl)cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The compound [1-(4' biphenyl)-3-methylcyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method for making platinum (IV) compounds of the formula,
[(R1 )a(R2)bCp]Pt(R3)3.
where R1 is a C7-20 aromatic organic radical, R2 and R3 are each
independently a C1-22 aliphatic organic radical, Cp is a cyclopentadienyl
radical, "a" is an integer equal to 1 to 3 inclusive, "b" is an integer equal to 0 to
3 inclusive, and the sum of a + b is equal to 1 to 4 inclusive, comprising,
effecting reaction between a cyclopentadienide compound of the formula
(R1)a(R2)bCpM,
and a platinum (IV) compound of the formula,
XPt(R3)3,
where M is a metallic anion, and X is an anionic leaving group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method in accordance with claim 6, where X is halogen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A method in accordance with claim 6, where R1 is phenanthryl
or naphthyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>An irradiation-curable silicone composition comprising,
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) an alkenyl-substituted polydiorganosiloxane having alkenyl radicals
attached to silicon by carbon-silicon bonds, where the alkenyl radicals can be
in the terminal position, in the polymer backbone, or a combination thereof,</claim-text><claim-text>(b) a silicon hydride cross-linker, and,</claim-text><claim-text>(c) an effective amount of a photo-active cyclopentadienylplatinum (IV)
compound of the formula,
[(R1 )a(R2)bCp]Pt(R3)3.
which is sufficient to convert the irradiation-curable silicone composition to a
tack-free state when said composition is subjected to 240-400 nm light, where
R1 is a C7-20 aromatic organic radical, R2 and R3 are each independently a C1-22
aliphatic organic radical, Cp is a cyclopentadienyl radical, "a" is an integer
equal to 1 to 3 inclusive, "b" is an integer equal to 0 to 3 inclusive, and the
sum of a + b is equal to 1 to 4 inclusive.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An irradiation-curable silicone composition in accordance with claim 9,
where the photo-active cyclopentadienyl-Pt(IV) compound is [1-methyl-3-(9'-phenanthryl)-cyclopentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum or [1-methyl-3-(2'-naphthyl)cyc!opentadienyl]trimethyl
platinum.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A method of coating a substrate with a cured tack-free silicone film,
which comprises,
<claim-text><claim-text>(1) applying onto the surface of the substrate to a thickness of about 0.5 to
about 5 mil, an irradiation-curable silicone composition comprising,
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) an alkenyl-substituted polydiorganosiloxane having alkenyl radicals
attached to silicon by carbon-silicon bonds, where the alkenyl radicals can be
in the terminal position, in the polymer backbone, or a combination thereof,</claim-text><claim-text>(b) a silicon hydride cross-linker, and,</claim-text><claim-text>(c) an amount of a photo-active cyclopentadienylplatinum (IV) compound of
the formula,
[(R1)a(R2)bCp]Pt(R3)3,
which is sufficient to convert the irradiation-curable silicone composition to a
tack-free state, and</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>(2) irradiating the surface of the applied irradiation- curable silicone
composition with light in the range of 240-400 nm, where R1 is a C7-20
aromatic organic radical, R2 and R3 are each independently a C1-22 aliphatic
organic radical, Cp is a cyclopentadienyl radical, "a" is an integer equal to 1 to
3 inclusive, "b" is an integer equal to 0 to 3 inclusive, and the sum of a + b is
equal to 1 to 4 inclusive.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A substrate coated with an irradiation-curable silicone composition
comprising, a platinum (IV) compound having the formula,
[(R1)a(R2)bCp]Pt(R3)3,
and any reaction products thereof, where R1 is a C7-20 aromatic organic
radical, R2 and R3 are each independently a C1-22 aliphatic organic radical, Cp
is a cyclopentadienyl radical, "a" is an integer equal to 1 to 3 inclusive, "b" is
an integer equal to 0 to 3 inclusive, and the sum of a + b is equal to 1 to 4
inclusive.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A substrate according to claim 12, in which the silicone coating
composition has been irradiation-cured.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>