<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1160313-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1160313" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="8168887" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20011205"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1160313-A1" status="new" fvid="23305809"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1160313</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20011205</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00111746-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00111746</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000602</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-00111746-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00111746</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000602</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B08B   1/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B08B   1/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B08B   3/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B08B   3/08        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/24        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/43        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/43        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   7/22        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   7/30        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   7/50        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   7/50        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  17/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  17/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D  11/00B2D8</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D  17/04B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/24B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   7/30</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Zusammensetzung und Einrichtung zum Reinigen von electronischen Geräten</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Cleaning composition and device for electronic equipment</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition et disposatif pour nettoyer les appareils électroniques</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0195336-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0195336</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4966481-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4966481</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5938858-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5938858</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 198640 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class D25, AN 1986-261049 XP002151459 &amp; JP 61 188498 A (RICOH KK), 22 August 1986 (1986-08-22)</text><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PROCTER &amp; GAMBLE</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>THE PROCTER &amp; GAMBLE COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>THE PROCTER &amp;amp; GAMBLE COMPANY</last-name><address><street>One Procter &amp;amp; Gamble Plaza</street><city>Cincinnati, Ohio 45202</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ARGENTIERI ANDREA</name><address><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ROSSI SERGIO</name><address><country>IT</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SCIALLA STEFANO</name><address><country>IT</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SUEER GOEKCE MURAT</name><address><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ARGENTIERI, ANDREA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ROSSI, SERGIO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SCIALLA, STEFANO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SUEER GOEKCE, MURAT</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ARGENTIERI, ANDREA</last-name><address><street>Avenue du Congo 2</street><city>1050-Ixelles</city><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ROSSI, SERGIO</last-name><address><street>Via Formignana, 68</street><city>44100 Ferrara</city><country>IT</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SCIALLA, STEFANO</last-name><address><street>Via F. B. Rastrelli 81</street><city>00128 Rome</city><country>IT</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Süer Gökce, Murat</last-name><address><street>Sint Annalaan 132 B</street><city>1800-Vilvoode</city><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kohol, Sonia</last-name><address><street>Procter &amp;amp; Gamble European Service GmbH Sulzbacher Strasse 40</street><city>65824 Schwalbach am Taunus</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country> <country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country> <country>MC</country> <country>NL</country> <country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention relates to a chemical cleaning composition and a device
for the application of such composition. Claimed and described is the use of a
cleaning composition comprising a fluorinated carbon compound on household
and office equipment and further an optimised applicator comprising such
cleaning composition.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="77" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="127"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">Field of the invention</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a chemical cleaning composition and a device
for the application of such composition. More particularly, the invention relates to
the cleaning of electronic equipment and electric or electronic appliances by
such composition and device. Claimed is the use of a cleaning composition
comprising at least one fluorinated carbon compound on household and office
equipment. Further claimed is an applicator for such composition.</p><heading><u style="single">Background of the invention</u></heading><p num="0002">Private households acquire a high and constantly increasing number of
electronic equipment. In most western households one will find a radio, a TV set,
a stereo rack, a camera, a calculator, a telephone and likely also at least one
remote control for at least one such device. More recently developed devices,
which at the beginning of the 21<sup>st</sup> century also become more and more common,
are portable and desktop personal computers, palmtop devices, mobile phones,
touch screen LCD displays, CD, DVD, MP3 audio and video equipment, play
stations and the like.</p><p num="0003">These devices, both when used in a private ambience and in a business
environment, represent a particular challenge in terms of cleanness and
hygiene. Being largely designed in view of technical needs rather than ease of
cleaning, they often comprise difficult to reach and/or difficult to clean surfaces, 
a prime example for such a surface being a keyboard or keypad, which in one or
the other form is comprised by most such devices.</p><p num="0004">A further challenge in relation to the cleaning of any such device, is that they are
typically delicate and further will suffer damage from contact with water or most
other liquids. When water intrudes such device, e.g. via the keypad, due to the
highly integrated and compact design of such devices, liquid is bound to induce
a short-circuit and thereby typically unrepairable damage.</p><p num="0005">Besides the need for cleanness and hygiene in a private ambience and for the
comfort of the user, often such devices are shared between different users, e.g.
computers and telephones, in particular in a business and office environment,
where cleanness is particularly relevant for the comfort of usage and lack of
cleanness may even mean a risk a spreading infections. In a further aspect
cleanness may be required for the proper functioning of a device, e.g. a touch
screen LCD display.</p><p num="0006">A number of dedicated cleaning devices for electronic and other delicate
equipment is known. Some devices solely or predominately rely on the
mechanical removal of dirt, dust and the like. For example, DE 29813015
discloses a sponge shaped to match the contours of a typical keyboard and DE
19609940 discloses a device comprising a number of brushes, which can be
mechanically adjusted to match the contour of a given keyboard. DE 29715059
discloses a cleaning device for computer keyboards comprising a wedge-shaped
pad of absorbent material. In GB 2276311 a hand-held furniture vacuum cleaner
is disclosed, also for use on computer keyboards, and in view of the same usage
in US 5,345,651 a nozzle brush attachment for a vacuum cleaner is disclosed. A
product comprising a brush and a wiping surface, to be used particularly for
cameras and optical equipment, is marketed under the name of "LensPen" by
International Parkside Products of Vancouver, Canada. </p><p num="0007">Other devices employ cleaning liquids and rely less on purely mechanical
removal of dust and dirt. For example, US 5,624,239 discloses a portable device
comprising a fluid source and a vacuum device. Kensington of California, USA,
markets pre-moistured wipes for use on computers, keyboards and other office
equipment, however, the wipes are said not to be suitable for notebook and anti-glare
screens. CleanTex of New York, USA, markets a variety of cleaning wipes
for different surfaces including those for computers and computer screens. 3M of
Minnesota, USA, under the trade name of "Keyboard Cleaner" markets a three
piece kit comprising a mechanical device and a cleaning solution.</p><p num="0008">Obviously, a large number of chemical compositions is known to be useful for
cleaning tasks. Some consumers are known to use home care products, such as
detergents and all purpose cleaners (appropriately diluted in water), also for
technical equipment in their household. An alternative choice may be to use an
isopropyl alcohol, which for example is comprised by CleanTex wipe No. 833,
which is recommended for computer screens.</p><p num="0009">Other compositions are known to be useful for specific industrial applications:
US 5,246,618 discloses compositions based on fluorochlorohydrocarbons,
alcohols and at least one ester and particularly their use for removing soldering
flux and soldering flux residue from printed circuit boards. WO 99/38947
discloses an organic-based composition comprising a fluorinated compound, a
high polarity solvent and a low polarity solvent. The composition is disclosed for
use in the cleaning industry and in a preferred method of usage an object to be
cleaned is treated with the boiling composition and the vapours thereof. The
composition is disclosed as suitable for circuit boards and live electrical circuits
and also sensitive plastic surfaces, including polycarbonate and polyacrylic
surfaces.</p><p num="0010">US 5,980,642 discloses a method for removal of water from surfaces by use of a
composition comprising a fluoropolyether, the method to be used in particular in
the electronics and fine mechanics field. </p><p num="0011">US 5,780,414 discloses solvents consisting of certain hydrofluoropolyethers as
cleaning rinsing agents and their use for the removal of oily substances.</p><p num="0012">JP 63178198A2 discloses a composition comprising mainly
trichlorotrifluoroetane which is said to be suitable for word processors, personal
computers and keyboards. Chlorinated compounds are known to contribute to
the depletion of ozone in the ozonosphere and further to the global warming.
Considering that, in those developed countries where a large number of
consumers employ sophisticated electronic equipment of the mentioned types,
among consumers there is also a considerable awareness of environmental
issues, such composition is not ideal for a product to be sold on a large scale. In
view of the prior art, it remains an objective to provide:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>a cleaning device and composition of high cleaning performance suitable for
household and office equipment and similar equipment as listed herein.</li><li>a cleaning device and composition suitable for the multitude of different
surface, including plastic surfaces and delicate surfaces, found on such
equipment.</li><li>a cleaning device and composition which is environmentally friendly.</li><li>a cleaning device and composition which is easy to apply and use.</li><li>a cleaning device and composition which is safe to use and preferably avoids
skin contact of any cleaning composition with the skin of the user.</li><li>a cleaning device and composition which is electro-safe.</li><li>a cleaning device which further provides optimal mechanical dust and dirt
removal performance.</li></ul></p><heading><u style="single">Summary of the invention</u></heading><p num="0013">The present invention relates to a chemical cleaning composition and a device
for the application of such composition. Claimed is the use of a cleaning
composition comprising at least one fluorinated carbon compound on household
and office equipment and further an optimised applicator comprising such
cleaning composition.</p><heading><u style="single">Brief description of the drawings</u></heading><p num="0014">It is believed that the invention will be better understood from the following
description in conjunction with the accompanying drawings in which:</p><p num="0015">Figure 1 is a side view of a preferred applicator according to the present
invention shown in its configuration for transport and storage.</p><p num="0016">Figure 2 is a side view of a preferred applicator according to the present
invention shown in its usage configuration.</p><p num="0017">Figure 3 is an exploded view of the preferred applicator shown in Figure 1.</p><p num="0018">Figures 4a to 6b give cross sectional and top views of preferred sponges for the
applicator of Figures 1 and 2.</p><heading><u style="single">Detailed description of the invention</u></heading><heading><u style="single">The cleaning composition</u></heading><p num="0019">To allow a more detailed and clear description of the present invention, in the
following paragraphs firstly a number of terms, as used herein, will be defined. </p><p num="0020">The term "fluorinated carbon compound", as used herein, denotes any
compound comprising organic molecules each molecule comprising at least one
carbon atom, at least one hydrogen atom and at least one fluorine atom.</p><p num="0021">The term "perfluorinated carbon compound", as used herein, denotes any
fluorinated carbon compound in which the ratio of fluorine atoms to hydrogen
atoms is at least 1:1, preferably 5:1, more preferably 10:1, most preferably 20:1.
The term "perfluorinated carbon compound", as used herein, is meant to
comprise any of the compounds sometimes referred to as "partially fluorinated
carbon compounds" or "semi-fluorinated carbon compounds".</p><p num="0022">The term "perfluoropolyether", as used herein, denotes a perfluorinated carbon
compound with one or more etheric functionalities in the form CF<sub>x</sub>R<sub>y</sub>-O-CF<sub>x'</sub>R'<sub>y'</sub>
where x+y=x'+y'=3 and R and R', each independently, may be either a fluorine
atom or a perfluorinated carbon compound. Examples of perfluoropolyethers
compounds include those of the general formula
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">F<sub>3</sub>-C-O-[(CF<sub>2</sub>-CF-CF<sub>3</sub>-O)<sub>n</sub>-(CF<sub>2</sub>-O)<sub>m</sub>]-CF<sub>3</sub>,</st32:che>
wherein m=1 to 10, n=0 to 5, preferably m=1 to 7 and n=0 to 4, most preferably
m=1 to 5 and n=0 to 3.</p><p num="0023">The term "H-terminated perfluoropolyether", as used herein, denotes a
perfluorinated carbon compound with one or more etheric functionalities in the
form CF<sub>x</sub>R<sub>y</sub>-O-CF<sub>x'</sub>R'<sub>y'</sub> where x+y=x'+y'=3 and R and R', each independently may
be a fluorine atom, a hydrogen atom or a perfluorinated carbon compound.
Examples of perfluoropolyethers compounds include those of the general
formula
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">HF<sub>2</sub>-C-O-[(CF<sub>2</sub>-CF<sub>2</sub>-O)<sub>n</sub>-(CF<sub>2</sub>-O)<sub>m</sub>]-O-CF<sub>2</sub>H or F<sub>3</sub>-C-O-[(CF<sub>2</sub>-CF<sub>2</sub>-O)<sub>n</sub>-(CF<sub>2</sub>-O)<sub>m</sub>]-O-CF<sub>2</sub>H</st32:che>
wherein m=1 to 10, n=0 to 5, preferably m=1 to 7 and n=0 to 4, most preferably
m=1 to 5 and n=0 to 3.</p><p num="0024">The term "electrosafe", as used herein, denotes a liquid formulation with a
dielectric constant of less than 30, preferably less than 25, more preferably less 
than 20, yet more preferably less than 15, even more preferably less than 12, yet
even more preferably less than 10, most preferably less than 8.</p><p num="0025">The term "household or office equipment", as used herein, denotes all devices to
be used in a household or business environment and all devices sold to
consumers. The term "electronic household or office equipment", as used
herein, denotes all household and office equipment which comprises an
electronic circuit.</p><p num="0026">The term pen-shaped, as used herein, denotes a shape which can thought as
comprised by a cylinder, which has a height of less than 50 cm, preferably less
than 30 cm, more preferably less than 20 cm, most preferably less then 15 cm
and a height to diameter ratio of less than 3:1, more preferably less than 5:1, yet
more preferably less than 7:1, most preferably 10:1.</p><p num="0027">The term "dust and dirt" comprises any organic or inorganic material deposited
on an item, which is not wanted there, in particular for reasons of cleanness and
hygiene.</p><p num="0028">Any composition which comprises at least one fluorinated carbon compound and
which can be used for cleaning purposes the scope of the present invention.
Preferred compositions comprise at least one perfluorinated carbon compound
and/or preferably at least one perfluoropolyether and/or more preferably H-terminated
perfluoropolyether.</p><p num="0029">Preferred perfluoropolyethers and H-terminated perfluoropolyethers are
available on the market, e.g. from Ausimont, Italy, under the tradenames Galden
HT200, Galden D02, Galden D100, H-Galden, "grado B", H-Galden "grado C"
and H-Galden "grado D", the H-Galden products being the more preferred ones. </p><p num="0030">The preferred fluorinated carbon compounds possess excellent cleaning
properties. For example, it has been found that a very small amount of cleaning
composition, about 0.5 ml, suffices to clean the screen of a portable computer
from dust, soil, grease, finger marks and the like giving the screen the visual
appearance of high cleanness. It also has been observed, that, at least
subjectively, the cleaned computer screen is less easily re-soiled, namely by
fingermarks.</p><p num="0031">These compounds are preferred also for a number of further relevant benefits,
which in part contribute to the excellent cleaning results and in part are
independent additional benefits:</p><p num="0032">The preferred fluorinated carbon compounds exhibit excellent lubrication
properties. Excellent lubrication promotes the even spreading of the cleaning
composition. This allows to use low amounts of cleaning composition and makes
it easier to reach portions of equipment which are difficult to access.</p><p num="0033">Further the cleaning composition of the present invention have been found to
impart shine to the cleaned surfaces. Especially for plastic surfaces the cleaning
in combination with the achieved shine give the impression of a surface renewal.</p><p num="0034">In a further highly important aspect the cleaning composition of the present
invention are electro-safe. Hence, even when the cleaning composition comes in
contact with electric or electronic parts the composition - as opposed to most
other cleaning compositions and liquids - will not induce a short-circuit or any
other damage - even while the parts are connected to a power supply and
electric currents are present. This makes the cleaning composition safe to use
on expensive and delicate equipment and is highly reassuring to the consumer.</p><p num="0035">In another aspect, the cleaning composition of the present invention is
environmentally friendly. Electro-safe compounds often comprise chlorinated
compounds, which are known to contribute to the ozone depletion of the 
ozonosphere and further to the concerning effect known as global warming. The
preferred perfluoropolyethers and in particular the H-terminated
perfluoropolyethers of the present invention are believed to have an ozone
depletion potential of zero.</p><p num="0036">The cleaning composition according to the present invention in a further aspect
are safe to use from a health point of view and in particular skin safe, which is
important when such cleaning composition are used by a variety of consumers,
including very young and very old ones.</p><p num="0037">Another great benefit of the cleaning compositions according to the present
invention is their low flammability risk, which is key for a cleaning composition to
be marketed to a variety of consumers and to be used and stored in a great
variety of circumstances and locations.</p><p num="0038">In addition to the foregoing considerations, the compositions used herein are
preferably formulated such that they are easily dispensed and are not so viscous
or self-adhesive in nature that they render the cleaning applicator (10) unhandy or
difficult to use. Preferably the cleaning compositions described herein are
formulated as liquid cleaning compositions. In one alternative they may be
provided as a gel. A preferred cleaning composition according to the present
invention comprises:
<sl><li>(a) <u style="single">Fluorinated carbon compounds</u> - The compositions herein comprise
from 0.001% to 99.99%, preferably from 1% to 90%, more preferably
from 5% to 80% of fluorinated carbon compounds, most preferably H-terminated
perfluoropolyethers.</li><li>(b) <u style="single">Solvent</u> - The compositions herein comprise from 1% to 99% of
solvents, preferably from 2% to 90%, more preferably from 5% to 25%.
Preferred solvents are organic carbon compounds comprising at least 
one of the following functionalities: alcohol, ether, ketone. Examples
are isopropyl alcohol and ethanol.</li><li>(c) <u style="single">Other Optionals</u> - The compositions herein may comprise minor
amounts of various optional ingredients, including preservatives, anti-static
agents, fragrances, odor absorbing components, and the like. If
used, such optional ingredients will typically comprise from 0.0001% to
10%, preferably from 0.001% to 8%, more preferably from 0.01% to
2%, by weight, of the cleaning composition. Preferred optionals are
namely the following:
<sl><li><u style="single">Surfactants</u> - Preferred surfactants include nonionic surfactants, in
particular fluorinated or perfluorinated nonionic surfactants and
anionic surfactant, in particular fluorinated or perfluorinated anionic
surfactants.</li><li><u style="single">Anti-static agents</u> - Highly preferred cleaning composition according
to the present invention comprise an anti-static agent. If used, such
anti-static agents will typically comprise at least 0.5%, typically from
2% to 8%, by weight, of the compositions. Preferred anti-static
agents include the series of sulfonated polymers available as
VERSAFLEX 157, 207, 1001, 2004 and 7000, from National Starch
and Chemical Company and polymeric surfactants such as
Crodastat 100 and 200 from Croda.</li><li><u style="single">Fragrances/Perfumes</u> - The cleaning composition of the present
invention can also optionally provide a "scent signal" in the form of a
pleasant odor which signals the removal of malodor from
equipment. The scent signal is designed to provide a fleeting
perfume scent, and is not designed to be overwhelming or to be
used as an odor masking ingredient. When perfume is added as a
scent signal, it is added only at very low levels, e.g., from 0% to 
0.5%, preferably from 0.003% to 0.3%, more preferably from
0.005% to 0.2%, by weight of the usage composition.</li><li>When stronger levels of perfume are preferred, relatively higher
levels of perfume can be added. Any type of perfume can be
incorporated into the composition of the present invention.</li><li><u style="single">Odor absorbing components</u> - The compositions of the present
invention may further comprise an optional cyclodextrin. This will
impart the composition with odour absorbing properties, which is
especially useful for application on inanimate surfaces to control the
malodour.</li><li>As used herein, the term "cyclodextrin" includes any of the known
cyclodextrins such as unsubstituted cyclodextrins containing from
six to twelve glucose units, especially, alpha-cyclodextrin, betacyclodextrin,
gamma-cyclodextrin and/or their derivatives and/or
mixtures thereof. The preferred cyclodextrins are available, e.g.,
from Cerestar USA, Inc. and Wacker Chemicals (USA), Inc.</li><li>Typical levels of cyclodextrin in usage compositions for usage
conditions are from 0.01% to 5%, preferably from 0.1% to 4%, more
preferably from 0.2% to 2% by weight of the composition.</li></sl></li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Examples of cleaning compositions</u></heading><p num="0039">Having due regard to the foregoing considerations, the following illustrates
preferred examples of stain removal compositions, but is not intended to be
limiting thereof.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1:</u></heading><p num="0040">A cleaning composition was formulated to comprise the following components (%
denoted % by weight): <ul list-style="bullet"><li>H-terminated perfluoropolyether ("H-Galden, Grado-D" from Ausimont)   85%</li><li>Isopropyl alcohol   14.5%</li><li>Perfluorosurfactant Zonyl FSN100 (DuPont)   0.49%</li><li>Perfume   0.01%</li></ul></p><p num="0041">With this cleaning composition very satisfactory cleaning results and a pleasing
surface shine were achieved on laptop computer keyboards and screens,
Palmtop devices, remote controls and cellular phones.</p><heading><u style="single">Application and applicator</u></heading><p num="0042">The compositions disclosed herein can be applied to surfaces in many different
ways. For example, they may be poured from any suitable container onto the
areas selected for treatment. A pad, wipe, cloth or sponge made of any material,
for example paper, a textile material, a non-woven material or open-cell or
closed-cell foam may assist in the application of the cleaning composition,
namely in the spreading of the composition and also in the removing of the
composition.</p><p num="0043">Any integral or separate portion of the applicator (10) which is used to contact
the object to be cleaned and to apply cleaning composition to it, is herein
referred to as application device (40). While for some applicators (10) the
application device (40) is integral with a storage device for the cleaning
composition, one example being a wipe pre-moistured with a cleaning liquid,
preferred applicators (10) according to the present invention comprise a
application device (40) which is separate from a storage device and preferably in
temporary or permanent liquid communication therewith.</p><p num="0044">More preferably an applicator (10) is used which allows for the application of a
small and easily controlled amount of cleaning composition. Yet more preferably 
the applicator (10) also allows to spread the cleaning composition over a
selected surface area. Most preferably the applicator (10) allows also for
mechanical removal and collection of dust and dirt and of excess cleaning
composition.</p><p num="0045">Suitable applicators (10) comprise containers, e.g. small plastic bottles, with a
preferably small orifice, e.g. a nozzle, aerosol and pump spray applicators (10),
pen-style applicators (10) comprising e.g. a nib. Highly preferred applicators (10)
further comprise an integrated wiping surface and may comprise an additional
brush (30).</p><p num="0046">Preferably the applicators (10) are portable and more preferably of a format
which conveniently can be carried in a pocket or handbag, highly preferred
applicators (10) have a pen-shape, as defined above, and hence resemble in
shape a fountain pen. Optionally the applicator (10) may comprise a clip (18).</p><p num="0047">Preferred applicators (10) according to the present invention comprise
application devices (40) which exhibit a certain compression resistance and
preferably also a certain ratio of the compression resistance to friction
resistance.</p><p num="0048">The friction resistance of the application device (40) should be in a certain
range, since a minimum friction is required for satisfactory mechanical removal
of dust and dirt and a maximum friction should not be exceeded to ensure that
the application device (40) can be comfortably moved or wiped over a surface.
This range follows from the preferred compression resistance to friction
resistance ratio specified below.</p><p num="0049">The compression resistance of the application device (40) is preferably also
confined to a certain range: A compressible, i.e. soft application device (40)
ensures comfortable usage and good conforming to the contours of the object to
be cleaned (improving cleaning performance). Such good conforming to the 
contours of the object is particularly desirable when cleaning for example a
keyboard where thorough cleaning can only be achieved if the application device
(40) reaches into the recesses defined by protruding keys. A too compressible
application device (40) on the other hand induces a risk that solid parts of the
applicator (10), e.g. the sponge mounting (42) come into contact with the object
to be cleaned and may induce damage such as scratches. Preferably the
application device (40) exhibits a compression resistance from 0.1 kPa to 500
kPa, more preferably 0.5 kPa to 200 kPa, most preferably 1 kPa to 100 kPa.</p><p num="0050">According to the present invention it has surprisingly been found that the
appropriate friction resistance should be selected in view of a given compression
resistance, for example a very compressible application device (40) will typically
be handled by a user without exerting much pressure and hence should have a
sufficient friction resistance to ensure good mechanical dust and dirt removal.
Highly preferred application devices (40) according to the present invention
exhibit a ratio of compression resistance to friction resistance from 0.01 to 1,
more preferably 0.02 to 0.7, most preferably 0.1 to 0.5.</p><p num="0051">A highly preferred applicator (10) according to the present invention is shown in
Figures 1 to 3. As to be seen from these Figures, according to the present
invention, a highly preferred applicator (10) will comprise a sponge (40). Most
preferably such sponge (40) is releasably attached to the applicator (10), so that
it can be replaced by another sponge (40). Preferably such sponge (40) is
provided with a mounting (42) to make the releasable contact with the applicator
(10). Replacement by another sponge (40) may be desired if a sponges (40) has
acquired dirt. Such replacement may also be desired to use sponge (40) of
different size and shape for different cleaning tasks. For example, a consumer
may wish to use a large triangular sponge (40) for cleaning a TV set, but a small
sponge (40) for cleaning a keyboard. Preferably the sponges (40) are replaced
with their respective mountings. </p><p num="0052">It has been found that according to the present invention particularly preferred
application devices (40) to be used on household and office equipment and
preferably with an electrosafe cleaning composition, are application devices (40)
with a tilted wiping surface. The term "tilted wiping surface" as used herein
denotes a wiping surface which is tilted with regard to the plane perpendicular to
the longitudinal axis. The longitudinal axis of an applicator (10) denotes the axis
which is essentially parallel to the forearm of a user using the applicator (10) and
which preferably is an axis of symmetry of the applicator (10) as shown in Figure
1 for an pen-shaped applicator (10). Tilt angles between 10° and 40° are
preferred, tilt angles from 25° to 35° are most preferred. Such a tilted wiping
surface has been found particularly useful for cleaning computer keyboards
which typically are tilted with regard on the surface on which they stand.</p><p num="0053">It has been found that according to the present invention particularly preferred
sponges (40) to be used on household and office equipment and preferably with
an electrosafe cleaning composition, are application devices (40) comprising a
straight edge. An application device (40) comprises a straight edge, as used
herein, if the cross section of the application device (40) parallel with and
adjacent to the wiping surface comprises a straight line, preferred application
devices (40) comprising a straight edge according to the present invention has
the form of a half-circle, a rectangle, a square, a triangle or an isosceles triangle,
the latter being most preferred. Application devices (40) comprising a straight
edge have been found particularly useful for the cleaning of larger surfaces e.g.
TV sets and screens.</p><p num="0054">In one preferred embodiment of the present invention the applicator (10) is
provided as a kit with a set of sponges (40), the set preferably comprising from
two to five sponges (40). A highly preferred set of sponges (40) is shown in
Figures 4a to 6b. This set comprises three sponges (40). A first sponge (40) has
a cross-section (taken perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the applicator
(10)) which is essentially circular and has a diameter of about 16 mm (cf. Fig.
4a). This sponge (40) is not cut parallel to the plane perpendicular to the 
longitudinal axis but forms an angle of about 30° with this plane (cf. Fig. 4b). The
sponge (40) has been found particularly useful for the cleaning of computer
keyboards. A second sponge (40) is comprised which also has a circular cross-section
(in the plane perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the applicator (10))
and has a diameter of about 35 mm (cf. Fig. 5a). The wiping surface of this
sponge (40) is essentially perpendicular to the longitudinal axis (cf. Fig. 5b). A
sponge (40) of this size and shape has been found most useful for the cleaning
of e.g. Hi-fi equipment. A third sponge (40) is comprised, the cross-section of
which (in the plane perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the applicator (10)) is
triangular and more particularly has the shape of a isosceles triangle with a base
length of about 55 mm for each side (cf. Fig. 6a). The wiping surface is
essentially perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the applicator (10) (cf. Fig.
6b). This size and shape of the sponge (40) have been found particularly useful
for the cleaning of larger surfaces e.g. the screen of a TV-set. Of course, the
present invention is not limited to particularly sets of sponges (40) or sponges
(40) of any shape (including namely any cross-section and thickness), size and
material. Also may the wiping surface be tilted with regard to the plane
perpendicular to the longitudinal axis at any angle.</p><p num="0055">While any sponge (40) is suitable, most preferred are dual layer sponges (40),
which preferably comprise a closed cell foam layer and an open cell foam layer.
Preferably the compression resistance of the layer to contact the devices to be
cleaned is from 0.5 kPa to 10 kPa, more preferably 1 kPa to 4 kPa, while the
compression resistance of the layer contacting the sponge mounting is from 1
kPa to 200 kPa, more preferably 5 kPa to 100 kPa. An open cell foam layer
absorbs and distributes the cleaning composition well. Therefore, it is preferred
to use such layer for contact with the device to be cleaned. However, especially
for a large sponge (40) which is provided from opened cell foam the absorptive
capacity of the sponge (40) becomes very large and more cleaning composition
than needed is absorbed and hence cleaning composition, which often is
expensive, remains unused. Therefore, preferred dual layer sponges (40)
employ a closed cell foam in contact with the mounting (42) of the sponge (40). </p><p num="0056">Such closed cell foam layer does have a very low absorptive capacity and hence
easily transmits the cleaning composition, but is soft and flexible and therefore
ensures a good contact of the wiping surface with the object to be cleaned and
further has damping properties as to ensure a soft and gentle cleaning and to
prevent contact of the mounting (42) of the sponge (40) with the device to be
cleaned.</p><p num="0057">A preferred applicator (10) according to the present invention also comprises a
storage device for the cleaning composition. Most preferably, such storage
device is provided in form of a cartridge (20) which fits into the main chassis (12)
of the applicator (10), but is a separate piece and can be replaced by another
cartridge (20). Such cartridge (20) may be a refillable cartridge (20) or may be a
non-refillable cartridge (20). The cartridge (20) may comprise a pumping device
(22) for the cleaning composition or a pumping device (22) may be provided
separately from the cartridge (20). In a most preferred embodiment of the
present invention a non-refillable cartridge (20) is provided together with a pump
(22) which seals the cartridge (20) so that the consumer does not come into
contact with the cleaning composition. While any pumping device (22) is in
accordance with the present invention a preferred pumping device (22) will be
small in size as to fit into the applicator (10) and will deliver a pre-defined and
small amount of cleaning composition each time the pumping device (22) is
activated. The preferred amount of cleaning composition released each time the
pump (22) is activated is from 0.01 ml to 0.1 ml, more preferably from 0.05 ml to
0.1 ml. Preferably, the storage device allows to store from 1 ml to 100 ml of
cleaning composition, more preferably from 3 ml to 20 ml, most preferably from
5 ml to 10 ml of the cleaning composition.</p><p num="0058">A particularly preferred pumping device (22) according to the present invention is
a miniature pump in combination with a capillary (24) extending into the storage
device and being in liquid communication with the cleaning composition. With
such pumping device (22) upon mechanical pressure a vacuum is created which
leads to the release of the defined amount of cleaning composition present in 
the capillary (24). Such a mechanism is not only cheap to produce but ensures
the release of a pre-defined amount of cleaning composition each time the pump
(22) is activated. In a further aspect of such pumping device (22), which is
particularly relevant to the present invention, this device cannot be operated
when being hold upside down or horizontally: When pumping device (22) and
cartridge (20) are hold upside down or horizontally the end of the capillary (24) is
no more in liquid communication with the cleaning composition and therefore no
cleaning composition can be released. Typically, the pumping device (22) is
operated by exertion of pressure via the sponge (40) and the sponge (40)
mounting onto the pumping device (22). Hence, the pumping device (22) could
be operated unintentionally when the sponge (40) is used for spreading cleaning
composition. However, when the device is used for spreading cleaning
composition it is typically hold upside down or in a horizontal position and when
the pumping device (22) described above is used unintentional release of
cleaning composition is therefore prevented.</p><p num="0059">Preferably the main chassis (12) of the applicator (10) is provided with a visual
indicator which indicates a user, how much cleaning composition is left in the
cartridge. Preferably such visual indicator is present in the main chassis (12) in
the form of a broken wall or window (14).</p><p num="0060">The applicator (10) according to the present invention can optionally provided
with a brush (30). While such brush (30) can be made of any material including
any artificial material and also hair a preferred materials are PET and nylon. The
brush (30) can be used for the dusting of surfaces. This dusting may be
independent from the application of cleaning composition or may be a
preparational step for the later application of the cleaning composition. In the
preferred embodiment of the applicator (10) shown in Figures 1 to 3, the brush
(30) is protected by a sliding protector which is movably attached to the main
chassis (12) of the applicator (10). When the brush (30) is not used the sliding
brush protector (32) will fully cover the brush (30). When the brush (30) is used
the protector (32) can be slided over the main chassis (12). </p><p num="0061">According to the present invention it is contemplated to provide the cleaning
composition and the cleaning applicator (10) and other parts in form of the kit.
One preferred such kit, referred to as "starter kit", may comprise the complete
applicator (10) including one sponge (40) and sponge mounting (42) and one
cartridge (20) and may further comprise any number of, preferably one or two,
further cartridges (20) and sponges (40) and sponge mountings (42). A
particularly preferred set of sponges (40) is the set of three sponges (40)
depicted in Figure 4a - 6b. A starter kit may also comprise further cartridges with
cleaning composition. A further preferred kit according to the present invention,
referred to as "refill kit", may comprise any number of cartridges with cleaning
composition and may further comprises replacement sponges (40). The
replacement sponges (40) may be provided with or without a respective sponge
mounting (42).</p><p num="0062">The cleaning composition disclosed herein has been found highly suitable to be
used for any type of office and household equipment. Preferred is the use of the
cleaning composition according to the present invention on devices belonging to
the group of devices operated by electrical power, irrespective if the power is
supplied externally, typically via a power cable, or is supplied internally e.g. by a
battery or solar cell. Even more preferred is the use of the cleaning composition
according to the present invention on devices belonging to the group of devices
comprising an electronic circuit. Also preferred is the use of the cleaning
composition according to the present invention on devices belonging to the
group of devices comprising optical elements, e.g. lenses. Highly preferred is the
use of the cleaning composition according to the present invention on devices
belonging to the group of devices which are encapsulated by a housing, box,
chassis, frame or the like. Also highly preferred is the use of the cleaning
composition according to the present invention on devices belonging to the
group of devices comprising a user interface, which may e.g. comprise a
keyboard, a keypad, a touch screen, a single switch or a set of switches. Most
preferred is the use of the cleaning composition according to the present 
invention for devices which fall into two, preferably three, most preferably all of
the above defined groups of devices.</p><p num="0063">Examples of devices for which the disclosed cleaning composition is highly
suitable include all audio and video devices, namely: TV sets, Hi-fi stereo sets
and their respective components (cassette player, tuner, turn-table, amplifier,
loudspeaker; etc.) and front panels, video tape recorder, MP3 player, CD/DVD
players, musical instruments, like electronic pianos, portable devices of the
named kinds (including devices commonly referred to as "Walkman") and
remote controls for any such device.</p><p num="0064">Other examples include personal communication devices, namely desktop and
cellular phones, fax machines and answer machines.</p><p num="0065">Further examples include optical equipment, namely photo cameras and video
cameras, camcorders, magnification lenses, glasses and projectors.</p><p num="0066">Further examples include data processing devices and related devices, namely
personal desktop, portable computers, palmtop computers, personal organisers
and peripheral equipment, including printers, storage devices, scanners and
keyboards, LCD screens, CRT screens and touch LCD screens.</p><p num="0067">Yet further examples a number of portable devices, namely hand-held electronic
games (such devices are frequently referred to as "game-boys" or "play
stations").</p><p num="0068">Even further examples include office and business equipment, namely
photocopy machines, cashier terminals, calculators.</p><p num="0069">Yet even further examples include household appliances such as coffee
machines, toasters, water boilers, ovens and their front panels, dish washers 
and their front panels, fridges, vacuum cleaners, tools and power tools (e.g.
electric drills) and the like.</p><p num="0070">Even further examples include precious items, namely watches, jewellery, coins,
silver ware and the like.</p><heading><b>Friction resistance</b></heading><p num="0071">Friction resistance, as used herein, refers to friction force per contact area and is
measured as follows: The application device is clamped to the load arm of a
Plint dual axis reciprocating rig (such as model TE75R, MRPRA RUBBER
CONSULTANTS). The angle of the fabric treatment applicator relative to the
contact surface is adapted to maximise the contact area. The clamping
arrangement provided a consumer realistic vertical load, R, on the application
device of 3N. The coefficient of friction is then measured between the application
device and a window glass surface mounted on soft counter surface provided by
a 2 mm thick sheet of soft rubber mounted with double sided adhesive to a flat
aluminium plate. The application device is measured wet using a composition as
given in Example 1. The coefficient of friction is measured over the central 10
mm of four traverses of 20 mm in both the forward and reverse direction at a
speed of 1 mm s<sup>-1</sup> and an average value calculated. Measurements with the
application device in final measuring position are repeated three times to check
reproducibility.</p><heading><b>Compression resistance</b></heading><p num="0072">Compression resistance is measured in accordance with ISO 3386-1 norm and,
as used herein, refers to the median CV<sub>40</sub> value as defined in ISO 3386-1,
measured at a temperature of 23 degree Celsius and 50% relative humidity.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>Use of a cleaning composition comprising a chlorine-free fluorinated carbon
compound on household and office equipment.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>Use of a cleaning composition according to Claim 1 wherein said chlorine-free
fluorinated carbon compound is selected from the group of chlorine-free
perfluorinated carbon compound, perfluoropolyether, H-terminated
perfluoropolyether.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>Use of a cleaning composition according to any of the preceding claims
wherein said household or office equipment is selected from the group
comprising: TV sets, Hi-fi stereo sets and their respective components
(cassette player, tuner, turn-table, amplifier, loudspeaker; etc.), video tape
recorder, MP3 player, CD/DVD players, musical instruments, like electronic
pianos, portable devices of the named kinds (including devices commonly
referred to as "Walkman"), hand-held electronic games and remote controls
for any such device.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>Use of a cleaning composition according to any of the preceding claims
wherein said household or office equipment is selected from the group
comprising: personal desktop, portable computers, palmtop computers,
personal organisers and peripheral equipment, including printers, storage
devices, scanners and keyboards, LCD screens, CRT screens and touch LCD
screens, desktop and cellular phones, fax machines and answer machines.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>Use of an applicator (10) comprising an application device (40) on electronic
household or office equipment, characterised in that said application device
(40) has a compression resistance from 1 kPa to 100 kPa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>Use of an applicator (10) comprising an application device (40) on electronic
household or office equipment, characterised in that said an application
device (40) comprises a dual layer sponge.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>Use of an applicator (10) comprising an application device (40) on electronic
household or office equipment, characterised in that said application device
(40) comprises a straight edge.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>Use of an applicator (10) comprising an application device (40) on electronic
household or office equipment, characterised in that said application device
(40) comprises a tilted wiping surface.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>An applicator (10) comprising an application device (40) and an electrosafe
cleaning composition, characterised in that said application device (40) has a
ratio of compression resistance to friction resistance from 0.1 to 0.5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An applicator (10) comprising an application device (40) and an electrosafe
cleaning composition, characterised in that said application device (40)
comprises a dual layer sponge.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>An applicator (10) comprising an application device (40) and an electrosafe
cleaning composition, characterised in that said application device (40)
comprises a straight edge.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>An applicator (10) comprising an application device (40) and an electrosafe
cleaning composition, characterised in that said application device (40)
comprises a tilted wiping surface.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>An applicator (10) according to any one of the preceding claims,
characterised in that said applicator (10) comprises a storage device and a
separated application device (40).</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>An applicator (10) according to Claim 13, characterised in that said storage
device comprises a replaceable cartridge (20).</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>An applicator (10) according to any one of the preceding claims,
characterised in that said application device comprises a sponge (40).</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>An applicator (10) according to any one of the preceding claims,
characterised in that said applicator (10) further comprises a brush (30).</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A kit for cleaning hard surfaces the kit comprising at least one applicator (10),
at least one cartridge comprising a cleaning composition and at least two
application devices (40).</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>