<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2001018267-A1" country="WO" doc-number="2001018267" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25587900" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20010315"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2001018267-A1" status="new" fvid="77507912"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2001018267</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010315</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="ZA-0000161-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>ZA</country><doc-number>0000161</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20000905</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="ZA-9905746-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>ZA</country><doc-number>9905746</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990907</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>C22B   3/18</main-classification><further-classification>C22B  11/00</further-classification><further-classification>C22B  11/08</further-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B   3/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B   3/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B   3/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B  11/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B  15/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B  15/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B  11/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B  11/08</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B  15/00L4D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B  19/22</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B  19/26</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B  23/04B6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B  23/04P</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B   3/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B   3/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B   3/18</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">RECOVERY OF PRECIOUS METAL FROM SULPHIDE MINERALS BY BIOLEACHING</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">RECUPERATION D'UN METAL PRECIEUX A PARTIR DE MINERAUX SULFURES PAR LIXIVIATION BIOLOGIQUE</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0808910-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0808910</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="FR-2640284-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>FR</country><doc-number>2640284</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-2225256-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2225256</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4721526-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4721526</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5007620-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5007620</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5102104-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5102104</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5127942-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5127942</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5429659-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5429659</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5482534-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5482534</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5914441-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5914441</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998026100-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998026100</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199247 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class D16, AN 1992-382454 XP002154635 &amp; AU 13186 92 A (MOUNT ISA MINES LTD), 1 October 1992 (1992-10-01)</text><sources><source category="Y"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BASSON PETRUS</name><address><country>ZA</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BATTY JOHN DE KLERK</name><address><country>ZA</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BILLITON INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DEW DAVID WILLIAM</name><address><country>ZA</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NORTON ALAN</name><address><country>ZA</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BASSON, PETRUS</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BATTY, JOHN, DE KLERK</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BILLITON INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY B.V.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DEW, DAVID, WILLIAM</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NORTON, ALAN</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BASSON PETRUS</name><address><country>ZA</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BATTY JOHN DE KLERK</name><address><country>ZA</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DEW DAVID WILLIAM</name><address><country>ZA</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NORTON ALAN</name><address><country>ZA</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BASSON, PETRUS</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BATTY, JOHN, DE KLERK</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DEW, DAVID, WILLIAM</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NORTON, ALAN</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties> </bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A method of recovering a precious metal from a sulphide mineral slurry which contains the precious metal which includes the steps of subjecting the slurry to a bioleaching process, supplying a feed gas which contains in excess of 21% oxygen by volume to the slurry, and recovering precious metal from a bioleach residue of the bioleaching process.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>L'invention concerne un procédé de récupération d'un métal précieux à partir d'une suspension de minéraux sulfurés contenant ce métal précieux, qui consiste en ce qui suit: soumettre la suspension à la lixiviation biologique; injecter dans la suspension un gaz d'alimentation qui contient un excès de 21 % d'oxygène en termes de volume; et récupérer le métal précieux à partir du résidu du procédé de lixiviation biologique.</p></abstract> <description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>--><p num="p0001"> RECOVERY OF PRECIOUS METAL FROM SULPHIDE MINERALS BY BIOLEACHING</p> <p num="p0002">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</p> <p num="p0003">This invention relates to the recovery of precious metal from sulphide minerals</p><p num="p0004">As used herein the phrase ' precious metal" includes gold and silver</p><p num="p0005">Commercial bioleach plants which are currently in operation treating precious metal beanng sulphide minerals typically operate within the temperature range of 40°C to 50°C and rely on sparging air to the bioleach reactors to provide the required oxygen Operation at this relatively low temperature and the use of air to supply oxygen limit the rate of sulphide mineral oxidation that can be achieved</p><p num="p0006">The use of high temperatures between 50°C and 100°C greatly increases the rate of precious metal beanng sulphide mineral leaching</p><p num="p0007">The solubility of oxygen is however limited at high temperatures and the leaching rate becomes limited In the case of using air for the supply of oxygen the effect of limited oxygen solubility is such that the leaching rate becomes dependent on and is limited by the rate of oxygen transfer from the gas to the liquid phase <sup>(1 2)</sup></p><p num="p0008">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</p><p num="p0009">The invention provides a method of recovering a precious metal from a sulphide mineral slurry which contains the precious metal which includes the steps of (a) subjecting the slurry to a bioleaching process</p><p num="p0010">(b) supplying a feed gas which contains in excess of 21 % oxygen by volume to the slurry, and</p><p num="p0011">(c) recoveπng precious metal from a bioleach residue of the bioleaching process 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
The bioleach residue may be subjected to a liquid/solid separation step to produce residue solids and solution, and the precious metal may be recovered from the residue solids.</p><p num="p0012">The slurry may be an aqueous slurry containing significant quantities of precious metal eg. gold, or silver, bearing sulphide minerals.</p><p num="p0013">The precious metal may be recovered from the residue solids by a cyanidation process. In this form of the invention the bioleaching process of step (a) may be carried out in a reactor and the method may include the step of feeding off-gas from the reactor to the cyanidation process. This would be done particularly in the case of gold recovery to enhance the leaching of gold.</p><p num="p0014">The precious metal may be recovered from the residue solids by at least one of the following: a resin-in-puip process, a carbon-in-pulp process, and a carbon-in-leach process.</p><p num="p0015">The said solution which is obtained by the aforementioned liquid/solid separation step may be subjected to a neutralisation process. In this process the pH of the solution may be adjusted by the addition of limestone or lime or both.</p><p num="p0016">The neutralisation step may be carried out to precipitate arsenic as ferric arsenate.</p><p num="p0017">As used herein the expression "oxygen enriched gas" is intended to include a gas, eg. air, which contains in excess of 21% oxygen by volume. This is an oxygen content greater than the oxygen content of air. The expression "pure oxygen" is intended to include a gas which contains in excess of 85% oxygen by volume.</p><p num="p0018">Preferably the feed gas which is supplied to the slurry contains in excess of 85% oxygen by volume ie. is substantially pure oxygen.</p><p num="p0019">The method may include the step of maintaining the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry within a desired range which may be determined by the operating conditions and the type of microorganisms used for leaching. The applicant has established that a lower limit for the dissolved oxygen concentration to sustain 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
microorganism growth and mineral oxidation, is in the range of from 0.2 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 4.0 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup>. On the other hand if the dissolved oxygen concentration is too high then microorganism growth is inhibited. The upper threshold concentration also depends on the genus and strain of microorganism used in the leaching process and typically is in the range of from 4 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 10 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup>.</p><p num="p0020">Thus, preferably, the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry is maintained in the range of from 0.2 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 10 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup>.</p><p num="p0021">The method may include the steps of determining the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry and, in response thereto, of controlling at least one of the following: the oxygen content of the feed gas, the rate of supply of the feed gas to the slurry, and the rate of feed of slurry to a reactor.</p><p num="p0022">The dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry may be determined in any appropriate way, e.g. by one or more of the following: by direct measurement of the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry, by measurement of the oxygen content in gas above the slurry, and indirectly by measurement of the oxygen content in off-gas from the slurry, taking into account the rate of oxygen supply, whether in gas enriched or pure form, to the slurry, and other relevant factors.</p><p num="p0023">The method may include the step of controlling the carbon content of the slurry. This may be achieved by one or more of the following' the addition of carbon dioxide gas to the slurry, and the addition of other carbonaceous mateπal to the slurry.</p><p num="p0024">The method may extend to the step of controlling the carbon dioxide content of the feed gas to the slurry in the range of from 0.5% to 5% by volume. A suitable figure is of the order of 1 % to 1.5% by volume. The level of the carbon dioxide is chosen to maintain high rates of microorganism growth and sulphide mineral oxidation</p><p num="p0025">The bioleaching process is preferably carried out at an elevated temperature. As stated hereinbefore the bioleaching rate increases with an increase in operating temperature. Clearly the microorganisms which are 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
used for bioleaching are determined by the operating temperature and vice versa. As the addition of oxygen enriched gas or substantially pure oxygen to the slurry has a cost factor it is desirable to operate at a temperature which increases the leaching rate by an amount which more than compensates for the increase in operating cost. Thus, preferably, the bioleaching is carried out at a temperature in excess of 40°C.</p><p num="p0026">The bioleaching may be carried out at a temperature of up to 100°C or more and preferably is carried out at a temperature which lies in a range of from 60°C to 85°C.</p><p num="p0027">In one form of the invention the method includes the step of bioleaching the slurry at a temperature of up to 45°C using mesophile microorganisms. These microorganisms may, for example, be selected from the following genus groups: Acidithiobacillus (formerly Thiobacillus); Leptosprillum; Ferromicrobium; and Acidiphilium.</p><p num="p0028">In order to operate at this temperature the said microorganisms may, for example, be selected from the following species:</p><p num="p0029">Acidithiobacillus caldus (Thiobacillus caldus); Acidithiobacillus thiooxidans (Thiobacillus thiooxidans); Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans (Thiobacillus ferrooxidans): Acidithiobacillus acidophilus (Thiobacillus acidophilus); Thiobacillus prosperus; Leptospirillum ferrooxidans; Ferromicrobium acidophilus; and Acidiphilium cryptum.</p><p num="p0030">If the bioleaching step is carried out at a temperature of from 45°C to 60°C then moderate theπmophile microorganisms may be used. These may, for example, be selected from the following genus groups: Acidithiobacillus (formerly Thiobacillus); Acidimicrobium; Sulfobacillus; Ferroplasma (Ferriplasma); and Alicy clobacillus.</p><p num="p0031">Suitable moderate thermophile microorganisms may, for example, be selected from the following species: Acidithiobacillus caldus (fonmeriy Thiobacillus caldus); Acidimicrobium ferrooxidans; Sulfobacillus acidophilus; Sulfobacillus disulfidooxidans; Sulfobacillus thermosulfidooxidans; Ferroplasma acidarmanus; Thermoplasma acidophilum: and Alicyclobacillus acidocaldrius. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
It is preferred to operate the leaching process at a temperature in the range of from 60°C to 85°C using thermophilic microorganisms These may for example be selected from the following genus groups Acidothermus, Sulfolobus Metallosphaera, A dianus, Ferroplasma (Ferriplasma), Thermoplasma, and Picrophilus</p><p num="p0032">Suitable thermophilic microorganisms may, for example, be selected from the following species Sulfolobus metallicus, Sulfolobus acidocaldanus Sulfolobus thermosulfidooxidans, Acidianus infemus, Metallosphaera sedula, Ferroplasma acidarmanus Thermoplasma acidophilum Thermoplasma volcanium, and Picrophilus oshimae</p><p num="p0033">The slurry may be leached in a reactor tank or vessel which is open to atmosphere or substantially closed In the latter case vents for off-gas may be provided from the reactor</p><p num="p0034">The invention also provides a method of recovering a precious metal from an aqueous slurry which contains precious metal sulphides which includes the steps of</p><p num="p0035">(a) bioleaching the slurry at a temperature in excess of 40°C,</p><p num="p0036">(b) controlling the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry at a value in the range of 0,2 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 10 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> and</p><p num="p0037">(c) recovenng the precious metal from a bioleach residue of step (a)</p><p num="p0038">Preferably the temperature in step (a) is in excess of 60°C A preferred operating temperature is in the range of 60°C to 85°C</p><p num="p0039">In step (b) the dissolved oxygen concentration may be controlled by controlling the addition of gas which contains in excess of 21 % oxygen by volume to the slurry</p><p num="p0040">In step (c) the bioleach residue may be subjected to a separation step to produce residue solids and solution and the precious metal may be recovered from the residue solids by at least one of the following a cyanidation process a resin-in-pulp process a carbon-m-pulp process and a carbon-in-leach process 
<!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>-->
The invention also extends to a method of enhancing the oxygen mass transfer coefficient from a gas phase to a liquid phase in a precious metal bearing sulphide mineral slurry which includes the step of supplying a feed gas containing in excess of 21 % oxygen by volume to the slurry</p><p num="p0041">The feed gas preferably contains in excess of 85% oxygen by volume</p><p num="p0042">The method may include the step of raising the temperature of the slurry</p><p num="p0043">The invention further extends to a method of bioleaching an aqueous slurry containing precious metal bearing sulphide minerals which includes the steps of bioleaching the slurry at a temperature above 40°C and maintaining the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry in the range of from 0 2 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 10 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup></p><p num="p0044">The dissolved oxygen concentration may be maintained by supplying gas containing in excess of 21% oxygen by volume to the slurry The temperature is preferably in the range of from 60°C to 85°C</p><p num="p0045">The invention is also intended to cover a precious metal recovery system which includes a reactor vessel, a source which feeds a precious metal bearing sulphide slurry to the vessel, an oxygen source a device which measures the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry in the vessel, a control mechanism whereby in response to the said measure of dissolved oxygen concentration, the supply of oxygen from the oxygen source to the slurry is controlled to achieve a dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry within a predetermined range, a separator for separating a bioleach residue from the reactor vessel into residue solids and a solution, and a recovery plant which recovers precious metal from the residue solids</p><p num="p0046">Various techniques may be used for controlling the supply of oxygen to the slurry and hence for controlling the dissolved oxygen content or concentration in the slurry at a desired value Use may for example be made of valves which are operated manually For more accurate control use may be made of an automatic control system These techniques are known in the art and are not further described herein 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>-->
As has been indicated oxygen and carbon dioxide may be added to the slurry in accordance with predetermined cπteπa Although the addition of these materials may be based on expected demand and measurement of other performance parameters, such as ιron(ll) concentration, it is preferred to make use of suitable measurement probes to sample the actual values of the critical parameters</p><p num="p0047">For example use may be made of a dissolved oxygen probe to measure the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry directly To achieve this the probe is immersed in the slurry The dissolved oxygen concentration may be measured indirectly by using a probe in the reactor off-gas or by transmitting a sample of the off-gas, at regular intervals, to an oxygen gas analyser Again it is pointed out that measuring techniques of this type are known in the art and accordingly any appropriate technique can be used</p><p num="p0048">A preferred approach to the control aspect is to utilise one or more probes to measure the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry whether directly or indirectly The probes produce one or more control signals which are used to control the operation of a suitable valve or valves, eg solenoid valves, automatically so that the supply of oxygen to an air stream which is being fed to the slurry is varied automatically in accordance with real time measurements of the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry</p><p num="p0049">Although it is preferred to control the addition of oxygen to a gas stream which is fed to the slurry a reverse approach may be adopted in that the oxygen supply rate to the reactor vessel may be maintained substantially constant and the rate of supply of the sulphide mineral slurry to the reactor vessel may be vaned to achieve a desired dissolved oxygen concentration</p><p num="p0050">The invention is not limited to the actual control technique employed and is intended to extend to vaπations of the aforegoing approaches and to any equivalent process</p><p num="p0051">Gold and silver bearing iron sulphide flotation concentrates frequently contain pyrrhotite and under these conditions the method of the invention is of particular benefit, because pyrrhotite has a high leaching rate even at typical mesophile operating temperatures which is further increased at the higher temperatures used with moderate and extreme thermophiles Thus the benefits of the invention, including a high specific reactor 
<!-- EPO <DP n="10"/>-->
sulphide oxidation duty and reduced specific power requirement for oxidation, will be obtained duπng the bioleaching of typical gold beanng sulphide concentrates, even at mesophile operating temperatures.</p><p num="p0052">It is well known that bioleach residues continuing relatively high levels of elemental sulphur result in high consumptions of cyanide in the subsequent cyanidation process for recovery of gold</p><p num="p0053">The low level of elemental sulphur present in the bioleach residues produced by bioleaching with thermophiles leads the applicant to believe that cyanide consumption in the gold and silver leaching stage will be substantially reduced, bringing significant cost savings Typical mesophile bioleach residues arising from the treatment of gold beanng sulphides consume 10 - 20kg/t of sodium cyanide, which could be reduced to around less than 2kg/t The savings on a plant treating 150 000 tonnes per annum concentrate yielding 100 000 tonnes per annum of bioleach residue would be of the order of USS0 8 to 1 2 million per annum</p><p num="p0054">The reactor off-gas, if richer in oxygen than air, may optionally be added to the cyanidation process (when used) to enhance the leaching of gold</p><p num="p0055">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</p><p num="p0056">The invention is further described by way of example with reference to the accompanying drawings in which Figure 1 is a schematic representation of a portion of a plant in which the invention is earned out,</p><p num="p0057">Figures 2 3 and 4 reflect various results and parameters obtained from operating a bioreactor using the principles of the invention, and</p><p num="p0058">Figure 5 is a process flow chart of the method of the invention applied to the recovery of gold and silver 
<!-- EPO <DP n="11"/>--></p><p num="p0059">DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0060">General Principles</p><p num="p0061">The limitation of low oxygen solubility dunng bioleaching, using air, at high temperatures, which in turn limits the rate of reaction, requires enrichment of the air with oxygen iβ. air with an oxygen content greater than 21 % by volume, or the use of pure oxygen (defined as being greater than 85% oxygen by volume) The use of oxygen enriched air or pure oxygen overcomes the limited rate of reaction due to oxygen supply constraints, but has two major disadvantages a) the provision of oxygen enπched air or pure oxygen is expensive and requires a high utilisation (&gt;60%) of the oxygen to warrant the additional expense <sup>&lt;3)</sup>, and b) if the oxygen level in solution becomes too high microorganism growth is prevented and sulphide mineral bioleaching stops <sup>&lt;4)</sup></p><p num="p0062">Therefore, in order to realise the benefits of high rates of sulphide mineral leaching at high temperatures in commercial bioleaching plants, the drawbacks of requmng expensive oxygen and the πsk of failure if the dissolved oxygen levels become too high must be overcome</p><p num="p0063">The bioleaching of sulphide minerals at an elevated temperature results in a high rate of sulphide mineral oxidation but is dependent on the supply of oxygen and carbon dioxide to maintain high rates of sulphide mineral oxidation and of microorganism growth at adequate rates The absorption of oxygen and carbon dioxide in the bioleaching reactor is limited, in each case, by the rate of mass transfer from the gas phase into the solution phase For oxygen the rate of oxygen absorption is defined by equation (1) as follows R = M. (C* - C<sub>L</sub>) (1) where R = Oxygen demand as mass (kg) per unit volume (m<sup>3</sup>) per unit tιme(s) (kg/m<sup>3</sup>/s),</p><p num="p0064">M = Oxygen mass transfer coefficient in reciprocal seconds (s <sup>1</sup>),</p><p num="p0065">C<sup>*</sup> = Saturated dissolved oxygen concentration as mass (kg) per unit volume (m<sup>3</sup>) (kg/m<sup>3</sup>), and 
<!-- EPO <DP n="12"/>-->
 C<sub>L</sub> = Dissolved oxygen concentration in solution as mass (kg) per unit volume (m<sup>3</sup>) (kg/m<sup>3</sup>)</p><p num="p0066">The factor (C<sup>*</sup> - C<sub>L</sub>) is referred to as the oxygen driving force A similar equation may be used to describe the rate of carbon dioxide supply to the solution If the sulphide mineral oxidation rate is increased the oxygen demand increases proportionately To meet a higher oxygen demand either the oxygen mass transfer coefficient (M) or the oxygen dπving force (C<sup>*</sup>-C<sub>L</sub>) must be increased</p><p num="p0067">An increase in the oxygen mass transfer coefficient may be achieved by increasing the power input to the bioleach reactor mixer This improves gas dispersion in the sulphide mineral slurry With this approach, however an increase in the oxygen mass transfer coefficient of for example 40% requires an increase in the power input to the mixer by a factor of as much as 200% with a commensurate increase in operating costs</p><p num="p0068">The oxygen driving force may be increased by increasing the saturated dissolved oxygen concentration C<sup>*</sup> and reducing the dissolved oxygen content or concentration C<sub>L</sub></p><p num="p0069">Microorganism population growth is limited or prevented if the dissolved oxygen concentration C<sup>*</sup> reaches too high a level A concentration level above 4 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> has been found to be detπmental to 
<img id="imgf000012_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="23" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000012_0001.tif" inline="no" he="4"/>
 strains Certain Acidithiobacillus strains however have been found to be tolerant to dissolved oxygen concentrations of up to 10 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup></p><p num="p0070">The applicant has established that a lower limit for the dissolved oxygen concentration to sustain microorganism growth and mineral oxidation is in the range of from 0 2 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 4 0 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> Thus, in order to provide an adequate or optimum supply of oxygen, the dissolved oxygen concentration in the sulphide mineral slurry must be monitored and where appropriate, the addition of oxygen to the sulphide mineral slurry must be controlled in order to maintain the minimum dissolved oxygen concentration in solution at a value of from 0 2 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 4 0 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup><!-- EPO <DP n="13"/>-->
On the other hand the dissolved oxygen concentration must not exceed an upper threshold value at which microorganism growth is prevented It is pointed out that the upper threshold concentration depends on the genus and strain of microorganism used in the bioleaching process A typical upper threshold value is in the range of from 4 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 10 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup></p><p num="p0071">As has been previously indicated the rate of sulphide mineral oxidation, which can be achieved when operating at a relatively low temperature of the order of from 40°C to 55°C, is limited In order to increase the rate of oxidation it is desirable to make use of thermophiles and to operate at temperatures in excess of 60°C Any suitable microorganism capable of operating within this temperature range may be used The optimum operating temperature is dependent on the genus and type of microorganism used Thus moderate thermophiles of the type Sulfobacillus are suitable for operating at a temperature of up to 65°C Thermophiles of the type Sulfolobus are suitable for operating at temperatures of from 60°C to at least 85°C Sulfolobus metallicus for example, shows optimal growth in the temperature range of from 65°C to 70°C</p><p num="p0072">The applicant has established that the operation of the bioleaching process, using a gas enriched with oxygen, or pure oxygen, as the oxidant, at elevated temperatures of from 40°C to 85°C increases the specific sulphide oxidation duty of the reactor considerably, results in an unexpected and significantly enhanced oxygen mass transfer rate, increases the oxygen utilisation providing that the dissolved oxygen concentration is controlled above the point where microorganism growth and mineral oxidation are prevented and below the point at which microorganism growth is inhibited, and the overall power required for the oxidation of sulphide minerals is significantly reduced</p><p num="p0073">The method of the invention represents a significant improvement compared to a bioleach operation earned out at a temperature of from 40°C to 45°C with air</p><p num="p0074">The controlled addition of oxygen enriched air or pure oxygen directly into the bioreactor improves the oxygen utilisation efficiency The oxygen utilisation for a conventional commercial bioleach plant (at least 100m<sup>3</sup> in volume) operating at from 40°C to 45°C with air may be expected to achieve a maximum oxygen utilisation 
<!-- EPO <DP n="14"/>-->
factor of from 40% to 50% Consequently only 40% to 50% of the total mass of oxygen supplied to the bioleach plant is used to oxidise the sulphide minerals With the method of the invention the oxygen utilisation is significantly higher of the order of from 60% to 95% The higher oxygen utilisation is achieved by controlled oxygen addition and results from the enhanced oxygen mass transfer rate and by operating at low dissolved oxygen concentrations in the solution phase</p><p num="p0075">It will be appreciated that although high oxygen demand in bioleach reactors has come about pπmanly by the use of higher temperatures, rapidly leaching sulphide minerals at temperatures below 60°C using mesophile or moderate thermophile microorganisms will have similarly high oxygen demands The method of the invention is therefore not restπcted to suit thermophiles or extreme thermophiles, but also mesophile and moderate thermophile microorganisms</p><p num="p0076">Another advantage of using air enπched with oxygen or pure oxygen is that the evaporation losses are reduced because there is less inert gas removing water vapour from the top of the reactor This is particularly important in areas where water is scarce or expensive</p><p num="p0077">In carrying out the method of the invention the temperature of the slurry in the bioleach vessel or reactor may be controlled in any suitable way known in the art In one example the bioleach reactor is insulated and heating takes place by means of energy which is released by the oxidation of sulphides The temperature of the slurry is regulated using any suitable cooling system for example an internal cooling system</p><p num="p0078">Table 1 shows typical data for specific sulphide oxidation duty and oxygen utilisation when bioleaching with air at 40°C to 45°C in two commercial bioreactors Plant A and Plant B respectively (greater than 100m<sup>3</sup> in volume) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="15"/>-->
Table 1 Commercial Bioreactor Performance Results</p><p num="p0079"><img id="imgf000015_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="148" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000015_0001.tif" inline="no" he="75"/></p><p num="p0080">At low temperatures (40°C - 50°C), with air as the inlet gas, which applies to the results for the commercial reactors, Plant A and Plant B, presented in Table 1 , the oxygen utilisations achieved are expected and the oxygen mass transfer coefficients (M) correspond to the applicant's design value. The applicant has determined that if the method of the invention were to be applied to Plant A, the plant performance would be significantly increased, as indicated by the results presented in Table 2.</p><p num="p0081">Table 2 Predicted Improvement In Commercial Bioreactor Perfonmance</p><p num="p0082"><img id="imgf000015_0002" orientation="portrait" wi="174" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000015_0002.tif" inline="no" he="75"/><!-- EPO <DP n="16"/>-->
The results clearly show the benefit of the invention in achieving higher rates of reaction by the combination of bioleaching at high temperature adding oxygen enπched gas and by controlling the dissolved oxygen concentration to a predetermined low level (e g 0 2 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 4 0 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> ) The specific sulphide oxidation duty of the reactor is increased by almost threefold Clearly the upper dissolved oxygen concentration should not be increased above a value at which microorganism growth is inhibited or stopped</p><p num="p0083">Even though additional capital for the production of oxygen is required the savings in reactor and other costs at least offset this additional expense Additionally, the specific power consumption per kg sulphide oxidised is decreased by approximately one-third In a plant oxidising 300 tonnes of sulphide per day, the power saving, assuming a power cost of US$0 05 per kWh would amount to US$2 8 million per annum The high oxygen utilisation and increased specific sulphide oxidation capacity of the reactor represent in combination a considerable improvement over conventional bioleaching practice conducted at lower temperatures with oxygen supplied by air</p><p num="p0084">Bioleaching Plant</p><p num="p0085">Figure 1 of the accompanying drawings shows a bioleaching plant 10 in which bioleaching is earned out, in accordance with the pπnciples of the invention</p><p num="p0086">The plant 10 includes a bioreactor 12 with an agitator or mixer 14 which is driven by means of a motor and gearbox assembly 16</p><p num="p0087">In use a tank or vessel 18 of the reactor contains a sulphide mineral slurry 20 An impeller 22 of the agitator is immersed in the slurry and is used for mixing the slurry in a manner which is known in the art</p><p num="p0088">A probe 24 is immersed in the slurry and is used for measuring the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry A second probe 26 inside the tank 18 above the surface level 28 of the slurry, is used for measuring the carbon dioxide content in the gas 30 above the slurry 20 
<!-- EPO <DP n="17"/>-->
An oxygen source 32, a carbon dioxide source 34 and an air source 36 are connected through respective control valves 38, 40 and 42 to a sparging system 44, positioned in a lower zone inside the tank 18, immersed in the slurry 20</p><p num="p0089">The probe 24 is used to monitor the dissolved oxygen concentration in the sulphide mineral slurry 20 and provides a control signal to a control device 46 The control device controls the operation of the oxygen supply valve 38 in a manner which is known in the art but in accordance with the principles which are described herein in order to maintain a desired dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry 20</p><p num="p0090">The probe 26 measures the carbon dioxide content in the gas above the sulphide mineral slurry 20 The probe 26 provides a control signal to a control device 48 which in turn controls the operation of the valve 40 in order to control the addition of carbon dioxide from the source 34 to a gas stream flowing to the sparger 44</p><p num="p0091">The air flow rate from the source 36 to the sparger 44 is controlled by means of the valve 42. Normally the valve is set to provide a more or less constant flow of air from the source 36 to the sparger and the additions of oxygen and carbon dioxide to the air stream are controlled by the valves 38 and 40 respectively Although this is a preferred approach to adjusting the oxygen and carbon dioxide contents in the air flow to the sparger other techniques can be adopted For example it is possible, although with a lower degree of preference, to adjust the air stream flow rate and to mix the adjustable air stream with a steady supply of oxygen and a vanable supply of carbon dioxide, or vice versa Another possibility is to have two separate air stream flows to which are added oxygen and carbon dioxide respectively Irrespective of the technique which is adopted the objective remains the same, namely to control the additions of oxygen and carbon dioxide to the slurry 20</p><p num="p0092">Slurry 50 is fed from a slurry feed source 52 through a control valve 54 and through an inlet pipe 56 into the interior of the tank 18 The slurry feed rate may be maintained substantially constant, by appropriate adjustment of the valve 54, to ensure that slurry is supplied to the tank 18 at a rate which sustains an optimum leaching rate The supplies of air, oxygen and carbon dioxide are then regulated, taking into account the substantially constant slurry feed rate, to achieve a desired dissolved oxygen concentration in the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="18"/>-->
slurry 20 in the tank, and a desired carbon dioxide content in the gas 30 above the slurry Although this is a preferred approach it is apparent that the slurry feed rate could be adjusted, in response to a signal from the probe 24 to achieve a desired dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry In other words the rate of oxygen addition to the slurry may be kept substantially constant and the slurry feed rate may be vaned according to requirement</p><p num="p0093">Another variation which can be adopted is to move the probe 24 from a position at which it is immersed in the slurry to a position designated 24A at which it is located in the gas 30 above the level 28 The probe then measures the oxygen contained in the gas above the slurry iβ the bioreactor off-gas The oxygen content in the off-gas can also be used as a measure to control the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry, taking any other relevant factors into account</p><p num="p0094">Conversely it may be possible to move the carbon dioxide probe 26 (provided it is capable of measuring the dissolved carbon dioxide content) from a position at which it is directly exposed to the gas 30 to a position designated 26A at which it is immersed in the slurry in the tank The signal produced by the probe at the position 26A is then used, via the control device 48, to control the addition of carbon dioxide from the source 34 to the air stream from the source 36</p><p num="p0095">Although the carbon dioxide source 34 which provides carbon dioxide in gas form is readily controllable and represents a preferred way of introducing carbon into the slurry 20 it is possible to add suitable carbonate materials to the slurry 50 before feeding the slurry to the reactor Carbonate material may also be added directly to the sulphide mineral slurry 20 in the reactor In other cases though there may be sufficient carbonate in the sulphide mineral slurry so that it is not necessary to add carbon, in whatever form, to the slurry nor to control the carbon content in the slurry</p><p num="p0096">It is apparent from the aforegoing description which relates to the general principles of the invention that the supply of oxygen to the slurry is monitored and controlled to provide a desired dissolved oxygen concentration level in the slurry 20 This can be done in a vanety of ways eg by controlling one or more of 
<!-- EPO <DP n="19"/>-->
the following in an appropriate manner namely the slurry feed rate, the air flow rate from the source 36, the oxygen flow rate from the source 32 and any vaπation of the aforegoing</p><p num="p0097">The carbon dioxide flow rate is changed in accordance with the total gas flow rate to the sparger 44 in order to maintain a concentration in the gas phase i e in the gas stream to the reactor, of from 0 5% to 5% carbon dioxide by volume This carbon dioxide range has been found to maintain an adequate dissolved carbon dioxide concentration in the slurry a factor which is important in achieving effective leaching</p><p num="p0098">The addition of oxygen to the sulphide mineral slurry 20 is controlled in order to maintain the minimum dissolved oxygen concentration in solution at a value of from 0 2 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 4 0 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> The upper threshold value depends on the genus and strain of microorganism used in the bioleaching process and typically is in the range of from 4 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 10 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup></p><p num="p0099">Figure 1 illustrates the addition of oxygen from a source 32 of pure oxygen The pure oxygen can be mixed with air from the source 36 Any other suitable gas can be used in place of the air The addition of oxygen to air results to what is referred to in this specification as oxygen enriched gas iβ a gas with an oxygen content in excess of 21% by volume It is possible though to add oxygen substantially in pure form directly to the slurry As used herein pure oxygen is intended to mean a gas stream which contains more than 85% oxygen by volume</p><p num="p0100">The temperature in the bioleach reactor or vessel may be controlled in any appropriate way using techniques which are known in the art In one example the tank 18 is insulated and heating takes place by means of energy which is released by the oxidation of sulphides The temperature of the slurry 20 is regulated using an internal cooling system 70 which includes a plurality of heat exchanger cooling coils 72 connected to an external heat exchanger 74</p><p num="p0101">The vessel 18 may be substantially sealed by means of a lid 80 Small vents 82 are provided to allow for the escape of off-gas The off-gas may if required be captured or treated in any appropriate way before being released to atmosphere Alternatively according to requirement the tank 18 may be open to atmosphere 
<!-- EPO <DP n="20"/>-->
The microorganisms chosen for the leaching process will determine the leaching temperature, and vice versa. The applicant has found that a preferred operating temperature is above 60°C, for example in the range of 60°C to 85°C. In this range thermophilic microorganisms, in any appropriate combination, are employed. In the range of from 45°C to 60°C, on the other hand, moderate thermophiles are employed while at temperatures below 45°C mesophiles are used. These microorganisms may, for example, be chosen from those referred to hereinbefore.</p><p num="p0102">Although the benefit of adding oxygen to the slurry which is to be leached, by making use of oxygen enπched air or, more preferably, by making use of substantially pure oxygen ie. with an oxygen content in excess of 85%, is most pronounced at high temperatures at which greater leaching rates are possible, a benefit is nonetheless to be seen when oxygen enriched air or substantially pure oxygen is added to the slurry at lower temperatures, of the order of 40°C or even lower. At these temperatures the leaching rates are slower than at elevated temperatures and although an improvement results from using oxygen enriched air the cost thereof is generally not warranted by the relatively small increase in leaching rate.</p><p num="p0103">Test Results</p><p num="p0104">The importance of maintaining an adequate supply of oxygen and hence a sufficiently high dissolved oxygen concentration to sustain microorganism growth and mineral oxidation is shown in the results presented in Figure 2 If the dissolved oxygen is allowed to drop below 1 5 ppm, and particularly below 1.0 ppm, biooxidation becomes unstable, which is indicated by higher ιron(ll) concentrations in solution, of greater than 2 g/l. At consistent levels of biooxidation, achieved by maintaining a dissolved oxygen concentration above 1.5 ppm, in this experiment, ιron(ll) is rapidly oxidised to ιron(lll), and ιron(ll) concentrations remain generally below 1.0 g/l.</p><p num="p0105">The results presented in Figure 2 were obtained from operation of a first or pπmary reactor of a continuous pilot plant treating a chalcopyπte concentrate at a feed solids concentration of 10% by mass and a temperature of 77°C, with Su/fo/oύL/s-like archaea. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="21"/>-->
The effect of increasing the oxygen content of the feed gas to a bioreactor and controlling the dissolved oxygen concentration, in accordance with the principles of the invention, was tested in an experiment using a 5m<sup>3</sup> bioreactor which was operated with a continuous pyπte or blended pyrrhotite and pynte flotation concentrate feed, at a temperature of about 77°C using a mixed culture of Sulfolobus- ke archaea and a solids density of 10% by mass The carbon dioxide content in the bioleach inlet gas was controlled at a level of between 1 and 1 5 % by volume The dissolved oxygen concentration was generally within the range 0 4 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 3 0 x 10<sup>'3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> The results of the experiment are presented in Figure 3</p><p num="p0106">From the graphs presented in Figure 3 it is clear that, when sparging with air (enπched with carbon dioxide 20 7% oxygen and 1 0% carbon dioxide), the maximum oxygen demand (directly proportional to the sulphide oxidation duty) was limited to 11 3 kg/m<sup>J</sup>/day since the dissolved oxygen concentration which was achievable using air only (i e not enriched with oxygen) was just sufficient to maintain microorganism growth</p><p num="p0107">By controlling the oxygen content of the inlet gas, the oxygen addition rate, and the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry in the range of 0 4 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 3 0 x 10<sup>'3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup>, the oxygen demand, i e the sulphide mineral oxidation rate, was increased dramatically The dissolved oxygen concentration was controlled to a low value, but above the minimum limit for successful microorganism growth, so that the utilisation of oxygen was maximised The results show the oxygen demand, or sulphide oxidation duty, was increased by over threefold Thus by increasing the oxygen content in the inlet gas from 20 7% to a maximum of 90 8% the specific oxygen demand was increased from 11 3 kg/m<sup>3</sup>/day to 33 7 kg/m<sup>3</sup>/day In addition, by controlling the dissolved oxygen concentration to a low value, but above the minimum value for sustained microorganism growth the oxygen utilisation was maximised The oxygen utilisation showed a general increase with an increase in the oxygen content of the inlet gas from 29% (for an inlet gas oxygen content of 20 7%) to 91 % (for inlet gas containing 85 5% oxygen)</p><p num="p0108">The high oxygen utilisations achieved of well over 60% are much better than expected Analysis of the results indicates that the oxygen mass transfer coefficient (M), as defined by equation (1), is significantly and unexpectedly enhanced for operation of the bioreactor at a high temperature (77°C ) and with a high oxygen content in the inlet gas (from 29% to 91 % in the expeπment) In fact, the oxygen mass transfer coefficient (M) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="22"/>-->
is increased by a factor of 2 69 on average, compared to the applicant s design value This enhancement is after considering the improvement in the mass transfer coefficient due to temperature which would be expected to increase the value of M by a factor of 1 59 for a temperature increase from 42°C to 77°C, according to the temperature correction factor proposed by Smith et al <sup>(5)</sup> This correction factor has been demonstrated experimentally to be valid for a temperature in the range of from 15°C to 70°C <sup>(6)</sup></p><p num="p0109">The determination of the enhanced oxygen mass transfer coefficient is shown from the results presented in Figure 4 where the oxygen demand divided by the design oxygen mass transfer coefficient (M<sub>aeS</sub>ιgn) is plotted against the oxygen driving force, as defined in equation (1) The slope of the regression line plotted through the data indicates the enhancement in the oxygen mass transfer coefficient by a factor of 2 69</p><p num="p0110">Process Example</p><p num="p0111">The inventive principles in the preceding section have been described in the context of sulphide minerals in general and, as will be appreciated by those skilled in the art these principles can be applied to precious metal bearing sulphide minerals</p><p num="p0112">Figure 5 of the accompanying drawings is a flow sheet representation of the method of the invention applied to the recovery of gold and silver from a gold and silver beanng sulphide concentrate which is in slurry form The slurry is designated by the reference numeral 50 The plant shown in Figure 1 bears the reference numeral 10 and the oxygen and carbon dioxide sources 32 and 34 respectively in Figure 1 are similarly labelled in Figure 5 The control techniques which have been described in connection with Figure 1 are used to regulate the operation of the plant 10 in Figure 5</p><p num="p0113">The slurry 50 is leached in the plant 10 containing one or more bioleach reactors using oxygen enπched gas or substantially pure oxygen 32 as the oxidant The oxygen concentration in the plant 10 is controlled to a suitable value depending on the type of microorganism used for leaching</p><p num="p0114">A residue slurry 100 produced by the plant 10 contains solubilised iron predominantly in the ferric state and if arsenic is present in the concentrate this appears in solution in the pentavalent state The residue slurry 100 
<!-- EPO <DP n="23"/>-->
is subjected to a liquid/solid separation step 102 producing washed solids 104 which are treated for gold recovery in a suitable way eg by cyanidation, a carbon-in-pulp, a carbon-in-leach, or a resin-m-pulp, process 106 Residue slurry 108 produced by the step 106 is disposed of The precious metal content is subjected to a further recovery process 110 eg elution and gold electrowmning steps These aspects are known in the art and consequently are not further described herein</p><p num="p0115">Solution 112 produced in the liquid/solid separation step 102, which contains all of the solubilised metal such as iron and arsenic, is fed to a neutralisation step 114 where the pH of the solution is adjusted by the addition of limestone 116 and lime 118 resulting in the precipitation of arsenic as an environmentally stable feme arsenate 120 which is then disposed of If there is insufficient carbonate in the slurry 50, in the plant 10, then some of the carbon dioxide gas 122 generated in the neutralisation step, is directed to the slurry in the bioleach plant This may be done by adding the carbon dioxide to the source 34 or blending the carbon dioxide with the gas stream from the oxygen source 32</p><p num="p0116">Off-gas 130 from the reactor 10, if ncher in oxygen than air, may be added to the cyanidation process 106 (when employed) to enhance the leaching of gold and reduce the cyanide consumption</p><p num="p0117">Anticipated Results in Applying the Method of the Invention to the Recovery of Gold and Silver</p><p num="p0118">The following results were achieved by applying the method of the invention to the leaching of a West Australian nickel concentrate The applicant is of the opinion that similar results would be achieved when leaching gold (or silver) bearing sulphide minerals, operating under similar conditions</p><p num="p0119">Table 3 Sulphur Compounds in Nickel Bioleach Residues</p><p num="p0120"><img id="imgf000023_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="169" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000023_0001.tif" inline="no" he="51"/></p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="24"/>--><claim-text>CLAIMS</claim-text><claim-text>1 A method of recovenng a precious metal from a sulphide mineral slurry which contains the precious metal which includes the steps of (a) subjecting the slurry to a bioleaching process,</claim-text><claim-text>(b) supplying a feed gas which contains in excess of 21 % oxygen by volume to the slurry, and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) recovenng precious metal from a bioleach residue of the bioleaching process</claim-text><claim-text>2 A method according to claim 1 wherein the bioleach residue is subjected to a liquid/solid separation step to produce residue solids and solution and precious metal is recovered from the residue solids</claim-text><claim-text>3 A method according to claim 2 wherein precious metal is recovered from the residue solids by a cyanidation process</claim-text><claim-text>4 A method according to claim 3 wherein the bioleaching process of step (a) is earned out in a reactor and which includes the step of feeding off-gas from the reactor to the cyanidation process</claim-text><claim-text>5 A method according to claim 2 wherein precious metal is recovered from the residue solids by at least one of the following a restn-in-pulp process a carbon-in-pulp process and a carbon-m-leach process</claim-text><claim-text>6 A method according to any one of claims 2 to 5 wherein the said solution is subjected to a neutralisation step</claim-text><claim-text>7 A method according to claim 6 wherein the pH of the solution is adjusted in the neutralisation step by the addition of at least one of the following limestone and lime</claim-text><claim-text>8 A method according to claim 6 or 7 wherein the neutralisation step is earned out to precipitate arsenic as feme arsenate 
<!-- EPO <DP n="25"/>-->
A method according to any one of claims 6 to 8 which includes the step of feeding carbon dioxide, generated in the neutralisation step, to the slurry in the bioleaching process</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 9 wherein the precious metal is at least one of the following gold or silver</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 10 wherein the feed gas contains in excess of 85% oxygen by volume</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 11 which includes the step of controlling the supply of the feed gas to the slurry to maintain the dissolved oxygen content in the slurry within a desired range</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 12 wherein the said dissolved oxygen content is maintained in the range of from 0 2 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 10 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup></claim-text><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 13 which includes the step of controlling the carbon content of the slurry</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 14 wherein the said carbon content is controlled by one or more of the following the addition of carbon dioxide gas to the slurry and the addition of other carbonaceous material to the slurry</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 15 which includes the step of controlling the carbon dioxide content of the feed gas in the range of from 0 5% to 5 0% carbon dioxide by volume</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 16 which includes the step of bioleaching the slurry at a temperature in excess of 40 °C 
<!-- EPO <DP n="26"/>-->
A method according to claim 17 wherein the said temperature is in the range of from 40°C to 100°C</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 18 wherein the said temperature is in the range of from 60 C to 85 C</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 16 which includes the step of bioleaching the slurry at a temperature of up to 45°C using mesophile microorganisms</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 20 wherein the microorganisms are selected from the following genus groups Acidithiobacillus, Thiobacillus, Leptospnllum, Ferromicrobium; and Acidiphilium</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 20 or 21 wherein the said microorganisms are selected from the following species Acidithiobacillus caldus (Thiobacillus caldus), Acidithiobacillus thiooxidans (Thiobacillus thiooxidans), Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans (Thiobacillus ferrooxidans), Acidithiobacillus acidophilus (Thiobacillus acidophilus), Thiobacillus prosperus, Leptospinllum ferrooxidans. Ferromicrobium acidophilus and Acidiphilium cryptum</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 16 which includes the step of bioleaching the slurry at a temperature of from 45°C to 60°C using moderate thermophile microorganisms</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 23 wherein the microorganisms are selected from the following genus groups Acidithiobacillus (formerly Thiobacillus) Acidimicrobium, Sulfobacillus, Ferroplasma (Ferriplasma), and Alicyclobacillus</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 23 or 24 wherein the said microorganisms are selected from the following species Acidithiobacillus caldus (fonmeriy Thiobacillus caldus), Acidimicrobium ferrooxidans Sulfobacillus acidophilus, Sulfobacillus disulfidooxidans, Sulfobacillus thermosulfidooxidans Ferroplasma acidarmanus Thermoplasma acidophilum, and Alicyclobacillus acidocaldπus 
<!-- EPO <DP n="27"/>-->
A method according to any one of claims 1 to 16 which includes the step of bioleaching the slurry at a temperature of from 60°C to 85°C using thermophilic microorganisms</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 26 wherein the microorganisms are selected from the following genus groups A dothermus Sulfolobus, Metallosphaera Acidianus, Ferroplasma (Ferriplasma),</claim-text><claim-text>Thermoplasma, and Picrophilus</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 26 or 27 wherein the said microorganisms are selected from the following species Sulfolobus metallicus, Sulfolobus acidocaldaπus, Sulfolobus thermosulfidooxidans, Acidianus infernus, Metallosphaera sedula, Ferroplasma acidarmanus,</claim-text><claim-text>Thermoplasma acidophilum Thermoplasma volcanium and Picrophilus oshimae</claim-text><claim-text>A method of bioleaching a slurry containing precious metal beanng sulphide minerals which includes the steps of (a) bioleaching the slurry using suitable microorganisms at a temperature in excess of 40°C, and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) controlling the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry within a predetermined range</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 29 wherein the said dissolved oxygen concentration is controlled by controlling the supply of oxygen to the slurry</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 30 wherein the oxygen is supplied to the slurry in the form of oxygen enriched gas or substantially pure oxygen</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 29 to 31 wherein the said temperature is in the range of from 60°C to 85°C</claim-text><claim-text>A method of enhancing the oxygen mass transfer coefficient from a gas phase to a liquid phase in a precious metal bearing sulphide mineral slurry which includes the step of supplying a feed gas containing in excess of 21 % oxygen by volume to the slurry 
<!-- EPO <DP n="28"/>-->
A method according to claim 33 wherein the feed gas contains in excess of 85% oxygen by volume.</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 33 or 34 which includes the step of raising the temperature of the slurry</claim-text><claim-text>A method of bioleaching an aqueous slurry containing precious metal bearing sulphide minerals which includes the steps of</claim-text><claim-text>(a) bioleaching the slurry at a temperature above 40°C, and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) maintaining the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry in the range of from 0.2 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 10 x 10<sup>"3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup></claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 36 wherein the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry is maintained by supplying gas containing in excess of 21% oxygen by volume to the slurry</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 36 or 37 wherein the temperature is in the range of from 60°C to 85°C</claim-text><claim-text>A method of recovenng a precious metal from an aqueous slurry which contains precious metal bearing sulphides which includes the steps of-</claim-text><claim-text>(a) bioleaching the slurry at a temperature in excess of 40°C,</claim-text><claim-text>(b) controlling the dissolved oxygen content in the slurry at a value in the range of from 0 2 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> to 10 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup>. and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) recovenng precious metal from a bioleach residue of step (a)</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 39 wherein in step (a) the temperature is in excess of 65°C</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 39 or 40 wherein, in step (b), the dissolved oxygen content is controlled by controlling the addition of gas which contains in excess of 21 % oxygen by volume to the slurry</claim-text><claim-text>A method according to claim 41 wherein the gas contains in excess of 85% oxygen by volume 
<!-- EPO <DP n="29"/>-->
A method according to any one of claims 39 to 42 wherein in step (c) the bioleach residue is subjected to a separation step to produce residue solids and solution, and precious metal is recovered from the residue solids by at least one of the following a cyanidation process, a resin-m- pulp process, a carbon-m-pulp process, and a carbon-m-leach process</claim-text><claim-text>A precious metal recovery system which includes a reactor vessel, a source which feeds a precious bearing metal sulphide mineral slurry to the vessel, an oxygen source, a device which measures the dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry in the vessel, a control mechanism whereby, in response to the said measured dissolved oxygen concentration, the supply of oxygen from the oxygen source to the slurry is controlled to achieve a dissolved oxygen concentration in the slurry within a predetermined range, and a recovery plant which recovers precious metal from a bioleach residue from the reactor vessel</claim-text><claim-text>A system according to claim 44 wherein the oxygen source supplies oxygen in the form of oxygen enπched air or substantially pure oxygen to the slurry</claim-text><claim-text>A system according to claim 44 or 45 wherein the reactor vessel is operated at a temperature in excess of 60°C</claim-text><claim-text>A system according to any one of claims 44 to 46 wherein the recovery plant recovers precious metal by means of a cyanidation process and off-gas from the reactor vessel is used in the cyanidation process 
<!-- EPO <DP n="30"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>REFERENCES</claim-text><claim-text>1 Bailey, A D and Hansford, G S , (1996) Oxygen mass transfer limitation of batch bio-oxidation at high solids concentration Minerals Eng , 7(23), pp293-303</claim-text><claim-text>2 Myerson, A S , (1981) Oxygen mass transfer requirements during the growth of Thiobacillus ferrooxidans on iron pyπte, Biotechnol, Bioeng , Vol 23, pp1413</claim-text><claim-text>3 Peter Greenhalgh, and Ian Ritchie, (1999), Advancing Reactor Design For The Gold Bioleach Process, Minproc Ltd, Biomine 99, 23-25 Aug 1999, Perth Australia, pp52-60</claim-text><claim-text>4 Brock Biology of Microogranisms Eight Edition, 1997 Madigan M T Martinko J M Parker J Prentia Hall International, Inc , London</claim-text><claim-text>5 J M Smith K van't Riet and J C Middleton, (1997), Scale-Up of Agitated Gas-Liquid Reactors for</claim-text><claim-text>Mass Transfer, in Proceedings of the 2<sup>nd</sup> European Conference on Mixing, Cambπdge, England, 30 March - 1 Apπl 1997, pp F4-51 - F4-66</claim-text><claim-text>6 Boogerd F C , Bos P Kuenen J G Heijnen, J J &amp; Van der Lans, R G J M, Oxygen and Carbon Dioxide Mass Transfer and the Aerobic, Autotrophic Cultivation of Moderate and Extreme Thermophiles A Case Study Related to the Microbial Desulfuπzation of Coal, Biotech Bioeng , 35 1990, p 1111 - 1119 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>