<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1035117-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1035117" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="8239957" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000913"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1035117-A1" status="new" fvid="22929269"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1035117</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000913</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99200675-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99200675</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990308</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-99200675-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99200675</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990308</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 251/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 251/60        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07D 251/60</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07D251:60</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung von Melamin aus Harnstoff</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method for preparing melamine from urea</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour la préparation de la mélamine a partir d'urée</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0747366-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0747366</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0808836-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0808836</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4565867-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4565867</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997020826-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997020826</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997047609-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997047609</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998055466-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998055466</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DSM NV</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DSM N.V.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DSM N.V.</last-name><address><street>Het Overloon 1</street><city>6411 TE Heerlen</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TJIOE TJAY TJIEN</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TJIOE, TJAY TJIEN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TJIOE, TJAY TJIEN</last-name> <address><street>Hillenraedstraat 7</street><city>6136 BR Sittard</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook> </inventor> </inventors> </parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Method for preparing melamine from urea via a
high-pressure process in which solid melamine is obtained
by transferring the melamine melt to an expansion vessel
where the melamine melt is cooled by incorporated
ammonia. Excess ammonia gas is added to the melamine melt
to produce a gas/liquid mixture having a mass ratio of at
least 0.01. This two-phase mixture is then sprayed via a
spraying means into an expansion vessel, the expansion
vessel having an ammonia environment with a reduced
ammonia pressure. The melamine melt is cooled and
solidified by the expansion and evaporation of the
incorporated ammonia to form melamine powder. The
melamine melt is thereby directly converted into a
melamine powder after which the melamine powder is cooled
further and the ammonia pressure is released.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The invention relates to a method for
preparing melamine from urea via a high-pressure process
in which solid melamine is obtained by transferring a
melamine melt to a vessel where it is cooled with a
cooling medium such as ammonia to produce solid high
purity melamine.</p><p num="0002">Various methods for the production of
melamine have been described in previous publications
including, inter alia, EP-A-747366 which describes a
high-pressure process for preparing melamine from urea.
In particular, EP-A-747366 describes how urea is
pyrolyzed in a reactor, operating at a pressure of from
10.34 to 24.13 MPa and a temperature of from 354 to
454°C, to produce a reactor product. This reactor
product, containing liquid melamine, CO<sub>2</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> , is
transferred under pressure as a mixed stream to a
separator.</p><p num="0003">In this separator, the reactor product is
separated into a gaseous stream and a liquid stream. The
gaseous stream contains primarily CO<sub>2</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> waste gases
and melamine vapor. The liquid stream mainly comprises a
melamine melt. The gaseous stream is transferred to a
scrubber unit, while the liquid stream is transferred to
a product-cooling unit.</p><p num="0004">In the scrubber unit, the gaseous stream is
scrubbed with molten urea. The heat transfer achieved in
the scrubber unit both preheats the molten urea and cools
the gaseous stream to a temperature from 177 to 232°C. 
The molten urea also scrubs the gaseous stream to remove
the melamine vapor from the waste gases. The preheated
molten urea, along with the melamine that was scrubbed
from the CO<sub>2</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> waste gases, is then fed into the
reactor.</p><p num="0005">In the product-cooling unit, the melamine
melt is cooled and solidified with a liquid cooling
medium to produce a solid high purity melamine product
without the need for additional purification. The
preferred liquid cooling medium is one that forms a gas
at the temperature of the melamine melt and at the
pressure in the product-cooling unit. EP-A-747366
identifies liquid ammonia as the preferred liquid cooling
medium with the pressure in the product-cooling unit
being above 4.14 MPa.</p><p num="0006">Although according to EP-A-747366 the purity
of the solid melamine product obtained using the
disclosed process was greater than 99 wt%, this degree of
purity has proven difficult to maintain continuously on a
commercial scale. The inability to maintain a purity
greater than 99 wt% is a drawback that renders the
melamine produced less suitable for more demanding
applications, particularly melamine-formaldehyde resins
used in laminates and/or coatings.</p><p num="0007">Other methods have been suggested to overcome
these drawbacks, including among them the applicant's
earlier application, WO 98/55466, which used an external
spray of liquid ammonia or cool ammonia gas spray to cool
the melamine melt, which may be mixed with a minor amount
of ammonia gas, as it was sprayed into the cooling
vessel. Although this method represented a significant 
improvement over the prior art methods, the method
described in WO 98/55466 still required an external spray
of a cooling medium to solidify the melamine. The most
efficient cooling of the melamine melt with an external
spray, however, depends upon thorough atomization of the
melamine melt (to maximize surface area) and thorough
mixing of the atomized melamine melt and the cooling
medium spray. A lack of uniformity in the melamine
droplet size or spray pattern, and/or non-homogeneous
mixing of the droplets and the cooling medium will
produce less than optimum results.</p><p num="0008">Yet another method is taught in WO 97/20826
which provides for the solidifaction of the melamine
through expansion and evaporation of dissolved ammonia.
WO 97/20826 teaches the use of relatively high pressures,
up to 40 MPa, at temperatures up to 60°C above the
melting point of melamine, followed by expansion of the
melamine melt at a pressure between 20 MPa and amospheric
pressure. In order to get a quantity of ammonia into
solution sufficient to provide the desired cooling, the
initial pressures are preferably high and the pressure
drop during the relaxation step is large. In general,
however, using higher pressures in a commercial plant
necessitates increased capital investment in process
vessels, piping, and pumps, and results in higher
operating costs. It is preferable, therefore, to operate
at the lowest possible pressure at which satisfactory
results may be obtained.</p><p num="0009">The object of the present invention is to
provide an improved method for preparing melamine from
urea, in which melamine is obtained directly from liquid 
melamine melt as a dry powder having a high degree of
purity. More particularly, the object of the present
invention is to obtain an improved high-pressure process
for preparing melamine from urea, in which melamine is
obtained directly from the liquid melamine melt as a dry
powder having a high degree of purity by cooling and
solidifying via an incorporated cooling medium.</p><p num="0010">The applicant has found that high purity
melamine can be produced from the melamine melt, which
has a temperature between the melting point of melamine
and 450°C, preferably less than 45°C, and more preferably
less than 30°C above the melting point, by incorporating
sufficient excess ammonia into the melamine melt in an
ammonia injection vessel to form a gas/liquid mixture
having a gas/liquid mass ratio between 0.01 and 1.0, and
preferably between 0.03 and 0.9. This gas/liquid mixture
is then sprayed via a spraying means into an expansion
vessel to cool and solidify the melamine by expanding and
evaporating the incorporated ammonia in the reduced
pressure expansion vessel. The expansion vessel includes
an ammonia atmosphere that, although preferably held at a
pressure between 0.5% and 60% of the pressure of the
ammonia injection vessel, more preferably between 0.5%
and 30% of the pressure of the ammonia injection vessel,
is still above atmospheric pressure. The melamine powder
thereby obtained may then be cooled further in the
expansion vessel, or in a separate cooling vessel, and
the pressure reduced to atmospheric pressure to obtain
the final melamine powder product.</p><p num="0011">In the ammonia injection vessel, ammonia is
injected into the melamine melt, the quantity of ammonia 
injected being more than necessary to saturate the
melamine melt at equilibrium. The excess ammonia is
maintained in the melamine melt as ammonia bubbles, the
melamine melt and ammonia bubbles forming a two-phase
gas/liquid mixture.</p><p num="0012">In the expansion vessel, the gas/liquid
mixture is rapidly decompressed to cool and solidify the
molten melamine. The expansion and vaporization of the
excess ammonia in the gas/liquid mixture is sufficient to
solidify the melamine without the need for any external
cooling medium such as gas or liquid ammonia sprays,
aqueous ammonia solutions, or other cooling means.
Further cooling of the solid melamine may, however, be
desirable and may be achieved by applying various
techniques as disclosed in the prior art, particularly
through the introduction of liquid ammonia or cool
ammonia gas into the solid melamine.</p><p num="0013">The advantage of the method according to the
present invention is the continuous production, on a
commercial scale, of dry melamine powder with a purity
above 98.5 wt%, and generally above 99 wt%, that has very
good color characteristics. The high purity melamine
produced according to the present invention is suitable
for virtually any melamine application, including
melamine-formaldehyde resins used in laminates and/or
coatings. At similar operating conditions, the melamine
powder produced according to the present invention
provides other advantages over the melamine produced by
the prior art processes including reduced particle size,
increased surface area, and increased porosity.</p><p num="0014">The preparation of melamine preferably uses 
urea as the raw material, the urea being fed into the
reactor as a melt and reacted at elevated temperature and
pressure. Urea reacts to form melamine, and the by-products
NH<sub>3</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>, according to the following reaction
equation:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">6 CO(NH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub><sup>®</sup> C<sub>3</sub>N<sub>6</sub>H<sub>6</sub> + 6 NH<sub>3</sub> + 3 CO<sub>2</sub></st32:che></p><p num="0015">The production of melamine from urea can be
carried out at high pressure, preferably between 5 and
25 MPa, without the presence of a catalyst, at reaction
temperatures between 325 and 450°C, and preferably
between 350 and 425°C. The by-products NH<sub>3</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> are
usually recycled to an adjoining urea factory.</p><p num="0016">The above-mentioned objective of the
invention is achieved by employing an apparatus suitable
for the preparation of melamine from urea. An apparatus
suitable for the present invention may comprise a
scrubber unit, a reactor having either an integrated
gas/liquid separator or a separate gas/liquid separator,
an ammonia injection vessel, an expansion vessel, and
possibly additional cooling vessels. It will be
appreciated that the configuration of the ammonia
injection vessel is not restricted and may, depending on
the plant configuration, comprise a portion of the piping
between the reactor, or the gas/liquid separator, and the
expansion vessel.</p><p num="0017">In one embodiment of the invention, melamine
is prepared from urea in an apparatus comprising a
scrubber unit, a melamine reactor having either an
integrated gas/liquid separator or a separate gas/liquid 
separator, an ammonia injection vessel, an expansion
vessel, and an optional cooling vessel. In this
embodiment, the urea melt is fed into a scrubber unit
operating at a pressure of from 5 to 25 MPa, preferably
from 8 to 20 MPa, and at a temperature above the melting
point of urea. This scrubber unit may be provided with a
cooling jacket or internal cooling bodies to provide
additional temperature control.</p><p num="0018">As it passes through the scrubber unit, the
urea melt contacts the reaction waste gases coming from
the melamine reactor or the separate gas/liquid
separator. The reaction gases mainly consist of CO<sub>2</sub> and
NH<sub>3</sub> and may include melamine vapor. The urea melt scrubs
the melamine vapor from the CO<sub>2</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> waste gases and
carries this melamine along back to the reactor. In the
scrubbing process, the waste gases are cooled from the
temperature of the reactor, i.e., from 350 to 425°C, to
from 170 to 240°C, the urea being heated to from 170 to
240°C. The CO<sub>2</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> waste gases are removed from the
top of the scrubber unit and may, for example, be
recycled to an adjoining urea factory, where they can be
used as raw materials for the urea production.</p><p num="0019">The preheated urea melt is drawn off from the
scrubber unit, together with the melamine scrubbed from
the waste gases, and transferred to the high pressure
reactor operating at pressures between 5 and 25 MPa, and
preferably between 8 and 20 MPa. This transfer may be
achieved using a high-pressure pump or, where the
scrubber is positioned above the reactor, by gravity, or
a combination of gravity and pumps.</p><p num="0020">In the reactor, the urea melt is heated to a 
temperature between 325 and 450°C, preferably between
about 350 and 425°C, under a pressure between 5 and
25 MPa, preferably between 8 and 20 MPa, to convert the
urea into melamine, CO<sub>2</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub>. In addition to the urea
melt, a certain amount of ammonia can be metered into the
reactor as, for example, a liquid or hot vapor. The
additional ammonia, although optional, may serve, for
example, to prevent the formation of condensation products
of melamine such as melam, melem and melon, or to
promote mixing in the reactor. The amount of additional
ammonia supplied to the reactor may be up to 10 moles
ammonia per mole of urea, preferably up to 5 moles
ammonia per mole of urea, and, most preferably, up to
2 moles of ammonia per mole of urea.</p><p num="0021">The CO<sub>2</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> produced in the reaction, as
well as any additional ammonia supplied, collect in the
separation section, for example in the top of the reactor
or in a separate gas/liquid separator positioned
downstream of the reactor, and are separated from the
liquid melamine. If a separate, downstream gas/liquid
separator is used, it may be advantageous for additional
ammonia to be metered into this separator. The amount of
ammonia in this case is 0.01-10 moles of ammonia per mole
of melamine, and preferably 0.1-5 moles of ammonia per
mole of melamine. Adding additional ammonia to the
separator promotes the rapid separation of carbon dioxide
from the reactor product, thus preventing the formation
of oxygen-containing by-products. As described above, the
gas mixture removed from the gas/liquid separator may be
passed to the scrubber unit in order to remove melamine
vapor and preheat the urea melt. </p><p num="0022">The melamine melt, having a temperature
between the melting point of melamine and 450°C, is drawn
off from the reactor, or from the downstream gas/liquid
separator, and optionally cooled, is then fed into an
ammonia injection vessel. In the ammonia injection
vessel, excess ammonia is added to the melamine melt to
produce a gas/liquid mixture in which ammonia is present
both in solution and as a separate gas phase. Sufficient
ammonia is added to produce a two-phase stream in which
the gas/liquid mass ratio is between 0.01 and 1.0, and
preferably between 0.03 and 0.9. This gas/liquid mixture
is then sprayed into an expansion vessel to obtain the
solid melamine product.</p><p num="0023">Prior to spraying in the expansion vessel,
however, the melamine melt may be cooled from the reactor
temperature or gas/liquid separator temperature to a
temperature closer to, but still above, the melting point
of melamine. The melamine melt, which is drawn off from
the reactor at a temperature typically above 380°C, may
be cooled to a temperature preferably not more than 45°C,
and more preferably not more than 30°C, above the
melamine melting point before being sprayed into the
expansion vessel. The lower the temperature of the melt
before expansion, the lesser ammonia is needed for
cooling and solidifying the melamine melt in the
expansion vessel. The melamine melt may be cooled in the
gas/liquid separator, the ammonia injection vessel, or in
an additional apparatus positioned downstream from the
reactor and before the expansion vessel. It is
contemplated that cooling can take place by injection of
a cooling medium, for example ammonia gas having a 
temperature below the temperature of the melamine melt,
or by passing the melamine melt through a heat exchanger.</p><p num="0024">The melamine and ammonia mixture, is
transferred to a spraying means as a two-phase mixture
and there it is sprayed through a spraying means into an
expansion vessel to solidify the melamine and form a dry
melamine powder. The spraying means is an apparatus by
which the gas/liquid mixture is converted into droplets,
by causing the melt to flow at high speed into the
expansion vessel. The spraying means may be a nozzle or
valve. The outflow velocity of the gas/liquid mixture
from the spraying means is, as a rule, greater than
20 m/s, and is preferably greater than 50 m/s. The
outflow velocity is defined as the nominal volumetric
flow of the mixture (in m<sup>3</sup>/s) devided by the smallest
cross sectional flow area in the nozzle or valve (in m<sup>2</sup>).</p><p num="0025">The expansion vessel contains an ammonia
environment and operates at an increased ammonia
pressure. The melamine droplets from the spraying means
are cooled by energy transfer from the molten melamine to
the expanding and evaporating ammonia to produce melamine
powder. The melamine powder thus formed can have a
temperature between 100°C and the solidification point of
melamine, and preferably below 300°C.</p><p num="0026">In another embodiment of the present
invention the melamine powder formed by spraying the
gas/liquid mixture into the expansion vessel is held in
the expansion vessel for a predetermined contact time
under an increased ammonia pressure and at a temperature
above 200°C. The duration of this contact time is
preferably between 5 minutes and 2 hours. During this 
contact time, the temperature of the melamine product can
remain virtually constant or it may be cooled to a
temperature above 200°C. Additional cooling of the
solidified melamine may be effected through the addition
of cool ammonia gas or liquid ammonia, separately or in
combination with mechanical agitation and indirect
cooling through contact with cooled surfaces. Examples of
means for mechanically agitating the melamine powder
include a screw and rotating drum, a rotating bowl,
rotating discs, rotating segmented discs, rotating pipes
and the like.</p><p num="0027">Once the melamine powder has been cooled to a
temperature below 200°C, the ammonia pressure may be
released. Preferably, the ammonia gas is completely
removed (to an amount below 1000 ppm, preferably below
300 ppm, and, most preferably, below 100 ppm) by blowing
air through the melamine powder. The ammonia pressure may
be released before, or in conjunction with, cooling the
melamine powder from a temperature below 200°C to ambient
temperature.</p><p num="0028">The invention will be explained in more
detail with reference to the following examples and
comparative examples.</p><heading><u style="single">Example I</u></heading><p num="0029">To a melamine melt, which is saturated with
ammonia at a temperature of 359 °C and a pressure of 20.4
MPa, additional ammonia gas with the same temperature is
added. The liquid flow is 4.8 kg/hour and the additional
ammonia gas flow is 1.4 kg/hour. This two-phase flow is
depressurized in a vessel wherein an ammonia pressure of 
2.5 MPa is maintained, resulting in solidification of the
melamine melt. The melamine melt is further cooled with
liquid ammonia and the vessel is depressurized. The
product has a melamine purity of 99.6%.</p><heading><u style="single">Example II</u></heading><p num="0030">To a melamine melt, which is saturated with
ammonia at a temperature of 353 °C and a pressure of 17.9
MPa, additional ammonia gas with the same temperature is
added. The liquid flow is 4.8 kg/hour and the additional
ammonia gas flow is 0.9 kg/hour. This two-phase flow is
depressurized in a vessel with an ammomia pressure of 1.8
MPa, resulting in solidification of the melamine melt.
The melamine melt is further cooled with liquid ammonia
and the vessel is depressurized. The product has a
melamine purity of 99.2%.</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative example A</u></heading><p num="0031">The same experiment as mentioned in example I
is performed without the additional ammonia gas flow. So
only a single phase melamine melt is depressurized in the
quench vessel. The product has a melamine purity of
98.7%.</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative example B</u></heading><p num="0032">The same experiment as mentioned in example
II is performed without the additional ammonia gas flow.
So only a single phase melamine melt is depressurized in
the quench vessel. The product has a melamine purity of
98.5%.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>Method for preparing melamine from urea via a high-pressure
process characterized in that, high purity
melamine can be produced from the melamine melt,
which has a temperature between the melting point
of melamine and 450°C, by incorporating sufficient
excess ammonia into the melamine melt in an ammonia
injection vessel to form a two-phase gas/liquid
mixture, the gas/liquid mixture having a gas/liquid
mass ratio of between 0.01 and 1.0, thereafter
spraying the gas/liquid mixture via spraying means
into an expansion vessel to cool and solidify the
melamine by expanding and evaporating of the
incorporated ammonia in the reduced pressure
expansion vessel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>Method according to Claim 1, characterized in that
the gas/liquid mass ratio is between 0.03 and 0.9.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>Method according to either one of Claims 1-2,
characterized in that the temperature of the
melamine melt being sprayed into the expansion
vessel is between the melting point of melamine and
a temperature 45°C above the melting point of
melamine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>Method according to either one of Claims 1-3,
characterized in that the temperature of the
melamine melt being sprayed into the expansion
vessel is between the melting point of melamine and
a temperature 30°C above the melting point of
melamine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>Method according to Claims 1-4, characterized in
that the expansion vessel include an ammonia
pressure held between 0.5% and 60% of the pressure
of the ammonia injection vessel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>Method according to Claims 1-4, characterized in
that the expansion vessel include an ammonia
pressure held between 0.5% and 30% of the pressure
of the ammonia injection vessel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>Method according to Claims 1-6, characterized in
that the configuration of the ammonia injection
vessel comprise a portion of the piping between the
reactor or the gas/liquid separator and the
expansion vessel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>Method according to Claims 1-7, characterized in
that the outflow velocity of the gas/liquid mixture
from the spraying means is greater than 50 m/sec.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>Method according to Claims 1-8, characterized in
that the ammonia pressure is released if the
melamine powder has a temperature below 200°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>Method for the preparation of melamine as
substantially described in the specification and
the examples.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="169" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="254" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="170" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="252" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90020001" orientation="portrait" wi="169" status="new" file="90020001.tif" he="250" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>