<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1424357-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1424357" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="30769110" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040602"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1424357-A1" status="new" fvid="24046977"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1424357</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040602</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03257439-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03257439</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031126</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-6588602-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6588602</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021127</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/16        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/34        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/3492      20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/52        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/521       20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/523       20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/56        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  25/00        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  25/06        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  33/00        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  33/20        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  71/00        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  71/12        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/3492S</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/523</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/56</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Additiv für thermoplastische Harze und flammhemmende Harzzusammensetzungen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Additive for thermoplastic resins and flame retardant resin compositions</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Additif pour des résines thermoplastiques et compositions de résines ignifuges</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0425710-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0425710</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0653458-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0653458</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1270613-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1270613</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-2002226684-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002226684</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4618636-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4618636</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1995016736-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1995016736</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199637 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A13, AN 1996-368436 XP002272166 &amp; JP 08 176450 A (SUMITOMO BAKELITE CO LTD) 9 July 1996 (1996-07-09)</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199830 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A13, AN 1998-343419 XP002272165 &amp; JP 10 130454 A (TECHNO POLYMER KK) 19 May 1998 (1998-05-19)</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 2002, no. 12, 12 December 2002 (2002-12-12) &amp; JP 2002 226684 A (DAINIPPON INK &amp; CHEM INC), 14 August 2002 (2002-08-14)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEN ELECTRIC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1 River Road</street><city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ARAKALI RADHAKRISHNA</name><address><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>BAJGUR CHANDRA S</name><address><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PECAK WILLIAM</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ARAKALI, RADHAKRISHNA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BAJGUR, CHANDRA S.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PECAK, WILLIAM</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ARAKALI, RADHAKRISHNA</last-name><address><street>232/13, Snehsadan IV Main Road</street><city>Bangalore Mass. 560066</city><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BAJGUR, CHANDRA S.</last-name><address><street>82, 6th Main, 1E Cross BSK 3rd Stage, 2nd Phase</street><city>Bangalore Karnataka 585106</city><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PECAK, WILLIAM</last-name><address><street>54 Western Avenue</street><city>Cohoes New York 12047</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Szary, Anne C.</last-name><address><street>London Patent Operation General Electric International, Inc. 15 John Adam Street</street><city>London WC2N 6LU</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A thermoplastic resin composition with improved flame retardance, flow and heat
deflection temperature includes a thermoplastic resin; resorcinol diphenyl phosphate;
and an additive blend. The additive blend includes a combination of melamine
polyphosphate and ferrocene. The thermoplastic composition reduces the amounts of
resorcinol diphenyl phosphate required for effective flame retardancy. Moreover, the
effective amounts of melamine polyphosphate and ferrocene do not deleteriously
affect other properties of the thermoplastic composition such as Izod strength, flow
properties, and heat deflection temperatures. A process for manufacturing a
thermoplastic composition is also disclosed.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present disclosure relates to an additive for thermoplastic resins and to resin
compositions containing such additives. In particular, the present disclosure relates to
additives which enable improved flame retardant characteristics, heat deflection
temperatures and flow rates of thermoplastic resins such resin compositions
containing polyphenylene ether (PPE), high impact polystyrene (HIPS) and the like.
The present disclosure also relates to a process for the preparation of a thermoplastic
resin composition containing such additives and with improved flame retardant, heat
deflection temperature and flow properties.</p><p num="0002">Thermoplastic resins have use in different industries such as materials for parts of
electric and electronic appliances and also for parts of automobiles. Thermoplastic
resin compositions such as high impact polystyrene (HIPS) and polyphenylene ether
(PPE) resin compositions are also useful as adhesives, sealants, gels, automotives,
cabling, electrical applications, aerospace, sporting equipment, electrical laminates
and IC encapsulation materials. Polyphenylene ether resins are also useful as
additives for various thermoplastic and thermoset materials. The physical, electrical
and chemical properties of polyphenylene ether resin compositions make them ideal
for a wide variety of industrial applications.</p><p num="0003">U.S. Patent Nos. 3,383,435; 4,128,602 and 4,128,603 disclose thermoplastic polymer
blends comprising polyphenylene ether (PPE) and vinylaromatic polymers, such as
styrene polymers which are useful as molding materials. An important advantage of
the polymer blends comprising polyphenylene ethers and styrene polymers is that, by
admixing halogen-free additives, in particular phosphorus-containing compounds, it is
possible to obtain molding materials which are flame-retardant and can therefore be
used for many applications in the electrical industry. In particular, the test for flame
retardancy according to UL 94 is critical for use in the electrical industry. In this test,
a flame is applied repeatedly to vertically fastened test specimens. The test specimen
heats up to a very great extent. In some cases, this leads to the dripping of flaming 
polymer material and ignition of the cotton wool mounted below the rod. This
undesirable behavior is observed in particular when large amounts of flameproofing
agents must be used in order to achieve short combustion times.</p><p num="0004">Styrenic polymer compositions such as HIPS, containing various polymeric additives
such as rubbers to improve mechanical properties, acrylonitrile/butadiene/styrene
(ABS) type compositions are widely used because of their mechanical properties.
HIPS for example is widely used in the production of molded consumer goods, such
as in the production of parts of television cabinets. ABS is used in production of parts
that require higher toughness and chemical resistance. However, styrenic type
polymers suffer from relatively high flammability, thereby limiting their applications
involving subjection of the molded parts to high temperatures.</p><p num="0005">Several attempts have been made in the art to improve the flame retardancy of
thermoplastic resins such as PPE and HIPS compositions. However, most of the
solutions offered suffer from one disadvantage of the other.</p><p num="0006">Resorcinol bis(diphenyl phosphate) (also referred herein as "RDP") has been used as
a flame retardant aid in PPE/PPO/HIPS formulations to give effective flame
retardance performance. It is also an effective plasticizer, which provides desirable
mechanical and chemical properties to the polymer resin. In the art, it is also known
that the amount of RDP in the thermoplastic resin should preferably be at a minimum
both from the point of view of the cost of the additive and also since it has been found
that large amounts of RDP (greater than about 16-20 parts of RDP) result in
reduction of the modulus of the resin formulation as well as impairs the heat
deflection temperature properties of the resin formulation. Several compounds have
been tried in the art as co-additives with RDP that would enable the reduction of RDP
in the resin formulation. For example, both ferrocene and melamine polyphosphate
have been tried individually as co-additives for RDP to be used in resin formulations.
However, a problem faced in the use of either ferrocene or melamine polyphosphate
as a co-additive with RDP is that while it is possible to reduce the amount of RDP and
retain the flame retardance performance of the resin formulation, other properties of
the resin such as flowability and Izod impact are impaired. In particular, for example, 
when melamine polyphosphate is used as a co-additive, to obtain effective flame
retardance, large quantities thereof have to be used. This often results in bleeding of
the melamine polyphosphate from the resin at high temperatures during processing.</p><p num="0007">It is also known in the art for example that addition of a halogen flame retardant
imparts flame retardancy to thermoplastic polyester resins. However, the use of
halogen flame retardants results in the formation of halogen compounds which act as
impurities in the resin compositions. It is also observed that halogen products are
sometimes formed as thermal decomposition products and result in corrosion of the
kneader, molding machine, mold, and other equipment used in the kneading and
molding steps. The use of halogen based flame retardants also suffers from the added
disadvantage of formation of poisonous gas due to decomposition thereof.</p><p num="0008">Attempts have been made to avoid the use of halogen based flame retardants by using
phosphorous based compounds. For example, Japanese published application JP-A
55-82149 discloses a method for improving flame retardancy of thermoplastic
polyester compositions comprising addition of red phosphorus or a phosphoric acid
compound thereto. However, it is observed that the addition of red phosphorous while
avoiding the disadvantages of use of halogen based flame retardants does not improve
the flame retardancy. This problem is sought to be overcome in the process disclosed
in Japanese published application JP A 8-73720. The process disclosed herein
comprises the addition of a calcium or aluminum salt of phosphinic acid to the
polyester. The disadvantage of this process however is that in order to enhance the
flame retardancy, the additive has to be added in large quantities, as a result of which
the moldability of the polyester is impaired.</p><p num="0009">JP-A-5-179123 discloses a composition which is made flame-retardant by addition of
an organic phosphorus flame retardant. The flame-retardant resin composition of this
disclosure comprises inter alia, a polycarbonate resin and contains an organic
phosphorus flame retardant, a boron compound, organopolysiloxane, and a
fluororesin. The flame-retardant resin composition of JP-A-6-192553 comprises a
polycarbonate resin and a polyalkylene terephthalate resin and contains a graft 
copolymer, an oligomeric organic phosphorus flame retardant, and a fluorinated
polyolefin.</p><p num="0010">However, the use of red phosphorus poses several handling problems. Red
phosphorous poses the danger of dust explosion and also may emit smell or gas when
processed in high temperature. It is also observed that red phosphorus alone does not
provide the desired flame retardance and requires to be used in either large quantities
or in combination with another flame retardant or a flame retardation aid. Attempts
have been made to overcome these problems by coating the surface of red phosphorus
for stabilization. For example, JP-A-52-142751, JP-B-5-18356, and JP-A-5-239260
disclose red phosphorus coated with a thermosetting resin, aluminum hydroxide, and
the like. JP-B-2-37370 proposes a flame-retardant resin composition comprising a
polyester resin and thermosetting resin-coated red phosphorus and, if desired, a
reinforcing filler. JP-A-5-239260 and JP-A-5-247264 disclose a flame-retardant resin
composition comprising a thermoplastic resin such as polycarbonate, polyester resin,
and the like, and electrolessly plated red phosphorus.</p><p num="0011">In the fields where such flame-retardant resin compositions are used as, for example,
electric and electronic parts, simplification of assembly and cost reduction have been
desired, and it has been promoted to make parts integral or thinner. Therefore,
materials used in these parts are required to show satisfactory flowability in molding
and to maintain high heat resistance and high flame retardance.</p><p num="0012">Addition of organic phosphorus flame retardant to a polycarbonate resin in an attempt
to impart sufficient flame retardance also results in considerable reduction in heat
resistance. Polycarbonate resin compositions containing red phosphorus or stabilized
red phosphorus also lack long-term heat stability. Thus, moldings made thereof are
often deformed on prolonged exposed to a temperature no higher than around 150°C.
Another problem faced in the use of phosphorous-based flame retardants is that the
compositions obtained thereby suffer from poor molding processability due to low
flowability. While the problem of flow can be overcome by molding at a high
temperature, this results in the red phosphorous emitting a disagreeable smell and
decomposition gas being generated which contaminates the mold. </p><p num="0013">In the prior art, preferred flame retardant aids include phosphorous compounds such
as elemental phosphorous, organic phosphonic acids, phosphonates, phosphinates,
phosphinites, phosphine oxides such as triphenylphosphine oxide, phosphines,
phosphites and phosphates. Suitable phosphates include phenylbisdodecyl phosphate,
phenylbisneopentyl phosphate, phenylethylene hydrogen phosphate, phenyl-bis-3,5,5'-trimethylhexyl
phosphate, ethyldiphenyl phosphate, 2-ethylhexyl di(p-tolyl),
phosphate, diphenyl hydrogen phosphate, bis(2-ethyl-hexyl)p-tolylphosphate, tritolyl
phosphate, bis(2-ethylhexyl)-phenyl phosphate, tri(nonylphenyl)phosphate, phenylmethyl
hydrogen phosphate, di(dodecyl)p-tolyl phosphate, tricresyl phosphate,
triphenyl phosphate, isopropylated triphenyl phosphate, halogenated triphenyl
phosphate, dibutylphenyl phosphate, 2-chlorethyldiphenyl phosphate, p-tolyl
bis(2,5,5'-trimethylhexyl)phosphate, 2-ethylhexyldiphenyl phosphate and the like.</p><p num="0014">Generally triphenyl phosphate, the alkylated triphenyl phosphates, including
isopropylated and butylated triphenyl phosphates, bis-neopentyl piperidinyl
diphosphate, tetraphenyl bisphenol-A diphosphate, tetraphenyl resorcinol
diphosphate, hydroquinone diphosphate, bisphenol-A diphosphate, bisphenol-A
polyphosphate, mixtures of these compounds and derivatives of these compounds are
the most preferred phosphates.</p><p num="0015">The use of triphenyl phosphate (TPP) as a flame retardant additive for various
polymer compositions is taught for example in US Patents 4,526,917 and 5,206,276.
However, the use of TPP as a flame retardant additive is thought to depend on the
presence of oxygen in the polymer chain or in the simultaneous use of halogen
containing flame retardants (Jurgen Troitzsch, Carl Hanserverlag, <i>"International
Plastics Flammability Handbook'</i> 2<sup>nd</sup> Ed., 1990, pp47 - 49). As a result, TPP has
been used in industry in the preparation of polycarbonates and polyethers but not
significantly used for the preparation of styrenic polymer compositions.</p><p num="0016">As pointed out above, these additives are required to be used in large amounts to
obtain the desired result. The use of large amounts of additive impacts on the heat
deflection temperature and flow properties of the resin. Poor melt flow can impact 
the size and type of the part being prepared from thermoplastic resin and also further
affect the equipment in which the composition is being processed.</p><p num="0017">U.S. Patent No. 4,154,712 teaches that processability can be improved by decreasing
the molecular weight of the polyphenylene ether polymers. Reduction of molecular
weight of the PPE polymers however sometimes adversely affects other properties
such as impact strength. It is known that in order to aid processing, flow promoters
such as polystyrene, saturated polyalicyclic resins and terpene phenol can be added to
the PPE resins so as to reduce viscosity and impart high flow to the resulting
composition. However, the addition of polystyrene, terpene phenol and other similar
flow promoters reduce the heat deflection temperature (HDT) of the product and
typically increase the flammability of the PPE resin, as measured under UL94
standard protocol.</p><p num="0018">U.S. Patent No. 5,376,724 discloses PPE compositions containing a resinous additive
comprising vinyl aromatic monomers such as sytrene monomers or a hydrocarbon
compound containing at least 35 wt % aromatic units which are said to improve flow
of the resin composition with only minor reductions in HDT values and impact
strength. U.S. Patent No. 5,081,185 describes compositions comprising a blend of
two or more polyphenylene ether resins with one resin having high intrinsic viscosity
values of at least about 3.8 dl/g and the other having low intrinsic viscosity values of
no greater than 0.33 dl/g. The blend of the two PPE resins exhibits higher melt flow
with no substantial decrease in heat deflection temperature (HDT) when compared to
the high intrinsic viscosity PPE resin of the blend.</p><p num="0019">U.S. Patent No. 6,414,084 teaches a polyphenylene ether resin, where the PPE resin
has an intrinsic viscosity of more than 0.2 dl/g as measured in chloroform at 25°C;
and a dendritic polymer with a melt viscosity in the range of 1 to 250 Pa at a
temperature of 110°C and shear rate of 30 sec<sup>-1</sup>. The dendritic polymer is present in
an amount of 30 wt % or less and is of a starburst configuration and comprises
polyester branching units bound to a core. </p><p num="0020">The use of ferrocene as a flame retardant aid is taught in Linteris, G. T.; Rumminger,
M. D.; Babushok, V. I.; Tsang, W. in Combustion Institute, Symposium
(International) on Combustion, 28th. Proceedings. Vol 2. July 20-August 4, 2000,
Edinburgh, Scotland, Combustion Institute, Pittsburgh, PA, Candel, S.; Driscoll, J. F.;
Burgess, A. R.; Gore, J. P., Editors, 2965-2972 pp, 2000.</p><p num="0021">Another problem of using additives such as resorcinol diphenylphosphate (RDP) and
other phosphorous compounds is that the cost overruns are high. Attempts have been
made to reduce the amounts of additives such as RDP by using it in combination with
melamine polyphosphate or ferrocene. While the use of melamine polyphosphate
(MPP) or ferrocene provide good results in terms of flowability and flame retardance,
there is a significant impact on the Izod strength of the molded product. This problem
is particularly acute at high levels of loading of ferrocene or MPP, which however is
required to obtain good flame retardance.</p><p num="0022">As can be seen it is desirable to provide a thermoplastic resin formulations such as
PPE or HIPS with high flow characteristics with reduced loadings of flow modifier to
minimize the impact on HDT values, impact properties and flame retardance.</p><heading>BRIEF SUMMARY</heading><p num="0023">Disclosed herein is an additive blend for a flame retardant thermoplastic resin
composition comprising an organo phosphate compound other than melamine
polyphosphate, the additive blend comprising melamine polyphosphate; and ferrocene
or an organo iron compound. In a preferred embodiment, the melamine
polyphosphate is in an amount of about 0.5 to about 5 parts by weight and the
ferrocene or the organo iron compound s in an amount of about 0.2 to about 5.0 parts
by weight for every 100 parts by weight of resin composition.</p><p num="0024">A thermoplastic resin composition with improved flame retardance, tensile properties,
flex, and heat deflection temperature comprises a thermoplastic resin; an organo
phosphate compound other than melamine polyphosphate; melamine polyphosphate;
and ferrocene or an organo iron compound. In one embodiment, the composition
comprises less than or equal to about 20 parts by weight of the resorcinol bis(diphenyl 
phosphate) for every 100 parts by weight of the thermoplastic resin, wherein the
melamine polyphosphate is in an amount of about 0.5 to about 5.0 parts by weight and
the ferrocene or the organo ion compound is in an amount of about 0.2 to about 5.0
parts by weight based on the amount of the rescorcinol bis(diphenyl phosphate) in the
composition.</p><p num="0025">A method for the manufacture of a thermoplastic resin composition extrudate with
improved flame retardance, flowability and heat deflection temperature performance
comprises mixing a thermoplastic resin, an organo phosphate other than melamine
polyphosphate, melamine polyphosphate, and ferrocene to produce a mixture; and
extruding the mixture.</p><p num="0026">The above described and other features are exemplified in the following detailed
description.</p> <heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading><p num="0027">The disclosure relates to novel additive compositions for use as flame retardant aids
and/or flow enhancers and/or impact modifiers for thermoplastic resin compositions.
Thermoplastic resin compositions within the contemplation of the disclosure include
for example, polyphenylene ether resin (PPE) compositions and styrenic polymer
compositions such as HIPS as well as ABS type compositions.</p><p num="0028">The polyphenylene ether polymers (also referred to herein as "PPE") used in
compositions are known polymers comprising a plurality of aryloxy repeating units
preferably with at least 50 repeating units of Formula (I):
<img id="img-00080001" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/>
wherein in each of said units independently, each Q<sup>1</sup> is independently hydrogen,
halogen, alkyl (preferably primary or secondary lower alkyl containing up to 7 carbon 
atoms), aryl (preferably phenyl), halohydrocarbon groups (preferably haloalkyl)
having at least two carbons between the halogen atoms and the phenyl nucleus of
Formula (I), aminoalkyl, hydrocarbonoxy or halohydrocarbonoxy wherein at least two
carbon atoms separate the halogen and oxygen atoms and at least two carbon atoms
separate the halogen atoms and the phenyl nucleus of Formula (I).</p><p num="0029">Each Q<sup>2</sup> is independently hydrogen, halogen, alkyl (preferably primary or secondary
lower alkyl up to 7 carbon atoms), aryl (preferably phenyl), halohydrocarbon
(preferably haloalkyl) having at least two carbon atoms between the halogen atoms
and the phenyl nucleus of Formula (I), hydrocarbonoxy groups or
halohydrocarbonoxy groups wherein at least two carbon atoms separate the halogen
and oxygen atoms and at least two carbon atoms separate the halogen atoms from the
phenyl nucleus of Formula (I). Each Q<sup>1</sup> and Q<sup>2</sup> suitably contain up to about 12
carbon atoms and most often, each Q<sup>1</sup> is an alkyl or phenyl, especially C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> alkyl
and each Q<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen.</p><p num="0030">The term "polyphenylene ether resin," as used in the specification and claims herein,
includes unsubstituted polyphenylene ether polymers, substituted polyphenylene ether
polymers wherein the aromatic ring is substituted, polyphenylene ether copolymers
and blends thereof. Also included are polyphenylene ether polymers containing
moieties prepared by grafting onto the polyphenylene ether in a known manner such
materials as vinyl monomers or polymers such a polystyrenes and elastomers, as
described in U.S. Patent No. 5,089,566 issued to S. Bruce Brown. Coupled
polyphenylene ether polymers in which coupling agents such as low molecular weight
polycarbonates, quinones, heterocycles and formals undergo reaction in the known
manner with the hydroxy groups of two phenyl ether chains to produce a high
molecular weight polymer are also included.</p> <p num="0031">The polyphenylene ether polymers used in the compositions may also have various
end groups such as amino alkyl containing end groups and 4-hydroxy biphenyl end
groups, typically incorporated during synthesis by the oxidative coupling reaction.
The polyphenylene ether polymers may be functionalized or "capped" with end
groups, which add further reactivity to the polymer and in some instances provide 
additional compatibility with other polymer systems that may be used in conjunction
with the polyphenylene ether polymers to produce an alloy or blend. For instance, the
polyphenylene ether polymer may be functionalized with an epoxy end group, a
phosphate end group or ortho ester end group by reacting a functionalizing agent such
as 2-chloro-4(2-diethylphosphato epoxy)6-(2,4,6-trimethyl-phenoxy)-1,3,5-trizene,
with one of the end groups of the polyphenylene ether polymer, i.e., one of the
terminal hydroxyl groups.</p> <p num="0032">It will be apparent to those skilled in the art from the foregoing that the polyphenylene
ether polymers contemplated for use include all of those presently known, irrespective
of the variations in structural units.</p> <p num="0033">Suitable polyphenylene ether polymers useful include but are not limited to poly(2,6-dimethyl-1,4-phenylene
ether); poly(2,3,6-trimethyl-1,4-phenylene) ether; poly(2,6-diethyl-1,4-phenylene)
ether; poly(2-methyl-6-propyl-1,4-phenylene) ether; poly(2,6-dipropyl-1,4-phenylene)
ether; poly(2-ethyl-6-propyl-1,4-phenylene)ether; poly(2,6-dilauryl-1,4-phenylene)
ether; poly(2,6-diphenyl-1,4-phenylene) ether; poly(2,6-dimethoxy-1,4
phenylene) ether; poly(2,6-diethoxy-1,4-phenylene) ether; poly(2-methoxy-6-ethoxy-1,4-phenylene)
ether; poly(2-ethyl-6-stearyloxy-1,4-phenylene)
ether; poly(2,6-dichloro-1,4-phenylene) ether; poly(2-methyl-6-phenyl-1,4-phenylene)
ether; poly(2-ethoxy-1,4-phenylene) ether; poly(2-chloro-1,4-phenylene)
ether; poly(2,6-dibromo-1,4-phenylene) ether; poly(3-bromo-2,6-dimethyl-1,4-phenylene)
ether; mixtures thereof, and the like.</p><p num="0034">Suitable copolymers include random copolymers containing 2,6-dimethyl-1,4-phenylene
ether units and 2,3,6-trimethyl- 1,4-phenylene ether units.</p><p num="0035">The polyphenylene ether resins employed in the compositions of this invention have
an intrinsic viscosity greater than about 0.2 dl/g, as measured in chloroform at 25°C,
and generally have a number average molecular weight within the range of about
3,000 to 40,000 and a weight average molecular weight in the range of 20,000 to
80,000, as determined by gel permeation chromotography. </p><p num="0036">The polyphenylether ether polymers suitable for use in this invention may be prepared
by any of a number of processes known in the art from corresponding phenols or
reactive derivatives thereof. Polyphenylene ether resins are typically prepared by the
oxidative coupling of at least one monohydroxy aromatic compound such as 2,6-xylenol
or 2,3,6-trimethylphenol. Catalysts systems are generally employed for such
coupling and contain at least one heavy metal compound such as copper, manganese,
or cobalt compounds, usually in combination with various other materials. Catalyst
systems containing a copper compound are usually combinations of cuprous or cupric
ions, halide (e.g., chloride, bromide, or iodide) ions and at least one amine such as
cuprous chloride- trimethylamine. Catalyst systems which contain manganese
compounds are generally alkaline systems in which divalent manganese is combined
with such anions as halide, alkoxide or phenoxide. Most often, the manganese is
present as a complex with one or more complexing and/or chelating agents such as
dialkylamines, alkylenediamines, o-hydroxy aromatic aldehydes, o-hydroxyazo
compounds and o-hydroxyaryl oximes. Examples of manganese containing catalysts
include manganese chloride-and manganese chloride-sodium methylate. Suitable
cobalt type catalyst systems contain cobalt salts and an amine.</p><p num="0037">Examples of catalyst systems and methods for preparing polyphenylether resins are
set forth in U.S. Patent Nos. 3,306,874, 3,306,875, 3,914,266 and 4,028,341 (Hay);
U.S. Patent Nos. 3,257,357 and 3,257,358 (Stamatoff); U.S. Patent Nos. 4,935,472
and 4,806,297 (S.B. Brown et al.); and U.S. Patent No. 4,806,602 issued to Dwayne
M. White et al.</p><p num="0038">In general, the molecular weight of the polyphenylene ether resins can be controlled
by controlling the reaction time, the reaction temperature, and the amount of catalyst.
Longer reaction times will provide a higher average number of repeating units and a
higher intrinsic viscosity. At some point, a desired molecular weight (intrinsic
viscosity) is obtained and the reaction terminated by conventional means. For
example, in the case of reaction systems which make use of a complex metal
catalysts, the polymerization reaction may be terminated by adding an acid, e.g.,
hydrochloric acid, sulfuric acid and the like or a base e.g., potassium hydroxide and
the like or the product may be separated from the catalyst by filtration, precipitation 
or other suitable means as taught by Hay in U.S. Patent No. 3,306,875. The PPE
preferably comprises a compatibilized or functionalized PPE, wherein compatibility is
meant to include the minimization of gross phase separation between the components
of the blend (i.e., the PPE and any other ingredients of the blend). Increased tensile
elongation, reduced delamination tendency, increased ductility and improved phase
morphology stabilization are generally indicators of improved compatibilization. The
desirable physical properties of the blend are determined partly by the improvement in
the compatibilization between the blend components.</p><p num="0039">The PPE preferably comprises a compatibilized or functionalized PPE, wherein
compatibility is meant to include the minimization of gross phase separation between
the components of the blend (i.e., the PPE and any other ingredients of the blend).
Increased tensile elongation, reduced delamination tendency, increased ductility and
improved phase morphology stabilization are generally indicators of improved
compatibilization. The desirable physical properties of the blend are determined
partly by the improvement in the compatibilization between the blend components.</p><p num="0040">Styrenic polymer compositions are prepared from one or more monoalkenyl aromatic
compounds. Representative monoalkenyl aromatic compounds include styrene, alkyl
substituted styrenes such as alpha-alkyl-styrenes, and ring substituted styrenes.
Examples of alpha-alkyl-styrenes include alpha-methyl styrene and alpha-ethyl-styrene,
while examples of ring substituted styrenes include o-ethyl-styrene, 2,4-dimethyl-styrene
and vinyltoluene, such as p-vinyltoluene, vinyl anthracene, and
mixtures thereof. The polymer matrix preferably utilizes styrene and/or alpha-methyl
styrene as the monoalkenyl aromatic monomer, with styrene being the most preferred
monoalkenyl aromatic compound. One or more additional co-monomers such as
unsaturated nitriles, for example acrylonitrile, can also be included in the
polymerizable monomer mixture.</p><p num="0041">While the thermoplastic resins described above are of wide utility in several
applications due to their excellent chemical and mechanical properties, it is often
necessary to add flame retardant aids to improve such performance. As explained in
the section on background to the disclosure, it is important to utilize flame retardant 
additives in reduced amounts such that all properties such as flowability, heat
deflection temperature and flame retardance of the thermoplastic resin are preserved
or enhanced.</p><p num="0042">The compositions of the present invention also comprise at least one flame retardant,
generally an organic phosphate. The organic phosphate is preferably an aromatic
phosphate compound of the formula:
<img id="img-00130001" orientation="unknown" wi="71" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="28"/>
wherein R is the same or different and is an alkyl, cycloalkyl, aryl, alkyl substituted
aryl, halogen substituted alkyl, aryl substituted alkyl, halogen, or a combination of
any of the foregoing, provided at least one R is aryl.</p><p num="0043">Examples include phenyl bisdodecyl phosphate, phenylbisneopentyl phosphate,
phenyl-bis (3,5,5'-tri-methyl-hexyl phosphate), ethyldiphenyl phosphate, 2-ethylhexyldi(p-tolyl)
phosphate, bis-(2-ethylhexyl) p- tolylphosphate, tritolyl phosphate,
bis-(2-ethylhexyl) phenyl phosphate, tri- (nonylphenyl) phosphate, di (dodecyl) p-tolyl
phosphate, tricresyl phosphate, triphenyl phosphate, dibutylphenyl phosphate, 2-chloroethyldiphenyl
phosphate, p-tolyl bis(2,5,5'-trimethylhexyl) phosphate, 2-ethylhexyldiphenyl
phosphate, and the like. The preferred phosphates are those in
which each R is aryl. Especially preferred is triphenyl phosphate, which may be
either unsubstituted or substituted, for example, isopropylated triphenyl phosphate.</p><p num="0044">Alternatively, the organic phosphate can be a di- or polyfunctional compound or
polymer having one or a mixture of the following formulas: <img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="99" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="51"/>
or
<img id="img-00140002" orientation="unknown" wi="117" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140002.tif" inline="no" he="49"/>
or
<img id="img-00140003" orientation="unknown" wi="133" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140003.tif" inline="no" he="56"/>
wherein R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup>, R<sup>3</sup>, R<sup>4</sup>, R<sup>5</sup>, R<sup>6</sup>, and R<sup>7</sup> are independently, a hydrocarbon of C1 to C20,
aryl, or alkyl- substituted aryl; X<sup>1</sup> , X<sup>2</sup>, and X<sup>3</sup> are halogen; m and r are 0 or integers
from 1 to 4, and n and p are from 1 to 30. When m and/or r are 0, the aromatic rings
preferably contain hydrogen without halogen substitution.</p><p num="0045">Examples include the (tetraphenyl)bisphosphates of resorcinol, hydroquinone and
bisphenol-A, respectively, or their polymeric counterparts. Methods for the
preparation of the aforementioned di- and polyfunctional aromatic phosphates are
described in British Patent No. 2, 043,083. </p><p num="0046">Another development is the use of certain cyclic phosphates, for example, diphenyl
pentaerythritol diphosphate, as a flame retardant agent for polyphenylene ether resins,
as is described by Axelrod in U.S. Pat. No. 4,254,775.</p><p num="0047">Other suitable flame-retardant additives include compounds containing
phosphorus - nitrogen bonds, such as phosphonitrilic chloride, phosphorus ester amides, phosphoric
acid amides, phosphonic acid amides, phosphinic acid amides, tris(aziridinyl)
phosphine oxide, or tetrakis(hydroxymethyl) phosphonium chloride. These flame-retardant
additives are commercially available.</p><p num="0048">Preferred phosphate flame retardants include those based upon resorcinol such as, for
example, resorcinol bis(dipheny phosphate), as well as those based upon bis-phenols
such as, for example, bis-phenol A tetraphenyl diphosphate. Phosphates containing
substituted phenyl groups are also preferred. In an especially preferred embodiment,
the organophosphate is selected from the group consisting of resorcinol bis( diphenyl
phosphate), bis-phenol A bis(diphenyl phosphate), and mixtures containing at least
one of the foregoing.</p><p num="0049">In combination with the phosphate compound, the compositions preferably include
ferrocene or ferrocene derivatives. Suitable ferrocene derivatives are the di-π
cyclopentadieneyl iron complexes represented by the following formula.
<img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="46" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="67"/></p><p num="0050">Various substituents may be pendant on the cyclopentadienyl ring. Representatives of
these compounds are di-π-cyclopentadienyl iron (ferrocene), bis-indenyl-iron (II)
(dibenzferrocene), 1,1'- diacetylferrocene, 1,2 diacetylferrocene, 1,1-diferroceneylethane,
dimethylaminoethylferrocene, methylamino methyl-ferrocene,
ferrocenylacetonitrile, ferrocenylcarbonal, ferrocene-sulfonic acid, 1,2 di-ferrocenylethane,
di-ferrocenylmethane, phenylferrocene, ferrocenecarboxaldhyde,
the Ω-ferrocenyl aliphatic acids, phenylcyclopentaferrocene, 1,1' (-1,3-cyclopenylene)
ferrocene phenylcyclopentylferrocene and like compounds, benzoylferrocene,
acetylferrocene. Also heterocyclic π complexes such as azaferrocene may be utilized.
While not wanting to be bound by theory, a feature of the ferrocenes that is believed
to enhance the flame retardant characteristics of polymer compositions is the presence
of the following structure within the molecule.
<img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="30" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="59"/></p><p num="0051">Since ferrocene is aromatic, it can undergo aromatic substitution reactions such as
Friedel-Crafts acylation, alkylation, sulfonation, and aminomethylation, providing a
wide range of ferrocene compounds and derivatives. Preferably, the ferrocene
derivatives do not degrade the polymer resins in which they are incorporated. Other
suitable organo iron compounds include iron(II) acetylacetonate, iron imidazolyl and
benzimidazolyl.</p><p num="0052">The present disclosure is based on the surprising recognition that the use of select
amounts of both melamine polyphosphate and ferrocene, in combination, not only
enables a reduction in the amount of RDP, but also improves the flame retardance and
significantly improves the flex, tensile properties, and heat deflection temperature of
the thermoplastic resin composition. </p><p num="0053">The additive composition preferably comprises for every 100 parts by weight of
thermoplastic composition about 0.5 to about 5.0 parts of melamine polyphosphate
and about 0.2 to about 5.0 parts of ferrocene or an organo iron compound. More
preferably, the additive composition comprises for every 12 parts of resorcinol
diphenyl phosphate in the thermoplastic composition about 0.5 to about 5.0 parts of
melamine polyphosphate and about 0.2 to about 5.0 parts of ferrocene or an organo
iron compound. More preferably, the additive composition comprises for every 12
parts of resorcinol diphenyl phosphate, 0.5 parts of melamine polyphosphate and 0.2
parts of ferrocene or an organo iron compound, more preferably 0.5 parts of ferrocene
or an organo iron compound to every 0.5 parts of melamine polyphosphate. The
additive composition can also comprise for every 12 parts of RDP, 1.0 parts of MPP
and 0.2 parts of ferrocene or an organo iron compound, more preferably 0.5 parts of
ferrocene or an organo iron compound to every 1.0 parts of MPP.</p><p num="0054">Without wishing to be bound by any theory, it is believed that the ferrocene and MPP
work both by condensed phase and vapor phase mechanisms. Ferrocene is known to
catalyze C - C coupling reactions and thus help in cross linking and reduction of fuel
generation. Prior art literature teaches that metallocenes are effective catalysts in
olefin polymerisation. Therefore, it is also believed that ferrocene could be reducing
fuel generation by catalyzing repolymerisation of olefinic residues released from
styrenic polymers such as HIPS.</p><p num="0055">The thermoplastic resin composition may also comprise effective amounts of at least
one other additive selected from the group consisting of drip retardants, dyes,
pigments, additional flow enhancers, impact modifiers, colorants, reinforcing agents,
fillers, glass fibers, stabilizers, antistatic agents, plasticizers and lubricants.</p><p num="0056">The thermoplastic resin composition of the disclosure is generally prepared by
blending the ingredients under conditions appropriate to obtain an intimate blend.
The blending can be done using a single or a twin screw type extruder or any mixing
device capable of applying a shear to the components. All ingredients may be added
initially to the processing system. </p><p num="0057">The thermoplastic compositions of the disclosure may also be prepared using separate
extruders in the processing or using a single extruder with multiple feed ports
enabling the addition of multiple components during processing. It is preferable to
employ at least one vent port in each section between the feed ports to allow venting
(either atmospheric or vacuum) of the melt. Volatile impurities in the blend
composition for example, can be removed by applying a vacuum to the melt through a
vent port provided in the mixing device. Blending times and temperatures, as well as
component addition can be adjusted by those skilled in the art without undue
experimentation. Molded articles prepared from the compositions of the present
disclosure also represent another embodiment of the disclosure.</p><p num="0058">The following examples are provided to illustrate some embodiments of the present
disclosure. They are not intended to limit the disclosure in any aspect. All
percentages are by weight based on the total weight of the entire composition, unless
otherwise indicated and all parts are parts by weight.</p><heading>Example 1.</heading><p num="0059">A first control resin formulation was prepared by intimately blending polyphenylene
ether resin with resorcinol diphenylphosphate (RDP) as additive in an amount of 16
parts of RDP for every 100 parts by weight of the polyphenylene ether resin. The
polyphenylene ether resin was Noryl 190 X available from the General Electric
Company.</p><p num="0060">A portion of the first control resin formulation was taken and extruded in a GEP
Selkirk 53mm Twin Screw, W&amp;P extruder at a feed rate of 300 pounds per hour, at a
screw speed of 270 rpm, and at 72 % torque. The extrudate was the tested for flame
retardance, Izod impact, flow, flex and heat deflection temperature. The values
obtained are given in Table 1 below. Details of the test procedures follows Table 1. </p><heading>Example 2.</heading><p num="0061">A second control resin formulation was prepared by intimately blending the Noryl
190 X polyphenylene ether resin with RDP as an additive in an amount of 12 parts of
RDP for every 100 parts by weight of polyphenylene ether resin.</p><p num="0062">A portion of the second control resin formulation was taken and extruded in a GEP
Selkirk 53mm Twin Screw, W&amp;P extruder at a feed rate of 300 pounds per hour, at a
screw speed of 270 rpm and 72 % torque. The extrudate was the tested for flame
retardance, Izod impact, flow, flex and heat deflection temperature. The values
obtained are given in Table 1 below.</p><heading>Example 3.</heading><p num="0063">An additive composition was prepared by intimately blending melamine
polyphosphate (MPP) and ferrocene into a portion of the first control resin
formulation (prepared in Example 1) such that the amount of MPP is 0.5 parts by
weight and ferrocene is 0.2 parts by weight for every 100 parts by weight of the
polyphenylene ether resin. Thus, for every 16 parts of RDP in the formulation, the
amount of MPP is 0.5 parts by weight and ferrocene is 0.2 parts by weight.</p><p num="0064">The formulation so obtained was extruded under the same conditions as in Example 1.
The extrudate was the tested for flame retardance, Izod impact, flow, flex and heat
deflection temperature. The values obtained are given in Table 1 below.</p><heading>Example 4.</heading><p num="0065">An additive composition was prepared by intimately blending MPP and ferrocene into
a portion of the second control resin formulation (prepared in Example 2) such that
the amount of MPP is 0.5 parts by weight and ferrocene is 0.5 parts by weight for
every 100 parts of the polyphenylene ether resin. Thus, for every 12 parts of RDP in
the formulation, the amount of MPP is 0.5 parts by weight and ferrocene is 0.5 parts
by weight. </p><p num="0066">The resin formulation so obtained was extruded under the same conditions as in
Example 1. The extrudate was the tested for flame retardance, Izod impact, flow, flex
and heat deflection temperature. The values obtained are given in Table 1 below.</p><heading>Example 5.</heading><p num="0067">An additive composition was prepared by intimately blending melamine
polyphosphate (MPP) and ferrocene into a portion of the second control resin
formulation (prepared in Example 2) such that the amount of MPP is 1.0 parts by
weight and ferrocene is 0.2 parts by weight for every 100 parts of the polyphenylene
ether resin. Thus, for every 12 parts of RDP in the formulation, the amount of MPP is
1.0 parts by weight and ferrocene is 0.2 parts by weight.</p><p num="0068">The resin formulation so obtained was extruded under the same conditions as in
Example 1. The extrudate was the tested for flame retardance, Izod impact, flow, flex
and heat deflection temperature. The values obtained are given in Table 1 below.</p><heading>Example 6.</heading><p num="0069">An additive composition was prepared by intimately blending MPP and ferrocene into
a portion of the second control resin formulation (as prepared in Example 2) such that
the amount of MPP is 1.0 parts by weight and ferrocene is 0.5 parts by weight for
every 100 parts of the polyphenylene ether resin. Thus, for every 12 parts of RDP in
the thermoplastic resin formulation, the amount of MPP is 1.0 parts by weight and
ferrocene is 0.5 parts by weight.</p><p num="0070">The resin formulation so obtained was extruded under the same conditions as in
Example 1. The extrudate was the tested for flame retardance, Izod impact, flow, flex
and heat deflection temperature. The values obtained are given in Table 1 below. <tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Example</entry><entry align="center">Average Flame out time (seconds)</entry><entry align="center">Izod impact (ftlb/in)</entry><entry align="center">Flex Modulus (psi)</entry><entry align="center">Flex Strength (psi)</entry><entry align="center">Flow at 1,500/s

(Pa-s)</entry><entry align="center">Heat deflection temperature (°F)</entry><entry align="center">Tensile % elongation</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">2.99</entry><entry align="center">4.67</entry><entry align="center">344,500</entry><entry align="center">12,810</entry><entry align="center">181.2</entry><entry align="center">188.5</entry><entry align="center">19.06</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">4.21</entry><entry align="center">4.84</entry><entry align="center">357,800</entry><entry align="center">13,410</entry><entry align="center">223.6</entry><entry align="center">205.7</entry><entry align="center">18.41</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry><entry align="center">3.38</entry><entry align="center">361,600</entry><entry align="center">13,400</entry><entry align="center">226.0</entry><entry align="center">204.9</entry><entry align="center">23.94</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">1.92</entry><entry align="center">2.65</entry><entry align="center">361,200</entry><entry align="center">13,430</entry><entry align="center">226.5</entry><entry align="center">202.2</entry><entry align="center">23.61</entry></row><row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">2.09</entry><entry align="center">2.09</entry><entry align="center">361,100</entry><entry align="center">13,430</entry><entry align="center">230.6</entry><entry align="center">205.7</entry><entry align="center">22.81</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">1.68</entry><entry align="center">2.00</entry><entry align="center">362,200</entry><entry align="center">13,500</entry><entry align="center">230.3</entry><entry align="center">206.8</entry><entry align="center">23.51<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0071">As shown in Table 1, a comparison of control examples 1 and 2 (containing no MPP
and ferrocene) with examples 3-6 (containing MPP and ferrocene) indicates that
flame retardancy is improved while maintaining other properties for the compositions,
i.e., Izod impact strength, flexural modulus, flex strength, flowability, heat deflection
and tensile % elongation.</p><heading>Example 7.</heading><p num="0072">In this example, the formulations obtained in Examples 3 and 5 were subjected to iron
analysis by inductively coupled plasma (ICP). Against an expected iron purity of
0.060% (based on 98% purity), the iron obtained by ICP analysis is expected to be
~0.057%. Thus, the iron loss during extrusion is only ∼ 5%. The actual values of iron
obtained from the samples ranged from 0.054 to 0.0599%. The ICP analysis error is
±5%.</p><p num="0073">Tests for flame retardancy were performed according to UL-94 protocol for a VO
rating using test bars of the thermoplastic resin formulations. </p><p num="0074">The compositions made in the above examples were tested for flammability using a
flame retardant testing tool, which provides a prediction of the likelihood that a
particular UL standard, such as UL-94 will be passed. The UL-94 protocol calls for
bar-shaped specimens of dimensions 5"(12.7 cm) x ½" (1.3 cm), 1.6 mm thickness,
UL-94 ratings being specified for the thickness. A flame having an inner cone of
height ¾" (1.9 cm) is applied to each specimen so that a distance of 3/8" (1.0 cm)
separates the lower end of the specimen from base of the flame. The flame is held in
that position for 10 seconds and then removed. A burn time is defined as the time
required for the flame issuing from the specimen to disappear. If burning of the
specimen ceases within 30 seconds, the flame is reapplied for an additional 10
seconds. The criteria for V-0, V-1, and V-2 ratings are listed below in Table 2.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Vertical Flame Class Requirements</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">94V-0</entry><entry align="left">94V-1</entry><entry align="left">94V-2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Individual bum time (seconds)</entry><entry align="left">≤10</entry><entry align="left">≤30</entry><entry align="left">≤30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total burn time (seconds)</entry><entry align="left">≤50</entry><entry align="left">≤250</entry><entry align="left">≤250</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(5 specimens)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glowing time (seconds)</entry><entry align="left">≤30</entry><entry align="left">≤60</entry><entry align="left">≤60</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(individual specimen)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Drip particles that ignite cotton</entry><entry align="left">NO</entry><entry align="left">NO</entry><entry align="left">YES</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0075">For a V-0 rating, no individual burn times, from the first or second application may
exceed 10 seconds. The total of the burn times for any five specimens may not
exceed 50 seconds. Drip particles that ignite a piece of cotton gauze situated below
the specimen are not allowed. </p><p num="0076">For a V-1 rating, no individual burn times, from the first or second application may
exceed 30 seconds. The total of the burn times for any five specimens may not
exceed 250 seconds. Drip particles that ignite a piece of cotton gauze situated below
the specimen are not allowed.</p><p num="0077">For a V-2 rating, no individual burn times, from the first or second application may
exceed 30 seconds. The total of the burn times for any five specimens may not
exceed 250 seconds. Drip particles that ignite a piece of cotton gauze situated below
the specimen are allowed.</p><p num="0078">Heat deflection temperatures were determined by a test procedure based on ASTM D-648.</p><p num="0079">Notched Izod tests were performed by a test procedure based on ASTM D-256. The
results of the test are reported in terms of energy absorbed per unit of specimen width
and expressed as foot times pounds per inch (ft.lbs/in.).</p><p num="0080">Shear viscosity (i.e., flow) was measured at each shear rate using a Kayeness capillary
rheometer.</p><p num="0081">Advantageously, adding both MPP and ferrocene (or an organo ion compound) to a
thermoplastic formulation containing RDP as a flame retardant provides increased
flame retardancy to the thermoplastic resin formulation compared to formulations that
did not contain the additive combination of MPP and ferrocene. Surprisingly, the use
of effective amounts of ferrocene(or an organo ion compound) and MPP used in the
combination does not impair the Izod impact of the formulation. Moreover, the flex
and flow rate of the resin formulation is also not impaired. It is also noted that the heat
deflection temperature profile of the resin formulation is not impaired by the use of
MPP and ferrocene (or an organo ion compound) as co-additives with RDP.</p><p num="0082">While the disclosure has been described with reference to an exemplary embodiment,
it will be understood by those skilled in the art that various changes may be made and
equivalents may be substituted for elements thereof without departing from the scope
of the disclosure. In addition, many modifications may be made to adapt a particular 
situation or material to the teachings of the disclosure without departing from the
essential scope thereof. Therefore, it is intended that the disclosure not be limited to
the particular embodiment disclosed as the best mode contemplated for carrying out
this disclosure, but that the disclosure will include all embodiments falling within the
scope of the appended claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An additive blend for a flame retardant thermoplastic resin comprising an
organo phosphate compound other than melamine polyphosphate, the additive blend
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>melamine polyphosphate; and</claim-text><claim-text>ferrocene or an organo iron compound.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The additive blend of Claim 1, wherein the melamine polyphosphate is in an
amount of about 0.5 to about 5.0 parts by weight and the ferrocene or the organo iron
compound is in an amount of about 0.2 to about 5.0 parts by weight for every 100
parts by weight of resin composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A thermoplastic resin composition with improved flame retardance, tensile
properties, flex, and heat deflection temperature, the composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a thermoplastic resin;</claim-text><claim-text>an organo phosphate compound other than melamine polyphosphate;</claim-text><claim-text>melamine polyphosphate; and</claim-text><claim-text>ferrocene or an organo iron compound.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The thermoplastic resin composition of Claim 3, wherein the composition
comprises less than or equal to about 20 parts by weight of the organic phosphate
compound for every 100 parts by weight of the thermoplastic resin, wherein the
melamine polyphosphate is in an amount of about 0.5 to about 5.0 parts by weight and
the ferrocene or the organo iron compound is in an amount of about 0.2 to about 5.0
parts by weight based on the amount of the organo phosphate compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The thermoplastic resin composition of any preceding Claim, wherein the
organo iron compound is selected from the group consisting of iron acetylacetonate,
iron imidazolyl , iron benzimidazolyl, di-π-cyclopentadienyl iron (ferrocene), bis-indenyl-iron
(II) (dibenzferrocene), 1,1'- diacetylferrocene, 1,2 diacetylferrocene, 1,1-diferroceneylethane,
dimethylaminoethylferrocene, methylamino methyl-ferrocene,
ferrocenylacetonitrile, ferrocenylcarbonal, ferrocene-sulfonic acid, 1,2 di-ferrocenylethane,
di-ferrocenylmethane, phenylferrocene, ferrocenecarboxaldhyde,
the Ω-ferrocenyl aliphatic acids, phenylcyclopentaferrocene, 1,1' (-1,3-cyclopenylene)
ferrocene phenylcyclopentylferrocene, benzoylferrocene, acetylferrocene and
azaferrocene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The thermoplastic resin composition of Claim 3, wherein the organo
phosphate of formula:

wherein R is the same or different and is an alkyl, cycloalkyl, aryl, alkyl substituted
aryl, halogen substituted alkyl, aryl substituted alkyl, halogen, or a combination of
any of the foregoing, provided at least one R is aryl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The thermoplastic resin composition of Claim 3, wherein the organo
phosphate compound is selected from the group consisting of RDP and BPA-DP.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The thermoplastic resin composition of Claim 3, wherein the thermoplastic
resin comprises a polyphenylene ether resin, an acrylonitrile/butadienestyrene rubber,
or a styrenic polymer composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The thermoplastic resin composition of Claim 8, wherein the styrenic polymer
composition is a high impact polystyrene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The thermoplastic resin composition of Claim 8, wherein the styrenic polymer
composition comprises a homopolymer or copolymer of a monoalkenyl aromatic
compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The thermoplastic resin composition of Claim 10, wherein the monoalkenyl
aromatic compound is selected from the group consisting of styrene, alkyl substituted
styrenes, ring substituted styrenes, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The thermoplastic resin composition of Claim 11, wherein the alkyl
substituted styrene comprises an alpha-alkyl-styrene selected from alpha-methyl
styrene, alpha-ethyl-styrene and a mixture thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The thermoplastic resin composition of Claim 11 wherein the ring substituted
styrene is selected from the group consisting of o-ethyl-styrene, 2,4-dimethyl-styrene,
p-vinyltoluene, vinyl anthracene, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A method for the manufacture of a thermoplastic resin composition extrudate
with improved flame retardance, flowability and heat deflection temperature
performance, said method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>mixing a thermoplastic resin, an organo phosphate compound other than melamine
polyphosphate, melamine polyphosphate, and ferrocene or an organo iron compound
to produce a mixture; and</claim-text><claim-text>extruding the mixture.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>