<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-0990688-A1" country="EP" doc-number="0990688" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22593909" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000405"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-0990688-A1" status="new" fvid="22798077"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0990688</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000405</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99119258-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99119258</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990928</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-16430898-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>16430898</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981001</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09J 123/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09J 123/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09J 131/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09J 131/04        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09J 123/08+C</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Wassergetragene druckempfindliche Ethylene/&amp;Vinylacetat Klebstoffe</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Water borne pressure sensitive vinyl acetate/ethylene adhesive compositions</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Compositions aqueuses d'adhésifs sensibles à la pression dérivées de copolymères d'éthylène et acétate vinyliques</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-3827056-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>3827056</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0185356-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0185356</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0890625-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0890625</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="T" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3692723-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3692723</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4287329-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4287329</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>AIR PRODUCTS POLYMERS LP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AIR PRODUCTS POLYMERS, L.P.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>AIR PRODUCTS POLYMERS, L.P.</last-name><address><street>7201 Hamilton Boulevard</street><city>Allentown, PA 18195-1501</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BOTT RICHARD HENRY</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DANIELS CHRISTIAN LEONARD</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MAO CHUNG-LING</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VRATSANOS MENAS SPYROS</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BOTT, RICHARD HENRY</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DANIELS, CHRISTIAN LEONARD</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MAO, CHUNG-LING</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VRATSANOS, MENAS SPYROS</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BOTT, RICHARD HENRY</last-name><address><street>1610 Cherry Lane</street><city>Macungie, PA 18062</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DANIELS, CHRISTIAN LEONARD</last-name><address><street>7438 Catalpa Drive</street><city>Macungie, PA 18062</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MAO, CHUNG-LING</last-name><address><street>4696 Sweetbriar Circle</street><city>Emmaus, PA 18049</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VRATSANOS, MENAS SPYROS</last-name><address><street>1809 Jennifer Drive</street><city>Breinigsville, PA 18031</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kador, Ulrich, Dr.</last-name><address><street>Kador &amp;amp; Partner Corneliusstrasse 15</street><city>80469 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention is directed to improved vinyl acetate ethylene pressure
sensitive adhesive emulsion polymers. The improvement in the aqueous based,
emulsion polymerized pressure sensitive adhesives resides in:
<sl><li>a high ethylene content copolymer having a Tg of from -25 to -70°C;</li><li>a tensile storage modulus measured at one hertz and at a temperature of -20°C
embraced by the points on a plot of storage modulus and temperature of from 1 times
10<sup>6</sup> and the points 4 times 10<sup>9</sup> dynes/cm<sup>2</sup> and less that 1 times 10<sup>7</sup> dynes/cm<sup>2</sup> measured
at 50°C.</li></sl><img id="img-00000001"  orientation="unknown"  wi="93"  img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="76"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading><p num="0001">Not applicable.</p><heading>STATEMENT REGARDING FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH OR
DEVELOPMENT</heading><p num="0002">Not applicable.</p><heading>TECHNICAL FIELD</heading><p num="0003">This invention relates to improved aqueous based pressure vinyl
acetate/ethylene pressure sensitive adhesive emulsions.</p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0004">Pressure sensitive adhesives are widely used for fabricating paper labels,
laminating polymeric films such as laminating poly(vinyl chloride), polyester, etc., for
forming decals, repositionable notes and other related products. Most of the pressure
sensitive adhesives have been solvent based but in recent years government
regulations have forced the industry to develop environmentally friendly aqueous based
pressure sensitive adhesives.</p><p num="0005">Aqueous based pressure sensitive adhesives comprised of polymerized
monomer units of vinyl acetate and ethylene (VAE), and/or acrylic esters, etc. have been
inferior to the solvent based pressure sensitive adhesives in that they do not have 
sufficient dry tack or cohesive strength and the lack of desirable properties limits the use
of these polymers as pressure sensitive adhesives.</p><p num="0006">There is a wide variety of applications for pressures sensitive adhesives and by
pressure sensitive it is meant that that the polymer exhibits dry tack and will
instantaneously adhere to a substrate with finger tip pressure at temperatures ranging
from -20 to 25°C. Most applications for permanent type pressure sensitive adhesives
require excellent peel, tack and shear. Repositionable adhesives may require less tack
but sufficient tack and cohesive strength to adhere to a substrate and yet be able to be
removed without a portion of the adhesive adhering to the substrate. These pressure
sensitive adhesives should also be resistant to oozing from the substrate when applied
thereto and placed under pressure as in roll stock. Aqueous emulsion pressure
sensitive adhesives must also be able to be coated on the various adhesive substrates
such as Mylar, polyvinyl chloride and silicon containing coated polymers.</p><p num="0007">The following patents describe a variety of emulsion polymers incorporating vinyl
esters and their use as adhesives:</p><p num="0008">U.S. 5,276,084 discloses aqueous based pressure sensitive adhesives based on
polymers comprising vinyl acetate, ethylene, alkyl acrylates dialkyl maleate and
fumarates, hydroxyalkyl acrylates, acrylamide and unsaturated carboxylic acids such as
acrylic acid. The polymers are low in ethylene content, e.g., 5 to 30% by weight of the
polymer.</p><p num="0009">U.S. 4,694,056 discloses vinyl acetate based pressures sensitive adhesives
which comprise vinyl acetate, dioctyl maleate and acrylic acid polymerized in the
presence of polyvinyl alcohol, and ethoxylated acetylenic glycol. </p><p num="0010">U.S. 5,665,816 discloses aqueous dispersions of polymerized units of vinyl
acetate, ethylene and vinyl or acrylic ester or acrylic esters which carry epoxide groups.
A cellulose ether such as hydroxyethyl cellulose is also included in partly grafted form.
The resulting polymers have a glass transition temperature of from 0 to -40°C and are
used as adhesives.</p><p num="0011">U.S. 3,562,229 discloses solvent polymerized copolymers of ethylene and vinyl
esters where the vinyl esters are derived from long chain carboxylic acids, e.g., versatic
acid which are mixtures of C<sub>9-11</sub> carboxylic acids, Isotridecanoic and isononanoic are
representative acids. The solvent based polymers incorporating vinyl esters of versatic
acid were alleged to be superior to polymers incorporating vinyl laurate which has the
same number of carbon atoms.</p><p num="0012">U.S. 4,322,516 discloses pressure sensitive adhesive emulsions whose
copolymers comprise:
<sl><li>(a) 10-30 wt% ethylene,</li><li>(b) 29-69 wt% acrylic acid esters of alcohols,</li><li>(c) 20-55 wt% vinyl acetate,</li><li>(d) 0.2-8 wt% (meth)acrylamide, and</li><li>(e) 0-12 wt% other olefinically unsaturated comonomers.</li></sl></p><p num="0013">Tackifying agents are incorporated into the ethylene based pressure sensitive
adhesives to enhance effectiveness.</p><p num="0014">U.S. 4,128,518 discloses a pressure-sensitive adhesive comprised of an
aqueous emulsion of vinyl acetate/ethylene copolymer having an ethylene content of
from 15 to 40% and a benzene-insoluble part of less than 30% by weight. The intrinsic
viscosity of the benzene soluble portion is from 0.4 to 1.4 dl per gram. The polymer is
prepared in the presence of a protective colloid and a polyoxyethylenic nonionic
surfactant. In the polymerization process, the vinyl acetate monomer is added 
continuously during the emulsion polymerization process. Polymers having an ethylene
content in excess of 40% were unsuited due to low tack presumably caused by high
ethylene crystallinity.</p><p num="0015">U.S. 5,622,783 discloses vinyl acetate/ethylene/vinyl chloride adhesive wherein
the polymer contains at least 40% by weight of vinyl acetate. The pressure sensitive
adhesive when applied from an organic solvent is particularly adapted for adhering
substrates to plasticized polyvinyl chloride.</p><heading>BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0016">The present invention is directed to improved aqueous based pressure sensitive
adhesive emulsion polymers based upon copolymers of vinyl acetate and ethylene. The
improvement in the aqueous based, emulsion polymerized vinyl acetate/ethylene
pressure sensitive adhesives resides in:
<sl><li>a high ethylene content copolymer (&gt;45%) having a Tg of from -20 to -70°C and
preferably from -25 to -45°C; and,</li><li>a tensile storage modulus measured at one hertz and embraced by the points on
a plot of storage modulus and temperature of from 1 times 10<sup>6</sup> and 4 times 10<sup>9</sup>
dynes/cm<sup>2</sup> at a temperature of -20°C and less than 1 times 10<sup>7</sup> dynes/cm<sup>2</sup> but greater
than 1 times 10<sup>3</sup> at 50°C.</li></sl></p><p num="0017">There are significant advantages associated with the above aqueous based
pressure sensitive adhesive emulsions and the process for producing these emulsions
and these advantages include:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>an ability to be coated on a variety of adhesive substrates; </li><li>an ability to adhere to hard to adhere surfaces such as Mylar polyester, corona
treated polyethylene and polypropylene;</li><li>an ability to generate a class of water borne vinyl acetate/ethylene
pressure sensitive adhesives which have an excellent balance of peel
and cohesive strength while retaining dry tack; and,</li><li>an ability to effect bonding vinyl and other substrates which contain
plasticizers.</li></ul></p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0018">The drawing is a plot of storage modulus verses temperature for a series of vinyl
acetate/ethylene copolymers and a commercial acrylic pressure sensitive adhesive.</p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0019">Emulsion polymerization of ethylenically unsaturated monomers such as lower
vinyl esters, typically represented by vinyl acetate or vinyl propionate, to produce
aqueous based adhesive emulsions is well known. The improvement resides in
pressure sensitive adhesive compositions of vinyl acetate and ethylene which are high in
ethylene content. Traditionally, vinyl acetate/ethylene based pressures sensitive
adhesives had been prepared at low ethylene content, i.e., below about 40% by weight
and generally below 35%, and incorporated substantial levels of soft monomers such as
dioctyl maleate or higher alkyl esters of (meth)acrylic acid.</p><p num="0020">The aqueous based pressure sensitive adhesive emulsions are based on
emulsions which comprise a colloidal dispersion of copolymerized units of vinyl acetate
and ethylene in water. The copolymers present in the pressure sensitive adhesives are 
typically derived from the following monomers and within the percentage proportions
listed below:
<sl><li>(a) 25-65 wt% vinyl acetate, preferably 40-50 wt%;</li><li>(b) from 45 to 65 wt% of ethylene; preferably from about 45-55 wt%;</li><li>(c) 0.2-10 wt% alpha, beta-ethylenically unsaturated monocarboxylic
acid, preferably 0.5 to 2%;</li><li>(d) 0-10 % wt% of a vinyl ester of saturated aliphatic acids, preferably
a vinyl ester of a C<sub>8-13</sub><i>neo</i>-acid;</li><li>(e) 0-10 wt% di-(C<sub>1-13</sub>) alkyl maleate/fumarate, preferably 0 to 10 wt%;</li><li>(f) 0-10 wt% (C<sub>1-8</sub>) alkyl esters of acrylic and methacrylic acid; and,</li><li>(g) 0-5 wt% of a (C<sub>1-13</sub>) hydroxyalkyl (meth)acrylate.</li></sl></p><p num="0021">As noted, a variety of comonomers, e.g., other ethylenically unsaturated
monomers sometimes employed in the formation of the aqueous based vinyl
acetate/ethylene pressure sensitive adhesive emulsions can be copolymerized with
these monomers to form high ethylene content vinyl acetate/ethylene pressure sensitive
adhesives. For example, C<sub>1-13</sub> alkyl (meth)acrylate monomers, preferably C<sub>1-8</sub> alkyl
(meth)acrylates which include methyl methacrylate, ethyl acrylate, butyl acrylate, hexyl
acrylate, 2-ethylhexyl acrylate, isooctyl acrylate, isodecyl acrylate and the like, diesters
of maleic acid or fumaric acid, the diester being formed by the reaction of the acid with a
C<sub>1-13</sub> alkanol, such as, <i>n</i>-octyl alcohol, isooctyl alcohol, butyl alcohol, isobutyl alcohol,
methyl alcohol, amyl alcohol, C<sub>1-8</sub> alkyl vinyl ethers and alpha, beta-ethylenically
unsaturated C<sub>3-6</sub> carboxylic acids can be incorporated into the polymer. Unsaturated
acids which include methacrylic acid, crotonic acid and acrylic acid and alkyl vinyl ethers
such as methyl vinyl ether, ethyl vinyl ether, isopropyl vinyl ether, <i>n</i>-propyl vinyl ether,
<i>tert</i>-butyl vinyl ether and <i>n</i>- and isobutyl vinyl ether can also be employed. Also included 
for use with the above monomers are vinyl esters of C<sub>8-13</sub><i>neo</i>-acids which are comprised
of a single vinyl ester or mixture of tri- and tetramers which have been converted to the
corresponding single or mixture of C<sub>8-13</sub><i>neo</i>-acids.</p><p num="0022">The sum of the monomers used to form the pressure sensitive vinyl
acetate/ethylene copolymers is 100 percent. Generally, not more than about 20% and
preferably not more than 10% by weight of a fourth or more monomer is incorporated
into the polymer. As stated, the emulsion copolymers are designed to have a T<sub>g</sub> of less
than -20°C, preferably -25 to -45°C. A preferred copolymer thus consists essentially of
polymerized units of vinyl acetate, ethylene and an unsaturated carboxylic acid with an
ethylene content from 45 to 55% by weight and an acid content of from 0.5 to 2% by
weight. Preferably, the unsaturated carboxylic acid is acrylic acid.</p><p num="0023">The method of producing the latex polymers of this invention is believed to be an
important factor in producing the pressure sensitive vinyl acetate/ethylene adhesives
high in ethylene content with tensile mechanical properties that provide excellent peel
strength while retaining sufficient cohesive strength to make it useful. Process steps
that are considered to be particularly important are: controlling the amount of vinyl
acetate in the reaction medium at the beginning and during the polymerization process,
adding initiator at the high end of the amounts typically used in emulsion polymerization
reactions and controlling polymerization temperature. It is believed that these process
steps serve to control the polymer molecular weight and ultimately the viscoelastic
properties as shown by tensile dynamic mechanical data in the storage
modulus/temperature plots.</p><p num="0024">One factor relevant to providing a vinyl acetate/ethylene polymer having a high
ethylene content and yet impart dry tack to the polymer is the delay addition of the vinyl 
acetate and monomers. More specifically, the reaction vessel is charged initially with
less than 15%, preferably less than 10%, vinyl acetate by weight, and the remaining
vinyl acetate is delay fed (i.e. added during polymerization) so that the unreacted vinyl
acetate concentration is maintained below about 7%, preferably below 5%, based on
total monomers, during the polymerization process. Vinyl acetate monomer is added at
a rate that limits the polymerization time to no longer than about 10 hours, preferably
less than 6 hours. Short reaction times, i.e., less than 6 hours, are preferred in order to
maximize throughput during production and to improve product performance.</p><p num="0025">The quantity of ethylene entering into the copolymer is influenced by unreacted
vinyl acetate, pressure, agitation and viscosity of the polymerization medium. Thus, to
increase the ethylene content of the copolymer, high pressures, greater agitation and a
low viscosity can be employed. Ethylene pressure in the reactor ranges from about 500
psig to 2000 psig (34 to 136 atm), preferably about 900 to 1400 psig to produce the
desired Tg.</p><p num="0026">Polymerization can be initiated by thermal initiators or by a redox system. A
thermal initiator should be used at temperatures at or above about 70°C and redox
systems are preferred when a polymerization temperature below about 70°C is used.
The viscoelastic properties are influenced by small changes in temperature and by
initiator composition and concentration. The amount of thermal initiator used in the
process is 0.1 to 3 wt%, preferably from 0.5 to 1.5wt%, based on total monomers.
Thermal initiators are well known in the emulsion polymer art and include, for example,
ammonium persulfate, sodium persulfate, and the like. The amount of oxidizing and
reducing agent in the redox system is about 0.1 to 3 wt%. Any suitable redox system
known in the art can be used; for example, the reducing agent can be a bisulfite, a 
sulfoxylate, ascorbic acid, erythorbic acid, and the like. The oxidizing agent can include
hydrogen peroxide, organic peroxide such as <i>t</i>-butyl peroxide, persulfates, and the like.</p><p num="0027">Chain transfer agents, well known in the aqueous emulsion polymerization, are
typically used in the polymerization process but are not required. Examples of chain
transfer agents include dodecyl mercaptan, mercaptocarboxylic acids, and esters of
mercaptocarboxylic acid. The chain transfer agent is added at levels of about 0.02 to 2
wt%, preferably 0.1 to 1 wt%, based on the weight of monomers.</p><p num="0028">Effective emulsion polymerization reaction temperatures range from about 50
and 100 °C; preferably 75 to 90 °C when using a thermal initiator such as ammonium
persulfate.</p><p num="0029">In order to maintain the pH of the system at the desired value, there is suitably
added a buffering agent of any convenient type. Any alkaline material which is
compatible with the stabilizing agent can be used as the buffer. The amount of buffer is
that sufficient to adjust the pH of the system within the desired range, e.g., 2.5 to 10 and
preferably 3.5 and 8.5. The amount of buffer is generally about 0.1 to 0.5% by weight,
based on the monomers.</p><p num="0030">The reaction time will also vary depending upon other variables such as the
temperature, the catalyst, and the desired extent of the polymerization. It is generally
desirable to continue the reaction until less than 0.5% of the vinyl ester remains
unreacted. Under these circumstances, a reaction time of about 6 hours has been
found to be generally sufficient for complete polymerization, but reaction times ranging
from 2 to 10 hours have been used, and other reaction times can be employed, if
desired. </p><p num="0031">The stabilizing system typically consists of 0.5-5 wt%, of a surfactant or a blend
of surfactants based on total monomer charged to the system. The surfactants
contemplated for the invention include any of the known and conventional surfactants
and emulsifying agents, principally the nonionic and anionic materials, heretofore
employed in the emulsion copolymerization of vinyl acetate and ethylene;
polyalkoxylated surfactants being especially preferred. The use of protective colloids
such as polyvinyl alcohol and hydroxyethyl cellulose as a component of the stabilizing
system, in contrast to stabilizing systems for many vinyl acetate/ethylene based
adhesives, should be avoided. The presence of conventional levels of polyvinyl alcohol,
e.g., 1 to 3% based upon monomers, in the polymerization process tends to result in a
polymer having undesirable loop tack. Although it may be possible to use a small
amount, e.g., &lt;0.5% based upon the weight of total monomers of a protective colloid
such as polyvinyl alcohol, in most cases it is preferred the polymer emulsion should be
substantially devoid of protective colloid. Among the nonionic surfactants found to
provide good results are the ethoxylated secondary alcohols such as the Igepal
surfactants supplied by Rhone-Poulenc and Tergitols supplied by Union Carbide and
sulfosuccinates. The Igepal surfactants are members of a series of alkylphenoxypoly(ethyleneoxy)ethanols
having alkyl groups containing from about 7-18 carbon atoms,
and having from about 4 to 100 ethyleneoxy units, such as the octylphenoxy
poly(ethyleneoxy)ethanols, nonylphenoxy poly(ethyleneoxy)ethanols, and
dodecylphenoxy poly(ethyleneoxy)ethanols. Examples of nonionic surfactants include
polyoxyalkylene derivatives of hexitol (including sorbitans, sorbides, manitans, and
mannides) anhydride, partial long-chain fatty acid esters, such as polyoxyalkylene
derivatives of sorbitan monolaurate, sorbitan monopalmitate, sorbitan monostearate,
sorbitan tristearate, sorbitan monooleate and sorbitan trioleate. </p><p num="0032">The stabilizing system, including delay addition of monomers and stabilizer
influences the resulting particle size of the polymer. Preferred polymer particle size
diameters will have a number average of from 0.1 to 0.4µ and a weight average particle
size from 0.15 to 0.8µ.</p><p num="0033">Cast films of the VAE pressure sensitive adhesive emulsion polymers of this
invention should have a tensile storage modulus (test frequency of 6.28 rad/sec) within
the area encompassed by the following data points: 1x10<sup>6</sup> and 4x10<sup>9</sup> dynes/cm<sup>2</sup> at -20°C,
and 1x10<sup>3</sup> and 1x10<sup>7</sup> dynes/cm<sup>2</sup> at 50°C and preferably within the area encompassed by
the following data points: 5x10<sup>6</sup> and 2x10<sup>8</sup> dynes/cm<sup>2</sup> at -20°C, and 1x10<sup>4</sup> and 1x10<sup>6</sup>
dynes/cm<sup>2</sup> at 50°C. It has been found in this invention that tensile mechanical
properties, specifically tensile storage modulus, provide an accurate measure of
viscoelastic properties in evaluating adhesive properties of pressure sensitive adhesives.
The low temperature storage modulus values, as defined, is believed to account for
good tack and peel which are required for use at room temperature. High temperature
storage modulus is an indicator of cohesive strength.</p><p num="0034">Without intending to be bound by theory, it is believed that vinyl acetate/ethylene
(VAE) emulsion polymers having a tensile storage modulus below the area
encompassed by the numbers as described above will be too soft for providing
acceptable shear and VAE emulsion polymers having a tensile modulus above the area
will not have sufficient tack and peel strength at room temperature for difficult to bond
surfaces.</p><p num="0035">The following examples are provided to illustrate various embodiments of the
invention and are not intended to restrict the scope thereof. </p><heading>Example 1</heading><heading>Preparation of VAE Pressure Sensitive Adhesives
∼50% Ethylene, 85°C and Use of Thermal Initiator</heading><p num="0036">A copolymer was prepared in a 35 gallon stainless steel reactor with a maximum
operating pressure of about 2000 psi. The reactor was equipped with a jacket for
cooling, a mechanical turbine agitator, and metering pumps for addition of the various
feeds. De-ionized water was used for all experiments.</p><p num="0037">The reactor was charged with 28,100 g of water, 2,170 g of Igepal CO-887 (70%
solution of a 30 mole nonylphenol ethoxylate), 2,025 g of Polystep B-27 (30% solution
of a sodium salt 4 mole sulfated nonylphenol ethoxylate)and 2,400 g of vinyl acetate.
After the initial charges the reactor was purged with nitrogen and ethylene and heated
under agitation to 85°C, then pressurized to 1400 psig with ethylene. Addition of an
ammonium persulfate solution (814 g ammonium persulfate, 271 g sodium bicarbonate
and 7059 g water) was begun and fed to the reactor uniformly over 5 hours. Upon
evidence of an exotherm (about 5 minutes after beginning the persulfate feed), addition
of a monomer solution was begun and added uniformly over a 5 hour period. The
monomer solution consisted of: 32,000 g of vinyl acetate, 912 g of acrylic acid.</p><p num="0038">During the polymerization ethylene was introduced to the reactor at a rate
sufficient to maintain the pressure at 1400 psi. Samples were taken during
polymerization to maintain the vinyl acetate content to less than 5% by weight. Three
hours after initiation 3,760 g water was fed to the reactor uniformly over a two hour
period. At the completion of the vinyl acetate - acrylic acid monomer addition the
ethylene feed to the reactor was discontinued. A total of 37,003 g (including that used to
initially pressurize the reactor) of ethylene was added to the reactor. The contents were 
then held at 85 °C for an additional 45 min and then cooled to 32 °C. The contents were
then transferred to a 60 gallon vessel where vacuum was used to remove any unreacted
ethylene.</p><p num="0039">The physical properties of the resultant latex were:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">% non-volatile</entry><entry align="left">57.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tg</entry><entry align="left">-35 °C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity</entry><entry align="left">150 cps</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(Brookfield RVF viscometer, #4 spindle,</entry><entry align="left">20 rpm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">pH</entry><entry align="left">4.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">coagulum</entry><entry align="left">&lt;0.1% (100 mesh screen)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">percent ethylene (wt%)</entry><entry align="left">∼50</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 2</heading><heading>Delay Surfactant Addition In Preparation of VAE</heading><p num="0040">The procedure of Example 1 was essentially repeated except that a portion of the
surfactant stabilizer was added as a delay and the solids level was adjusted. The
reactor was charged with 32,500 g of water, 1,285 g of Igepal CO-887 (70% solution of a
30 mole nonylphenol ethoxylate), 1,500 g of Polystep B-27 (30% solution of a sodium
salt 4 mole sulfated nonylphenol ethoxylate) and 2,400 g of vinyl acetate. After the initial
charges the reactor was purged with nitrogen and ethylene and heated under agitation
to 85 °C., then pressurized to 1400 psig with ethylene. Addition of an ammonium
persulfate solution (390 g ammonium persulfate, 117 g sodium bicarbonate and 3,395 g
water) was begun and fed to the reactor uniformly over 5 hours.</p><p num="0041">Upon evidence of an exotherm (about 5 minutes after beginning the persulfate
feed), addition of a monomer solution was begun and added uniformly over a 5 hour
period. The monomer solution consisted of: 27,000 g vinyl acetate and 800 g acrylic
acid. A solution of 2,000 g water, 600 g sodium vinyl sulfonate (25%) and 1,500g of the
Polystep B-27 surfactant was also added over the same 5 hour period. During the 
polymerization ethylene was introduced to the reactor at a rate sufficient to maintain the
pressure at 1400 psi. The vinyl acetate level was maintained below about 5% by weight
during polymerization. At the completion of the vinyl acetate - acrylic acid monomer
addition the ethylene feed to the reactor was discontinued. A total of 34,046 g (including
that used to initially pressurize the reactor) of ethylene was added to the reactor. The
contents were then held at 85 °C for an additional 45 min and cooled to 32 °C. The
contents were then transferred to a 60 gallon vessel where vacuum was used to
remove any unreacted ethylene. At this point 40 g of Colloids<sup>TM</sup> 675 (a proprietary
defoamer composition supplied by Rhone-Poulenc) was added to reduce foaming</p><p num="0042">After pulling vacuum on the vessel for 30 minutes the following solutions were
added to further reduce any unreacted monomers; 2.5 g ferrous ammonium sulfate in 90
g water, 30 g sodium formaldehyde sulfoxylate in 180g water and 40g of <i>t</i>-butyl
hydroperoxide (70%) in 250 g water.</p> <p num="0043">The physical properties of the resultant latex were:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">% non-volatile</entry><entry align="left">58.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tg</entry><entry align="left">-31 °C</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">Viscosity</entry> <entry align="left">990 cps</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(Brookfield RVF viscometer, #4 spindle,</entry><entry align="left">20 rpm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">pH</entry><entry align="left">3.81</entry></row><row><entry align="left">coagulum (100 mesh screen)</entry><entry align="left">&lt;0.1%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">percent ethylene (wt%)</entry><entry align="left">∼50</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0044">The only real significance between this example and that of Example 1 appeared
to be in the overall quality of the latex. The delay addition of the surfactant resulted in
fewer grits and a better overall quality of the latex. </p><heading>Example 3</heading><heading>Effect Of Redox Initiator And Lower Reaction Temperature
(50°C) And The Use Of A <i>t</i>-Butylhydroperoxide Redox System</heading><p num="0045">The procedure of Example 1 was repeated except that a 3800 ml pressure
reactor equipped with a turbine agitator, a cooling jacket, pumps and delay feeds to
allow introduction of various solutions and monomers throughout the course of the
reaction was employed. Again, de-ionized water was used for all experiments. A redox
initiator and lower reaction temperature was used.</p><p num="0046">The reactor was charged with 700 g of water, 40.5 g of Igepal CO-887 (70%
aqueous solution nonionic surfactant supplied by Rhone Poulenc), 47.7 g of Polystep B-27
(30% aqueous solution, anionic surfactant supplied by Stepan Co.), 5 g of a 1%
aqueous solution of ferrous ammonium sulfate, 0.48 g of acetic acid and 75 g of vinyl
acetate.</p><p num="0047">After purging the reactor with nitrogen and ethylene the reactor was heated to
50°C and pressurized with 415 g of ethylene, the resulting pressure was 1050 psig.
During the pressurization, 15 g of 15% aqueous solution of sodium formaldehyde
sulfoxylate was added. After pressure equilibration, the reaction was initiated by the
addition of a 10% aqueous solution of <i>tert</i>-butylhydroperoxide at a rate of 0.6 gm/min;
the <i>tert</i>-butylhydroperoxide solution consisted of: 256 g of water, 56 g of 70% aqueous
solution of <i>tert</i>-butylhydroperoxide, 63 g of Polystep B-27 and 25 g of a 25 % aqueous
solution of sodium vinyl sulfonate. When initiation was observed by an increase in
reactor temperature, delay feeds of vinyl acetate/acrylic acid (971 gms/28.6gms) and
sodium formaldehyde sulfoxylate (15% aqueous solution) were begun at 3.7 gm/min and
1.1 gm/min, respectively. The addition rate of the 10% aqueous solution of <i>tert</i>-butylhydroperoxide was increased to 1.1 gm/min. During the reaction, the ethylene
pressure was ramped to 1400 psig. The vinyl acetate/acrylic acid mixture was added
over 4 hours and the addition rates of the <i>tert</i>-butylhydroperoxide and sodium
formaldehyde sulfoxylate were increased incrementally to 3.1 gm/min during the course
of the reaction.</p><p num="0048">The physical properties of the resultant latex were:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">% non-volatile</entry><entry align="left">42</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tg</entry><entry align="left">-29°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity</entry><entry align="left">40cps</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(Brookfield RVF viscometer, #4 spindle,</entry><entry align="left">12 rpm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">coagulum (100 mesh screen)</entry><entry align="left">&lt;0.1%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">percent ethylene (wt%)</entry><entry align="left">40-50</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 4</heading><heading>VAE Employing Lower Thermal Initiator Concentration And
A Higher (90°C) Reaction Temperature</heading><p num="0049">The procedure of Example 2 was repeated except the reactor was charged with:
1037 g of water, 40.5 g of Igepal CO-887, 47.7 g of Polystep B-27 and 64 g of vinyl
acetate. After purging the reactor with nitrogen and ethylene, the reactor was heated to
90°C and pressurized with 1400 psig of ethylene. When the pressure and temperature
had equilibrated, the reaction was initiated through the addition of a 7.5% solution of
ammonium persulfate. When initiation was observed, a vinyl acetate delay consisting of
971 g of vinyl acetate and 28.6 g of acrylic acid was started at a rate of 3.7 g/min.
Another delay solution consisting of 102 g of water, 70 g of Polystep B-27 and 28 g of a
25% aqueous solution of sodium vinyl sulfonate was also added at a rate of 0.56
gm/min. The ethylene pressure was maintained at 1400 psig throughout the reaction
and the monomer delay was added over 4 hours. A total of 137 g of the ammonium 
persulfate solution were added, 135 g of the surfactant solution were added and 895 g of
the monomer solution were added.</p><p num="0050">The physical properties of the resultant latex were:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">% non-volatile</entry><entry align="left">53</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tg</entry><entry align="left">-31°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity</entry><entry align="left">170cps</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(Brookfield RVF viscometer, #4 spindle,</entry><entry align="left">12 rpm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">coagulum (100 mesh screen)</entry><entry align="left">&lt;0.1%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">percent ethylene (wt%)</entry><entry align="left">40-50</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 5</heading><heading>VAE Employing Lower Thermal Initiator Concentration At 85 °C.</heading><p num="0051">The procedure of Example 4 was repeated with the exception that the reaction
was conducted at 85 °C.</p><p num="0052">The physical properties of the resultant latex were:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">% non-volatile</entry><entry align="left">58.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tg</entry><entry align="left">-31 °C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity</entry><entry align="left">990 cps</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(Brookfield RVF viscometer, #4 spindle,</entry><entry align="left">20 rpm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">coagulum (100 mesh screen)</entry><entry align="left">&lt;0.1%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">percent ethylene (wt%)</entry><entry align="left">40-50</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 6</heading><heading>VAE Using Carboxyethyl Acrylate Monomer</heading><p num="0053">The procedure of Example 4 was repeated with the exception that the carboxyl
containing monomer was changed. The reactor was charged with: 1037 g of water, 40.5
g of Igepal CO-887, 47.7 g of Polystep B-27 and 64 g of vinyl acetate. After purging the
reactor with nitrogen and ethylene, the reactor was heated to 85°C and pressurized with 
1400 psig of ethylene. When the pressure and temperature had equilibrated, the
reaction was initiated through the addition of a 10 % solution of ammonium persulfate.
When initiation was observed, a vinyl acetate delay consisting of 943 g of vinyl acetate
and 57.6 g of carboxyethyl acrylate (β CEA supplied by Rhone Poulenc) was started at a
rate of 3.7 g/min. Another delay solution consisting of 102 g of water, 70 g of Polystep
B-27 and 28 g of a 25% aqueous solution of sodium vinyl sulfonate was also added at a
rate of 0.56 gm/min. The ethylene pressure was maintained at 1400 psig throughout the
reaction and the monomer delay was added over 4 hours. A total of 138 g of the
ammonium persulfate solution were added, 135 g of the surfactant solution were added
and 895 g of the monomer solution were added.</p><p num="0054">The physical properties of the resultant latex were:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">% non-volatile</entry><entry align="left">55</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tg</entry><entry align="left">-32°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity</entry><entry align="left">350cps</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(Brookfield RVF viscometer, #4 spindle,</entry><entry align="left">12 rpm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">coagulum (100 mesh screen)</entry><entry align="left">&lt;0.1%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">percent ethylene (wt%)</entry><entry align="left">40-50</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Comparative Example 7</heading><heading>VAE Emulsions Low Temperature (65°C)
And Thermal Initiator Concentration</heading><p num="0055">The procedure of Example 4 was repeated in an effort to generate a vinyl
acetate/ethylene polymer having storage modulus data points outside the desired range.</p><p num="0056">The reactor was charged with: 1037 g of water, 40.5 g of Igepal CO-887, 47.7 g
of Polystep B-27 and 64 g of vinyl acetate. After purging the reactor with nitrogen and
ethylene, the reactor was heated to 65°C and pressurized with 1300 psig of ethylene. 
When the pressure and temperature had equilibrated, the reaction was initiated through
the addition of a 10 % solution of ammonium persulfate. When initiation was observed,
a vinyl acetate delay consisting of 971 g of vinyl acetate and 28.8 g of acrylic acid was
started at a rate of 3.0 g/min. Another delay solution consisting of 102 g of water, 70 g
of Polystep B-27 and 28 g of a 25% aqueous solution of sodium vinyl sulfonate was also
added at a rate of 0.45 gm/min. The ethylene pressure was maintained at 1300 psig
throughout the reaction and the monomer delay was added over 5 hours. A total of 138
g of the ammonium persulfate solution were added, 135 g of the surfactant solution were
added and 895 g of the monomer solution were added.</p><p num="0057">The physical properties of the resultant latex were:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">% non-volatile</entry><entry align="left">58.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tg</entry><entry align="left">-31 °C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity</entry><entry align="left">990 cps</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(Brookfield RVF viscometer, #4 spindle,</entry><entry align="left">20 rpm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">coagulum (100 mesh screen)</entry><entry align="left">&lt;0.1%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">percent ethylene (wt%)</entry><entry align="left">40-50</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Comparative Example 8</heading><heading>Vinyl Acetate-Ethylene-Acrylic Acid Polymers
Delay Addition-Polyvinyl Alcohol Stabilized</heading><p num="0058">A series of polymers was prepared in a one-gallon reactor equipped with a jacket
for cooling, a mechanical turbine agitator, and metering pumps for addition of the various
feeds. Deionized water was used. The reactor was charged with 1113 g of water, 57.0
g of Airvol® 203 poly (vinyl alcohol) (supplied by Air Products and Chemicals, Inc.), 40.7
g of Igepal CO-887 (70% solution of a 30 mole nonylphenolethoxylate supplied by
Rhone-Poulenc) and 75.0 g vinyl acetate. After the initial charging, the reactor was 
purged with nitrogen followed by an ethylene purge, and heated under agitation to 85 °C,
then pressurized to 1000 psig (68 atm) with ethylene. Addition of an ammonium
persulfate (40 g ammonium persulfate (APS), 17 g sodium bicarbonate and 347 g water)
solution was begun at a rate of 2.5 g/min; after 8 minutes the feed rate was slowed to
2.0 g/min. Upon evidence of an exotherm (about 5 minutes after beginning the
persulfate feed), addition of a second monomer solution was begun and added uniformly
over a 3-hour period. The second monomer solution consisted of: 1225.2 g vinyl
acetate, 57.0 g acrylic acid, and 9.5 g n-dodecyl mercaptan, as chain transfer agent.
During the polymerization, ethylene was introduced to the reactor at a rate sufficient to
maintain the pressure at 1000 psig. The persulfate addition was discontinued 15 minutes
after the monomer addition was complete. The contents were then held at 85 °C for an
additional 45 minutes and then cooled to 32 °C The contents were then transferred to a
3-gallon vessel where vacuum was used to remove any unreacted ethylene. At this
point, 2 g of Colloids<sup>TM</sup> 675 (a proprietary defoamer composition supplied by Rhone-Poulenc)
was added to reduce foaming, followed by 1 g of sodium erythorbate in 10 g of
water, then 1 g of <i>t</i>-butyl hydroperoxide in 10 g of water, to reduce residual vinyl acetate.</p><heading>Example 9</heading><heading>Particle Size Study</heading><p num="0059">A series of emulsions was prepared in accordance with Example 5 for the
purpose of determining the effect of initiator concentration and level on particle size.</p><p num="0060">In Run 9a the ammonium persulfate initiator concentration was 10% and a total
of 274g were added during the reaction. </p><p num="0061">In Run 9b the ammonium persulfate initiator concentration was 10% and a total
of 138g were added during the reaction.</p><p num="0062">In Run 9c the ammonium persulfate initiator concentration was 105 and a total of
138g were added during the reaction; the initial amount of vinyl acetate being added to
the reactor was 128 g.</p><p num="0063">In Run 9d, the ammonium persulfate initiator concentration was 10% and 138 g
were used; the initial amount of vinyl acetate added to the reactor was 256 g..</p><p num="0064">The particle size results are shown in Table 1.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Run</entry><entry align="center">Number average particle size (µm)</entry><entry align="center">Weight average particle size (µm)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">9a</entry><entry align="center">0.14</entry><entry align="center">0.24</entry></row><row><entry align="right">9b</entry><entry align="center">0.11</entry><entry align="center">0.20</entry></row><row><entry align="right">9c</entry><entry align="center">0.10</entry><entry align="center">0.19</entry></row><row><entry align="right">9d</entry><entry align="center">0.10</entry><entry align="center">0.19</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0065">These results indicate that the particle size achieved during the polymerization
runs is reasonably constant throughout even though there were significant variations in
initial and final initiator concentration and levels.</p><heading>Example 10</heading><heading>Testing of VAE Polymers For Peel, Tack and Shear</heading><p num="0066">The vinyl acetate/ethylene polymers of Examples 3-7 were tested for peel
strength, loop tack and shear in accordance with accepted procedures and the results
are shown in Table 1. <img id="img-00220001" orientation="unknown" wi="154" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00220001.tif" inline="no" he="217"/><img id="img-00230001" orientation="unknown" wi="145" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00230001.tif" inline="no" he="215"/><img id="img-00240001" orientation="unknown" wi="148" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00240001.tif" inline="no" he="216"/><img id="img-00250001" orientation="unknown" wi="152" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00250001.tif" inline="no" he="182"/></p><p num="0067">The results show that even though the polymer compositions of Examples 3-7
were similar (similar glass transition temperatures) there is a difference in their
performance as pressure sensitive adhesives. For example, the shear value of the
redox catalyzed, low temperature polymerization of Example 3 resulted in extremely low
shear value, i.e., less than 1 hour. Presumably, this was caused by low molecular 
weight due to high initiator concentration. In contrast, Examples 4-6 show polymers
having good shear resistance (5 to 100 hours) as well as good loop tack (30 minute
dwell &gt;1.5) and peel adhesion to stainless steel (&gt;1.5 and preferably &gt;2). Example 7
indicates an extreme in shear performance. In Example 7, the temperature of
polymerization was relatively low (65 °C) even though a thermally activated initiator was
used. Example 8 shows the difference associated with lower ethylene content (35% by
weight) and the use of polyvinyl alcohol as a stabilizing agent. The incorporation of
polyvinyl alcohol protective colloid in the emulsion apparently accounted for the
reduction in loop tack and increase in shear. This is noted in the Fig where the low
temperature valued is above the desired range.</p><p num="0068">It is believed the low temperature polymerization associated with the thermal
initiator resulted in a lower radical flux leading to molecular weight build. The molecular
weight build is evidenced by the higher low temperature storage modulus values
compared to Examples 4 and 5 (to be discussed in Example 9). Thus, it is believed the
high linear molecular weight is responsible for the extreme shear resistance and that it
also responsible for limiting the flow and wetting necessary to achieve good loop tack
and peel resistance values.</p><p num="0069">Example 3 was prepared at a temperature lower than Example 7 but a redox
initiator was used instead and the results show that the pressure sensitive adhesive
performance is not related exclusively to either the glass transition temperature or the
polymerization temperature. The use of a redox initiator at a lower temperature but
employing a redox initiator provided the necessary radial flux to meet the viscoelastic
properties as shown in Example 8. Thus, it can be seen the performance rather is 
related to the combination of conditions which allow preparation of a material having
mechanical properties defined by the DMA storage modulus criteria.</p><p num="0070">Examples 4 and 5 show the influence of temperature. All totaled, the results
show excellent adhesion to stainless steel, i.e. a peel and loop tack value or at least 2 as
measured by the test and a shear value of at least 5 and preferably at least 8 hours and
not greater than about 100 hours.</p><p num="0071">Some of the polymers set forth in Examples 1-8 also were analyzed by
differential scanning calorimetry. This technique suggested the presence of low levels of
crystalline regions within the materials described by these examples. In contrast to the
prior art, it was surprisingly found that the presence of such crystallinity did not preclude
the utility of these materials as pressure sensitive adhesives. Although the presence of
crystallinity at such low levels is difficult to accurately characterize, the presence among
the samples tested is consistent. Based upon the performance of the polymers
prepared, the presence of this level of crystalline material did not limit the utility of these
high ethylene content polymers as pressure sensitive adhesives.</p><p num="0072">To summarize, many combinations of temperature, initiator concentration, chain
transfer agent concentration, monomer concentration and other conditions can be found
which could lead to the desirable adhesive properties found in these materials.
Therefore, the dynamic mechanical properties in terms of the storage modulus limits, in
combination with the polymer composition, provide the most accurate and predictive
capability of a vinyl acetate/ethylene copolymer as a pressure sensitive adhesive. </p><heading>Example 9</heading><heading>Pressure Sensitive Adhesive Peel, Tack and Shear Evaluation</heading><p num="0073">The emulsions of Example 2, as well as two commercial acrylic pressure
sensitive adhesives, were coated on a pilot coater at about 50 ft/min with a three- zone
forced air drying oven at temperatures ranging from 60 - 110 °C using Polyslik
siliconized release liner at a coat weight of about 25 g/m<sup>2</sup>. The coated materials were
then transferred onto 60# Britecoat paper, 2 mil Mylar and FlexCon vinyl film. The
emulsion was able to coat on the siliconized Polyslik release liner without the need for
any further formulating such as wetting agents or thickeners. The pressure sensitive
properties were measured by PSTC methods for peel, loop tack and shear as previously
described.</p><p num="0074">The results are tabulated in Table 2. The typical pressure sensitive properties for
a commercial acrylic emulsion sold under the trademark Flexcryl 1625 bonded to Mylar
film are provided for comparison purposes.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Sample</entry><entry align="center">Flexcryl 1625</entry><entry align="center">Example 2</entry><entry align="center">Example 2</entry><entry align="center">Example 2</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">2 mil Mylar</entry><entry align="center">2-mil Mylar</entry><entry align="center">60# Britecoat</entry><entry align="center">Vinyl Film</entry></row><row><entry align="left">180° Peel g/25mm<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">1360</entry><entry align="left">2087</entry><entry align="left">Paper tear</entry><entry align="left">2087</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Loop Tack g/25mm<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">1134</entry><entry align="left">1179</entry><entry align="left">1905</entry><entry align="left">1560</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Shear (hour)<sup>3</sup></entry><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="left">38</entry><entry align="left">22</entry><entry align="left">23<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0075">The results show the high degree of loop tack and the high peel strength relative
to the commercial acrylic emulsion. It also should be noted that shear values are quite
good compared to the commercial adhesive. </p><heading>Example 11</heading><heading>Dynamic Mechanical Testing</heading><p num="0076">The copolymers of Examples 1 and 2, as well as commercial copolymers were
measured for tensile storage modulus in accordance with the following procedure.</p><p num="0077">Dynamic mechanical testing of the polymer samples was accomplished using the
following procedure. ASTM-D-4065-94 and ASTM-D-5026-94 were used as guidelines
for this procedure. Each polymer emulsion was cast as a film and allowed to dry a
minimum of several days at ambient conditions. The dry film thickness was typically in
the range of 1 to 1.5 mm. The specimens used for testing were die cut from the film and
were about 6.3 mm wide and 30 mm long. The specimens were tested on a
Rheometrics Solid Analyzer (RSA II), from Rheometric Scientific, Inc., to obtain the
tensile dynamic mechanical properties. Data were obtained every 6 °C over a -100 to
200 °C range using a fiber/film fixture and a deformation frequency of 6.28 rad/sec. To
help ensure linear viscoelastic conditions, the applied strains were typically 0.05% in the
glassy region and up to 1% in the rubbery region. A soak time of one minute was used
at each temperature to ensure isothermal conditions. For each temperature, the RSA II
calculated the tensile storage modulus (E'), tensile loss modulus (E''), and <st32:f xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">tangent delta</st32:f>
(<st32:f xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">tan d</st32:f>) based on the width, thickness and length of the sample.</p><p num="0078">The results are shown in the figure.</p><p num="0079">An interesting concept gained from a viewing of the figure is that the vinyl
acetate/ethylene polymers produced herein have a storage modulus temperature
relationship that follows the storage modulus temperature relationship for a commercial
acrylic pressure sensitive adhesive. It is believed that is why the preferred vinyl
acetate/ethylene polymers, such as those from Example 3 et seq., are effective as
pressure sensitive adhesives.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>In an aqueous vinyl acetate/ethylene pressure sensitive adhesive
comprised of polymerized units of vinyl acetate and ethylene, and a carboxyl containing
monomer and from 0-20 wt % of one or more additional ethylenically unsaturated
copolymerizable monomer, based on the total weight of the polymerized monomers, the
improvement for enhanced pressure sensitivity of the vinyl acetate/ethylene polymer
which comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a copolymer having an ethylene content greater than 45% by weight and a Tg of
from -25 to -70°C; and,</claim-text><claim-text>a tensile storage modulus measured at one hertz encompassed within the points
on a plot of tensile storage modulus and temperature of from 1 times 106 and 4 times 109
dynes/cm2 at a temperature of -20°C and 1 times 107 dynes/cm2 and 1 X 103 at a
temperature of 50°C.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The adhesive of Claim 1 wherein the weight percent of ethylene is from
about 45 to 65% by weight of the copolymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The adhesive of Claim 2 wherein the tensile storage modulus measured
at one hertz is embraced by the points from 5x106 and 2x108 dynes/cm2 at -20°C, and
1x104 and 1x106 dynes/cm2 at 50°C</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The adhesive of Claim 3 wherein the ethylenically unsaturated carboxylic
acid is incorporated into the polymer in an amount of from 0.2 to 10% by weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The adhesive of Claim 4 wherein the stabilizing system for the aqueous
vinyl acetate/ethylene pressure sensitive adhesive is comprised of an ethoxylated
secondary alcohol or a sulfosuccinate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The adhesive of Claim 4 wherein the ethylene content of the polymer is
from 45 to 55% by weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The adhesive of Claim 6 wherein the particle size diameter of the polymer
in the emulsion has a number average of from 0.1 to 0.4 µ and a weight average from
0.15 to 0.8µ..</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The adhesive of Claim 7 wherein the emulsion is stabilized with a
surfactant selected for the group consisting of an ethoxylated secondary alcohol or a
sulfosuccinate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The emulsion of Claim 3 wherein the aqueous vinyl acetate/ethylene
pressure sensitive adhesive consists essentially of the polymerized monomers
designated (a) through (c) in the following weight percentages:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) 40-50 wt% vinyl acetate;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) 45 -55 wt% of ethylene; and,</claim-text><claim-text>(c) 0.5-2 wt% alpha, beta-ethylenically unsaturated monocarboxylic
acid;</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The emulsion of Claim 9 wherein the copolymer has a Tg of from -25 to
-35°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The emulsion of Claim 10 wherein the unsaturated carboxylic acid is
acrylic acid.</claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure num="1"><img id="img-00330001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00330001.tif" inline="no" he="191"/></figure></drawings><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="154" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="240" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="240" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>