<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1378290-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1378290" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="29720417" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040107"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1378290-A1" status="new" fvid="23935488"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1378290</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040107</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03254225-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03254225</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030702</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-18765202-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>18765202</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020702</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  23/89        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  23/89        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B   3/38        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B   3/40        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  23/89D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C01B   3/38D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C01B   3/40</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01J23:89G2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01J23:89G4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01B203:02D4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01B203:10B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01B203:10B4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01B203:10B6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01B203:10D12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01B203:10D2B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01B203:10D8</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Silber- oder goldstabilisierte und Nickel enthaltende Katalysatoren sowie Verfahren zur Herstellung von Synthesegas</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Silver- or gold-stabilized nickel-containing catalysts and process for production of syngas</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Catalyseurs contenants du nickel stabilisé par de l'argent ou de l'or et procédé pour la fabrication de gaz de synthèse</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0884274-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0884274</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4060498-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4060498</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>BESENBACHER F. ET AL : "Design of a Surface Alloy Catalyst for Steam Reforming" SCIENCE, AMERICAN ASSOCIATION FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF SCIENCE,, US, vol. 279, 1998, pages 1913-1915, XP002257559 ISSN: 0036-8075</text><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>CHU Y ET AL: "PARTIAL OXIDATION OF METHANE TO CARBON MONOXIDE AND HYDROGEN OVER NIO/LA2O3/DELTA AI2O3 CATALYST" APPLIED CATALYSIS A: GENERAL, ELSEVIER SCIENCE, AMSTERDAM, NL, vol. 134, no. 1, 4 January 1996 (1996-01-04), pages 67-80, XP000199016 ISSN: 0926-860X</text><sources><source category="Y"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>GRISEL RJH ET AL : "A comparative study of the oxidation of CO and CH4 over Au/MOx/Al2O3 catalysts" CATALYSIS TODAY, AMSTERDAM, NL, vol. 64, 2001, pages 69-81, XP002257560</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>SHISHIDO T ET AL: "Partial oxidation of methane over Ni/Mg-Al oxide catalysts prepared by solid phase crystallization method from Mg-Al hydrotalcite-like precursors" APPLIED CATALYSIS A: GENERAL, ELSEVIER SCIENCE, AMSTERDAM, NL, vol. 223, no. 1-2, 10 January 2002 (2002-01-10), pages 35-42, XP004329706 ISSN: 0926-860X</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CONOCOPHILIPS COMPANY</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CONOCOPHILIPS COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ConocoPhilips Company</last-name><address><street>600 North Dairy Ashford</street><city>Houston, TX 77079</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MASLOV SERGEJ A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>RAMANI SRIRAM</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>XU BANG C</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MASLOV, SERGEJ A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>RAMANI, SRIRAM</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>XU, BANG C.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MASLOV, SERGEJ A.</last-name><address><street>1000 South Pine RW</street><city>Ponca City, Oklahoma 74602-1267</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>RAMANI, SRIRAM</last-name><address><street>1000 South Pine RW</street><city>Ponca City, Oklahoma 74602-1267</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>XU, BANG C.</last-name><address><street>600 North Dairy Ashford</street><city>Houston, Texas 77079</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Towler, Philip Dean</last-name><address><street>Frank B. Dehn &amp;amp; Co., European Patent Attorneys, 179 Queen Victoria Street</street><city>London EC4V 4EL</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A method is disclosed for converting light alkanes (e.g.
methane or natural gas) to synthesis gas employing a stabilized
Ni-based catalyst that is active for catalyzing the net partial
oxidation of the hydrocarbon, in the presence of O<sub>2</sub> to CO and H<sub>2</sub>.
Certain preferred catalysts comprise Ni alloyed with a Ni-stabilizing
amount of gold or silver, and a lanthanide element,
carried on a refractory support.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><heading><b>Field of the Invention</b></heading><p num="0001">The present invention generally relates to Ni-based
catalysts and processes that employ such catalysts for
catalytically converting light hydrocarbons (e.g., natural gas)
to synthesis gas. More particularly, the invention relates to
stabilized Ni-containing catalysts that are active for catalyzing
the selective partial oxidation of methane and other light
hydrocarbons to CO and H<sub>2</sub>.</p><heading><b>Description of Related Art</b></heading><p num="0002">Large quantities of methane, the main component of natural
gas, are available in many areas of the world, and natural gas is
predicted to outlast oil reserves by a significant margin.
However, most natural gas is situated in areas that are
geographically remote from population and industrial centers.
The costs of compression, transportation, and storage make its
use economically unattractive.</p><p num="0003">To improve the economics of natural gas use, much research
has focused on methane as a starting material for the production
of higher hydrocarbons and hydrocarbon liquids. The conversion
of methane to hydrocarbons is typically carried out in two steps.
In the first step, methane is reformed with water to produce
carbon monoxide and hydrogen (i.e., synthesis gas or syngas). In
a second step, the syngas is converted to hydrocarbons, for
example, using the Fischer-Tropsch process to provide fuels that
boil in the middle distillate range, such as kerosene and diesel
fuel, and hydrocarbon waxes. Present day industrial use of
methane as a chemical feedstock typically proceeds by the initial
conversion of methane to carbon monoxide and hydrogen by either
steam reforming, which is the most widely used process, or by dry
reforming. Steam reforming proceeds according to Equation 1.
<st32:chr xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">CH<sub>4</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>O ↔ CO + 3H<sub>2</sub></st32:chr> 
Although steam reforming has been practiced for over five
decades, efforts to improve the energy efficiency and reduce the
capital investment required for this technology continue.</p><p num="0004">The partial oxidation of hydrocarbons, e.g., natural gas or
methane is another process that has been employed to produce
syngas. While currently limited as an industrial process,
partial oxidation has recently attracted much attention due to
significant inherent advantages, such as the fact that
significant heat is released during the process, in contrast to
the steam reforming processes, which are endothermic. Partial
oxidation of methane proceeds exothermically according to the
following reaction stoichiometry:
<st32:chr xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">CH<sub>4</sub> + 1/2 O<sub>2</sub> → CO + 2H<sub>2</sub></st32:chr></p><p num="0005">In the catalytic partial oxidation processes, natural gas
is mixed with air, oxygen or oxygen-enriched air, and is
introduced to a catalyst at elevated temperature and pressure.
The partial oxidation of methane yields a syngas mixture with a
H<sub>2</sub>:CO ratio of 2:1, as shown in Equation 2. This ratio is more
useful than the H<sub>2</sub>:CO ratio from steam reforming for the
downstream conversion of the syngas to chemicals such as methanol
and to fuels. Furthermore, oxidation reactions are typically
much faster than reforming reactions. This makes possible the
use of much smaller reactors for catalytic partial oxidation
processes. The syngas in turn may be converted to hydrocarbon
products, for example, fuels boiling in the middle distillate
range, such as kerosene and diesel fuel, and hydrocarbon waxes by
processes such as the Fischer-Tropsch synthesis.</p><p num="0006">The selectivities of catalytic partial oxidation to the
desired products, carbon monoxide and hydrogen, are controlled by
several factors, but one of the most important of these factors
is the choice of catalyst composition. Difficulties have arisen
in the prior art in making such a choice economical. Typically,
catalyst compositions have included precious metals and/or rare
earths. The large volumes of expensive catalysts needed by the
existing catalytic partial oxidation processes have placed these
processes generally outside the limits of economic justification. </p><p num="0007">A number of process regimes have been described in the
literature for the production of syngas via catalyzed partial
oxidation reactions. The noble metals, which typically serve as
the best catalysts for the partial oxidation of methane, are
scarce and expensive. The more widely used, less expensive,
catalysts have the disadvantage of promoting coke formation on
the catalyst during the reaction, which results in loss of
catalytic activity. Moreover, in order to obtain acceptable
levels of conversion of gaseous hydrocarbon feedstock to CO and
H<sub>2</sub> it is typically necessary to operate the reactor at a
relatively low flow rate, or space velocity, using a large
quantity of catalyst.</p><p num="0008">For successful operation at commercial scale, however, the
catalytic partial oxidation process must be able to achieve a
high conversion of the methane feedstock at high gas hourly space
velocities, and the selectivity of the process to the desired
products of carbon monoxide and hydrogen must be high. Such high
conversion and selectivity must be achieved without detrimental
effects to the catalyst, such as the formation of carbon deposits
("coke") on the catalyst, which severely reduces catalyst
performance. Accordingly, substantial effort has been devoted in
the art to the development of economical catalysts allowing
commercial performance without coke formation. Not only is the
choice of the catalyst's chemical composition important, the
physical structure of the catalyst and catalyst support
structures must possess mechanical strength and porosity, in
order to function under operating conditions of high pressure and
high flow rate of the reactant and product gasses. Another
continuing objective in this field is to develop stronger
catalysts and catalyst supports that do not cause a high pressure
drop when subjected to high pressure reactant gases.</p><p num="0009">Of the methods that employ nickel-containing catalysts for
oxidative conversion of methane to syngas, typically the nickel
is supported by alumina or some other type of ceramic support.
For example, V. R. Choudhary et al. (<i>J</i>. <i>Catal.,</i> Vol. 172, pages
281-293, 1997) disclose the partial oxidation of methane to
syngas at contact times of 4.8 ms (at STP) over supported nickel 
catalysts at 700 and 800°C. The catalysts were prepared by
depositing NiO-MgO on different commercial low surface area
porous catalyst carriers consisting of refractory compounds such
as SiO<sub>2</sub>, Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, SiC, ZrO<sub>2</sub> and HfO<sub>2</sub>. Catalysts were also prepared
by depositing NiO on the catalyst carriers with different
alkaline and rare earth oxides such as MgO, CaO, SrO, BaO, Sm<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
and Yb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.</p><p num="0010">U.S. Pat. No. 5,500,149 (assigned to British Gas plc)
describes a Ni/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> catalyst that catalyzes the reaction CO<sub>2</sub> +
CH<sub>4</sub> → 2CO + 2H<sub>2</sub> , and demonstrates how reaction conditions can
affect the product yield. The partial oxidation of methane to
synthesis gas using various transition metal catalysts under a
range of conditions has been described by Vernon, D.F. et al.
<i>(Catalysis Letters</i> 6:181-186 (1990)). European Pat. App. Pub. No.
640561 discloses a catalyst for the catalytic partial oxidation
of hydrocarbons comprising a Group VIII metal on a refractory
oxide having at least two cations. Multimonolith combustors are
discussed by M.F.M. Zwinkels, et al. in a chapter entitled
"Catalytic Fuel Combustion in Honeycomb Monolith Reactors" (Ch.
6, A. Cybulski et al., eds., STRUCTURED CATALYSTS AND REACTORS. 1998.
Marcel Dekker, Inc., pp.149-177.)</p><p num="0011">European Patent No. EP 303,438 (assigned to Davy McKee
Corporation) describes a catalytic partial oxidation process for
converting a hydrocarbon feedstock to synthesis gas using steam
in addition to oxygen. Certain high surface area monoliths
coated with metals or metal oxides, e.g., Pd, Pt, Rh, Ir, Os, Ru,
Ni, Cr, Co, Ce, La, which are active as oxidation catalysts, are
employed in that process. Other suggested coating metals are
noble metals and metals of groups IA, IIA, III, IV, VB, VIB, or
VIIB of the periodic table of the elements.</p><p num="0012">M.B. Davis et al. discloses that in the presence of excess
oxygen, bulk Ni is relatively inert as a catalyst for oxidation
of methane in air at temperatures of about 1,000°C, while Pt and
Pt-Rh are catalytically active <i>(Combustion and Flame</i> (2000) 123:
159-174). Those investigators showed that 40-mesh Ni gauze did
not ignite and there was no conversion of methane under methane 
partial oxidation conditions, however once temperatures greater
than 1,375°K were reached, a homogeneous ignition was apparent.</p><p num="0013">U.S. Pat. Nos. 3,957,682 and 4,083,799 (assigned to Texaco,
Inc.) disclose an Iconel metal screen consisting of about 50-95%
nickel that is a methane steam reforming catalyst. In these
processes the Ni catalyst is initially activated by heating in an
oxygen-containing gas. Similarly, U.S. Pat. No. 5,112,527
(assigned to Amoco Corporation) also describes Ni as a reforming
catalyst in the presence of steam, a gaseous lower alkane and air
and in combination with a Group VIII metal having partial
oxidation activity.</p><p num="0014">Japanese Pat. App. No. S59-184701 (assigned to Hiroshima
Laboratory) describes certain Ni-Cr and Ni-Mb alloy powder
catalysts that are active as methanol reformers.</p><p num="0015">Liao, M.-S., et al. ("Dissociation of methane on different
transition metals," <i>J</i>. <i>Mol. Catal. A: Chem.</i> (1998) 136:185-194)
give a theoretical comparison between Ru, Ir, Rh, Ni, Pd, Pt, Cu,
Ag and Au. Those authors concluded that transition metals are
very active, and coinage metals are inactive for generating CO
and H<sub>2</sub> from methane. Methane dissociation in the presence of
adsorbed oxygen was also modeled.</p><p num="0016">J. Nakamura et al. <i>(Sekiyo Gakkaishi</i> (1993) 36:97-104)
discuss the production of syngas by partial oxidation of CH<sub>4</sub> over
Group VIII metal catalysts. A variety of SiO<sub>2</sub>-supported metals
were studied. Rh, Ru and Ni produced CO<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>O below 700°K,
whereas CO and H<sub>2</sub> were produced above 700°K via CO<sub>2</sub>/H<sub>2</sub>O reforming
of excess CH<sub>4</sub>. Pt at 900°K also produced syngas, but reverse
water-gas shift was active on this metal. Fe and Co only produced
CO<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>O.</p><p num="0017">T. Hayakawa et al. <i>(Sekiyo Gakkaishi</i> (1996) 39:314-321)
describe certain (La,Sr)(Co,Ni) oxide catalysts, having a
perovskite structure, that are said to be active for the
oxidative conversion of methane to synthesis gas. The stable
activity of La<sub>0.8</sub>Sr<sub>0.2</sub>CO<sub>0.8</sub>Ni<sub>0.2</sub>O<sub>3-6</sub> catalyst is said to be likely due
to high dispersion of Ni metal and the presence of La<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and SrO
as the carriers of the Ni catalyst. </p><p num="0018">U.S. Pat. No. 5,149,464 is directed to a method for
selectively oxygenating methane to carbon monoxide and hydrogen
by bringing the reactant gas mixture at a temperature of about
650°C. to 900°C. into contact with a solid catalyst which is
generally described as being either:
<sl><li>a) a catalyst of the formula M<sub>x</sub>M'<sub>y</sub>O<sub>z</sub>, where:
<sl><li>M is at least one element selected from Mg, B, Al, Ln, Ga,
Si, Ti, Zr and Hf; Ln is at least one member of lanthanum and the
lanthanide series of elements;</li><li>M' is a d-block transition metal, and each of the ratios
x/y and y/z and (x+y)/z is independently from 0.1 to 8; or</li></sl></li><li>b) an oxide of a d-block transition metal; or</li><li>c) a d-block transition metal on a refractory support; or</li><li>d) a catalyst formed by heating a) or b) under the
conditions of the reaction or under non-oxidizing conditions.
The d-block transition metals are said to include those having
atomic number 21 to 29, 40 to 47 and 72 to 79 (i.e., the metals
Sc, Ti, V, Cr, Mn, Fe, Co, Ni, Cu, Zr, Nb, Mo, Tc, Ru, Rh, Pd,
Ag, Hf, Ta, W, Re, Os, Ir, Pt and Au).</li></sl></p><p num="0019">U.S. Patent No. 5,997,835 (assigned to Haldor Topsoe A/S)
discloses that addition of small amounts of gold to a nickel-containing
catalyst provides a catalyst with suppressed carbon
deposition during steam reforming of hydrocarbons. Although gold
decreases the catalytic activity of the nickel catalyst, the
catalyst still provides sufficient activity for steam reforming.
The gold and nickel are said to form a type of surface alloy.</p><p num="0020">Soviet Union Patent No. 1189500 (N. N. Kundo et al.)
describes certain Ni or Ni-Cr alloy catalysts for air-O<sub>2</sub>
conversion of CH<sub>4</sub> at atmospheric pressure. The catalyst is
prepared by treating a polyurethane foam matrix with a suspension
of Ni powder in aqueous carboxymethylcellulose, and then
calcining in a reducing atmosphere.</p> <p num="0021">WO 99/35082 (assigned to Regents of the University of
Minnesota) describes certain unsupported transition metal
monolith catalysts for catalyzing the partial oxidation of
methane to 
synthesis gas. Transition metals said to be useful are Fe, Os,
Co, Rh, Ir, Ni, Cu, Pd, Pt and mixtures thereof. Nickel
supported on alumina monoliths was not found to be useful for
syngas production.</p><p num="0022">U.S. Patent No. 5,648,582 (assigned to Regents of the
University of Minnesota) describes certain ceramic monolith
supported rhodium, nickel and platinum catalysts for the
catalytic partial oxidation of methane in gas phase at very short
residence time (800,000 to 12,000,000 h<sup>-1</sup>) . Increasing the
catalyst temperature improved selectivities for CO and H<sub>2</sub>
products and improved methane conversion.</p><p num="0023">Li, Yu and Shen (<i>J Fuel Chem and Tech</i> (2001) 29:112-115)
describe the effects of increasing pressure on partial oxidation
of methane to syngas using nickel on an alumina support as the
catalyst. It was concluded that at high pressure, the partial
oxidation of methane is thermodynamically unfavorable. Not only
does it affect the selectivities to H<sub>2</sub> and CO, high pressure also
restrains the decomposition of CH<sub>4</sub> over the NiO form of catalyst.
Decomposition of CH<sub>4</sub> over the Ni<sup>0</sup> form of the catalyst occurs
quickly, however.</p><p num="0024">In order to operate at very high flow rates, at high
pressure and using smaller catalyst beds in the smaller, short
contact time (i.e., millisecond range) catalytic partial
oxidation (CPOX) reactors, the catalysts should be highly active,
have excellent mechanical strength, resistance to rapid
temperature fluctuations and thermal stability at partial
oxidation reaction temperatures. Conventional Ni-based
catalysts suffer from Ni metal loss and carbon formation, which
prevents their use under high pressure and high flow rate
conditions, which are required for short contact time CPOX
processes. Presently, most Ni-based syngas catalysts are
promoted with precious metals such as Rh or Pt, to deter coking.
In addition to being very expensive, those catalysts usually
operate at high reaction temperatures of more than 1,000°C and
tend to promote steam reforming. Accordingly, there is a
continuing need for more commercially attractive catalyst
compositions for the catalytic partial oxidation of hydrocarbons, 
particularly methane, or methane containing feeds, in which the
catalyst retains a high level of activity and selectivity to
carbon monoxide and hydrogen under conditions of high gas space
velocity, elevated pressure and temperature during extended use
on stream.</p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</b> </heading> <p num="0025">The stabilized nickel catalysts and the methods of the
present invention overcome some of the drawbacks of existing
syngas catalysts and processes for converting light hydrocarbons
to syngas. The new catalysts, which include a nickel-stabilizing
metal are more stable and give higher syngas yield than
conventional Ni-based catalysts under conditions of high gas
space velocity and elevated pressure. In the preferred syngas
production methods, the reaction stoichiometry favors the
catalytic partial oxidation reaction as the primary reaction
catalyzed by the nickel-stabilized catalyst. The term "Ni-stabilizing
metal" means a metal, preferably gold or silver, that
is capable of alloying or otherwise combining or associating with
metallic nickel such that the melting point of nickel is
increased above at least the minimum operating temperature of a
CPOX syngas production process and/or volatilization of the
nickel is deterred under syngas reactor operating conditions. As
a result of their enhanced stability and longer on stream life,
these "stabilized" nickel-based catalysts, even containing 1 wt.%
or more of silver or gold (based on total catalyst weight), are
more economically feasible for use under commercial-scale
conditions than rhodium or platinum promoted nickel catalysts.</p> <p num="0026">Another advantage of the new catalysts employed for syngas
production is that they demonstrate a high level of activity and
selectivity to carbon monoxide and hydrogen under conditions of
high gas hourly space velocity, elevated pressure and high
temperature. The improved stability also manifests itself in
terms of more constant reactor exit temperatures and product gas
compositions.</p><p num="0027">In accordance with certain embodiments of the present
invention a method or process of converting a C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>5</sub> hydrocarbon, 
such as methane or natural gas, and O<sub>2</sub> to a product gas mixture
containing CO and H<sub>2</sub>, is provided. The process comprises mixing
the hydrocarbon-containing feed and an O<sub>2</sub> containing feed to
provide a reactant gas feed mixture. The O<sub>2</sub> containing feedstock
may be pure oxygen gas, air or O<sub>2</sub>-enriched air. The reactant gas
mixture may also include incidental or non-reactive species, in
lesser amounts than the primary hydrocarbon and oxygen
components. Some such species are H<sub>2</sub>, CO, N<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>x</sub>, CO<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>O, Ar,
SO<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>S, as can exist normally in natural gas deposits.
Additionally, in some instances, it may be desirable to include
nitrogen gas in the reactant gas mixture to act as a diluent.
Nitrogen can be present by addition to the reactant gas mixture
or can be present because it was not separated from the air that
supplies the oxygen gas. The reactant gas mixture is fed into a
suitable reactor (a "short contact time reactor") where it comes
into contact with a catalytically effective amount of a
stabilized Ni-based catalyst in the reaction zone of the reactor
such that each portion of reactant gas mixture flowing over the
catalyst is in contact with the catalyst for no more than about
200 milliseconds, preferably under 50 milliseconds, more
preferably under 20 milliseconds, with 10 milliseconds being
highly preferred. The method also includes maintaining catalytic
partial oxidation (CPOX) promoting conditions during the
contacting such that syngas is produced containing a molar ratio
of H<sub>2</sub>:CO of about 2:1. As used herein, the term "about" or
"approximately," when preceding a numerical value, has its usual
meaning and also includes the range of normal measurement
variations that is customary with laboratory instruments that are
commonly used in this field of endeavor (e.g., weight,
temperature or pressure measuring devices), preferably within
±10% of the stated numerical value.</p><p num="0028">Advantageously, certain preferred embodiments of the
process are operated at superatmospheric reactant gas pressure
(preferably in excess of 2 atmospheres or about 200 kPa) to
efficiently produce synthesis gas. The nickel-based catalyst
comprises nickel and a Ni-stabilizing metal, such as Au,
preferably disposed on a refractory support. The term "Ni-stabilizing
metal" means a metal, preferably gold or silver, that 
is capable of alloying or otherwise combining or associating with
metallic nickel such that the melting point of nickel is
increased above at least the minimum operating temperature of a
CPOX syngas production process and/or volatilization of the
nickel is deterred under syngas reactor operating conditions. In
certain embodiments, the Ni-stabilizing metal comprises up to
about 3.3% by weight of the total metal content of the supported
catalyst employed in the method. In certain embodiments, the
refractory support comprises a material chosen from the group
consisting of zirconia, alumina, cordierite, mullite, magnesia,
titania, silica, beryllia, thoria, lanthania, calcium oxide, and
combinations thereof.</p><p num="0029">Also provided in accordance with certain embodiments of the
present invention is a supported nickel-based syngas catalyst
comprising Ni, a Ni-stabilizing metal capable of alloying with
the Ni, preferably Au or Ag, and a refractory support. In
preferred embodiments the catalyst also contains a lanthanide
element, more preferably ytterbium or samarium. In some
embodiments, the supported nickel-based syngas catalyst comprises
one or more structures such as monoliths, gauzes, disks,
granules, beads, pills, pellets, cylinders, trilobes, extrudates,
and spheres. In preferred embodiments the supported nickel-based
syngas catalyst comprises an alloy of Ni and a nickel-stabilizing
amount of Au or Ag, in their reduced metal states, carried on a
refractory support such as a partially stabilized (MgO) zirconia
foam monolith. In some embodiments the supported nickel-based
syngas catalyst includes a refractory support containing
zirconia, alumina, magnesia, titania, silica, beryllia, thoria,
lanthania, calcium oxide, and mixtures of those.</p><p num="0030">The term "maintaining CPOX promoting conditions" refers to
regulating hydrocarbon feedstock composition, pressure, space
velocity, gas preheating and catalyst temperature and contact
time such that the direct partial oxidation reaction is favored
(as shown in Equation 2, in the representative case of methane as
the hydrocarbon). At the same time, preferably the reaction
conditions are also manipulated, e.g., by varying the
carbon:oxygen ratio of the reactant gas mixture, so as to sustain
the reaction autothermally. In certain embodiments of the method, 
the contacting comprises contacting the reactant gas mixture with
a supported nickel-based catalyst comprising nickel a Ni-stabilizing
amount of gold or silver, and a refractory support,
which may be in the form of monoliths, granules, spheres,
particles and pellets.</p><p num="0031">According to certain preferred embodiments of the present
invention, a highly productive process for partially oxidizing a
reactant gas mixture comprising methane and oxygen to form
synthesis gas comprising carbon monoxide and hydrogen is
provided. This process comprises passing the reactant gas
mixture over a Ni-Au or Ni-Ag alloy-containing catalyst, which
also contains Yb, in a reactor under process conditions that
include maintaining a molar ratio of methane to oxygen ratio in
the range of about 1.5:1 to about 3.3:1, the gas hourly space
velocity is maintained in excess of about 20,000 h<sup>-1</sup>, preferably
100,000 h<sup>-1</sup> or more, the reactant gas mixture is maintained at a
pressure in excess of about two atmospheres and at a preheat
temperature of between about 30°C and 750°C. Under these process
conditions within the reactor, the high surface area catalyst
structure causes the partial oxidation of the methane to proceed
at high productivity, i.e., with at least 85% methane conversion,
85% selectivity to carbon monoxide and 85% selectivity to
hydrogen. In preferred embodiments, the productivity is at least
90% methane conversion, 90% selectivity to carbon monoxide, and
90% selectivity to hydrogen, more preferably at least 95% methane
conversion, 95% selectivity to carbon monoxide and 95%
selectivity to hydrogen.</p><p num="0032">The terms "distinct" or "discrete" structures or units, as
used herein, refer to supports in the form of divided materials
such as granules, beads, pills, pellets, cylinders, trilobes,
extrudates, spheres or other rounded shapes, or another
manufactured configuration. Alternatively, the divided material
may be in the form of irregularly shaped particles. Preferably
at least a majority (i.e., &gt;50%) of the particles or distinct
structures have a maximum characteristic length (i.e., longest
dimension) of less than six millimeters, preferably less than
three millimeters. The term "monolith" as used herein is any 
singular piece of material of continuous manufacture such as
solid pieces of metal or metal oxide or foam materials or
honeycomb structures. In some embodiments, two or more catalyst
monoliths are stacked in the catalyst zone of the reactor. In
any case, the new stabilized nickel catalysts, catalyst systems
or catalyst beds have sufficient porosity, or sufficiently low
resistance to gas flow, to permit a stream of said reactant gas
mixture to pass over the catalyst at a gas hourly space velocity
(GHSV) of at least about 20,000 h<sup>-1</sup>, preferably at least about
100,000 h<sup>-1</sup>, which corresponds to a weight hourly space velocity
(WHSV) of about 200 - 1,000 h<sup>1</sup>, when the reactor is operated to
produce synthesis gas. Preferably the reactor is operated at a
reactant gas pressure greater than 2 atmospheres (about 200 kPa),
which is advantageous for optimizing syngas production space-time
yields.</p><p num="0033">In some embodiments, the reactant gas mixture is preheated
to about 30°C - 750°C before contacting the catalyst. The
preheated feed gases pass through the catalytic materials to the
point at which the partial oxidation reaction initiates. An
overall or net catalytic partial oxidation (CPOX) reaction
ensues, and the reaction conditions are maintained to promote
continuation of the process, which preferably is sustained
autothermally.</p><p num="0034">For the purposes of this disclosure, the term "net partial
oxidation reaction" means that the partial oxidation reaction
shown in Reaction 2, above, predominates. However, other
reactions such as steam reforming (see Reaction 1), dry reforming
(Reaction 3) and/or water-gas shift (Reaction 4) may also occur
to a lesser extent.
<st32:chr xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">CH<sub>4</sub> + CO<sub>2</sub> ↔ 2 CO + 2 H<sub>2</sub></st32:chr><st32:chr xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">CO + H<sub>2</sub>O ↔CO<sub>2</sub> + H<sub>2</sub></st32:chr>
The relative amounts of the CO and H<sub>2</sub> in the reaction product
mixture resulting from the catalytic net partial oxidation of the
methane, or natural gas, and oxygen feed mixture are preferably
about 2:1 H<sub>2</sub>:CO, similar to the stoichiometric amounts produced
in the partial oxidation reaction of Reaction 2. </p><p num="0035">As used herein, the terms "autothermal" "adiabatic" and
"self-sustaining" mean that after initiation of the partial
oxidation reaction, no additional or external heat must be
supplied to the catalyst in order for the production of synthesis
gas to continue. Under autothermal or self-sustaining reaction
conditions the feed is partially oxidized and the heat produced
by that exothermic reaction drives the continued net partial
oxidation reaction. Consequently, under autothermal process
conditions there is no external heat source required. The net
partial oxidation reaction conditions are promoted by optimizing
the concentrations of hydrocarbon and O<sub>2</sub> in the reactant gas
mixture, preferably within the range of about a 1.5:1 to about
3.3:1 ratio of carbon:O<sub>2</sub> by weight. In some embodiments, steam
may also be added to produce extra hydrogen and to control the
outlet temperature. The ratio of steam to carbon by weight
ranges from 0 to 1. The carbon:O<sub>2</sub> ratio is the most important
variable for maintaining the autothermal reaction and the desired
product selectivities. Pressure, residence or contact time
(inverse of the GHSV), amount of feed preheat and amount of
nitrogen dilution, if used, also affect the reaction products.
Maintaining net CPOX reaction promoting conditions also includes
maintaining a catalyst residence time of no more than about 200
milliseconds, preferably less than 50 milliseconds, more
preferably less than 20 milliseconds. In certain of the most
highly preferred embodiments, the contact time for the reactant
gas mixture is 10 milliseconds or less. This is accomplished by
passing the reactant gas mixture over, or through the porous
structure of the catalyst system at a gas hourly space velocity
(GHSV) of about 20,000-100,000,000 h<sup>-1</sup>, preferably about 50,000-50,000,000
h<sup>-1</sup>, more preferably about 100,000 - 25,000,000 h<sup>-1</sup>.
The latter range corresponds to a weight hourly space velocity
(WHSV) of 1,000 to 25,000 h<sup>-1</sup>. In preferred embodiments of the
process, the catalyst system catalyzes the net partial oxidation
of at least 90% of a methane feedstock to CO and H<sub>2</sub> with a
selectivity for CO and H<sub>2</sub> products of at least about 90% CO and
90% H<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0036">In certain embodiments of the process, the step of
maintaining net partial oxidation reaction promoting conditions 
includes keeping the temperature of the reactant gas mixture at
about 30°C - 750°C° and keeping the temperature of the catalyst in
the range of about 350-2,000°C, preferably between about 450-1,200°C,
by adiabatic, self-sustaining reaction. In some
embodiments, the process includes maintaining the reactant gas
mixture at a pressure of about 100-32,000 kPa (about 1 - 32
atmospheres), preferably about 200 - 10,000 kPa (about 2 - 10
atmospheres), while contacting the catalyst.</p><p num="0037">In some embodiments, the process comprises mixing a
methane-containing feedstock and an O<sub>2</sub>-containing feedstock
together in a carbon:O<sub>2</sub> ratio of about 1.5:1 to about 3.3:1,
preferably about 1.7:1 to about 2.1:1, and more preferably about
2:1). Preferably the methane-containing feedstock is at least 80
% methane, more preferably at least 90%.</p><p num="0038">According to certain embodiments of the present invention,
a method of converting a light hydrocarbon and O<sub>2</sub> to a product
mixture containing CO and H<sub>2</sub> is provided. The process includes
forming a reactant gas mixture comprising a light hydrocarbon
containing gas and an O<sub>2</sub> containing gas, and, in a reactor,
passing the reactant gas mixture over a refractory supported
nickel-gold or nickel-silver alloy catalyst prepared by
sequentially applying a gold or silver precursor compound, such
as a gold or silver salt, to a nickel precursor compound, such as
a nickel salt, to the support and stabilizing the catalyst.
The term "refractory support" refers to any material that is
mechanically stable to the high temperatures of a catalytic
partial oxidation reaction, which is typically 500°C - 1,600°C,
but may be as high as 2,000°C. Suitable refractory support
materials include zirconia, magnesium stabilized zirconia,
zirconia stabilized alumina, yttrium stabilized zirconia, calcium
stabilized zirconia, alumina, cordierite, titania, silica,
magnesia, niobia, vanadia and the like. Preferably the alumina
component is alpha-alumina.</p><p num="0039">In certain embodiments the Ni-stabilized catalyst
comprises up to about 1 wt.% Au (by weight of the total metal
content of the supported catalyst). In certain embodiments the 
Ni-stabilized catalyst comprises up to about 3.3 wt.% Ag and
about 2 wt% Yb. In certain embodiments the supported nickel-based
syngas catalyst comprises an amount of the Ni-stabilizing metal
that provides a catalyst that favors the CPOX reaction over other
possible hydrocarbon oxidation reactions when the catalyst is
employed in a reaction zone of a millisecond contact time syngas
production reactor under CPOX promoting conditions. These and
other embodiments, features and advantages of the present invention
will become apparent with reference to the following description.</p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</b></heading><p num="0040">New Ni-based syngas production catalysts contain nickel
promoted with a Ni-stabilizing metal, preferably Au, carried on
refractory supports such as zirconia, alumina or cordierite, are
prepared as described below. A preferred support material is
partially stabilized zirconia (PSZ), modified with an alkaline
earth metal oxide or a lanthanide metal oxide. These promoted Ni
catalysts are capable of catalytically converting C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>5</sub>
hydrocarbons (e.g., methane or natural gas) to synthesis gas
containing CO and H<sub>2</sub>. They are preferably in the form of foams,
monoliths, granules, spheres, pellets, pills, beads and
particles. It is now demonstrated that new Au promoted nickel
catalyst structures, especially when prepared as described in the
following example, are highly active syngas production catalysts
with sufficient thermal stability to resist melting and metal
loss at reaction temperatures when employed on-stream in a short
contact time reactor for synthesis gas production. Without
wishing to be restricted to a particular theory, it is concluded
from the present studies that alloying Ni with Au, Ag or another
suitable alloying metal, serves to elevate the melting
temperature of the nickel and deter loss of nickel at on-stream
CPOX syngas production temperatures. Activity of the catalyst is
therefore preserved over a longer period of time than is possible
with conventional nickel catalysts used for syngas production.
It is also observed in the present studies that the promoter
serves to lower the light-off and reaction temperatures and to
reduce coking of the catalyst during operation. Including a
lanthanide element, preferably Yb, further enhances catalyst 
performance. The new stabilized Ni catalysts are expected to
serve as good substitutes for the more costly rhodium catalysts
that are employed today in CPOX syngas production processes. A
Ni-stabilized catalyst is more resistant to high temperature
reactor operating conditions (up to at least 1,600°C) and is
longer lived, experiencing reduced coking on stream, than a
typical metallic nickel-based syngas catalyst.</p><p num="0041">A preferred catalyst support structure is a foam monolith
made of partially (MgO) stabilized zirconia (PSZ), or alpha-alumina.
Another refractory ceramic oxide foam monolith that is
chemically and physically stable under the required partial
oxidation reaction conditions could be substituted for the PSZ
monolith, if desired. The term "monolith" refers to any singular
piece of material of continuous manufacture such as solid pieces
of metal or metal oxide or foam materials or honeycomb
structures. Two or more such catalyst monoliths may be stacked in
the catalyst zone of the reactor if desired. In any case, the
catalyst device, system or bed has sufficient porosity, or
sufficiently low resistance to gas flow, to permit a stream of
said reactant gas mixture to pass over the catalyst at a gas
hourly space velocity (GHSV) of at least about 20,000 h<sup>-1</sup>,
preferably at least 100,000 h<sup>-1</sup>, when the reactor is operated to
produce synthesis gas and elemental sulfur from a mixture of H<sub>2</sub>S
and light hydrocarbon.</p><p num="0042">For example, zirconia, alumina, cordierite, mullite,
magnesia, titania, silica, beryllia, thoria, lanthania, calcium
oxide, and mixtures of those materials can serve as satisfactory
support materials. Also, thermally stabilizing substances other
than MgO could also be used with success in the supports, such as
calcium or yttrium oxide. Suitable foams for use in the
preparation of the catalyst preferably have from 30 to 150 pores
per inch (12 to 60 pores per centimeter). Alternative support
structures for the catalyst include refractory oxide honeycomb
monolith structures, such as a honeycomb substrate made of
cordierite or mullite (which are available from known commercial
sources), or other configuration having longitudinal channels or
passageways permitting high space velocities with a minimal 
pressure drop. Preferred supports have a tortuosity of about
1.0. Such configurations are known in the art and described, for
example, X. Xu and J.A. Moulijn, "Transformation of a Structured
Carrier into Structured Catalyst" in STRUCTURED CATALYSTS AND REACTORS,
A. Cybulski and J.A. Moulijn (Eds.), Marcel Dekker, Inc., 1998,
(Ch. 21) p. 599-615.</p><p num="0043">Still other suitable support geometries include discrete or
divided structures or units in the form of divided materials such
as granules, beads, pills, pellets, cylinders, trilobes,
extrudates, spheres or other rounded shapes, or another
manufactured configuration. Alternatively, the divided material
may be in the form of irregularly shaped particles. Preferably
at least a majority (i.e., &gt;50%) of the particles or distinct
structures have a maximum characteristic length (i.e., longest
dimension) of less than ten millimeters, preferably less than
five millimeters. These particulate supports are impregnated
with the catalyst precursor materials as described above for the
PSZ monolith, or by any suitable technique, including
impregnation, washcoating, adsorption, ion exchange,
precipitation, co-precipitation, deposition precipitation, sol-gel
method, slurry dip-coating, microwave heating, and other
methods known in the art for preparing a supported catalyst. The
granule or spheres preferably range in size from 50 microns to 6
mm in diameter (i.e., about 120 mesh, or even smaller, to about
1/4 inch). More preferably the particles are no more than 3 mm
in their longest characteristic dimension, or range from about 80
mesh (0.18 millimeters) to about 1/8 inch, and more preferably
about 35-50 mesh. The term "mesh" refers to a standard sieve
opening in a screen through which the material will pass, as
described in the Tyler Standard Screen Scale (C.J. Geankoplis,
TRANSPORT PROCESSES AND UNIT OPERATIONS, Allyn and Bacon, Inc., Boston,
MA, p. 837), hereby incorporated herein by reference. According
to this scale, 20-120 wire mesh screen has 0.841 - 0.122 mm sieve
opening with 0.510 - 0.89 mm nominal wire diameter. Preferably
the support materials are pre-shaped as granules, spheres,
pellets, or other geometry that provides satisfactory engineering
performance, before application of the catalytic materials.
Although it is preferred that the promoter and the nickel are 
applied by sequential impregnation, as exemplified below,
catalysts with acceptable activity can also be prepared by
applying the nickel and promoter metal salts simultaneously as a
mixture.</p><heading><b>Process of Producing Synthesis Gas</b></heading><p num="0044">For the production of syngas, any suitable reaction regime
may be applied in order to contact the reactants with a
stabilized Ni catalyst described above. One suitable regime is a
fixed bed reaction regime, in which the catalyst is retained
within a reaction zone in a fixed arrangement, retained using
fixed bed reaction techniques that are well known and have been
described in the literature. A hydrocarbon and O<sub>2</sub>-containing
reactant gas mixture is contacted with a stabilized nickel-based
catalyst in a reaction zone maintained at partial oxidation-promoting
conditions of temperature, pressure and flow rate, as
indicated below, effective to produce an effluent stream
comprising carbon monoxide and hydrogen. Preferably a short or
millisecond contact time reactor is employed. Several schemes
for carrying out catalytic partial oxidation (CPOX) of
hydrocarbons in a short contact time reactor are well known and
have been described in the literature. Preferably methane and
an O<sub>2</sub>-containing feedstock are combined to provide the reactant
gas mixture. Natural gas, or other light hydrocarbons having
from 2 to 5 carbon atoms, and mixtures thereof, also serve as
satisfactory feedstocks. The O<sub>2</sub> containing feedstock is
preferably pure oxygen gas, but it may also be air or O<sub>2</sub>-enriched
air. In addition, the oxygen-containing gas may also comprise
steam and/or CO<sub>2</sub> in addition to oxygen. The reactant gas mixture
is fed into a reactor where it comes into contact with a
catalytically effective amount of a stabilized nickel catalyst
carried on a refractory support. The reactant gas mixture passes
over the catalyst at a gas hourly space velocity of at least
about 20,000 h<sup>-1</sup>, which corresponds to a weight hourly space
velocity (WHSV) of about 200 h<sup>-1</sup>, when the reactor is operated to
produce synthesis gas. The hydrocarbon feedstock and/or the
oxygen-containing gas may be pre-heated before contacting the
catalyst, preferably the reactant gas mixture is pre-heated to a 
temperature of about 30-750°C, more preferably not more than
about 525°C. Catalytically inert porous ceramic foam monoliths
are preferably placed before and after the catalyst as radiation
shields. The inlet radiation shield also typically aids in
uniform distribution of the feed gases into the catalyst zone.</p><p num="0045">The reactant gas mixture passes over the catalyst and the
catalytic materials are heated to the point at which they ignite
and start the reaction. An autothermal net catalytic partial
oxidation reaction preferably ensues, and the reaction conditions
are managed so as to promote continuation of the autothermal
process. For the purposes of this disclosure, "autothermal"
means that after catalyst ignition, no additional heat must be
supplied to the catalyst in order for the production of synthesis
gas to continue. Autothermal reaction conditions are promoted
by optimizing the concentrations of hydrocarbon and O<sub>2</sub> in the
reactant gas mixture, preferably within the range of about a
1.5:1 to about 2.3:1 ratio of carbon:oxygen. The
hydrocarbon:oxygen ratio is an important variable for maintaining
the autothermal CPOX reaction and the desired product
selectivities, although maintaining the desired temperature, for
example, may in some instances require variation of the
carbon:oxygen ratio. Pressure, residence time, amount of feed
preheat and amount of nitrogen dilution, if used, also affect the
reaction products. The process preferably includes maintaining a
catalyst residence time of no more than about 200 milliseconds,
more preferably under 50 milliseconds, and still more preferably
under 20 milliseconds, with 10 milliseconds or less being highly
preferred for the reactant gas mixture. This is accomplished by
passing the reactant gas mixture over the catalyst at a gas
hourly space velocity (GHSV) of about 20,000-10,000,000 h<sup>-1</sup>,
preferably about 50,000-6,000,000 h<sup>-1</sup>. This range of preferred
gas hourly space velocities corresponds to a weight hourly space
velocity (WHSV) of about 500 to 60,000 h<sup>-1</sup>. Under near optimal
reaction conditions, a preferred catalyst catalyzes the net
partial oxidation of at least 90% of a methane feedstock to CO
and H<sub>2</sub> with a selectivity for CO and H<sub>2</sub> products of at least about
90% CO and 90% H<sub>2</sub>. Maintaining CPOX reaction promoting 
conditions may include keeping the temperature of the catalyst in
the preferred range of about 450-1,200°C, and maintaining a
reactant gas pressure of about 100-32,000 kPa, preferably about
200-10,000 kPa, while contacting the catalyst. Near ideal
operating conditions also include mixing a methane-containing
feedstock and an O<sub>2</sub>-containing feedstock together in a
carbon:oxygen ratio of about 1.5:1 to about 2.2:1, and preferably
about 2:1. Preferably the methane-containing feedstock is at
least about 50% methane by volume, more preferably at least 80 %
methane. Natural gas is mostly methane, but it can also contain
up to about 25 mole % ethane, propane, butane and higher
hydrocarbons. The new syngas generation process is suitable for
the conversion of gas from naturally occurring reserves of
methane, which can also contain carbon dioxide, nitrogen,
hydrogen sulfide, and other minor components. The product gas
mixture emerging from the reactor preferably has the desired
Fischer-Tropsch syngas feed H<sub>2</sub>:CO ratio of 2:1.

   The following examples are offered by way of illustration,
and not by way of limitation. Those skilled in the art will
recognize that variations of the invention embodied in the
example can be made, especially in light of the teachings of the
various references cited herein, the disclosures of which are
incorporated by reference.</p><heading><b>Example 1: 11 wt% Ni- 0.2 wt% Au Ally on PSZ</b></heading><p num="0046">A representative Au-promoted Ni catalyst containing 11% Ni
and 0.2% Au (by weight of the total supported catalyst) supported
on a MgO stabilized PSZ monolith was prepared by dissolving
Ni(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>·xH<sub>2</sub>O (Aldrich) in water to form an aqueous solution.
The concentration of the Ni solution and the amount loaded onto
the PSZ monolith were chosen so as to provide the final wt % of
Ni metal stated in <b>Table 1</b>. A PSZ(MgO containing) monolith about
12 mm diameter and 9.5 mm (3/8 inch) thick and containing 80
pores per linear inch (ppi) (Vesuvius Hi-Tech Ceramics, NY or
Porvair Advanced Materials Inc., NC) was situated on a Teflon®
plate resting on a warm (75°C) hotplate. The Ni salt solution
was gradually added to the monolith, allowing the water to 
evaporate between saturations. The dried monolith was then
calcined in air (static or flowing) according to the following
program: heat from room temperature (RT) to about 125°C at a rate
of about 3°C/min, dwell at that temperature for about 60 min;
heat from about 125°C to about 400-900°C, preferably about 500°C,
at a rate of about 1-10°C/min, preferably about 5°C/min, dwell at
that temperature for about 120-360 min, or more, preferably about
180 min.</p><p num="0047">Next, an aqueous solution of Au(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> was added
dropwise to saturate the Ni-coated PSZ monolith. The
concentration of the Au solution and the amount loaded onto the
PSZ monolith was chosen so as to provide the final wt % of Au
stated in <b>Table 1</b>. The Au salt solution was gradually added to
the monolith, allowing the water to evaporate between
saturations. The dried monolith was then calcined in air,
according to the program described above for the Ni-impregnated
monolith.</p><p num="0048">This final calcined PSZ supported Ni-Au catalyst was then
reduced in flowing H<sub>2</sub> (or H<sub>2</sub>/N<sub>2</sub> mixture) at a flow rate of about
0.1 - 1 normal liters per minute (NLPM), or more, preferably
about 0.6 NLPM, while applying heat according to the following
program: heat from room temperature (RT) to about 125°C at a rate
of temperature increase of 3°C/min, dwell for about 30 min at
that temperature; heat from about 125°C to about 300 to 900°C,
preferably about 500°C, at a rate of increase of about 1 to
10°C/min, preferably about 3°C/min, dwell at that temperature for
about 60 - 360 min, or more, preferably about 180 min. The
catalytic activity of the resulting Ni/Au catalyst was evaluated
under partial oxidation reaction promoting conditions in a
laboratory scale short contact time reactor, as described below
under "Test Procedure."</p><heading><b>Example 2. (Comparative) 4 wt% Rh - 5 wt% Sm on PSZ Foam</b></heading><p num="0049">Sm(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>·6H<sub>2</sub>O (Aldrich) was dissolved in sufficient water
to form an aqueous solution. A PSZ monolith about 15 mm long and
12 mm diameter was situated on a Teflon® plate resting on a warm 
(75°C) hotplate. Satisfactory PSZ monoliths can be obtained
commercially (Vesuvius Hi-Tech Ceramics, NY or Porvair Advanced
Materials Inc., NC). The entire Sm salt solution was gradually
added to the monolith, allowing the water to evaporate between
saturations. The dried monolith was then calcined in air (static
or flowing) according to the following program: heat from room
temperature (RT) to about 125°C at a rate of about 3°C/min, dwell
at that temperature for about 60 min; heat from about 125°C to
about 400-900°C, preferably about 500°C, at a rate of about 1-10°C/min,
preferably about 5°C/min, dwell at that temperature for
about 120-360 min, or more, preferably about 180 min.</p><p num="0050">An aqueous solution of RhCl<sub>3</sub>.xH<sub>2</sub>O was added dropwise to
saturate the Sm-coated PSZ monolith, prepared as described in the
above paragraph. The Rh salt solution was gradually added to the
monolith, allowing the water to evaporate between saturations.
The dried monolith was then calcined in air, according to the
program described above.</p><p num="0051">This final calcined Rh/Sm/PSZ catalyst system was then
reduced in flowing H<sub>2</sub> (or H<sub>2</sub>/N<sub>2</sub> mixture) at a flow rate of about
0.1 - 1 NLPM, or more, preferably about 0.6 NLPM, while applying
heat according to the following program: heat from room
temperature (RT) to about 125°C at a rate of temperature increase
of 3°C/min, dwell for about 30 min at that temperature; heat from
about 125°C to about 300 to 900°C, preferably about 500°C, at a
rate of increase of about 1 to 10°C/min, preferably about
3°C/min, dwell at that temperature for about 60 - 360 min, or
more, preferably about 180 min. The concentrations of the Sm
and Rh solutions and the amounts loaded onto the PSZ monolith
were chosen so as to provide a final wt.% of each metal of 4
wt.% Rh and 5 wt.% Sm (wt. % of total weight of the metal content
of the catalyst and support).</p><heading><b>Test Procedure-1</b></heading><p num="0052">Representative promoted Ni-based catalysts were evaluated
for ability to catalyze the partial oxidation reaction in a 
conventional flow apparatus in a conventional flow apparatus
using a quartz reactor with a length of 12 inches, an outside
diameter of 19 mm and an inside diameter of 13 mm. Ceramic foam
pieces of 99% Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (12 mm outside diameter x 5 mm thick, with 45
pores per linear inch) were placed before and after the catalyst
as radiation shields. The inlet radiation shield also aided in
uniform distribution of the feed gases. An Inconel-sheathed,
single point K-type (Chromel/Alumel) thermocouple was placed
axially inside the reactor, touching the top (inlet) face of the
radiation shield. A high temperature S-Type (Pt/Pt 10% Rh) bare-wire
thermocouple was positioned axially touching the bottom face
of the catalyst, and was used to indicate the reaction
temperature. The catalyst and the two radiation shields were
tightly sealed against the inside walls of the quartz reactor by
wrapping the shields radially with a high purity (99.5%) alumina
paper. A 600-watt band heater set at 90% electrical output was
placed around the quartz tube, providing heat to light off the
reaction and preheat the feed gases. The bottom of the band
heater corresponded to the top of the upper radiation shield.

   In addition to the thermocouples placed above and below
the catalyst, the reactor also contained two axially positioned,
triple-point thermocouples, one before and another after the
catalyst. These triple-point thermocouples were used to
determine the temperature profiles of the reactants and products
that were subjected to preheating and quenching, respectively.</p><p num="0053">The runs were conducted at a CH<sub>4</sub>:O<sub>2</sub> molar ratio of 2:1 with
a combined flow rate of 7.7 SLPM (standard liters per minute),
corresponding to a gas hourly space velocity of 350,000 - 400,000
h<sup>-1</sup> and at a pressure of 5 psig (136 kPa) . The reactor effluent
was analyzed using a gas chromatograph equipped with a thermal
conductivity detector. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><b>Catalyst Performance</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>Example</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Catalyst</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>CH<sub>4</sub> Conv.</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>CO Sel.</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>H<sub>2</sub> Sel.</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">11% Ni-0.2% Au/PSZ monolith</entry><entry align="center">77.8</entry><entry align="center">93</entry><entry align="center">94.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center">(Comparative) 2</entry><entry align="center">4% Rh/5% Sm/PSZ monolith</entry><entry align="center">81.4</entry><entry align="center">94.2</entry><entry align="center">91.5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0054">There are two major problems associated with the use of
conventional Ni-containing catalysts for catalyzing the partial
oxidation of methane: coking and nickel evaporation. In the
present series of studies, it was observed that a Au-promoted
nickel catalyst avoided the coking problem. As shown in <b>Table 1</b>,
the catalytic performance of the Au-promoted Ni catalyst,
supported on a PSZ monolith is close to that of a PSZ supported
4% Rh/5% Sm catalyst, prepared and evaluated under similar test
conditions. In these studies it was also observed that the Ni-Au
surface alloy also appears to deter evaporation of Ni over the
course of a 3-4 hour period of time on stream in a CPOX reactor
producing synthesis gas.</p><heading><b>Example 3: Ag-Yb-promoted Ni-MgO solid solution catalyst</b></heading><p num="0055">A silver and ytterbium-promoted Ni-MgO solid solution
catalyst supported on 80-ppi PSZ foam was prepared according to
the following procedure, given here for laboratory-scale batches.
<sl><li>(a) A solution containing 0.4779 gram of Mg (NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>.6H<sub>2</sub>O
(Aldrich 23,717-5) in 1.7355 grams of distilled and de-ionized
(DDI) water was prepared at about 60°C on a hotplate. Part of
this solution was added drop wise to PSZ foam (partially
stabilized zirconia with Mg, 80-ppi, 3/8" L x ½" D, 0.7496 gram).</li><li>(b) The wet PSZ foam is dried at about 60°C for 2 hours
on the hotplate and calcined in air according to the following
schedule: 5°C/min ramp up to 125°C; hold at 125°C for 1 hour;
5°C/min ramp up to 500°C; hold at 500°C for 3 hours; 10°C/min 
ramp down to room temperature. After this calcination step, the
loaded support contained 4.68 wt% MgO based on the weight of PSZ
support.</li><li>(c) Next, a solution containing 1.5665 grams of
Ni(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>.6H<sub>2</sub>O (Aldrich 24,407-4) in 4.5905 grams of DDI water was
prepared at about 60°C on the hotplate. Part of this solution
was added drop wise to the MgO-coated PSZ foam. The wet support
was then dried at about 60°C for 1 hour on the hotplate, and
calcined in air according to the following schedule: 5°C/min ramp
up to 125°C; hold at 125°C for 1 hour; 5°C/min ramp up to 500°C;
hold at 250°C for 1 hour; ramp up to 900°C; hold at 900°C for 3
hours; 10°C/min ramp down to room temperature. After this
calcination step, the support contained 7.58 wt% NiO based on the
weight of PSZ support.</li><li>(d) Addition of the nickel nitrate solution, drying and
calcination were repeated, using the same procedure as described
in (c), above. After the second Ni impregnation, the calcined
catalyst intermediate (i.e., NiO+MgO-coated support) contained
18.9 wt% NiO based on the weight of PSZ support. This weight of
NiO corresponds to 14.9 wt% of Ni based on the weight of PSZ
support.</li><li>(e) Next, 0.0399 gram of Yb(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>.5H<sub>2</sub>O and 0.0555 gram of
Ag(NO<sub>3</sub>) .xH<sub>2</sub>O (Aldrich 20,913-8) were dissolved in 0.6746 gram of
DDI water at about 60°C on the hotplate and added drop wise to
the (NiO+MgO)-coated PSZ foam. The wet foam was then dried at
about 60°C for 1 hour on the hotplate, and calcined in air
according to the following schedule: 1°C/min ramp up to 140°C;
hold at 140°C for 2 hours; 5°C/min ramp down to room temperature.
After calcination, the loaded support contained 2.05 wt% Yb and
3.3 wt% Ag based on the weight of PSZ support.</li><li>(f) Finally, the loaded support was reduced with H<sub>2</sub> using
1:1 by volume flow of N<sub>2</sub>:H<sub>2</sub> mixture at 0.2 standard liter per
minute (SLPM) measured at 0°C and 1 atm pressure, using the
following schedule: 3°C/min ramp up to 125°C; hold at 125°C for
0.5 hour; 3°C/min ramp up to 800°C; hold at 800°C for 3 hours;
5°C/min ramp down to room temperature. The composition of the 
final catalyst was 3.3 wt% Ag, 2.05 wt% Yb, 14.9 wt% Ni and 4.68
wt% MgO.</li></sl></p><heading><b>Test Procedure-2</b></heading><p num="0056">The catalytic performance of the Ag-Yb-promoted Ni-MgO
solid solution catalyst of Example 2 was evaluated in a pilot
plant reactor at 45 psig. The partial oxidation reactions were
carried out in a conventional flow apparatus using a 19 mm O.D. x
13 mm I.D. quartz insert embedded inside a refractory-lined steel
vessel. The quartz insert contained a catalyst system containing
at least one porous monolith catalyst (about 12 mm O.D. x 15 mm
high) held between two foam disks. In the case of the pill-supported
catalyst (Example 10), the catalyst was packed between
the two foam disks. The upper disk typically consisted of 65-ppi
PSZ and the bottom disk typically consisted of 30-ppi zirconia-toughened
alumina. Preheating the methane or natural gas that
flowed through the catalyst system provided the heat needed to
start the reaction. Oxygen was mixed with the methane or natural
gas immediately before the mixture entered the catalyst system.
Once the reaction started, it proceeded autothermally. Two Type
K thermocouples with ceramic sheaths were used to measure
catalyst inlet and outlet temperatures. The molar ratio of CH<sub>4</sub>
to O<sub>2</sub> was generally about 2:1, however the relative amounts of
the gases, the catalyst inlet temperature and the reactant gas
pressure could be varied by the operator according to the
parameters being evaluated (see Table 2). The product gas
mixture was analyzed for CH<sub>4</sub>, O<sub>2</sub>, CO, H<sub>2</sub>, CO<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> using a gas
chromatograph equipped with a thermal conductivity detector. A
gas chromatograph equipped with flame ionization detector
analyzed the gas mixture for CH<sub>4</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>2</sub>. The CH<sub>4</sub>
conversion levels and the CO and H<sub>2</sub> product selectivities
obtained for a catalyst evaluated in this test system are
considered predictive of the conversion and selectivities that
will be obtained when the same catalyst is employed in a
commercial scale short contact time reactor under similar
conditions of reactant concentrations, temperature, reactant gas
pressure and space velocity. <tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry nameend="8" namest="1"><b>Catalyst Performance of Ag-Yb-promoted Ni-MgO Solid Solution Catalyst</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>Preheat T (deg.C)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Operating Pressure (psig)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>O<sub>2</sub>/Fuel molar ratio</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>GHSV (h<sup>-1</sup>)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Reaction T (deg.C)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>CH<sub>4</sub>/O<sub>2</sub> conv. (%)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>CO/H<sub>2</sub> sel. (%)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>H<sub>2</sub>:CO ratio</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center">425</entry><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">0.5461</entry><entry align="center">1,632,000</entry><entry align="center">1145</entry><entry align="center">83.4/98.9</entry><entry align="center">92.5/84.2</entry><entry align="center">1.77</entry></row><row><entry align="center">425</entry><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">0.5386</entry><entry align="center">1,632,000</entry><entry align="center">1142</entry><entry align="center">75.8/99.5</entry><entry align="center">84.5/71.9</entry><entry align="center">1.64</entry></row><row><entry align="center">425</entry><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">0.5042</entry><entry align="center">1,570,000</entry><entry align="center">1151</entry><entry align="center">70.6/99.5</entry><entry align="center">79.8/67.8</entry><entry align="center">1.58</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables>
As shown in Table 2, the performance varied as a function of the
Oxygen/Fuel (CH<sub>4</sub>) ratio. As the ratio increased, conversion and
selectivity increased, which indicated that the catalyst is
selective to syngas generation. A non-selective catalyst would
show an increase in CO<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>O selectivity and a corresponding
decrease in CO and H<sub>2</sub> selectivity, but the fact that the syngas
selectivity increased with increasing oxygen content in the feed
confirms the syngas-selective nature of this catalyst
composition. It should be noted that this performance was
achieved at a contact time of 2.2 milliseconds (corresponding to
a GHSV of 1,632,000 h<sup>-1</sup>) , which demonstrates the activity of the
catalyst for short contact time CPOX reaction. By controlling
the Oxygen/Fuel ratio and flowrates, it is expected that further
improvement in syngas performance will be achieved with this
preferred catalyst formulation.

   While the preferred embodiments of the invention have been
shown and described, modifications thereof can be made by one
skilled in the art without departing from the spirit and
teachings of the invention. The embodiments described herein are
exemplary only, and are not intended to be limiting. For
example, pure methane was employed in the representative test
procedures, however, any light hydrocarbon (i.e., C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>5</sub>) gaseous
feedstock could also serve as a satisfactory feedstock for the
catalytic partial oxidation reaction catalyzed by the new Ni-based
catalysts. Many variations and modifications of the
invention disclosed herein are possible and are within the scope 
of the invention. The discussion of certain references in the
Description of Related Art, above, is not an admission that they
are prior art to the present invention, especially any references
that may have a publication date after the priority date of this
application. The disclosures of all patents, patent applications,
and publications cited herein are hereby incorporated by
reference.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A stabilized nickel-based catalyst comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>nickel;</claim-text><claim-text>gold or silver; and</claim-text><claim-text>a refractory support, said catalyst being active for
selectively catalyzing the partial oxidation of CH4 to CO and H2
under catalytic partial oxidation promoting conditions in a short
contact time reactor, and wherein said gold or silver is present
in an amount sufficient to increase the melting point of said
nickel under said catalytic partial oxidation promoting
conditions.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The catalyst of claim 1 further comprising a lanthanide
element.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The catalyst of claim 2 wherein said lanthanide element is
Sm or Yb.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The catalyst of claim 3 wherein said Yb is present in an
amount of 2 wt.%. based on the total metal content of the
supported catalyst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The catalyst of any one of claims 1 to 4 comprising up to
3.3 wt% Ag or Au based on the total metal content of the
supported catalyst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The catalyst of claim 5 comprising up to 1 wt% Au or Ag.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The catalyst of any one of claims 1 to 6 comprising a Ni-Au
or Ni-Ag alloy.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The catalyst of claim 7 wherein said alloy has a melting
temperature above 2000°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The catalyst of any one of claims 1 to 8 wherein said
nickel and gold or silver are in their reduced metal states.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The catalyst of any one of claims 1 to 9 wherein said Ni is
the form of a Ni-MgO solid solution.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The catalyst of any one of claims 1 to 10 wherein said
refractory support has a structure chosen from the group
consisting of monoliths, granules, beads, pills, pellets,
cylinders, trilobes, extrudates and spheres.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The catalyst of any one of claims 1 to 11 wherein said
refractory support comprises a material chosen from the group
consisting of zirconia, alumina, cordierite, mullite, magnesia,
titania, silica, beryllia, thoria, lanthania, calcium oxide, and
combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The catalyst of claim 12 wherein said refractory support
comprises partially stabilized zirconia.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The catalyst of claim 13 wherein said partially stabilised
zirconia is MgO stabilised zirconia.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A method of converting a C1-C5 hydrocarbon to a product gas
mixture comprising CO and H2, the method comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>contacting a reactant gas mixture comprising said
hydrocarbon and a source of O2 with a catalyst according to any
one of claims 1 to 15 in the reaction zone of a syngas production
reactor such that a portion of reactant gas mixture flowing over
said catalyst is in contact with said catalyst for no more than
about 200 milliseconds; and</claim-text><claim-text>maintaining autothermal net catalytic partial oxidation
promoting conditions during said contacting.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The method of claim 15 wherein said contacting comprises
contacting a reactant gas mixture comprising said hydrocarbon and
a source of oxygen with said catalyst at a contact time of less
than 50 milliseconds.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The method of claim 16 comprising a contact time of less
than 10 milliseconds.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The method of any one of claims 15 to 17 wherein said step
of maintaining said catalyst at CPOX conditions during said
contacting includes maintaining a temperature in the range of
about 350°C - 2,000°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The method of claim 18 wherein said step of maintaining
CPOX promoting conditions comprises maintaining a temperature in
the range of 450°C - 1,200°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The method of any one of claims 15 to 19 wherein said step
of maintaining CPOX promoting conditions during said contacting
includes maintaining gas pressure in the range of about 100-32,500
kPa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>The method of claim 20 wherein said step of maintaining
CPOX promoting conditions during said contacting includes
maintaining gas pressure in the range of about 200-10,000 kPa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>The method of any one of claims 15 to 21 wherein the
conversion of said hydrocarbon is greater than 70%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>The method of any one of claims 15 to 22 wherein the
selectivity for CO product is greater than 70% and the
selectivity for H2 product is greater than 70%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>The method of any one of claims 15 to 23 further comprising
mixing a methane-containing feedstock and an O2-containing
feedstock to provide a reactant gas mixture feedstock having a
carbon:oxygen molar ratio in the range of about 1.5:1 to about
3.3:1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="25"><claim-text>The method of claim 24 wherein said mixing provides a
reactant gas mixture feed having a carbon:oxygen ratio in the
range of about 1.7:1 to about 2.1:1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="26"><claim-text>The method of any one of claims 15 to 25 further comprising
combining steam and/or CO2 with said hydrocarbon feedstock.</claim-text></claim><claim num="27"><claim-text>The method of any one of claims 15 to 26 wherein said C1-C5
hydrocarbon comprises at least about 80 % methane by volume.</claim-text></claim><claim num="28"><claim-text>The method of any one of claims 15 to 27 comprising
preheating said reactant gas mixture.</claim-text></claim><claim num="29"><claim-text>The method of claim 28 comprising preheating said reactant
gas mixture to a temperature in the range of 30°C to 750°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="30"><claim-text>The method of any one of claims 15 to 29 comprising passing
said reactant gas mixture over said catalyst at a gas hourly
space velocity in the range of about 20,000 - 100,000,000 h-1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="31"><claim-text>The method of any one of claims 15 to 30 comprising
maintaining autothermal net CPOX reaction promoting conditions
during said contacting.</claim-text></claim><claim num="32"><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 15 to 31 wherein
during said contacting, said hydrocarbon and said oxygen
concentration in said reactant gas mixture feedstock is adjusted
to a carbon:oxygen ratio in the range of 1.7:1 to 2.1:1, such
that the CPOX reaction is favored.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>