<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1004682-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1004682" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26807456" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000531"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1004682-A1" status="new" fvid="22837512"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1004682</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000531</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99420222-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99420222</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991109</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-10986898-P" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>10986898</doc-number><kind>P</kind><date>19981124</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-32405999-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>32405999</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990601</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22D   1/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22D   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C21C   5/48        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C21C   5/48        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B   9/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B   9/05        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B  21/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22B  21/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B22D   1/00G1</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C21C   5/48</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B  21/06D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22B   9/05</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Gasspüleinrichtung aus monolithischer Keramik zum Einleiten von Gasen in eine Metallschmelze</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Monolithic ceramic gas diffuser for injecting gas into a molten metal bath</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Diffuseur monolithique en céramique pour l'injection par bullage de gaz dans un bain de métal en fusion</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="BE-489718-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>BE</country><doc-number>489718</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="DE-4012952-C1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>4012952</doc-number><kind>C1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0819770-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0819770</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="FR-2763079-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>FR</country><doc-number>2763079</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-59038321-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>59038321</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-63313631-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>63313631</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3881709-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3881709</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5560874-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5560874</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1992004473-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1992004473</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>LARSEN D A: "DEGASSING ALUMINUM USING STATIC FINE-PORE REFRACTORY DIFFUSERS" JOM,US,MINERALS, METALS AND MATERIALS SOCIETY, WARRENDALE, vol. 49, no. 8, 1 August 1997 (1997-08-01), pages 27-28, XP000731709 ISSN: 1047-4838</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 008, no. 126 (C-228), 13 June 1984 (1984-06-13) &amp; JP 59 038321 A (SUMITOMO KINZOKU KOGYO KK), 2 March 1984 (1984-03-02)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 013, no. 153 (M-813), 13 April 1989 (1989-04-13) &amp; JP 63 313631 A (NITTOKU FUAANESU KK), 21 December 1988 (1988-12-21)</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BLASCH PRECISION CERAMICS INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BLASCH PRECISION CERAMICS, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Blasch Precision Ceramics, Inc.</last-name><address><street>580 Broadwayoad</street><city>Albany, New York 12204</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LARSEN DAVID A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>REXFORD DONALD G</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WEBSTER EARLE R JR</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LARSEN, DAVID A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>REXFORD, DONALD G.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WEBSTER, EARLE R. JR.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>LARSEN, DAVID A.</last-name><address><street>7 Whispering Hills Drive</street><city>Clifton Park, NY 12065</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>REXFORD, DONALD G.</last-name><address><street>1623 Mariaville Scotch Church Road</street><city>Pattersonville, NY 12137</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WEBSTER, EARLE R. JR.</last-name><address><street>8 Trevor Court</street><city>Clifton Park, NY 12065</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Vuillermoz, Bruno</last-name><address><street>Cabinet Laurent &amp;amp; Charras B.P. 32 20, rue Louis Chirpaz</street><city>69131 Ecully Cédex</city><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states> </international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A monolithic, fired ceramic gas diffuser for injecting gas into a molten metal bath,
including a first portion (22,33), a second portion (21,34) integrated with the first portion, and a bore (24,32)
passing through the first portion and communicating with the second portion for supplying
gas to the second portion, wherein at least the second portion (21,34) has a network of
interconnected pores that provides preferential gas flow from the bore through the second
portion to inject gas into the molten metal bath.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="96" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no"  he="102"/><img id="img-00000002" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="ad"  file="00000002.tif"  inline="no"  he="86"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This application claims priority from U.S. Provisional Application Serial No.
60/109,868, filed November 24, 1998, the entirety of which is incorporated herein by
reference.</p> <heading><b>Background of the Invention</b> </heading> <p num="0002">The present invention relates to a monolithic ceramic gas diffuser for injecting gas
into a molten metal bath, and more particularly relates to such a diffuser that includes a
portion through which injection gas will preferentially flow.</p><p num="0003">When making metal and metal alloy products, it is often necessary to create a bath of
molten metal that will later be cast into molds of various shapes and sizes. With certain
specific alloys, such as aluminum alloys, the molten aluminum is highly sensitive to the
presence of hydrogen gas, which tends to form voids in the cast product. Additionally,
molten aluminum oxidizes freely when exposed to air, and the resultant aluminum oxide has
a density very similar to the metal itself. This results in aluminum oxide being suspended in
the melt, causing "hard spots" upon solidification, an undesirable result.</p><p num="0004">In an attempt to prevent both problems, it is conventional to inject a "cleansing gas"
such as argon, nitrogen, chlorine, or freon into the molten aluminum in the form of gas
bubbles. The hydrogen in the molten aluminum is either absorbed or attaches to the
cleansing gas bubbles, which rise to and exit from the surface of the molten aluminum.
Additionally, any aluminum oxide suspended in the molten aluminum can be floated to the
surface by the gas bubbles. This is a mechanical process, and is basically independent of
the type of gas used.</p><p num="0005">Fig. 1 shows a holding box 1 that contains molten metal 2 therein. Gas injection
nozzles or spargers 3 are located at various positions in communication with the molten
metal to inject gas, supplied from a gas supply line 4, into the molten metal. Fig. 2 shows
an example of an existing sparger that typically would be positioned in the floor of holding
box 1. The sparger 5 includes a highly permeable ceramic member 6 encased in a steel can
7 through an interposed refractory or mortar adhesive 8. A gas supply pipe 9 supplies gas to 
the permeable ceramic member 6 to inject gas into the molten metal.</p><p num="0006">The problem with the sparger shown in Fig. 2 is that it requires the presence of steel
can 7 to encase the permeable ceramic member 6 to insure that gas bubbles are injected only
through the end face of permeable ceramic member 6 into the molten metal. Consequently,
the sparger shown in Fig. 2 is relatively expensive to manufacture. Moreover, the sparger is
susceptible to cracking at the interfaces between permeable ceramic member 6, mortar 8 and
steel can 7, due to the differences in thermal expansion coefficient among the various
materials. Still further, the permeable ceramic member 6 used in such conventional spargers
have large pore size, generally greater than 30 microns in diameter, and thus the size of the
gas bubbles injected into the molten metal is relatively large. It would be preferred to inject
smaller gas bubbles as they would be more effective in removal of the hydrogen gas
contained in the molten metal, thus requiring less gas volume to accomplish degassing of
the molten metal.</p><p num="0007">Fig. 3 shows another example of a gas injection mechanism in the form of a
generally cylindrical graphite lance 10. The lance is immersed in the molten metal and gas
is introduced through the relatively large opening 11 formed in the end of the lance. The
problem with such graphite or other ceramic lances is similar to the problem associated with
the sparger shown in Fig. 2, in that it is difficult to inject small gas bubbles into the molten
metal using such a device. Moreover, graphite tends to oxidize and corrode, and is also
rather fragile; thus it requires frequent replacement.</p><p num="0008">Fig. 4 shows an example of a rotary degasser developed by Blasch Precision
Ceramics, Inc. The rotary degasser 12 includes an elongate shaft 13 having an axial bore 14
extending therethrough, and an impeller 15 integrated with one end of shaft 13. The
impeller has a plurality of blades 16 extending radially outwardly from the axis of shaft 13,
and gas ports 14a passing radially outwardly through the impeller. The rotary degasser is
immersed in molten metal and rotated by a drive member (not shown) while gas is injected
into the molten metal through ports 14a and a large opening 17 formed in the end face of
impeller 15. Rotation of the impeller facilitates mixing of the injected gas with the molten
metal. The problem with this rotary degasser, however, is that the size of the gas bubbles
introduced into the molten metal is still quite large, and thus relatively inefficient for 
degassing the molten metal.</p><p num="0009">It would be desirable to provide a gas diffuser that is (1) highly resistant to cracking
due to thermal cycling and other factors encountered during molten metal manufacturing,
(2) capable of injecting uniform, relatively small gas bubbles into a bath of molten metal,
and (3) relatively easy and inexpensive to manufacture. The gas diffusers to date, however,
have not been able to fulfill all of these requirements.</p><heading><b>Summary of the Invention</b></heading><p num="0010">It is an object of the present invention to provide a gas diffuser that overcomes all
the drawbacks associated with the prior art discussed above.</p><p num="0011">In accordance with a first object of the present invention, a monolithic, fired ceramic
gas diffuser is provided, which includes a first portion, a second portion integrated with the
first portion, and a bore passing through the second portion and communicating with the
first portion for supplying injection gas to the first portion. At least the first portion has a
network of interconnected pores that provide preferential gas flow (i.e., a path of least
resistance) through the first portion to inject gas into the molten metal bath.</p><p num="0012">The gas diffuser of the present invention is highly resistant to cracking as a result of
thermal cycling since it is produced as a monolithic ceramic body. There are no lamination
interfaces of substantially dissimilar material, such as in the sparger shown in Fig. 2, that
would invite cracking problems. Additionally, the network of interconnected pores in the
first portion of the gas diffuser can be engineered quite easily to enable the injection of very
uniform, small bubbles of gas into the molten metal. Still further, the gas diffuser of the
present invention is relatively easy and inexpensive to manufacture, as it can be produced
using conventionally available materials and conventionally recognized processing
techniques, such as those disclosed in U.S. Patent Nos. 4,246,209 and 4,569,920, the
entireties of which are incorporated herein by reference.</p><p num="0013">In accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention, the gas flow
characteristics of the first and second portions of the monolithic ceramic gas diffuser are
controlled to provide preferential gas flow through the first portion of the diffuser. More
preferably, the gas flow characteristics are controlled by varying the permeability and/or 
thickness (in the gas flow direction) of the first and second portions. It is most preferable
that the permeability of the second portion is less than the permeability of the first portion,
so that the first portion defines a so-called path of least resistance in the gas diffuser through
which the injection gas is more likely to pass. Accordingly, the specific geometry of the gas
diffuser can be selected so that the first portion thereof is located in a position that will
provide the most efficient injection of gas into the molten metal.</p><p num="0014">It is another object of the present invention to provide a monolithic, fired ceramic
rotary gas diffuser for injecting gas into a molten metal bath, which includes an elongate
shaft having an axial bore passing therethrough and an impeller integrated with one end of
the shaft. At least a portion of the impeller has a network of interconnected pores that
provide preferential gas flow (i.e., a path of least resistance) from the bore through the
impeller portion to inject gas into the molten metal bath. This embodiment of the present
invention incorporates the inventive gas diffuser into a rotary shaft/impeller configuration,
to obtain the mixing functionality that is added by an impeller configuration.</p><p num="0015">These and other objects of the present invention will become more apparent after
reading the following detailed description of the invention taken in conjunction with the
appended drawings.</p><heading><b>Brief Description of the Drawings</b></heading><p num="0016"><sl><li>Fig. 1 is a diagram showing a conventional molten metal holding box used in the
production of cast metal parts;</li><li>Fig. 2 is a cross-sectional view of a prior art sparger;</li><li>Fig. 3 is a cross-sectional view of a prior art lance;</li><li>Fig. 4 is a cross-sectional view of a rotary degasser;</li><li>Fig. 5 is a cross-sectional view of a sparger according to the present invention;</li><li>Figs. 6A and 6B are cross-sectional and end views of a rotary gas diffuser according
to the present invention;</li><li>Figs. 7A and 7B are cross-sectional and end views of an alternative rotary gas
diffuser according to the present invention;</li><li>Fig. 8 is a cross-sectional view of a lance according to the present invention; and </li><li>Fig. 9 is a cross-sectional view of an alternative sparger according to the present
invention..</li></sl></p><heading><b>Detailed Description of the Invention</b></heading><p num="0017">Fig. 5 is a cross-sectional view showing an example of the present invention in the
form of a sparger 20. The sparger generally takes the shape of a truncated cone, and is
formed as a monolithic ceramic structure including a first tip portion 21 and a second main
body portion 22 that is integrated with the bottom end region of first portion 21. A
commingled region 23 can be detected optically between the first and second portions of the
fired body, and generally is a hybrid of the two portions. There is no interfacial lamination
to speak of, however, between the two portions. A bore 24 extends through second portion
22 and communicates with first portion 21. Injection gas is supplied through bore 24 and is
ejected out of the end of sparger 20 through first portion 21.</p><p num="0018">In accordance with the present invention, the gas flow characteristics of the first 21
and second 22 portions are selected such that there is a preference for the injection gas to
flow through first portion 21 (i.e., portion 21 is a path of least resistance when compared to
portion 22). As a result, portion 22 effectively acts to form the foundation of the sparger 20
and defines a conduit (bore 24) for transporting gas to and through first portion 21.</p><p num="0019">It is preferred to control the gas flow characteristics of first portion 21 and second
portion 22 so that first portion 21 provides a path of least resistance for the gas introduced
into bore 24. One way of doing this is to control the permeability of the two portions such
that first portion 21 is substantially more permeable than second portion 22. One skilled in
the art will understand that gas flow characteristics of a ceramic body depend upon the
permeability of that body and the thickness thereof in the direction of gas flow.
Accordingly, when it is stated that first portion 21 is "more permeable" than second portion
22, this can be accomplished by varying the permeability and/or thickness (in the direction
of gas flow) of those portions. Although not absolutely necessary, it is usually the case that
first portion 21 is thinner (in the direction of gas flow) and more permeable than second
portion 22, and also has higher porosity than second portion 22.</p><p num="0020">As a result of the process used to form sparger 20, which will be discussed in more 
detail later herein, first portion 21 and second portion 22 include a network of
interconnected pores through which fluid (e.g., gas) can flow. Accordingly, while second
portion 22 may in fact be permeable, in accordance with the present invention, first portion
21 is made more permeable to provide preferential gas flow through first portion 21 as
opposed to second portion 22.</p><p num="0021">Any known ceramic material could be used to make the gas diffuser shown in Fig. 5.
It is desirable, however, that the material have sufficient refractory properties and be
substantially non-reactive with the molten metal with which it will contact. Examples of
ceramic materials that could be used include alumina, silica, silicon carbide, magnesia,
alumina magnesia spinel, aluminum titanate, zirconia, mullite, sillimanite, cordierite and
composites and mixtures thereof. Again, the specific material selected will depend largely
upon the molten metal with which the part will be used.</p><p num="0022">Since these types of gas diffusers are considered consumable components regardless
of the materials used to form them, and thus will have a tendency to chip or break over time,
it is preferred to make the diffuser from a ceramic material having a lower density than that
of the molten metal with which it will be used. This will ensure that any parts of the gas
diffuser that might chip or break during use would float to the top of the molten metal for
easy removal (along with alumina precipitates in the case of an aluminum melt).</p><p num="0023">The gas diffuser shown in Fig. 5 can be formed in accordance with conventional
ceramic processing techniques, such as those disclosed in U.S. Patent Nos. 4,246,209 and
4,569,920. However, one exemplary method for forming the gas diffuser shown in Fig. 5
will now be explained.</p><p num="0024">Two ceramic batches are prepared to form each of the respective first and second
portions 21 and 22. While not critical, it is preferred that the compositions of the two
batches are substantially identical except for the addition of a standard pore forming agent
(and sometimes additional water or aqueous liquid) in the first batch that will be used to
form first portion 21. The amount of pore forming agent included in the first batch is also
not critical, provided that the first portion 21 of the resultant fired part has adequate strength
to withstand gas injection pressures and defines a gas path of least resistance when
compared to the second portion 22 of that part. </p><p num="0025">Once the two batch materials have been separately mixed into a wet, thixotropic
state, the first batch material is deposited into a lower, closed end of a mold that effectively
defines a negative impression of the gas diffuser shown in Fig. 5. How much of the first
batch material added to the mold at this stage will be determined by how thick the first
portion 21 of the final product is intended to be. The second batch material used to form
second portion 22 is then deposited on top of the first batch material already in the mold and
around a columnar shaped member that, when removed after casting, will define bore 24 of
the gas diffuser. Of course, the first and second batch materials do not have to be deposited
in the mold in this order; the specific geometry of the cast part and the respective positions
of the first and second portions will dictate the order in which the batch materials are
introduced into the mold.</p><p num="0026">It is preferred that the mold is vibrated while the batch materials are being added
thereto and/or after both batch materials have been introduced into the mold, to facilitate
commingling of the two batch materials at least in the interface region therebetween. This
will insure that a good bond is created between the two portions during subsequent firing,
and thus insure the absence of any structurally weak interfacial joint between the two
portions.</p><p num="0027">After the batch materials have been cast into the mold and vibrated as discussed
above, the cast product is further processed and fired using conventional techniques, such as
those disclosed in the above-referenced patents. If a freeze casting process is to be used to
form the gas diffuser, then it may be desirable to deposit the first batch material in the mold,
freeze that portion of the casting until it becomes partially rigid (but not fully solidified),
and then vibratory cast the second batch material to form second portion 22. This is one
way by which the amount of commingling between the raw materials for first portion 21
and the second portion 22 can be controlled. That is, the first batch material that forms first
portion 21 will not commingle as easily if it is in a partially frozen state, as would be the
case if this alternative method were employed. The amount of commingling between the
two batch materials that is desired, or that can be tolerated, can be controlled in this manner.
In the case of a relatively thin first portion 21, it may be necessary to employ this alternative
method to prevent complete commingling of the two batch materials during the vibratory 
casting process. That is, if the thickness of first portion 21, and thus the amount of the raw
material added to the mold to form that portion, is relatively small compared to the
thickness of second portion 22, and thus the amount of raw material cast into the mold to
form that portion, the action of vibrating the mold could easily consume the entirety of the
first batch material intended to form first portion 21. In such a case, it would be preferable
to freeze the first batch material that is to form first portion 21 before vibratory casting the
second batch material that is to form second portion 22.</p><p num="0028">The formation techniques discussed above are effective to provide a monolithic
ceramic gas diffuser having first and second portions of substantially different gas
permeability, while avoiding any significant interfacial laminations that might crack during
thermal cycling. The integrity of the commingled region between first portion 21 and
second portion 22 in the fired ceramic product can be improved by using the same ceramic
raw materials in the batch compositions for the first 21 and second 22 portions. The only
difference, again, would be that the first batch material used to form first portion 21 would
have a higher content of pore forming agent (and sometimes additional water or aqueous
liquid) so that, when fired, the first portion will allow the passage of gas therethrough more
readily than through second portion 22. To the extent the fired ceramic part will not be
subjected to significant thermal cycling, it could be possible to employ dissimilar
compositions when forming the first portion 21 and second portion 22. In this regard, the
materials used for each portion should be selected with a view to matching the thermal
expansion coefficients of each material sufficiently enough to prevent cracking and/or
delamination at the commingled region between the two portions.</p><p num="0029">While there is no particular limit on the permeability of the first portion 21 and
second portion 22, from a practical standpoint the second portion 22 should have a
permeability of 10 centidarcies or less, and the first portion 21 should have a permeability of
5 centidarcies or more, the important point being that the difference between the gas flow
characteristics through each portion is substantial enough to provide a preferential gas path
through first portion 21 as opposed to second portion 22.</p><p num="0030">Although there is also no particular limitation on the size of the pores contained in
the first portion 21 and second portion 22, from a practical standpoint the pore size in the 
first portion 21 should range from 3 microns to 25 microns in diameter to provide reduced
gas bubble size in application. Pore size is not critical in the second portion 22 as long as
there is preferential gas path through first portion 21 as opposed to second portion 22. If the
pore size is the same in both portions, the first portion 21 should contain a higher volume of
open porosity to insure preferential gas flow therethrough.</p><p num="0031">Figs. 6A and 6B are cross-sectional and end views, respectively, of a rotary gas
diffuser 30 according to the present invention. The rotary gas diffuser includes an elongate
shaft 31 having an axial bore 32 passing therethrough. An impeller 33 is integrated to one
end of shaft 31. A surface portion 34 of impeller 33 has gas flow characteristics that, when
compared to the gas flow characteristics of the remaining portions of the rotary gas diffuser,
provide preferential gas flow therethrough from axial bore 32 into the molten metal bath
with which the rotary gas diffuser is used. Aside from the geometric differences between
the sparger shown in Fig. 5 and the rotary gas diffuser shown in Fig. 6, all of the features
described above with respect to the sparger shown in Fig. 5 apply equally as well to the
rotary gas diffuser shown in Figs. 6A and 6B.</p><p num="0032">Figs. 7A and 7B are cross-sectional and end views of an alternative rotary gas
diffuser according to the present invention. Like reference numerals are used in Figs. 6 and
7 to designate like parts. The end face 34 of the rotary gas diffuser 30 shown in Fig. 7A
takes the shape of a truncated cone, at least a portion of which defines a path of least
resistance for injecting gas into the molten metal. Since rotary gas diffusers are typically
oriented vertically, there is a tendency for gas bubbles to collect on the planar bottom face
of the impeller shown in Fig. 6A. Such trapped gas agglomerates to form large-sized
bubbles which periodically separate from the end face of the gas diffuser and mix with the
molten metal. The introduction of such large-sized gas bubbles into the molten metal makes
the overall degassing process less efficient, as described above in connection with prior art
gas diffusers. The shape of the end face of the rotary gas diffuser in Fig. 7 is designed to
minimize the area on which gas bubbles could agglomerate. Accordingly, the small-sized
gas bubbles made available by the present invention can be better maintained.</p><p num="0033">Fig. 8 is a cross-sectional view showing a generally cylindrical lance according to
the present invention. Like reference numerals have been used in Figs. 5 and 8 to designate 
like features of the respective structures. Aside from differences in geometric size and
shape, the features in connection with the sparger of Fig. 5 apply equally as well to the lance
shown in Fig. 8.</p><p num="0034">Fig. 9 is a cross-sectional view showing a different shape that could be used to form
a sparger like the one shown in Fig. 5. The sparger shown in Fig. 9 could be any shape
(e.g., circular, square, etc.) in radial cross-section. Like reference numerals have been used
in Figs. 5 and 9 to designate like parts.</p><p num="0035">The structure of the presently claimed gas diffuser overcomes all of the drawbacks
associated with the prior art discussed above and also enables the formation of smaller,
more uniform gas bubbles to be injected into the molten metal. As a result, the volume of
gas necessary to accomplish the same degassing objectives sought by the prior art devices is
substantially reduced. For example, it has been estimated that the rotary degasser shown in
Fig. 4 would need approximately five times the volume of injection gas to accomplish the
same degassing result that can be accomplished using the rotary degasser shown in Fig. 6.
Accordingly, not only is the rotary degasser of the present invention more durable and easier
and cheaper to manufacture than conventional gas diffusers, it also provides a substantial
savings in the amount of injection gas that is required to degas a given molten metal batch.</p><p num="0036">The following examples provide more detail about specific embodiments of the
present invention. One skilled in the art, however, will understand that various changes and
modifications could be made without departing from the spirit of the present invention.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 1:</u></b></heading><p num="0037">For application in degassing of molten aluminum, a monolithic, fired ceramic
diffuser was formed in the shape of a lance tube, substantially as shown in Fig. 8. The
method employed will be explained.</p><p num="0038">A metal mold was prepared. It was a negative impression of a lance tube of nominal
size of 2 inches outside diameter x 0.5 inches thick x 24 inches long, with one end open and
the other end closed with a rounded shape. Two individual batches of ceramic mix were
batched and mixed separately. The two batches were viscous, similar in consistency to wet
concrete mix or slightly thicker, and both included silicon carbide, alumina, boron nitride, 
silica sol, and lipolysilicate. Also, in the case of the first batch used to form first portion 21,
organic fillers and additional aqueous silica sol were included in the mixture to impart
additional porosity and permeability. The second batch was used to form second portion 22
and the first batch was used to form first portion 21.</p><p num="0039">More specifically, the composition of the first batch included 70.5 wt% SiC grains
(refractory grade), 5.0 wt% tabular alumina grains, 24.0 wt% reactive alumina powder, 0.5
wt% boron nitride powder, 21.2 wt% silica sol, 0.10 wt% lithium polysilicate and 1.8 wt %
organic pore former, and the composition of the second batch included 70.5 wt% SiC grains
(refractory grade), 5.0 wt% tabular alumina grains, 24.0 wt% reactive alumina powder, 0.5
wt% boron nitride powder, 10.5 wt% silica sol and 0.10 wt% lithium polysilicate.</p><p num="0040">It was calculated that, for the geometry of this lance and based upon the
density of the first batch, it would require about 480 grams of wet mix to fill the lower 4 to
6 inches of length of the mold to form the first end portion 21. Thus, this amount of wet
ceramic was weighed out and placed in a container. The mold was then rigged for
vibration, and the wet first batch was cast into the mold while it was being vibrated.
Immediately following the placement of the pre-measured amount of first batch into the
mold, a predetermined amount of second batch (in a wet state) was added directly on top of
the first batch while the mold was still under vibration. Once the mold was filled, the
vibration was discontinued, and the filled mold was refrigerated in a freezing environment
until solidification occurred (in accordance with the method described in US Patents
4,246,209 and 4,569,920). The filled mold was removed from the freezing environment and
disassembled. The frozen ceramic shape was warmed to thaw and air dried, followed by
firing in a kiln at 1700 °F for 1-2 hours hold time to form a monolithic ceramic in the shape
of a lance tube. Upon inspection, there was no discernible joint, seam or crack(s) between
first portion 21 and second portion 22.</p><p num="0041">The open end of the lance tube was connected to a regulated air line with
approximately 3 to 5 psi pressure, and then totally immersed in an aquarium of water, and
the air bubbles observed. The bubble pattern showed that nearly 100% of the air bubbles
were being emitted from the first portion 21 near the closed end of the tube in the last 6 
inches (approximately) of length of the closed end. The observed bubbles were uniform and
relatively small in size.</p><p num="0042">After removal from the aquarium, this ceramic tube was thoroughly dried, and then
cut lengthwise in half. The cut tube half-sections were examined under an optical
microscope, and no discernible cracks, joints, or seams were observed: the body was
monolithic. There was, however, a distinguishable "commingled" ceramic region between
the first portion 21 and the second portion 22, which comprised about 1 to 1.5 inches of the
total tube length. This commingled region had a combination of the microstructures
resulting from both the first batch material (used to form first portion 21) and the second
batch material (used to form second portion 22).</p><p num="0043">Fired sample parts made from both the first and second batch compositions were
tested to confirm resistance to molten aluminum alloy #7075, with results indicating that
these refractory compositions were resistant to this alloy. Additionally, the first and second
portions of the fired product were tested, and the nominal properties for these compositions,
as fired, including modules of rupture, bulk density, apparent porosity, permeability,
thermal expansion coefficient, and calculated chemical analysis, were as follows:
<sl><li><u style="single">First Portion:</u><dl compact="compact" tsize="48"><dt>Calculated chemical analysis:</dt><dd>65.2 % silicon carbide

27.3 % alumina

6.7 % silica

0.5 % boron nitride</dd><dt>Bulk density:</dt><dd>2.15 g/cc</dd><dt>Modulus of Rupture (room temperature):</dt><dd>9.4 MPa</dd><dt>Apparent porosity:</dt><dd>31.2%</dd><dt>Permeability:</dt><dd>14.5 centidarcies</dd><dt>Median Pore Diameter:</dt><dd>5.3 microns</dd><dt>Reversible Linear Thermal Expansion Coefficient:</dt><dd>5.5 x 10<sup>-6</sup>/degree C</dd></dl></li><li><u style="single">Second Portion:</u><dl compact="compact" tsize="48"><dt>Calculated chemical analysis:</dt><dd>67.3 % silicon carbide

28.2 % alumina

3.8 % silica

0.5 % boron nitride</dd><dt>Bulk density:</dt><dd>2.57 g/cc</dd><dt>Modulus of Rupture (room temperature):</dt><dd>30.3 MPa</dd><dt>Apparent porosity:</dt><dd>20.3 %</dd><dt>Permeability:</dt><dd>0.5 centidarcies (note: significantly lower in permeability
than first portion)</dd><dt>Reversible Linear Thermal Expansion Coefficient:</dt><dd>5.5 x 10<sup>-6</sup>/degree C</dd></dl></li></sl></p><p num="0044">This preformed monolithic composite ceramic lance would be used in application
for degassing of molten aluminum. It would be used by applying pressurized argon (or
other suitable cleansing gas) into the inlet of the open end of the tube, and then immersing
the closed end into the molten aluminum. The cleansing gas bubbles would be uniform and
small, and would provide effective degassing with minimal gas usage.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 2:</u></b></heading><p num="0045">The same procedure was used to make the same shape as specified in Example 1,
with one procedural exception: After the pre-measured amount of wet first batch material
was placed in the vibrating mold to form first portion 21 (in a green state), the vibration was
turned-off and the partially filled mold was placed in the freezing environment until the wet
mix became more rigid in the mold but not solid. The mold was then removed from the
freezing environment, the vibration was again started on the mold, and wet second batch
material was added directly on top of the wet (actually somewhat rigid) first batch material
already in the mold. Once the mold was filled, the vibration was discontinued, and the filled
mold was refrigerated in a freezing environment until solidification occurred (in accordance
with the method described in US Patents 4,246,209 and 4,569,920). The remaining process 
for this example was the same as depicted in Example 1. It was also tested in an aquarium
filled with water, and the results were the same as in Example 1. Upon comparison of the
microstructures of the fired product resulting from each Example, however, it was seen that
the product resulting from Example 2 had a thinner commingled region as a result of the
freezing step employed after casting of first portion 21.</p><p num="0046">While the present invention has been particularly shown and described with
reference to the preferred mode as illustrated in the drawing, it will be understood by one
skilled in the art that various changes in detail may be effected therein without departing
from the spirit and scope of the invention as defined by the claims. For example, while it is
preferred to use pore forming agents (and sometimes additional water or aqueous liquid) to
control the gas flow characteristics of the second portion of the gas diffuser, it is possible to
rely instead upon other factors, such as differences in particle size, to establish the requisite
preferential gas flow through the second portion.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A monolithic, fired ceramic gas diffuser for injecting gas into a molten metal
bath, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first portion;</claim-text><claim-text>a second portion integrated with said first portion; and</claim-text><claim-text>a bore passing through said second portion and communicating with said first
portion for supplying gas to said first portion;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein at least said first portion has a network of interconnected pores that provides
preferential gas flow from said bore through said first portion to inject gas into the molten
metal bath.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic gas diffuser of claim 1, wherein the gas flow
characteristics of said first and second portions are controlled to provide preferential gas
flow through said first portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic gas diffuser of claim 2, wherein said gas flow
characteristics are controlled by varying at least one of the permeability and gas flow
thickness of said first and second portions.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic gas diffuser of claim 1, wherein the permeability of
said first portion is greater than the permeability of said second portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic gas diffuser of claim 1, wherein the porosity of said
first portion is greater than the porosity of said second portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic gas diffuser of claim 1, wherein the gas flow
thickness of said first portion is less than the gas flow thickness of said second portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic gas diffuser of claim 1, wherein the density of the
ceramic material used to form the gas diffuser is less than that of the molten metal with
which it will be used.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A monolithic, fired ceramic rotary gas diffuser for injecting gas into a molten
metal bath, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an elongate shaft having an axial bore passing therethrough; and</claim-text><claim-text>an impeller integrated with one end of said shaft, wherein at least a portion of said
impeller has a network of interconnected pores that provides preferential gas flow from said
bore through said portion of said impeller to inject gas into the molten metal bath.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic rotary gas diffuser of claim 8, wherein the gas flow
characteristics of said elongate shaft and said impeller are controlled to provide preferential
gas flow through said portion of said impeller.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic rotary gas diffuser of claim 9, wherein said gas flow
characteristics are controlled by varying at least one of the permeability and gas flow
thickness of said elongate shaft and said portion of said impeller.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic rotary gas diffuser of claim 8, wherein the
permeability of said elongate shaft is less than the permeability of said portion of said
impeller.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic rotary gas diffuser of claim 8, wherein the porosity
of said elongate shaft is less than the porosity of said portion of said impeller.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic rotary gas diffuser of claim 8, wherein the gas flow
thickness of said elongate shaft is greater than the gas flow thickness of said portion of said
impeller.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic rotary gas diffuser of claim 8, wherein the density of
the ceramic material used to form the gas diffuser is less than that of the molten metal with
which it will be used.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic rotary gas diffuser of claim 8, wherein said impeller
has a bottom end face that encompasses at least said network of interconnected pores, and
said bottom end face is substantially non-perpendicular to a longitudinal axis of said
elongate shaft.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The monolithic ceramic rotary gas diffuser of claim 15, wherein said bottom
end face extends in a direction away from said elongate shaft.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A method of forming a monolithic, fired ceramic gas diffuser for injecting
gas into a molten metal bath, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>preparing a first batch material that will form, when fired, a first region of the gas
diffuser having first gas flow characteristics;</claim-text><claim-text>depositing the first batch material in a mold to define a first portion of a casting;</claim-text><claim-text>preparing a second batch material that will form, when fired, a second region of the
gas diffuser having second gas flow characteristics different from said first gas flow
characteristics;</claim-text><claim-text>depositing the second batch material in the mold, in contact with the first batch
material, to form a second portion of the casting; and</claim-text><claim-text>firing the casting to form the monolithic, fired ceramic gas diffuser.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The method of claim 17, wherein the first and second gas flow characteristics
are controlled to provide preferential gas flow through the first portion of the monolithic,
fired ceramic gas diffuser.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The method of claim 18, wherein the gas flow characteristics are controlled
by varying at least one of the permeability and gas flow thickness of the first and second
portions of the monolithic, fired ceramic gas diffuser.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The method of claim 17, wherein the permeability of the first portion is
greater than the permeability of the second portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>The method of claim 17, wherein the porosity of the first portion is greater
than the porosity of the second portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>The method of claim 17, wherein the gas flow thickness of the first portion is
less than the gas flow thickness of the second portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>The method of claim 17, wherein the mold is vibrated at least while the
second batch material is deposited therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>The method of claim 17, wherein the first portion of the casting is partially
frozen before the second batch material is cast into the mold.</claim-text></claim><claim num="25"><claim-text>The method of claim 24, wherein the entire casting is frozen before being
fired.</claim-text></claim><claim num="26"><claim-text>The method of claim 17, wherein the first and second gas flow characteristics
are controlled to provide preferential gas flow through the second portion of the monolithic,
fired ceramic gas diffuser.</claim-text></claim><claim num="27"><claim-text>The method of claim 26, wherein the gas flow characteristics are controlled
by varying at least one of the permeability and gas flow thickness of the first and second
portions of the monolithic, fired ceramic gas diffuser.</claim-text></claim><claim num="28"><claim-text>The method of claim 17, wherein the permeability of the second portion is
greater than the permeability of the first portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="29"><claim-text>The method of claim 17, wherein the porosity of the second portion is greater
than the porosity of the first portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="30"><claim-text>The method of claim 17, wherein the gas flow thickness of the second
portion is less than the gas flow thickness of the first portion.</claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure num="1"><img id="img-00200001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00200001.tif" inline="no" he="128"/></figure><figure num="2"><img id="img-00210001" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00210001.tif" inline="no" he="142"/></figure><figure num="3"><img id="img-00220001" orientation="unknown" wi="94" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00220001.tif" inline="no" he="135"/></figure><figure num="4"><img id="img-00230001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00230001.tif" inline="no" he="115"/></figure><figure num="5"><img id="img-00240001" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00240001.tif" inline="no" he="134"/></figure><figure num="6"><img id="img-00250001" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00250001.tif" inline="no" he="182"/></figure><figure num="7"><img id="img-00260001" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00260001.tif" inline="no" he="201"/></figure><figure num="8"><img id="img-00270001" orientation="unknown" wi="118" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00270001.tif" inline="no" he="133"/></figure><figure num="9"><img id="img-00280001" orientation="unknown" wi="118" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00280001.tif" inline="no" he="99"/></figure></drawings><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="173" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="271" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="176" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="269" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90020001" orientation="portrait" wi="179" status="new" file="90020001.tif" he="270" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>