<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1624089-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1624089" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="35005835" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20060208"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1624089-A1" status="new" fvid="24549831"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1624089</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20060208</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-05254297-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>05254297</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20050708</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-88704504-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>88704504</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040708</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  53/48        20060101ALI20051017BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  53/48        20060101CLI20051017BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01D  53/52        20060101ALI20051017BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23F  11/08        20060101ALI20051017BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23F  11/08        20060101CLI20051017BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23F  11/10        20060101AFI20051017BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23F  11/10        20060101CLI20051017BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23F  11/12        20060101ALI20051017BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23F  11/14        20060101ALI20051017BHEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C02F   1/72</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23F  11/08</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23F  11/12A</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Verhinderung von Geruchsbildung durch Schwefelwasserstoff in wässrigen Medien</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method of preventing hydrogen sulfide odor generation in an aqueous medium</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé de prévention de la formation d'odeur due à l'hydrogène sulfuré dans un milieu aqueux</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="FR-2705957-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>FR</country><doc-number>2705957</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-1991765-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>1991765</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-2426318-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>2426318</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-2606873-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>2606873</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3459852-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3459852</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3514410-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3514410</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3585069-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3585069</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3669613-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3669613</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4220550-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4220550</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4289639-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4289639</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4310435-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4310435</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5405531-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5405531</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6666975-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6666975</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1992001481-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1992001481</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998051625-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998051625</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE COMPENDEX [Online] ENGINEERING INFORMATION, INC., NEW YORK, NY, US; JACQUEZ RICARDO B ET AL: "Biochemical control of sulfide production in wastewater collection systems" XP002348427 Database accession no. EIX93031396107</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEN ELECTRIC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>General Electric Company</last-name><address><street>One River Road</street><city>Schenectady, New York 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHEN ZHUO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>RITZ DAVID B</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SEGAL WENDY</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WHITEKETTLE WILSON K</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHEN, ZHUO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>RITZ, DAVID B.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SEGAL, WENDY</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WHITEKETTLE, WILSON K.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CHEN, ZHUO</last-name><address><street>1498 Woodview Road Yardley</street><city>Pennsylvania 19067</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>RITZ, DAVID B.</last-name><address><street>716 Quail Circle Hatfield</street><city>Pennsylvania 19440</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SEGAL, WENDY</last-name><address><street>6 Quincy Manor Lane Burlington</street><city>New Jersey 08016</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WHITEKETTLE, WILSON K.</last-name><address><street>2150 Cambridge Circle Jamison</street><city>Pennsylvania 18929</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Szary, Anne Catherine, Dr.</last-name><address><street>London Patent Operation General Electric International, Inc. 15 John Adam Street</street><city>London WC2N 6LU</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IS</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country> <country>LT</country><country>LU</country><country>LV</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country> <country>PL</country> <country>PT</country> <country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="pa01">The present invention relates to a fast acting chemical treatment for preventing the generation of hydrogen sulfide odor by the microbial metabolic activities of sulfate reducing bacteria. Specifically, the invention relates to a method for preventing hydrogen sulfide odor generation in a sulfur species-containing aqueous medium, which includes adding to the aqueous medium a sulfide scavenger treatment selected from the group consisting of glyoxal, triazine, n-chlorosuccinimide, and mixtures thereof.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="p0001">The present invention relates to a fast-acting, aqueous phase chemical treatment for preventing the generation of hydrogen sulfide odor in an aqueous medium.</p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="p0002">The reactivity between various aldehydes and sulfidic compounds (H<sub>2</sub>S, mercaptans, etc.) has been known in the art for some time. For example, Marks in U.S. Pat. No. 1,991,765 discloses a method of reacting hydrogen sulfide and an aldehyde in an aqueous solution having a pH between 2 and 12 at a temperature between substantially 20°C and 100°C. After Marks' disclosure in 1935, many patents appeared disclosing the use of aldehydes during acid cleaning of iron sulfide deposits, including U.S. Pat. Nos. 2,606,873; 3,514,410; 3,585,069; 3,669,613; 4,220,550; 4,289,639; and 4,310,435. Consumption of the hydrogen sulfide liberated by acidification of sulfide-containing deposits increased the safety of such operations. Decreased corrosivity of the aldehyde-containing acids is also disclosed in the prior art, sometimes with the addition of ancillary corrosion inhibitors.</p><p num="p0003">Menaul in U.S. Pat. No. 2,426,318 discloses a method of inhibiting the corrosive action of natural gas and oil containing soluble sulfides on metals by utilizing an aldehyde and preferably formaldehyde.</p><p num="p0004">Roehm in U.S. Pat. No. 3,459,852 discloses a process for deodorizing and reducing the biochemical demand of an aqueous solution which contains at least one compound of hydrogen sulfide and compounds containing the -SH group. Roehm's process comprises mixing the solution with a sulfide-active alpha, beta unsaturated aldehyde or ketone in an amount sufficient to form sulfur-containing reaction product of the<!-- EPO <DP n="2"> --> sulfide active aldehyde or ketone. Two such sulfide-active compounds disclosed by Roehm are acrolein and 3-buten-2-one.</p><p num="p0005">Formaldehyde, formaldehyde with SO<sub>3</sub><sup>2-</sup>, and acrolein are all commercially used hydrogen sulfide (H<sub>2</sub>S) scavengers. However, formaldehyde produces a solid reaction product and reverts readily to formaldehyde and free H<sub>2</sub>S. Acrolein is more expensive than formaldehyde as well as extremely toxic and dangerous to handle. The use of SO<sub>3</sub><sup>2-</sup> with formaldehyde eliminates the re-release of H<sub>2</sub>S but not solids formation.</p><p num="p0006">Despite the prior art approaches to H<sub>2</sub>S scavenging, the provision of a product that can prevent the H<sub>2</sub>S formation microbiologically (rather than removal of H<sub>2</sub>S after it is formed) is highly desirable since it is a more effective way of controlling H<sub>2</sub>S odor and preventing corrosion and related problems. Existing H<sub>2</sub>S prevention methods that include utilizing biocides to kill microbes such as Sulfate Reducing Bacteria (SRBs) are non-selective and will kill other microorganisms, and may be detrimental to the wastewater remediation processes. These concerns are effectively negated by the utilization of the hydrogen sulfide prevention methods of the present invention, often combined with a H<sub>2</sub>S scavenging component chemical.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="p0007">The present invention relates to a fast acting chemical treatment for preventing the generation of hydrogen sulfide odor by the microbial metabolic activities of sulfate reducing bacteria. Specifically, the invention relates to a method for preventing hydrogen sulfide odor generation in a sulfur species-containing aqueous medium, which comprises adding to the aqueous medium an effective amount for the purpose of a sulfide scavenger treatment selected from the group consisting of glyoxal, triazine, n-chlorosuccinimide, and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="p0008">The present invention further relates to a method for controlling corrosion in a hydrogen sulfide-containing aqueous medium, which method comprises adding to the aqueous medium an effective amount for the purpose of the treatments noted above.<!-- EPO <DP n="3"> --></p><heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading><p num="p0009">The present invention utilizes chemicals which can act as redox potential buffers to treat a liquid medium containing microorganisms (such as but not limited to sulfate reducing bacteria, or SRB), which can generate H<sub>2</sub>S odor by converting sulfur species of higher oxidation states to sulfides (S<sup>2-</sup>). By the addition of a small but effective amount of such agents to the liquid (e.g., wastewater, cooling water or water/hydrocarbon emulsion) medium, the sulfide is not microbiologically produced. These agents are introduced in two different ways (alone or in combination) in order to maintain the system redox potential at a level which is less favorable for the microbials to produce H<sub>2</sub>S. They function to: (1) quickly scavenge sulfide species generated so that the system redox potential will not further decrease as a result of S<sup>2-</sup> production; and (2) provide additional redox potential adjustment/maintenance by introducing mild oxidant and/or alternative nutrient sources for the microorganisms in the system.</p><p num="p0010">Since H<sub>2</sub>S is a highly corrosive gas, preventing H<sub>2</sub>S from forming in systems such as cooling systems and storage tanks also provides an effective means of corrosion control. Further, in a preferred embodiment, the present invention relates to a method for preventing hydrogen sulfide odor generation in a hydrogen sulfide-containing aqueous medium, which comprises adding to the aqueous medium an effective amount for the purpose of a combination of (a) glyoxal and (b) a metal nitrate compound. Such materials, in a weight ratio of (a) to (b) of from about 1:3 to 1000:1, may be added to the aqueous medium in need of treatment. About 10 ppm of the treatment is preferably added to the aqueous medium, with an amount of treatment of from about 2-6 ppm being particularly preferred.</p><p num="p0011">It has been found that the treatment of the present invention is effective and fast-acting in preventing the generation of hydrogen sulfide odor in an aqueous medium with a pH of from about 6.5 to 8. The preferred nitrate compound is magnesium nitrate, or Mg(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>. A ratio of components (a) to (b) of about 3:1 is particularly preferred.<!-- EPO <DP n="4"> --></p><p num="p0012">The invention will be further illustrated by the following examples, which are included as being illustrations of the invention and which should not be construed as limiting the scope thereof.</p><heading>Examples</heading><p num="p0013">The test protocol was as follows: 100 mL serum bottles were filled with synthetic nutrient medium, then stoppered, capped, and autoclaved, and allowed to cool to at least 35°C. Using a 1 mL syringe with needle, the treatment was added at desired dosages to prepared serum bottles (triplicates of each dosage). No treatment was added for baseline controls. At least 6 baseline serum bottles were used. Using a 1 mL syringe with needle, 0.1 mL of prepared culture was added to each serum bottle.</p><p num="p0014">Next, a 10<sup>10</sup> cells/ml concentration of the sulfate reducers was prepared (using autoclaved synthetic nutrient medium) inside an anaerobic chamber. Using a 1 ml syringe with needle, 0.1 ml of the prepared sulfate reducers culture was added to each serum bottle. The bottles were then incubated at the desired temperature.</p><p num="p0015">The baseline dissolved sulfide levels were then measured to determine if the samples were ready for efficacy analysis. Using a 30 mL syringe with needle, 30 mL of sample was removed from each serum bottle. About 25 mL of the sample was added to a 30 mL bottle containing 0.125 mL zinc acetate solution, followed by adding 1 mL of 1N NaOH. The sulfide in the fixed sample was then measured. The remaining 5 mL of sample in the syringe was used for pH determination. Separate field studies were also conducted.</p><p num="p0016">As shown in Table I below, the treatments of the present invention are non-biocidal in nature, i.e., antimicrobial activities are not irreversibly affected after treatment. Furthermore, the treatments of the present invention do not result in a significant alteration of medium pH at appropriate dosages. Note that at application dosages for all chemical treatments listed, approximately 100% inhibition of H<sub>2</sub>S production was achieved (Glyoxal at 40% actives tested throughout).<!-- EPO <DP n="5"> --><tables id="tabl0001" num="0001"><table frame="all"><title>Table I - Effect of treatment on medium pH and toxicity</title><tgroup cols="5" rowsep="1" colsep="1"><colspec colwidth="33mm" colnum="1" colsep="1" colname="col1"/><colspec colwidth="33mm" colnum="2" colsep="1" colname="col2"/><colspec colwidth="34mm" colnum="3" colsep="1" colname="col3"/><colspec colwidth="34mm" colnum="4" colsep="1" colname="col4"/><colspec colwidth="34mm" colnum="5" colsep="1" colname="col5"/><thead><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Chemical Treatment</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">Scavenger Dosage (ppm active)</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">Medium pH after Treatment</entry><entry nameend="col4" align="left" namest="col4" valign="top">SRB Growth after Treatment</entry><entry nameend="col5" align="left" namest="col5" valign="top">PetriFilm Count after Treatment</entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">None</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">0</entry><entry nameend="col3" char="." align="char" charoff="43" namest="col3" valign="top">6.5</entry><entry nameend="col4" align="left" namest="col4" valign="top">10<sup>8</sup></entry><entry nameend="col5" align="left" namest="col5" valign="top">5.2x10<sup>8</sup></entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Glyoxal</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">8</entry><entry nameend="col3" char="." align="char" charoff="43" namest="col3" valign="top">6.5</entry><entry nameend="col4" align="left" namest="col4" valign="top">10<sup>8</sup></entry><entry nameend="col5" align="left" namest="col5" valign="top">8.3x10<sup>8</sup></entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Glyoxal:Mg(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> (3:1 ratio)</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">8</entry><entry nameend="col3" char="." align="char" charoff="43" namest="col3" valign="top">6.5</entry><entry nameend="col4" align="left" namest="col4" valign="top">10<sup>8</sup></entry><entry nameend="col5" align="left" namest="col5" valign="top">6.1x10<sup>8</sup></entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Triazine</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">8</entry><entry nameend="col3" char="." align="char" charoff="43" namest="col3" valign="top">6.5</entry><entry nameend="col4" align="left" namest="col4" valign="top">10<sup>8</sup></entry><entry nameend="col5" align="left" namest="col5" valign="top">5.5x10<sup>8</sup></entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Glutaraldehyde (registered biocide)</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">200</entry><entry nameend="col3" char="." align="char" charoff="43" namest="col3" valign="top">7.5</entry><entry nameend="col4" align="left" namest="col4" valign="top">0</entry><entry nameend="col5" align="left" namest="col5" valign="top">0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="p0017">As further shown in Table II below, the sulfide scavenger activity of the present invention is also effective in corrosion control.
<tables id="tabl0002" num="0002"><table frame="all"><title>Table II - Effect of treatment on corrosion rate reduction</title><tgroup cols="4" rowsep="1" colsep="1"><colspec colwidth="35mm" colnum="1" colsep="1" colname="col1"/><colspec colwidth="50mm" colnum="2" colsep="1" colname="col2"/><colspec colwidth="35mm" colnum="3" colsep="1" colname="col3"/><colspec colwidth="46mm" colnum="4" colsep="1" colname="col4"/><thead><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Corrosion Coupon</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">Treatment Dosage Glyoxal:Mg(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> (3:1 ratio) (ppm)</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">Corrosion Rate (mpy)</entry><entry nameend="col4" align="left" namest="col4" valign="top">Corrosion Rate Reduction (%)</entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Mild Steel</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">0</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">54</entry><entry nameend="col4" align="left" namest="col4" valign="top">-</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Pre-treated Mild Steel</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">0</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">46</entry><entry nameend="col4" align="left" namest="col4" valign="top">-</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Mild Steel</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">10</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">3.2</entry><entry nameend="col4" char="." align="char" charoff="47" namest="col4"  valign="top">94.1</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Pre-treated Mild Steel</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left"  namest="col2"  valign="top">10</entry><entry nameend="col3"  align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">3.5</entry><entry nameend="col4" char="." align="char" charoff="47" namest="col4" valign="top">92.4</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="p0018">As shown in Table III, the combination of sulfide scavenger (e.g., glyoxal) and nitrate provided enhanced H<sub>2</sub>S odor control at very low dosages. Note that nitrate compounds alone at the same application dosages resulted in no appreciable odor control effect.<!-- EPO <DP n="6"> --><tables id="tabl0003" num="0003"><table frame="all"><title>Table III - Effectiveness of different scavenger blends on H<sub>2</sub>S inhibition using real municipal wastewater</title><tgroup cols="3" rowsep="1" colsep="1"><colspec colwidth="82mm" colnum="1" colsep="1" colname="col1"/><colspec colwidth="49mm" colnum="2" colsep="1" colname="col2"/><colspec colwidth="36mm" colnum="3" colsep="1" colname="col3"/><thead><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Chemical Treatment</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">Scavenger Dosage (ppm active)</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">Head Space H<sub>2</sub>S, ppm</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Field Study 1:</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top"/></row></thead><tbody><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Glyoxal</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">0.3</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">27</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">3.8</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">8</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">6.0</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">7</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">8</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">2</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">10</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">0.5</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Glyoxal:Mg(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> (3:1 ratio)</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">0.3</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">27</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">2.4</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">2</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">3.5</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">1.5</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">4.3</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">1.5</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">5.7</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">2</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Mg(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub></entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">10</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">27</entry></row></tbody></tgroup><tgroup cols="3" rowsep="1" colsep="1"><colspec colwidth="82mm" colnum="1" colsep="1" colname="col1"/><colspec colwidth="49mm" colnum="2" colsep="1" colname="col2"/><colspec colwidth="36mm" colnum="3" colsep="1" colname="col3"/><thead><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Field Study 2:</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top"/></row></thead><tbody><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Glyoxal</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">0.5</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">47</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">4.0</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">12</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">6.0</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">0.1</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">8.0</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">0.1</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">10.0</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">5.0*</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Glyoxal:Mg(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> (3:1 ratio)</entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">0.5</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">47</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">2.4</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">0.1</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">3.3</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">0.1</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">4.3</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">0.1</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top"/><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">5.7</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">0.1</entry></row><row><entry nameend="col1" align="left" namest="col1" valign="top">Mg(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub></entry><entry nameend="col2" align="left" namest="col2" valign="top">10</entry><entry nameend="col3" align="left" namest="col3" valign="top">47</entry></row></tbody></tgroup><tgroup cols="3" rowsep="0"><colspec colwidth="82mm" colnum="1" colname="col1"/><colspec colwidth="49mm" colnum="2" colname="col2"/><colspec colwidth="36mm" colnum="3" colname="col3"/><tbody><row><entry nameend="col3" align="justify" namest="col1" valign="top">* operational variation with this data point</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="p0019">The treatment of the present invention was also found to be stable with time and temperature, ranging from about 3°C to about 35°C, although the present invention is expected to be effective within a temperature range of from about 0°C to about 50°C.</p><p num="p0020">While the present invention has been described with respect to particular embodiments thereof, it is apparent that numerous other forms and modifications of<!-- EPO <DP n="7"> --> the invention will be obvious to those skilled in the art. The appended claims and this invention generally should be construed to cover all such obvious forms and modifications, which are within the scope of the present invention.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="c-en-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>A method for preventing hydrogen sulfide odor generation in a sulfur species-containing aqueous medium, which comprises adding to the aqueous medium an effective amount for the purpose of a sulfide scavenger treatment selected from the group consisting of glyoxal, triazine, n-chlorosuccinimide, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>The method as recited in claim 1, wherein the sulfide scavenger treatment is a combination of (a) glyoxal and (b) a metal nitrate compound.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>The method as recited in claim 1, wherein less than about 10 ppm of the treatment is added to the aqueous medium.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>The method as recited in claim 1, wherein said aqueous medium comprises a wastewater medium.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0005" num="0005"><claim-text>The method as recited in claim 2, wherein the weight ratio of (a) to (b) is from about 1:3 to 1000:1.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0006" num="0006"><claim-text>A method for controlling corrosion in a sulfur species-containing aqueous medium, which comprises adding to the aqueous medium an effective amount for the purpose of a sulfide scavenger treatment selected from the group consisting of glyoxal, triazine, n-chlorosuccinimide, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0007" num="0007"><claim-text>The method as recited in claim 6, wherein the sulfide scavenger treatment is a combination of (a) glyoxal and (b) a metal nitrate compound.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0008" num="0008"><claim-text>The method as recited in claim 6, wherein less than about 10 ppm of the treatment is added to the aqueous medium.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0009" num="0009"><claim-text>The method as recited in claim 6, wherein said aqueous medium comprises a water/hydrocarbon emulsion.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0010" num="0010"><claim-text>A method for preventing hydrogen sulfide odor generation in a sulfur species-containing aqueous medium, which comprises adding to the aqueous medium an<!-- EPO <DP n="9"> --> effective amount for the purpose of a redox potential buffer, including one or more non-biocidal components.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>