<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1298148-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1298148" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="8180972" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030402"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1298148-A1" status="new" fvid="23731882"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1298148</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030402</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01203657-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01203657</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010927</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-01203657-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01203657</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010927</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/00        20060101C I20060521RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/64        20060101A I20060521RMWO        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/645       20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/659       20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/6592      20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F  10/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F  10/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F  10/00+4/6592B4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08F4:659K</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08F4:659L</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Katalysatorbestandteil, der ein Metallocen mit zwei Tetrahydroindenyl-Liganden enthält, zur Herstellung eines Polyolefins</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Catalyst component comprising a metallocene with two tetrahydroindenyl ligands for producing a polyolefin</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composant de catalyseur comprenant un métallocène ayant deux ligands tetrahydroindényle pour la préparation d'une polyoléfine</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0692505-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0692505</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0697418-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0697418</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6143846-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6143846</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ATOFINA RES S A</name><address><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ATOFINA RESEARCH S.A.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Atofina Research S.A.</last-name><address><street>Zone Indusrielle C</street><city>7181 Seneffe (Feluy)</city><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>The designation of the inventor has not yet been filed</last-name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep"  status="new" lang="EN"><p>Provided is a catalyst component for producing a polyolefin, which catalyst component
comprises a metallocene catalyst having a structure according to a formulae (I):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">(THI)<sub>2</sub>R"MQ<sub>p</sub></st32:che>
wherein each THI is a tetrahydroindenyl derivative which may be substituted or
unsubstituted, provided that at least one of the tetrahydroindenyl derivatives is substituted
at the 2-position or the 4-position; R" is a structural bridge to impart stereorigidity
between the two THI groups; M is a metal from Group IIIB, IVB, VB or VIB; Q is a
hydrocarbyl group having from 1-20 carbon atoms, or a halogen; and p is the valence of
M minus 2.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a catalyst component and catalyst system for use in
preparing polyolefins, especially polyethylene having a high molecular weight and
improved mechanical properties, whilst retaining good processing properties. The
invention further relates to a process for producing polyolefins using the catalyst
component or catalyst system.</p><p num="0002">Metallocene catalysts have been known to be useful in the production of polyolefins for
some time. The first generation of metallocene catalysts were unbridged metallocenes.
These catalysts provided a new route into polyolefin resins. However, polyolefin resins
produced using unbridged metallocenes were found to have poor processibility, despite
having good optical properties, such as high transparency and low haze.</p><p num="0003">In order to improve the properties of the resins, bridged metallocene catalysts were
developed. Such bridged metallocene catalysts are disclosed in published PCT application
number WO91/03500. Typical such supported bridged metallocenes are Et(IndH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub>
and Et(Ind)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub> (IndH<sub>4</sub> is an unsubstituted tetrahydroindenyl (THI) group, and Ind is
an unsubstituted indenyl group). Other such known bridged metallocenes comprise
substituted cyclopentadienyl ligands, such as those disclosed in published patent
US 4 892 851. In these metallocenes, the substitution pattern was designed with a view to
controlling the stereochemistry of polypropylene produced from the catalysts.</p><p num="0004">Resins produced from this second generation of metallocene catalysts display improved
mechanical properties due to their higher molecular weight. In addition, such resins have
better processing properties due to the presence of different chain architecture and
probably long chain branches. However, the processibility and the co-monomer content
of such resins is still less than is desired.</p><p num="0005">Resins produced from Ziegler-Natta and chromium-based catalysts may have the same or
similar processing and mechanical properties as compared with their counterparts formed 
using metallocene catalysts. However, such resins display inferior optical and mechanical
properties.</p><p num="0006">Thus, it is still desirable to produce high quality resins using metallocene catalysts that
have more superior mechanical and processing properties.</p><p num="0007">It is an object of the present invention to overcome the problems associated with the
above prior art catalysts. Accordingly, the present invention provides a catalyst
component for producing a polyolefin, which catalyst component comprises a
metallocene catalyst having a structure according to a formulae (I):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">(THI)<sub>2</sub>R"MQ<sub>p</sub></st32:che>
wherein each THI is a tetrahydroindenyl derivative which may be substituted or
unsubstituted, provided that at least one of the tetrahydroindenyl derivatives is substituted
at the 2-position or the 4-position; R" is a structural bridge to impart stereorigidity
between the two THI groups; M is a metal from Group IIIB, IVB, VB or VIB; Q is a
hydrocarbyl group having from 1-20 carbon atoms, or a halogen; and p is the valence of
M minus 2.</p><p num="0008">By substituted, in the context of the present invention it is meant that any of the positions
on the tetrahydroindenyl group may comprise a substituent in place of a hydrogen atom.
Thus, whilst each substituted THI group may be a tetrahydroindenyl group with the
substituent present on the five-membered ring, it may alternatively be a group that
comprises the same pattern of saturation as tetrahydroindenyl, but in which one or more
of the hydrogen atoms on the six-membered ring has been replaced. Alternatively, and
preferably, the substituents may be present on both the five-membered and the
six-membered ring. </p><p num="0009">Each catalyst component comprises two THI derivative ligands. The two ligands may be
different. However, it is preferred that the two THI ligands of the catalyst component are
the same.</p><p num="0010">The present invention further provides a method for producing a polyolefin, which
method comprises polymerising an olefin monomer (or an olefin monomer and a
co-monomer) in the presence of a catalyst component (or catalyst system comprising the
catalyst component) as defined above.</p><p num="0011">The substitution pattern of the THI ligands on the metallocene catalysts leads to the
advantages of the present invention. The substitution pattern and numbering of the
ligands of the present catalysts will be discussed in more detail below.</p><p num="0012">The ligand, THI, used in catalysts of formula (I) is a tetrahydroindenyl-type ligand, in
which, in the context of the present invention, the substituent positions are numbered
from 1-7 according to the system set out in the structure below:
<img id="img-00030001" orientation="unknown"  wi="54"  img-format="tif"  img-content="cf" file="00030001.tif" inline="no" he="34"/></p><p num="0013">To distinguish substitution in the first THI ligand from the second, the second is
numbered according to the same system, but from 1'-7', in accordance with convention. In
this type of catalyst, the position of the bridge is not particularly limited, and is preferably
a 1,1'-bridge, a 2,2'-bridge or a 1,2'-bridge, a 1,1'-bridge being most preferred.</p><p num="0014">The position of the substituent or substituents on the two THI ligands is not particularly
limited, provided that at least one of the ligands is substituted in the 2-position and/or the
4-position. Provided that this criterion is satisfied, the THI ligands may have any 
substitution pattern, including being unsubstituted or fully substituted. In preferred
embodiments both of the THI ligands are substituted. Typically, both of the THI ligands
comprise substituents in the 2-position and/or in the 4-position. Most preferably both of
the THI ligands comprise substituents in the 2-position and the 4-position. In these
embodiments the other positions in the ring may also comprise substituents, or may be
unsubstituted. Particularly preferred metallocene catalysts with a 1,1'-bridge have the
following substitution patterns: 2; 4; 2,4; 2,2'; 4,4'; 2,4'; 2,4,2'; 2,4,4'; and 2,4,2',4'
wherein only those positions indicated comprise a substituent. It should be noted that
since the basic structures of both THI derivatives are identical, patterns such as 2,4' and
4,2' are identical.</p><p num="0015">The use of a catalyst as defined above (in which the THI derivatives are substituted
according to the above specific substitution patterns) to produce a polyolefin, leads to
polyolefins that have improved physical and mechanical properties, are easily processed
and have good optical properties.</p> <p num="0016">Thus, the polyolefin resins produced by the catalyst system of the present invention have
improved processibility and solidification properties in injection blow moulding and
injection moulding, whilst simultaneously showing high transparency and flexibility.</p><p num="0017">The substituent or substituents present on the THI ligands in the above-described
catalysts are not particularly limited. The above ligands, when comprising more than one
substituent, may be substituted with the same substituent throughout, or with different
substituents. Typically the substituents are independently selected from an aryl group and
a hydrocarbyl group having from 1-20 carbon atoms. The most preferred substituents are
methyl groups. Other preferred substituents include phenyl (Ph), benzyl (Bz),
naphthyl (Naph), indenyl (Ind) and benzindenyl (BzInd), as well as Et, n-Pr, i-Pr, n-Bu,
t-Bu, Me<sub>3</sub>Si, alkoxy (preferably R-O, where R is C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> alkyl), cycloalkyl, and halogen.</p><p num="0018">Preferred THI derivatives include: 2-Me,4-PhTHI; 2-Me,4-NaphTHI; and
2-Me,4,5-BzIndTHI. The most preferred catalyst components comprise at least one on 
these ligands, and preferably two such ligands. It is particularly preferred that the two
THI ligands of the catalyst components are the same.</p><p num="0019">The type of bridge present between the THI rings in the present catalyst components is
not itself particularly limited. Typically R" comprises an alkylidene group having 1 to 20
carbon atoms, a germanium group (e.g. a dialkyl germanium group), a silicon group (e.g.
a dialkyl silicon group), a siloxane group (e.g. a dialkyl siloxane group), an alkyl
phosphine group or an amine group. Preferably, the substituent comprises a hydrocarbyl
radical having at least one carbon atom to form the bridge, such as a substituted or
unsubstituted ethylenyl radical (e.g. Et, -CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-). Most preferably R" is Et or Me<sub>2</sub>Si.</p><p num="0020">The metal, M, in the metallocene catalyst is preferably a metal from Group IIIB, IVB, VB
or VIB of the periodic table. Typically, M is Ti, Zr, Hf, or V and Q is preferably a
halogen, typically Cl. Typically the valence of the metal is 4, such that p is 2.</p> <p num="0021">The most preferred catalyst components of the present invention are:
<sl><li>Me<sub>2</sub>Si(2-MeTHI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub> </li> <li>Et(2-MeTHI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub></li><li>Me<sub>2</sub>Si(2-Me,4-PhTHI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub></li><li>Et(2-Me,4-PhTHI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub></li><li>Me<sub>2</sub>Si(2-Me,4-NaphTHI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub></li><li>Et(2-Me,4-NaphTHI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub></li><li>Me<sub>2</sub>Si(2-Me,4,5-BzIndTHI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub></li><li>Et(2-Me,4,5-BzIndTHI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub></li></sl></p><p num="0022">The catalyst system of the present invention is not particularly limited provided that it
comprises at least one metallocene catalyst component as defined above. Thus the system
may comprise further catalysts, if necessary, such as further metallocene catalysts
according to the present invention, or other catalysts. </p><p num="0023">The catalyst system of the present invention comprises, in addition to the above catalyst
component, one or more co-catalysts capable of activating the metallocene catalyst.
Typically, the co-catalyst comprises an aluminium- or boron-containing co-catalyst.</p><p num="0024">Suitable aluminium-containing co-catalysts comprise an alumoxane, an alkyl aluminium
compound and/or a Lewis acid.</p><p num="0025">The alumoxanes that can be used in the present invention are well known and preferably
comprise oligomeric linear and/or cyclic alkyl alumoxanes represented by the formula
(A):
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="50" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="23"/>
for oligomeric linear alumoxanes; and formula (B)
<img id="img-00060002" orientation="unknown" wi="41" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060002.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
for oligomeric cyclic alumoxanes,

wherein n is 1-40, preferably 10-20; m is 3-40, preferably 3-20; and R is a C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>8</sub> alkyl
group, preferably methyl. Generally, in the preparation of alumoxanes from, for example,
aluminium trimethyl and water, a mixture of linear and cyclic compounds is obtained.</p><p num="0026">Suitable boron-containing co-catalysts may comprise a triphenylcarbenium boronate,
such as tetrakis-pentafluorophenyl-borato-triphenylcarbenium as described in
EP-A-0427696: <img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="82" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/>
or those of the general formula below, as described in EP-A-0277004 (page 6, line 30 to
page 7, line 7):
<img id="img-00070002" orientation="unknown" wi="71" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070002.tif" inline="no" he="29"/></p><p num="0027">The catalyst system may be employed in the gas phase or in a solution polymerisation
process, which is homogeneous, or a slurry process, which is heterogeneous in a single or
tandem reactor configuration. In a solution process, typical solvents include
hydrocarbons having 4-7 carbon atoms such as heptane, toluene or cyclohexane. In a
slurry process it is necessary to immobilise the catalyst system on an inert support,
particularly a porous solid support such as talc, inorganic oxides and resinous support
materials such as polyolefin. Preferably, the support material is an inorganic oxide in its
finely divided form.</p><p num="0028">Suitable inorganic oxide materials which are desirably employed in accordance with this
invention include group IIA, IIIA, IVA, or IVB metal oxides such as silica, alumina and
mixtures thereof. Other inorganic oxides that may be employed either alone or in
combination with the silica, or alumina are magnesia, titania, zirconia, and the like. Other
suitable support materials, however, can be employed, for example, finely divided
functionalised polyolefins such as finely divided polyethylene. </p><p num="0029">Preferably, the support is a silica support having a surface area of from 100-1000 m<sup>2</sup>/g,
more preferably from 200-700 m<sup>2</sup>/g, and a pore volume of from 0.5-4 ml/g, more
preferably from 0.5-3 ml/g.</p><p num="0030">The amount of alumoxane and metallocenes usefully employed in the preparation of the
solid support catalyst can vary over a wide range. Generally the aluminium to transition
metal mole ratio is in the range between 1:1 and 100:1, preferably in the range 5:1 and
80:1 and more preferably in the range 5:1 and 50:1.</p><p num="0031">The order of addition of the catalyst and alumoxane to the support material can vary. In
accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention alumoxane dissolved in
a suitable inert hydrocarbon solvent is added to the support material slurried in the same
or other suitable hydrocarbon liquid and thereafter the catalyst component is added to the
slurry.</p><p num="0032">Preferred solvents include mineral oils and the various hydrocarbons which are liquid at
reaction temperature and which do not react with the individual ingredients. Illustrative
examples of the useful solvents include the alkanes such as pentane, iso-pentane, hexane,
heptane, octane and nonane; cycloalkanes such as cyclopentane and cyclohexane, and
aromatics such as benzene, toluene, ethylbenzene and diethylbenzene.</p><p num="0033">Preferably the support material is slurried in toluene and the catalyst component and
alumoxane are dissolved in toluene prior to addition to the support material.</p><p num="0034">The polyolefins that the present catalyst is capable of producing are not particularly
limited. It is particularly preferred that the catalyst is capable of producing polyethylene
and/or polypropylene.</p><p num="0035">The catalyst component or catalyst system of the present invention are used in the method
of the present invention to produce polyolefin resins. It is especially preferred that the 
method of the present invention is a method of producing a polyethylene or a
polypropylene.These polyolefins can be monomodal or multimodal.</p><p num="0036">The conditions employed for polymerisation in the method of the present invention are
not particularly limited, provided they are sufficient to effectively polymerise the
particular monomeric olefin used as a starting material. When the monomer to be
polymerised in the present method is ethylene, the preferred polymerisation conditions
are from 70-110°C, more preferably from 70-90°C (e.g. around 80°C) using a
hydrocarbon solvent such as isobutane or hexane. Preferably polymerisation takes place
in the presence of hydrogen and an alkene co-monomer such as 1-butene or 1-hexene.</p><p num="0037">The polymerisation process in which the catalyst systems of the present invention can be
used is not particularly limited. Preferably the catalysts are employed in a process for
polymerising ethylene. More preferably the process is a process for producing a
polyethylene with a bimodal or multimodal molecular weight distribution. Such processes
may employ a dual site catalyst to achieve bimodality and one or both of the catalytic
sites may be provided by metallocene catalysts as described in the present invention.</p><p num="0038">The invention will now be described in further detail by way of example only, with
reference to the following non-limiting specific embodiments.</p><heading><b>Examples</b></heading><heading><i>Catalyst preparation</i></heading><p num="0039">One catalyst component of the present invention, (Me<sub>2</sub>Si)(2-MeTHI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub> (catalyst 1),
was prepared in accordance with the method of W. Spalek; A. Antberg, J. Rohrmann, A.
Winter, B. Bachmann, P. Kiprof, J. Behm, and W. A. Hermann, Angew. Chem. Int. Eng.
Ed. 1992, 31, 1347. A further catalyst component of the present invention,
(Et)(2-MeTHI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub> (catalyst 2), was prepared in accordance with the method of H. H.
Brintzinger, Journal of Organometallic Chemistry, 1982, 232, 233. For comparative
purposes two similar catalysts, (Me<sub>2</sub>Si)(THI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub> and (Et)(THI)<sub>2</sub>ZrCl<sub>2</sub> (catalysts 3 
and 4 respectively) in which both THI ligands were unsubstituted, were prepared.
Catalyst 4 was prepared according to F. R. W. P. Wild, M. Wasiucuinek, G. Huttner, and
H. H. Brintzinger, Journal of Organometallic Chemistry, 1985, 288, 63.</p><p num="0040">The support used was silica having a total pore volume of 4.22 ml/g and a surface area of
322 m<sup>2</sup>/g. This silica is further prepared by drying under a high vacuum on a schlenk
line for three hours to remove physically absorbed water. 5 g of this silica were
suspended in a round bottom flask equipped with a magnetic stirrer, a nitrogen inlet and a
dropping funnel.</p><p num="0041">To produce activated catalyst, amounts of approximately 0.3 g of catalysts 1-4 were each
reacted with 25 ml of methylalumoxane (MAO 30 wt. % in toluene), at a temperature of
25°C for 10 minutes to give solutions of the corresponding metallocene cations and the
anionic methylalumoxane oligomer.</p><p num="0042">Then the resulting solutions comprising the metallocene cations and the anionic
methylalumoxane oligomer were added to the support under a nitrogen atmosphere via
the dropping funnel, which was immediately replaced with a reflux condenser. The
mixtures were each heated to 110°C for 90 minutes. The reaction mixtures were then
cooled to room temperature, filtered under nitrogen and washed with toluene.</p><p num="0043">The catalyst systems obtained were then washed with pentane and dried under a mild
vacuum.</p><p num="0044">The catalyst systems of the present invention comprising catalyst components 1 and 2,
and the comparative catalyst systems comprising catalyst components 3 and 4, were used
to polymerise ethylene. In each polymerisation reaction, the ethylene was polymerised in
a 41 bench reactor at 80°C. An isobutane solvent (21) was used comprising 6 % wt.
ethylene. A 1 hr residence time was used. The molecular weight (Mw) of the polymer
products produced as well as their HLMI values are shown below in Table 1. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2"><b>Substituted (invention)</b></entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4"><b>Unsubstituted (comparison)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>Cat. &amp; bridge</b></entry><entry align="center">Catalyst 1 (Si)</entry><entry align="center">Catalyst 2 (Et)</entry><entry align="center">Catalyst 3 (Si)</entry><entry align="center">Catalyst 4 (Et)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>M<sub>w</sub>/kDa</b></entry><entry align="center">399</entry><entry align="center">360</entry><entry align="center">329</entry><entry align="center">326</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>HLMI (g/10mins)</b></entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry><entry align="center">0.22</entry><entry align="center">0.27</entry><entry align="center">0.22</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0045">Comparing the properties of the polyethylene products produced by the third generation
catalysts (substituted catalysts of the present invention) with the closest second generation
catalysts (unsubstituted), it is clear that the catalysts of the present invention give a much
higher molecular weight product than the comparative catalysts whilst displaying a
similar or reduced HLMI. This is particularly demonstrated by the M<sub>w</sub> and HLMI values
for catalyst 1 which are 399k and 0.15 respectively, the highest and lowest values for the
tested polymers. It is preferable that the molecular weight is as high as possible to benefit
the mechanical properties of the polymer produced.</p><p num="0046">The HLMI measured in the above Examples is the high load melt index and is measured
according to the procedures of ASTM D 1238 using a load of 21.6 kg at a temperature of
190°C.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A catalyst component for producing a polyolefin, which catalyst component
comprises a metallocene catalyst having a structure according to a formulae (I):
(THI)2R"MQp
wherein each THI is a tetrahydroindenyl derivative which may be substituted or
unsubstituted, provided that at least one of the tetrahydroindenyl derivatives is substituted
at the 2-position or the 4-position; R" is a structural bridge to impart stereorigidity
between the two THI groups; M is a metal from Group IIIB, IVB, VB or VIB; Q is a
hydrocarbyl group having from 1-20 carbon atoms, or a halogen; and p is the valence of
M minus 2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to claim 1, which component comprises a
metallocene catalyst of formula (I) in which both THI derivatives are substituted THI
derivatives.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to claim 1 or claim 2, which component
comprises a metallocene catalyst of formula (I) in which one THI derivative comprises
substituents at both the 2-position and the 4-position.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to any preceding claim, which component
comprises a metallocene catalyst of formula (I) in which both of the THI derivatives
comprise substituents at both the 2-position and the 4-position.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to any preceding claim, which component
comprises a metallocene catalyst of formula (I) in which both of the THI derivatives have
the same pattern of substitution.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to any preceding claim, wherein the substituents
on the THI derivatives are independently selected from aryl derivatives having from 1-20
carbon atoms, hydrocarbyl derivatives having from 1-20 carbon atoms, cycloalkyl
derivatives, silane derivatives, alkoxy derivatives and halogens.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to claim 6, wherein the substituents on the THI
derivatives are independently selected from Ph, Bz, Naph, Ind, BzInd, Me, Et, n-Pr, i-Pr,
n-Bu, t-Bu, and Me3Si.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to claim 7, wherein the substituents comprise
methyl groups.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to any preceding claim, wherein M is Ti, Zr, Hf,
or V.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to any preceding claim, wherein Q is Cl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to any preceding claim, wherein p is 2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to any preceding claim, wherein R" is substituted
or unsubstituted and comprises a group selected from an alkylene derivative having from
1-20 carbon atoms, a dialkyl germanium derivative, a dialkyl silicon derivative, a dialkyl
siloxane derivative, an alkyl phosphine derivative or an amine derivative.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to claim 12, wherein R" comprises an Me2Si
derivative or an Et derivative.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A catalyst component according to any preceding claim, wherein the metallocene
catalyst is immobilised on a solid support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A catalyst system comprising a catalyst component as defined in any preceding
claim, and further comprising an aluminium- or boron-containing co-catalyst capable of
activating the catalyst component.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A method for producing a polyolefin, which method comprises polymerising an
olefin monomer in the presence of a catalyst component or catalyst system as defined in
any of claims 1-15.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A method according to claim 16, wherein the olefin monomer is ethylene or
propylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A polyolefin, obtainable according to a method as defined in claim 16 or claim 17.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>Use of a catalyst component or catalyst system as defined in any of claims 1-15
for the preparation of a monomodal or multimodal polyolefin in a single or tandem
reactor configuration.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>Use according to claim 19 for the preparation of a monomodal or multimodal
polyethylene or polypropylene in a single or tandem reactor configuration.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>