<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1072644-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1072644" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="23416243" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010131"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1072644-A1" status="new" fvid="23051701"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1072644</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010131</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00114928-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00114928</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000715</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-36001499-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>36001499</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990723</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/24        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/24        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  21/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  21/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  51/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  51/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/04        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/10+B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/10+B5</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/16+B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/16+B5</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L51:06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L83:04</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verwendung von Silan-gepfropften Polyolefinen in epdm/Polyolefin DVA (dynamische Vulkanisierung) mit verbessertem Druckverformungsrest</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Use of a silane grafted polyolefin in epdm/polyolefin dva to improve compression set</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Utilisation de polyoléfine à greffe silane dans EPDM/polyoléfine DVA (VULCANISATION DYNAMIQUE) ayant une déformation permanente améliorée</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0776937-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0776937</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0855426-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0855426</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4803244-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4803244</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997047665-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997047665</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998021251-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998021251</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998027154-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998027154</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>ADVANCED ELASTOMER SYSTEMS</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ADVANCED ELASTOMER SYSTEMS, L.P.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Advanced Elastomer Systems, L.P.</last-name><address><street>388 South Main Street</street><city>Akron, Ohio 44311-1059</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ABDOU-SABET SABET</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MEDSKER ROBERT E</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>PATEL RAMAN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ABDOU-SABET, SABET</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MEDSKER, ROBERT E.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PATEL, RAMAN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ABDOU-SABET, SABET</last-name><address><street>3568 Knollwood Lane</street><city>Akron, Ohio 44333</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MEDSKER, ROBERT E.</last-name><address><street>13145 Kaufman Avenue</street><city>Hartville, Ohio 44632</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PATEL, RAMAN</last-name><address><street>578 Sun Valley Drive</street><city>Akron, Ohio 44333</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Weber, Thomas</last-name><address><street>Patentanwälte von Kreisler-Selting-Werner, Bahnhofsvorplatz 1 (Deichmannhaus)</street><city>50667 Köln</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A thermoplastic vulcanizate (TPV) from a blend of a first
thermoplastic polyolefin, a second thermoplastic olefin and a rubber is
described. The rubber is crosslinked with a hydrosilylation crosslinking
agent. The second polyolefin includes at least one OR group pendant to
a Si atom chemically attached via one or more intermediate molecules to
said second polyolefin. R can be hydrogen or an alkyl of 1 to 8 carbon
atoms. The OR groups can react with the hydrosilylation catalyst to
reduce the compression set of the TPV.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single"><b>FIELD OF INVENTION</b></u></heading><p num="0001">Polyolefins with a pendant -SiOR, -Si(OR)<sub>2</sub>, or -Si(OR)<sub>3</sub> groups are
desirable components for thermoplastic vulcanizates from a semi-crystalline
polyolefin and an unsaturated rubber crosslinked via
hydrosilylation. The -SiOR groups and their hydrolysis products are
generally reactive with hydrosilylation crosslinking agents. The resulting
reaction product can help generate the right interaction between the
polyolefin phase and rubber phase to provide enhanced physical
properties such as decreased compression set.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>BACKGROUND OF INVENTION</b></u></heading><p num="0002">Union Carbide Corporation U.S. Patent 4,803,244 teaches the
preparation of thermoplastic elastomers from admixing under reaction
conditions an unsaturated elastomer, a thermoplastic polymer and a
multifunctional organosilicon compound (hydrosilylation agent) and a
catalyst capable of hydrosilylating the carbon-carbon double bonds of
the unsaturated elastomer. This patent used a high level of catalyst and
produced relatively low levels of completely crosslinked rubber (gel).</p><p num="0003">Sumitomo Bakelite Co. has U.S. Patent 5,597,867, which teaches
the components of U.S. 4,803,244 along with a compatibilizing agent
and if necessary paraffinic oil. The compatibilizing agent generally has a
component molecularly compatible with the rubber and a component
molecularly compatible with the thermoplastic resin e.g. a block
copolymer, a random copolymer, or a graft copolymer in which at least
two monomers are polymerized.</p><p num="0004">Advanced Elastomer Systems, L.P. has a U.S. Patent 5,672,660
which teaches an improved process for the preparation of thermoplastic 
elastomers by hydrosilylation crosslinking using a platinum containing
hydrosilylation catalyst and specific unsaturated diene-containing
rubbers.</p><p num="0005">The Dow Chemical Company has U.S. Patent 5,741,858, which
teaches silane-crosslinked molded articles of a polyolefin elastomer and a
crystalline polyolefin. Generally a silane with unsaturation and a
hydrolyzable group are grafted via the unsaturation to a crystalline
polyolefin and to a polyolefin elastomer. Thereafter, crosslinking is
accomplished by hydrolyzing any alkoxy groups and thereafter
dehydrocondensation of the silanol groups.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>SUMMARY OF INVENTION</b></u></heading><p num="0006">A thermoplastic vulcanizate from a first semi-crystalline polyolefin,
an unsaturated rubber and a second thermoplastic polyolefin having at
least one pendant -OR group from a silicon atom chemically attached to
the second polyolefin. The unsaturated rubber or a portion thereof is
crosslinked with a hydrosilylation crosslinking agent. The second
polyolefin with said pendant -OR group facilitates optimal interaction
between the first polyolefin and the unsaturated rubber. R is hydrogen
or an alkyl group of 1 to 8 carbon atoms. The pendant -OR group or its
hydrolysis product can chemically bond with the hydrosilylation
crosslinking agent. Thus, the -OR groups can function as reaction sites
to bond the second polyolefin to the rubber phase via the hydrosilylation
crosslinking agent. The second polyolefin (especially if it is a semi-crystallilne
polyolefin such as polyethylene or polypropylene) will
preferably be located in or adjacent to the semi-crystalline polyolefin.
The amount of said second polyolefin is desirably from about 2 to about
25 wt% of the weight of said first polyolefin and said unsaturated
rubber. The first polyolefin is desirably polypropylene and the
unsaturated rubber or a portion thereof is desirably EPDM. </p><heading><u style="single"><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</b></u></heading><p num="0007">A thermoplastic vulcanizates from a first semi-crystalline
polyolefin, an alkoxysilane or silanol functionalized polymer and an
unsaturated elastomer crosslinked with a hydrosilylation crosslinking
agent is disclosed. The alkoxysilane or silanol functionalized polymer
functions to generate the desirable extent of interaction between the
semi-crystalline polyolefin and the unsaturated rubber. Said polymer is a
semicrystalline polyolefin with at least one -OR including OH group
pendant directly from an Si atom, which Si atom is chemically attached
via one or more intermediate molecules to said second polyolefin.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>Alkoxysilane or Silanol Functionalized Polyolefin</b></u></heading><p num="0008">An example according to this description is Linklon™ XPM
800H from Mitsubishi. It is generally characterized as a silane grafted
semi-crystalline polypropylene with about 0.01 moles of pendant Si(OR)<sub>n</sub>
groups per 100 grams of polymer where R is C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>8</sub> and n is from 1 to
3.</p><p num="0009">It can generally be any grafted polyolefin polymer with or
without residual unsaturation e.g. polyolefins with at least 80 wt% more
desirably at least 90 and preferably at least 95 wt% repeating units from
a single olefin monomer, preferably monoolefin, having from 2 to 12
carbon atoms. Preferred polyolefins are copolymers with at least 80
wt% repeating units from ethylene and or propylene. The functional
group grafted onto the polyolefin polymer could be any molecule with
olefinic unsaturation, a silicon atom, and at least one -OR or OH group
pendant to said silicon atom in the molecule. The variable R can be a
hydrogen or an alkyl of 1 to 8 or 12 carbon atoms, an alkoxyalkyl of 2
to 8 carbon atoms such as methoxyethyl or an acetyl group. Examples
of the molecules include: <img id="img-00040001" orientation="unknown" wi="96" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif" inline="no" he="63"/>
   where each R is as defined above. Such molecules are
available from silane manufacturers and distributors such as O.S.I.
Specialty Inc in Danbury, Connecticut. The amount of the grafted Si(OR)
groups is desirably from about 0.005 to about 0.1 moles per 100g
of said grafted polyolefin polymer and more desirably is from about .015
to about .025 moles. Such technology is taught in Japanese Patent
57012051 A2 issued January 21, 1982.</p><p num="0010">The alkoxysilane or silanol functionalized polymer can also be a
copolymer including repeating units from olefins and olefinically
unsaturated molecules having at least one OR group pendant to a Si
atom as previously described. Such copolymers desirably have at least
60, more desirably at least 70, and preferably at least 80 wt %
repeating units from one or more olefins preferably monoolefins of from
2 to 8 or 12 carbon atoms. Preferably the olefins are ethylene and/or
propylene. The amount of the olefinically unsaturated molecule, having
at least one OR group pendant to a Si atom, incorporated in the
copolymer is desirably from about 0.1 to 20 wt % and more desirably
from about 0.5 to 7.5 wt % based on the weight of said polymer. Such
copolymers and their preparation are described in U.S. 5,266,627 and
the references therein which are hereby incorporated by reference. </p><p num="0011">The amount of the alkoxysilane or silanol functionalized
polyolefin in the thermoplastic vulcanizate is desirably from about 0.1 or
5 to about 20 or 25 wt % and more desirably from about 1 or 5 to 15 or
20 wt % based upon the weight of said first thermoplastic polyolefin
and alkoxysilane or silanol functionalized polymer.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>Thermoplastic Vulcanizates</b></u></heading><p num="0012">Thermoplastic elastomer compositions may be prepared by
melt blending a thermoplastic resin and a rubber, until the blend is
homogeneous. If a composition of vulcanized rubber in a thermoplastic
matrix is desired, crosslinking agents (also referred to as curatives or
vulcanizing agents) are added to the blend and crosslinking occurs during
the mixing. This latter process is described as dynamic vulcanization.</p><p num="0013">A wide range of thermoplastic resins and rubbers and/or their
mixtures have been used in the preparation of thermoplastic elastomers,
including polypropylene, HDPE, LDPE, VLDPE, LLDPE, cyclic olefin
homopolymers or copolymers as well as olefinic block copolymers,
polystyrene, polyphenylene sulfide, polyphenylene oxide and ethylene
propylene copolymer (EP) thermoplastics. The rubbers include ethylene
propylene diene rubber (EPDM), acrylonitrile butadiene rubber (NBR)
copolymers of isobutylene and divinylbenzene, and natural rubber (NR)
as the elastomers. When the elastomer component is crosslinked,
agents such as sulfur, peroxide, phenolics and ionic compounds are
often used.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>Hydrosilylation Agents</b></u></heading><p num="0014">Hydrosilylation has also been disclosed as a crosslinking
method in U.S. Patent 5,672,660, hereby incorporated by reference. In
this method a silicon hydride having at least two SiH groups in the
molecule is reacted with the carbon-carbon multiple bonds of the 
unsaturated (i.e. containing at least one carbon-carbon double bond)
rubber component of the thermoplastic elastomer, in the presence of the
thermoplastic resin and a hydrosilylation catalyst. Silicon hydride
compounds useful in the process of the invention include
methylhydrogen polysiloxanes, methylhydrogen dimethyl-siloxane
copolymers, alkyl methyl polysiloxanes, bis(dimethylsilyl)alkanes and
bis(dimethylsilyl)benzene.</p><p num="0015">Preferred silicon hydride compounds may be described by the
formula
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="114" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="41"/>
where each R, R', and R'' is independently selected from the group
consisting of H, alkyls comprising 1 to 20 carbon atoms, cycloalkyls
comprising 4 to 12 carbon atoms and aryls. In formula (1) it is preferred
that each R be independently selected from a group consisting of alkyls
comprising 1 to 6 carbon atoms. Even more preferred is R = methyl, R'
represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl or alkoxy group having from 1 to
about 24 carbon atoms, R'' represents R or a hydrogen atom, D
represents the group
<img id="img-00060002" orientation="unknown" wi="47" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060002.tif" inline="no" he="53"/><sl><li>D' represents the group
<img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="43" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="47"/></li><li>T represents the group
<img id="img-00070002" orientation="unknown" wi="44" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070002.tif" inline="no" he="50"/></li><li>m is an integer having a value ranging from 1 to 50,</li><li>n is an integer having a value ranging from 1 to 50, and</li><li>p is an integer having a value ranging from 0 to 6.</li></sl></p><p num="0016">Particularly preferred polyorganosiloxanes are those in which the
silicon atom of the silicon hydride functionality is bound by
heteroatoms/atoms having lone pairs of electrons. The preferred
polyorganosiloxanes may also be substituted with appropriate
functionality permitting solubility in the reaction media. A type of this
functionalization is described in U.S. Pat. No. 4,046,930 which teaches
alkylation of polyorganosiloxanes. Weight percent of alkylation should
be controlled to permit adequate reaction rates which maybe reduced
due to steric constraints.</p><p num="0017">The amount of silicon hydride compound useful in the process of
the present invention can range from about 0.1 to about 10.0 mole 
equivalents of SiH per carbon-carbon double bond in the rubber, and
preferably is in the range of about 0.5 to about 5.0 mole equivalents of
SiH per carbon-carbon double bond in the rubber component of the
thermoplastic elastomer.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>Thermoplastic Resins</b></u></heading><p num="0018">Thermoplastic resins useful in the compositions produced by the
invention include crystalline polyolefin homopolymers and copolymers.
They are desirably prepared from monoolefin monomers having 2 to 20
carbon atoms, such as ethylene, propylene, 1-butene, 1-pentene and the
like, as well as copolymers derived from linear and cyclic olefins, with
propylene being preferred. As used in the specification and claims the
term polypropylene includes homopolymers of propylene as well as
reactor copolymers of polypropylene which can contain about 1 to about
20 wt% of ethylene or an α-olefin comonomer of 4 to 20 carbon atoms,
and mixtures thereof. The polypropylene can be crystalline, isotactic or
syndiotactic polypropylene. Commercially available polyolefins may be
used in the practice of the invention. Other thermoplastic resins which
are substantially inert to the rubber, the silicon hydride and the
hydrosilylation catalyst would also be suitable. Blends of thermoplastic
resins may also be used.</p><p num="0019">The amount of thermoplastic resin and alkoxysilane or silanol
functionalized polyolefin found to provide useful compositions is
generally from about 5 to about 90 weight percent, based on the weight
of the rubber and resin. Preferably, the thermoplastic resin and
alkoxysilane or silanol functionalized polyolefin content will range from
about 20 to about 80 percent by weight of the total polymer.</p><p num="0020">Desirably the alkoxysilane or silanol functionalized polyolefin is
present in such low amounts that the thermoplastic phase of the
thermoplastic vulcanizate remains melt processable after repeated 
exposure to water and reaction of the alkoxysilane or silanol groups of
the alkoxysilane or silanol functionalized polymer. A thermoplastic
vulcanizate will be considered melt processable if the physical properties
generally decrease less than 10% subsequent to reprocessing.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>Rubbers</b></u></heading><p num="0021">Unsaturated rubbers useful to prepare thermoplastic elastomers
according to the invention include monoolefin copolymer rubbers
comprising non-polar, rubbery copolymers of two or more -monoolefins,
preferably copolymerized with at least one polyene, usually a diene.
However, unsaturated monoolefin rubber such as EPDM rubber is more
suitable. EPDM is a polymer of ethylene, propylene and one or more
non-conjugated diene or non-conjugated dienes, and the monomer
components may be polymerized using Ziegler-Natta or metallocene
catalyzed reactions, among others. Satisfactory non-conjugated dienes
include 5-ethylidene-2-norbornene (ENB); 1,4-hexadiene (HD); 5-methylene-2-norbornene
(MNB); 1,6-octadiene; 5-methyl-1,4-hexadiene;
3,7-dimethyl-1,6-octadiene; 1,3-cyclopentadiene; 1,4-cyclohexadiene;
dicyclopentadiene (DCPD); 5-vinyl-2-norbornene (VNB) and the like, or a
combination thereof.</p><p num="0022">In one embodiment of the invention, it has been found that rubber
having a structure in which the diene monomer has carbon-carbon
multiple bonds which are predominately unencumbered, i.e. bonds which
are sterically unhindered such as terminal or pendant double bonds,
provide a greatly improved rate of cure in the hydrosilylation curing
process of the invention. Included in this embodiment are structures in
which the bonds either normally are unencumbered or are easily
isomerized to form a sterically unencumbered double bond, which is then
rapidly hydrosilated, e.g. 1,4-hexadiene or ENB. This improvement is
particularly significant where a fully cured rubber component is desired. 
The use of rubber in which the diene component is selected from the
group consisting of 5-ethylidene-2-norbornene, 5-methyl-1,4-hexadiene,
1,4-hexadiene and 5-vinyl-2-norbornene is preferred. 5-vinyl-2-norbornene
is particularly preferred as a diene component of such
rubber.</p><p num="0023">Butyl rubbers are also useful in the compositions of the invention.
As used in the specification and claims, the term "butyl rubber" includes
copolymers of an isoolefin and a conjugated monoolefin and divinyl
aromatic monomers, and the halogenated derivatives derivatives of such
copolymers and terpolymers. The useful butyl rubber copolymers
comprise a major portion of isoolefin and a minor amount, usually less
than 30 wt%, of a conjugated multiolefin. The preferred copolymers
comprise about 85-99.5 wt% of a C<sub>4-7</sub> isoolefin such as isobutylene
and about 15-0.5 wt% of a multiolefin of 4-14 carbon atoms, such as
isoprene, butadiene, dimethyl butadiene, 4-methyl-1,4-pentadiene and
piperylene. Commercial butyl rubber, useful in the invention, is a
copolymer of isobutylene and minor amounts of isoprene. Other butyl
co- and terpolymer rubbers are illustrated by the description in U.S. Pat.
No. 4,916,180. Polymers from isobutylene and aromatic divinyl e.g.
(divinylbenzene) are particularly preferred as an elastomer suitable for
hydrosilylation crosslinking, as are the halogenated derivatives of butyl
rubber such as chlorobutyl and bromobutyl. The structure and
composition of co- and terpolymer rubbers from isobutylene and
aromatic divinyl compounds are disclosed in U.S. Patents 3,584,080 and
4,916,180 hereby incorporated by reference.</p><p num="0024">A further rubber suitable in the invention is natural rubber. The
main constituent of natural rubber is the linear polymer cis-1,4-polyisoprene.
It is normally commercially available in the form of
smoked sheets and crepe. Synthetic polyisoprene can also be used with
the particularly preferred synthetic polyisoprene elastomers being those 
that contain vinyl functionality pendant to the main polymer chain, i.e.
1,2-enchainments.</p><p num="0025">Polybutadiene is also a suitable elastomer for hydrosilylation
curing, with polybutadienes that contain vinyl functionality being the
most preferred.</p><p num="0026">Blends of any of the above rubbers may also be employed, rather
than a single olefinic rubber.</p><p num="0027">In preparing the compositions of the invention, the amount of
rubber generally ranges from about 95 to about 10 weight percent,
based on the weight of the rubber and thermoplastic resin. Preferably,
the rubber content will be in the range of from about 80 to about 20
weight percent of total thermoplastic resin, alkoxysilane or silanol
functionalized polyolefin, and rubber.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>Hydrosilylation Catalysts</b></u></heading><p num="0028">It has previously been understood that any catalyst, or catalyst
precursor capable of generating a catalyst in situ, which will catalyze the
hydrosilylation reaction with the carbon-carbon bonds of the rubber can
be used. Such catalysts have included transition metals of Group VIII
such as palladium, rhodium, platinum and the like, including complexes
of these metals. Chloroplatinic acid has been disclosed as a useful
catalyst in U.S. Pat. No. 4,803,244 and European Application No.
651,009, which further disclose that the catalyst may be used at
concentrations of 5 to 10,000 parts per million by weight and 100 to
200,000 parts per million by weight based on the weight of rubber,
respectively.</p><p num="0029">It has been found in the process of the present invention that
significantly lower concentrations of platinum-containing catalyst can be
used, while obtaining improvement in both the speed of the reaction and
the efficiency of the crosslinking. Concentrations of catalyst in the 
range of about 0.01 to about 20, 50, 100 or 400 parts per million by
weight, expressed as platinum metal, are effective in rapidly and
completely curing the rubber in the process of dynamically vulcanizing
blends of thermoplastic resin and rubber. These low catalyst
concentrations are particularly effective in combination with a diene-containing
rubber having carbon-carbon multiple bonds which are
predominately sterically unhindered Catalyst concentrations of about
0.1 to about 4 parts per million by weight based on the weight of
rubber, expressed as platinum metal, are particularly preferred for the
preferred EPDM rubbers.</p><p num="0030">Platinum-containing catalysts which are useful in the process of
the invention are described, for example, in U.S. Pat. No. 4,578,497;
U.S. Pat. No. 3,220,972; and U.S. Patent No. 2,823,218 all of which
are incorporated herein by this reference. These catalysts include
chloroplatinic acid, chloroplatinic acid hexahydrate, complexes of
chloroplatinic acid with sym-divinyltetramethyldisiloxane, dichloro-bis(triphenylphosphine)
platinum (II), cis-dichloro-bis(acetonitrile)
platinum (II), dicarbonyldichloroplatinum (II), platinum chloride and
platinum oxide. Zero valent platinum metal complexes such as Karstedt's
catalyst are particularly preferred, as described in U.S. Pat. No.
3,775,452; U.S. Pat. No. 3,814,730; and U.S. Pat. No. 4,288,345 all
of which are incorporated herein by this reference.</p> <p num="0031">In order for the catalyst to function most efficiently in the
dynamic vulcanization environment, it is important that it is inherently
thermally stable, or that its activity is inhibited to prevent too rapid a
reaction or catalyst decomposition. Appropriate catalyst inhibitors that
are suitable to stabilize the platinum catalyst at high temperatures
include 1,3,5,7-tetravinyl-1,3,5,7-tetramethylcyclotetrasiloxane and its
higher analogs such as vinyl cyclic pentamer. However, other olefins
that are stable above 165° C are also useful. These include maleates, 
fumarates and the cyclic pentamer. It is also particularly preferred in the
invention to use a catalyst that remains soluble in the reaction medium.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>Additives</b></u></heading><p num="0032">The thermoplastic elastomer may contain conventional additives,
which can be introduced into the composition in the thermoplastic resin,
the rubber, or in the blend either before, during or after the
hydrosilylation and curing. Examples of such additives are antioxidants,
processing aids, reinforcing and nonreinforcing fillers, pigments, waxes,
rubber processing oil, extender oils, antiblocking agents, antistatic
agents, ultraviolet stabilizers, plasticizers (including esters), foaming
agents, flame retardants and other processing aids known to the rubber
compounding art. Such additives may comprise from about 0.1 to
about 300 percent by weight based on the weight of the final
thermoplastic elastomer product. Fillers and extenders which can be
utilized include conventional inorganics such as calcium carbonate,
clays, silica, talc, titanium dioxide, carbon black and the like. Additives,
fillers or other compounds which may interfere with the hydrosilylation
should be added after curing reaches the desired level.</p> <p num="0033">In another embodiment, it has been found that the heat aging
properties of compositions prepared according to the invention can be
greatly improved by the addition of a metal chelating agent to the blend.
This effect is believed to be due to the fact that the hydrosilylation
catalyst is in an active valence state. This form of the platinum metal
accelerates degradation of the thermoplastic elastomer, particularly
under conditions of elevated temperature over an extended time.
Chelation prevents the metal from causing degradation.</p> <p num="0034">Typical chelating agents useful for this purpose include materials
such as 1,2-bis(3,5-di-ter-butyl-4-hydroxyhydrocinnamoyl)hydrazine and
the like. Surprisingly, these agents may be incorporated into the 
composition prior to or after the hydrosilylation curing. Amounts of
chelating agent ranging from about 0.025 parts per hundred parts of
rubber (phr) to about 10 phr have been found to be useful, and amounts
in the range of about 0.1 phr to 2 phr are preferred.</p> <p num="0035">In a further embodiment of the invention, it has been
demonstrated that reducing residual or unreacted silicon hydride
functionality in the thermoplastic elastomer products results in
compositions which have improved heat stability. Unreacted silicon
hydride may be reduced or eliminated by reacting the silicon hydride
with compounds containing active hydrogen, carbon-carbon multiple
bonds, carbon-oxygen double bonds or carbon-nitrogen double bonds
and the like. The residual silicon hydride reacts with these compounds
to eliminate the silicon hydride functionality and form silicon-oxygen or
carbon-silicon bonds.</p><p num="0036">Typical compounds useful for this purpose are silica and water.
These agents are incorporated into the composition after the
hydrosilylation cure is complete. Water may be introduced as steam
anytime after cure in a single or two pass operation. As previously
mentioned the majority of the thermoplastic phase remains melt
processable after this rather than being crosslinked as set forth in EP
0855 426 A1 Amounts of such compounds may be estimated by
measuring residual silicon hydride and adding a stoichiometric amount of
the compound. One may also desire to add a stoichiometric excess if
necessary to eliminate a sufficient amount of the residual silicon hydride
in order to realize the desired improvement in heat aging properties.
Amounts of such compounds ranging from about one mole equivalent to
about 10 mole equivalents have been found to be useful, and amounts in
the range of about 1 to 3 mole equivalents are preferred. </p><heading><u style="single"><b>Extender Oil</b></u></heading><p num="0037">The rubber processing or extender oils used in thermoplastic
elastomers generally are paraffinic, naphthenic or aromatic oils derived
from petroleum fractions. The type will be that ordinarily used in
conjunction with the specific rubber or rubbers present in the
composition, and the quantity based on the total rubber content of the
thermoplastic elastomer may range from zero to several hundred parts
per hundred rubber. Important to the efficiency of the catalyst is that
the oils and other additives contain no or very low concentrations of
compounds that are catalyst inhibitors or that interfere with the activity
of the catalyst. These compounds include phosphines, amines, sulfides,
thiols or other compounds that may be classified as Lewis bases. Lewis
bases, or other compounds that have a pair of electrons available for
donation, will react with the platinum catalyst, effectively neutralizing its
activity. It has been discovered that the presence of such compounds
has a surprisingly detrimental impact on hydrosilylation curing in the
process of dynamic vulcanization of the rubber component of the
thermoplastic elastomer compositions. If the concentration of
compounds which have the chemical reactivity of Lewis bases, such as
compounds containing sulfur or nitrogen, is maintained at or below a
level which provides less than about 1000 ppm and 300 ppm of sulfur
and nitrogen respectively, then the amount of platinum catalyst required
to promote efficient hydrosilylation curing in dynamic vulcanization can
be substantially reduced, usually to the range of about 4 ppm or less,
without impact on the cure state of the rubber or the tensile properties
of the thermoplastic elastomer product. Concentrations of sulfur and
nitrogen below about 500 and 200 ppm respectively are more preferred,
and concentrations of less than about 30 ppm sulfur and less than about
100 ppm nitrogen are most preferred. It has been discovered that, even
at catalyst concentrations as low as 0.25 ppm, full cure of the elastomer 
can be achieved if the concentration of sulfur and nitrogen is within the
most preferred ranges.</p><p num="0038">Most paraffinic petroleum oils for the rubber industry are derived
from a crude oil distillation stream. A typical refining history would
include some type of dewaxing to reduce the pour point, a solvent
extraction to physically remove aromatic compounds and a hydrotreating
process to chemically modify aromatic structures. Both extraction and
hydrotreating result in a net increase in the total concentration of
saturated hydrocarbon structures and a net decrease in the total
aromatic, sulfur and nitrogen-containing compound concentration. The
degree of reduction in concentration of these compounds in the oil is
dependent upon the type and severity of the refining employed, and the
nature of the crude oil. White and paraffinic oils have been treated more
extensively than aromatic and napthenic oils and would contain a smaller
concentration of aromatic, sulfur and/or nitrogen compounds. It is
difficult to elucidate the exact chemical structure of these compounds
due to their complexity. The tendency of an oil to interfere with
platinum catalyzed hydrosilylation is directly related to the concentration
of sulfur and nitrogen containing compounds, as well as compounds
which contain phosphorus, tin, arsenic, aluminum and iron.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>Processing</b></u></heading><p num="0039">The rubber component of the thermoplastic elastomer is generally
present as small, i.e. micro-size, particles within a continuous
thermoplastic resin matrix, although a co-continuous morphology or a
phase inversion is also possible depending upon the amount of rubber
relative to plastic and the degree of cure of the rubber. The rubber is
desirably at least partially crosslinked, and preferably is completely or
fully crosslinked. It is preferred that the rubber be crosslinked by the
process of dynamic vulcanization. As used in the specification and 
claims, the term "dynamic vulcanization" means a vulcanization or
curing process for a rubber blended with a thermoplastic resin, wherein
the rubber is vulcanized under conditions of shear at a temperature at
which the mixture will flow. The rubber is thus simultaneously
crosslinked and dispersed as fine particles within the thermoplastic resin
matrix, although as noted above other morphologies may exist. Dynamic
vulcanization is effected by mixing the thermoplastic elastomer
components at elevated temperatures in conventional mixing equipment
such as roll mills, Banbury mixers, Brabender mixers, continuous mixers,
mixing extruders and the like. The unique characteristic of dynamically
cured compositions is that, notwithstanding the fact that the rubber
component is partially or fully cured, the compositions can be processed
and reprocessed by conventional plastic processing techniques such as
extrusion, injection molding and compression molding. Scrap or flashing
can be salvaged and reprocessed.</p><p num="0040">The terms "fully vulcanized" and "fully cured" or "fully
crosslinked" as used in the specification and claims means that the
rubber component to be vulcanized has been cured or crosslinked to a
state in which the elastomeric properties of the crosslinked rubber are
similar to those of the rubber in its conventional vulcanized state, apart
from the thermoplastic elastomer composition. The degree of cure can
be described in terms of gel content, or conversely, extractable
components. Gel content reported as percent gel (based on the weight
of crosslinkable rubber) is determined by a procedure which comprises
determining the amount of insoluble polymer by soaking the specimen
for 48 hours in organic solvent at room temperature, weighing the dried
residue and making suitable corrections based upon knowledge of the
composition. Thus, corrected initial and final weights are obtained by
subtracting from the initial weight the weight of soluble components,
other than rubber to be vulcanized, such as extender oils, plasticizers 
and components of the composition soluble in organic solvent, as well
as that rubber component of the product which is not intended to be
cured. Any insoluble polyolefins, pigments, fillers, and the like are
subtracted from both the initial and final weights. The rubber
component can be described as fully cured when less than about 5%,
and preferably less than 3%, of the rubber which is capable of being
cured by hydrosilylation is extractable from the thermoplastic elastomer
product by a solvent for that rubber. Alternatively the degree of cure
may be expressed in terms of crosslink density. All of these descriptions
are well known in the art, for example in U.S. Pat. Nos. 4,593,062,
5,100,947 and 5,157,081, all of which are fully incorporated herein by
this reference.</p><p num="0041">The following general procedure was used in the preparation of
thermoplastic elastomers by the process of the invention, as set forth in
the examples. The thermoplastic resin and oil extended rubber were
placed in a heated internal mixer, with the hydrosilylation agent and
hydrosilylation catalyst. The hydrosilylation agent and catalyst can be
incorporated into the composition by any suitable technique, for example
by injection as solutions in oil or as neat components, although a dilute
catalyst solution is preferred. Additives such as antioxidants, ultraviolet
stabilizers and fillers may also be added as a slurry in oil. Masterbatches
of the components may also be prepared to facilitate the blending
process. The mixture was heated to a temperature sufficient to melt the
thermoplastic component, and the mixture was masticated, with added
processing oil if desired, until a maximum of mixing torque indicated that
vulcanization had occurred. Mixing was continued until the desired
degree of vulcanization was achieved.</p><p num="0042">The order of addition of the hydrosilylation agent and
hydrosilylation catalyst was found to be important. Maximum catalyst
efficiency was obtained when the hydrosilylation agent was added first 
to the blend, followed by the hydrosilylation catalyst. The mechanical
properties of the thermoplastic elastomer products, as well as the degree
of cure, were improved when this order of addition was followed.</p><p num="0043">The invention will be better understood by reference to the
following examples which serve to illustrate but not limit the present
process. In the examples, the following test methods were used to
determine the properties of the thermoplastic elastomer products.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Hardness (Shore A/D)</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 2240</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ultimate tensile strength (UTS - psi)</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 412</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ultimate elongation (UE - %)</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 412</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Modulus at 100 or 300% elongation (M1 or M3 - psi)</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D412</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compression set (CS - %) Method B, 22 hrs 100°C</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 395</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil swell (OS - %)</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 471</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single"><b>EXAMPLES</b></u></heading><p num="0044">When a silane grafted polyolefin is used in an EPDM/polyolefin DVA
which has been dynamically vulcanized using hydrosilylation,
improvements are observed in compression set properties of the
composition with little or no changes in the other properties. A
reduction in compression set of between 10 and 25% is observed. The
following are examples that were formulated with a silane grafted
polypropylene from Mitsubishi, Linklon XPM 800H. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>Control A</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 1</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Control B</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 2</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Control C</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Example 3</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Recipes</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Si-H (phr)</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elastomer</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pt Calalyst (ppm)</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil (phr)</entry><entry align="center">130</entry><entry align="center">130</entry><entry align="center">130</entry><entry align="center">130</entry><entry align="center">130</entry><entry align="center">130</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Clay Filler (phr)</entry><entry align="center">42</entry><entry align="center">42</entry><entry align="center">42</entry><entry align="center">42</entry><entry align="center">42</entry><entry align="center">42</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polypropylene (phr)</entry><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">88</entry><entry align="center">79</entry><entry align="center">153</entry><entry align="center">138</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Linklon (phr)</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">15</entry></row><row><entry align="left"> </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Shore A</entry><entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="center">83</entry><entry align="center">83</entry><entry align="center">91</entry><entry align="center">90</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UTS</entry><entry align="center">880</entry><entry align="center">880</entry><entry align="center">1500</entry><entry align="center">1470</entry><entry align="center">1920</entry><entry align="center">1910</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UE</entry><entry align="center">380</entry><entry align="center">330</entry><entry align="center">470</entry><entry align="center">410</entry><entry align="center">500</entry><entry align="center">490</entry></row><row><entry align="left">M1</entry><entry align="center">350</entry><entry align="center">370</entry><entry align="center">800</entry><entry align="center">830</entry><entry align="center">1170</entry><entry align="center">1090</entry></row><row><entry align="left">M3</entry><entry align="center">770</entry><entry align="center">820</entry><entry align="center">1200</entry><entry align="center">1260</entry><entry align="center">1540</entry><entry align="center">1460</entry></row><row><entry align="left">CS%</entry><entry align="center">28.3</entry><entry align="center">22.0</entry><entry align="center">43.0</entry><entry align="center">38.8</entry><entry align="center">52.0</entry><entry align="center">45.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">OS%</entry><entry align="center">96</entry><entry align="center">94</entry><entry align="center">71</entry><entry align="center">69</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">56</entry></row><row><entry>The Elastomer in this example was Keltan P597 from DSM Copolymer in Baton Rouge, LA. This
polymer contains 100 phr of oil. The amount of rubber in the table represents the rubber less the oil
and the amount of oil shown in the table includes the oil added with the rubber.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0045">Controls A, B, and C and Examples 1, 2, and 3 vary in their
relative ratio of thermoplastic to rubber. The additional second
polypropylene (Linklon) in the examples was substituted for an
equivalent weight of conventional polypropylene in the preceeding
control. The substitution typically results in similar Shore A hardness
and modulus values in each control and following example. The Linklon
could have been an added component but that would dilute the relative
amount of other components. The compression set (CS) always
decreased with the addition of Linklon and the other physical properties
were generally comparable.</p><p num="0046">While the best mode and preferred embodiment of the
invention has been set forth in accord with the Patent Statutes, the
scope of the invention is not limited thereto, but rather is defined by the
attached claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A thermoplastic elastomer, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) a melt processable first thermoplastic polyolefin</claim-text><claim-text>b) an unsaturated rubber crosslinked with a hydrosilylation
crosslinking agent and interdispersed with said thermoplastic
polyolefin</claim-text><claim-text>c) a second thermoplastic polyolefin with at least one -(OR)
group pendant directly from an Si atom, which Si atom is
chemically attached via one or more intermediate molecules to
said second polyolefin wherein R is a hydrogen or an alkyl of 1 to 8
carbon atoms, said second thermoplastic polyolefin having been
exposed to and optionally reacted with said hydrosilylation
crosslinking agent, and wherein said second polyolefin is present
from about 0.1 to about 25 weight percent of the combined weight
of said first and second thermoplastic polyolefins.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A thermoplastic elastomer according to claim 1, wherein said
second polyolefin with at least one pendant OR group and said Si atom
are present together in an amount from about 5 to about 20 wt. %
based upon the weight of said first semi-crystalline thermoplastic
polyolefin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A thermoplastic elastomer according to claim 2, wherein second
semi-crystalline thermoplastic polyolefin is the reaction product of a
semi-crystalline polyolefin with a silane having a group and an -Si-OR,
-Si(OR)2, or -Si(OR)3 group or combinations thereof wherein each OR
independently is a hydroxyl or alkoxy group of 1 to 8 carbon atoms.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A thermoplastic elastomer according to claim 3, further including
from about 0.1 to about 100 ppm of platinum metal derived from a
platinum catalyst used to catalyze said hydrosilylation crosslinking agent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A thermoplastic elastomer according to claim 3, wherein said first
semi-crystalline polyolefin comprises polypropylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A thermoplastic elastomer according to claim 4, wherein said first
semi-crystalline polyolefin comprises polypropylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A thermoplastic elastomer according to claim 3, having a weight
ratio of about 20 to about 80 parts by weight of said combined first and
second thermoplastic polyolefin to about 80 to about 20 parts by weight
of said unsaturated rubber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A thermoplastic elastomer according to claim 7, wherein said
unsaturated rubber comprises EPDM.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A process for preparing a thermoplastic vulcanizate, comprising:
blending in any order
<claim-text><claim-text>a) a first semi-crystalline thermoplastic polyolefin</claim-text><claim-text>b) an unsaturated rubber and</claim-text><claim-text>c) a second thermoplastic polyolefin present in an amount from
about 0.1 to about 25 weight percent based on the combined
weight of said first and second polyolefin including at least one OR
group bonded to a silicon atom pendantly attached to said second
polyolefin wherein R is a hydrogen or an alkyl of 1 to 8 carbon
atoms and</claim-text><claim-text>d) a hydrosilylation crosslinking agent and
chemically bonding at least a portion of said second polyolefin
to said hydrosilylation crosslinking agent,
<claim-text><claim-text>crosslinking said rubber with said hydrosilylation crosslinking
agent,
wherein said blending, chemically bonding, and crosslinking
steps need not be in any particular order and any one or more steps
can occur concurrently.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A process according to claim 9, further including a hydrosilylation
catalyst which includes a platinum atom.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A process according to claim 9, wherein said crosslinking of said
unsaturated rubber occurs after at least said first polyolefin and said
unsaturated rubber are blended.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A process according to claim 9, wherein said crosslinking of said
unsaturated rubber occurs after said first polyolefin, said second
polyolefin and said unsaturated rubber are blended.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A process according to claim 10, wherein said hydrosilylation
catalyst is present after said first polyolefin, said second polyolefin, and
said unsaturated rubber are blended and said catalyst promotes both the
crosslinking of said unsaturated rubber and the chemical bonding of said
second polyolefin to said rubber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A process according to claim 9, wherein said first polyolefin, said
second polyolefin and said unsaturated rubber are blended at least
contemporaneously with said crosslinking of said unsaturated rubber and
said chemical bonding of at least a portion of said second polyolefin to
said unsaturated rubber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A process according to claim 13, wherein said first polyolefin
comprises polypropylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A process according to claim 15, wherein said unsaturated rubber
comprises EPDM.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A process according to claim 14, wherein said first polyolefin
comprises polypropylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A process according to claim 17, wherein said unsaturated rubber
comprises EPDM.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A process according to claim 17, wherein said second polyolefin
comprises a backbone of at least 80 weight percent repeat units from
propylene.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>