<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1433751-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1433751" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="32463487" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040630"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1433751-A1" status="new" fvid="24069591"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1433751</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040630</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03258009-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03258009</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031218</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002369748-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002369748</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021220</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  21/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  21/06        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  35/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  35/02        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01G  23/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01G  23/04        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01G  23/053       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01G  23/08        20060101AFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C01G  23/053B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M01P6:12</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung von Titanoxid</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">A method for producing titanium oxide</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new"  lang="FR">Procédé de fabrication d'oxyde de titane</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1031538-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1031538</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1178011-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1178011</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1338564-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1338564</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-764084-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>764084</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SUMITOMO CHEMICAL CO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SUMITOMO CHEMICAL COMPANY, LIMITED</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SUMITOMO CHEMICAL COMPANY, LIMITED</last-name><address><street>5-33, Kitahama 4-chome</street><city>Chuo-ku Osaka 541-8550</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OKUSAKO KENSEN</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OKUSAKO, KENSEN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OKUSAKO, KENSEN</last-name><address><street>1-2-433, Sairenji-cho</street><city>Niihama-shi Ehime</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Cresswell, Thomas Anthony</last-name><address><street>J.A. KEMP &amp;amp; CO. 14 South Square Gray's Inn</street><city>LONDON WC1R 5JJ</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents> </parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country> </ep-contracting-states> </designated-states> </international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention provides a method for producing a titanium oxide. The
method can be applied to produce a titanium oxide having a large specific surface
area. The method typically entails calcining at least one titanium oxide precursor
selected from a titanium hydroxide and titanium peroxide, wherein the calcination
occurs in the presence of nitrogen and at a steam pressure of at most about 8,000 Pa.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>Technical Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a method for producing
a titanium oxide. More specifically, the present invention
relates to a method for producing a titanium oxide having a
large specific surface area, which is useful as a catalyst.</p><heading>Background of the Invention</heading><p num="0002">Titanium oxide has been widely utilized as a catalyst.
For example, titanium oxide has been used as a hydrogenation
catalyst for producing higher alcohols and as a carrier for
a catalyst treating exhaust gas. Given such circumstances,
the uses of titanium oxide has been expanded and a titanium
oxide having a high specific surface area has been desired.</p><p num="0003">It has been known that titanium oxide can be produced
by a method of hydrolyzing a titanium compound such as a
titanium sulfate and a titanium chloride to obtain a
titanium hydroxide and calcining the titanium compound.
However, by such conventional method, it has been difficult
to produce a titanium oxide having a large specific surface area.</p><heading>Summary of the Invention</heading><p num="0004">One of objects of the present invention is to provide a
method for producing a titanium oxide having a large
specific surface area. The method typically comprises the
step of calcining at least one titanium oxide precursor
selected from a titanium hydroxide and a titanium peroxide,
wherein said calcination is conducted in the presence of
nitrogen molecules and at a steam pressure of at most about
8,000 Pa.</p><heading>Brief Description of the Drawings</heading><p num="0005"><sl><li>Figure 1 shows a schematic diagram of an air-blow
furnace which can be used in the present invention.</li><li>Figure 2 shows a schematic diagram of a fluidized-bed
furnace which can be used in the present invention.</li><li>Figure 3 shows a schematic diagram of a tubular-type
furnace which can be used in the present invention.</li><li>Figure 4 shows a schematic diagram of a device which
can be employed in the present invention (see, Example 1).</li></sl></p><heading>Detailed Description of the Invention</heading><p num="0006">In the present invention, a titanium oxide precursor is
calcined to produce a titanium oxide.</p><p num="0007">The titanium oxide precursor is at least one compound
selected from a titanium hydroxide and a titanium peroxide. 
Examples of the titanium hydroxide include Ti(OH)<sub>2</sub>, Ti(OH)<sub>3</sub>,
Ti(OH)<sub>4</sub>, TiO(OH)<sub>2</sub> and the like. The titanium hydroxide can
be produced by a method in which a titanium compound in an
aqueous solution thereof is reacted with a base. Examples
of a titanium compound that can be utilized in such a method
include a titanium chloride, a titanium oxychloride, a
titanium sulfate, a titanium oxysulfate and the like. The
utilized base may be a sodium hydroxide, a sodium carbonate,
a sodium hydrogencarbonate, a potassium hydroxide, a
potassium carbonate, a potassium hydrogencarbonate, an
ammonia, an amine, an imine, an amino acid, a hydroxylamine
derivative, a hydrazine derivative or the like. The molar
amount of such a base to be used may be about 1.1 times or
more, preferably about 1.5 times or more, and about 20 times
or less, preferably about 10 times or less, based on the
stoichiometric molar amount of base for converting the
titanium compound to titanium hydroxide. The reaction can
be conducted at a temperature of about 70°C or lower,
preferably at a temperature of about 60 °C or lower, and
even more preferably at a temperature of about 55 °C or
lower. The temperature may be about 0 °C or higher, and is
preferably about 5 °C or higher. Alternatively, the
titanium hydroxide can be produced by heating the aqueous 
solution of the titanium compound to a temperature, for
example, of about 95 °C or higher to carry out hydrolysis of
the titanium compound.</p><p num="0008">The titanium peroxide can take at least 3 general forms
for the calcination. For example, the titanium peroxide can
be a compound in which some of its Ti-O-H bonds in a
titanium hydroxide (such as Ti(OH)<sub>2</sub>, Ti (OH)<sub>3</sub> , Ti(OH)<sub>4</sub> and
Ti0(OH)<sub>2</sub>) have been replaced to Ti-O-O-H bonds or the like.
Examples of such a titanium peroxide include Ti(OH)<sub>3</sub>OOH.
Further, the titanium peroxide can be a compound in which
some of its Ti-O bonds in a titanium oxide (such as TiO,
Ti<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and TiO<sub>2</sub>) have been replaced to Ti-O-O bonds or the
like. Examples of such a titanium peroxide include
TiO<sub>2</sub>(OH)<sub>2</sub>. Furthermore, the titanium hydroxide may be a
combination thereof, such as a compound encompassed by
formula (I).
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Ti(O<sub>2</sub>)<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub>(OH)<sub>z</sub></st32:che>
wherein "x" represents more than 0 but less than 4 (0&lt;x&lt;4),
"y" represents at least 0 but less than 2 (0≦y&lt;2), and "z"
represents at least 0 but less than 4 (0≦z&lt;4). Examples of
such a titanium peroxide include Ti (O<sub>2</sub>) (OH)<sub>2</sub> and Ti(O<sub>2</sub>)O(OH)<sub>2</sub>.
The titanium peroxide can be produced by mixing a hydrogen
peroxide with the aqueous solution of the above-described
titanium compound and then reacting the resulting mixture 
with a base. The molar amount of hydrogen peroxide to be
used in such a case may be at least about 0.1 time,
preferably at least about 1 time, and may be at most about 5
times, of the molar amount of titanium atom present in the
titanium compound. Similar to the above, the utilized base
may be a sodium hydroxide, a sodium carbonate, a sodium
hydrogencarbonate, a potassium hydroxide, a potassium
carbonate, a potassium hydrogencarbonate, an ammonia, an
amine, an imine, an amino acid, a hydroxylamine derivative,
a hydrazine derivative or the like. The amount of the base
to be used may be about 1.1 times or more, preferably about
1.5 times or more, and about 20 times or less, preferably
about 10 times or less, based on the stoichiometric molar
amount of base for converting the titanium compound to
titanium peroxide. The reaction with the base may be
conducted at a temperature of about 65 °C or lower, is
preferably at about 60 °C or lower, and is even more
preferably at about 55 °C or lower. The temperature may be
about 0 °C or higher, and is preferably 5 °C or higher.</p><p num="0009">The thus-obtained titanium oxide precursor can be
washed, if needed. The washing can be conducted by
utilizing water or a hydrogen peroxide, which may be 
followed by a procedure involving filtration, centrifuge,
decantation or the like.</p><p num="0010">The titanium oxide precursor (which may be optionally
washed as described above) is typically calcined in the
presence of steam (or water vapor) and nitrogen gas, wherein
the steam pressure is at most about 8,000 Pa. The lower the
steam pressure is, the larger specific surface area the
resulting titanium oxide tends to have. In this regard, it
is preferable to conduct the calcination under the steam
pressure of at most about 3,000 Pa, more preferably of at
most about 600 Pa and even more preferably of at most about
200 Pa. Typically, the calcination is conducted at a total
gas pressure of at least about 10,000 Pa, and preferably at
least about 90,000 Pa. The calcination may be also
conducted at a total gas pressure of at most about 200,000
Pa and preferably at most about 150,000 Pa. Although not
outside the scope of the present invention, when the total
pressure is lower than the above lower limit, heat
transmission during the calcination can be lowered, which
results in lowering heat efficiency in the calcination.</p><p num="0011">The calcination is typically conducted in the presence
of nitrogen molecules. The amount of nitrogen molecules in
the calcination environment may be at least about 50 % by
volume, and is preferably at least about 70 % by volume, 
based on the total volume of the total gas volume in the
environment. The calcination may also be carried out in the
presence of other gases, such as a helium, a neon, an argon,
a krypton, a xenon, a carbon dioxide, a nitrogen oxide, a
nitrogen dioxide, an ammonia, an oxygen and the like.</p><p num="0012">The steam pressure and the nitrogen-molecules amount in
the calcination environment can be regulated by introducing
a gas into the calcination environment. It is preferable
that the gas is prepared to have the appropriate steam
pressure and/or nitrogen-molecules amount before introducing
the gas into the calcination environment. The gas is
typically nitrogen and/or the other gas as above-described,
such as a helium, a neon, an argon, a krypton, a xenon, a
carbon dioxide, a nitrogen oxide, a nitrogen dioxide, an
ammonia, an oxygen and the like. In order to adjust the
steam pressure, such gases may be prepared by compressing
the provided gas, condensing the steam (or water vapor)
present in the gas, removing the condensed steam from the
gas, and then decompressing the gas. The gases may also be
prepared by treating the provided gas with a dehumidifier, a
moisture absorbent or the like to remove the steam from the
gas. In order to adjust the nitrogen-molecules amount, an
additional gas (such as nitrogen and the other gas), which 
may have been dehumidified, can be introduced into the
calcination environment.</p><p num="0013">The environment for the calcination can be maintained
in a furnace that can maintain a sufficient temperature, the
nitrogen amount for the calcination and the steam pressure
for the calcination. Examples of such a furnace include a
tunnel furnace, a far infrared radiation furnace, a
microwave furnace, a shaft furnace, a reverberatory furnace,
a rotary furnace, a roller herce furnace, a pneumatic
conveying dryer, a flowing furnace, a tubular-type electric
furnace, a box-type electric furnace and the like. It is
preferable that the furnace can provide a gas from outside
of the calcination environment into the calcination
environment. The gas may be heated before or after being
introduced into the calcination environment. Typically,
such preferred types of the furnaces have a device for
controlling the amount of gas introduced into the
calcination environment. Such preferred types of furnaces
provide easier control over the steam pressure and the
nitrogen amount in the calcination environment. For example,
such preferred types of furnaces can more easily regulate
the fluctuations of steam pressure and nitrogen amount
arising from the steam released from heating the titanium
oxide precursor. </p><p num="0014">Illustrations of the furnace are given in Figures 1, 2
and 3. The devices depicted in Figures 1 and 2 are devices
which can continuously deliver the calcination product out
of the calcination device, while the titanium oxide
precursor is continuously added to the device. The device
depicted in Figure 3 is a device which can calcine the
titanium oxide precursor by, first, adding the titanium
oxide precursor to the calcination device; second, stopping
the addition of the titanium oxide precursor; and third,
adding hot gas into the calcination device.</p><p num="0015">The device depicted in Figure 1 is typically known as a
pneumatic conveying dryer. The air-blow furnace has pipes 1,
3, 5 and 8, a dehumidifier 2, a heater 4, a main chamber 6,
a feeding inlet 7, a separator 9, a solid exit 10 and a gas
exit 11. Pipe 1 is for introducing gas such as an air and
is connected to the dehumidifier 2. Pipe 3 connects the
dehumidifier 2 to the heater 4. Pipe 5 connects the heater
4 to the main chamber 6. Pipe 8 connects the main chamber 6
to the separator 9. In the pneumatic conveying dryer, the
titanium oxide precursor is introduced into the main chamber
6 through the feeding inlet 7 and contacts the hot gas
introduced through pipe 5. The hot gas carries the titanium
oxide precursor so that the titanium oxide precursor
circulates around the main chamber 6 and is calcined. The 
calcination product is delivered to the separator 9 through
the pipe 8 to separate the calcination product from the gas.
The calcination product exits through the solid exit 10.
The gas containing the steam arising from heating the
titanium oxide precursor exits through the gas exit 11.
Further, the pneumatic conveying dryer typically has a
thermometer located at one or two or more locations in the
main chamber 6 to monitor the calcination temperature. The
gases, such as an ammonia and a nitrogen, which have been
dehumidified, can be introduced into the pipe 3 or pipe 5 to
regulate the calcination environment. While Figure 1
depicts an pneumatic conveying dryer with one chamber, the
pneumatic conveying dryer may have 2 or more chambers to
regulate the residence time (or calcination time) of the
titanium oxide precursor in the furnace. In such cases, the
chambers may be connected with one another. The pneumatic
conveying dryer may have another pipe (not shown) which
connects the solid exit 10 with the feeding inlet 7 so that
the calcination product from the solid exit 10 is introduced
into the furnace to be calcined again.</p><p num="0016">Further, the device shown in Figure 2 is known as a
flowing furnace. The flowing furnace has pipes 12, 14, 16
and 22, a dehumidifier 13, a heater 15, a main chamber 17, a
feeding inlet 20, a separator 23, lattice boards 18 and 19, 
medium 21, a solid exit 24 and a gas exit 25. Pipe 12 is
for introducing gas such as an air and is connected to the
dehumidifier 13. Pipe 14 connects the dehumidifier 13 to
the heater 15. Pipe 16 connects the dehumidifier 15 to the
main chamber 17. Pipe 22 connects the main chamber 17 to
the separator 23. In the flowing furnace, the lattice
boards 18 and 19 are located at the upper and lower portions,
respectively, in the main chamber 17. The main chamber 17
is packed with medium 21. The titanium oxide precursor is
introduced into the main chamber 17 through the feeding
inlet 20 and contacts the hot gas introduced through pipe 16.
The titanium oxide precursor is calcined while flowing in
the main chamber 17. The calcination product is delivered
to the separator 23 through the pipe 22 to separate the
calcination product from the gas. The calcination product
exits through the solid exit 24. The gas containing the
steam arising from heating the titanium oxide precursor
exits through the gas exit 25.</p><p num="0017">The device depicted in Figure 3 may be called a
tubular-type electric furnace. The tubular-type electric
furnace has pipes 26 and 28, a dehumidifier 27, a heater
(not shown), a tubular main chamber 29 and a gas exit 30.
Pipe 26 is for introducing gas such as an air and is 
connected to the dehumidifier 27. Pipe 28 connects the
dehumidifier 27 to a main chamber 29. The heater is
installed for heating the inside of the main chamber 29.
Examples of the heater include a resistance heater, an
induction heater and the like. In the tubular-type electric
furnace, the titanium oxide precursor is placed into the
main chamber 29. The gas introduced into pipe 26 is treated
in the dehumidifier 27 so as to have an appropriate steam
pressure, and is then introduced into the main chamber 29
through pipe 28. The gas is heated in the main chamber 29.
The titanium oxide precursor is calcinated in the main
chamber 29 by maintaining the heat and environment provided
by the gas introduced through pipe 28. The gas containing
the steam arising from heating the titanium oxide precursor
exits through gas exit 30. After the calcination, the main
chamber 29 is cooled so that the calcination product can be
removed from the main chamber 29.</p><p num="0018">When the gas is introduced into a calcination device
(such as a furnace), the total volumetric amount of the gas
to be introduced may be at least about 100 times and is
preferably at least about 1,000 times, in terms of the
volume converted in a standard state, based on the total
volume of the titanium oxide precursor to be calcined. As 
used herein, "standard state" refers to an environment at
20 °C under 1 atmosphere.</p><p num="0019">The temperature of the calcination is a temperature at
which the titanium oxide precursor can be converted to a
titanium oxide. The calcination may be conducted at a
temperature of at least about 200 °C, is preferably at least
about 250°C, and is more preferably at least about 300 °C.
Further, the calcination may be conducted at a temperature
of at most about 650 °C, is preferably at most about 550 °C,
and is more preferably at most about 500 °C.</p><p num="0020">The period of time for the calcination may depend on
the type of furnace utilized for the calcination and the
calcination temperature. The calcination may be conducted
for at least about 10 minutes and is preferably at least
about 30 minutes. Further, the calcination may be conducted
at most about 24 hours.</p><p num="0021">In accordance with the present invention, a titanium
oxide having a large specific surface area, which is useful
for a catalyst, can be easily produced.</p><p num="0022">The invention being thus described, it will be apparent
that the same may be varied in many ways. Such variations
are to be regarded as within the spirit and scope of the
invention, and all such modifications as would be apparent to 
one skilled in the art are intended to be within the scope of
the following claims.</p><p num="0023">The entire disclosure of the Japanese Patent
Application No. 2002-369748 filed on December 20, indicating
specification, claims, drawings and summary, are
incorporated herein by reference in their entirety.</p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0024">The present invention is described in more detail by
following Example, which should not be construed as a
limitation upon the scope of the present invention.</p><p num="0025">In Example and Comparative example below, crystallinity
phase and BET specific surface area of the produced titanium
oxide were obtained in accordance to the following methods.</p><heading>Crystallinity:</heading><p num="0026">Using an X-ray diffraction apparatus (device name:
RAD-IIA, manufactured by Rigaku Corporation), an X-ray
diffraction spectrum of the titanium oxide was measured
under the condition of:
<sl><li>X-ray tube: Cu,</li><li>tube voltage: 40 kV,</li><li>tube current: 35 mA,</li><li>diffusion slit: 1 degree, </li><li>scattering slit: 1 degree,</li><li>light income slit: 0.30 mm,</li><li>sampling width: 0.020 degree, and</li><li>scanning rate: 2.00 degree/min.,</li></sl>
and crystallinity of the titanium oxides was examined from
the obtained spectrum.</p><heading>BET specific surface area:</heading><p num="0027">The BET specific surface area (m<sup>2</sup>/g) was measured in a
nitrogen absorption method using an automatic specific
surface area measurement device (device name: Monosorb,
manufactured by Yuasa Ionics, Co., Ltd.). The measurement
of the BET specific surface area was conducted under the
condition of:
<sl><li>Desorption temperature: 200 °C,</li><li>Desorption time: 30 minutes, and</li><li>Absorption temperature: -196 °C (77 K).</li></sl></p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0028">An aqueous solution of titanium oxysulfate was prepared
by dissolving 3388g of a titanium oxysulfate (manufactured
by Tayca Corporation) in 2258g of ion exchange water. A
thousand three hundred seven grams (1307g) of a 35 % aqueous
hydrogen peroxide solution was added to the aqueous solution 
of titanium oxysulfate, under ice cooled conditions. In the
resulting mixture, the molar amount of the hydrogen peroxide
was 1 time based on the amount of titanium atom of the
titanium oxysulfate therein.</p><p num="0029">Four thousand seven hundred grams (4,700g) of ion
exchange water was added to a reaction container that was
equipped with pH electrodes and a pH controller which
connects to the pH electrodes and supplies
a 25 % by weight of aqueous ammonia (special grade,
manufactured by Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Ltd.) so as
to adjust the pH of a liquid in the reaction container to be
constant. The pH predetermined value of the pH controller
was set to 4. The supplying rate of the aqueous ammonia was
set to 50.3 ml/min. When a pH value of a liquid in the
reaction container becomes lower than the predetermined
value, the aqueous ammonia is begun to be supplied, and the
supplying was continued at the above-mentioned supplying
rate until the pH of the liquid attains to the predetermined
value. The above-obtained mixure was added to the reaction
container at a rate of 50.3 ml/min, while stirring the
resulting mixture in the container at 145 rpm, to react with
the aqueous ammonium which was supplied to the container by
the pH controller. The reaction temperature was from 24 °C
to 55 °C.
 
The obtained reaction mixture was maintained for 1 hour with
stirring, and then was supplied with a 25 % by weight of
aqueous ammonia (special grade, manufactured by Wako Pure
Chemical Industries, Ltd.) to obtain a slurry. The total
amount of the aqueous ammonia supplied to the reaction
vessel was 3746 g, which was 2 times the amount needed to
stoichiometrically convert the titanium oxysulfate into a
titanium hydroxide. The slurry was filtered to obtain a
solid therein. The obtained solid was washed with ion
exchanged water and was dried in the air at 150 °C for 15
hours to obtain a powder of titanium oxide precursor. The
obtained titanium oxide precursor was a white powder
containing a titanium peroxide.</p><p num="0030">The titanium oxide precursor was calcined using the
device depicted in Figure 4. The device comprised pipes 31
and 32, a main chamber 33, a cover 34 placed for the main
chamber and a shelf 35 in the main chamber 33. Pipe 31 was
connected to the pipe 32, which was connected to the main
chamber 33. Pipe 31 was utilized to introduce gas and was
connected to pipe 32. Pipe 32 was utilized to heat a gas
introduced therein.</p><p num="0031">Twenty grams (20g) of the titanium oxide precursor was
thinly spread on the shelf 35, so that the thickness thereof
was low. After the cover 34 was placed on the main chamber 
33, the device was placed in a furnace (trade name:
Supertemp Oven, manufactured by Asahi Kagaku Co., Ltd.). The
main chamber was heated to 370 °C at a rate of 200 °C /hour
and was maintained at 370 °C for 1 hour to calcine the
titanium oxide precursor to obtain a titanium oxide, while
introducing a gas which had been prepared to have a steam
pressure of 2,500 Pa. The gas introduced in the main
chamber had a total pressure of 101,000 Pa, had a nitrogen
amount of 79 % by volume, and had also present therein
oxygen, carbon dioxide and argon. The gas was introduced
into the main chamber 33 from outside of the furnace and
through pipe 31 at a rate of 1 L/minute.</p><p num="0032">The device was allowed to cool to a room temperature of
about 25 °C . Then, the titanium oxide was recovered from
the main chamber 33. The total amount of gas introduced
into the main chamber 33 was 9,000 times by volume in terms
of the volume converted in the standard state, based on the
volume of the titanium oxide precursor. The properties of
the titanium oxide are shown in Table 1. Furthermore, the
titanium oxide showed a photocatalytic activity by
irradiation of a visible light having a wavelength of at
least 430 nm. With the photocatalytic activity, an aldehyde
was able to be decomposed to a carbon dioxide. </p><heading>Comparative Example 1</heading><p num="0033">A titanium oxide was obtained with the same procedures
as described in Example 1, except that the steam pressure of
the gas introduced into the main chamber 33 was changed to
10,100 Pa. The properties of the titanium oxide are shown
in Table 1.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Example 1</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Example 1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Main crystallinity</entry><entry align="center">Anatase</entry><entry align="center">Anatase</entry></row><row><entry align="center">BET specific surface area (m<sup>2</sup>/g)</entry><entry align="center">81</entry><entry align="center">55</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for producing a titanium oxide, the method comprising the
step of calcining at least one titanium oxide precursor selected from a titanium
hydroxide and a titanium peroxide, wherein said calcination is conducted in the
presence of nitrogen molecules and at a steam pressure of at most about 8,000 pa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1, further comprising the step of reacting
a titanium compound in an aqueous solution thereof with a base to obtain the
titanium oxide precursor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1, further comprising the step of mixing
an aqueous solution of a titanium compound with a hydrogen peroxide and reacting
the resulting mixture with a base to obtain the titanium oxide precursor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A method according to claim 2 or 3, wherein the titanium compound
is at least one compound selected from a titanium chloride, a titanium oxychloride, a
titanium sulfate and a titanium oxysulfate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 4, further comprising
the step of washing said at least one titanium oxide precursor before the calcination.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 5, wherein the
calcination is conducted under a total gas pressure of at least about 10,000 Pa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 6, wherein the
calcination is conducted in a furnace into which a gas is introduced, wherein the gas
has a steam pressure of at most about 8,000 Pa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 7, wherein the
calcination is conducted in a furnace into which a gas is introduced in a volumetric
amount of at least about 100 times in terms of the volume converted in the standard
state, based on the total volume of the titanium oxide precursor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method according to claim 7 or 8, wherein the gas contains nitrogen
molecules, has a steam pressure of at most about 8,000 Pa and is introduced in a
volumetric amount of at least about 100 times in terms of the volume converted in a
standard state based on the volume of the titanium oxide precursor.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>