<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1046621-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1046621" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="23136283" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20001025"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1046621-A1" status="new" fvid="22984666"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1046621</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20001025</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00108451-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00108451</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000418</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-29511799-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>29511799</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990419</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  22/00        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  22/08        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  24/00        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  24/12        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23F  11/00        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23F  11/00        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23F  11/10        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23F  11/14        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Korrisonshemmender Zementzusatz</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Corrosion inhibiting admixture for concrete</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Additif pour ciment inhibitant la corrosion</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0312387-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0312387</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0754658-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0754658</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999067184-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999067184</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>CHEMICAL ABSTRACTS, vol. 83, no. 16, 20 October 1975 (1975-10-20) Columbus, Ohio, US; abstract no. 136404f, KODAMA, KAZUMI: "Corrosion inhibitor for cement mortar and concrete reinforcements" XP000183250 &amp; JP 50 016719 A (NISSO MASTER BUILDERS CO., LTD) 21 February 1975 (1975-02-21)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 197534 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class E16, AN 1975-56306W XP002139866 &amp; JP 50 018522 A (NISSO MAS BUIL CO), 27 February 1975 (1975-02-27)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 198935 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A97, AN 1989-254337 XP002140592 &amp; SU 1 460 070 A (W-SIBE DEEP SURV BO), 23 February 1989 (1989-02-23)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199231 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class E12, AN 1992-257421 XP002140507 &amp; SU 1 675 324 A (AS AZERB ADDITIVES CHEM INST), 7 September 1991 (1991-09-07)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199338 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class E13, AN 1993-301484 XP002140508 &amp; SU 1 763 468 A (ODESS PISTON RINGS CONSTR TECHN INST), 23 September 1992 (1992-09-23)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199701 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A26, AN 1997-010200 XP002140509 &amp; SU 1 075 725 A (PETROCHEM PROCESSES INST), 10 April 1996 (1996-04-10)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199701 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A26, AN 1997-010284 XP002140506 &amp; SU 1 374 704 A (ROST PROMSTROINIIPROEKT DES RES INST), 27 April 1996 (1996-04-27)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TOMAHAWK INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TOMAHAWK, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Tomahawk, Inc.</last-name><address><street>1105 North Market Street, Suite 1300</street><city>Wilmington, Delaware 19899</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KINNEY FREDERICK D</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LANE DONALD R</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MELENDEZ JOSE A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MUNTEANU VIOLETA F</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KINNEY, FREDERICK D.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LANE, DONALD R.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MELENDEZ, JOSE A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MUNTEANU, VIOLETA F.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KINNEY, FREDERICK D.</last-name><address><street>7956 Twin Oaks Drive</street><city>Broadview Heights, Ohio 44147</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>LANE, DONALD R.</last-name><address><street>3623 Brush Road</street><city>Richfield, Ohio 44286</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MELENDEZ, JOSE A.</last-name><address><street>1336 Schneider Street, N.W.</street><city>North Canton, Ohio 44721</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MUNTEANU, VIOLETA F.</last-name><address><street>483 West Broadway Street</street><city>Alliance, Ohio 44601</city><country>US</country></address> </addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Gervasi, Gemma, Dr.</last-name><address><street>Notarbartolo &amp;amp; Gervasi S.p.A., Corso di Porta Vittoria, 9</street> <city>20122 Milano</city> <country>IT</country> </address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>BE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GR</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep"  status="new" lang="EN"><p>A corrosion inhibiting admixture for concrete is disclosed comprising a
combination of organic (amines) and inorganic (nitrites) fractions that provide a
synergistic effect when present at a specific ratio. Such a synergistic effect occurs
when the amine:nitrite ratio (% by weight) is between 1.5 to 2.5 resulting in the
admixture providing excellent corrosion inhibiting capabilities.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="101" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="94"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">TECHNICAL FIELD</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates, in general, to a corrosion inhibitor for
concrete having steel reinforcing rods (rebar) therein and, more particularly, to an
admixture which can be mixed with the concrete when in the plastic state and which
prevents corrosion of the steel reinforcing rods over an extended period of time
when the concrete is exposed to chloride ion environments.</p><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND ART</u></heading><p num="0002">Reinforced concrete structures, such as highways, bridges, parking garages,
and the like are very susceptible to corrosion from common chloride deicing salts
which are applied to their respective surfaces and which cause corrosion of the steel
reinforcing rods (rebar) which are an integral part of their structure. Similarly,
reinforced concrete structures which are exposed to aggressive marine
environments, such as piers, docks and bridge supports, are also susceptible to
corrosion of the reinforcing rods therein. In either case, such corrosion is usually
caused by chloride ions that penetrate through the surface of the concrete and
contact the reinforcing rods. The electro-chemical process by which corrosion of
the reinforcing rods and rod degradation occurs is well known.</p><p num="0003">Under highly alkaline conditions, such as that which exists in Portland
cement concrete, an oxidized film forms on the steel reinforcing rods inhibiting the
corrosion of the rods. (The steel rods are said to have become "passivated.")
However, when chloride ions are allowed to penetrate into the concrete and reach
the reinforcing rods, the first phase of the corrosion process (the initiation phase)
commences. In this phase, there is no noticeable weakening of the concrete
structure, but carbonation and chloride ion penetration occurs. Carbonation reduces 
the pH of the concrete, thus reducing the corrosion protection usually provided to
the reinforcing rods by the alkaline concrete. Eventually, the passivity of the steel
reinforcing rods breaks down as the oxidized film on the rods is broken and decays.
Such breakage of the film generally occurs locally exposing the steel rods. As the
oxidized film decays, the electrical resistance of the steel rods, i.e., the property
that prevents the surface of the steel rods from polarizing and forming anodes and
cathodes, is compromised. As a result, the small exposed portion of a steel rod acts
as an anode, and the larger unexposed portion of the rod, still covered by the
oxidized film, acts as a cathode resulting in the creation of a potential difference
between the anode and the cathode. When the potential difference between the
anode and the cathode is great enough, the steel reinforcing rod begins to corrode,
i.e., metal ions are removed from the rod at its anode. As a result, corrosion takes
place in spots (pitting) along the surface of the steel reinforcing rod resulting in the
commencement of the second phase of the corrosion process (the propagation
phase).</p><p num="0004">During the propagation phase, the effective sectional area of the steel
reinforcing rod is progressively reduced by the corrosion causing a significant
reduction in the strength of the rod. As the number of corrosion spots (pits)
increases, they interconnect with one another spreading over the entire surface of
the steel rod. In the initial stages of corrosion, ferrous hydroxide is formed which
immediately oxidizes into iron oxides which are the main components of rust. In
the course of the rust formation, the corroding rod expands at the point of rust
formation. The localized expansion of the steel reinforcing rod caused by the
formation of rust results in a high expansion pressure being applied to the concrete
surrounding the expanded portion of the rod causing cracks to develop in the
concrete along the surface of the rod. As the cracks develop in the concrete,
additional chloride ions are permitted to contact the steel reinforcing rods,
accelerating the corrosion of same and the spalling of the concrete surface. If
corrosion and spalling are permitted to continue, the steel reinforcing rods, as well
as the surrounding concrete, deteriorate to the point where the structural integrity of
the concrete structure may be jeopardized. In order to remedy this condition, the 
removal and replacement of a substantially large area of concrete is required which
is a very costly process.</p><p num="0005">Several approaches have been taken to repair concrete structures which have
undergone or are susceptible to corrosion deterioration of the steel reinforcing rods
therein. For example, severely deteriorated concrete can be removed and an
overlay applied to the deteriorated structure. Large areas of chloride contaminated
concrete, however, will remain in place, and although the corrosion and
deterioration process will be slowed, the corrosion process continues.
Alternatively, scarification of the top portion of concrete, e.g. on a bridge deck, can
be utilized to remove a major portion of the chloride contaminated concrete
permitting the application of a corrosion inhibiting agent to the concrete surrounding
the steel reinforcing rods. After a corrosion inhibiting agent has been applied to
the surrounding concrete, a new concrete overlay is formed thereon. A preferred
rehabilitative technique requires complete removal of the concrete surrounding the
steel reinforcing rods prior to the application of a new overlay.</p><p num="0006">Until now the corrosion inhibiting admixtures that have been developed for
mixing with concrete when in the plastic state have been limited in their ability to
delay the onset of corrosion in the steel reinforcing rods within the concrete, i.e.,
the initiation phase of corrosion, or to slow such corrosion after it has started, i.e.,
the propagation phase of corrosion. In view of the foregoing, it has become
desirable to develop an admixture that can be mixed with the concrete when in the
plastic state and which significantly delays the onset of corrosion in the steel
reinforcing rods within the concrete and slows such corrosion after it has
commenced even when the concrete is exposed to chloride ion environments. It is
also desirable for such an admixture to protect the reinforcing rods in concrete that
has partially or completely carbonated reducing the pH of the concrete and
accelerating the onset of the protective oxide film deterioration in a chloride
containing environment. Ideally, the admixture would also maintain and preferably
increase the pH of the concrete. </p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0007">The present invention solves the problems associated with the prior art
approaches to minimizing corrosion of steel reinforcing rods in concrete as well as
other problems by providing a unique corrosion inhibiting admixture comprising a
combination of organic (on the basis of amine) and inorganic (on the basis of nitrite)
fractions that provide a synergistic effect when present in a specific ratio. The
range of the optimal amine:nitrite ratio (% by weight) is between 1.5 to 2.5. The
admixture is introduced into concrete when in the plastic state by placing same in
the mix water during the batching process or at the construction site. The
admixture is thoroughly distributed throughout the concrete to provide substantially
uniform levels of corrosion protection within the concrete. In an alternate
embodiment of the present invention, a portion of the nitrite is replaced with lithium
nitrite to minimize any undesirable alkali-silica reactions in the concrete. It has
been found that the introduction of either embodiment of the aforementioned
admixture into concrete when in the plastic state significantly delays the onset of
corrosion of the steel reinforcing rods within the concrete and slows such corrosion
after it has commenced even when the concrete is exposed to aggressive, salt-bearing
environments. In addition, the admixture increases the pH of concrete
which has carbonated.</p><heading><u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u></heading><p num="0008"><sl><li>Figure 1 is a graph of the degree (amount) of corrosion in reinforced
concrete versus time for the technical service life of reinforced concrete.</li><li>Figure 2 is a graph of corrosion initiation time versus the amount of
corrosion inhibiting admixture added to concrete.</li><li>Figure 3 is a graph illustrating performance improvement (increase in
corrosion initiation time) versus the amount of corrosion inhibiting admixture added
to concrete. </li><li>Figure 4 is a graph comparing the permeability of plain concrete, concrete to
which the corrosion inhibiting admixture of the present invention has been added
thereto, and concrete to which a competitor's corrosion inhibiting admixture has
been added thereto.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</u></heading><p num="0009">The present invention is directed to a corrosion inhibiting admixture which
can be introduced into concrete when in the plastic state by placing the admixture in
the mix water during the batching process or at the construction site. Corrosion
inhibiting admixtures are presently available, however, their effectiveness in
preventing or minimizing corrosion and degradation of reinforcing rods within the
concrete is somewhat limited. Through electro-chemical testing it has been found
that an admixture comprised of organic amines, inorganic nitrites, gluconate and
water provides excellent corrosion inhibiting capabilities. Amines that can be
utilized include, but are not limited to, primary, secondary and tertiary amines.
Examples of such amines include alkylamines, alkanolamines, alkyletheramines,
mixtures of amines and alkanolamines, and mixtures of alkanolamines, tertiamines
and alkyletheramines. Nitrites that can be utilized include alkali and alkaline earth
metals such as sodium nitrite, lithium nitrite, calcium nitrite and potassium nitrite.
Similarly, through electro-chemical testing, it has been found that the amine:nitrite
ratio (percentage by weight) has a synergistic effect on the corrosion inhibiting
capabilities of the admixture. In the aforementioned admixture, the range of the
optimal amine:nitrite ratio (% by weight) is between 1.5 to 2.5. In this admixture
the amines comprise about 20% to 40% by weight of the admixture and the nitrites
comprise about 15 to 30% by weight of the admixture.</p><p num="0010">Tests were conducted comparing concrete containing the aforementioned
corrosion inhibiting admixture against concrete without the admixture. For
example, a concrete mix comprised of 19. 15 pounds of cement, 49.66 pounds of
sand, 64.48 pounds of coarse aggregate and 10.95 pounds of water was prepared for
control and comparison purposes. Similarly, a second mix comprised of 19.15 
pounds of cement, 49.66 pounds of sand, 64.48 pounds of coarse aggregate, 9.12
pounds of water and 420 milliliters of the aforementioned admixture was prepared.
The test results for each of the concrete mixes are shown below:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>Plain Concrete</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Concrete with Admixture</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Slump</entry><entry align="center">3.75</entry><entry align="center">4.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Percentage Air</entry><entry align="center">6.4</entry><entry align="center">7.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compressive Strength (1 day)</entry><entry align="center">1528 psi</entry><entry align="center">2116 psi</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compressive Strength (4 days)</entry><entry align="center">3251 psi</entry><entry align="center">3919 psi</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compressive Strength (7 days)</entry><entry align="center">4077 psi</entry><entry align="center">4230 psi</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compressive Strength (28 days)</entry><entry align="center">4869 psi</entry><entry align="center">5002 psi</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0011">In another test, a concrete mix comprised of 517 pounds of concrete, 1330 pounds
of sand, 1741 pounds of coarse aggregate and 268 pounds of water was prepared for
control and comparison purposes. Similarly, a second mix comprised of 517
pounds of concrete, 1330 pounds of sand, 1741 pounds of coarse aggregate, 232
pounds of water and 3 gallons of the aforementioned admixture was prepared. The
test results of the concrete mixes are shown below:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>Plain Concrete</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Concrete with Admixture</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Slump</entry><entry align="center">6.25</entry><entry align="center">5.25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Percentage Air</entry><entry align="center">8.0</entry><entry align="center">7.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compressive Strength (1 day)</entry><entry align="center">1551 psi</entry><entry align="center">2638 psi</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compressive Strength (3 days)</entry><entry align="center">3179 psi</entry><entry align="center">3653 psi </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compressive Strength (7 days)</entry><entry align="center">3894 psi</entry><entry align="center">4122 psi</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compressive Strength (28 days)</entry><entry align="center">4899 psi</entry><entry align="center">5020 psi</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0012">As can be seen from the test results, the addition of the aforementioned corrosion
inhibiting admixture to concrete when in the plastic state does not adversely affect
the physical properties of the resulting "set" concrete since the slump, percentage
air entrained and compressive strengths are virtually unaffected by the addition of
the admixture.</p><p num="0013">It has been found that the addition of the aforementioned corrosion inhibiting
admixture to concrete significantly increases the amount of time that elapses before
the start of corrosion in the concrete, i.e., it significantly delays the onset of the
corrosion initiation phase. In addition, the addition of the aforementioned corrosion
inhibiting admixture to concrete significantly reduces the rate of corrosion in the
concrete after corrosion has commenced, i.e., it significantly increases the time of
the corrosion propagation phase. Thus, the addition of the aforementioned
corrosion inhibiting admixture to concrete provides a two-fold benefit. The
foregoing corrosion process phases are shown graphically in Figure 1 which is a
graph of the degree (amount) of corrosion in reinforced concrete versus time for the
technical service life of reinforced concrete and is the accepted model in the
industry of the corrosion phenomena in reinforced concrete due to the chloride ion
environment and carbonation. During the corrosion initiation phase, which is
affected by the amount of atmospheric carbon dioxide and chloride ions to which
the concrete is subjected, any corrosion is minimal and there is no noticeable
weakening of the concrete structure. When corrosion or rust starts to form, i.e., at
point "a" on the graph, the rate of corrosion is affected by the level of oxygen
within the surrounding air and the temperature and relative humidity of the
surrounding air. The addition of the corrosion inhibiting admixture of the present
invention significantly moves point "a" to the right, i.e., it increases the amount of
time that elapses before corrosion commences, and also decreases the slope of the 
line to the right of point "a", i.e., it reduces the rate of corrosion with respect to
time after corrosion commences. It has been found experimentally that the addition
of the corrosion inhibiting admixture of the present invention to concrete increases
the time of the corrosion initiation phase by a factor of about 1.7 to 2.7 versus the
time for same if the admixture was not utilized. It has also been found
experimentally that the addition of the corrosion inhibiting admixture of the present
invention to concrete decreases the corrosion rate of the steel reinforcing rods
within same to about 7 x 10 <sup>-4</sup> mm/year. This extremely low corrosion rate, in
effect, places the steel reinforcing rods in a passive state resulting in a technical
service life of the reinforced concrete of between 90 to 100 years.</p><p num="0014">It has also been found that the amount of corrosion inhibiting admixture
added to the concrete has a significant effect on the corrosion inhibiting properties
of the resulting mix. For example, referring to Figure 2, if no admixture is added
to the concrete, the corrosion initiation time is significantly less than 200 days. If,
however, 1.5 gallons of the corrosion inhibiting admixture is added to each cubic
yard of concrete, the corrosion initiation time increases to more than 200 days.
Similarly, if 3 gallons of the corrosion inhibiting admixture is added to each cubic
yard of concrete, the corrosion initiation time increases to almost 300 days, and if
4.5 gallons of the admixture is added to each cubic yard of concrete, the corrosion
initiation time increases to almost 400 days. The performance improvement through
increasing the amount of admixture to the concrete, i.e., increase in corrosion
initiation time, is shown graphically in Figure 3.</p><p num="0015">These significant increases in corrosion initiation time as a result of the
addition of the corrosion inhibiting admixture of the present invention to concrete
can, in part, be attributed to the fact that the admixture also increases the density of
the "set" concrete, thus decreasing its permeability to chloride ion penetration.
Such permeability is shown graphically in Figure 4 which illustrates the
permeability of plain concrete, i.e., concrete without any corrosion inhibiting
admixture added thereto, after 7 and 28 days versus concrete with the corrosion
inhibiting admixture of the present invention added thereto in two concentrations (3
gallons/yd.<sup>3</sup> and 4.5 gallons/yd.<sup>3</sup>) and after 7 and 28 days and versus concrete
having W.R. Grace &amp; Company's DCI corrosion inhibiting admixture added 
thereto in the same concentrations and for the same time periods. By reviewing the
foregoing graphs, it is apparent that the addition of the corrosion inhibiting
admixture of the present invention to concrete significantly decreases the
permeability of the concrete to chloride ion penetration, thus significantly increasing
the technical service life of the concrete. It is also apparent that by increasing the
amount of admixture to the concrete, the permeability of the concrete to chloride
ion penetration is further decreased thus increasing the corrosion initiation time.</p><p num="0016">In essence, the corrosion inhibiting admixture of the present invention is a
significant improvement over presently available corrosion inhibiting admixtures
since it is a complex anodic-cathodic, organic-inorganic inhibitor that can protect
the steel reinforcing rods in concrete that has developed cracks or has become
carbonated to the depth of the reinforcing rods. Presently available corrosion
inhibiting admixtures utilize only inorganic anodic inhibitors based on nitrites.
When a crack forms in concrete or the concrete cover over the reinforcing rods
carbonates, oxygen is allowed to contact the reinforcing rods and the pH
environment is lowered to below that necessary to promote a high polarization
resistance of the rod surface and maintain a high passive state. When reinforcing
rods in concrete containing only anodic inhibitors are exposed to increased oxygen
concentrations by the formation of a crack or the surrounding concrete has become
carbonated, a nitrite based anodic inhibitor actually causes the passive oxide layer to
decay more rapidly than if the anodic inhibitor was not present. In this
environment, the anodic inhibitor can actually accelerate the corrosion process. The
complex anodic-cathodic, organic-inorganic inhibitor of the present invention blocks
access of oxygen to the surface of the steel reinforcing rods and maintains an
elevated pH that is necessary to maintain the stability of the passive oxide layer on
the reinforced rods even in carbonated concrete contaminated with chloride ions.</p><p num="0017">Concrete typically contains alkali materials which may be present in the
cement, aggregate, and admixtures. In addition, silica compounds are typically
found in the aggregate components of concrete. Silica is subject to attack and
dissolution by hydroxide ions present in alkaline materials. Different forms of silica
show varying degrees of susceptibility to such dissolution. If there are sufficient
alkali metal ions present, the alkali metal ions may react with the reactive forms of 
silica causing the aggregate particles containing the silica to swell and form an
alkali-silica gel which can absorb water and swell. Such swelling can exert internal
pressures within the concrete causing the concrete to crack. This process is referred
to in the industry as an alkali-silica reaction (ASR). This reaction can decrease the
ability of the concrete to withstand other forms of attack, such as from the chloride
ions within deicing salts, resulting in increased penetration of the chloride ions into
the concrete allowing these ions to contact the reinforcing rods therein. Thus, an
alkali-silica reaction can significantly increase the degree of corrosion of the
reinforcing rods within the concrete. In order to minimize the effect of this reaction
on the reinforcing rods within the concrete, a portion of the nitrite within the
aforementioned admixture may be replaced with lithium nitrite.</p><p num="0018">Certain improvements and modifications will occur to those skilled in the act
upon reading the foregoing. It should be understood that all such modifications and
improvements have been deleted herein for the sake of conciseness and readability,
but are properly within the scope of the following claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A corrosion inhibiting admixture for concrete comprising a combination of
amines and nitrites provided in an amine: nitrite ratio (% by weight) of between
about 1.5 to 2.5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The corrosion inhibiting admixture as defined in claim 1 wherein said
amines comprise primary, secondary or tertiary amines.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The corrosion inhibiting admixture as defined in claim 1 wherein said nitrites
comprise alkali and alkaline metal earths.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The corrosion inhibiting admixture as defined in claim 1 wherein said
amines comprise about 20% to 40% by weight of said admixture.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The corrosion inhibiting admixture as defined in claim 1 wherein said nitrites
comprise about 15 to 30% by weight of said admixture.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The corrosion inhibiting admixture as defined in claim 1 wherein the
addition of said admixture to concrete having steel reinforcing rods therein increases
the time required for the commencement of corrosion on the reinforcing rods by a
factor of about 1.7 to 2.7 versus the time for the commencement of corrosion on
reinforcing rods in concrete without the addition of a corrosion inhibiting admixture
thereto.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The corrosion inhibiting admixture as defined in claim 6 wherein increasing
the amount of said admixture to concrete having reinforcing rods therein
significantly increases the time required for the commencement of corrosion on the
reinforcing rods.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The corrosion inhibiting admixture as defined in claim 1 wherein the
addition of said admixture to concrete having reinforcing rods therein decreases the
rate of corrosion of the reinforcing rods, after corrosion has commenced, to about 7
x 10-4 mm/year.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The corrosion inhibiting admixture as defined in claim 1 wherein the
addition of said admixture to concrete decreases the permeability of the concrete to
ion penetration.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The corrosion inhibiting admixture as defined in claim 1 wherein said
combination further includes gluconates.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The corrosion inhibiting admixture as defined in claim 1 wherein said
combination further includes water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The corrosion inhibiting admixture as defined in claim 1 wherein the
addition of said admixture to concrete increases the pH of the concrete minimizing
the effects of carbonation of the concrete.</claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure num="1"><img id="img-00130001" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="150"/></figure><figure num="2"><img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="215"/></figure><figure num="3"><img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="240"/></figure></drawings><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="242" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="243" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90020001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90020001.tif" he="243" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90030001" orientation="portrait" wi="156" status="new" file="90030001.tif" he="236" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>