<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1002782-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1002782" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="8552936" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000524"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1002782-A2" status="new" fvid="22841101"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1002782</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20000524</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99660178-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99660178</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991116</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="FI-982497-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>FI</country><doc-number>982497</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981118</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  29/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  29/141       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  31/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  31/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  31/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07H   1/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07H   1/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C13K  13/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C13K  13/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C  29/141</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C  31/18</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C  31/24</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C13K  13/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C13K  13/00B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung von Polyolen aus Arabinoxylan-enthaltendem Material</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method of producing polyols from arabinoxylan-containing material</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour la préparation de polyols à partir d'une matière contenant de l'arabinoxylane</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-618164-C" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>618164</doc-number><kind>C</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4008285-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4008285</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4752579-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4752579</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4816078-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4816078</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4880919-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4880919</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5084104-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5084104</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998050589-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998050589</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999057326-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999057326</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>HUMPHLETT W J: "SYNTHESIS OF SOME ESTERS AND LACTONES OF ALDONIC ACIDS" CARBOHYDRATE RESEARCH,NL,AMSTERDAM, vol. 4, no. 2, 1967, pages 157-164, XP000863144</text><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>JEANES A ET AL: "PREPARATION OF meso-ERYTHRITOL AND d-ERYTHRONIC LACTONE FROM PERIODATE-OXIDIZED STARCH" JOURNAL OF ORGANIC CHEMISTRY., vol. 20, 1955, pages 1565-1568, XP002134519 AMERICAN CHEMICAL SOCIETY. EASTON., US ISSN: 0022-3263</text><sources><source category="AD"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>XYROFIN OY</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>XYROFIN OY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>XYROFIN OY</last-name><address><street>Keilaranta 9</street><city>02150 Espoo</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ALEN RAIMO</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HEIKKILAE HEIKKI</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KAUKO SIRU</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LINDROOS MIRJA</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NURMI JUHA</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SARMALA PAEIVI</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TYLLI MATTI</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ALEN, RAIMO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HEIKKILAE, HEIKKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KAUKO, SIRU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LINDROOS, MIRJA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NURMI, JUHA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SARMALA, PAEIVI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TYLLI, MATTI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Alén, Raimo</last-name><address><street>Ratamestarinkatu 13 A 17</street><city>00520 Helsinki</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Heikkilä, Heikki </last-name><address><street>Ristiniementie 32 G 33</street><city>02320 Espoo</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KAUKO, SIRU</last-name><address><street>Latvatie 17</street><city>40320 Jyväskyla</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>LINDROOS, MIRJA</last-name><address><street>Pohjoispiha 8</street><city>02400 Kirkkonummi</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NURMI, JUHA</last-name><address><street>Nahkurinpiha 2</street><city>02400 Kirkkonummi</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Sarmala, Päivi</last-name><address><street>Harju 1 A 3</street><city>02460 Kantvik</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TYLLI, MATTI</last-name><address><street>Ristikalliontie 19</street><city>02460 Kantvik</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Syvänen, Ralf Ossian</last-name><address><street>Oy Kolster Ab, Iso Roobertinkatu 23, P.O. Box 148</street><city>00121 Helsinki</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The invention relates to a method of producing xylitol and erythritol from arabinoxylan-containing
material. According to the invention, the arabinoxylan-containing
material is hydrolyzed and xylose and arabinose are separated
from the obtained hydrolysate, whereafter the xylose is reduced to xylitol, and
the xylitol is recovered, and the arabinose is subjected to alkaline oxidation to
obtain erythronic acid which is reduced to erythritol, and the erythritol is recovered.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The invention relates to a method of producing polyols from xylan-containing
hemicellulose, in particular the invention relates to a method of producing
xylitol and erythritol from arabinoxylan-containing material.</p><p num="0002">Xylitol is a sugar alcohol which occurs in nature and which is most
commonly produced by reducing xylose, and whose sweetness corresponds
to "ordinary sugar", but whose calorie content (2.4 kcal/g) is lower than that of
ordinary sugar. Small amounts of xylitol occur in many fruits and vegetables,
and it is also produced by the human body as a normal metabolic product. The
metabolic, odontological and technical properties of xylitol make it an extremely
good special sweetener for a variety of uses, such as chewing gums,
sweets, bakery products, etc. An example is the independence of xylitol metabolism
of insulin metabolism, allowing also diabetics to use xylitol. Xylitol
also has a slowing effect on bowel function and reduces nutrient absorption,
making it usable in slimming diets. Furthermore, it has been found that xylitol
is noncariogenic, even anticariogenic.</p><p num="0003">Despite the numerous advantages of xylitol, its use has been rather
limited. This is due to the relatively high price of xylitol, which in turn results
from high production costs.</p><p num="0004">Previously xylitol was mainly produced by hydrolyzing a material
rich in xylan. A monosaccharide mixture, containing large amounts of xylose,
is thus obtained. Thereafter, xylose is reduced to xylitol by catalytic reduction
(hydrogenation), in general in the presence of a nickel catalyst, such as Raney
nickel. The literature of the field describes numerous methods of producing
xylose and/or xylitol from xylan-containing material. As examples can be given
US patent publication 3,784,408 (Jaffe et al.), US patent publication 4,066,711
(Melaja et al.), US patent publication 4,075,406 (Melaja et al.), US patent publication
4,008,285 (Melaja et al.) and US patent publication 3,586,537 (Steiner
et al.). Xylitol can also be produced from glucose as disclosed in US Patent
5,631,150 (Harkki et al.) or from hexose as disclosed in US Patents 5,563,303,
5,238,826 and 5,096,820 and from oses and uloses as disclosed in WO
9,720,860.</p><p num="0005">In several plants the majority of hemicellulose is xylan, which can
be hydrolyzed to xylose. A primary raw material of xylan is the hemicellulose of
e.g. hardwood, corn cobs and bagasse, which mainly consists of xylan. Recently, 
there has been an increasing interest in the utilization of xylan and xylose
obtained as by-products in pulp industry. Xylose is formed, for instance, in
acid sulphite cookings, in which typical bases are Mg<sup>2+</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> and Na<sup>+</sup>. A
cooking liquor of neutral sulphite cookings can also be used as a raw material
after the xylo-oligomers of oligomeric and polymeric xylan have been hydrolyzed.
In the cooking liquor of acid sulphite cookings the hemicelluloses are
mainly in the form of monosaccharides.</p><p num="0006">When using sulphite cooking liquor as a raw material of xylose, the
problem is the variability of cooking conditions. Depending on the conditions,
hemicellulose of wood dissolves in different ways yielding smaller or greater
amounts of xylose. Cooking conditions which yield little xylose, may yield considerable
amounts of xylonic acid.</p><p num="0007">A drawback with the previous methods is that only the xylose-rich
hemicellulose is utilized and the rest of the hemicellulose structures is left unutilized.</p><p num="0008">Like other sugar alcohols, erythritol is highly thermostable and acid
stable. Like mannitol, it has poor solubility, and like xylitol, its solution heat is
low.
<img id="img-00020001" orientation="unknown" wi="67" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00020001.tif" inline="no" he="36"/></p><p num="0009">Erythritol is a polyhydroxyalcohol occurring widely in nature, for instance,
as a metabolic product and storage material in algae and fungi. Fruits,
for instance melons, grapes and pear, contain erythritol. Various microorganisms,
such as bacteria, fungi and yeasts, produce erythritol, and therefore
it occurs in food products prepared by fermentation processes, such as
wine and beer, and in processed vegetables, such as soya sauce.</p><p num="0010">Since erythritol is introduced into the system along with the food, it
can be found in many tissues and fluids of the body, such as the lens tissue of
the eye, blood serum, sperm, amniotic fluid and urine. In human urine it is the
principal sugar alcohol.</p><p num="0011">Many osmophilic yeasts are able to produce polyhydroxyalcohols.
Yeasts like this and yeast-like fungi are found as contaminants in substances 
with high sugar content, such as honey. Resistance against high sugar and
salt content is typical of them.</p><p num="0012">Erythritol is prepared biotechnically by hydrolyzing wheat and corn
starches to glucose which is fermented mainly to erythritol by means of an
osmophilic yeast <i>(Moniliella pollinis),</i> as disclosed in EP 136,803, EP 136,802,
EP 262,463, and EP 327,342. The yield of the fermentation process is about
50% and e.g. ribitol or glycerol is formed as a by-product. The osmophilic
property of yeast has a consequence that the dry solids content of the reaction
liquor is high. From purified and concentrated liquor, it is possible to crystallize
pure erythritol. A variety of other yeasts having osmophilic properties produce
erythritol together with glycerol and/or D-arabinitol, but the problem is separation
and purification of erythritol from the reaction mixture. Moreover, it has
been found that certain yeasts yield acetoin as a by-product, the removal of
which is difficult. A. Jeanes (<i>J. org. Chem 20,</i> 1565-1568, 1955) describes
preparation of erythritol from erythronic acid. The publication by W.J. Humphlett,
<i>Carbohydrate Res. 4,</i> 157-164, 1967, describes preparation of
erythronic acid from L-arabinose.</p><p num="0013">Erythritol, like other sugar alcohols used as sweeteners, such as
sorbitol, maltitol and lactitol, is tooth-friendly and suitable for diabetics. Because
of the small molecular size, erythritol reacts in metabolism in a totally
different manner from other sugar alcohols. Consequently, the most important
differences are its considerably lower energy content in comparison with other
sugar alcohols and the system's higher tolerance to said substance.</p><p num="0014">The nutritional value of erythritol is considerably lower than that of
other special sweeteners. Only 20% of erythritol can continue from the small
intestine to the large intestine and therein only half of the substance, at most,
converts to volatile fatty acids and further to energy to be used by the body.
On the average, 50 to 60% of the original energy content of other special
sweeteners remains for use in the body, but of erythritol the percentage is only
about 10, which corresponds to 0.3 kcal/g of the energy content.</p><p num="0015">Oral bacteria cannot utilize erythritol, as they cannot utilize other
polyhydroxyalcohols either. In the tests conducted, it was found that oral bacteria,
in particular the main cause of caries, <i>Streptococcus mutans,</i> cannot use
erythritol for growth. Hence, it is possible to avoid the formation of organic acids
and plaque, which contribute to the emergence of caries. This is why the
use of erythritol as a sweetener makes the food products tooth-friendly. </p><p num="0016">In a 10% solution, the sweetness of erythritol is 60 to 70% as compared
with cane sugar. The taste profile of erythritol is very similar to that of
cane sugar, and it has no bitter after-taste. Therefore it suits well for improving
the taste of other sweetening agents, such as aspartame.</p><p num="0017">It has now been found that xylitol and erythritol can be produced in
an advantageous manner from an arabinoxylan-containing material.</p><p num="0018">β-D-xylo-pyranose units linked with a 1-4 glycosidic bond form the
main chain of D-xylans. These polysaccharides occur in all plants and almost
all plant parts. Proper D-xylan, formed from D-xylose alone, occurs rarely, and
most D-xylan structures have other sugars as side chains.</p><p num="0019">One of the common side chains is L-arabinose, which in most cases
is in the form of furanose. L-arabinose often forms the side chain alone, even
though the chain may even comprise a plurality of sugar groups. In different
plants, the proportion of L-arabinose and D-xylose varies greatly, depending
on how branched said molecule is.</p><p num="0020">The present invention relates to a method of producing xylitol and
erythritol from arabinoxylan-containing material. The method is characterized
in that the arabinoxylan-containing material is hydrolyzed and xylose and
arabinose are separated from the obtained hydrolysate, whereafter the xylose
is reduced to xylitol and the xylitol is recovered, and the arabinose is subjected
to alkaline oxidation to obtain erythronic acid which is reduced into erythritol
and the erythritol is recovered.</p><p num="0021">Advantageously, said separation can be performed chromatographically.
Xylitol and erythritol can be advantageously recovered by prior
art crystallization methods.</p><p num="0022">Xylose and arabinose can be recovered as an intermediate product
through crystallization. The crystallization can be suitably performed such that
the xylose and arabinose fractions obtained from separation are first concentrated,
whereafter the xylose and the arabinose are crystallized by using a
suitable cooling program and seed crystals. A preferred alternative is to remove
hexose from the obtained hydrolysate by yeast fermentation. One advantageous
method to perform hydrolysis of hemicellulose is to employ xylanolytic
enzymes. One advantageous method of alkaline oxidation is accomplished
such that, during the reaction, erythronic acid crystallizes from the
methanol-containing reaction mixture. In alkaline oxidation, anthraquinone can
be used advantageously. </p><p num="0023">The method has an advantage that a by-product obtained from
xylitol production can be used for producing erythritol. Arabinoxylan-containing
material is advantageously corn or barley fibers. Hydrolysis is performed with
an acid, advantageously using an aqueous solution of sulphuric acid at a temperature
of about or exceeding 100 °C. Separation of xylose and arabinose
from the obtained hydrolysate is advantageously performed chromatographically,
whereby a simulated moving bed (SMB) can be used. Chromatographic
separation can be suitably performed in two separation steps, whereby in the
first step the salts and part of the arabinose are removed, and in the second
step the xylose and the arabinose are separated from one another. In the first
separation, a column is advantageously filled with a strongly acid cation exchange
resin, which is regenerated into the form of Na<sup>+</sup>. The second separation
is advantageously performed with a cation exchange resin, which is regenerated
into the form of Ca<sup>2+</sup>.</p><p num="0024">Reduction of xylose to xylitol is advantageously performed by catalytic
reduction. Suitable catalysts include Raney-type catalysts and noble-metal
catalysts, such as Ru, Pd and Pt. A suitable reduction temperature is 80
to 130 °C, preferably 100 to 110 °C and the reduction is suitably carried out at
a pressure of 30 to 60 bar, preferably 40 to 50 bar. Alkaline oxidation of arabinose
to erythronic acid is preferably carried out in a methanol-water solution. A
preferable oxidation temperature is 20 to 50 °C. Reduction of erythronic acid is
preferably carried out catalytically. Suitable catalysts include Ru, Rh, Pd and
Pt, preferably Ru. A suitable reduction temperature is 80 to 130 °C, preferably
100 to 110 °C, and the reduction is carried out suitably at a pressure of 80 to
130 bar, preferably 100 to 110 bar.</p><p num="0025">Following examples illustrate the invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0026">The raw material of hydrolysis was corn fiber having the following composition:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">- dry substance (DS)</entry><entry align="right">95.3 g/100 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- ash</entry><entry align="right">0.6 % on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- starch</entry><entry align="right">4.3 % on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- metal cations (analysis by AAS)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - Ca</entry><entry align="right">610 ppm on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - K</entry><entry align="right">150 ppm on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - Mg</entry><entry align="right">880 ppm on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - Na</entry><entry align="right">67 ppm on DS </entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">- carbohydrates after hydrolysis (analysis by GLC)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - xylose</entry><entry align="right">39.2 % on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - glucose</entry><entry align="right">15.6 % on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - arabinose</entry><entry align="right">29.8 % on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - mannose</entry><entry align="right">0.4 % on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - galactose</entry><entry align="right">3.5 % on DS</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables>
An amount of 2.0 kg DS of corn fiber was weighed into an acid resistant autoclave
vessel. 10.0 l of 1% sulphuric acid was mixed with the fiber material, hydrolysis
was started at 120 °C for 60 minutes. Warming up to a temperature of
120 °C took 55 minutes. The hydrolysate vessel rotated about its transverse
axis thereby mixing the mixture.

At the end of the hydrolysis, the autoclave was degassed. The solution phase
was drained from the autoclave through a filter and was cooled. The solid
residue was removed from the autoclave and washed with ion exchange water.
The mixture was filtered and the filtrate was combined with the hydrolysate.
The solution (= hydrolysate) was analysed for carbohydrates (by GLC).
Yields from the hydrolysis and the composition of the hydrolysate are as follows:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Yield (%/corn fiber DS)</entry><entry align="center">Composition (% /hydrolysate DS)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Carbohydrates</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">- glucose</entry><entry align="center">5.2</entry><entry align="center">5.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- xylose</entry><entry align="center">34.3</entry><entry align="center">37.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- galactose</entry><entry align="center">4.8</entry><entry align="center">5.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- rhamnose</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- arabinose</entry><entry align="center">29.5</entry><entry align="center">32.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- mannose</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Sulfate</b></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5.4</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables> </p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0027">The raw material of hydrolysis was barley fiber after removal of starch. The
raw material composition was as follows:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">- dry substance (DS) 95.5 g / 100 g</entry></row> <row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">- carbohydrates after hydrolysis (analysis by HPLC, Pb<sup>+2</sup> form ion exchange resin):</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">   - glucose</entry><entry align="right">21.2 % on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - xylose</entry><entry align="right">21.2 % on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - galactose + rhamnose</entry><entry align="right">1.6 % on DS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   - arabinose + mannose</entry><entry align="right">11.2 % on DS</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables>
An amount of 10 g DS of barley fiber was weighed into an acid resistant autoclave
vessel. 150 ml of 0.25 w-% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> was mixed with the fiber (liquid to
solid ratio 15:1). The hydrolysis was started at 142 °C for 1 hour. Warming up
to a temperature of 142 °C took 25 minutes.</p><p num="0028">After hydrolysis, the vessel was cooled to room temperature. The
content of the vessel was filtered. The hydrolysis residue on the filter was
washed, and all washing waters were combined with the original filtrate. The
filtrate was analysed for carbohydrates (by HPLC).</p><p num="0029">The carbohydrate yields from the hydrolysis and the composition of
the hydrolysate are shown in Table 2.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Yield (%/barley fiber DS)</entry><entry align="center">Composition (%/hydrolysate DS)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Carbohydrates</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">- glucose</entry><entry align="center">2.1</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- xylose</entry><entry align="center">18.7</entry><entry align="center">31.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- galactose + rhamnose</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">2.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- arabinose</entry><entry align="center">9.1</entry><entry align="center">15.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Sulfate</b></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Acetic acid</b></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Nitrogen</b></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">3.3</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><p num="0030">The solution prepared according to Example 1 was subjected to
chromatographic separation in a chromatographic separation column. Two
separation steps were used: the first separation (Na<sup>+</sup> form resin) for removing
the salts and part of the arabinose, and the second separation (Ca<sup>2+</sup> form
resin) for separating the xylose and the arabinose from one another.</p><p num="0031">The separation was carried out in the chromatographic separation
column as a batch process. The whole equipment consists of a feed tank, a
feed pump, a heat exchanger, a column, an outlet pump, product containers,
feed pipes and product pipes for feed solution and eluent water, and a control
device and control valves for liquid to be discharged.</p><p num="0032">The first separation was carried out using a column filled with a
strongly acid cation exchange resin (manufactured by Finex Oy, Finland) having
a cross-linkage degree of 6.5 % DVB and an average particle size of 0.41
mm. 1.5 m<sup>3</sup> of said resin was fed into the separation column with a diameter of
0.6 m and was regenerated to sodium (Na<sup>+</sup>) form.</p><p num="0033">The process temperature was 65 °C and the flow rate was adjusted
to 0.5 m/h.</p><p num="0034">The solution was concentrated to 30 g/ 100 g and pH of the feed
solution was adjusted to 5.5 with 50 w-% NaOH solution and the solution was
filtered with a pressure filter using diatomaceous earth as a filter aid.</p><p num="0035">The feed solution was pumped through the heat exchanger and the
feeding device onto a resin bed. The feed solution was eluted by feeding ion
exchange water to the top of the column. The density and conductivity of the
outcoming solution was measured on-line, and on the basis of the obtained
information the outflow was collected and divided into four fractions: residual
fraction (containing salts and small amounts of sugars), recycle fraction
(containing e.g. glucose, galactose and xylose), xylose fraction (containing
most of the xylose and about half of the arabinose) and arabinose fraction.</p><p num="0036">The amount of dry substance as well as the xylose and arabinose
content of the feed solution are shown in Table 3. <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">COMPOSITIONS AND YIELDS</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Feed solution</entry><entry align="center">Xylose fraction</entry><entry align="center">Arabinose fraction</entry></row><row><entry align="left">fraction DS, kg</entry><entry align="center">36</entry><entry align="center">19.7</entry><entry align="center">6.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">DS content g/100 g</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">13.9</entry><entry align="center">6.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">xylose, % on DS</entry><entry align="center">36.2</entry><entry align="center">52.5</entry><entry align="center">9.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">arabinose, % on DS</entry><entry align="center">31.2</entry><entry align="center">28.9</entry><entry align="center">79.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">xylose, yield %</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">79.3</entry><entry align="center">5.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">arabinose, yield %</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">50.7</entry><entry align="center">49.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0037">The xylose fraction obtained from the first separation was evaporated
to a concentration of 30 g/100 g, and the second separation was carried
out with a cation exchange resin regenerated to Ca<sup>2+</sup> ion form in order to purify
xylose and arabinose. The cross-linkage degree of the resin (manufactured by
Finex Oy, Finland) was 5.5 % DVB and the average particle size was 0.31
mm.</p><p num="0038">The second separation was carried out in separation columns having
a resin volume of 200 l. The equipment corresponded to that used in the
first separation. The process temperature was 65 °C and the flow rate was
adjusted to 0.6 m/h. The outflow was collected and divided into four fractions:
residual fraction (containing small amounts of e.g. glucose, galactose, xylose)
and recycle fraction (containing small amounts of e.g. glucose, galactose and
xylose) and xylose fraction and arabinose fraction.</p><p num="0039">The amount of dry substance as well as xylose and arabinose content
of the feed solution are given in Table 4.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">COMPOSITIONS AND YIELDS</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Feed solution</entry><entry align="center">Xylose fraction</entry><entry align="center">Arabinose fraction</entry></row><row><entry align="left">fraction DS, kg</entry><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">DS content, g/100 g</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">12.0</entry><entry align="center">8.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">xylose, % on DS</entry><entry align="center">52.5</entry><entry align="center">78.8</entry><entry align="center">4.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">arabinose, % on DS</entry><entry align="center">28.9</entry><entry align="center">2.8</entry><entry align="center">82.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">xylose, yield %</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">87.5</entry><entry align="center">2.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">arabinose, yield %</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5.6</entry><entry align="center">72.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 4</u></heading><p num="0040">The xylose fraction obtained from the chromatographic separation
was evaporated in a rotavapor (Büchi Rotavapor R-151) to 81.7% dry substance
content. The mass (4 kg) was transferred into a 5-litre vertical, glass
reaction vessel (70 °C). The vessel was provided with a jacket connected to a
programmable water bath, and mixing was performed with an anchor-shaped
mixer blade. An amount of 1 g of properly milled xylose was dosed as seed
crystals into the mass. A linear 40-hour cooling program (from 70 °C to 25 °C)
was started.</p><p num="0041">After cooling, the mass was mixed at 25 °C for about 5 hours, before
the crystals were separated by centrifuging (Hettich Roto Silenta II centrifuge,
basket diameter 24 cm, screen openings 0.15 mm) 3,500 rpm for 5
minutes. The crystal cake was washed with 80 ml distilled water.</p><p num="0042">The centrifuging results are shown in Table 5.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Mass introduced into centrifuge (g)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>743</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">DS of the mass (w-%)</entry><entry align="center">81.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Purity of the mass (% on DS)</entry><entry align="center">78.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Crystal cake (g)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>295</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">DS of the cake (w-%)</entry><entry align="center">98.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Purity of the cake (% on DS)</entry><entry align="center">99.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Purity of the run-off (% on DS)</entry><entry align="center">59.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Yield in centrifugation, DS/DS (w-%)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>48</b></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 5</u></heading><p num="0043">The arabinose fractions from the chromatographic separations were
evaporated to 71.2 % dry substance content with a rotavapor (Büchi Rotavapor
R-151). The mass (1.6 kg) was transferred into a 2-litre vertical, glass
reaction vessel (65 °C). The vessel was provided with a thermal jacket connected
to a programmable water bath, and mixing was performed with an anchor-shaped
mixer blade. The mass was seeded with 100 g of milled arabinose,
and a linear cooling program to 30 °C in 40 hours was started. At the 
end of the program, the mass was mixed at 30 °C for 6 hours, before the
crystals were separated by centrifugation (Hettich Roto Silenta II centrifuge;
basket diameter 24 cm). Rotation speed was 4,000 rpm for 5 minutes. The
crystals were washed with 80 ml distilled water during centrifugation. The centrifuging
results are shown in the following table.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Mass introduced into centrifuge (g)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>662</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">DS of the mass (w-%)</entry><entry align="center">71.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Purity of the mass (% on DS)</entry><entry align="center">82.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Crystal cake (g)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>205</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">DS of the cake (w-%)</entry><entry align="center">99.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Purity of the cake (% on DS)</entry><entry align="center">98.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Purity of the run-off (% on DS)</entry><entry align="center">70.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Yield in centrifugation, DS/DS (w-%)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>43</b></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 6</u></heading><p num="0044">The L-arabinose obtained from the crystallization of L-arabinose
was subjected to oxidation with oxygen.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1"><b>Test conditions:</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">L-arabinose</entry><entry align="left">9.73 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">NaOH</entry><entry align="left">6.66 g</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">methanol-water solution (ratio by weight 1:1)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">total sample volume</entry><entry align="left">200 ml</entry></row><row><entry align="left">reaction time</entry><entry align="left">10 h</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">mixing at 60 Hz speed for 1 sec, at 5-sec intervals</entry></row><row><entry align="left">oxygen pressure</entry><entry align="left">abt. 4.7 bar</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0045">The starting solution was prepared by dissolving sodium hydroxide
(6.66 g) first in a small amount of methanol-water solution (ratio by weight 1:1)
and by adding the cooled starting solution to an L-arabinose-methanol-water
solution. The obtained solution (clear, slightly pale yellow) was introduced into
a laboratory-scale reactor (400 ml) provided with a rotating (60 Hz) mixer. The
sample solution in the closed reactor was flushed for one minute with oxygen
flow, whereafter the reactor was pressurized with oxygen (abt. 4.7 bar). The 
oxygen line between the gas container and the reactor was kept open during
the whole reaction. The reactor was adjusted to mix the sample continuously
in 1-second sequences at 5-second intervals. The reaction time was 10 hours.
The starting temperature of the reaction was adjusted to 22 °C, i.e. the reaction
was started at room temperature. At the end of the reaction, the temperature
was 48 °C.</p><p num="0046">The reaction product obtained was light, milk-like mixture, from
which an amount was taken for analysis immediately after mixing. Thereafter
said amount was centrifuged (1,500 rpm), whereby a white, fine precipitate
and a clear solution were separated. The separated precipitate was dissolved
in ion exchange water, which was combined for gas chromatographic analyses
with the clear liquid phase previously separated in centrifugation.</p><p num="0047">From the above-prepared reaction product solution, inert arabinose
and erythronic acid were analysed by gas chromatography (GC/FID) as silylated
derivatives, using xylitol as an internal standard. The volatile acids
(formic acid and acetic acid) were analysed as benzoic esters.</p><p num="0048">The results are shown in the following Table 7.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Composition of a product obtained from L-arabinose in alkaline methanol-water solution in the presence of oxygen</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compound</entry><entry align="left">Proportion % on organic DS<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Arabinose<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="right">2.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formic acid</entry><entry align="right">27.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Acetic acid</entry><entry align="right">&lt; 0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Erythronic acid</entry><entry align="right">59.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Others</entry><entry align="right">10.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="right">100.0<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 7</u></heading><p num="0049">Xylose was dissolved and purified (decolorized and demineralized)
using a strongly acid cation exchange resin (Dow 88<sup>R</sup>) and a weakly basic anion
exchange resin (Dow 66<sup>R</sup>). Temperature during purification was 40 °C and
the flow rate was 4 bed volumes/hour.</p><p num="0050">Hydrogenation was carried out using a batch-type autoclave
(Medimex).</p><p num="0051">The hydrogenation conditions were as follows: temperature 110 °C,
xylose dry substance 50 g/100 g, hydrogen pressure 40 bar and catalyst load
10% catalyst slurry/ xylose DS.</p><p num="0052">The catalyst used was Raney-type nickel catalyst (Chemcat J 10
GS<sup>R</sup>).</p><p num="0053">The purity of the feed xylose was 99.5 on DS and purity of the xylitol
product was 99.0 % on DS.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 8</u></heading><p num="0054">The liquid material fed for hydrogenation process was prepared
from L-arabinose using a basic oxidation process. The composition of the
material fed for solution purification was the following: 59.9 %/DS of erythronic
acid, 27.7 %/DS of formic acid, 2.1 %/DS of arabinose.</p><p num="0055">The liquid was purified (decolorized, demineralized and decationized)
using strongly acid cation exchange resin (Purolite C 155<sup>R</sup>), polymeric
adsorbent (Dowex Optipore<sup>R</sup>) and weakly basic anion exchange resin (Purolite
A 100<sup>R</sup>). During a 10-litre cycle, 5 litres of each resin was used sequentially at
a temperature of 40 °C, the flow rate being 1 bed volume per hour. Thereafter,
evaporation to remove the formic acid was carried out before hydrogenation.</p><p num="0056">The feed syrup concentration for hydrogenation was 19.5 g/100ml.
Hydrogenation was carried out in following conditions: temperature was 100
°C, hydrogen pressure was 100 bar, catalyst load 13% on DS (dry substance
of catalyst and dry substance of support/feed material). Hydrogenation was
carried out using Medimex (5 litre) batch-type autoclave. The catalyst was Ru
on carbon support (Engelhardt CP 56 x L/R/WW).</p><p num="0057">The erythritol content of the syrup after hydrogenation was about 80
to 82 % on dry substance. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 9</u></heading><p num="0058">Hydrogenated syrup, containing 80.3 % erythritol on dry substance,
was evaporated in a rotavapor (Büchi Rotavapor R-151). During evaporation,
spontanous crystals were produced, whereby the evaporation process was
interrupted. The mass temperature was 57 °C. The KF dry substance content
assayed on the mass sample was 70.9 %. The mass was introduced into a
vertical, 2-litre, glass reaction vessel whose temperature was set at 57 °C. The
vessel was provided with a thermal jacket connected to a programmable water
bath, and mixing was carried out with an anchor-shaped mixer blade. The
mass was cooled to 37 °C in 40 hours by a linear cooling program. At the end
of the cooling program, the mass was mixed at 37 °C for 8 hours, before the
crystals were separated by centrifugation (Hettich Roto Silenta II centrifuge;
basket diameter 24 cm). The mass was centrifuged for 5 minutes at 4,000
rpm. During centrifugation, the crystals were washed with 80 ml distilled water.
The centrifugation results are shown in Table 8.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Mass introduced into centrifuge (g)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>620</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">DS of the mass (w-%)</entry><entry align="center">70.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Purity of the mass (% on DS)</entry><entry align="center">80.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Crystal cake (g)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>200</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">DS of the cake (w-%)</entry><entry align="center">97.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Purity of the cake (% on DS)</entry><entry align="center">96.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Purity of the run-off (% on DS)</entry><entry align="center">65.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Yield in centrifugation, DS/DS (w-%)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>44</b></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method of producing xylitol and erythritol from arabinoxylan-containing
material, characterized in that the arabinoxylan-containing
material is hydrolyzed and xylose and arabinose are separated from the obtained
hydrolysate, whereafter the xylose is reduced to xylitol and the xylitol is
recovered, and the arabinose is subjected to alkaline oxidation to obtain
erythronic acid which is reduced to erythritol and the erythritol is recovered.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method as claimed in claim 1, characterized in that
the arabinoxylan-containing material is corn fibers.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method as claimed in claim 1, characterized in that
the arabinoxylan-containing material is barley fibers.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of claims 1 to 3, characterized
in that hydrolysis is carried out using sulphuric acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of claims 1 to 4, characterized
in that separation of xylose and arabinose is carried out chromatographically.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of claims 1 to 5, characterized
in that the xylose and/or arabinose are purified by crystallization.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of claims 1 to 6, characterized in that reduction of xylose is carried out catalytically with hydrogen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of claims 1 to 7, characterized
in that the obtained xylitol is recovered by crystallization.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method as claimed in claim 7, characterized in that
the catalyst is Raney-Ni.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A method as claimed in claim 1, characterized in that
oxidation of arabinose is carried out in a methanol-water solution.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A method as claimed in claim 1 or 10, characterized in
that oxidation is carried out with oxygen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of claims 1 to 6, 10 or 11,
characterized in that reduction of erythronic acid is carried out catalytically
with hydrogen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A method as claimed in claim 12, characterized in that
the catalyst is Ru.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of claims 1, 10, 11, 12 or 13,
characterized in that the obtained erythritol is recovered by crystallization.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>