<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1454968-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1454968" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="32821188" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040908"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1454968-A1" status="new" fvid="24147261"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1454968</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040908</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04004875-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04004875</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040302</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2003057690-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2003057690</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030304</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C2B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Dispergierte Pigmente enthaltende wässrige Aufzeichnungsflüssigkeit und bedrucktes Material</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid and printed material</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Liquide d'enregistrement aqueux contenant un pigment dispersé et matériau imprimé</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1086975-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1086975</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1167466-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1167466</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1270251-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1270251</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000052106-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000052106</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2003062331-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2003062331</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MIKUNI COLOR WORKS</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI CHEM CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SEIKO EPSON CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MIKUNI SHIKISO KABUSHIKI KAISHA</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI CHEMICAL CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SEIKO EPSON CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MIKUNI SHIKISO KABUSHIKI KAISHA</last-name><address><street>138-1, Kokubunji, Mikuni-cho</street><city>Himeji-shi, Hyogo 671-0234</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Mitsubishi Chemical Corporation</last-name><address><street>33-8, Shiba 5-chome, Minato-ku</street><city>Tokyo 108-0014</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SEIKO EPSON CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>4-1, Nishi-Shinjuku 2-chome</street><city>Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo 163-0811</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KAKIUCHI MUNETAKA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KAMAMASU SEIJI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KATAOKA SHUICHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OHYA KIMIHIKO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OYANAGI TAKASHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KAKIUCHI, MUNETAKA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KAMAMASU, SEIJI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KATAOKA, SHUICHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OHYA, KIMIHIKO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OYANAGI, TAKASHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kakiuchi, Munetaka, c/oMitsubishi Chemical Corp.</last-name><address><street>1, Toho-cho</street><city>Yokkaichi-shi Mie</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kamamasu, Seiji, c/oMikuni Shikiso Kabushiki Kaish</last-name><address><street>138-1, Kokubunji Mikunino-cho</street><city>Himeji-shi Hyogo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kataoka, Shuichi, c/oSeiko Epson Corporation</last-name><address><street>3-5, Owa 3-chome</street><city>Suwa-shi Nagano</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Ohya, Kimihiko, c/oMikuni Shikiso Kabushiki Kaish</last-name><address><street>138-1, Kokubunji Mikunino-cho</street><city>Himeji-shi Hyogo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Oyanagi, Takashi, c/oSeiko Epson Corporation</last-name><address><street>3-5, Owa 3-chome</street><city>Suwa-shi Nagano</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hartz, Nikolai, Dr.</last-name><address><street>Wächtershauser &amp;amp; Hartz Weinstrasse 8</street><city>80333 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
containing at least a pigment and a resin, which
comprises from 60 to 200 parts by weight of the resin to
100 parts by weight of the pigment, wherein at least one
of the resin is a water-dispersible urethane type resin,
a weight fraction of a polyurethane urea part of which is
at most 2.0 wt% to the urethane resin, and the pigment
dispersed. in the recording liquid has a dispersion
particle size D50 of from 40 to 100 nm.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a pigment-dispersed
aqueous recording liquid, particularly a pigment-dispersed
aqueous recording liquid suitable as an ink jec
recording liquid or a handwriting recording liquid, and
also relates to a printed material.</p><p num="0002">Ink jec recording has a high resolution, and it is
therefore used as a printing method for a photographic
tone digital image. Most of photographic tone ink jet
recordings for domestic or office uses include a method
of printing an aqueous recording liquid using a dye as a
coloring material by ink jet system on a paper or a film
(both of which are referred to as a printing paper)
having a surface smoothly coated with a resin or an
inorganic material. A dye has been used for a long time
as a coloring material for an ink jet recording liquid
since it is hardly solidified during long term storing of
a recording liquid or it hardly clogs a nozzle of an ink
jet printer. Also, since the dye can relatively 
uniformly dye a coat layer of an ink jet printing paper,
it colors without damaging a glossy feeling derived from
the smoothness of the coat layer and provides a printed
material having a glossy feeling.</p><p num="0003">However, an ink jet-printed paper printed with an
aqueous recording liquid using a dye as a coloring
material is poor in water resistance, weather resistance
and light resistance.</p><p num="0004">Therefore, in order to improve an ink jet recording
liquid, a pigment has been used as a coloring material
excellent in water resistance, weather resistance and
light resistance to improve water resistance, weather
resistance and light resistance of a printed material.
However, the recording liquid using a pigment tends to be
denatured and to degrade storage stability due to
agglomeration and settling of the pigment, and also tends
co clog an ink jet nozzle.</p><p num="0005">Also, a pigment causes problems that when a pigment
is penetrated into a coat layer of an ink jet printing
paper, gloss is good but a color-developing property is
not good as compared with a dye, and that when the
pigment is solidified to form a pigment layer on the coat
layer, a color-developing property is good but glossy
feeling is bad. Also, it has been tried to improve gloss
by adding a water-soluble resin of styrene derivative or
the like (see, for example, JP-A-6-116522 and JP-A-2002-20673),
but when such a water-soluble resin is added, a 
solid content becomes large and a viscosity is raised,
thereby disturbing ejection of ink and degrading storage
stability.</p><p num="0006">Also, in order to solve such problems in respect of
viscosity increase and storage stability, it has been
proposed to use a urethane type resin as a water-soluble
resin (see, for example, JP-A-6-279718, JP-A-7-82516 and
JP-A-10-168151). For example, JP-A-6-279718 proposes an
ink jet recoding liquid, wherein printing performance and
abrasion resistance are improved and clogging of an
ejecting nozzle is prevented by using a urethane type
resin having a molecular weight of at most 5,000 and
having a specific functional group such as a carboxyl
group introduced therein.</p><p num="0007">Further, JP-A-7-82516 proposes a intermediate
transferring type ink jet recording liquid having
printing performance and abrasion resistance improved by
using a volatile alkali material and a colloidal
dispersion resin such as a urethane resin.</p><p num="0008">Still further, JP-A-10-168151 discloses to use an
aqueous recording liquid containing a urethane type resin
having a high acid value of 100 to 250 mgKOH/g obtained
from carboxylated diol and polyisocyanate as a printing
method using ink jet. It proposes to form a high density
image having no blur by using such a recording liquid.</p><p num="0009">As described above, as a result of many trials,
there has been produced an aqueous recording liquid 
having a pigment dispersed, which has storage stability,
does not clog a nozzle, and provides water resistance,
weather resistance and light resistance on a printed
material. For example, as a black recording liquid,
there are enumerated HP51645A of Hewlett-Packard , BCI-3eBK
of CANON, ICBK23 and ICMB23 of Seiko Epson, FPB-BK
of Roland (type numbers) and the like.</p><p num="0010">However, according to the present techniques
represented by these recording liquids, it has been
difficult to provide a photographic tone recording liquid
which produces both photographic tone blackness and
glossy feeling on a printed material aiming at a
photographic image quality printing paper and which gives
abrasion resistance on a printed surface. Thus, in order
to aim at a photographic image quality printing paper and
to provide photographic tone blackness and gloss, there
have been sold ink jet printing papers such as PM
photographic paper, photoprofessional, QP photographic
paper or the like. They have an ink-receiving layer
comprising a porous layer having pores of at most
nanometer scale or an ink-receiving layer having a
swelling type polymer coated on at least one side of
printing media, and have such a smoothness on the surface
as a photographic paper, but a pigment type ink has not
imparted satisfactory glossy feeling and blackness to
these photographic image quality printing papers having
these ink-receiving layer surfaces. </p><p num="0011">An object of the present invention is to provide an
aqueous recording liquid having a pigment dispersed,
which gives storage stability, does not clog a nozzle,
imparts satisfactory water resistance, weather resistance
and light resistance to a printed paper, provides both
photographic tone blackness and glossy feeling on a
printed material aiming at media having a smooth surface,
and also imparts quite high abrasion resistance to a
printed surface.</p><p num="0012">The present inventors have intensively studied with
regard to a water-soluble high molecular material added
for the purpose of dispersion stability of 3 pigment and
for improving gloss of a printed material or abrasion
resistance of a recording liquid. As this result, it has
been discovered that viscosity increase of an aqueous
dispersion can be prevented and dispersion stability of a
pigment can be maintained by using a urethane type resin
having a hydrolyzable group such as an ester bond or an
amide bond in a much smaller amount, e.g. having a
polyurethane urea part in a smaller amount, but having a
relatively high molecular weight exceeding 5,000, and
also even by using this resin in a large amount to a
pigment (e.g. at least 60 parts by weight to 100 parts of
a pigment) to improve abrasion resistance.</p><p num="0013">Further, it has been discovered that when a
dispersed particle size of a pigment dispersed in a
pigment dispersed aqueous liquid using such a urethane 
type resin is within a specific range, the pigments
remained on the surface of a printed material printed by
such a recording liquid are densely aligned, and gloss
and abrasion resistance of the printed material become
remarkably satisfactory.</p><p num="0014">Thus, the essential features of the present
invention reside in:
<sl><li>(1) a pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
containing at least a pigment and a resin, which
comprises from 60 to 200 parts by weight of the resin to
100 parts by weight of the pigment, wherein at least one
of the resin is a water-dispersible urethane type resin,
a weight fraction of a polyurethane urea part of which is
at most 2.0 wt% to the urethane resin, and the pigment
dispersed in the recording liquid has a dispersion
particle size D50 of from 40 to 100 nm;</li><li>(2) the pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to the above feature (1), wherein the pigment
includes at least a carbon black having a DBP absorption
amount of from 30 ml/100 g to 100 ml/100 g;</li><li>(3) the pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to the above feature (1) or (2), wherein the
urethane type resin has a weight average molecular weight
of higher than 5,000 but not higher than 100,000;</li><li>(4) the pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to any one of the above features (1) to (3),
wherein an acid value as a free acid of the urethane type 
resin is from 20 mgKOH/g to 100 mgKOH/g;</li><li>(5) the pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to any one of the above features (1) to (4),
wherein the resin includes a resin having an acid value
of at least 50 mgKOH/g as a free acid in addition to the
water-dispersible urethane type resin;</li><li>(6) the pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to any one of the above features (1) to (5),
wherein a solid-printed part having 14.5 mg per square
inch of a pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
printed by ink jet recording system on a photographic
image quality paper provides a printed thickness of at
least 20 nm, an optical density of at least 2 and a 20°
gloss value of at least 60;</li><li>(7) the pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to any one of the above features (1) to (6),
wherein the pigment includes a carbon black and a pigment
other than the carbon black;</li><li>(6) the pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to the above feature (7), wherein the pigment
other than the carbon black is a cyan pigment;</li><li>(9) a printed material printed with a pigment-dispersed
aqueous recording liquid as defined in any one of the
above features (1) to (8);</li><li>(10) the printed material according to the above feature
(9), wherein the printing is carried out by ejecting a
pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid by an ink jet 
nozzle on a material to be recorded;</li><li>(11) the printed material according to the above feature
(9) or (10), which has a printed thickness of at least 20
nm, an optical density of at least 2 and a 20° gloss
value of at least 60;</li><li>(12) the printed material according to any one of the
above features (9) to (11), which has an arithmetic
average roughness of at most 0.04;</li><li>(13) the printed material according to any one of the
above features (9) to (12), wherein the pigment-dispersed
aqueous recording liquid contains at least a carbon black
and the printed material is a black printed material;</li><li>(14) a pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid wherein
a solid-printed part having 14.5 mg of ink per square
inch printed by ink jet recording system on a
photographic image quality paper provides a printed
thickness of at least 20 nm, an optical density of at
least 2 and a 20° gloss value of at least 60;</li><li>(15) the pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according co the above feature (14), which contains at
least a carbon black;</li><li>(16) a printed material printed by ejecting a pigment-dispersed
aqueous recording liquid through an ink jet
nozzle on a material to be recorded, which provides a
printed thickness of at least 20 nm, an optical density
of at least 2 and a 20° gloss value of at least 60; and</li><li>(17) the printed material according to the above feature 
(16), wherein at least 14.5 mg per square inch of ink is
deposited on a photographic image quality paper by solid-printing.</li></sl></p><p num="0015">Hereinafter, the present invention is described in
more details.</p><p num="0016">Firstly, a pigment used in the preset invention is
described. The pigment usable in the present invention
is not specially limited, but may be any one of an
organic pigment and an inorganic pigment. Their examples
are illustrated below.</p><p num="0017">In the present invention, a black pigment,
particularly a carbon black, is used as a pigment
excellent in blackness, gloss, and other performances. A
usable carbon black is not specially limited, but
includes acetylene black, channel black, furnace black,
and the like. Among them, channel black and furnace
black have preferably high blackness, and furnace black
is particularly preferable.</p><p num="0018">In view of printing grade, the above-mentioned
carbon blacks preferably have a DBP absorption amount of
generally from 30 ml/100 g to 100 ml/100 g, more
preferably from 50 ml/100 g to 80 ml/100 g. If the DEP
absorption amount is less than 30 ml/100 g, it is hardly
dispersible, and if the DBP absorption amount is more
than 100 ml/100 g, its dispersed particle size becomes
finally large and a gloss of printed material is lowered.
Since a carbon black having a large DBP absorption amount 
has a structure well developed, pulverization can not be
effected smaller than the structure even when it is tried
to be pulverized smaller.</p><p num="0019">A volatile content of carbon black is generally at
most 8 wt%, preferably at most 6 wt%. pH is generally
from 1 to 11, and in view of storage stability of a
recording liquid, it is preferably from 3 to 10, more
preferably from 6 to 9. A BET specific surface area is
generally at least 100 m<sup>2</sup>/g, preferably from 150 to 600
m<sup>2</sup>/g, more preferably from 260 to 500 m<sup>2</sup>/g. If the
specific surface area is too small, blackness is lowered
since an area absorbing light becomes small, and if the
specific surface area is too large, ejection of ink is
not satisfactorily effected since an amount of a
dispersant necessary for dispersion becomes large. A
primary particle size is generally at most 30 nm,
preferably at most 20 nm, more preferably at most 16 nm,
most preferably at most 15 nm.</p><p num="0020">The DBP absorption amount is a value measured in
accordance with JIS K6221 A method, the volatile content
is a value measured in accordance with JIS K6221, and the
primary particle size is a value of arithmetic average
particle size (number average) measured by an electron
microscope.</p><p num="0021">Examples of the above-mentioned carbon blacks
include #2650, #2600, #2300, #2200, #1000, #980, #970,
#966, #960, #950, #900, #850, MCF-88, #55, #52, #47, #45, 
#45L, #44, #33, #32, #30 (manufactured by Mitsubishi
Chemical Corporation), Special Black4A, 550, Printex 95,
90, 85, 80, 75, 45, 40 (manufactured by Degussa Co.,
Ltd.), Rega 1660, Rmogul L, monarch 1400, 1300, 1100, 800,
900 (manufactured by Cabot Co., Ltd.), Raven 7000, 5750,
5250, 3500, 3500, 2500 ULTRA, 2000, 1500, 1255, 1200,
1190 ULTRA, 1170, 1100 ULTRA, Raven 5000 UIII
(manufactured by Columbian Co., Ltd.), and the like.</p><p num="0022">Examples of a yellow pigment include C.I. Pigment
Yellow 1, 2, 3, 12, 13, 14, 16, 17, 73, 74, 75, 83, 93,
95, 97, 98, 114, 128, 129, 151, 154 and the like.</p><p num="0023">Also, examples of a magenta pigment include C.I.
Pigment Red 5, 7, 12, 48(Ca), C.I. 48(Mn), 57(Ca), 57:1,
112, 123, 168, 184, 202 and the like.</p><p num="0024">Examples of a cyan pigment include C.I. Pigment Blue
1, 2, 3, 15:3, 15:4, 16, 22, 60, 4, 60 and the like.</p> <p num="0025">In addition to the above pigment, C.I. Pigment Red
209, 122, 224, 177, 194, C.I. Pigment Orange 43, C.I.
Pigment violet 19, 23, 37, C.I. Pigment Green 36, 7, C.I.
Pigment Blue 15:6, 209 and the like are usable.</p><p num="0026">Also, in the present invention, a pigment used is
not limited to one pigment but may be used in combination
with one or more of the above pigments.</p><p num="0027">The present invention provides a particularly
excellent performance if it is used as a black pigment-dispersed
aqueous recording liquid. It is particularly
preferable to use a carbon black in the black pigment-dispersed 
aqueous recording liquid among the above-mentioned
pigments. Also, in addition to a carbon black,
by using other pigments in combination therewith, a black
color printed material having a satisfactory bluish color
can be obtained. The pigment to be combined is
preferably a cyan pigment, particularly C.I. Pigment Blue
15:3.</p><p num="0028">Also, the pigments used in the pigment-dispersed
aqueous recording liquid (sometimes hereinafter simply
referred to as "recording liquid") of the present
invention may be chemically treated (oxidation treatment,
fluorination treatment or the like), or may be physically
or chemically bonded with a dispersant, a surfactant or
the like (graft-modification treatment, adsorption with a
dispersant before dispersing or the like). Examples of
the pigments thus treated include Cab-o-jet 200 or Cab-o-jet
300 (manufactured by Cabot Co., Led.), and the like.</p><p num="0029">Next, a urethane type resin used in the present
invention is explained hereinafter.</p> <p num="0030">The urethane type resin is a high molecular material,
the main chain of which has a polyurethane structure
bonded with a urethane bond, and includes a well known
urethane resin.</p> <p num="0031">In the present invention, it is particularly
preferable to use a water-dispersible urethane resin
among the urethane type resin. Such a water-dispersible
urethane resin is generally one having a hydrophilic 
component necessary for stably dispersing in water
introduced into the main chain of a polyurethane
structure or a water dispersion of polyurethane obtained
by dispersing with an outside emulsifier, but a self-dispersible
type (self-emulsifiable type) polyurethane
having a hydrophilic component introduced into the main
chain is more preferable. It may be in any form of
colloidal dispersion, emulsion, suspension or slurry.</p> <p num="0032">Examples of the urethane type resin used in the
present invention include preferably various water-dispersible
urethane type resins (ester type urethane
resin, ether type urethane resin, carbonate type urethane
resin and the like) obtained by reacting a diisocyanate
compound, a diol compound such as polyether diols,
polyester diols, polycarbonate diols or the like, and a
diol containing an acid group such as a carboxylic acid
group, a sulfonic acid group or the like.</p><p num="0033">Examples of the diisocyanate compound include an
aliphatic diisocyanate compound such as hexamethylene
diisocyanate, 2,2,4-trimethylhexamethylene diisocyanate
or the like, an alicyclic diisocyanate compound such as
isophorone diisocyanate, hydrogenated xylene diisocyanate,
1,4-cyclohexane diisocyanate, 4,4'-dicyclohexylmethane
diisocyanate or the like, an arylaliphatic diisocyanate
compound such as xylylene diisocyanate,
tetramethylxylylene diisocyanate or the like, and an
aromatic diisocyanate compound such as toluylene 
diisocyanate, phenylmethane diisocyanate or the like, and
their modified materials of diisocyanates (such as
carbodiimide, uretodion, uretoimine-containing modified
products).</p><p num="0034">Examples of the diol compound include a polyether
diol such as polyethylene glycol, polypropylene glycol,
polytetramethylene ether glycol, polyhexamethylene ether
glycol or the like, a polyester diol such as polyethylene
adipate, polybutylene adipate, polyneopentyl adipate,
poly-3-methylpentyl adipate, polyethylene/butylene
adipate, polyneopentyl/hexyl adipate or the like, a
polylactone diol such as polycaprolactone diol or the
like, and a polycarbonate diol. In view of storage
stability of ink, it is preferable to use a diol compound
of polyether type, polyester type or polycarbonate type,
more preferably polyether type or polycarbonate type,
most preferably polyether type. The polyether type or
polycarbonate type diol compound has a satisfactory
storage stability since it is hardly denatured by
hydrolysis.</p><p num="0035">Examples of the acid group-containing diol include
dimethylolacetic acid, dimethylolbutanoic acid,
dimethylolpropionic acid, dimethylolbutyric acid and the
like. Particularly, dimethylolbutanoic acid is
preferable.</p><p num="0036">Examples of a method for preparing a urethane type
resin include a solution method which comprises preparing 
an isocyanate-terminated prepolymer in a low boiling
solvent (such as acetone) unreactive with an isocyanate
group, introducing a hydrophilic group such as diamine or
polyol therein, effecting phase change by diluting with
water, and distilling off a solvent to obtain a
polyurethane dispersion, a prepolymer method which
comprises preparing an isocyanate group-terminated
prepolymer having a hydrophilic group introduced,
dispersing in water, and extending a chain with an amine,
other hot melt method, a method of using water medium as
a chain extender of a urethane prepolymer in an
emulsifier aqueous solution, a method which comprises a
step of sulfonating an aromatic ring of a urethane
prepolymer having a free isocyanate group obtained from
an aromatic polyisocyanate and a hydrophobic polyol, a
method of using a block isocyanate, and other well known
methods, but should not be limited thereto.</p><p num="0037">Particularly, a urethane type resin may be prepared
by the prepolymer method, and a polyhydroxy compound
having a low molecular weight may be used at that time.
Examples of the polyhydroxy compound having a low
molecular weight include the above illustrated starting
materials of the polyester diol, such as glycol and
alkylene oxide-low mol adduct, a trihydric alcohol such
as glycerin, trimethylolethane or trimethylolpropane, its
alkylene oxide-low mol adduct, and the like.</p><p num="0038">In case of an aqueous type urethane resin, it is 
generally known to use a method which comprises effecting
phase change of a urethane polymer prepared in an organic
solvent phase and emulsifying to further extend a chain
in an aqueous phase. It is usual to use polyamines such
as diamine as a chain extender at that time. For example,
the urethane prepolymer is subjected to neutralization of
an acid group derived from dimethylolalkanoic acid and
chain extension with water or di- or triamine after or
while neutralizing. Examples of the polyamines used as a
chain extender in the amine extension include generally
diamine or triamine. Their particular examples include
hexamethylenediamine, isophoronediamine, hydrazine,
piperazine and the like.</p><p num="0039">However, it has been found that storage stability of
a recording liquid containing a urethane type resin
prepared by using polyamines as a chain extender tends to
be poor. This is because a urethane resin (a
polyurethane resin containing a polyurethane urea part)
having a chain extended with an amine tends to be
hydrolyzed, and it is further considered that polyamines
formed by hydrolysis also works as an agglomerating agent
in the pigment-dispersed recording liquid, thus causing
double bad influences.</p><p num="0040">One of the essential features of the present
invention is to use a urethane type resin in which a
weight fraction of a polyurethane urea part in the
urethane type resin is at most 2.0 wt%. A satisfactory 
recording liquid having an excellent storage stability
can be obtained by using such a specific urethane type
resin, having the resin present in a specific ratio to a
pigment and employing a pigment having a dispersed
particle size in such a specific range as described below.
The ink jet recording liquid thus obtained maintains
stably excellent physical properties, and can be
satisfactorily printed by ejecting under severe strict
conditions. Also, the stability of pigment dispersion
state at the time of drying a photographic image quality
printing paper surface is improved (prevention of
agglomeration), thereby providing a satisfactory
smoothness of the surface, a resin gloss of a polymer of
the main urethane type resin, and both satisfactory gloss
and blackness improved in an ink-receiving layer of the
photographic image quality printing paper surface due to
uniform presence of the pigment within a film having a
satisfactory film-formability. Thus, it is considered
that the pigment is satisfactorily dispersed in such a
stable state as to achieve high optical performances and
the urethane type resin itself contributes to the
improved gloss.</p><p num="0041">A weight fraction of polyurethane urea part in a
urethane type resin is at most 2.0 wt%, preferably at
most 1-8 wt%, more preferably at most 1-5 wt%, most
preferably at most 1.0 wt%, and it is further preferable
not to contain a substantial amount of the polyurethane 
urea part.</p><p num="0042">Such a desired polyurethane type resin having an
aimed molecular weight can be prepared by not using a
chain extender such as a polyamine in a conventional well
known preparation method. Also, it is preferable to
carry out the preparation of a polyurethane type resin
under substantially anhydrous conditions. This is to
prevent a polyisocyanate compound as a starting material
for a urethane type resin from reacting with water
content to produce a polyamine. Thus, this is to avoid
the production of a polyurethane urea part.</p><p num="0043">A weight fraction of a polyurethane urea part in the
urethane type resin, i.e. a chain-extended part such as
diamines introduced by an amine extender, can be
determined from a weight ratio of polyamines in the
starting materials charged in the preparation of the
urethane type resin used in the present invention. For
example, the weight ratio can be determined by dividing
the weight of polyamines by the total weight of all
starting materials used in the preparation of the
polyurethane type resin.</p><p num="0044">Heretofore, when a pigment type ink was used on a
photographic image quality printing paper having a glossy
surface, the gloss was lowered since fine agglomeration
of the pigment was caused on the glossy surface. However,
according to the present invention, the agglomeration of
a pigment is prevented and a satisfactory dispersion 
state is maintained on the surface of a paper to be
recorded, thereby providing improved gloss and blackness.</p><p num="0045">In the present invention, it is preferable to use a
polyether type urethane resin as a urethane type resin,
particularly from viewpoints of stability of ink and
gloss of a printed material.</p><p num="0046">A urethane type resin may be used in a form of an
alkali metal salt of Li, Na or K, or in a form of an
organic amine salt of ammonia, dimethylamine, (mono-, di-,
tri-)ethanolamine or the like. They can be obtained by
further neutralizing a urethane type resin obtained by
the above-mentioned methods. A base used for this
neutralization may be optionally selected depending on a
counter ion or the like of a desired salt, and their
examples include an alkylamine such as butylamine or
triethylamine, an alkanolamine such as monoethanolamine,
diethanolamine or triethanolamine, morpholine, ammonia,
or an inorganic base such as sodium hydroxide or the like.</p><p num="0047">In order to improve storage stability and ejecting
stability of a recording liquid, the lower limit of an
acid value of a free acid of the above urethane type
resin used in the present invention is preferably at
least 20 mgKOH/g, more preferably at least 30 mgKOH/g,
more further preferably at least 50 mgKOH/g, most
preferably at least 60 mgKOH/g.</p><p num="0048">Also, the upper limit of an acid value is preferably
at most 200 mgKOH/g, more preferably at most 100 mgKOH/g, 
most preferably at most 85 mgKOH/g, particularly at most
70 mgKOH/g. If the lower limit of an acid value is lower
than 15 mgKOH/g, water-solubility is lost, and if the
upper limit of an acid value exceeds 200 mgKOH/g,
abrasion resistance and water resistance of a coated film
are lowered and a viscosity becomes too high, thereby
sometimes causing a problem of unsatisfactory ejecting
performance. Also, in order to maintain a satisfactorily
stable ejecting performance, a weight average molecular
weight of the above high molecular material is usually at
most 300,000, preferably at most 100,000, more preferably
at most 50,000, most preferably at most 30,000. On the
other hand, the lower limit of the weight average
molecular weight is usually higher than 5,000, preferably
at least 8,000, more preferably at least 10,000, most
preferably at least 12,000. If the molecular weight is
too high, a viscosity becomes high, thereby lowering an
ejecting performance.</p><p num="0049">On the other hand, if the molecular weight is at
most 5,000, the urethane type resin tends to become
greatly water-soluble, and a gloss-imparting effect is
lowered. Also, liquid stability tends to be lowered.</p><p num="0050">Further, in addition to the above urethane type
resin, it is preferable to use other various water-soluble
resins in combination therewith. Typical
examples of such a water-soluble resin include an anionic
water-soluble high molecular material. </p><p num="0051">In view of storage stability of a recording liquid,
the anionic water-soluble high molecular material in a
free acid form has an acid value of generally at least 40
mgKOH/g, preferably at least 50 mgKOH/g, more preferably
at least 100 mgKOH/g, most preferably at least 150
mgKOH/g. If the acid value is lower than 40 mgKOH/g, an
electrostatic repulsing force derived from a functional
group of a resin adsorbed on a pigment becomes small,
thereby degrading dispersion and dispersion stability.
Also, a copolymer having a hydrophobic group is
preferable in view of dispersion stability of carbon
black, and water resistance and abrasion resistance of a
printed material.</p><p num="0052">Examples of the hydrophobic group in a high
molecular material include an organic group having an
aromatic ring such as a phenyl group, a benzyl group or a
naphthyl group which may be substituted, and an alkyl
group, an alkenyl group, an alkynyl group or a cycloalkyl
group, which has a carbon number of at least 4 and may be
branched or substituted, and among them, an organic group
having an aromatic ring is preferable.</p><p num="0053">Concrete examples of the anionic water-soluble high
molecular material used in the present invention include
(α-methyl) styrene/maleic acid copolymer, (α-methyl)styrene/(meth)acrylic
acid copolymer, (α-methyl)styrene/(meth)acrylic
acid ester/(meth)acrylic
acid copolymer, (meth)acrylic acid ester/(meth)acrylic 
acid copolymer, (meth)acrylic acid ester/maleic acid
copolymer and/or their salts, and preferable examples
include (α-methyl)styrene/(meth)acrylic acid copolymer.
In the present specification, "(α-methyl)styrene" means
"α-methylstyrene and/or styrene", and "(meth)acrylic
acid" means "methacrylic acid and/or acrylic acid".</p><p num="0054">The anionic water-soluble high molecular material
used herein may be any of a block polymer, a graft
polymer and a random polymer, but in view of a
manufacturing cost, a graft polymer or a random polymer
is preferable, and particularly a random polymer is
preferable. Also, in view of ejecting stability, their
weight average molecular weight is preferably at most
50,000, more preferably at most 15,000, most preferably
at most 10,000. If the molecular weight becomes too high,
a viscosity becomes high and an ejecting performance
becomes poor. Further, a copolymer having an acid value
of at least 150 mgKOH/g may be used in a form of an
alkali metal salt of Li, Na or K, or an organic amine
salt of ammonia, dimethylamine or (mono-, di-,
tri-)ethanolamine.</p><p num="0055">Examples of commercially available products of the
above high molecular material or high molecular material
solution include "Johncryl 67", "679", "680", "682",
"683", "690" and/or their salts, "Johncryl 52", "57",
"60", "62", "63", "70", "354", "501", "6610", and the
like, manufactured by Johnson Polymer Co., Ltd. </p><p num="0056">A medium used for a recording liquid of the present
invention is usually an aqueous medium containing water
as the main component, but it is preferable to have a
water-soluble organic solvent added to water.</p><p num="0057">The above water-soluble organic solvent is
classified into one having a function as a moisture-retaining
agent and one having a function as a
penetrating solvent.</p><p num="0058">Examples of the former material as a moisture-retaining
agent include ethylene glycol, propylene glycol,
1,3-propanediol, diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol,
polyethylene glycol (particular examples: "#200", "#300",
"#400", "#4000" and "#6000" manufactured by Wako Pure
Chemical Industries, Ltd.), glycerin, 2-pyrrolidone, N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone,
1,3-dimethylimidazolinone,
thiodiglycol, sulfolane, dimethylsulfoxide, neopentyl
alcohol, trimethylolpropane, 2,2-dimethylpropanol, and
the like.</p><p num="0059">Examples of the penetrating solvent (penetrating
assistant) include ethylene glycol monomethyl ether,
ethylene glycol dimethyl ether, ethylene glycol monoethyl
ether, ethylene glycol diethyl ether, ethylene glycol
mono-n-propyl ether, ethylene glycol monoisopropyl ether,
ethylene glycol mono-n-butyl ether, ethylene glycol mono-sec-butyl
ether, ethylene glycol monoisobutyl ether,
ethylene glycol mono-tert-butyl ether, ethylene glycol
mono-n-amyl ether, ethylene glycol mono-n-hexyl ether, 
propylene glycol monomethyl ether, propylene glycol
dimethyl ether, propylene glycol monoethyl ether,
propylene glycol diethyl ether, propylene glycol mono-n-propyl
ether, propylene glycol monoisopropyl ether,
propylene glycol mono-n-butyl ether, propylene glycol
mono-sec-butyl ether, propylene glycol monoisobutyl ether,
propylene glycol mono-tert-butyl ether, diethylene glycol
monomethyl ether, diethylene glycol dimethyl ether,
diethylene glycol monoethyl ether, diethylene glycol
mono-n-propyl ether, diethylene glycol monoisopropyl
ether, diethylene glycol mono-n-butyl ether, diethylene
glycol mono-sec-butyl ether, diethylene glycol
monoisobutyl ether, diethylene glycol mono-tert-butyl
ether, dipropylene glycol monomethyl ether, dipropylene
glycol monoethyl ether, dipropylene glycol mono-n-propyl
ether, triethylene glycol mono-n-butyl ether,
polyethylene glycol monopropyl ether, polyethylene glycol
monobutyl ether, ethylene glycol adduct of glycerin
(particular examples: "Liponic EG-1" manufactured by
Lipochemical Co., Ltd.), and the like.</p><p num="0060">These organic solvents may be used respectively
alone or in a mixture of two or more.</p><p num="0061">Also, in order to enhance the penetrating property
of a recording liquid, various surfactants may be used
for the recording liquid of the present invention.
Examples of the surfactants include various surfactants
such as an anionic surfactant, a nonionic surfactant, a 
cationic surfactant or an amphoteric surfactant.</p><p num="0062">Examples of the nonionic surfactant include
aliphatic acid salts, alkylsulfuric acid ester salts,
alkylbenzenesulfonic acid salts, alkylnaphthalenesulfonic
acid salts, alkylsulfosuccinic acid salts,
alkyldiphenyletherdisulfonic acid salts, alkylphosphoric
acid salts, polyoxyethylenealkylsulfuric acid ester salts,
polyoxyethylenealkylarylsulfuric acid ester salts,
alkanesulfonic acid salts, naphthalenesulfonic acid
formalin condensates, polyoxyethylenealkylphosphoric acid
esters, N-methyl-N-oleoyltaurinic acid salts, α-olefinsulfonic
acid salts, and the like.</p><p num="0063">The nonionic surfactant is not specially limited,
but one having an ethylene oxide structure or a propylene
oxide structure is preferable in view of storage
stability and printing density, and among them, one
having an NLB value of from 9 to 17, particularly from 10
to 16, is more preferable.</p><p num="0064">Particular examples of the nonionic surfactant
include polyoxyethylene nonyl phenyl ether,
polyoxyethylene octyl phenyl ether, polyoxyethylene alkyl
ether, polyoxyethylene lauryl ether, polyoxyethylene
oleyl ether, polyoxyethylene tridecyl ether,
polyoxyethylene cetyl ether, polyoxyethylene stearyl
ether, polyoxyethylene alkylamine, aminopolyoxyethylene,
sorbitan aliphatic acid ester, polyoxyethylene sorbitan
laurate, polyoxyethylene sorbitan palmitate, 
polyoxyethylene sorbitan stearate, polyoxyethylene
sorbitan oleate, naphtholethylene oxide adduct, acetylene
glycol ethylene oxide adduct, bisphenol A ethylene oxide
adduct, oxyethylene oxypropylene block polymer, sorbitan
aliphatic acid ester, polyoxyethylene sorbitan aliphatic
acid ester, polyoxyethylene sorbitol aliphatic acid ester,
glycerin aliphatic acid ester, polyoxyethylene aliphatic
acid ester, polyoxyethylene alkylamine, α-olefin sulfonic
acid salt, and the like. Commercially available products
of the nonionic surfactant are usable, examples of which
include Surfinol 440, Surfinol 465 and Surfinol 485
(manufactured by Air Products and Chemicals, Inc.),
Acetylenol EH and Acetylenol EL (manufactured by Kawaken
Fine Chemicals Co., Ltd.) and the like.</p><p num="0065">on the other hand, examples of the cationic
surfactant and the amphoteric surfactant include
alkylamine salts, quaternary ammonium salts,
alkylbetaines, aminoxides, and the like.</p><p num="0066">A nonionic surfactant having a low molecular weight
is used in an amount of usually from 0.1 to 3 parts by
weight, preferably from 0.5 to 1 part by weight, to 100
parts by weight of a recording liquid. A surface tension
of the recording liquid is appropriately controlled by a
kind and an amount of the nonionic surfactant of a low
molecular weight, but the surface tension of the
recording liquid of the present invention is preferably
from 25 dyne/cm to 54 dyne/cm. If the surface tension 
exceeds 54 dyne/cm, a penetrating speed of the recording
liquid into a material to be recorded becomes too slow,
and consequently a printing speed must be made lower. On
the other hand, if the surface tension of the recording
liquid is smaller than 25 dyne/cm, a penetrating speed of
the recording liquid into a material to be recorded
becomes too high, and consequently a satisfactory
printing density can not be obtained.</p><p num="0067">The composition of the recording liquid may be made
into an ink composition having a satisfactory penetrating
property to recording media and also having an excellent
continuous ejecting stability by incorporating a
surfactant having an acetylene bond therein, for example,
as illustrated in JP-A-2001-302,950. Also, a propylene
oxide adduct of a lower alcohol may be added thereto in
combination therewith. Further, as illustrated in JP-A-2000-3,760,
a specific compound having an acetylene bond,
1,5-pentanediol, a butylether type solvent or the like
may be contained therein.</p><p num="0068">Still further, as illustrated in JP-A-2000-30,237,
it is possible to prepare an ink composition containing
an acetylene glycol type surfactant and/or a polysiloxane
type surfactant, an alkyl ether derivative of a
polyhydric alcohol having an alkyl group having a carbon
number of at least 3 (preferably from 3 to 6) as an
organic solvent and/or a 1,2-alkanediol, which is a
satisfactory ink composition excellent in color 
reproducibility and having a high penetrating property
and a short drying time.</p><p num="0069">In addition to the above components, the recording
liquid of the present invention may further contain a
mildew-proofing agent, a fertilizer, a pH adjusting agent,
urea or the like, if necessary. Particularly, examples
of a pH adjusting agent, a solubility accelerating agent
and an antioxidant include an alkanolamine such as
diethanolamine, triethanolamine or the like.</p><p num="0070">A method for preparing the recording liquid of the
present invention is not specially limited, but may be a
well known method, and its examples include a method
(master batch method) which comprises obtaining a high
concentration dispersion by dispersing the above pigment
in the presence of the above necessary water-soluble
resin and the above necessary additives in a medium, and
then further adding the above urethane type resin and the
above necessary additives and medium to the dispersion
thus obtained, thereby adjusting a concentration to
prepare a recording liquid, or a method which comprises
dispersing the above pigment in the presence of the above
respective resin components and the above necessary
additives in a medium to prepare a recording liquid. The
above master batch method is efficient in respect of
carrying out the dispersing treatment at a high
concentration and adjusting the dispersed particle sizes
to a desired size. </p><p num="0071">Examples of a dispersing machine used for the
dispersing treatment include a dispersing machine using
media and a dispersing machine without using media.
Examples of the dispersing machine using media include a
ball mill, a sand mill, a dynomill, a DCP mill and the
like. Examples of the dispersing machine without using
media include a roll mill, an ultrasonic dispersing
machine and the like, and in addition to these dispersing
machines, other well known dispersing machines may be
used.</p><p num="0072">In the present invention, it is preferable to remove
coarse particles by a filtering device or a centrifugal
separator after pulverizing and dispersing treatments by
the above dispersing machines.</p><p num="0073">A pigment is used in an amount of preferably from
0.1 to 10 wt%, more preferably from 0.2 to 5 wt%, most
preferably from 1 to 4 wt%, to the total weight of the
recording liquid. If the amount of the pigment is less
than 0.1 wt%, coloring becomes poor, and if che amount of
the pigment exceeds 10 wt%, a viscosity becomes too high
and a gloss becomes poor. A water-soluble resin
(typically the above water-soluble anionic high molecular
material other than a specific urethane type resin which
is the essential component of the present invention) is
used in an amount of preferably from 5 to 100 parts by
weight (in terms of solid content), more preferably from
10 to 50 parts by weight, to 100 parts by weight of a 
pigment.</p><p num="0074">A urethane type resin is used in an amount of
preferably from 60 to 200 parts by weight (in terms of
solid content), more preferably from 70 to 150 parts by
weight, to 100 parts by weight of a pigment.</p><p num="0075">The total amount of these resins is from 60 to 200
parts by weight (in terms of solid content), preferably
from 70 to 150 parts by weight, to 100 parts by weight of
a pigment. If the resin amount is too small, stability
of the recording liquid becomes poor, and the resin
amount is too large, a viscosity becomes high, thereby
degrading an ejecting property and deteriorating a gloss
of a printed material. Thus, the above-mentioned range
is an appropriate range. Also, a water-soluble organic
solvent in the above recording liquid is used in an
amount of from 5 to 30 wt%, but in view of storage
stability, this amount is preferably from 5 to 20 wt%,
more preferably from 8 to 20 wt%.</p><p num="0076">One kind of these pigments, resins, additives and
organic solvents may be used respectively alone, but two
or more kinds of these respective components may be used
in combination to further improve physical properties.</p><p num="0077">Also, in view of dispersion stability, ejecting
stability and printed material quality, it is preferable
to adjust an average dispersion particle size of a
pigment in the recording liquid in a range of from 40 to
100 nm, more preferably from 50 to 85 nm. Further, in 
view of dispersion stability and ejecting stability, it
is preferable to adjust the maximum dispersion particle
size of a pigment to at most 5 µm, more preferably at
most 1 µm.</p><p num="0078">Measurement of an average dispersion particle size
and a particle size distribution of a pigment in the
recording liquid of the present invention is made by a
particle size analyzer by light scattering method
("Microtrac UPA150" manufactured by Nikkiso Co., Ltd.),
and D50 (D50 indicates a particle size wherein 50% of
particles have at most this particle size) in the
particle size distribution is an average dispersion
particle size value of the recording liquid. A minimum
dispersion particle size is a value of minimum particle
size among particle sizes wherein a dispersion particle
having a particle size larger than this particle size is
not present.</p><p num="0079">The recording liquid of the present invention is
used not only for ink jet recording and writing tools but
also for other uses. However, the recording liquid of
the present invention is particularly suitable for ink
jet recording, i.e. a method for forming a printed
material (printing) on a material to be recorded by
ejecting from an ink jet nozzle.</p><p num="0080">A material to be recorded is classified into a plain
paper having a mono-layer structure comprising cellulose,
a loading material, a sizing agent and the like and a 
special printing paper having a multi-layer structure
comprising an ink-receiving layer provided on at least
one side of a substrate, but the recording liquid of the
present invention is usable for all of materials to be
recorded, which include a plain paper, a recycle paper,
an ink jet printing paper (coat paper, glossy paper or
the like), an ink jet printing film (coat film, glossy
film or the like), an OHP film and the like. Among them,
the recording liquid of the present invention can be
satisfactorily used for a recording material developed
for obtaining a photographic image quality, such as a
recording material having an ink-receiving layer
comprising a porous layer of at most nanometer scale
provided on at least one side of a printing medium or
having an ink-receiving layer formed by coating a
swelling type polymer on at least one side of a printing
medium (photographic image quality paper), thereby
enabling printing having a satisfactory gloss and a high
optical density (OD) value.</p><p num="0081">When printing by ink jet system on such a
photographic image quality paper, it is preferable that a
photographic tone-printed material provides a
photographic tone gloss feeling by visual evaluation,
which has a 20° gloss of preferably at least 60, more
preferably at least 65, most preferably at least 70. A
printed material providing such a gloss preferably has an
arithmetic average roughness Ra of at most 0.04 µm, 
particularly at most 0.03 µm. Also, in order to obtain a
clear image having a high contrast, it is preferable that
a printed material has a printed density (OD) of at least
2, more preferably at least 2.2, most preferably at least
2.3. Also, in order to achieve such a high OD, a
printing film thickness is preferably at least 20 nm,
more preferably at least 100 nm. most preferably at least
150 nm, particularly at least 200 nm. On the other hand,
if the printing film thickness is too thick, it has been
discovered that the gloss of the printed surface tends to
be lowered. Thus, it is preferable that the printing
film thickness is at most 300 nm, more preferably at most
250 nm. Particularly, it is desirable that a printed
material having an ink deposited in an amount of at least
14.5 mg per square inch by solid-printing satisfies these
conditions.</p><p num="0082">Also, when the recording liquid providing such a
photographic tone-printed material is solid-printed in an
ink amount of at least 14.5 mg per square inch on a
photographic image quality printing paper, it is
preferable that the printed material has a printing film
thickness of at least 20 nm, an OD value of at least 2.0
and a 20° gloss of at least 60.</p><p num="0083">Further, it is preferable that a recording liquid
provides a printing film thickness of at least 100 nm,
more preferably at least 150 nm, most preferably at least
200 nm, on the printed material. Also, it is preferable 
that the printing film thickness is at most 300 nm, more
preferably at most 250 nm, and that the printing film
thickness is from 100 to 300 nm, more preferably from 150
to 200 nm. Further, it is preferable that the recording
liquid provides a printed material having an OD value of
at least 2.2, more preferably at least 2.3. Still
further, it is preferable that the recording liquid
provides a printed material having a 20° gloss of at
least 65, more preferably at least 70. Also, it is
preferable that the recording liquid provides a printed
surface having an arithmetic average roughness Ra of at
most 0.04 µm, more preferably at most 0.03 µm.</p><p num="0084">In the present invention, the photographic image
quality printing paper means a PM photographic paper
manufactured by Seiko Epson Corporation, and particularly
a material to be printed, which has a 20° gloss of at
least 15 as a blank paper.</p><p num="0085">Also, the solid-printing for depositing 14.5 mg per
square inch of ink is carried out by loading an ink into
a printer MJ8000C manufactured by Seiko Epson Corporation
and electing "Super Fine Mode" (with regard to "basic
configuration" in the printer properties, "recommendation
configuration" is elected as "mode configuration" and
"superfine printing paper" is elected as "kinds of paper
to be used").</p><p num="0086">Hereinafter, the present invention is further
illustrated in more details with reference to Examples. 
The terms "part" and "%" are based on weight unless
otherwise specified. Also, physical properties of carbon
blacks used herein are illustrated in the following Table
1, and evaluation of obtained dispersions and printed
materials and measurement methods of physical properties
were carried out as illustrated in the following
paragraphs (1) to (9).
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">Nitrogen-adsorbing specific surface area (m<sup>2</sup>/g)</entry><entry align="left">DBP absorption amount (ml/100 g)</entry><entry align="left">pH</entry></row><row><entry align="left">carbon Black (A) manufactured by Mitsubishi Chemical Corporation</entry><entry align="center">395</entry><entry align="center">77</entry><entry align="center">7.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">"MCF88" manufactured by Mitsubishi Chemical Corporation</entry><entry align="center">170</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">"#45" manufactured by Mitsubishi Chemical Corporation</entry><entry align="center">115</entry><entry align="center">53</entry><entry align="center">8</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>(1) Measurement of dispersion particle size distribution</heading><p num="0087">A dispersion or a recording liquid was diluted with
ion-exchanged water, and its dispersion particle size
distribution was measured by a particle size distribution
meter ("Microtrac UPA150" manufactured by Nikkiso Co.,
Ltd.). A value of D50 (D50 indicates a value wherein 50%
of particles have a size of at most this particle size)
in the particle size distribution is an average
distribution particle size. </p><heading>(2) Measurement of viscosity</heading><p num="0088">A viscosity of a recording liquid was measured by an
E type viscometer at 25°C.</p><heading>(3) Storage stability test</heading><p num="0089">A recording liquid was placed in a glass-made
sampling bottle, and was maintained at 70°C for 1 week in
a sealed state to measure a dispersion particle size
distribution. The storage stability was measured by a
difference in D50 values before and after maintaining at
70°C for 1 week.
<sl><li>○: An absolute value of a difference in D50 values
before and after maintaining at 70°C for 1 week is at
most 2 nm.</li><li>Δ: An absolute value of a difference in D50 values
before and after maintaining at 70°C for 1 week is larger
than 2 nm but at most 6 nm.</li><li>× : An absolute value of a difference in D50 values
before and after maintaining at 70°C for 1 week is larger
than 6 nm.</li></sl></p><heading>(4) Printing test</heading><p num="0090">A recording liquid was loaded into a cartridge of an
ink jet printer MJ8000C manufactured by Seiko Epson
Corporation, and solid-printing was carried out on an ink
jet printer photographic image quality glossy printing
paper (PM photographic printing paper) by "superfine
mode" to evaluate the printed materials on the basis of
the following three standards. <sl><li>○: A satisfactory printed material having no print-missing
and no light brush-stroke is obtained.</li><li>Δ: There is substantially no problem although there
is a slight print-missing.</li><li>× : Print-missing is remarkable.</li></sl></p><heading>(5) Measurement of printing density</heading><p num="0091">A density (OD) of the printed materials obtained by
the above printing test was measured by a Macbeth
densitometer (RD914). A larger numerical value indicates
a more satisfactory printing density, and a density of at
least 2 is defined as a pass standard.</p><heading>(6) Measurement of gloss</heading><p num="0092">The printed materials obtained by the above printing
test were measured in respect of a 20° gloss by a gloss
meter ("Microtrigloss" manufactured by BYK-Gardner). A
larger value indicates a more satisfactory gloss, and a
gloss value of at least 60 is judged as a pass standard.</p><heading>(7) Measurement of printing film thickness and
measurement of printing surface roughness (Ra)</heading><p num="0093">A liquid droplet was measured at an observation
magnification of 2,000 times by using "Ultradepth
configuration-measuring microscope VK-8500" manufactured
by Keyence Corporation to measure a film thickness and a
surface roughness.</p><heading>(8) Visual photographic tone evaluation</heading><p num="0094">The printed materials obtained by the above printing
test were visually evaluated in respect of photographic 
tone on the basis of the following four standards.
<sl><li>○: Glossy and black</li><li>Δ : Glossy but not black</li><li>× : Black but not glossy</li><li>×× : Not black and not glossy</li></sl></p><heading>(9) Water resistance test</heading><p num="0095">The printed materials obtained in the above printing
test were bathed in ion-exchanged water at 25°C for one
minute, and then presence or absence of blur was observed.
<sl><li>○: There is observed no blur.</li><li>× : There is observed blur.</li></sl></p><heading>(Preparation of urethane type resin)</heading><heading>(1) Preparation of urethane type resins (A) to (C)</heading><heading>1 ○Preparation of urethane prepolymer</heading><p num="0096">Urethane type resins (A) to (C) were prepared by the
following method. Respective components as shown in the
following Table 2 were reacted in an acetone solvent
under N<sub>2</sub> stream to obtain a urethane prepolymer.</p><heading>2 ○ Preparation of aqueous type polyurethane emulsion</heading><p num="0097">The above obtained urethane prepolymer was dropwise
added to deionized water containing 12 parts of
triethylamine to be dispersed therein, and acetone was
removed under reduced pressure to obtain a polyurethane
emulsion. The polyurethane emulsion thus obtained had a
solid content, a weight average molecular weight (Mw) and
an acid value as shown in the following Table 2.</p><p num="0098">The weight average molecular weight was a value 
measured by GPC in terms of polystyrene calculation, and
the acid value was measured in accordance with DIN53402.</p><heading>(2) Preparation of urethane type resin (D)</heading><p num="0099">Urethane resin (D) was prepared in accordance with
the following method. A urethane prepolymer was obtained
by reacting such a monomer composition comprising a
polyester polyol of neopentyl glycol, 1,6-hexanediol and
adipic acid, dimethylolbutanoic acid, IPDI and TMXDI as
shown in the following Table 2 in the same manner as in
the above "1 ○ Preparation of urethane prepolymer" in "(1)
Preparation of urethane type resins (A) to (C)". The
urethane prepolymer thus obtained was dispersed in
deionized water containing 8 parts of triethylamine, and
2.4 parts of 2-[(2-aminoethyl)amino]ethanol was dropwise
added to be dispersed, and acetone was removed under
reduced pressure to obtain a polyurethane emulsion. The
polyurethane emulsion thus obtained had a solid content,
a weight average molecular weight (Mw) and an acid value
as shown in the following Table 2. <img id="img-00400001" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00400001.tif" inline="no" he="227"/></p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0100">Respective components as shown in the following
Table 3 were dispersed by a beads mill dispersing machine
using 0.8 mm of zirconia beads to obtain an average
dispersion particle size of 61.9 nm by monitoring its
particle size distribution, and the dispersion thus
obtained was subjected to a centrifugal separator and was
filtrated by a 5 µm filter to remove coarse particles,
thus obtaining a carbon black dispersion.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Components</entry><entry align="left">Blending ratio (parts)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Styrene-acrylic acid type copolymer (25 wt% aqueous solution of potassium salt of "Johncryl 683" (acid value 160 mgKOH/g, Mw=8000) manufactured by Johnson Polymer Co., Ltd.)</entry><entry align="center">10.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ion-exchanged water</entry><entry align="center">71.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glycerin</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">"Proxel GXL S"</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">"MCF88" manufactured by Mitsubishi Chemical Corporation</entry><entry align="center">13</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry>("Proxel GXL S" is an antiseptic agent manufactured by Abyssia Co., Ltd.)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0101">To the carbon black dispersion thus obtained, was
added 26 parts of the 30 wt% ether type urethane type
resin (A) obtained in the above "Preparation of urethane
type resin", and 32.5 parts of triethylene glycol
monobutyl ether, 32.5 parts of glycerin, 3.25 parts of
"Surfinol 465" (tradename, manufactured by Air Products
and Chemicals, Inc . ) and 130.75 parts of ion-exchanged 
water were added thereto to obtain a recording liquid.
The recording liquid thus obtained had an average
dispersion particle size of 67 nm and a viscosity of 4.05
mPa·s. The recording liquid was evaluated in accordance
with the above evaluation methods (1) to (9). The
evaluation results are shown in the following Table 6.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 2</heading><p num="0102">Respective components as shown in the following
Table 4 were dispersed by a beads mill dispersing machine
using 0.8 mm zirconia beads to obtain an average
dispersion particle size of 59.8 nm by monitoring its
particle size distribution, and the dispersion thus
obtained was subjected to a centrifugal separator and was
filtrated by a 5 µm filter to remove coarse particles,
thus obtaining a carbon black dispersion.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Components</entry><entry align="left">Blending ratio (parts)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Styrene-acrylic acid type copolymer (25 wt% aqueous solution of potassium salt of "Johncryl 679" (acid value 215 mgKOH/g, Mw=8500) manufactured by Johnson Polymer Co., Ltd.)</entry><entry align="center">10.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ion-exchanged water</entry><entry align="center">71.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glycerin</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">"Proxel GXL S"</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">"Carbon Black (A)" manufactured by Mitsubishi Chemical Corporation</entry><entry align="center">13</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0103">To the carbon black dispersion thus obtained, was
added 34.67 parts of the 30 wt% ether type urethane type 
resin (A) obtained in the above "Preparation of urethane
type resin", and 32.5 parts of triethylene glycol
monobutyl ether, 32.5 parts of glycerin, 3.25 parts of
"Surfinol 465" and 122.08 parts of ion-exchanged water
were added thereto to obtain a recording liquid. The
recording liquid thus obtained had an average particle
size of 60 nm and a viscosity of 4.63 mPa·s. The
recording liquid was evaluated in accordance with the
above evaluation methods (1) to (9). The evaluation
results are shown in the following Table 6.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 3</heading><p num="0104">A carbon black dispersion was obtained by the same
operation as in Example 2.</p><p num="0105">Separately, respective components as shown in the
following Table 5 were dispersed by a beads mill
dispersing machine using 0.8 mm zirconia beads to obtain
an average dispersion particle size of 81 nm by
monitoring its particle size distribution, and the
dispersion thus obtained was subjected to a centrifugal
separator and was filtrated by a 5 µm filter to remove
coarse particles, thus obtaining a cyan pigment
dispersion. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Components</entry><entry align="left">Blending ratio (parts)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Styrene-acrylic acid type copolymer (25 wt% aqueous solution of ammonium salt of "Johncryl 679" (acid value 215 mgKOH/g, Mw=8500) manufactured by Johnson Polymer Co., Ltd.)</entry><entry align="center">1.29 1.29</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ion-exchanged water</entry><entry align="center">8.84</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glycerin</entry><entry align="center">0.62</entry></row><row><entry align="left">"Proxel GXL S"</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cyan pigment Pig 15:3</entry><entry align="center">1.61</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="center">12.37</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0106">The above obtained carbon black dispersion and cyan
pigment dispersion were mixed, and 34.7 parts of the 30
wt% ether type urethane type resin (B) obtained in the
above "Preparation of urethane type resin" was added to
the above obtained mixture, and 36-52 parts of
triethylene glycol monobutyl ether, 36.52 parts of
glycerin, 3.65 parts of "Surfinol 465" and 141.49 parts
of ion-exchanged water were added thereto to obtain a
recording liquid. The recording liquid thus obtained had
an average dispersion particle size of 78 nm and a
viscosity of 4.30 mPa·s. The recording liquid was
evaluated in accordance with the above evaluation methods
(1) to (9). The evaluation results are shown in the
following Table 6.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 4</heading><p num="0107">A carbon black dispersion was obtained by the same
operation as in Example 2, except that "#45" manufactured
by Mitsubishi Chemical Corporation was used as a carbon
black in place of "Carbon Black (A)". </p><p num="0108">To the carbon black dispersion thus obtained, was
added 43.35 parts of the 30 wt% ester type urethane type
resin (C) obtained in the above "Preparation of
polyurethane type resin", and 36.52 parts of triethylene
glycol monobutyl ether, 36.52 parts of glycerin, 3.65
parts of "Surfinol 465" and 132.8 parts of ion-exchanged
water were added thereto to obtain a recording liquid.
The recording liquid thus obtained had an average
dispersion particle size of 80 nm and a viscosity of 4.25
mPa·s. The recording liquid was evaluated in accordance
with the above evaluation methods (1) to (9). The
evaluation results are shown in the following Table 6.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 5</heading><p num="0109">A carbon black dispersion was obtained by the same
operation as in Example 2, except that "MCFSS"
manufactured by Mitsubishi Chemical Corporation was used
as a carbon black in place of "carbon Black (A)".</p><p num="0110">The carbon black dispersion thus obtained was mixed
with the cyan pigment dispersion obtained in Example 3,
and to the resultant mixture, was added 43.35 parts of
the 30 wt% ester type urethane type resin (C) obtained in
the above "Preparation of urethane type resin", and 36.52
parts of triethylene glycol monobutyl ether, 36.52 parts
of glycerin, 3.65 parts of "Surfinol 465" and 132.8 parts
of ion-exchanged water were then added thereto to obtain
a recording liquid. The recording liquid thus obtained
had an average dispersion particle size of 72 nm and a 
viscosity of 4.10 mPa·s. The recording liquid was
evaluated in accordance with the above evaluation methods
(1) to (9). The evaluation results are shown in the
following Table 6.</p><heading>COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0111">To a carbon black dispersion obtained by the same
operation as in Example 5, was added 26 parts of the 30
wt% ester type urethane type resin (D) obtained in the
above "Preparation of urethane type resin", and 32.5
parts of triethylene glycol monobutyl ether, 32.5 parts
of glycerin, 3.25 parts of "Surfinol 465" and 130.75
parts of ion-exchanged water were then added thereto to
obtain a recording liquid. The recording liquid thus
obtained had an average dispersion particle size of 60 nm
and a viscosity of 3.08 mPa·s. The recording liquid was
evaluated in accordance with the above evaluation methods
(1) to (9). The evaluation results are shown in the
following Table 6.</p><heading>COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 2</heading><p num="0112">A carbon black dispersion obtained by the same
operation as in Example 5 was mixed with the cyan pigment
dispersion obtained in Example 3, and to the resultant
mixture, was added 17.28 parts of the 30 wt% urethane
type resin (C) obtained in the above "Preparation of
urethane type resin", and 36.52 parts of triethylene
glycol monobutyl ether, 36.52 parts of glycerin, 3.65
parts of "Surfinol 465" and 158.91 parts of ion-exchanged 
water were then added thereto to obtain a recording
liquid. The recording liquid thus obtained had an
average dispersion particle size of 81 nm and a viscosity
of 5.18 mPa·s. The recording liquid was evaluated in
accordance with the above evaluation methods (1) to (9).
The evaluation results are shown in the following Table 6.</p><heading>COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 3</heading><p num="0113">Pure ink HP51645A was loaded into an ink jet printer
DJ970Cxi manufactured by Hewlett-Packard Development
Company to carry out solid-printing by normal mode on an
ink jet printer printing paper (PM photographic printing
paper), and the solid-printing was evaluated in
accordance with the above method. The evaluation results
are shown in the following Table 6.</p><heading>COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 4</heading><p num="0114">Pure ink BCI-3eBK was loaded into an ink jet printer
BJ610F manufactured by CANON Inc., to carry out solid-printing
by normal mode on an ink jet printer printing
paper (PM photographic printing paper), and the solid-printing
was evaluated in accordance with the above
method. The evaluation results are shown in the
following Table 6.</p><heading>COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 5</heading><p num="0115">To a carbon black dispersion obtained in Example 2,
was added 8.67 parts of the 30 wt% ester type urethane
type resin (C) obtained in the above "Preparation of
urethane type resin", and 32.5 parts of triethylene 
glycol monobutyl ether, 32.5 parts of glycerin, 3.25
parts of "Surfinol 465" and 148.08 parts of ion-exchanged
water were added thereto to obtain a recording liquid.
The recording liquid thus obtained had an average
dispersion particle size of 47 nm and a viscosity of 3.40
mPa·s. The recording liquid was evaluated in accordance
with the above evaluation methods (1) to (9). The
evaluation results are shown in the following Table 6.</p><heading>COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 6</heading><p num="0116">To a carbon black dispersion was obtained by the
same operation as in Example 5.</p><p num="0117">The carbon black dispersion thus obtained was mixed
with the cyan pigment dispersion obtained in Example 3,
and 8.66 parts of the 30 wt% ester type urethane type
resin (C) obtained in the above "Preparation of urethane
type resin" was added to the above obtained mixture, and
36.52 parts of triethylene glycol monobutyl ether, 36.52
parts of glycerin, 3.65 parts of "Surfinol 465" and
167.49 parts of ion-exchanged water were then added
thereto to obtain a recording liquid. The recording
liquid thus obtained had an average dispersion particle
size of 66 nm and a viscosity of 4.19 mPa·s. The
recording liquid was evaluated in accordance with the
above evaluation methods (1) to (9). The evaluation
results are shown in the following Table 6.</p><p num="0118">Examples 1 to 5 and Comparative Examples 1 to 6 are
summarized in the following Table 6. <img id="img-00490001" orientation="unknown" wi="150" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00490001.tif" inline="no" he="217"/><img id="img-00500001" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00500001.tif" inline="no" he="221"/></p><p num="0119">As described above, an aqueous recording liquid
having a pigment dispersed in accordance with the present
invention does not clog an ink jet nozzle, and is
satisfactory in respect of storage stability of the
recording liquid, water resistance, weather resistance
and light resistance of a printed material, and can
provide both satisfactory blackness and gloss feeling of
a printed material particularly on a photographic image
quality printing paper.</p><p num="0120">The entire disclosure of Japanese Patent Application
No. 2003-057690 filed on March 4, 2003 including
specification, claims and summary is incorporated herein
by reference in its entirety.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
containing at least a pigment and a resin, which
comprises from 60 to 200 parts by weight of the resin to
100 parts by weight of the pigment, wherein at least one
of the resin is a water-dispersible urethane type resin,
a weight fraction of a polyurethane urea part of which is
at most 2.0 wt% to the urethane resin, and the pigment
dispersed in the recording liquid has a dispersion
particle size D50 of from 40 to 100 nm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to Claim 1, wherein the pigment includes at
least a carbon black having a DBP absorption amount of
from 30 ml/100 g to 100 ml/100 g.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to Claim 1 or 2, wherein the urethane type
resin has a weight average molecular weight of higher
than 5,000 but not higher than 100,000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to any one of Claims 1 to 3, wherein an acid
value as a free acid of the urethane type resin is from
20 mgKOH/g to 100 mgKOH/g.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to any one of Claims 1 to 4, wherein the resin
includes a resin having an acid value of at least 50
mgKOH/g as a free acid in addition to the water-dispersible
urethane type resin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to any one of Claims 1 to 5, wherein a solid-printed
part having 14.5 mg per square inch of a pigment-dispersed
aqueous recording liquid printed by ink jet
recording system on a photographic image quality paper
provides a printed thickness of at least 20 nm, an
optical density of at least 2 and a 20° gloss value of at
least 60.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to any one of Claims 1 to 6, wherein the
pigment includes a carbon black and a pigment other than
the carbon black.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to Claim 7, wherein the pigment other than the
carbon black is a cyan pigment.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A printed material printed with a pigment-dispersed
aqueous recording liquid as defined in any one of Claims
1 to 8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The printed material according to Claim 9, wherein
the printing is carried out by ejecting a pigment-dispersed
aqueous recording liquid by an ink jet nozzle
on a material to be recorded.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The printed material according to Claim 9 or 10,
which has a printed thickness of at least 20 nm, an
optical density of at least 2 and a 20° gloss value of at
least 60.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The printed material according to any one of Claims
9 to 11, which has an arithmetic average roughness of at
most 0.04.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The printed material according to any one of Claims
9 to 12, wherein the pigment-dispersed aqueous recording
liquid contains at least a carbon black and the printed
material is a black printed material.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid wherein
a solid-printed part having 14.5 mg of ink per square
inch printed by ink jet recording system on a
photographic image quality paper provides a printed
thickness of at least 20 nm, an optical density of at
least 2 and a 20° gloss value of at least 60.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The pigment-dispersed aqueous recording liquid
according to Claim 14, which contains at least a carbon
black.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A printed material printed by ejecting a pigment-dispersed
aqueous recording liquid through an ink jet
nozzle on a material to be recorded, which provides a
printed thickness of at least 20 nm, an optical density
of at least 2 and a 20° gloss value of at least 60.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The printed material according to Claim 16, wherein
at least 14.5 mg per square inch of ink is deposited on a
photographic image quality paper by solid-printing.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>