<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1038846-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1038846" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="23043621" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000927"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1038846-A1" status="new" fvid="22960877"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1038846</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000927</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00301984-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00301984</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000310</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-27337099-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>27337099</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990322</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03C  13/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03C  13/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C03C  13/06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M03C213:02</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Mineralwollezusammensetzung mit verbesserter Hitzebeständigkeit und Löslichkeit in physiologischen Flüssigkeiten</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Mineral wool composition with enhanced biosolubility and thermostability</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition de laine minerale présentant une biosolubilité et une thermostabilité ameliorées</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-29808918-U1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>29808918</doc-number><kind>U1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="FR-2223328-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>FR</country><doc-number>2223328</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-10273332-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>10273332</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4461840-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4461840</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1983001947-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1983001947</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999008969-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999008969</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ARMSTRONG WORLD IND INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ARMSTRONG WORLD INDUSTRIES, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Armstrong World Industries, Inc.</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 3001 Liberty and Charlotte Streets</street><city>Lancaster Pennsylvania 17604</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BRUN PIERRE</name><address><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OLESKE PETER J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BRUN, PIERRE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OLESKE, PETER J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BRUN, PIERRE</last-name><address><street>7 rue des Roches</street><city>25270 Chapelle d'Huin</city><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OLESKE, PETER J.</last-name><address><street>1350 Hyde Park Drive</street><city>Lancaster, Pennsylvania 17601</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Eastwood, Simon Christopher</last-name><address><street>Stevens Hewlett &amp;amp; Perkins 1 St Augustine's Place</street><city>Bristol BS1 4UD</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A mineral fiber composition having enhanced biosolubility characteristics,
comprising by percentage weight:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="6"><dt>Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></dt><dd>16 to 25</dd><dt>CaO</dt><dd>&gt;29</dd><dt>SiO<sub>2</sub></dt><dd>30 to 40</dd><dt>MgO</dt><dd>&lt;15</dd><dt>Iron</dt><dd>&lt;5, selected from the group
consisting of Fe, FeO
and Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></dd><dt>K<sub>2</sub>O</dt><dd>&lt;4</dd><dt>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></dt><dd>&lt;0.8</dd></dl>
The Kdis of the mineral fiber composition is in the range of greater than 1000 (ng/cm<sup>2</sup> * hr)
at pH 4.5.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">Technical Field and Background of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to a formulation of mineral fibers suitable as acoustical and
thermal insulation. One useful application of the mineral fiber formulation in accordance with
preferred embodiments of the invention is in the fabrication of acoustical ceiling boards. The
material is also suitable for use as loose fill insulation in, for example, attics and walls.</p><p num="0002">The mineral fibers must be stable enough to withstand the processing involved in
making the thermal and acoustical insulation products, and yet still exhibit acceptable levels of
solubility in biological systems.</p><p num="0003">The mineral fibers according to the embodiments of the invention disclosed in this
application are produced principally from slag. Slag is a non-metallic vitreous material consisting
primarily of silicates and alumino-silicates of lime, magnesia, and other bases. The four principal
oxides of typical slags are CaO (25-50% by weight), Si0<sub>2</sub> (25-50% by weight), MgO (2-25% by
weight) and Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub> (5-20% by weight). Unless otherwise specified, percentages used throughout this
specification are percent by weight. Slag is formed as a byproduct from metal extraction operations,
and may therefore be recovered from iron blast furnaces, open hearth steel furnaces, and copper, lead
and precious metal smelters. Slag is generally viewed as a waste stream with little utility and thus
as a commodity with a relatively low value. It can therefore provide a very cost-effective raw
material resource if economically processable into a commercially viable product.</p><p num="0004">Slag has proven useful in the production of certain man-made vitreous fibers,
sometimes called "mineral wool" or more specifically "slag wool." These terms are used
interchangeably in this application and refer to the matted, wool-like fibrous appearance of the 
product. Man-made mineral fibers are made by melting a suitable slag-based composition to form
a "melt" and then blowing or spinning the molten material with sufficient energy to cause it to be
mechanically transformed into fibers. The technology and knowledge base for such fiber production
is well established. Records indicate the production of slag wool as early as the 1840's in Wales, and
1873 in the United States.</p><p num="0005">In a standard mineral wool fiber, alumina and silica form the principal mechanical
strength and attachment elements. The other elements act as fluxes affecting the melt temperature
and viscosity profile of the formula. When the viscosity of the material is low and the melt flow rate
is too high the fibers will be thin and excessively large portions of the material will fail to form
fibers. Instead, some of the melt forms clumps or balls of vitreous material, sometimes referred to
as "shot." If the melt viscosity of the molten material is too high, then the resultant fibers will be
thick and brittle and in addition there will be too high a proportion of shot.</p><p num="0006">Both theoretical and empirical research have determined that certain materials have
an effect on the properties of mineral wool, and that varying the percentages of certain materials in
particular ways can effect the processing parameters and properties of the end product in either a
beneficial or detrimental manner.</p><p num="0007">For example, Calcium Oxide (CaO) decreases the viscosity of the melt, and increases
the slope of the temperature viscosity curve. An increase in the slope of the temperature viscosity
curve is detrimental to the properties of the end product. Generally, the slope of the temperature
viscosity curve should be relatively flat. If viscosity rises too quickly with temperature, then the
process control is difficult to achieve.</p><p num="0008">Aluminum Oxide (Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub>) increases the viscosity of the melt, and beneficially
decreases the slope of the temperature viscosity curve. Fiber ductility is also improved. </p><p num="0009">Magnesium Oxide (MgO) also increases the viscosity of the melt, and beneficially
decreases the slope of the temperature viscosity curve.</p><p num="0010">Iron (III) Oxide (Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) decreases melt viscosity.</p><p num="0011">Silicon Dioxide (SiO<sub>2</sub>) increases viscosity of the melt. It is added to balance the
formula and vary the solidification point of the fibers.</p><p num="0012">The approximate composition by weight of the four principal oxides that make up
most commercially available slag wool fibers are:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="23"><dt>Silicon Dioxide (SiO<sub>2</sub>)</dt><dd>38 - 45%</dd><dt>Calcium Oxide (CaO)</dt><dd>28 - 38%</dd><dt>Aluminum Oxide (Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub>)</dt><dd>9 - 14%</dd><dt>Magnesium Oxide (MgO)</dt><dd>2 - 12%</dd></dl></p><p num="0013">To achieve a suitable viscosity for good fiber formation SiO<sub>2,</sub> often in the form of
gravel or sandstone, is compounded with the slag. A measurement often used to evaluate a molten
mineral wool-forming composition is its "A/B Ratio." "A" is the sum of the SiO<sub>2</sub> percentage and the
Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub> percentage. "B" is the sum of the CaO percentage and the MgO percentage. Slag wool fibers
with an A/B ratio of 1.0 (<u style="single">i.e.</u>, equal percentages of A and B) have performed well in some
biosolubility tests, and not well in others. An A/B ratio of 1.0, however, is quite low, and the
viscosity of melts having such A/B ratios tends to be too low to achieve good fiber yields with car-type
spinning systems. Slag wool with A/B ratios in the range of 1.2 to 1.4 are more typical, and
these have not performed well in biosolubility tests.</p><p num="0014">Some other types of mineral fibers produced from raw materials other than slag have
been shown to be thermostable and suitable for producing acoustical ceiling board products, and 
have performed well in biosolubility tests. These fibers are typically formulated such that they either
have very low Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub> percentages (&lt;4% by weight) or very high Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub> percentages (&gt;18% by weight)
and low CaO percentage (&lt;29% by weight). These formulations cannot be readily achieved using
slag as a base material due to the inherent chemical composition of slag.</p><p num="0015">Biosolubility is generally considered a beneficial quality in products such as mineral
wool. Biosolubility does not refer to complete dissolution of the fibers within a biological system.
Rather, biosolubility refers to the ability of a biological organism to attack, weaken and ultimately
eject the fiber from the body. Any type of fiber of a certain size can become trapped in the lung as
a result of inhalation of air-entrained fibers. These fibers are detected as foreign to the organism and
attacked by lung fluid (which has a pH of about 7.4) and also by macrophages. Macrophages are an
important part of the body's defense mechanism. Macrophages are large phagocytic cells found in
the spleen, lymph nodes, liver and many other body tissues. They develop from monocytes and are
characterized by a horseshoe-shaped nucleus and nongranular cytoplasm. Macrophages have an
internal pH of about 4.5. If the macrophages are smaller than the fiber, several of the macrophages
collectively engulf a fiber. The macrophage and lung fluids chemically attack the fiber, weakening
it. The fiber can then be broken into pieces which are carried away by the macrophages. The
macrophages migrate to the trachea where they are trapped in mucous and ejected from the body by
being coughed-up in phlegm, or by being swallowed and eliminated through the digestive tract.
Biosolubility may be evaluated via animal tests such as those described in EU Directive 97/69/EC
or by in-vitro testing in simulated biological fluids, such as a 4.5 pH Gamble's solution. In general,
to pass the EU Directive 97/69/EC tests requires a solubility greater than 1000 Kdis (measured in
ng/cm<sup>2</sup> * hr). </p><p num="0016">The invention according to this application results from a novel appreciation and
application of the interrelationships between several of the constituent parts of slag, and how those
constituent parts can be manipulated to produce a mineral wool which has desirable and
commercially valuable properties while also having a relatively high degree of biosolubility.</p><heading><u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0017">Therefore, it is an object of the invention to provide a mineral wool composition
which has enhanced biosolubility.</p><p num="0018">It is another object of the invention to provide a mineral wool composition which has
enhanced thermostability.</p><p num="0019">It is another object of the invention to provide a mineral wool composition which has
properties which render it suitable for use in acoustical and thermal insulation products.</p><p num="0020">It is another object of the invention to provide a mineral wool composition which is
inexpensive to produce.</p><p num="0021">It is another object of the invention to provide a slag-based precursor for producing
a mineral wool composition which achieves the foregoing objects.</p><p num="0022">The practice of the invention involves the formulation of compounds which are based
on low cost slag and which are useful in the preparation of thermostable mineral fibers that also
display good biosolubility. Simultaneous thermostability and biosolubility are achieved by adding
alumina in specified amounts to the slag. The alumina acts to raise the viscosity of the molten
compound, allowing it to be readily processed into fibers with yields and properties similar to that
achieved with conventional slag-based compounds. The high alumina levels in combination with
levels of CaO of &gt;29% allows for the production of fibers which are highly soluble in biological 
fluids at a lower cost than can be produced using non-slag based systems. Although other systems
based on mined raw materials have shown good biosolubility, these compositions are more
expensive to produce due to the greater raw material cost and energy requirements.</p><p num="0023">These and other objects of the present invention are achieved in the preferred
embodiments disclosed below by providing a mineral fiber composition having enhanced
biosolubility, comprising by percentage weight:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="6"><dt>Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></dt><dd>16 to 25</dd><dt>CaO</dt><dd>&gt;29</dd><dt>SiO<sub>2</sub></dt><dd>30 to 40</dd><dt>MgO</dt><dd>&lt;15</dd><dt>Iron</dt><dd>&lt;5, selected from the group
consisting of Fe, FeO
and Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></dd><dt>K<sub>2</sub>O</dt><dd>&lt;4</dd><dt>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></dt><dd>&lt;0.8</dd></dl></p><p num="0024">Preferably, the biolsolubility of the mineral fiber composition has a Kdis greater than
1000 (ng/cm<sup>2</sup> * hr).</p><p num="0025">Determining the dissolution rate for these man made vitreous fibers was
accomplished by first putting the size-characterized fiber sample between two filter membranes of
a flow cell. A modified (pH adjusted to 4.5) Gamble's solution is contacted with the fibers. A mass
loss for the fibers is obtained by an analysis of the SiO<sub>2</sub> and Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> content of the eluate. The
dissolution velocity is calculated from the mass loss and the diameter distribution of the sample.
The units of measure are nano-grams per centimeter square per hour (ng/cm<sup>2</sup> * hr).</p><p num="0026">According to one preferred embodiment of the invention, the percentage by weight
of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is between 17 and 25. </p><p num="0027">According to another preferred embodiment of the invention, the percentage by
weight of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is between 19 and 22.</p><p num="0028">According to yet another preferred embodiment of the invention, the percentage by
weight of CaO is at least 30.</p><p num="0029">According to yet another preferred embodiment of the invention, the percentage by
weight of CaO is at least 31.</p><p num="0030">According to yet another preferred embodiment of the invention, the percentage by
weight of CaO + MgO is greater than the percentage by weight of SiO<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0031">According to yet another preferred embodiment of the invention, the weight of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
and SiO<sub>2</sub> is less than 60 percent of the total weight of the mineral wool composition.</p><p num="0032">According to yet another preferred embodiment of the invention, the weight of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
and SiO<sub>2</sub> is less than 55 percent of the total weight of the mineral wool composition.</p><p num="0033">According to yet another preferred embodiment of the invention, a slag-based
precursor is provided for the manufacture of a mineral wool composition having enhanced
biosolubility and thermostability. The slag-based precursor comprises slag, bauxite, silica-rich rock
and an energy source, wherein the mineral wool composition produced from the precursor comprises
by percentage weight the values according to the preferred embodiments of the resulting mineral
wool compositions described in this application. The energy source may be coke or electricity.</p><heading><u style="single">Description of the Preferred Embodiment and Best Mode</u></heading><p num="0034">Development of mineral wool products according to the invention resulted in part
from research observations which support the theory that high levels of combined basic oxides such
as CaO, MgO, Na<sub>2</sub>O and K<sub>2</sub>0 cause the fibers to display a rapid initial dissolution. If the slag
compound from which the mineral fibers are produced is too basic, the melt viscosity will likely be 
quite low, making it difficult to spin fibers of sufficient diameter and durability to be useful in the
manufacture of thermal and acoustical insulation products such as ceiling boards. SiO<sub>2</sub> is often used
as a viscosity modifier in slag wool processing. It raises the melt viscosity of the molten compound
and allows for a melt that is more readily spun into thicker fibers more suitable for use in producing
thermal and acoustical insulation products such as ceiling boards. Silica has also been shown to have
a negative effect on the biosolubility of fibers, and thus higher SiO<sub>2</sub> levels typically correlate to lower
biosolubility.</p><p num="0035">Increasing the Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub> concentration raises the melt viscosity of the molten slag-based
compositions. The SiO<sub>2</sub> level of such compounds may be reduced, while still maintaining a viscosity
that is suitable for good man made mineral fiber spinning. Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub> is amphoteric. At its typical
concentration (&lt;14%) in mineral wool fibers it acts as an acidic oxide. At higher concentrations it
displays the properties of a basic oxide.</p><p num="0036">Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> may also affect the fiber morphology in a similar manner to Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub> such that
the sum of these two oxides appears to be a significant contributing factor in the level of fiber
biosolubility. Higher levels of iron, however, tend to have a negative effect on the fiber formation
process by causing the viscosity of the melt to be lower, thus making spinning of fibers more
difficult. If the SiO<sub>2</sub> levels are to be kept low, then the total iron level must also be controlled,
typically at &lt;5% by weight.</p><p num="0037">Previous patents and other disclosures have shown the effect of both very high and
very low compositional concentrations of Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub> on fiber biosolubility. Suitable biosoluble
compositions that are also comprised of very high (&gt;29% by weight) CaO levels have not heretofore
been achieved. </p><p num="0038">Applicants have now achieved compositions disclosed herein with &gt;29% CaO in
combination with high levels of Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub>. The resultant fibers exhibit good biosolubility and thereby
allow for the use of slag as a raw material source.</p><p num="0039">It has been discovered that by adding Al<sub>2</sub>0<sub>3</sub> to slag-based compositions, specific fibers
with suitable properties can be created far more effectively than by other currently known means.
The most cost-effective means to this end to date utilizes slag, bauxite, and gavel as the constituent
ingredients for these compositions.</p><p num="0040">Two preferred embodiments of the invention are shown in Tables 1 and 2.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Bauxite</entry><entry align="center">Slag</entry><entry align="center">Gravel</entry><entry align="center">Fiber</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Recipe (Kg)</entry><entry align="center">130</entry><entry align="center">820</entry><entry align="right">50</entry></row><row><entry align="center">OXIDE (Wt. %)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">SiO<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">13</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="right">99</entry><entry align="center">34.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Fe</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">63</entry><entry align="center">14</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">20.4</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiO<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">CaO</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">36.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">MnO</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">MgO</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">3.4</entry></row><row><entry align="center">K<sub>2</sub>O</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Na<sub>2</sub>O</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">S</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">.4</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Bauxite</entry><entry align="center">Slag</entry><entry align="center">Gravel</entry><entry align="center">Fiber</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Recipe (Kg)</entry><entry align="center">170</entry><entry align="center">750</entry><entry align="right">80</entry></row><row><entry align="center">OXIDE (Wt. %)</entry> </row><row><entry align="center">SiO<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">13</entry><entry align="center">32</entry> <entry align="right">99</entry> <entry align="center">36.6</entry> </row><row><entry align="center">Fe</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">63</entry><entry align="center">14</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">20.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiO2</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">CaO</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">33.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">MnO</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">MgO</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">3.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">K<sub>2</sub>O</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Na<sub>2</sub>O</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">S</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">.4</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">&lt;0.2</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0041">The mineral wools produced in accordance with Tables 1 and 2 have a
relatively low silica content which reduces required energy input, and a relatively low iron
content which produces a light green/gray color suitable for the manufacture of white or
other light-colored acoustic ceiling tiles.</p><p num="0042">Somewhat less satisfactory embodiments of the mineral wool product are
shown in Tables 3 and 4. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Bauxite II</entry><entry align="center">Slag</entry><entry align="center">Gravel</entry><entry align="center">Fiber</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Recipe (Kg)</entry><entry align="center">200</entry><entry align="center">750</entry><entry align="right">50</entry></row><row><entry align="center">OXIDE (Wt. %)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">SiO<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="right">99</entry><entry align="center">33.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Fe</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">3.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">14</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">21</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiO<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">CaO</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">34.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">MnO</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.6</entry></row><row><entry align="center">MgO</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">3.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">K<sub>2</sub>O</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Na<sub>2</sub>O</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">S</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">.4</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="2">Weight Percentages</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Bauxite II</entry><entry align="center">Slag</entry><entry align="center">Gravel</entry><entry align="center">Fiber</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Recipe (Kg)</entry><entry align="center">180</entry><entry align="center">800</entry><entry align="center">20</entry></row><row><entry align="center">OXIDE (Wt. %)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">SiO<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">8.2</entry><entry align="center">36.3</entry><entry align="center">95.5</entry><entry align="center">34.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Fe</entry><entry align="center">19.9</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">3.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">55.7</entry><entry align="center">11.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">20.6</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiO<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center">CaO</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">29.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.03</entry></row><row><entry align="center">MnO</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">MgO</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">13</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">8.6</entry></row><row><entry align="center">K<sub>2</sub>O</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Na<sub>2</sub>O</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="center">S</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">.4</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0043">The mineral wools according to Tables 3 and 4 possess satisfactory
biosolubility and thermostability, but the relatively high percentage of iron causes the
products to have a deep chocolate brown color which creates difficulties in producing a light-colored 
product, such as a ceiling tile but is suitable for applications where a dark color is
preferred or where color is not a consideration.</p><p num="0044">The mineral wool products according to Tables 1, 2, 3 and 4 are produced by
charging a conventional cupula with slag, gravel, bauxite and coke. The material is heated
with a combination of oxygen and heated air to a temperature of between 1450 to 1480
degrees C. The material forms a molten mass in the bottom of the cupula and is drawn off
through a side opening. The molten material is gravity-fed onto a car-type spinning
apparatus. As the molten material flows out of the cupula, material higher in the cupula
moves downwardly forming additional molten material. The process is a continuous one.
Thus, as the level of the slag-based material in the cupula drops, additional slag, gravel,
bauxite and coke is added into the top of the cupula in the required percentages. The
material is preferably in relatively small fist-to-thumb-sized chunks. Smaller pieces pack too
closely together and retard movement of super-heated air and oxygen through the mass as
necessary for even heat distribution. Larger pieces have insufficient overall surface area
necessary for efficient heat transfer into the mass of the material. While it is desirable to
charge the cupula with a mixture of the materials, they can also be added in layers, since the
melting process tends to mix the materials.</p><p num="0045">In each case, approximately 140 to 170 Kg of coke is used per 1000 kg of
meltable stone, and is added along with the other materials as the cupula is recharged.</p><p num="0046">For cost control reasons the percentage of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> should be kept to &lt;23%.
Added Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> would be expected to only marginally improve solubility, but would also raise
raw material and energy requirement costs. The combined percentage of CaO + MgO should
be greater then SiO<sub>2</sub> and should fall between 37 and 45%. Lower percentages decrease 
biosolubility, and the higher percentages reduce melt viscosity and thereby create fiber-forming
difficulties. The combined Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and SiO<sub>2</sub> percentages should be less then 60% of
the total weight, preferably less then 55%.</p><p num="0047">The car-type spinning apparatus comprises a series of rapidly rotating rotors
which impart centrifugal mechanical energy to the molten material sufficient to cause it to
be formed into fibers as it is thrown off of the rotating surface of the rotors. This fiber-forming
process is conventional in the art. The rotational speed of the rotors ranges between
2900 rpm for the first rotor to 6400 for the last rotor in a four rotor system and affects the
diameter of the fibers thus produced. Optimum fiber diameter is in the range of 3 to 7
microns, with diameters in the general range of 7 microns being an upper limit for fibers
with satisfactory processing properties.</p><p num="0048">Biosolubility was determined utilizing test methodologies developed at the
Fraunhofer Institute, as shown below in Table 5.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center">OXIDE (wt. %)</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Sample #1</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Sample #2</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Sample #3</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Sample #4</entry><entry align="center">Sample of Table 2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">SiO<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">41.6</entry><entry align="center">39.6</entry><entry align="center">36.1</entry><entry align="center">38.8</entry><entry align="center">36.6</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Fe</entry><entry align="center">0.6</entry><entry align="center">0.6</entry><entry align="center">0.74</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">12.5</entry><entry align="center">10.1</entry><entry align="center">13.3</entry><entry align="center">22.1</entry><entry align="center">20.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiO<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">0.6</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">CaO</entry><entry align="center">36.5</entry><entry align="center">30.4</entry><entry align="center">39.4</entry><entry align="center">14.7</entry><entry align="center">33.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">MnO</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">0.75</entry><entry align="center">1.9</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">MgO</entry><entry align="center">4.8</entry><entry align="center">13.9</entry><entry align="center">3.9</entry><entry align="center">10.6</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">K<sub>2</sub>O</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="center">0.8</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">0.8</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Na<sub>2</sub>O</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">0.6</entry><entry align="center">0.9</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">S</entry><entry align="center">0.95</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">&lt;0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Kdis (pH 4.5) (ng/cm<sup>2</sup> * hr)</entry><entry align="center">375</entry><entry align="center">302</entry><entry align="center">667</entry><entry align="center">930</entry><entry align="center">1407</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0049">According to Table 5, the biosolubility of the Sample of Table 2 is
significantly improved over comparative samples. Note particularly the comparison with
Comparative Sample No. 4 (a rock wool) and its biosolubility of 930 Kdis. Comparative
Sample No. 4 was made in accordance with the disclosure of European Patent Specification
EP 0 790 962.</p><p num="0050">The correlation between Kdis and the animal tests of EU directive 97/69/BC
have been previously published.</p><p num="0051">Thermostability is demonstrated by fire-testing ceiling boards made from the
mineral wool according to the invention. Tests utilizing ASTM E 119 all indicated a sag of
10-20 mm--an acceptable range of values indicating adequate resistance to fire.</p><p num="0052">A mineral wool composition is described above. Various details of the
invention may be changed without departing from its scope. Furthermore, the foregoing
description of the preferred embodiment of the invention and the best mode for practicing
the invention are provided for the purpose of illustration only and not for the purpose of
limitation--the invention being defined by the claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A mineral fiber having enhanced thermostability and biosolubility
comprising by percentage weight:
Al2O316 to 25CaO&gt;29%SiO230 to 40MgO&lt;15Iron&lt;5, selected from the group consisting of Fe, FeO and Fe2O3K2O&lt;4P2O5&lt;0.8</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A mineral fiber according to claim 1, wherein the percentage weight of
Al2O3 is between 17 and 25.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A mineral fiber according to claim 1, wherein the percentage by weight of
Al2O3 is between 19 and 22.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A mineral fiber according to any preceding claim, wherein the percentage
by weight of CaO is at least 30.5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A mineral fiber according to any one of claims 1 to 3, wherein the
percentage by weight of CaO is at least 31.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A mineral fiber according to any preceding claim, wherein the percentage
by weight of CaO + MgO is greater than the percentage by weight of
SiO2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A mineral fiber according to any preceding claim, wherein the weight of
Al2O3 and SiO2 is less than 60 percent of the total weight of the mineral
wool composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A mineral fiber according to any one of claims 1 to 6, wherein the weight
of Al2O3 and SiO2 is less than 55 percent of the total weight of the mineral
wool composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A mineral fiber according to any preceding claim, wherein the biosolubility
of the mineral fiber composition is greater than 1000 ng/cm2 * hr at a pH
of 4.5.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="156" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="234" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="235" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>