<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1010715-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1010715" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22788154" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000621"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1010715-A1" status="new" fvid="22863480"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1010715</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000621</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99309314-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99309314</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991123</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-21173698-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>21173698</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981215</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   8/00        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   8/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   8/72        20060101AFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   8/72        20060101CFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   8/89        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61Q   1/00        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61Q   1/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61Q   1/12        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61Q   1/12        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61Q  15/00        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61Q  15/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61Q  17/04        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61Q  17/04        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  77/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  77/38        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  77/50        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/09        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/05        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/07        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  77/50</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08J   3/09+L83/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  83/04+B4S+C</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Siliconelastomer</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Silicone elastomer</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Elastomère silicone</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0869142-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0869142</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5066714-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5066714</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEN ELECTRIC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1 River Road</street><city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KILGOUR JOHN ALFRED</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KUO AN-LI</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KILGOUR, JOHN ALFRED</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KUO, AN-LI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KILGOUR, JOHN ALFRED</last-name><address><street>18 Royal Oak Drive</street><city>Clifton Park, New York 12065</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KUO, AN-LI</last-name><address><street>36 Turner Drive</street><city>Chappaqua, New York 10514</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Szary, Anne Catherine, Dr.</last-name><address><street>GE London Patent Operation, Essex House, 12-13 Essex Street</street><city>London WC2R 3AA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep"  status="new"  lang="EN"><p>The cross-linked hydrosilylation reaction product of an alkenyl functional
silicone compound, a silylhydride functional silicone compound; and one or
more α,β-unsaturated alkenes exhibits hydrolytic stability, compatibility with
organic solvents and is useful as a component in personal care compositions.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep"  status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to silicone polymers, more specifically to alkyl
substituted silicone elastomers.</p><p num="0002">Silicone compositions comprising a silicone fluid and a cross-linked silicone
elastomer are known, see for example, U.S. Patent No. 4,987,169,
coassigned U.S. Patent Nos. 5,760, 116; 4,987,169. Neither US '169 patent
nor the US '116 patent disclose dispersions of the silicone elastomer in fluids
other than silicone fluids.</p><p num="0003">WO 98/18849 discloses fatty alcohol or aliphatic glycol-grafted silicone gels
having enhanced oil compatibility. The grafted substituents are attached to
the silicone gel via Si-O-C bonds, which are readily susceptible to hydrolysis
in the presence of moisture.</p><p num="0004">What is needed in a hydrolytically stable silicone elastomer that is compatible
with media, such as hydrocarbons, other than silicone fluids.</p><p num="0005">In a first aspect, the present invention is directed to a cross-linked alkyl
substituted silicone elastomer, comprising the cross-linked hydrosilylation
reaction product of:
<sl><li>(i) an alkenyl functional silicone compound;</li><li>(ii) a silylhydride functional silicone compound; and</li><li>(iii) one or more α,β-ethylenically unsaturated alkenes.</li></sl></p><p num="0006">The silicone elastomer is hydrolytically stable, in that the alkyl substituents
are attached to the elastomer via Si-C bonds having good hydrolytic stability
and can be easily and economically prepared in a single step. As used
herein, the terminology "hydrolytically stable" means a tendency not to 
undergo changes in structure, such as, for example, cleavage of bonds, as a
result of exposure to moisture.</p><p num="0007">In a second aspect, the present invention is directed to a method for making a
cross-linked alkyl substituted silicone elastomer, comprising forming the
hydrosilylation reaction product of:
<sl><li>(i) an alkenyl functional silicone compound;</li><li>(ii) a silylhydride functional silicone compound; and</li><li>(iii) one or more α,β-ethylenically unsaturated alkenes.</li></sl></p><p num="0008">In a third aspect, the present invention is directed to a silicone composition,
comprising a liquid medium, said liquid medium comprising an organic liquid,
a silicone fluid or a mixture thereof; and a silicone elastomer of the present
invention dispersed in the liquid medium. The elastomer of the present
invention exhibits improved compatibility with organic liquids. As used herein,
the "compatibility" of an elastomer with a liquid refers to the ability to form a
stable dispersion of the elastomer in organic liquid.</p><p num="0009">In a fourth aspect, the present invention is directed to an emulsion comprising
an emulsion of a first liquid phase and a second liquid phase and a silicone
elastomer of the present invention dispersed in the emulsion.</p><p num="0010">In a fifth aspect, the present invention is directed to a personal care
composition comprising a silicone elastomer of the present invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Silicone Elastomer</u></heading><p num="0011">In preferred embodiment, the cross-linked alkyl substituted silicone elastomer
of the present invention comprises the cross-linked hydrosilylation reaction
product of, based on 100 parts by weight ("pbw") of the combined alkenyl
functional silicone compound, silylhydride functional silicone compound and 
α,β-ethylenically unsaturated alkenes, from 10 pbw to 99.9 pbw, more
preferably from 40 pbw to 99.5 pbw, even more preferably from 65 pbw to 95
pbw of the combined alkenyl functional silicone compound and silylhydride
functional silicone compound and from greater than 0.1 pbw to 90 pbw, more
preferably from 0.5 pbw to 60 pbw, even more preferably from 5 pbw to 35
pbw of the one or more α,β-ethylenically unsaturated alkenes.</p><p num="0012">In a preferred embodiment, the alkyl substituted silicone elastomer of the
present invention forms a cross-linked three dimensional network that does
not dissolve in, but is capable of being swollen by a suitable liquid medium,
such as for example, a low molecular weight silicone or an organic liquid.
The amount of crosslinking present in the cross-linked silicone elastomer
network may be characterized with respect to the degree of swelling exhibited
by the network in the liquid medium. In a preferred embodiment, the cross-linked
structure of the silicone elastomer is effective to allow the network to be
swollen by a low molecular weight silicone fluid, as defined more fully below,
from its original volume to a swollen volume that is a factor of from 1.01 to
5000, more preferably from 2 to 1000, and even more preferably from 5 to
500, times its original volume.</p><p num="0013">The cross-linked alkyl substituted silicone elastomer of the present invention
may be formed by each of several alternative methods.</p><p num="0014">In a first embodiment, the silylhydride functional silicone compound and one
or more α,β-ethylenically unsaturated alkenes are contacted under
hydrosilylation conditions to form an alkyl substituted silylhydride functional
silicone compound and the alkyl substituted silylhydride functional silicone
compound is subsequently contacted under hydrosilylation conditions with the
alkenyl functional silicone compound to form the a cross-linked alkyl
substituted silicone elastomer of the present invention. </p><p num="0015">In a second, and preferred, embodiment, the alkenyl functional silicone
compound, and silylhydride functional silicone compound and the one or
more α,β-ethylenically unsaturated alkenes are contacted under
hydrosilylation conditions to form the a cross-linked alkyl substituted silicone
elastomer of the present invention.</p><p num="0016">In a third embodiment, the alkenyl functional silicone compound, and
silylhydride functional silicone compound are contacted under hydrosilylation
conditions to form a silicone elastomer gel and the gel is subsequently
contacted under hydrosilylation conditions with the one or more α,β-ethylenically
unsaturated alkenes to form the a cross-linked alkyl substituted
silicone elastomer of the present invention.</p><p num="0017">In a preferred embodiment the alkenyl functional silicone compound
comprises one or more compounds of the formula (I):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">M<sub>a</sub>M<sup>vi</sup> <sub>b</sub>D<sub>c</sub>D<sup>vi</sup> <sub>d</sub>T<sub>e</sub>T<sup>vi</sup> <sub>f</sub>Q<sub>g</sub></st32:che>
wherein:
<sl><li>M is R<sup>1</sup>R<sup>2</sup>R<sup>3</sup>SiO<sub>1/2</sub>;</li><li>M<sup>vi</sup> is R<sup>4</sup>R<sup>5</sup>R<sup>6</sup>SiO<sub>1/2</sub>;</li><li>D is R<sup>7</sup>R<sup>8</sup>SiO<sub>2/2</sub>;</li><li>D<sup>vi</sup> is R<sup>9</sup>R<sup>10</sup>SiO<sub>2/2</sub>;</li><li>T is R<sup>11</sup>SiO<sub>3/2</sub>;</li><li>T<sup>vi</sup> is R<sup>12</sup>SiO<sub>3/2</sub>; and</li><li>Q is SiO<sub>4/2</sub>;</li><li>R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup>, R<sup>3</sup>,R<sup>7</sup>, R<sup>8</sup> and R<sup>11</sup> are each independently alkyl, preferably (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>60</sub>)alkyl,
aryl or aralkyl;</li><li>R<sup>4</sup>, R<sup>9</sup> and R<sup>12</sup> are each independently monovalent terminally unsaturated
hydrocarbon radicals; </li><li>R<sup>5</sup>, R<sup>6</sup> and R<sup>10</sup> are each independently monovalent terminally unsaturated
hydrocarbon radicals, alkyl, aryl or aralkyl, preferably (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>60</sub>)alkyl, aryl or
aralkyl, more preferably (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>60</sub>)alkyl;</li><li>a, b, c, d, e, f and g are each integers wherein:
<sl><li>a, b, e, f, and g are each greater than or equal to 0 and less than or equal to
50,</li><li>0 ≤ c ≤ 2000,</li><li>0 ≤ d ≤ 200, and provided that:</li><li>(a + b) ≤ (2 + 3e + 3f + 4g) and</li><li>1.5 ≤ (b + d + f) ≤ 200.</li></sl></li></sl></p><p num="0018">In a highly preferred embodiment, R<sup>4</sup> is a monovalent terminally unsaturated
(C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)hydrocarbon radical; R<sup>5</sup>, R<sup>6</sup>,R<sup>7</sup> and R<sup>8</sup> are each independently (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkyl;
R<sup>5</sup>, R<sup>6</sup>,R<sup>7</sup> and R<sup>8</sup> are each independently (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkyl; b is 2; 100 ≤ c
≤ 2000; and a, d, e, f and g are each 0.</p><p num="0019">In a preferred embodiment, the silylhydride functional silicone compound
comprises one or more compounds of the formula (II):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">M<sub>h</sub>M<sup>H</sup> <sub>i</sub>D<sub>j</sub>D<sup>H</sup> <sub>k</sub>T<sub>l</sub>T<sup>H</sup> <sub>m</sub>Q<sub>n</sub></st32:che><sl><li>M, D, T and Q are each defined as above</li><li>M<sup>H</sup> is R<sup>13</sup>R<sup>14</sup>R<sup>15</sup>SiO<sub>1/2</sub>;</li><li>D<sup>H</sup> is R<sup>16</sup>R<sup>17</sup>SiO<sub>2/2</sub>;</li><li>T<sup>H</sup> is R<sup>18</sup>SiO<sub>3/2</sub>;</li><li>R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup>, R<sup>3</sup>,R<sup>7</sup>, R<sup>8</sup> and R<sup>11</sup> are each independently alkyl, aryl or aralkyl;
R<sup>13</sup>, R<sup>16</sup> and R<sup>18</sup> are each independently H;</li><li>R<sup>14</sup>, R<sup>15</sup> and R<sup>17</sup> are each independently H, alkyl, aryl or aralkyl, 
preferably (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>60</sub>)alkyl, aryl or aralkyl, more preferably (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>60</sub>)alkyl;
and</li><li>h, i, j, k, I, m, and n are each integers wherein:
<sl><li>h, i, l, m and n are each greater than or equal to 0 and less than or equal
to 50,</li><li>0 ≤ j ≤ 2000,</li><li>0 ≤ k ≤ 200, and provided that:</li><li>(h + i) ≤ (2 + 3l + 3m + 4n) and</li><li>1.5 ≤ (i + k + m) ≤ 200.</li></sl></li></sl></p><p num="0020">In a highly preferred embodiment, R<sup>14</sup> and R<sup>15</sup> are each independently (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkyl,
and more preferably are each methyl; R<sup>13</sup> is H; 4 ≤ i ≤ 30; 1 ≤ n ≤ 15
and h, j, k, I and m are each 0. In an alternative highly preferred embodiment,
R<sup>14</sup>,R<sup>15</sup> and R<sup>17</sup> are each independently (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>)alkyl, R<sup>13</sup> and R<sup>16</sup> are each H;
h + i =2, 0 ≤ j ≤ 100, 2 ≤ k ≤ 100 and l, m and n are each 0.</p><p num="0021">Suitable monovalent terminally unsaturated hydrocarbon radicals include
monovalent linear or branched terminally unsaturated hydrocarbon groups. In
a preferred embodiment, the terminally unsaturated hydrocarbon radicals are
selected from linear or branched terminally unsaturated alkenyl groups
containing from 2 to 10 carbon atoms per group, such as, for example,
ethenyl, 2-propenyl, 1-methylethenyl, 2-methyl-2-propenyl, ethenylphenyl,
and 3-butenyl, 7-octenyl, more preferably, ethenyl, 2-propenyl.</p><p num="0022">Suitable monovalent alkyl groups include linear or branched alkyl groups. In
a preferred embodiment, monovalent alkyl groups are selected from linear or
branched alkyl groups containing from 1 to 60 carbons per group, such as, for
example, methyl, ethyl, propyl, iso-propyl, n-butyl, iso-butyl, sec-butyl, tert-butyl, 
pentyl, hexyl, heptyl, decyl, dodecyl, stearyl, cetyl, eicosyl, tridecyl,
hexadecyl.</p><p num="0023">As used herein, the term "aryl" means a monovalent unsaturated hydrocarbon
ring system containing one or more aromatic rings per group, which may
optionally be substituted on the one or more aromatic rings with one or more
alkyl groups, each preferably containing from 2 to 6 carbon atoms per alkyl
group and which, in the case of two or more rings, may be fused rings.
Suitable monovalent aromatic hydrocarbon radicals include, for example,
phenyl, tolyl, 2,4,6-trimethylphenyl, 2-isopropylmethylphenyl, 1-pentalenyl,
naphthyl, anthryl. Aralkyl includes, for example, phenylethyl, 2-(1-naphthyl)ethyl.</p><p num="0024">Suitable α,β-ethylenically unsaturated alkenes include linear or branched α,β-unsaturated
alkenes, which may , optionally, contain more than one
unsaturated site per molecule. In a preferred embodiment, the α,β-ethylenically
unsaturated alkenes are selected from the α,β-ethylenically
unsaturated alkenes containing from 2 to 60 carbon atoms per molecule, such
as, for example, ethene, propene, 2-methylpropene, 1-butene, 1,3-butadiene,
1-pentene, 2-methyl-1,3-butadiene, 1-dodecene, H<sub>2</sub>C=CH(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>13</sub>CH<sub>3,</sub>
H<sub>2</sub>C=CH(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>15</sub>CH<sub>3,</sub> H<sub>2</sub>C=CH(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>50</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>. In a preferred embodiment, the one
or more α,β-ethylenically unsaturated alkenes are selected from α,β-ethylenically
unsaturated(C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>24</sub>)alkenes.</p><p num="0025">In a preferred embodiment, the silicone elastomer of the present invention is
made by contacting one or more alkenyl functional compounds according to
formula (I) with one or more silylhydride functional silicone compounds
according to structural formula (II) and one or more α,β-ethylenically
unsaturated alkenes under hydrosilylation conditions.</p><p num="0026">As used herein, the terminology "(C<sub>n</sub>-C<sub>m</sub>)", wherein n and m are each integers,
in reference to an organic compound or substituent group means that the 
compound or group contains from n to m carbon atoms per molecule of the
compound or per group. As used herein, the terminology "each
independently selected from" in reference to organic substituents on an
organosiloxane repeating unit of a polyorganosiloxane polymer means that
each substituent group is selected independently from other substituent
groups on the repeating unit and independently from the substituent groups
on any other analogous repeating units of the polymer. A polyorganosiloxane
polymer described herein as including more than one of a particular type of
organosiloxane repeating unit, for example, diorganosiloxane ("D") units,
wherein the substituents on the units are "each independently selected" from
a defined group includes both polyorganosiloxane homopolymers, that is,
wherein the substituents on each of the organosiloxane repeating units of the
polymer are the same substituents, such as, for example, a
polydimethylsiloxane polymer, as well as polyorganosiloxane copolymers, that
is, a polymer containing two or more analogous organosiloxane repeating
units, each bearing different substituents, such as, for example, a
poly(dimethylsiloxane/methylphenylsiloxane) copolymer.</p><p num="0027">In a highly preferred embodiment, R<sup>4</sup> is a monovalent terminally unsaturated
(C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)hydrocarbon radical, more preferably, ethenyl or 2-propenyl, more
preferably ethenyl; R<sup>5</sup>, R<sup>6</sup>,R<sup>7</sup> R<sup>8</sup>, R<sup>14</sup> and R<sup>15</sup> are each independently (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)alkyl,
and more preferably are each methyl; R<sup>13</sup> is H; b is 2; 100 ≤ c ≤
2000; preferably 500 ≤ c ≤ 1500; 4 ≤ i ≤ 30; 1 ≤ n ≤ 15 and a, d, e, f, g, h, j, k, l
and m are each 0.</p><p num="0028">In an alternative highly preferred embodiment, R<sup>4</sup> is a monovalent terminally
unsaturated (C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>)hydrocarbon radical, more preferably, ethenyl or 2-propenyl,
more preferably ethenyl; R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup>, R<sup>3</sup>, R<sup>5</sup>, R<sup>6</sup>,R<sup>7</sup> R<sup>8</sup>, R<sup>14</sup>, R<sup>15</sup> and R<sup>17</sup>
are each independently (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>)alkyl, more preferably (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>)alkyl, still more
preferably methyl, R<sup>13</sup> and R<sup>16</sup> are each H; b is 2; 100 ≤ c ≤ 2000; preferably 
500 ≤ c ≤ 1500; h + i =2, 0 ≤ j ≤ 100, 2 ≤ k ≤ 100 and a, d, e, f, g, l, m and n
are each 0.</p><p num="0029">Suitable alkenyl functional silicone compounds and silylhydride functional
silicone compounds are described in, for example, U.S. Patents Nos.
5,506,289; 5,674,966; 5,717,010; 5,571,853; and 5,529,837, the disclosures
of which are each hereby incorporated by reference herein. The alkenyl
functionality and the silylhydride functionality may be combined into one
molecule self-curing molecule or compound, such as, for example, as
disclosed in U.S. patent 5,698,654.</p><p num="0030">In a preferred embodiment, the hydrosilylation reaction is carried out in the
presence of a hydrosilylation catalyst. Suitable catalysts are known, as
described in, for example, U.S. Patent Nos. 2,823,218; 3,159,601; 3,159,662;
and 3,775,452, and include, for example, ruthenium, osmium, rhodium,
iridium, palladium and platinum hydrosilylation catalysts.</p><p num="0031">In a preferred embodiment, the hydrosilylation reaction is carried out in a
reaction medium comprising one or more silicone fluids, one or more organic
liquids, each as more fully described below, or a mixture thereof.</p><heading><u style="single">Processing</u></heading><p num="0032">The crosslinked silicone elastomer of the present invention may then be
further swollen with additional solvent, which may be either the same as or
different from the reaction medium used in making the crosslinked silicone
polymer. The swollen crosslinked silicone elastomer is then subjected to
shear force, for example, using a two-roll mill, a homogenizer or a high shear
mixer, to break the elastomer into particles.</p><p num="0033">In a preferred embodiment, the swollen silicone elastomer is subjected high
flow induced shear by forcing the elastomer through an orifice at high
pressure. In a preferred embodiment, the viscosity of the swollen elastomer 
should be greater than 500 centiStokes ("cStk"), more preferably greater than
750 cStk, still more preferably greater than 1000 cStk and most preferably
over 5000 cStk. The orifice size is limited by the ability of the pumping
system to maintain sufficient pressure. In a preferred embodiment, the orifice
area is less than 0.5 square inches (in<sup>2</sup>), preferably less than 0.1 in<sup>2</sup>, more
preferably less than 0.05 in<sup>2</sup>, and most preferably less than 0.01 in<sup>2</sup>. In a
preferred embodiment, the pressure is above 500 pounds per square inch
(psi), more preferably above 1000 psi, still more preferably, over 1500 psi and
most preferably over 2000 psi.</p><heading><u style="single">Silicone Compositions</u></heading><p num="0034">In a preferred embodiment, the silicone composition of the present invention
comprises, based on 100 pbw of the composition, from 1 pbw to 99 pbw,
more preferably from 5 pbw to 95 pbw, and even more preferably 10 pbw to
90 pbw of the liquid medium, from 1 pbw to 99 pbw, more preferably from 5
pbw to 95 pbw, and even more preferably 10 pbw to 90 pbw of the silicone
particles.</p><p num="0035">In a preferred embodiment, the liquid medium consists essentially of an
organic liquid, more preferably a substantially non-polar organic liquid. In an
first alternative preferred embodiment, the liquid medium consists of a silicone
fluid. In a second alternative preferred embodiment, the liquid medium
comprises an organic liquid, more preferably a substantially non-polar organic
liquid, and a silicone fluid that is miscible with the organic liquid.</p><heading><u style="single">Silicone Emulsions</u></heading><p num="0036">In a preferred embodiment, the silicone emulsion of the present invention
comprises, based on 100 pbw of the combined amount of the first and second
liquids, from 0.1 pbw to 99.9 pbw, more preferably from 5 pbw to 95 pbw and
even more preferably from 15 pbw to 85 pbw, of the first liquid and from 0.1
pbw to 99.9 pbw, more preferably from 5 pbw to 95 pbw and even more 
preferably from 15 pbw to 80 pbw, of the second liquid and, based on 100
pbw of the silicone emulsion, from 0.001 pbw to 75 pbw, more preferably from
0.01 pbw to 40 pbw and even more preferably from 0.05 pbw to 20 pbw, of
the silicone elastomer of the present invention.</p><p num="0037">In a first highly preferred embodiment of the silicone emulsion of the present
invention, the first liquid phase is a continuous phase and the second liquid
phase is a discontinuous phase emulsified with the continuous first liquid
phase. In an alternative highly preferred embodiment of the silicone emulsion
of the present invention, the second liquid phase is a continuous phase and
the first liquid phase is a discontinuous phase emulsified with the continuous
second liquid phase.</p><p num="0038">In a preferred embodiment, the first liquid comprises a silicone fluid, a
substantially non-polar organic liquid, or a mixture thereof and the second
liquid comprises water, a substantially polar organic liquid or a mixture
thereof.</p><p num="0039">In a preferred embodiment, the silicone emulsion of the present invention
further comprises one or more emulsifying agents. Suitable emulsifying
agents useful in preparing the emulsions of the present include, for example,
silicone-containing emulsifying agents, emulsifying agents derived from
sorbitan compounds and emulsifying agents derived from fatty alcohols, more
preferably the emulsifying agent is selected from the group consisting of fatty
acid esters, sorbitan sesquioleate, sorbitan oleate, sorbitan isostearate,
polyglyceryl-3 oleate, alkoxylated alcohols such as laureth-4, laureth-7,
deceth-12, steareth-10, hydroxylated or alkoxylated derivatives of silicone
compounds such as dimethicone copolyol, cetyl dimethicone copolyol, and
lauryl methicone copolyol, glyceryl esters such as polyglyceryl-4-isostearyl
and mixtures thereof. </p><p num="0040">The first liquid, second liquid and silicone elastomer are mixed together to
form the silicone emulsion of the present invention. Preferably, the
components of the disperse phase is added to the components of the
continuous phase while subjecting the mixture of components to low shear
mixing and the mixture so formed is then subjected to high shear mixing. In a
preferred embodiment, a dispersion of the silicone elastomer of the present
invention in the first liquid is slowly added to the second liquid while
subjecting the combined phases to low shear mixing, such as, for example, in
a mixing tank equipped with a propeller-type stirrer, and then the mixture so
formed is subjected to high shear mixing, for example, in a Sonolator
apparatus, a Gaullen homogenizer or other high shear mixer, such as an
Eppenbach Mixer, to form the silicone emulsion. In a more highly preferred
embodiment, an emulsifying agent is combined with the first liquid prior to
adding the components of the first phase to the components of the second
phase.</p><heading><u style="single">Silicone Fluid</u></heading><p num="0041">Silicone fluids suitable for use as the silicone fluid component of the
composition of the present invention are those organosilicon compounds that
are in the liquid state at or near room temperature, for example, from about
20 °C about 50°C, and about one atmosphere pressure. In a preferred
embodiment, the silicone fluid component of the composition of the present
invention having a viscosity of below about 1,000 centistokes, preferably
below about 500 centistokes, more preferably below about 250 centistokes,
and most preferably below 100 centistokes, at 25°C. Suitable silicone fluids
include, for example, cyclic silicones of the formula D<sub>r</sub>, wherein D is defined
as above, R<sup>7</sup> and R<sup>8</sup> are each preferably methyl, and r is an integer wherein 3
≤ r ≤ 12, such as, for example, hexamethylcyclotrisiloxane ("D<sub>3</sub>"), octamethyl
cyclo- tetrasiloxane ("D<sub>4</sub>"), decamethylcyclopentasiloxane ("D<sub>5</sub>"), and 
dodecamethylcyclohexasiloxane ("D<sub>6</sub>") as well as linear organopolysiloxanes
having the formula (III):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">M'D'<sub>s</sub>M'</st32:che>
wherein:
<sl><li>M' is R<sup>19</sup>R<sup>20</sup>R<sup>21</sup>SiO<sub>1/2</sub>;</li><li>D' is R<sup>22</sup>R<sup>23</sup>SiO<sub>2/2</sub>;</li><li>R<sup>19</sup>, R<sup>20</sup>,R<sup>21</sup>, R<sup>22</sup> and R<sup>23</sup> are each independently alkyl, aryl or aralkyl;</li><li>s is an integer of from 0 to 300, wherein 0 ≤ s ≤ 300, preferably 0 ≤ s ≤ 100,
more preferably 0 ≤ s ≤ 50, and most preferably 0 ≤ s ≤ 20.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Organic Liquid</u></heading><p num="0042">Suitable organic liquids include any organic compound that is in the liquid
state at or near room temperature, for example, from about 20 °C about 50°C,
and about one atmosphere pressure, that is substantially inert to the silicone
phase, that is, does not undergo a chemical reaction with any of the
components of the silicone phase, under the anticipated conditions of
processing and use and that is suitable for use in the intended end-use
application, such as, for example, a cosmetic composition, to be prepared
from the non-aqueous silicone composition of the present invention.</p><p num="0043">As used herein, the terminology "substantially non-polar" means exhibiting a
dipole moment of less than about 0.9. Suitable substantially non-polar
organic liquids include, for example, linear or branched hydrocarbon liquids,
such as, for example, isododecane, hexadecane and octadecane, natural
oils, such as, for example, coconut oil, almond oil, apricot oil, mineral oils
castor oil and soybean oil, fatty alcohols such as octadecanol, dodecanol or
stearyl alcohol, fatty acids, such as, for example, stearic acid, lauric acid,
palmitic acid, esters, such as, for example, (C<sub>12</sub>-C<sub>15</sub>)alkylbenzoates, hexyl 
laurate, decyl stearate and glyceryl trioctanoate, as well as mixtures of two or
more of any of the above.</p><p num="0044">In a highly preferred embodiment, the substantially non-polar organic liquid
comprises a hydrocarbon liquid, more preferably a (C<sub>10</sub>-C<sub>24</sub>)alkane.</p><p num="0045">As used herein, the terminology "substantially polar" means exhibiting a
dipole moment of from about 0.9 to 4.5. Suitable substantially polar organic
liquids include organic hydroxylic liquids, such as, for example, alcohols,
glycols, polyhydric alcohols and polymeric glycols. More preferably, the
substantially polar organic liquid is selected from of alcohols including
polyhydric alcohols, glycols, including polymeric glycols, and mixtures thereof.
Preferably, the substantially polar organic liquid contains an (C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>)alcohol,
such as for example, ethanol, propyl alcohol and iso-propyl alcohol, a (C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>12</sub>)glycol,
such as for example, ethylene glycol, propylene glycol, dipropylene
glycol, tripropylene glycol, butylene glycol, iso-butylene glycol and methyl
propane diol, a polyhydric alcohol, such as for example, glycerin erythritol and
sorbitol, or a polymeric glycol, such as for example, polyethylene glycol,
polypropylene glycol mono alkyl ethers and polyoxyalkylene copolymers. In a
highly preferred embodiment, the substantially polar organic liquid is selected
from ethanol, propyl alcohol, iso-propyl alcohol, ethylene glycol, propylene
glycol, dipropylene glycol, tripropylene glycol, butylene glycol, iso-butylene
glycol, methyl propane diol, glycerin, erythritol sorbitol, polyethylene glycol,
polypropylene glycol mono alkyl ethers, polyoxyalkylene copolymers.</p><heading><u style="single">Personal care compositions</u></heading><p num="0046">The personal care applications where the silicone elastomer of the present
invention may be employed include, but are not limited to, deodorants,
antiperspirants, skin lotions, moisturizers, hair care products such as
shampoos, mousses and styling gels, protective creams such as sunscreen
and anti-aging products, color cosmetics such as lipsticks, foundations, 
blushes, makeup, and mascaras and other cosmetic formulations where
silicone components have been conventionally been added, as well as drug
delivery systems for topical application of medicinal compositions that are to
be applied to the skin.</p><p num="0047">Suitable personal care compositions are made by combining, in a manner
known in the art, such as, for example, by mixing, one or more of the above
components with the silicone elastomer of the present invention, the silicone
composition of the present invention or the silicone emulsion of the present
invention. Suitable personal care compositions may be in the form of a single
phase or in the form of an emulsion, including oil-in-water, water-in-oil and
anhydrous emulsions.</p><p num="0048">In a preferred embodiment, an anti-perspirant composition comprises one or
more active anti-perspirant agents, such as, for example, aluminum halides,
aluminum hydroxyhalides, for example, aluminum chlorohydrate, and
complexes or mixtures thereof with zirconyl oxyhalides and zirconyl
hydroxyhalides, such as for example, aluminum-zirconium chlorohydrate, and
the silicone elastomer of the present invention.</p><p num="0049">In a preferred embodiment, a skin care composition comprises silicone
elastomer of the present invention, and optionally, further comprises a
vehicle, such as, for example, a silicone oil or an organic oil. The skin care
composition may, optionally, further include emollients, such as, for example,
triglyceride esters, wax esters, alkyl or alkenyl esters of fatty acids or
polyhydric alcohol esters and one or more the known components
conventionally used in skin care compositions, such as, for example,
pigments, vitamins, such as, for example, vitamin C and vitamin E, sunscreen
or sunblock compounds, such as for example, titanium dioxide, oxybenzone
sunscreens and p-aminobenzoic acid. </p><p num="0050">In a preferred embodiment, a personal care composition comprises a non-aqueous
emulsion of the silicone elastomer of the present invention and one
or more water-sensitive dermatological active agents or cosmetic active
agents, such as for example, ascorbic acid or an enzyme, particularly a
protease, such as for example, enzyme sold under the trade name
SUBTILISIN SP 544 by Novo Nordisk or the enzyme sold under the trade
name LYSOVEG by Laboratoires Serobiologiques de Nancy.</p><p num="0051">The personal care composition of the present invention may, optionally,
further contain such know components as, for example, emollients,
moisturizers, humectants, pigments, colorants, fragrances, biocides,
preservatives, exfoliants, hormones, enzymes, medicinal compounds, antimicrobial
agents, anti-fungal agents, vitamins, salts, electrolytes, alcohols,
polyols, absorbing agents for ultraviolet radiation, botanical extracts,
surfactants, silicone oils, organic oils, waxes, thickening agents such as, for
example, fumed silica or hydrated silica, clays, such as, for example,
bentonite, and organo-modified clays.</p><heading><u style="single">Examples 1 and 2 and Comparative Example 1</u></heading><p num="0052">The silicone elastomer of Example 1 is made by combining: (i) 2000 grams of
divinyl siloxanes of the average formula M<sup>vi</sup><sub>2</sub>D<sub>900</sub>, wherein M<sup>vi</sup> and D are each
defined as for formula (I) above; R<sup>4</sup> is ethenyl; and R<sup>5</sup>, R<sup>6</sup>, R<sup>7</sup> and R<sup>8</sup> are each
methyl; (ii) 23.0 grams of silylhydride functional resins of the average formula
(M<sup>H</sup><sub>2</sub>Q)<sub>4</sub>, wherein M<sup>H</sup> and Q are each defined as for formula (II) above, R<sup>13</sup> is
H and R<sup>14</sup> and R<sup>15</sup> are each methyl; and (iii) 36 grams of mixed α, β-ethylenically
unsaturated (C<sub>16</sub>-C<sub>18</sub>) alkenes with 6000 grams of D<sub>5</sub> in 10 liter
mixer. A hydrosilylation catalyst (0.4 grams of 10% platinum catalyst solution)
was then added to the reactor. The contents of the reactor were then stirred
and heated to 80°C over 7 hours. The polymerized solid product, in the form
of a fluffy white powder, was then removed from the reactor, diluted to 4.75 
wt% solids with D<sub>5</sub> and subjected to high shear in a Sonolator homogenizer
(orifice size = 0.0007 in<sup>2</sup>) for four passes at 4500 psi to produce a clear gel.</p><p num="0053">The silicone elastomer of Example 2 is made by combining (i) 2000 grams of
the divinyl siloxanes described above in Example 1, (ii) 97 grams of linear
silylhydride-functional resins of the average formula M<sub>2</sub>D<sub>22</sub>D<sup>H</sup><sub>22</sub>, wherein: M, D
and D<sup>H</sup> are each defined as for formula (II) above, R<sup>16</sup> is H and R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup>, R<sup>3</sup>, R<sup>7</sup>,
R<sup>8</sup>, R<sup>13</sup>, R<sup>14</sup>, R<sup>15</sup> and R<sup>17</sup> are each methyl, and (iii) 43 grams of mixed α, β-ethylenically
unsaturated (C<sub>16</sub>-C<sub>18</sub>) alkenes with 6000 grams of D<sub>5</sub> in a 10 liter
mixer. The mixture was stirred and 5 ppm of platinum catalyst was added.
The reaction was heated to 80°C over 7 hours. The product was then diluted
to about 6.05% polymer content and then subjected to high shear in a
Sonolator® homogenizer for four passes at 4500 psi to generate a clear gel.</p><p num="0054">The composition of Comparative Example C1 was made by a process
analogous to that described above for the elastomer of Example 1 except that
the mixed (C<sub>16</sub>-C<sub>18</sub>)olefins were omitted from the reaction mixture. The
reaction product was diluted to 5.5 wt% solids with D<sub>5</sub> and subjected to high
shear in a Sonolator homogenizer for four passes at 4500 psi to produce a
clear gel.</p><p num="0055">Each of the compositions of Examples 1 and 2 and Comparative Example C1
were mixed with isododecane.</p><p num="0056">A sample of 50 pbw of the composition of Example 1 was diluted with 50 pbw
isododecane to form a visually clear mixture having a viscosity of 12,500 ctks,
with no evidence of precipitation of gel particles.</p><p num="0057">A sample of 50 pbw of the composition of Example 2 was blended with 30%
added isododecane. The resulting visually clear gel had a viscosity of 15,500
cSt. </p><p num="0058">A sample of the composition of Comparative Example C1 was also diluted
with isodecane. As isododecane is added to and mixed with the composition
of Comparative Example C1, the viscosity of the mixture so formed falls
rapidly to less than 100 cSt at about 30% added isododecane. Small particles
were observed on the sides of the flask.</p><p num="0059">These results observed for mixtures of isododecane with the compositions of
Examples 1 and 2 demonstrate the compatibility of the alkyl substituted
elastomers with the isododecane, i.e., it appears that the isododecane is able
to further swell the elastomeric particle to thereby maintain the viscosity of the
dispersion relatively stable. The clear visual appearance of the dispersions
provide further indication of compatibility of the alkyl substituted elastomers
with the isododecane.</p> <p num="0060">The results observed for Comparative Example C1 indicate that the
isododecane is not compatible with the elastomer of Comparative Example
C1, but rather appears to be drawing D5 from the elastomer particles,
resulting in a dramatic decrease in the viscosity of the mixture. Furthermore,
the small particles were observed on the sides of the flask, indicate
precipitation of the elastomer from the isododecane/D<sub>5</sub> solution.</p><heading><u style="single">Examples 3-8 and Comparative Examples C2-C6</u></heading><p num="0061">A silicone polymer was made by adding 182 pbw of a silicone resin having an
average formula of (MH<sub>2</sub>Q)<sub>4</sub>, 2000 pbw of a 40000 cSt terminally substituted
divinylpolysiloxane 276 pbw of (C<sub>24</sub>-C<sub>28</sub>)α-olefin and 6000 pbw of
decamethylcyclopentasiloxane to reaction vessel. A platinum catalyst (0.42
pbw of 10% solution) was added to the reaction vessel and the contents of
the reaction vessel were then mixed and heated to 80°C over 7 hours. The
product so formed was then removed from the reaction vessel and diluted
with additional decamethylcyclopentasiloxane until the polymer solids 
concentration was 5.5%. The diluted product was then subjected to high
shear in a Sonolator homogenizer for three passes at 4500 psi, to give a
clean, high viscosity gel.</p><p num="0062">The composition of Example 4 was made by diluting the gel of Example 3
with 20% by weight of isohexadecane. The isohexadecane was absorbed to
produce a clear gel with viscosity of 60,000 cSt.</p> <p num="0063">The composition of Comparative Example C2 was made by diluting
Comparative Example C1 with 20% by weight of isohexadecane. The
resulting mixture was a cloudy, free flowing liquid with a viscosity of less than
100 cSt.</p> <p num="0064">The composition of Example 5 was made by diluting the gel of Example 3
with 20% by weight of (C<sub>24</sub>-C<sub>28</sub>)α-olefin. Upon heating to the olefin melting
point, the mixture formed a clear solution and upon cooling, the product
mixture was a homogeneous, low melting soft waxy solid that spreads easily
onto the skin.</p> <p num="0065">The composition of Comparative Example C3 was made by diluting
Comparative Example C1 with 20% by weight of (C<sub>24</sub>-C<sub>28</sub>)α-olefin. Upon
heating to the melting point of the wax, a cloudy, heterogeneous mixture
consisting of large domains of wax and silicone elastomer was formed. On
cooling, a heterogeneous mixture of elastomer and wax was formed.</p><p num="0066">The composition of Example 6 was made by diluting the gel of Example 3
with 30% by weight of hydrogenated polyisobutene. The hydrogenated
polyisobutene was to produce a clear, homogeneous gel with a viscosity of
greater than 4000 cSt.</p><p num="0067">The composition of Comparative Example C4 was made by diluting
Comparative Example C1 with 30% by weight of hydrogenated polyisobutene.
The resulting mixture was a free flowing liquid of 988 cSt. </p><p num="0068">The composition of Example 7 was made by diluting the gel of Example 3
with 20% by weight of stearyl alcohol. Upon heating to melting point of the
stearyl alcohol, the stearyl alcohol was absorbed by the elastomer and
produced a visually clear solution. Upon cooling, the product mixture was a
homogeneous, low melting soft solid that spreads easily onto the skin.</p><p num="0069">The composition of Comparative Example C5 was made by diluting
Comparative Example C1 with 20% by weight of stearyl alcohol. Upon
heating to the melting point of the stearyl alcohol, a cloudy heterogeneous
solution was formed. On cooling, the stearyl alcohol solidified to form a
heterogeneous mixture of stearyl alcohol particles and siloxane.</p><p num="0070">The composition of Example 8 was made by diluting the gel of Example 3
with 20% by weight of isostearic acid. The isostearic acid was absorbed to
produce a clear, homogeneous gel with a viscosity of 76,000 cSt.</p><p num="0071">The composition of Comparative Example C6 was made by diluting
Comparative Example C1 with 20% by weight isostearic acid. The resulting
mixture was a cloudy, free flowing liquid of less than 100 cSt.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 9</u></heading><p num="0072">The make-up foundation composition of Example 9 is made by combining the
listed components in the relative amounts (in pbw) set forth below in TABLE I. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1"><u style="single"><i>Oil Phase</i></u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cyclopentasiloxane and dimethicone copolyol</entry><entry align="left">10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silicone elastoSiliconmer of Example 1</entry><entry align="left">10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C30-45 Alkyl Dimethicone</entry><entry align="left">2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cyclopentasiloxane</entry><entry align="left">20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bis-Phenyl Propyl Dimethicone</entry><entry align="left">10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sorbitan Oleate</entry><entry align="left">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pigment dispersion WE (Kobo)</entry><entry align="left">5</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1"><u style="single"><i>Water Phase</i></u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="left">42.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polysorbate 20</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">NaCl</entry><entry align="left">1</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0073">The silicone phase and water phase are made separately. The components
of the silicone phase are added to a mixing vessel in the order listed and
mixed together with moderate agitation. The components of the water phase
are added to a mixing vessel in the order listed and mixed together with
moderate agitation. The water phase is then added to the silicone phase at a
rate of addition is sufficiently slow to allow the water phase to be completely
incorporated in the silicone phase to provide a water-in-silicone emulsion
having a substantially homogeneous appearance.</p><p num="0074">The make-up foundation composition of Example 9 provides the excellent
sensory properties of an oil-in-silicone type foundation. The alkyl
functionalized elastomer stabilizes the emulsion and gives a smooth, silky feel
with even coverage. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 10-12</u></heading><p num="0075">The anhydrous emulsions of Examples 10-12 are made by combining the
listed components in the relative amounts (in pbw) set forth below in TABLE
II.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" align="left" namest="1"><u style="single"><i>Silicone Phase</i></u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cyclopentasiloxane and dimethicone copolyol</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silicone elastomer of Example 1</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">10</entry></row><row><entry nameend="4" align="left" namest="1"><u style="single"><i>Organic Phase</i></u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Butylene Glycol</entry><entry align="left">80</entry><entry align="left">--</entry><entry align="left">--</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Propylene Glycol</entry><entry align="left">--</entry><entry align="left">80</entry><entry align="left">--</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-methyl-1,3 Propane-Diol</entry><entry align="left">--</entry><entry align="left">--</entry><entry align="left">80</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0076">The components of the silicone phase are added to a mixing vessel in the
order listed and mixed together with moderate agitation. The organic phase
is then added to the silicone phase at a rate of addition is sufficiently slow to
allow the organic phase to be completely incorporated in the silicone phase to
provide a glycol-in-silicone emulsion having a substantially homogeneous
appearance.</p><p num="0077">The anhydrous emulsions of Examples 10-12 provide an excellent non-tacky
smooth feel.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 13</u></heading><p num="0078">The antiperspirant composition of Example 13 is made by combining the
listed components in the relative amounts (in pbw) set forth below in TABLE
III. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Silicone elastomerof Example 1</entry><entry align="left">80</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Aluminum Chlorohydrate</entry><entry align="left">20</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0079">Aluminum chlorohydrate is then added to the elastomer and mixed.</p><p num="0080">The antiperspirant composition of Example 13 illustrates the stabilization and
thickening effects of the alkyl functionalized elastomer of the present
invention. The resultant formula is creamy. Unlike most organic wax or clay
thickened systems, this formulation shows no syneresis or separation with
time. Additionally, the formula is smooth and easy to apply with virtually no
visually detectable residue.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 14</u></heading><p num="0081">The clear anhydrous gel antiperspirant compositions of Example 10-12 are
made by combining the listed components in the relative amounts (in pbw) set
forth below in TABLE IV. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1"><u style="single"><i>Silicone Phase</i></u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cyclomethicone and Dimethicone Copolyol</entry><entry align="left">2.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silicone elastomer of Example 1</entry><entry align="left">7.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bis-Phenyl Propyl Dimethicone</entry><entry align="left">14.5</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1"><u style="single"><i>Glycol Phase</i></u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polysorbate 80</entry><entry align="left">0.25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Propylene Glycol</entry><entry align="left">47.42</entry></row><row><entry align="left">30% ZAG solution in Propylene Glycol</entry><entry align="left">23.33</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(Westchlor A2Z 8106)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ethanol</entry><entry align="left">5.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0082">The components of Part A are mixed together, reserving 3 percent of the
propylene glycol for later use. The polysorbate 80 and ethanol are then
dissolved in remaining propylene glycol. The ZAG solution is added to
propylene glycol solution and mixed to form Part B. The refractive indices of
Part A and Part B are each measured. The reserved propylene glycol is
added by increments to part B to match the refractive index of Part B to Part
A within ∼0.00010 units. Once the desired refractive index match is obtained,
Part B is slowly to Part A with moderate shear mixing. The agitation is
gradually increased to high shear as the mixture thickens and then continued
for ∼5 minutes. The mixture is then homogenized for ∼2 minutes in a high
speed high shear mixer.</p><p num="0083">This example demonstrate a clear antiperspirant gel using an anhydrous
glycol-in-silicone form. The formulation is stable, and with excellent sensory
properties and provides a non-tacky, smooth and silky feel. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 15</u></heading><p num="0084">The oil-in-water gel composition of Example 13 is made by combining the
listed components in the relative amounts (in pbw) set forth below in TABLE
V.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1"><u style="single"><i>Part A</i></u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="left">88.79</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Disodium EDTA</entry><entry align="left">0.03</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Citric Acid (10% solution)</entry><entry align="left">0.03</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbomer</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1"><u style="single"><i>Part B</i></u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">1,3 butylene glycol</entry><entry align="left">2.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glycerin (99%)</entry><entry align="left">3.5</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1"><u style="single"><i>Part C</i></u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bis-Phenyl Propyl Dimethicone</entry><entry align="left">0.35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silicone elastomer of Example 1</entry><entry align="left">3.0</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1"><u style="single"><i>Part D</i></u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium Hydroxide (10% solution)</entry><entry align="left">1.6</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0085">The EDTA and citric acid are added to the water with moderate agitation until
dissolved. The Carbomer is then to the water mixture slowly until dissolved.
The components of B are then added to part A with moderate agitation. The
components of art C are then added to the mixture of parts A and B in order
listed. Part D is then added to the mixture with sweep agitation and pH
adjusted to 7.2. </p><p num="0086">The oil-in-water gel composition of Example 15 illustrates the stabilization and
detackification effects of elastomer in a carbomer thickened oil-in-water
emulsion. The formulation imparts a silky non-tacky and light feel to the skin.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A silicone elastomer, comprising the cross-linked hydrosilylation
reaction product of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) an alkenyl functional silicone compound;</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) a silylhydride functional silicone compound; and</claim-text><claim-text>(iii) one or more α,β-ethylenically unsaturated alkenes.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1, wherein the composition comprises the
cross-linked hydrosilylation reaction product of, based on 100 parts by weight
of the combined alkenyl functional silicone compound, silylhydride functional
silicone compound and α,β-ethylenically unsaturated alkenes, from 10 parts
by weight to 99.9 parts by weight of the combined alkenyl functional silicone
compound and silylhydride functional silicone compound and from greater
than 0.1 parts by weight to 90 parts by weight of the one or more α,β-ethylenically
unsaturated alkenes.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1, wherein the alkenyl functional silicone
compound comprises one or more compounds of the formula:
MaMvi bDcDvi dTeTvi fQg
wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>M is R1R2R3SiO1/2;</claim-text><claim-text>Mvi is R4R5R6SiO1/2;</claim-text><claim-text>D is R7R8SiO2/2;</claim-text><claim-text>Dvi is R9R10SiO2/2;</claim-text><claim-text>T is R11SiO3/2;</claim-text><claim-text>Tvi is R12SiO3/2; and</claim-text><claim-text>Q is SiO4/2;</claim-text><claim-text>R1, R2, R3,R7, R8 and R11 are each independently alkyl, aryl or aralkyl;R4, R9
and R12 are each independently monovalent terminally unsaturated
hydrocarbon radicals;</claim-text><claim-text>R5, R6 and R10 are each independently monovalent terminally unsaturated
hydrocarbon radicals, alkyl, aryl or aralkyl;</claim-text><claim-text>a, b, c, d, e, f and g are each integers wherein: a, b, e, f, and g are each
greater than or equal to 0 and less than or equal to 50, 0 ≤ c ≤ 2000 , 0 ≤ d ≤
200, and provided that: (a + b) ≤ (2 + 3e + 3f + 4g) and ≤ (b + d + f) ≤ 200.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The composition of claim 3, wherein R4 is a monovalent terminally
unsaturated (C2-C6)hydrocarbon radical; R5, R6,R7 and R8 are each
independently (C1-C6)alkyl; R5, R6,R7 and R8 are each independently (C1-C6)alkyl;
b is 2; 100 ≤ c ≤ 2000; and a, d, e, f and g are each 0.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1, wherein the silylhydride functional silicone
compound comprises one or more compounds of the formula:
MhMH iDjDH kTlTH mQn
wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>M is R1R2R3SiO1/2;</claim-text><claim-text>MH is R13R14R15SiO1/2;</claim-text><claim-text>D is R7R8SiO2/2;</claim-text><claim-text>DH is R16R17SiO2/2;</claim-text><claim-text>T is R11SiO3/2;</claim-text><claim-text>TH is R18SiO3/2;</claim-text><claim-text>Q is SiO4/2;</claim-text><claim-text>R1, R2, R3,R7, R8 and R11 are each independently alkyl, aryl or aralkyl;</claim-text><claim-text>R13, R16 and R18 are each independently H;</claim-text><claim-text>R14, R15 and R17 are each independently H, alkyl, aryl or aralkyl; and</claim-text><claim-text>h, i, j, k, I, m, and n are each integers wherein h, i, I, m and n are each greater
than or equal to 0 and less than or equal to 50, 0 ≤ j ≤ 2000 , 0 ≤ k ≤ 200, and
provided that (h + i) ≤ (2 + 31 + 3m + 4n) and 1.5 ≤ (i + k + m) ≤ 200.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method for making a cross-linked alkyl substituted silicone
elastomer, comprising forming the hydrosilylation reaction product of (i) an
alkenyl functional silicone compound; (ii) a silylhydride functional silicone
compound; and (iii) one or more α,β-unsaturated alkenes.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method of claim 6, wherein the cross-linked alkyl substituted
silicone elastomer is formed by contacting the alkenyl functional silicone
compound, silylhydride functional silicone compound and the one or more
α,β-ethylenically unsaturated alkenes under hydrosilylation conditions in a
medium comprising one or more silicone fluids, one or more organic liquids or
a mixture thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A silicone composition, comprising a liquid medium, said liquid medium
comprising an organic liquid; and a silicone elastomer dispersed in the liquid
medium, said elastomer comprising the cross-linked hydrosilylation reaction
product of (i) an alkenyl functional silicone compound; (ii) a silylhydride
functional silicone compound; and (iii) one or more α,β-ethylenically
unsaturated alkenes.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A silicone emulsion, comprising an emulsion of a first liquid phase and
a second liquid phase and further comprising a silicone elastomer dispersed
in the emulsion, said silicone elastomer comprising the cross-linked
hydrosilylation reaction product of (i) an alkenyl functional silicone compound;
(ii) a silylhydride functional silicone compound; and (iii) one or more α,β-ethylenically
unsaturated alkenes.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The silicone emulsion of claim 9, wherein the first liquid comprises a
silicone fluid, a substantially non-polar organic liquid or a mixture thereof and
the second liquid comprises water, a substantially polar organic liquid or a
mixture thereof.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="172" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="257" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="169" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="253" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>