<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2003055816-A2" country="WO" doc-number="2003055816" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="21821495" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20030710"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2003055816-A2" status="new" fvid="78582051"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2003055816</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20030710</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-0240076-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>0240076</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20021216</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-2461301-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>2461301</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011221</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>C03C  17/00</main-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03C  17/36        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C03C  17/36        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C03C  17/36</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M03C217:320</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M03C217:332</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M03C217:339</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M03C217:342</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M03C217:346</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">LOW-E COATING WITH HIGH VISIBLE TRANSMISSION</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">REVETEMENT A FAIBLE E PRESENTANT UN HAUT POUVOIR DE TRANSMISSION DANS LE DOMAINE DU VISIBLE</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-19732978-C1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>19732978</doc-number><kind>C1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="DE-4211363-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>4211363</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6306525-B1"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6306525</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998058885-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998058885</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GUARDIAN INDUSTRIES</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GUARDIAN INDUSTRIES CORP.</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>STACHOWIAK GRZEGORZ</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>STACHOWIAK, GRZEGORZ</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Coated articles are provided with an anti−reflection system (s) which enables high visible transmission and/or low visible reflection. Neutral color is also achievable in certain example embodiments. In certain example embodiments, the anti−reflection system(s) is used in conjunction with a double silver (Ag) layer stack which provides low sheet resistance and/or emissivity.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>La présente invention concerne des articles revêtus qui présentent un/des système(s) antireflet conférant un haut pouvoir de transmission dans le domaine du visible et/ou un faible pouvoir de réflexion dans le domaine du visible. On peut ainsi obtenir une couleur neutre dans certains modes de réalisation tenant lieu d'exemples. Dans certains modes de réalisation tenant lieu d'exemples, le(s) système(s) antireflet est/sont utilisé(s) en association avec un empilement de deux couches d'argent (Ag) qui confère une faible résistance de couche et/ou une faible émissivité.</p></abstract><description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="2"/>--><p num="p0001"> TITLE OF THE INNENTION</p><p num="p0002">LOW-E COATING WITH HIGH VISIBLE TRANSMISSION</p><p num="p0003">RELATED APPLICATION</p><p num="p0004">[0001] This application is related to U.S. Patent Application Serial No.</p><p num="p0005">09/794,224.</p><p num="p0006">BACKGROUND AND SUMMARY OF THE INNENTION</p><p num="p0007">[0002] The 09/794,224 application discloses coated articles having the following layer stack, as shown in Figure 1 herein, from the glass substrate outwardly:</p><p num="p0008">Table 1: Example Materials/Thicknesses</p><p num="p0009">Layer Preferred Ra (A) More Preferred (A) Example (A)</p><p num="p0010">Substrate (1-10 mm)</p><p num="p0011">TiO<sub>2</sub> 0-400 A 50-250 A 100 A</p><p num="p0012">Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub> 0-400 A 50-250 A 170 A</p><p num="p0013">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 5-100 A 10-50 A 18 A</p><p num="p0014">Ag 50-250 A 80-120 A 105 A</p><p num="p0015">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 5-100 A 10-50 A 16 A</p><p num="p0016">SnO<sub>2</sub> 0-800 A 500-850 A 650 A</p><p num="p0017">Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub> 0-800 A 50-250 A 170 A</p><p num="p0018">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 5-100 A 10-50 A 18 A</p><p num="p0019">Ag 50-250 A 80-120 A 105 A</p><p num="p0020">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 5-100 A 10-50 A 16 A</p><p num="p0021">SnO. 0-500 A 100-300 A 150 A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>-->
Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 0-500 A 100-300 A 250 A</p><p num="p0022">[0003] In other embodiments of 09/794,224, the bottom titanium oxide layer may be removed or replaced with a silicon nitride layer.</p><p num="p0023">[0004] While the aforesaid coated articles described in the 09/794,224 application provide good color, and good ultraviolet (UN) and/or infrared (IR) reflection, increased visible transmission and/or reduced visible reflection would sometimes be desirable.</p><p num="p0024">[0005] Neutral color is also desirable for coated articles in certain applications. Many conventional methods of making color of a coated article more neutral result in decreased visible transmission and/or increased visible reflection. Heretofore, it has been difficult to increase visible transmission and reduce visible reflection, while at the same time providing or maintaining rather neutral color and satisfactory solar control or thermal characteristics. Whether a color is "neutral" or not is subjective, and is a function of personal taste. However, generally speaking, color moving toward a neutral color target (e.g., a*=0, b*=0, or some other neutral color target such as transmissive a*=-2 and transmissive b*=-3.4) is desired, although such targets do not have to be met in all embodiments of this invention.</p><p num="p0025">[0006] In view of the above, it is an object of certain embodiments of this invention to provide a solar controlling coated article (i.e., an article including at least one and preferably two or more layers such as Ag and/or Au for reflecting IR and/or UV) having increased visible transmission and/or reduced visible reflectance. In certain example non-limiting embodiments of this invention, it is an object to combine such high visible transmission and/or reduced visible reflection with neutral color of the coated article. Alternatively, the use of an improved anti-reflection layer(s) system(s) may enable coatings to have or utilize more robust contact layer(s) (e.g., thicker for better durability) and/or thicker silver (Ag) layer(s) (i.e., improved thermal performance) while maintaining similar transmission characteristics if increased transmission is not a most desired feature (e.g., if durability is a most desired feature).</p><p num="p0026">[0007] Another object of this invention is to fulfill one or more of the above- listed objects and/or needs. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
 BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</p><p num="p0027">[0008] FIGURE 1 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to an embodiment of this invention, as disclosed in the 09/794,224 application.</p><p num="p0028">[0009] FIGURE 2 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to an embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0029">[0010] FIGURE 3 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0030">[0011] FIGURE 4 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0031">[0012] FIGURE 5 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0032">[0013] FIGURE 6 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0033">[0014] FIGURE 7 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0034">[0015] FIGURE 8 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0035">[0016] FIGURE 9 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0036">[0017] FIGURE 10 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0037">[0018] FIGURE 11 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0038">[0019] FIGURE 12 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0039">[0020] FIGURE 13 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
 [0021] FIGURE 14 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0040">[0022] FIGURE 15 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0041">[0023] FIGURE 16 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0042">[0024] FIGURE 17 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention.</p><p num="p0043">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF EXAMPLE EMBODIMENTS OF THE</p><p num="p0044">INNENTION</p><p num="p0045">[0025] The instant invention relates to coated articles which may be used in applications including but not limited to insulating glass (IG) window units, monolithic windows, skylight windows, and/or any other type of window. Coated articles according to this invention include an improved anti-reflection layer(s) system for reducing visible reflectance and/or increasing visible transmission in coated articles that provide solar control (e.g., IR and/or UV reflection) functionality. Surprisingly, in certain example embodiments it has been found that certain anti- reflection layer(s) systems of the instant invention can both: (a) improve visible transmission and/or reduce visible reflectance, while at the same time (b) achieving an acceptable neutral color of the resulting coated article.</p><p num="p0046">[0026] Fig. 2 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to an embodiment of this invention. The coated article of Fig. 2, like all other coated articles herein, may be used in any of the aforesaid applications (e.g., architectural windows, etc.). The coated article of Fig. 2 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices of refraction "n" at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
 silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) silicon oxide (e.g., Si0<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.4 to 1.7, preferably n=1.45) air (n=1.0)</p><p num="p0047">[0027] As shown in Fig. 2, the contact layers (i.e., NiCrO<sub>x</sub> layers) surround and contact the IR reflecting Ag layers. The NiCrO<sub>x</sub> layers herein are called "contact" layers because they each contact an IR reflecting layer (i.e., an Ag layer). The NiCrO<sub>x</sub> contact layers provide the most immediate chemical protection for the Ag layer, and also serve as adhesion and or nucleation layers. The contact layers may or may not be oxidation graded as described in the 09/794,224 application, in different embodiments of this invention. Moreover, instead of NiCrO<sub>x</sub>, one or more of the contact layers may be of or include other material(s) including but not limited to NiCr, NiCrN<sub>x</sub>, NiCrO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>, ZnO, Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, TiO<sub>2</sub>, ZnAlO<sub>x</sub>, Ni, Cr, CrN<sub>x</sub>, NiO<sub>x</sub>, NbO<sub>x</sub>, any combination thereof, and/or the like. Moreover, in any embodiment herein, materials such as titanium oxide or niobium oxide could even serve as top contact layers (i.e., above Ag layer(s)), in addition to dielectrics herein. Example thicknesses of the contact layers, and other layers herein, are discussed above in the Background and Summary section of this application. The above applies to contact layers in the Fig. 1-17 embodiments.</p><p num="p0048">[0028] Instead of Ag, other metallic IR reflecting materials (e.g., Au, Ag alloys, Au alloys, etc.) may be used for one or more of the IR reflecting layers (this applies to the Fig. 1-17 embodiments). The thickness of the metallic Ag layers (IR 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
reflecting layers) is chosen in order to achieve the desired thermal performance (see example thickness ranges above). For example, the Ag layer may be from about 50- 250 A thick, in order to achieve sheet resistance (R<sub>s</sub>) (before and/or after heat treatment) of less than or equal to 10.0 ohms/square, more preferably less than or equal to 8.0 ohms/square, even more preferably less than or equal to 5.0 ohms/square, and most preferably less than or equal to 4.0 ohms/square. In a similar manner, the Ag layer(s) thickness(es) are chosen so that the coating (or coated article) has a normal emissivity (E<sub>n</sub>) of no greater than 0.08, more preferably no greater than 0.06, and most preferably no greater than 0.05 (before and/or after heat treatment). The aforesaid emissivity and sheet resistance characteristics apply to the Fig. 1-17 embodiments.</p><p num="p0049">[0029] The IR reflecting and contact layers of the Fig. 2 coating (and the Fig.</p><p num="p0050">3-17 coatings) are discussed in the 09/794,224 application (incoφorated herein by reference), and are not discussed herein for reasons of simplicity. See the thicknesses/materials described in the 09/794,224 in this regard. The focus herein lies with the provision of dielectric layers which are utilized in order to: (a) increase visible transmission, (b) decrease visible reflection (e.g., glass side), and/or (c) provide neutral color. With respect to the Fig. 2 embodiment in particular, it will be shown below that the dielectric layers used therein (compared to in Fig. 1) result in a significant increase in visible transmission combined with a decrease in visible reflectance (glass and/or film side). This is beneficial.</p><p num="p0051">[0030] It can be seen that the Fig. 2 embodiment of this invention differs from</p><p num="p0052">Fig. 1 in that (a) the bottom silicon nitride layer from Fig. 1 has been removed, (b) a titanium oxide layer has been added in the middle portion M, (c) the middle silicon nitride layer from Fig. 1 has been removed, (d) titanium oxide and silicon oxide layers have been added to the top portion T of the coating in Fig. 2, and (e) the top silicon nitride layer from Fig. 1 has been removed. By using silicon oxide (i.e., stoichiometric SiO , or alternatively a non-stoichiometric form) over the top tin oxide layer, and by utilizing the titanium oxide (i.e., stoichiometric Ti0 , or alternatively a non-stoichiometric form such as TiO<sub>1</sub>.<sub>5</sub>n-<sub>1</sub>.<sub>99</sub>) layers as illustrated, the coating (layer system) can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index 
<!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>-->
 of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than that of the bottom dielectric portion B (see Fig. 2). In other words, nτ&lt;n<sub>M</sub>&lt;nβ, where nj is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, ΠM is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and nrj is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B (the "effective" index may be calculated as a weighted average of the portion, or by any other suitable technique/method). As shown in Fig. 2, each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer.</p><p num="p0053">[0031] By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction</p><p num="p0054">"n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of Fig. 2 enables increased visible transmission and/or reduced visible reflection to be achieved. Surprisingly, as will be shown below in the Examples of this embodiment, the anti-reflection system also enables fairly neutral color of the coated article. Moreover, in certain example embodiments of this invention, nj &lt;= 2.0. The silicon oxide layers herein may be from about 10-700 A thick in certain example embodiments of this invention, more preferably from 20-600 A thick, and most preferably from 50-500 A thick. Upper tin oxide layers herein (i.e., in top portion T above the top TR reflecting layer) may be from about 10-700 A thick in certain example embodiments of this invention, more preferably from 20-600 A thick, and most preferably from 40-400 A thick. Upper titanium oxide layers herein (i.e., in top portion T above trie top IR reflecting layer) may be from about 10-500 A thick in certain example embodiments of this invention, more preferably from 40-300 A thick. Middle titanium oxide layers herein (i.e., in middle portion M between the ER reflecting layers) may be from about 10-900 A thick in certain example embodiments of this invention, more preferably from 50-700 A thick. Bottom titanium oxide layers herein (i.e., in bottom portion B below the lower IR reflecting layer) may have thicknesses as discussed in 09/794,224. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>-->
 [0032] As with all embodiments herein, the illustrated layers are preferably deposited/formed via sputtering (see the Examples in the 09/794,224 application), although other deposition techniques may certainly be used in alternative embodiments of this invention.</p><p num="p0055">EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 2 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0056">[0033] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 2 embodiment, which are to be compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. Thus, the CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. For the simulation examples herein, the following indices of refraction were assumed at 550 nm: for glass, n=1.51; for Si<sub>3</sub>N , n=2.0; for SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>, n=1.72; for Si0<sub>2</sub>, n=1.45; for SnO<sub>2</sub>, n=2.0; for Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>, n=2.33; for SiZrN<sub>x</sub>, n=2.32; and for Ti0<sub>2</sub>, n=2.57 (note: approximately stoichiometric titanium oxide was assumed in all simulations herein). The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for the Example(s) and CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form. All glass substrates were the same with respect to thickness and color. The total dielectric parameter simply adds up the total thickness of all dielectric layers in the coating (i.e., does not include Ag or NiCrO<sub>x</sub> layers).</p><p num="p0057">[0034] It is noted that the examples and comparative examples (CEs) herein utilized more oxided NiCrO<sub>x</sub> layers than did the examples in the 09/794,224 application (this explains why the comparative examples herein, in monolithic non- heat-treated form, have higher visible transmission than monolithic non-heat treated products in the 09/794,224). However, this distinction is not relevant because all NiCrO<sub>x</sub> layers herein were assumed to have the same amount of oxidation, so that the comparisons herein between the CEs and the Examples are consistent. It is also noted that the indices for all Ag and NiCrO<sub>x</sub> layers are assumed to be the same for all such layers in the Examples and the CEs herein. For optical performance (e.g., visible transmission), each of the parameters in the tables below is with respect to 111. C, 2 degree observer. No example herein was considered heat treated. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="10"/>-->
 FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 2 embodiment) CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0058">Glass</p><p num="p0059">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A 285A</p><p num="p0060">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A oA</p><p num="p0061">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0062">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0063">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0064">TiO<sub>2</sub> OA 615A</p><p num="p0065">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 7A</p><p num="p0066">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165 A oA</p><p num="p0067">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A lδA</p><p num="p0068">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0069">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0070">TiO<sub>2</sub> OA 230A</p><p num="p0071">SnO<sub>2</sub> 227A 45A</p><p num="p0072">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A OA</p><p num="p0073">SiOχN<sub>y</sub> oλ oA</p><p num="p0074">SiO<sub>2</sub> OA 380A</p><p num="p0075">Total diel: 1606 A 1562 A</p><p num="p0076">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 2 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0077">Tvis a*<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> iass side ( ) a*<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfiimside ( ) a*<sub>f</sub> b*f Ex. 1: 79.2% -0.7 -0.8 4.7% 4.6 -4.9 3.8% 3.3 -2.3</p><p num="p0078">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0 
<!-- EPO <DP n="11"/>-->
 [0035] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 2 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased transmission T<sub>V</sub>i<sub>S</sub> %, 111. C, 2 deg.), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side reflection). Moreover, fairly neutral transmissive color is also provided. Surprisingly, it can be seen that the Fig. 2 embodiment provides more neutral color (e.g., transmissive a* and glass side reflective) than does the CE. In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 2) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>V</sub>i<sub>S</sub>) and better glass and or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>), and more neutral transmissive a*, glass side reflective a*, b* color than the Comparative Example (CE).</p><p num="p0079">[0036] Figure 3 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 3 embodiment differs from the Fig. 2 embodiment in that the top dielectric portion T includes only a silicon nitride layer (stoichiometric Si<sub>3</sub>N , or alternative a non-stoichiometric type of silicon nitride such as but not limited to a Si-rich type). The Fig. 3 embodiment differs from Fig. 1 (i.e., from the CE) in that (a) the bottom silicon nitride layer from Fig. 1 has been removed, (b) a titanium oxide layer has been added in the middle portion M, (c) the middle silicon nitride layer from Fig. 1 has been removed, and (d) the top tin oxide layer from Fig. 1 has been removed. As with all other embodiments herein which use titanium oxide, unless otherwise stated, the titanium oxide may be stoichiometric TiO<sub>2</sub>, or alternatively a non-stoichiometric form such as TiO1.50-1.99. Likewise, as with all other embodiments herein which use silicon nitride, unless otherwise stated the silicon nitride may be stoichiometric (Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>) or non-stoichiometric (e.g., Si-rich). The coated article of Fig. 3 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO ) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="12"/>-->
 tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silicon nitride (e.g., Si<sub>3</sub>N ) (n=1.8 to 2.0, preferably n=2.0) air (n=1.0)</p><p num="p0080">[0037] By using the silicon nitride over the top contact layer in the top dielectric portion T, and the higher index titanium oxide in the middle M and bottom B portion (diluted with the tin oxide in the middle portion M), the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, nτ&lt;xi<sub>M</sub>&lt;n<sub>B</sub>, where nτ is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T (i.e., of the silicon nitride layer in this embodiment), ΠM is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M (i.e., of the tin oxide and titanium oxide layers in this embodiment), and n<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B (i.e., of the titanium oxide layer in this embodiment). Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer (e.g. portions B and T in this Fig. 3 embodiment). By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti- reflection system of Fig. 3 enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. The term "effective" means the overall effective index n in a particular portion B, T or M, regardless of how many dielectric layers are provided therein. The anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments. The silicon nitride layer in portion T may be from about 10-900 A thick in certain example embodiments of this invention, more preferably from 20-600 A thick, and most preferably from 50-500 A thick. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="13"/>-->
 EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 3 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0081">[0038] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 3 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Examρle(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. Thus, the CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0082">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 3 embodiment) CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0083">Glass</p><p num="p0084">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A 276A</p><p num="p0085">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165 A OA</p><p num="p0086">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0087">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0088">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A o</p><p num="p0089">TiO<sub>2</sub> 0A 496A</p><p num="p0090">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 112A</p><p num="p0091">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165 A 0A</p><p num="p0092">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0093">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0094">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0095">TiO<sub>2</sub> oA 0A</p><p num="p0096">SnO<sub>2</sub> 227A 0A</p><p num="p0097">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A 420A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="14"/>-->
SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0098">SiO<sub>2</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0099">Total diel: 1606A 1304 A</p><p num="p0100">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 3 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0101">Tvis *<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> Rglass side (g) a*<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfιlm side (f) a*f b*f</p><p num="p0102">Ex. 1: 78.8% -0.8 -0.4 4.5% 3.9 -5.0 3.3% 3.3 -2.3</p><p num="p0103">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0104">[0039] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 3 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>V</sub>i<sub>s</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 3) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, the Example 1 of this embodiment also had more neutral color than the CE with respect to transmissive a*, and particularly with respect to glass side reflective a*, b*.</p><p num="p0105">[0040] Figure 4 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 4 embodiment differs from the Fig. 2 embodiment in that an additional silicon nitride layer has been added in the bottom dielectric portion B between the lower contact layer and the titanium oxide layer. The term "between" as used herein to state that a layer(s) is "between" layers x and y does not mean that the layer(s) contacts layer x or layer y; it merely means that the layer(s) is between the layers x and y regardless of whether other layer(s) are also between layers x and y. The coated article of Fig. 4 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) silicon nitride (e.g., Si<sub>3</sub>N ) (n=1.8 to 2.0, preferably n=2.0) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="15"/>-->
 nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) tin oxide (e.g., Sn0<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) silicon oxide (e.g., Si0<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.4 to 1.7, preferably n=1.45) air (n= 1.0)</p><p num="p0106">[0041] By using the silicon oxide, tin oxide, titanium oxide and silicon nitride dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, nχ&lt;n<sub>M</sub>&lt;n<sub>B</sub>, where n is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, n^ is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and Π<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="16"/>-->
 EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 4 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0107">[0042] The Tables below illustrate Examples 1-4 of the Fig. 4 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Examρle(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. Thus, the CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Examples 1-4 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0108">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 4 embodiment) CE Ex. 1 Ex. 2 Ex. 3 Ex. 4</p><p num="p0109">Glass</p><p num="p0110">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A 125A 269A 230 A 125 A</p><p num="p0111">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A 199A 54A 60 A 198 A</p><p num="p0112">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A 18A 18 A 18 A</p><p num="p0113">Ag 98A 98A 98 A 98 A 98 A</p><p num="p0114">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A 16 A 16 A 16 A</p><p num="p0115">TiO<sub>2</sub> 0A 481A 219 A 120 A 120 A</p><p num="p0116">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 113A 710 A 837 A 782 A</p><p num="p0117">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A OA 0 A O A O A</p><p num="p0118">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A 18 A 18 A 18 A 
<img id="imgf000016_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="124" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000016_0001.tif" inline="no" he="6"/></p><p num="p0119">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A 16 A 16 A 16 A</p><p num="p0120">TiO<sub>2</sub> OA 210A 181 A 190 A 190 A</p><p num="p0121">SnO<sub>2</sub> 227A 34A 32 A 32 A 10 A o</p><p num="p0122">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A 0A O A O A o A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="17"/>-->
 SiO<sub>x</sub>Ny 0A OA O A O A O A</p><p num="p0123">SiO<sub>2</sub> ■ 0A 404A 334 A 373 A 435 A</p><p num="p0124">Total diel: 1606 A 1566A 1799 A 1842 A 1860 A</p><p num="p0125">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 4 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0126">T<sub>v</sub>is a*<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> Rglassside(g) *<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfilmside (f) a*<sub>f</sub> b*<sub>f</sub></p><p num="p0127">Ex. 1: 78.3% -1.5 -0.1 5.0% 9.1 -7.1 3.9% 3.8 -2.4</p><p num="p0128">Ex. 2: 78.2% -1.7 0.9 4.5% 7.6 -11.9 4.1% 0.6 -3.5</p><p num="p0129">Ex. 3: 78.1% -1.6 0.6 4.5% 5.1 -9.4 4.0% 2.3 -3.0</p><p num="p0130">Ex. 4: 77.8% -2.1 1.2 4.5% 9.2 -12.4 3.9% 3.9 -2.4</p><p num="p0131">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0132">[0043] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 4 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>S</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Examples 1-4 (see Fig. 4) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Fairly neutral color was also achieved in the Example(s).</p><p num="p0133"><sup>'</sup> [0044] Figure 5 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 5 embodiment differs from the Fig. 3 embodiment in that an additional silicon nitride layer has been added in the bottom dielectric portion B between the lower contact layer and the titanium oxide layer, and a silicon oxide layer has been added over the silicon nitride layer in the top dielectric portion T. The coated article of Fig. 5 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="18"/>-->
 silicon nitride (e.g., Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.0, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silicon nitride (e.g., Si<sub>3</sub>N ) (n=1.8 to 2.0, preferably n=2.0) silicon oxide (e.g., Si0<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.4 to 1.7, preferably n=1.45) air (n=1.0)</p><p num="p0134">[0045] By using the silicon oxide, tin oxide, titanium oxide and silicon nitride dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than or equal to that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, where nr is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion</p><p num="p0135">T, nji is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and ns is the effective index of refraction of, the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="19"/>-->
 EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 5 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0136">[0046] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 5 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0137">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 5 embodiment)</p><p num="p0138">CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0139">Glass</p><p num="p0140">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A 125A</p><p num="p0141">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A 196 A</p><p num="p0142">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0143">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0144">NiCrOx 16A 16A</p><p num="p0145">TiO<sub>2</sub> 0A 488A</p><p num="p0146">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 91A o</p><p num="p0147">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A 0A</p><p num="p0148">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0149">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0150">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A o</p><p num="p0151">TiO<sub>2</sub> 0A 0A</p><p num="p0152">SnO<sub>2</sub> ink oA</p><p num="p0153">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A 379A o</p><p num="p0154">SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub> OA 0A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="20"/>-->
SiO<sub>2</sub> OA 147A</p><p num="p0155">Total diel: 1606A 1426 A</p><p num="p0156">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 5 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0157">T<sub>vis</sub> *<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> R<sub>g</sub>lassside(g) a*<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfilmside(f) a*<sub>f</sub> b*<sub>f</sub></p><p num="p0158">Ex. 1: 78.1% -1.5 0.0 5.0% 8.5 -6.7 3.8% 3.4 -2.5</p><p num="p0159">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0160">[0047] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 5 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>S</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 5) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>S</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had more neutral transmissive and glass side reflective color than the CE.</p><p num="p0161">[0048] Figure 6 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 6 embodiment differs from the Fig. 2 embodiment in that the upper tin oxide layer in the portion T has been removed from the Fig. 2 embodiment and an additional silicon nitride layer has been added in the bottom dielectric portion B between the lower contact layer and the titanium oxide layer. The coated article of Fig. 6 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) silicon nitride (e.g., Si<sub>3</sub>N ) (n=1.8 to 2.0, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="21"/>-->
 titanium oxide (e.g., Ti0<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) titanium oxide (e.g., Ti0<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) silicon oxide (e.g., SiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.4 to 1.7, preferably n=1.45) air (n= 1.0)</p><p num="p0162">[0049] By using the silicon oxide, tin oxide, titanium oxide and silicon nitride dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than or equal to that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, where n<sub>τ</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, n<sub>M</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and Π<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments.</p><p num="p0163">EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 6 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0164">[0050] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 6 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="22"/>-->
 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0165">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 6 embodiment)</p><p num="p0166">CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0167">Glass</p><p num="p0168">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A 125A</p><p num="p0169">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A 20lA</p><p num="p0170">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0171">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0172">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A o</p><p num="p0173">TiO<sub>2</sub> OA 477A o</p><p num="p0174">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 71A</p><p num="p0175">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A oA</p><p num="p0176">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0177">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0178">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0179">TiO<sub>2</sub> OA 195A</p><p num="p0180">SnO<sub>2</sub> 227A OA o</p><p num="p0181">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A OA</p><p num="p0182">SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub> OA oA</p><p num="p0183">SiO<sub>2</sub> OA 509A</p><p num="p0184">Total diel: 1606A 1578 A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="23"/>-->
SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 6 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0185">T<sub>v</sub>is a*<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> Rglass side (g) a*<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfilmside (f) a*<sub>f</sub> b*f</p><p num="p0186">Ex. 1: 78.1% -1.1 -0.3 4.9% 4.7 -2.6 3.4% 2.0 -4.7</p><p num="p0187">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0188">[0051] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 6 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>V</sub>i<sub>S</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 6) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub>) and better glass and or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had more neutral transmissive and glass side reflective color than the CE.</p><p num="p0189">[0052] Figure 7 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 7 embodiment differs from the Fig. 2 embodiment in that the upper titanium oxide layer from the Fig. 2 embodiment in portion T has been removed, and an additional silicon nitride layer has been added in Fig. 7 in the bottom dielectric portion B between the lower contact layer and the titanium oxide layer. The coated article of Fig. 7 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.I to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) silicon nitride (e.g., Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.0, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) 7 
<!-- EPO <DP n="24"/>-->
 silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) silicon oxide (e.g., SiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.4 to 1.7, preferably n= 1.45) air (n=1.0)</p><p num="p0190">[0053] By using the silicon oxide, tin oxide, titanium oxide and silicon nitride dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than or equal to that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, where Π<sub>T</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, nj<sub>v</sub>i is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and Π<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments.</p><p num="p0191">EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 7 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0192">[0054] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 7 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="25"/>-->
FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 7 embodiment) CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0193">Glass</p><p num="p0194">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A 125A</p><p num="p0195">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A 220A</p><p num="p0196">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0197">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0198">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0199">TiO<sub>2</sub> OA 17lA</p><p num="p0200">Sn0<sub>2</sub> 672A 690A o</p><p num="p0201">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A OA</p><p num="p0202">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0203">Ao- 98A 98A</p><p num="p0204">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A o</p><p num="p0205">TiO<sub>2</sub> OA oA</p><p num="p0206">SnO<sub>2</sub> 227A 307A</p><p num="p0207">Si<sub>3</sub>N 252A OA o</p><p num="p0208">SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub> OA 0A o</p><p num="p0209">SiO<sub>2</sub> OA 222A</p><p num="p0210">Total diel: 1606A 1735 A</p><p num="p0211">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 7 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0212">Tvis , *<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> Rglass side (g) a*<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfiim side (f) a*<sub>f</sub> b*f</p><p num="p0213">Ex. 1: 77.7% -2.1 1.5 4.5% 10.0 -13.7 3.7% 3.0 -2.7</p><p num="p0214">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0 
<!-- EPO <DP n="26"/>-->
 [0055] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 7 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>V</sub>i<sub>S</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 7) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had fairly neutral color.</p><p num="p0215">[0056] Figure 8 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 8 embodiment differs from the Fig. 4 embodiment in that the upper dielectric portion in the Fig. 8 embodiment includes a silicon oxynitride layer. The silicon oxynitride layer is beneficial in that its index of refraction n (at 550 nm) can be varied from 1.45 to 2.0, more preferably from 1.6 to 1.9, and most preferably from 1.65 to 1.85, in different embodiments of this invention. In this and all other silicon oxynitride inclusive embodiments herein, the silicon oxynitride layer may have a constant (or approximately constant, i.e., constant plus/minus about 5%) index of refraction n throughout its entire thickness in certain embodiments of this invention, but alternatively may be oxidation and/or nitride graded so as to have an index of refraction n which varies through the thickness of the layer (e.g., the index n may gradually decrease through the thickness of the silicon oxynitride layer moving toward the air). The coated article of Fig. 8 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) silicon nitride (e.g., Si<sub>3</sub>N ) (n=1.8 to 2.0, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) titanium oxide (e.g., TiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=2.1 to 2.7, preferably n=2.4 to 2.65) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="27"/>-->
 tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silicon oxynitride (e.g., SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>) (n=1.45-2.0, preferably n=1.6-1.9) air (n= 1.0)</p><p num="p0216">[0057] By using the silicon oxynitride, tin oxide, titanium oxide and silicon nitride dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n (e.g., n=1.72 at 550 nm, as an example of an index n of silicon oxynitride) less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than or equal to that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, where nr is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, Π<sub>M</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and Π<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air (not including the Ag or contact layers), the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments.</p><p num="p0217">EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 8 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0218">[0058] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 8 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table 
<!-- EPO <DP n="28"/>-->
 below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0219">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 8 embodiment) CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0220">Glass</p><p num="p0221">Ti0<sub>2</sub> 125A 125A</p><p num="p0222">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165 A 173A</p><p num="p0223">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0224">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0225">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0226">TiO<sub>2</sub> oA 144A</p><p num="p0227">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 665A</p><p num="p0228">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A oA</p><p num="p0229">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0230">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0231">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0232">TiO<sub>2</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0233">SnO<sub>2</sub> 227A OA</p><p num="p0234">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A OA</p><p num="p0235">SiO<sub>x</sub>Ny OA 503A</p><p num="p0236">SiO<sub>2</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0237">Total diel: 1606A 1610 A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="29"/>-->
SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 8 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0238">Tvi<sub>S</sub> a*<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> Rgiass side (g) a*<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rπim side (f) a*<sub>f</sub> b*<sub>f</sub></p><p num="p0239">Ex. 1: 76.8% -1.6 0.9 4.8% 3.1 -6.5 3.4% 3.7 -2.8</p><p num="p0240">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0241">[0059] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 8 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>V</sub>i<sub>s</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 8) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>V</sub>i<sub>S</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had more neutral glass side reflective color than the CE.</p><p num="p0242">[0060] Figure 9 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 9 embodiment differs from Fig. 1 in that (a) the bottom titanium oxide and silicon nitride layers in bottom portion B of Fig. 1 have been removed and replaced with a layer of or including silicon zirconium nitride (SiZrN), (b) the silicon nitride layer in the middle portion M of Fig. 1 has been removed, (c) a layer of or including silicon zirconium nitride has been added to the middle dielectric portion M in Fig. 9, and (d) the top silicon nitride layer in top portion T in Fig. 1 has been replaced with a layer of or including silicon oxide in Fig. 9. It is noted that the silicon zirconium nitride inclusive layers may be stoichiometric or non-stoichiometric in different embodiments<sup>'</sup> of this invention. Moreover, one or more of the silicon zirconium nitride (SiZrN) layers may be oxided, and/or may be replaced with layer(s) comprising niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> or any other suitable form). It is also noted that any of the tin oxide layers in portion(s) T and or M could be replaced with silicon nitride (e.g., stoichiometric or non-stoichiometric). The coated article of Fig. 9 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) silicon zirconium nitride (SiZrN<sub>x</sub>) (n=2.2-2.45, preferably n=2.32) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="30"/>-->
 nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO. silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silicon zirconium nitride (SiZrN<sub>x</sub>) (n=2.2-2.45, preferably n=2.32) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silicon zirconium nitride (SiZrN<sub>x</sub>) (n=2.2-2.45, preferably n=2.32) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) silicon oxide (e.g., SiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.4 to 1.7, preferably n=1.45) air (n= 1.0)</p> <p num="p0243">[0061] By using the silicon zirconium nitride, silicon oxide, and tin oxide dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, nτ&lt;n<sub>M</sub>&lt;n<sub>B</sub>, where nj is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, τiu is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and ns is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="31"/>-->
 EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 9 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0244">[0062] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 9 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0245">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 9 embodiment) CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0246">Glass</p><p num="p0247">SiZrN<sub>x</sub> 0A 352A</p> <p num="p0248">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A OA o</p> <p num="p0249">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A 0A</p> <p num="p0250">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0251">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0252">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0253">SiZrN<sub>x</sub> OA 232A</p><p num="p0254">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 680A</p><p num="p0255">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A OA</p><p num="p0256">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0257">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0258">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0259">SiZrN<sub>x</sub> 0A 125A</p><p num="p0260">Sn0<sub>2</sub> 227A 143A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="32"/>-->
Si<sub>3</sub>N 252A OA</p><p num="p0261">SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0262">Si0<sub>2</sub> OA 327A</p><p num="p0263">Total diel: 1606A 1859 A</p><p num="p0264">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 9 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0265">T<sub>VIS</sub> a*<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> Rglass side (g) *<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfilmside(f) a*f b*f</p><p num="p0266">Ex. 1: 77.4% -2.8 3.1 4.4% 7.8 -11.5 3.8% 3.3 -2.7</p><p num="p0267">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0268">[0063] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 9 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 9) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had fairly neutral color.</p><p num="p0269">[0064] Figure 10 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 10 embodiment differs from the Fig. 9 embodiment in that the upper silicon oxide and SiZrN inclusive layers in the top dielectric portion T have been removed. It is noted that the silicon zirconium nitride inclusive layers may be stoichiometric or non-stoichiometric in different embodiments of this invention. Moreover, one or more of the silicon zirconium nitride (SiZrN) layers may be oxided, and/or may be replaced with layer(s) comprising niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>Os or any other suitable form). The coated article of Fig. 10 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) silicon zirconium nitride (SiZrN<sub>x</sub>) (n=2.2-2.45, preferably n=2.32) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="33"/>-->
 nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silicon zirconium nitride (SiZrN<sub>x</sub>) (n=2.2-2.45, preferably n=2.32) tin oxide (e.g., Sn0<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) tin oxide (e.g., Sn0<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) air (n=1.0)</p><p num="p0270">[0065] By using the silicon zirconium nitride, silicon oxide, and tin oxide dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, nτ&lt;n<sub>M</sub>&lt;n<sub>B</sub>, where nx is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, Π<sub>M</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and n<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="34"/>-->
 EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 10 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0271">[0066] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 10 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0272">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 10 embodiment) CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0273">Glass o</p><p num="p0274">SiZrN<sub>x</sub> 0A 36θA</p><p num="p0275">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A 0A o</p><p num="p0276">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165 A 0A</p><p num="p0277">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0278">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0279">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0280">SiZrN<sub>x</sub> OA 24θA</p><p num="p0281">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 667A o</p><p num="p0282">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A 0A</p><p num="p0283">NiCrOx 18A 18A</p><p num="p0284">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0285">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0286">SiZrN<sub>x</sub> OA 0A</p><p num="p0287">SnO<sub>2</sub> 227A 399A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="35"/>-->
Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A OA o</p><p num="p0288">SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0289">SiO<sub>2</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0290">Total diel: 1606A 1666 A</p><p num="p0291">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 10 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0292">Tvis a*<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> Rglass side (g) a*<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfilm side (f) a*<sub>f</sub> b*<sub>f</sub></p><p num="p0293">Ex. 1: 77.3% -2.9 3.8 4.5% 9.2 -12.6 4.1% 3.2 -2.9</p><p num="p0294">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0295">[0067] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 10 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>S</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 10) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had fairly neutral transmissive color.</p><p num="p0296">[0068] <sup>'</sup> Figure 11 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 11 embodiment differs from the Fig. 10 embodiment in that the upper and middle tin oxide layers from Fig. 10 are replaced with respective layers of or including silicon nitride (stoichiometric or ion- stoichiometric). It is noted that the silicon zirconium nitride inclusive layers may be stoichiometric or non-stoichiometric in different embodiments of this invention. Moreover, one or more of the silicon zirconium nitride (SiZrN) layers may be oxided, and/or may be replaced with layer(s) comprising niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> or any other suitable form). The coated article of Fig. 11 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) silicon zirconium nitride (SiZrN<sub>x</sub>) (n=2.2-2.45, preferably n=2.32) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="36"/>-->
 nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silicon zirconium nitride (SiZrN<sub>x</sub>) (n=2.2-2.45, preferably n=2.32) silicon nitride (e.g., Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.0, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silicon nitride (e.g., Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.0, preferably n=2.0) air (n=1.0)</p><p num="p0297">[0069] By using the silicon zirconium nitride and silicon nitride dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle , dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, nτ&lt;n<sub>M</sub>&lt;n<sub>B</sub>, where n<sub>τ</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, Π<sub>M</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and Π<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="37"/>-->
 EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 11 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0298">[0070] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 11 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0299">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 11 embodiment) CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0300">Glass</p><p num="p0301">SiZrN<sub>x</sub> 0A 360A</p><p num="p0302">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A 0A</p><p num="p0303">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A oA</p><p num="p0304">NiCrOx 18A 18A</p><p num="p0305">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0306">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0307">SiZrN<sub>x</sub> 0A 229A</p><p num="p0308">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A OA</p><p num="p0309">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A 684A</p><p num="p0310">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0311">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0312">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0313">SiZrN<sub>x</sub> OA 0A</p><p num="p0314">SnO<sub>2</sub> 227A 0A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="38"/>-->
Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A 404A</p><p num="p0315">SiOχN<sub>y</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0316">Si0<sub>2</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0317">Total diel: 1606A 1677 A</p><p num="p0318">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 11 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0319">Tvis a*<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> Rglass side (g) a*<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfιlm side (f) a* b*<sub>f</sub></p><p num="p0320">Ex. 1: 77.3% -2.6 3.4 4.5% 9.0 -12.3 4.1% 3.9 -2.7</p><p num="p0321">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0322">[0071] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 11 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>V</sub>i<sub>S</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 11) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>S</sub>) and better glass and or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had fairly neutral color.</p><p num="p0323">[0072] Figure 12 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 12 embodiment differs from Fig. 1 in that (a) the bottom titanium oxide and silicon nitride layers in bottom portion B of Fig. 1 have been removed and replaced with a layer of or including niobium oxide (stoichiometric Nb<sub>2</sub>Os, or some non-stoichiometic form), (b) the silicon nitride layer in the middle portion M of Fig. 1 has been removed, (c) a layer of or including niobium oxide (stoichiometric Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>, or some non-stoichiometic form) has been added to the middle dielectric portion M in Fig. 12, and (d) the top silicon nitride layer in top portion T in Fig. 1 has been replaced with a layer of or including silicon oxide (stoichiometric or non-stoichiometric) in Fig. 12. The coated article of Fig. 12 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): 
<!-- EPO <DP n="39"/>-->
 glass (n=1.51) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) tin oxide (e.g., Sn0<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) tin oxide (e.g., Sn0<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) silicon oxide (e.g., Si0<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.4 to 1.7, preferably n=1.45) air (n= 1.0)</p><p num="p0324">[0073] By using the niobium oxide, silicon oxide, and tin oxide dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, nτ&lt;nM&lt;nB, where nr is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, Π<sub>M</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and Π<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be 
<!-- EPO <DP n="40"/>-->
 achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments.</p><p num="p0325">EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 12 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0326">[0074] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 12 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0327">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 12 embodiment) CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0328">Glass o</p><p num="p0329">NbχOy 0A 342A</p><p num="p0330">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A OA</p><p num="p0331">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A oA</p><p num="p0332">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0333">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0334">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0335">Nb<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub> OA 640A</p><p num="p0336">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 96A</p><p num="p0337">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A OA</p><p num="p0338">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A o</p><p num="p0339">A c 98A 98A</p><p num="p0340">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="41"/>-->
Nb<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub> OA 222A</p><p num="p0341">SnO<sub>2</sub> 227A 37A</p><p num="p0342">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A OA</p><p num="p0343">SiOχN<sub>y</sub> oA OA</p><p num="p0344">SiO<sub>2</sub> OA 372A</p><p num="p0345">Total diel: 1606A 1709 A</p><p num="p0346">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 12 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0347">Tvis a*<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> Rglass side (g) *<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfilm side (f) a*f b*<sub>f</sub></p><p num="p0348">Ex. 1: 78.5% -1.3 -0.3 4.6% 8.2 -8.6 4.0% 3.7 -2.4</p><p num="p0349">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0350">[0075] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 12 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 12) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>V</sub>i<sub>s</sub>) and better glass and or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had more neutral transmissive and glass side reflective color than the CE.</p><p num="p0351">[0076] Figure 13 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 13 embodiment differs from the Fig. 12 embodiment in that the top silicon oxide and niobium oxide layers in top dielectric portion T of Fig. 12 have been removed. The coated article of Fig. 13 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="42"/>-->
 silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) air (n=1.0)</p><p num="p0352">[0077] By using the niobium oxide and tin oxide dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, nτ&lt;nM&lt;nβ, where np is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, Π<sub>M</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and Π<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, ' the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments.</p><p num="p0353">EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 13 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0354">[0078] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 13 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="43"/>-->
 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0355">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 13 embodiment)</p><p num="p0356">CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0357">Glass</p><p num="p0358">Nb<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub> OA 347A</p><p num="p0359">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A OA</p><p num="p0360">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A OA</p><p num="p0361">NiCrOx 18A 18A</p><p num="p0362">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0363">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0364">Nb<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub> OA 639A</p><p num="p0365">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 90A</p><p num="p0366">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A OA</p><p num="p0367">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0368">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0369">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A o</p><p num="p0370">Nb<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0371">SnO<sub>2</sub> 227A 428A</p><p num="p0372">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A OA o</p><p num="p0373">SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0374">SiO<sub>2</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0375">Total diel: 1606 A 1504 A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="44"/>-->
SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 13 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0376">Tvis *<sub>t</sub> b*t Rglass side (g) a*<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfilm side (f) a*<sub>f</sub> b*f</p><p num="p0377">Ex. 1: 78.4% -1.5 0.1 4.6% 9.0 -9.9 4.1% 3.2 -2.6</p><p num="p0378">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0379">[0079] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 13 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 13) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>V</sub>j<sub>s</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had more neutral transmissive and glass side reflective color than the CE.</p><p num="p0380">[0080] Figure 14 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 14 embodiment differs from the Fig. 13 embodiment in that the top tin oxide layer of Fig. 13 has been replaced with a silicon nitride inclusive layer in Fig. 14. The coated article of Fig. 14 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="45"/>-->
 silicon nitride (e.g., Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.0, preferably n=2.0) air (n= 1.0)</p><p num="p0381">[0081] By using the niobium oxide, silicon nitride, and tin oxide dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle! dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, nτ&lt;n<sub>M</sub>&lt;nB, where 
<img id="imgf000045_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="5" img-format="tif" img-content="drawing" file="imgf000045_0001.tif" inline="no" he="4"/>
 is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, Π<sub>M</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and ΪI<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments.</p><p num="p0382">EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 14 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0383">[0082] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 14 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="46"/>-->
FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 14 embodiment)</p><p num="p0384">CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0385">Glass</p><p num="p0386">Nb<sub>x</sub>Oy OA 344A</p><p num="p0387">Ti0<sub>2</sub> 125A OA</p><p num="p0388">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A . OA</p><p num="p0389">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0390">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0391">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A o</p><p num="p0392">Nb<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub> OA 641A</p><p num="p0393">Sn0<sub>2</sub> 612k 89A</p><p num="p0394">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A OA</p><p num="p0395">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0396">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0397">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A 16A</p><p num="p0398">NbχO<sub>y</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0399">Sn0<sub>2</sub> ink o</p><p num="p0400">OA</p><p num="p0401">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> • 252A , 428A</p><p num="p0402">SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0403">SiO<sub>2</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0404">Total diel: 1606A 1502 A</p><p num="p0405">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 14 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0406">T<sub>v</sub>is a*<sub>t</sub> b*t Rglassside (g) a*<sub>g</sub> b*„ Rf,lmside(f) <sup>β</sup>*f b*f</p><p num="p0407">Ex. 1: 78.3% -1.4 0.0 4.6% 8.7 -9.3 4.1% 3.4 -2.5 
<!-- EPO <DP n="47"/>-->
CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0408">[0083] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 14 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>V</sub>i<sub>S</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 14) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>V1S</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had more neutral transmissive and glass side reflective color than the CE.</p><p num="p0409">[0084] Figure 15 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 15 embodiment differs from the Fig. 12 embodiment in that the two upper nickel chrome oxide contact layers have been removed from the Fig. 12 embodiment. The coated article of Fig. 15 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) silicon oxide (e.g., SiO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.4 to 1.7, preferably n=1.45) air (n= 1.0)</p><p num="p0410">[0085] By using the niobium oxide, silicon oxide, and tin oxide dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top 
<!-- EPO <DP n="48"/>-->
 dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, nτ&lt;nM&lt;nB, where n<sub>τ</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, Π<sub>M</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and n<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti -reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments.</p><p num="p0411">EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 15 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0412">[0086] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 15 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0413">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 15 embodiment)</p><p num="p0414">CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0415">Glass</p><p num="p0416">NbχO<sub>y</sub> 0A 337A o</p><p num="p0417">Ti0<sub>2</sub> 125A 0A</p><p num="p0418">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A 0A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="49"/>-->
NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0419">A°- 98A 98A</p><p num="p0420">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A OA</p><p num="p0421">NbxOy OA 564A</p><p num="p0422">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 169A</p><p num="p0423">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A OA</p><p num="p0424">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0425">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0426">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A oA</p><p num="p0427">Nb<sub>x</sub>Oy OA 209A</p><p num="p0428">Sn0<sub>2</sub> 227A 5θA</p><p num="p0429">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A oA</p><p num="p0430">SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub> oA oA</p><p num="p0431">SiO<sub>2</sub> oA 379A</p><p num="p0432">Total diel: 1606A 1708 A</p><p num="p0433">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 15 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0434">Tvis a*<sub>t</sub> . b*<sub>t</sub> R<sub>g</sub>lass side (g) a*<sub>g</sub><sup>.</sup> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfilm side (f) a*<sub>f</sub> b*<sub>f</sub></p><p num="p0435">Ex. 1: 82.1% -1.1 -0.8 4.5% 4.0 -3.9 3.8% . 1.4 -1.8</p><p num="p0436">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0437">[0087] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 15 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>v</sub>;<sub>s</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 15) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or . 
<!-- EPO <DP n="50"/>-->
R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had more neutral color than the CE.</p><p num="p0438">[0088] Figure 16 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 16 embodiment differs from the Fig. 15 embodiment in that the upper silicon oxide and tin oxide layers in top dielectric portion T have been replaced with a layer of or including silicon oxynitride. The coated article of Fig. 16 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>Os) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) silicon oxynitride (e.g., SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>) (n=1.45-2.0, preferably n=1.6-1.9) air (n=1.0)</p><p num="p0439">[0089] By using the niobium oxide, silicon oxynitride, and tin oxide dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, nχ&lt;nM&lt;n<sub>B</sub>, where nx is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, n<sub>M</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and Π<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different 
<!-- EPO <DP n="51"/>-->
dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments. The silicon oxynitride layer is beneficial in that its index of refraction n (at 550 nm) can be varied from 1.45 to 2.0, more preferably from 1.6 to 1.9, and most preferably from 1.65 to 1.85, in different embodiments of this invention. In this and all other silicon oxynitride inclusive embodiments herein, the silicon oxynitride layer may have a constant (or approximately constant, i.e., constant plus/minus about 5%) index of refraction n throughout its entire thickness in certain embodiments of this invention, but alternatively may be oxidation and/or nitride graded so as to have an index of refraction n which varies through the thickness of the layer (e.g., the index n may gradually decrease through the thickness of the silicon oxynitride layer moving toward the air).</p><p num="p0440">EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 16 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0441">[0090] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 16 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0442">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 16 embodiment)</p><p num="p0443">CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0444">Glass</p><p num="p0445">Nb<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub> 0A 342A 
<!-- EPO <DP n="52"/>-->
Ti0<sub>2</sub> 125A OA</p><p num="p0446">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A OA</p><p num="p0447">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0448">A°- 98A 98A</p><p num="p0449">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A OA</p><p num="p0450">NbχOy oA 554A</p><p num="p0451">Sn0<sub>2</sub> 672A 188A</p><p num="p0452">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A OA</p><p num="p0453">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0454">98A 98A</p><p num="p0455">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A OA</p><p num="p0456">Nb<sub>x</sub>Oy 0A 182 A</p><p num="p0457">Sn0<sub>2</sub> ink oA</p><p num="p0458">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A OA</p><p num="p0459">SiO<sub>x</sub>Ny OA 336A</p><p num="p0460">Si0<sub>2</sub> OA OA</p><p num="p0461">Total diel: 1606A 1602 A</p><p num="p0462">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 16 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0463">Tvis a*<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> Rglass side (g) &amp;*<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfilrn side (f) a*f b*f</p><p num="p0464">Ex. 1: 82.0% -1.1 -0.7 4.6% 4.5 -4.6 3.9% 1.5 -1.8</p><p num="p0465">CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0466">[0091] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 16 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>v</sub>j<sub>S</sub></p><p num="p0467">%), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side 
<!-- EPO <DP n="53"/>-->
visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 16) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Surprisingly, Example 1 also had more neutral color than the CE (especially glass side reflective color).</p><p num="p0468">[0092] Figure 17 is a cross sectional view of a coated article according to another embodiment of this invention. The Fig. 17 embodiment differs from the Fig. 14 embodiment in that an additional niobium oxide layer has been added to the top dielectric portion T, and the two top contact layers were NiCr (i.e. not significantly oxided). The coated article of Fig. 17 includes from the glass substrate outwardly (all indices n at 550 nm): glass (n=1.51) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium (NiCr) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) tin oxide (e.g., SnO<sub>2</sub>) (n=1.8 to 2.2, preferably n=2.0) nickel-chromium-oxide (NiCrO<sub>x</sub>) silver (Ag) nickel-chromium (NiCr) niobium oxide (e.g., Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) (n=2.25-2.5, preferably n=2.33) silicon nitride (e.g., Si<sub>3</sub>N ) (n=1.8 to 2.0, preferably n=2.0) air (n= 1.0)</p><p num="p0469">[0093] By using the niobium oxide, silicon nitride, and tin oxide dielectric layers as shown in this embodiment, the layer system can be characterized by the top dielectric portion T having an effective index of refraction n less than or equal to that of middle dielectric portion M, which in turn has an effective index of refraction n less than or equal to that of the bottom dielectric portion B. In other words, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="54"/>-->
 where nr is the effective index of refraction of the top dielectric portion T, Π<sub>M</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the middle dielectric portion M, and n<sub>B</sub> is the effective index of refraction of the bottom dielectric portion B. Each of the top, middle and bottom dielectric portions T, M and B, respectively, can include a plurality of different dielectric layers, although in alternative embodiments any or all of these portions need only include a single dielectric layer. By gradually decreasing the respective effective indices of refraction "n" from the innermost or bottom dielectric portion B, to the middle dielectric portion M, and on to the top dielectric portion T toward the air, the anti-reflection system of this embodiment enables increased visible transmission to be achieved. Surprisingly, the anti-reflection system may also enable fairly neutral color of the coated article in certain example embodiments. While the two upper contact layers were NiCr (not significantly oxided) in this embodiment,<sup>1</sup> it will be recognized by those skilled in the art that in other embodiments of this invention these NiCr contact layers may be nitrided.</p><p num="p0470">EXAMPLE(S) OF FIG. 17 EMBODIMENT</p><p num="p0471">[0094] The Tables below illustrate Example 1 of the Fig. 17 embodiment, compared to a Comparative Example(s) (CE) similar to Fig. 1 of the instant application. The CE relates to a coating that is similar to that illustrated in the 09/794,224 application. The thicknesses for each of the layers in the First Table below are in angstroms (A). The Second Table below sets forth the optical characteristics (e.g., visible transmission, color, etc.) for Example 1 and the CE based upon being annealed and in monolithic form.</p><p num="p0472">FIRST TABLE: LAYER STRUCTURE - thicknesses (Fig. 17 embodiment)</p><p num="p0473">CE Ex. 1</p><p num="p0474">Glass</p><p num="p0475">Nb<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub> 0A 346A</p><p num="p0476">TiO<sub>2</sub> 125A oA</p><p num="p0477">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A oA 
<!-- EPO <DP n="55"/>-->
NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0478">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0479">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 16A OA o o</p><p num="p0480">NiCr 0A 3A</p><p num="p0481">NbχO<sub>y</sub> OA 652A</p><p num="p0482">SnO<sub>2</sub> 672A 108A o</p><p num="p0483">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 165A OA</p><p num="p0484">NiCrO<sub>x</sub> 18A 18A</p><p num="p0485">Ag 98A 98A</p><p num="p0486">NiCrOx 16A OA o</p><p num="p0487">NiCr OA 3A</p><p num="p0488">Nb<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub> oA 88A</p><p num="p0489">SnO<sub>2</sub> ink OA</p><p num="p0490">Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> 252A 35θA o o</p><p num="p0491">SiOχN<sub>y</sub> OA OA o</p><p num="p0492">SiO<sub>2</sub> oA OA</p><p num="p0493">Total diel: 1606A 1544 A</p><p num="p0494">SECOND TABLE: OPTICAL PERFORMANCE (Fig. 17 embodiment; monolithic)</p><p num="p0495">Tvis a*<sub>t</sub> b*<sub>t</sub> Rglass side (g) a*<sub>g</sub> b*<sub>g</sub> Rfilm side (f a*<sub>f</sub> b*<sub>f</sub></p><p num="p0496">Ex. 1: 77.3% -1.8 -0.8 4.7% 10.3 -10.7 4.4% 4.1 -2.8 CE: 75.5% -2.1 0.2 5.9% 9.2 -10.6 5.2% 3.2 -1.0</p><p num="p0497">[0095] It can be seen from the Tables above regarding the Fig. 17 embodiment of this invention, that the anti-reflection system of the instant invention enables not 
<!-- EPO <DP n="56"/>-->
 only better visible transmission characteristics (i.e., increased visible transmission T<sub>v</sub>i<sub>s</sub> %), but also reduced reflection (e.g., lower glass side reflection and/or film side visible reflection). In particular, Example 1 (see Fig. 17) had better visible transmission (higher T<sub>V</sub>i<sub>S</sub>) and better glass and/or film side reflection (lower R<sub>g</sub> and/or R<sub>f</sub>) than the Comparative Example (CE - see Fig. 1). Fairly neutral transmissive color was also provided in Example 1.</p><p num="p0498">[0096] Accordingly, coated articles of certain example embodiments of this invention are characterized by one or more of the following parameters:</p><p num="p0499">Characteristic General More Preferred Most Preferred</p><p num="p0500">Tvis (HI- C 2 deg.): &gt;= 70% &gt;= 75% &gt;=76.5%</p><p num="p0501">R<sub>g</sub>Y (111. C, 2 deg.): &lt;= 11% &lt;= 9% &lt;=5.0%</p><p num="p0502">R<sub>f</sub>Y (111. C; 2 deg.): &lt;= 11% &lt;= 9% &lt;=5.0%</p><p num="p0503">T<sub>S</sub>oi<sub>ar</sub>: &lt;= 50 % &lt;= 48 %</p><p num="p0504">[0097] While the invention has been described in connection with what is presently considered to be the most practical and preferred embodiment, it is to be understood that the invention is not to be limited to the disclosed embodiment, but on the contrary, is intended to cover various modifications and equivalent arrangements included within the spirit and scope of the appended claims. For example and without limitation, materials other than those described above may be used in other embodiments of this invention without departing from the spirit of this invention. For example and without limitation, silicon oxide layers may be at least partially nitrided in certain embodiments, and silicon nitride layers may be at least partially oxided in certain embodiments. 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="57"/>--><claim-text/><claim-text>CLAIMS:</claim-text><claim-text>1. A coated article including a coating supported by a glass substrate, the coating comprising: first and second infrared (ER) reflecting layers comprising silver (Ag); a first dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide provided between the first IR reflecting layer and the glass substrate; a second dielectric layer having an index of refraction 1.8 &lt;= n &lt;= 2.2 provided between the first and second IR reflecting layers, wherein the second dielectric layer has an index of refraction n less than the index of refraction n of the first dielectric layer; a third dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide provided over the first and second IR reflecting layers; a fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxide provided over the third dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide; and wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 70%.</claim-text><claim-text>2. The coated article of claim 1, wherein the second dielectric layer comprises tin oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>3. The coated article of claim 1, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide located between the first and second ER reflecting layers.</claim-text><claim-text>4. The coated article of claim 3, wherein the another dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide is located under the second dielectric layer. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="58"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>5. The coated article of claim 3, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising tin oxide located between the third dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide and the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>6. The coated article of claim 1, wherein each of the first and second IR reflecting layers comprising Ag is sandwiched between and contacts a pair of contact layers, and wherein at least one of the contact layers adjacent each IR reflecting layer comprises at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub>, and NiCrN<sub>x</sub>.</claim-text><claim-text>7. The coated article of claim 3, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising silicon nitride located between the first dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide and the first IR reflecting layer comprising Ag.</claim-text><claim-text>8. The coated article of claim 1, wherein the first dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide includes TiO<sub>2</sub>, and wherein the silicon oxide comprises SiO<sub>2</sub>.</claim-text><claim-text>9. The coated article of claim 3, wherein the coated article is characterized by a visible transmission of at least 75%, a sheet resistance (R<sub>s</sub>) of no greater than 10 ohms/square, and a glass side visible reflectance &lt;=9%.</claim-text><claim-text>10. The coated article of claim 3, wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 76.5%.</claim-text><claim-text>11. An IG window unit comprising the coated article of claim 1.</claim-text><claim-text>12. A coated article including a coating supported by a glass substrate, the coating comprising: 
<!-- EPO <DP n="59"/>-->
 first and second infrared (ER) reflecting layers each comprising at least one of silver (Ag) and gold (Au); a first dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide provided between the first IR reflecting layer and the glass substrate; a second dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide provided between the first and second ER reflecting layers; a third dielectric layer having an index of refraction 1.8 &lt;= n &lt;= 2.2 provided between the first and second ER reflecting layers, wherein the third dielectric layer has an index of refraction n less than the index of refraction n of at least one of the first and second dielectric layers; a fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxide provided over the first and second ER reflecting layers; and wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 70%.</claim-text><claim-text>13. The coated article of claim 12, wherein the third dielectric layer comprises tin oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>14. The coated article of claim 12, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising silicon nitride provided between the second TR reflecting layer and the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>15. The coated article of claim 12, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide provided between the second ER reflecting layer and the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>16. The coated article of claim 12, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising tin oxide provided between the second ER reflecting layer and the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxide. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="60"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>17. The coated article of claim 12, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising silicon nitride located between the first dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide and the first ER reflecting layer.</claim-text><claim-text>18. The coated article of claim 12, wherein each of the first and second TR reflecting layers comprises Ag and is sandwiched between and contacts a pair of contact layers, and wherein at least one of the contact layers adjacent each ER reflecting layer comprises at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub>, and NiCrN<sub>x</sub>.</claim-text><claim-text>19. The coated article of claim 12, wherein the first and second dielectric layers comprising titanium oxide each include TiO<sub>2</sub>.</claim-text><claim-text>20. The coated article of claim 12, wherein the coated article is further characterized by a visible transmission of at least 75%, a sheet resistance (R<sub>s</sub>) of no greater than 10 ohms/square, and a glass side visible reflectance &lt;=9%.</claim-text><claim-text>21. The coated article of claim 20, wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 76.5%.</claim-text><claim-text>22. A window comprising the coated article of claim 12.</claim-text><claim-text>23. A coated article including a coating supported by a glass substrate, the coating comprising: first and second infrared (ER) reflecting layers each comprising at least one of silver (Ag) and gold (Au); a first dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide provided between the first ER reflecting layer and the glass substrate; a second dielectric layer comprising titanium oxide provided between the first and second ER reflecting layers; 
<!-- EPO <DP n="61"/>-->
 a third dielectric layer having an index of refraction 1.8 &lt;= n &lt;= 2.2 provided between the first and second TR reflecting layers, wherein the third dielectric layer has an index of refraction n less than the index of refraction n of at least one of the first and second dielectric layers; a fourth dielectric layer comprising at least one of silicon nitride and silicon oxynitride provided over the first and second ER reflecting layers; and wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 70%.</claim-text><claim-text>24. The coated article of claim 23, wherein the fourth dielectric layer comprises silicon oxynitride.</claim-text><claim-text>25. The coated article of claim 24, wherein the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxynitride is at least one of oxidation graded and nitrogen graded, so that an index of refraction n of the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxynitride changes from a first value in a first portion of the fourth dielectric layer to a smaller second value in a second portion of the fourth dielectric layer, wherein the second portion of the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxynitride with the smaller index of refraction n is further from the ER reflecting layers than is the first portion of the fourth dielectric layer.</claim-text><claim-text>26. A coated article including a coating supported by a glass substrate, the coating comprising, from the glass substrate outwardly: a first dielectric layer comprising silicon zirconium nitride; a first contact layer comprising at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub> and NiCrN<sub>x</sub>; a first ER reflecting layer comprising Ag; a second contact layer comprising at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub> and NiCrN<sub>x</sub>; a second dielectric layer comprising silicon zirconium nitride; 
<!-- EPO <DP n="62"/>-->
 a third dielectric layer having an index of refraction n less than an index of refraction n of at least one of the first and second dielectric layers; a third contact layer comprising at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub> and NiCrN<sub>x</sub>; a second IR reflecting layer comprising Ag; a fourth contact layer comprising at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub> and NiCrN<sub>x</sub>; a fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxide; and wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 70% and a sheet resistance (R<sub>s</sub>) of no greater than 10 ohms/square.</claim-text><claim-text>27. The coated article of claim 26, wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 75%.</claim-text><claim-text>28. The coated article of claim 26, wherein the third dielectric layer comprises tin oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>29. The coated article of claim 28, wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 76.5%.</claim-text><claim-text>30. The coated article of claim 26, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising tin oxide provided between the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxide and the fourth contact layer.</claim-text><claim-text>31. The coated article of claim 30, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising silicon zirconium nitride provided between the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxide and the second IR reflecting layer. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="63"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>32. A coated article including a coating supported by a glass substrate, the coating comprising, from the glass substrate outwardly: a first dielectric layer comprising silicon zirconium nitride; a contact layer comprising at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub> and NiCrN<sub>x</sub>; a first IR reflecting layer comprising Ag; a second dielectric layer comprising silicon zirconium nitride; a third dielectric layer having an index of refraction n less than an index of refraction of at least one of the first and second dielectric layers; a contact layer comprising at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub> and NiCrN<sub>x</sub>; a second ER reflecting layer comprising Ag; a fourth dielectric layer comprising at least one of tin oxide and silicon nitride; and wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 70% and a sheet resistance (R<sub>s</sub>) of no greater than 10 ohms/square.</claim-text><claim-text>33. The coated article of claim 32, wherein the third dielectric layer comprises one of silicon nitride and tin oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>34. The coated article of claim 32, wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 75%.</claim-text><claim-text>35. A coated article including a coating supported by a glass substrate, the coating comprising, from the glass substrate outwardly: a first dielectric layer comprising niobium oxide; a contact layer comprising at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub> and NiCrN<sub>x</sub>; a first ER reflecting layer comprising Ag; a second dielectric layer comprising niobium oxide; a third dielectric layer having an index of refraction n less than an index of refraction of at least one of the first and second dielectric layers; a contact layer comprising at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub> and NiCrN<sub>x</sub>; 
<!-- EPO <DP n="64"/>-->
 a second IR reflecting layer comprising Ag; a fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxide; and wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 70% and a sheet resistance (R<sub>s</sub>) of no greater than 10 ohms/square.</claim-text><claim-text>36. The coated article of claim 35, wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 75%, and neutral transmissive and/or glass side reflective color.</claim-text><claim-text>37. The coated article of claim 35, wherein the third dielectric layer comprises tin oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>38. The coated article of claim 35, wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 76.5%.</claim-text><claim-text>39. The coated article of claim 35, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising tin oxide provided between the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxide and the second ER reflecting layer.</claim-text><claim-text>40. The coated article of claim 39, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising niobium oxide provided between the another dielectric layer comprising tin oxide and the second IR reflecting layer.</claim-text><claim-text>41. The coated article of claim 35, further comprising a contact layer comprising at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub> and NiCrN<sub>x</sub> provided directly above and in contact with at least one of the ER reflecting layers. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="65"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>42. The coated articles of claim 35, wherein each of the dielectric layers comprising niobium oxide includes ND2O5.</claim-text><claim-text>43. A coated article including a coating supported by a glass substrate, the coating comprising, from the glass substrate outwardly: a first dielectric layer comprising niobium oxide; a first ER reflecting layer comprising at least one of Ag and Au; a second dielectric layer comprising niobium oxide; a third dielectric layer having an index of refraction n less than an index of refraction of at least one of the first and second dielectric layers; a second ER reflecting layer comprising Ag; a fourth dielectric layer comprising at least one of tin oxide and silicon nitride; and wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 70% and a sheet resistance (R<sub>s</sub>) of no greater than 10 ohms/square.</claim-text><claim-text>44. The coated article of claim 43, further comprising a contact layer including at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub> and NiCrN<sub>x</sub> provided directly in contact with at least one of said ER reflecting layers.</claim-text><claim-text>45. A coated article including a coating supported by a glass substrate, the coating comprising, from the glass substrate outwardly: a first dielectric layer comprising niobium oxide; a first ER reflecting layer comprising at least one of Ag and Au; a second dielectric layer comprising niobium oxide; a second ER reflecting layer comprising Ag; a third dielectric layer comprising niobium oxide; a fourth dielectric layer comprising at least one of silicon oxide, silicon oxynitride, tin oxide and silicon nitride; and 
<!-- EPO <DP n="66"/>-->
 wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 70% and a sheet resistance (R<sub>s</sub>) of no greater than 10 ohms/square.</claim-text><claim-text>46. The coated article of claim 45, further comprising a contact layer including at least one of NiCr, NiCrO<sub>x</sub> and NiCrN<sub>x</sub> provided directly in contact with at least one of said ER reflecting layers.</claim-text><claim-text>47. The coated article of claim 45, further comprising another dielectric layer comprising tin oxide located between the second ER reflecting layer and the second dielectric layer.</claim-text><claim-text>48. The coated article of claim 45, wherein the fourth dielectric layer comprises SiO<sub>2</sub>.</claim-text><claim-text>49. The coated article of claim 45, wherein the fourth dielectric layer comprises silicon oxynitride.</claim-text><claim-text>50. The coated article of claim 49, wherein the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxynitride is at least one of oxidation graded and nitrogen graded, so that an index of refraction n of the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon &gt; oxynitride changes from a first value in a first portion of the fourth dielectric layer to a smaller second value in a second portion of the fourth dielectric layer, wherein the second portion of the fourth dielectric layer comprising silicon oxynitride with the smaller index of refraction n is further from the ER reflecting layers than is the first portion of the fourth dielectric layer.</claim-text><claim-text>51. The coated article of claim 45, wherein the fourth dielectric layer comprises silicon nitride. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="67"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>52. A coated article including a coating supported by a glass substrate, the coating comprising: first and second infrared (ER) reflecting layers each comprising at least one of Ag and Au; a first dielectric portion having an effective index of refraction ni &lt;= 3.0 provided between the first ER reflecting layer and the glass substrate; a second dielectric portion having an effective index of refraction n<sub>2</sub> less than or equal to m, the second dielectric portion provided between the first and second ER reflecting layers; a third dielectric portion provided over the first and second ER reflecting layers, said third dielectric layer having an effective index of refraction n<sub>3</sub> less than ni and n , so that n<sub>3</sub> &lt; n<sub>2</sub> &lt;= ni ; and wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 70%.</claim-text><claim-text>53. The coated article of claim 52, wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 75%.</claim-text><claim-text>54. The coated article of claim 52, wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 76.5%.</claim-text><claim-text>55. The coated article of claim 52, wherein the first and second dielectric portions each comprises a layer comprising titanium oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>56. The coated article of claim 52, wherein the third dielectric portion comprises a layer comprising silicon zirconium nitride and a layer comprising silicon oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>57. The coated article of claim 52, wherein the third dielectric portion comprises a layer comprising niobium oxide and a layer comprising silicon oxide. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="68"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>58. The coated article of claim 52, wherein the second dielectric portion comprises a layer comprising tin oxide and a layer comprising one of niobium oxide and silicon zirconium nitride.</claim-text><claim-text>59. The coated article of claim 52, wherein the coated article has a visible transmission of at least 75% and a sheet resistance of no greater than 5 ohms/square.</claim-text><claim-text>60. The coated article of claim 52, wherein the coated article is an IG window unit. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>