<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1544251-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1544251" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34523250" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050622"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1544251-A1" status="new" fvid="24390984"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1544251</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050622</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04257878-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04257878</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20041216</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-74240703-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>74240703</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031219</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B65D   1/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B65D   1/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  69/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  69/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  67/02+B4K</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  69/00+B4K</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L67:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L69:00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Klare Polycarbonat Polyester Mischung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Clear polycarbonate polyester blend</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Melange de polycarbonate et de polyester transparent</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-5461120-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5461120</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2004020523-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2004020523</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>GEN ELECTRIC</last-name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1 River Road</street><city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>CHAKRABORTY MANATESH</last-name><address><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>JAYAKANNAN MANICKAM</last-name><address><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>JUIKAR VISHVAJIT CHANDRAKANT</last-name><address><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>KANNAN GANESH</last-name><address><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>SHAIKH ABBAS-ALLI GHUDUBHAI</last-name><address><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>TOTAD RAJASHEKHAR SHIDDAPPA</last-name><address><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>CHAKRABORTY, MANATESH</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>JAYAKANNAN, MANICKAM</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>JUIKAR, VISHVAJIT CHANDRAKANT</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>KANNAN, GANESH</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>SHAIKH, ABBAS-ALLI GHUDUBHAI</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>TOTAD, RAJASHEKHAR</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CHAKRABORTY, MANATESH</last-name><address><street>D 2/14 Chittaranjan Nagar P.O. Rajawadi Vidhyaviha</street><city>Mumbai Maharashtra 400 077</city><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>JAYAKANNAN, MANICKAM</last-name><address><street>13/743 Pournami Kunnukuzhy Trivandrum</street><city>Kerala 695 037</city><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>JUIKAR, VISHVAJIT CHANDRAKANT</last-name><address><street>1597, 4 Main Road E Block AECS Layout Kundanhalli</street><city>Bangalore Karnataka 560 037</city><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KANNAN, GANESH</last-name><address><street>202 Victorian Willows Airport Road</street><city>Bangalore Karnataka 560 017</city><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SHAIKH, ABBAS-ALLI GHUDUBHAI</last-name><address><street>Balagi Garden, Apt. 101 Khundalahalil Gate</street><city>Whitefield (PO) Bangalore 560 066</city><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Totad, Rajashekhar Shiddappa, 74/7 C/o VijayKumar</last-name><address><street>1st Main Laxmisagar Layout Mahadevapura Post</street><city>Bangalore Karnataka 560 048</city><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Szary, Anne Catherine, Dr.</last-name><address><street>London Patent Operation General Electric International, Inc. 15 John Adam Street</street><city>London WC2N 6LU</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country> <country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country> <country>GB</country> <country>GR</country> <country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IS</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LT</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An optically clear thermoplastic resin composition comprises structural units derived
from substituted or unsubstituted polycarbonate and substituted or unsubstituted
polyester, wherein said polyester comprises structural units derived from terephthalic
acid and a mixture of 1,4-cyclohexane dimethanol and ethylene glycol, wherein said
ethylene glycol is greater than about 60 mole percent based on total moles of 1,4-cyclohexane
dimethanol and ethylene glycol. In addition the composition disclosed
possess good environmental stress cracking resistance, flow and thermal properties.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="162"  img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="77"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep"  status="new"  lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention relates to an optically clear thermoplastic resin composition, a method
to synthesize the composition and articles made from the composition.</p><p num="0002">Polycarbonate is a useful engineering plastic for parts requiring clarity, high
toughness, and, in some cases, good heat resistance. However, polycarbonate also has
some important deficiencies, among them poor chemical and stress crack resistance,
poor resistance to sterilization by gamma radiation, and poor processability. Blends
polyesters with polycarbonates provide thermoplastic compositions having improved
properties over those based upon either of the single resins alone. Moreover, such
blends are often more cost effective than polycarbonate alone.</p><p num="0003">Transparent blends of polycarbonate (PC) and polyesters have attractive properties
such as toughness and chemical resistance. The miscibility of PC with the polyesters
gives the blends the clarity needed, but this is restricted to (semi)aliphatic polyesters
such as poly(cyclohexane dimethanol cyclohexane dicarboxylate) (PCCD) or a
glycolized copolyester such as polyethylene glycol cyclohexane dimethanol
terephthalate (PETG). PCT patent application no. WO 02/38675 discloses a
thermoplastic composition comprising PC, PCCD, and an impact modifier.</p><p num="0004">US 4,188,314, US 4,125,572; US 4,391,954; US 4,786,692; US 4,897,453, and
5,478,896 relate to blends of an aromatic polycarbonate and poly cyclohexane
dimethanol phthalate. US 4,125,572 relates to a blend of polycarbonate, polybutylene
terephthalate (PBT) and an aliphatic / cycloaliphatic iso/terephthalate resin. U.S.
Patent No. 6,281,299 discloses a process for manufacturing transparent polyester /
polycarbonate compositions, wherein the polyester is fed into the reactor after
bisphenol A is polymerized to a polycarbonate.</p><p num="0005">US 5,194,523 and US 5,207,967 describe the blending of polyester (polycyclohexane
dimethanol terephthalate, "PCT") with bisphenol-A polycarbonate to obtain blends
with improved low temperature impact strength and processability. US 4,786,692
describes a clear thermoplastic molding composition of polycarbonate with PETG
with the ethylene glycol content between 20 to 80 percent. However the patent 
requires that the said blend becomes semi transparent and opaque when the ethylene
glycol content is high at least greater than 50 percent. US 5,194,523 describes a clear
blend of polycarbonate and PETG where the amount of ethylene glycol is between 15
percent and 30 percent. The blends were synthesized using the residual catalyst
present in the polyester. U.S. 4,506,442 discloses a polycarbonate / polyester blend
and an uncatalyzed process for preparing the blend by melt reactions between PC and
polyesters for a long period of time (mixing time of up to 60 minutes).</p><p num="0006">The blends of polycarbonate with PETG having a ethylene glycol content of up to 67
percent prepared without the addition of external catalyst have been reported to be
unstable. Polycarbonate blends with PETG wherein the ethylene glycol content is
greater than 60 percent have been found to give opaque incompatible blends.</p><p num="0007">There is a continuing need for polycarbonate polyester blends having a good balance
of transparency, processability, solvent resistance and environmental stress cracking
resistance in addition to good mechanical and thermal properties.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0008">The present inventors have unexpectedly discovered that optically clear thermoplastic
resin compositions containing structural units derived from substituted or
unsubstituted polycarbonate and substituted or unsubstituted polyester, wherein said
polyester comprises structural units derived from terephthalic acid and a mixture of
1,4-cyclohexane dimethanol and ethylene glycol, wherein said ethylene glycol is
greater than about 60 mole percent based on total moles of 1,4-cyclohexane
dimethanol and ethylene glycol show excellent combinations of flow, thermal and
environmental resistance properties. Also disclosed is a synthesis method for the
optically clear thermoplastic resin compositions of the present invention and articles
derived from said compositions.</p><p num="0009">Various other features, aspects, and advantages of the present invention will become
more apparent with reference to the following description, accompanying drawings,
examples, and appended claims. </p><heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0010"><sl><li>FIG. 1 illustrates a schematic diagram of the extrusion process in the prior art.</li><li>FIG. 2 illustrates a schematic diagram of the extrusion process of the present
invention, allowing for extrusion at lower torque and specific energy consumption.</li></sl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0011">The present invention may be understood more readily by reference to the following
detailed description of preferred embodiments of the invention and the examples
included herein. In this specification and in the claims, which follow, reference will
be made to a number of terms which shall be defined to have the following meanings.</p><p num="0012">The singular forms "a", "an" and "the" include plural referents unless the context
clearly dictates otherwise.</p><p num="0013">"Optional" or "optionally" means that the subsequently described event or
circumstance may or may not occur, and that the description includes instances where
the event occurs and instances where it does not.</p><p num="0014">As used herein the term "polycarbonate" refers to polycarbonates incorporating
structural units derived from one or more dihydroxy aromatic compounds and
includes copolycarbonates and polyester</p><p num="0015">A component of the blend of the invention is an aromatic polycarbonate. The
aromatic polycarbonate resins suitable for use in the present invention, methods of
making polycarbonate resins and the use of polycarbonate resins in thermoplastic
molding compounds are well known in the art, see, generally, U.S Patent Nos.
3,169,121, 4,487,896 and 5,411,999, the respective disclosures of which are each
incorporated herein by reference.</p><p num="0016">Polycarbonates useful in the invention comprise repeating units of the formula:
<img id="img-00030001"  orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030001.tif" inline="no" he="19"/> 
wherein D<sup>1</sup> is a divalent aromatic radical derived from a dihydroxyaromatic
compound of the formula HO-D-OH, wherein D has the structure of formula:
<img id="img-00040001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/>
wherein A<sup>1</sup> represents an aromatic group including, but not limited to, phenylene,
biphenylene and naphthylene. In some embodiments E may be an alkylene or
alkylidene group including, but not limited to, methylene, ethylene, ethylidene,
propylene, propylidene, isopropylidene, butylene, butylidene, isobutylidene, amylene,
amylidene and isoamylidene. In other embodiments when E is an alkylene or
alkylidene group, it may also consist of two or more alkylene or alkylidene groups
connected by a moiety different from alkylene or alkylidene, including, but not
limited to, an aromatic linkage; a tertiary nitrogen linkage; an ether linkage; a
carbonyl linkage; a silicon-containing linkage, silane, siloxy; or a sulfur-containing
linkage including, but not limited to, sulfide, sulfoxide and sulfone; or a phosphorus-containing
linkage including, but not limited to, phosphinyl and phosphonyl. In other
embodiments E may be a cycloaliphatic group including, but not limited to,
cyclopentylidene, cyclohexylidene, 3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexylidene,
methylcyclohexylidene, 2-[2.2.1 ]-bicycloheptylidene, neopentylidene,
cyclopentadecylidene, cyclododecylidene and adamantylidene; a sulfur-containing
linkage, including, but not limited to, sulfide, sulfoxide or sulfone; a phosphorus-containing
linkage, including, but not limited to, phosphinyl or phosphonyl; an ether
linkage; a carbonyl group; a tertiary nitrogen group; or a silicon-containing linkage
including, but not limited to, silane or siloxy. R<sup>1</sup> independently at each occurrence
comprises a monovalent hydrocarbon group including, but not limited to, alkenyl,
allyl, alkyl, aryl, aralkyl, alkaryl, or cycloalkyl. In various embodiments a
monovalent hydrocarbon group of R<sup>1</sup> may be halogen-substituted, particularly fluoro- or
chloro-substituted, for example as in dichloroalkylidene, particularly
gem-dichloroalkylidene. Y<sup>1</sup> independently at each occurrence may be an inorganic atom 
including, but not limited to, halogen (fluorine, bromine, chlorine, iodine); an
inorganic group containing more than one inorganic atom including, but not limited
to, nitro; an organic group including, but not limited to, a monovalent hydrocarbon
group including, but not limited to, alkenyl, allyl, alkyl, aryl, aralkyl, alkaryl, or
cycloalkyl, or an oxy group including, but not limited to, OR<sup>2</sup> wherein R<sup>2</sup> is a
monovalent hydrocarbon group including, but not limited to, alkyl, aryl, aralkyl,
alkaryl, or cycloalkyl; it being only necessary that Y<sup>1</sup> be inert to and unaffected by the
reactants and reaction conditions used to prepare the polymer. In some particular
embodiments Y<sup>1</sup> comprises a halo group or C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> alkyl group. The letter "m"
represents any integer from and including zero through the number of replaceable
hydrogens on A<sup>1</sup> available for substitution; "p" represents an integer from and
including zero through the number of replaceable hydrogens on E available for
substitution; "t" represents an integer equal to at least one; "s" represents an integer
equal to either zero or one; and "u" represents any integer including zero.</p><p num="0017">In dihydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbons in which D is represented by formula
(II) above, when more than one Y<sup>1</sup> substituent is present, they may be the same or
different. The same holds true for the R<sup>1</sup> substituent. Where "s" is zero in formula
(II) and "u" is not zero, the aromatic rings are directly joined by a covalent bond with
no intervening alkylidene or other bridge. The positions of the hydroxyl groups and
Y<sup>1</sup> on the aromatic nuclear residues A<sup>1</sup> can be varied in the ortho, meta, or para
positions and the groupings can be in vicinal, asymmetrical or symmetrical
relationship, where two or more ring carbon atoms of the hydrocarbon residue are
substituted with Y<sup>1</sup> and hydroxyl groups. In some particular embodiments the
parameters "t", "s", and "u" each have the value of one; both A<sup>1</sup> radicals are
unsubstituted phenylene radicals; and E is an alkylidene group such as isopropylidene.
In some particular embodiments both A<sup>1</sup> radicals are p-phenylene, although both may
be o- or m-phenylene or one o- or m-phenylene and the other p-phenylene.</p><p num="0018">In some embodiments of dihydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbons E may be an
unsaturated alkylidene group. Suitable dihydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbons
of this type include those of the formula (III): <img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="47"/>
where independently each R<sup>4</sup> is hydrogen, chlorine, bromine or a C<sub>1-30</sub> monovalent
hydrocarbon or hydrocarbonoxy group, each Z is hydrogen, chlorine or bromine,
subject to the provision that at least one Z is chlorine or bromine.</p><p num="0019">Suitable dihydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbons also include those of the
formula (IV):
<img id="img-00060002" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060002.tif" inline="no" he="37"/>
where independently each R<sup>4</sup> is as defined hereinbefore, and independently R<sup>g</sup> and R<sup>h</sup>
are hydrogen or a C1-30 hydrocarbon group.</p><p num="0020">In some embodiments of the present invention, dihydroxy-substituted aromatic
hydrocarbons that may be used comprise those disclosed by name or formula (generic
or specific) in U.S. Patent Nos. 2,991,273, 2,999,835, 3,028,365, 3,148,172,
3,153,008, 3,271,367, 3,271,368, and 4,217,438. In other embodiments of the
invention, dihydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbons comprise bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)sulfide,
bis(4-hydroxyphenyl) ether, bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)sulfone,
bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)sulfoxide, 1,4-dihydroxybenzene, 4,4'-oxydiphenol, 2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)hexafluoropropane,
4,4'-(3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexylidene)diphenol;
4,4'-bis(3,5-dimethyl)diphenol, 1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-3-methylphenyl)cyclohexane; 4,4-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)heptane;
2,4'-dihydroxydiphenylmethane; bis(2-hydroxyphenyl)methane;
bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)methane; bis(4-hydroxy-5-nitrophenyl)methane;
bis(4-hydroxy-2,6-dimethyl-3-methoxyphenyl)methane; 1,1-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)ethane; 
1,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)ethane; 1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-2-chlorophenyl)ethane;
2,2-bis(3-phenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane; 2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3-methylphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3-ethylphenyl)propane; 2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3-isopropylphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3,5-dimethylphenyl)propane;
3,5,3',5'-tetrachloro-4,4'-dihydroxyphenyl)propane; bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexylmethane;
2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1-phenylpropane; 2,4'-dihydroxyphenyl
sulfone; dihydroxy naphthalene; 2,6-dihydroxy naphthalene;
hydroquinone; resorcinol; C1-3 alkyl-substituted resorcinols; methyl resorcinol,
catechol, 1,4-dihydroxy-3-methylbenzene; 2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)butane; 2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)-2-methylbutane;
1,1-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane; 4,4'-dihydroxydiphenyl;
2-(3-methyl-4-hydroxyphenyl-2-(4-hydroxyphenyl)propane; 2-(3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-2-(4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2-(3-methyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-2-(3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
bis(3,5-dimethylphenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)methane;
1,1-bis(3,5-dimethylphenyl-4-hydroxypbenyl)ethan'e; 2,2-bis(3,5-dimethylphenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,4-bis(3,5-dimethylphenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-2-methylbutane;
3,3-bis(3,5-dimethylphenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)pentane;
1,1-bis(3,5-dimethylphenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclopentane;
1,1-bis(3,5-dimethylphenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane; bis(3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)
sulfoxide, bis(3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl) sulfone and bis(3,5-dimethylphenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)sulfide.
In a particular embodiment the dihydroxy-substituted
aromatic hydrocarbon comprises bisphenol A.</p><p num="0021">In some embodiments of dihydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbons when E is an
alkylene or alkylidene group, said group may be part of one or more fused rings
attached to one or more aromatic groups bearing one hydroxy substituent. Suitable
dihydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbons of this type include those containing
indane structural units such as represented by the formula (V), which compound is 3-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1,1,3-trimethylindan-5-ol,
and by the formula (VI), which
compound is 1-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1,3,3-trimethylindan-5-ol: <img id="img-00080001" orientation="unknown" wi="97" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080001.tif" inline="no" he="43"/><img id="img-00080002" orientation="unknown" wi="97" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080002.tif" inline="no" he="44"/></p><p num="0022">Also included among suitable dihydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbons of the
type comprising one or more alkylene or alkylidene groups as part of fused rings are
the 2,2,2',2'-tetrahydro-1,1'-spirobi[1H-indene]diols having formula (VII) :
<img id="img-00080003" orientation="unknown" wi="124" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080003.tif" inline="no" he="55"/>
wherein each R<sup>6</sup> is independently selected from monovalent hydrocarbon radicals and
halogen radicals; each R<sup>7</sup>, R<sup>8</sup>, R<sup>9</sup>, and R<sup>10</sup> is independently C1-6 alkyl; each R<sup>11</sup> and
R<sup>12</sup> is independently H or C1-6 alkyl; and each n is independently selected from
positive integers having a value of from 0 to 3 inclusive. In a particular embodiment
the 2,2,2',2'-tetrahydro-1,1'-spirobi[1H-indene]diol is 2,2,2',2'-tetrahydro-3,3,3',3'-tetramethyl-1,1'-spirobi[1H-indene]-6,6'-diol
(sometimes known as "SBI"). Mixtures
of alkali metal salts derived from mixtures of any of the foregoing dihydroxy-substituted
aromatic hydrocarbons may also be employed. </p><p num="0023">The term "alkyl" as used in the various embodiments of the present invention is
intended to designate both linear alkyl, branched alkyl, aralkyl, cycloalkyl,
bicycloalkyl, tricycloalkyl and polycycloalkyl radicals containing carbon and
hydrogen atoms, and optionally containing atoms in addition to carbon and hydrogen,
for example atoms selected from Groups 15, 16 and 17 of the Periodic Table. The
term "alkyl" also encompasses that alkyl portion of alkoxide groups. In various
embodiments normal and branched alkyl radicals are those containing from 1 to about
32 carbon atoms, and include as illustrative non-limiting examples C1-C32 alkyl
optionally substituted with one or more groups selected from C1-C32 alkyl, C3-C15
cycloalkyl or aryl; and C3-C 15 cycloalkyl optionally substituted with one or more
groups selected from C1-C32 alkyl. Some particular illustrative examples comprise
methyl, ethyl, n-propyl, isopropyl, n-butyl, sec-butyl, tertiary-butyl, pentyl, neopentyl,
hexyl, heptyl, octyl, nonyl, decyl, undecyl and dodecyl. Some illustrative non-limiting
examples of cycloalkyl and bicycloalkyl radicals include cyclobutyl,
cyclopentyl, cyclohexyl, methylcyclohexyl, cycloheptyl, bicycloheptyl and
adamantyl. In various embodiments aralkyl radicals are those containing from 7 to
about 14 carbon atoms; these include, but are not limited to, benzyl, phenylbutyl,
phenylpropyl, and phenylethyl. In various embodiments aryl radicals used in the
various embodiments of the present invention are those substituted or unsubstituted
aryl radicals containing from 6 to 18 ring carbon atoms. Some illustrative non-limiting
examples of these aryl radicals include C6-C15 aryl optionally substituted
with one or more groups selected from C1-C32 alkyl, C3-C15 cycloalkyl or aryl.
Some particular illustrative examples of aryl radicals comprise substituted or
unsubstituted phenyl, biphenyl, toluyl and naphthyl.</p><p num="0024">Mixtures comprising two or more hydroxy-substituted hydrocarbons may also be
employed. In some particular embodiments mixtures of at least two monohydroxy-substituted
alkyl hydrocarbons, or mixtures of at least one monohydroxy-substituted
alkyl hydrocarbon and at least one dihydroxy-substituted alkyl hydrocarbon, or
mixtures of at least two dihydroxy-substituted alkyl hydrocarbons, or mixtures of at
least two monohydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbons, or mixtures of at least two
dihydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbons, or mixtures of at least one 
monohydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbon and at least one dihydroxy-substituted
aromatic hydrocarbon, or mixtures of at least one monohydroxy-substituted
alkyl hydrocarbon and at least one dihydroxy-substituted aromatic
hydrocarbon may be employed.</p><p num="0025">In yet another, the polycarbonate resin is a linear polycarbonate resin that is derived
from bisphenol A and phosgene. In an alternative embodiment, the polycarbonate
resin is a blend of two or more polycarbonate resins.</p><p num="0026">The aromatic polycarbonate may be prepared in the melt, in solution, or by interfacial
polymerization techniques well known in the art. For example, the aromatic
polycarbonates can be made by reacting bisphenol-A with phosgene, dibutyl
carbonate or diphenyl carbonate. Such aromatic polycarbonates are also commercially
available. In one embodiment, the aromatic polycarbonate resins are commercially
available from General Electric Company, e.g., LEXAN™ bisphenol A-type
polycarbonate resins.</p><p num="0027">The preferred polycarbonates are preferably high molecular weight aromatic
carbonate polymers have an intrinsic viscosity (as measured in methylene chloride at
25°C) ranging from about 0.30 to about 1.00. deciliters per gram. Polycarbonates
may be branched or unbranched and generally will have a weight average molecular
weight of from about 10,000 to about 200,000, preferably from about 20,000 to about
100,000 as measured by gel permeation chromatography. It is contemplated that the
polycarbonate may have various known end groups.</p><p num="0028">In one embodiment the optically clear thermoplastic composition comprises
polyesters. Methods for making polyester resins and the use of polyester resins in
thermoplastic molding compositions are known in the art. Conventional
polycondensation procedures are described in the following, see, generally, U.S.
Patent Nos. 2,465,319, 5,367,011 and 5,411,999, the respective disclosures of which
are each incorporated herein by reference.</p><p num="0029">Typically polyester resins include crystalline polyester resins such as polyester resins
derived from an aliphatic or cycloaliphatic diol, or mixtures thereof, containing from 
2 to about 10 carbon atoms and at least one aromatic dicarboxylic acid. Preferred
polyesters are derived from an aliphatic diol and an aromatic dicarboxylic acid and
have repeating units according to structural formula (VIII)
<img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="25"/>
wherein, R' is an alkyl radical compromising a dehydroxylated residue derived from
an aliphatic or cycloaliphatic diol, or mixtures thereof, containing from 2 to about 10
carbon atoms. R is an aryl radical comprising a decarboxylated residue derived from
an aromatic dicarboxylic acid.</p><p num="0030">Examples of aromatic dicarboxylic acids from which the decarboxylated residue R
may be derived are acids that contain a single aromatic ring per molecule such as,
e.g., isophthalic or terephthalic acid, 1,2-di(p-carboxyphenyl)ethane, 4,4'-dicarboxydiphenyl
ether, 4,4'- bisbenzoic acid and mixtures thereof, as well as acids
contain fused rings such as, e.g., 1,4- or 1,5-naphthalene dicarboxylic acids. In a
preferred embodiment, the dicarboxylic acid precursor of residue R is terephthalic
acid or, alternatively, a mixture of terephthalic and isophthalic acids.</p><p num="0031">Typically the polyester resin may comprise one or more resins selected from linear
polyester resins, branched polyester resins and copolymeric polyester resins. Suitable
linear polyester resins include, e.g., poly(alkylene phthalate)s such as, e.g.,
poly(ethylene terephthalate) ("PET"), poly(butylene terephthalate) ("PBT"),
poly(propylene terephthalate) ("PPT"), poly(cycloalkylene phthalate)s such as, e.g.,
poly(cyclohexanedimethanol terephthalate) ("PCT"), poly(alkylene naphthalate)s such
as, e.g., poly(butylene-2,6-naphthalate) ("PBN") and poly(ethylene-2,6-naphthalate)
("PEN"), poly(alkylene dicarboxylate)s such as, e.g., poly(butylene dicarboxylate).</p><p num="0032">In a preferred embodiment suitable copolymeric polyester resins include, e.g.,
polyesteramide copolymers, cyclohexanedimethanol-terephthalic acid-isophthalic
acid copolymers and cyclohexanedimethanol-terephthalic acid-ethylene glycol 
("PETG") copolymers. The polyester component can, without limitation, comprise
the reaction product of a glycol portion comprising 1,4- cyclohexanedimethanol and
ethylene glycol, wherein the ethylene glycol is greater than 60 mole percent based on
the total moles of 1,4- cyclohexanedimethanol and ethylene glycol with an acid
portion comprising terephthalic acid, or isophthalic acid or mixtures of both acids.
The polyester component may be prepared by procedures well known to those skilled
in this art, such as by condensation reactions. The condensation reaction may be
facilitated by the use of a catalyst, with the choice of catalyst being determined by the
nature of the reactants. The various catalysts for use herein are very well known in the
art and are too numerous to mention individually herein. Generally, however, when an
alkyl ester of the dicarboxylic acid compound is employed, an ester interchange type
of catalyst is preferred, such as Ti(OC<sub>4</sub>H<sub>9</sub>)<sub>6</sub> in n-butanol.</p><p num="0033">In one embodiment copolyester in the subject invention is a copolyester as described
above wherein the glycol portion has a predominance of ethylene glycol over 1,4-cyclohexanedimethanol,
preferably is about greater than 60 molar percent of ethylene
glycol based on the total mole percent of ethylene glycol and 1,4-cyclohexanedimethanol,
and the acid portion is terephthalic acid. In another
embodiment of the present invention the polyester comprises structural units derived
from terephthalic acid and a mixture of 1,4-cyclohexane dimethanol and ethylene
glycol, wherein said ethylene glycol is greater than about 75 mole percent based on
total moles of 1,4-cyclohexane dimethanol and ethylene glycol. In another
embodiment, the polyester resin has an intrinsic viscosity of from about 0.4 to about
2.0 dl/g as measured in a 60:40 phenol /tetrachloroethane mixture at 23°-30°C.</p><p num="0034">The synthesis of polycarbonate polyester blends requires the presence of a catalyst to
facilitate the formation of the blend. Generally, the transesterification catalyst (or
mixture of catalysts) is added in very small amount (ppm level) during the melt
mixing of polycarbonate and polyesters to promote the ester-carbonate exchange
reactions. The catalyst employed are compounds of alkaline earth metal oxides such
as magnesium oxides, calcium oxide, barium oxide and zinc oxide; alkali and alkaline
earth metal salts; a Lewis catalyst such as tin or titanium compounds; a nitrogen-containing
basic compound and the like. However, the presence of excess catalyst 
leads to yellowing or color formation and the blends therefore become less
transparent. Quenchers for example compounds like phosphoric acids, are typically
added to the blends during the extrusion process to quench the excess catalyst and
render the blends transparent. In one embodiment of the present invention additional
catalyst or quencher are not added while the thermoplastic resin is being synthesized.
In another embodiment of the present invention, the residual catalyst that is present in
the polyester component is activated to enhance the ester-carbonate interchange
reactions in reactive blending.</p><p num="0035">The composition of the present invention may include additional components which
do not interfere with the previously mentioned desirable properties but enhance other
favorable properties such as anti-oxidants, flame retardants, reinforcing materials,
colorants, mold release agents, fillers, nucleating agents, UV light and heat stabilizers,
lubricants, and the like. Additionally, additives such as antioxidants, minerals such as
talc, clay, mica, barite, wollastonite and other stabilizers including but not limited to
UV stabilizers, such as benzotriazole, supplemental reinforcing fillers such as flaked
or milled glass, and the like, flame retardants, pigments or combinations thereof may
be added to the compositions of the present invention.</p><p num="0036">The range of composition of the blends of the present invention is from about 10 to 90
weight percent of the polycarbonate component, 90 to about 10 percent by weight of
the polyester component. In one embodiment, the composition comprises about 25 -
75 weight percent polycarbonate and 75-25 weight percent of the polyester
component.</p><p num="0037">The rate at which polycarbonate, polyester and optional additives are delivered into
the extruder for melt mixing depends on the design of the screws of the extruder.
Characteristic residence times for the single-pass extrusion process of the invention
varies according to extrusion operating parameters and the screw design.</p><p num="0038">The conventionally employed screw extruder (10) is depicted in figure 1. The screw
comprises the screw shaft 12, which in turn has a plurality of screw elements 16.
Each element further consists of helical turns called screw flights 14. As the screw 
flights turn the components of the polymer is pushed forward. The twin screw
extruder also comprises of barrels. In the conventional extruder there are ten barrels
34 to 52. The screw flights 22 are oriented in a left handed helix manner, these
reverse elements that create higher back pressure. The screw also consists of a first
two lobe kneading block 18 which is at the barrel 2 i.e. 36 and a second two lobe
kneading block (26) at barrel number 8 (48). There is also present a three lobe
kneading block 20 between barrels 3 (38) and 4 (40). Also present in the screw shaft
are mixing elements 24, which further facilitates mixing. Atmospheric vent 30 is
present at barrel 5 (42) and a vacuum vent 32 at barrel 9 (50). The components are
fed into the extruder through the feed 28 at barrel 1 (34). The first two lobe kneading
block 18 can be eliminated since at that stage polymer is still in solid state and creates
higher torque and in turn it could result in wear of screw element and barrel. Further
the three lobe kneading block 20 is longer and that could be reduced. The reverse
elements 22 that create higher back pressure resulting in more torque. The second
two lobe kneading block 24 is negligible.</p><p num="0039">The conventional twin-screw extruder was modified (60) to obtain optically clear
resin composition is shown in figure 2. The screw was designed with initial
progressively compressed elements to increase the degree of fill at barrel No.2 and 3
(74 and 76 respectively). A three lobe kneading block 62 is placed at barrel 3 (76)
this is sufficient to melt down the polymer. A vacuum vent (68) is placed at barrel 4
(78) which helps suck the gaseous products that are present effectively. A two lobe
kneading block (64) is placed at barrel number 4 (78) which created a nominal back
pressure. A two lobe kneading elements 64 and 66 created an effective
devolatilazation. This was required when a need arises to add any ingredients through
side feeder. A set of mixing elements 24 was introduced for effective mixing at barrel
10 (90).</p><p num="0040">The screw design depicted in Figure 1 had a couple of limitations as it resulted in
higher torque even at lower feed rate and higher temperature. The throughput yield
that could be delivered was maximum of 10Kgs/Hr. In addition the torque produced
in the modified screw in Figure 2 is lower by at least about 30 percent with respect to
the conventionally used screw design. In one embodiment the torque produced is at 
least about 65 percent. The throughput yield obtained is at least about 10 kilogram
per hour (Kg/Hr) and in yet another embodiment the throughput yield is even at
higher output of 18 Kg/Hr. Specific energy of consumption is defined as the amount
of energy required to process a unit quantity of the resin through an extruder, that is
the energy consumed by the extruder per out put of the extruder. This is dependent on
the throughput yield and the rotations per minute of the screw. In one embodiment
the specific energy consumption in the modified screw in Figure 2 is at least about
0.288 kilo watt hour per kilogram (kWh/Kg). In another embodiment the specific
energy consumption in the modified screw is at least about 0.335 kWh/Kg and in yet
another embodiment the specific energy consumption in the modified screw is about
0.365 kWh/Kg.</p><p num="0041">In one embodiment, the residence time is about 5 seconds to 30 seconds. In a second
embodiment, it is 5 seconds to 20 seconds. In a third embodiment, it is 5 seconds to
10 seconds. In embodiments wherein no catalyst is used, the residence time is at the
high end of the range.</p><p num="0042">In one embodiment of the present invention the optically clear thermoplastic resin
composition of the present invention possess good edge cracking resistance and good
environmental stress cracking resistance. Edge cracking resistance is a condition
wherein visible cracks are formed on the edges of the articles while environmental
stress cracking are visible cracks produced when the composition is exposed to
environmental conditions.</p><p num="0043">The mixture of the optically clear thermoplastic resin composition so formed to may
be finally obtained in particulate form, for example by pelletizing or grinding the
composition. The composition of the present invention can be molded into useful
articles by a variety of means by many different processes to provide useful molded
products such as injection, extrusion, rotation, foam molding calender molding and
blow molding and thermoforming, compaction, melt spinning form articles. The
articles made from the composition of the present invention may be used widely in
house ware objects such as food containers and bowls, home appliances, as well as
films. </p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0044">Without further elaboration, it is believed that one skilled in the art can, using the
description herein, utilize the present invention to its fullest extent. The following
examples are included to provide additional guidance to those skilled in the art in
practicing the claimed invention. The examples provided are merely representative of
the work that contributes to the teaching of the present application. While only
certain features of the invention have been illustrated and described herein, many
modifications and changes will occur to those skilled in the art. Accordingly, these
examples are not intended to limit the invention, as defined in the appended claims, in
any manner.</p><p num="0045">In the following examples values for glass transition temperatures (Tg) were
determined by differential scanning calorimetry (DSC) at a heating rate of 20°C per
minute. Weight average molecular weights were measured by gel permeation
chromatography (GPC) versus polystyrene standards using chloroform as solvent.
The GPC column was a Mixed-C column with dimensions 300 millimeters (mm) x
7.5 mm available from Polymer Laboratories. Yellowness index or YI was measured
on a Gardner Colorimeter model XL-835. The percentage transmission and haze were
determined in accordance with test method ASTM D-1003. The melt volume rate
was measured as per ISO Standard 1133, 265 °C, 240 seconds, 2.16Kg, and 0.0825
inch orifice. The heat distortion temperature (also known as HDT) tests were
performed by placing HDT samples edgewise, at load of 1.8 MPa and heating rate of
120° C/hr (degree celsius/hr). Environmental stress cracking resistance was
measured making tensile bars of the samples and they were subjected to a constant
strain, these were then kept in an oven at 60 °C and the defects on the surface like
cracks and crazes were checked. Dynatup Impact tests were carried out using the
ASTM D3763 standard.</p><heading>Examples 1-3:</heading><p num="0046">In these examples, blends were made with 75 weight percent of polycarbonate
available from General Electric Company as Lexan® polycarbonate resin blended 
with a Glycol Modified Polyethylene Terephthalate PETG from SK Chemicals under
the name Skygreen S2008 (EG 64 mole %, CHDM 36 mole %). The polycarbonate
and the PETG were taken in two mega feeders and the feed ratio was adjusted to
maintain the weight ratio of 75% polycarbonate and 25% PETG. The blends were
compounded at 250°C on a modified WP25 mm co-rotating twin screw extruder,
yielding a pelletized composition in a single pass process. The modified screw design
employed for the process of blending is shown in Figure 2. Blends of PETG with
different grades of polycarbonate (PC100, PC105 and PC175) have been prepared.
The resulting pellets were dried for at least six hours at 100. °C before injection
molding into ASTM /ISO test specimens on an 80 ton, four oz. injection molding
machine operated at a temperature of about 280 °C. Samples molded from the blends
were tested for optical properties like % Transmission, % haze and yellowness index.</p><heading>Examples 4 and 5:</heading><p num="0047">In these examples, blends were made with 75 weight percent of polycarbonate
available from General Electric Company as Lexan® polycarbonate resin blended
with a Glycol Modified Polyethylene Terephthalate PETG from another source
purchased Eastman Chemical company was also included for the current invention.
This PETG grade is different from the previous PETG (SK Chemicals) in terms of
residual catalysts and additives. The polycarbonate and the PETG were taken in two
mega feeders and the feed ratio was adjusted to maintain the weight ratio of 75%
polycarbonate and 25% PETG. The blends were compounded at 250°C on a modified
ZSK 25 mm co-rotating twin screw extruder, yielding a pelletized composition in a
single pass process. The modified screw design employed for the process of blending
is shown in Figure 2. Blends of PETG with different grades of polycarbonate
(PC100, PC105 and PC 175) have been prepared. The resulting pellets were dried for
at least six hours at 100. °C before injection molding into ASTM /ISO test specimens
on an 80 ton, four oz. injection molding machine operated at a temperature of about
280 °C. Samples molded from the blends were tested for optical properties like %
Transmission, % haze and yellowness index. </p><p num="0048">Characterization data for blends of polycarbonate PETG which are examples of the
invention or which are comparative examples are shown in Table 1. In Table 1 the
abbreviations are defined as follows: CEx. = Comparative Example which falls
outside the scope of the invention. Comparative Example 1 was a blend of
polycarbonate available from General Electric Company as Lexan® polycarbonate
resin 105 with a Glycol Modified Polyethylene Terephthalate PETG from SK
Chemicals under the name Skygreen S2008 compounded using the same conditions in
a standard ZSK25 mm co-rotating twin-screw extruder. The data in Table 1 show that
the blends of PC-PETG of the invention possess surprisingly better properties when
the modified screw design was employed for compounding purpose.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">PC-PETG</entry><entry align="center">HDT (°C)</entry><entry align="center">Flex Modulus (GPa)</entry><entry align="center">MVR (cc / min)</entry><entry align="center">YI</entry><entry align="center">%T</entry><entry align="center">%H</entry></row><row><entry align="left">CEx 1</entry><entry align="left">PC105-SK</entry><entry align="center">102.63</entry><entry align="center">2.46</entry><entry align="center">8.786</entry><entry align="center">6.4</entry><entry align="center">85.9</entry><entry align="center">2.14</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex 1</entry><entry align="left">PC100-SK</entry><entry align="center">104.53</entry><entry align="center">2.48</entry><entry align="center">10.263</entry><entry align="center">7.5</entry><entry align="center">88.3</entry><entry align="center">0.93</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex 2</entry><entry align="left">PC105-SK</entry><entry align="center">106.7</entry><entry align="center">2.40</entry><entry align="center">6.239</entry><entry align="center">4.9</entry><entry align="center">87.8</entry><entry align="center">2.75</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex 3</entry><entry align="left">PC175-SK</entry><entry align="center">106</entry><entry align="center">2.41</entry><entry align="center">13.63</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry><entry align="center">88.7</entry><entry align="center">1.12</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex 4</entry><entry align="left">PC100-East</entry><entry align="center">110.36</entry><entry align="center">2.45</entry><entry align="center">9.991</entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry><entry align="center">74.4</entry><entry align="center">28.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex 5</entry><entry align="left">PC105-East</entry><entry align="center">105.8</entry><entry align="center">2.51</entry><entry align="center">6.867</entry><entry align="center">17.3</entry><entry align="center">80.6</entry><entry align="center">15.6</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0049">When 75% by weight of Polycarbonate (GE 100,105,175) and 25% by weight of
PETG SK S2008 were extruded on ZSK 25mm Mega compounder on Screw design
S1 with limited processing parameters, a clear blend was produced, having correlated
Haze of 2.14%, and 85.9% transmission of light and with Yellowness Index of
13.912. The same screw design produced opaque PC/PETG blend when of the PETG 
was obtained from Eastman Company was employed. Catalyst and quencher had to
be introduced to get clear compositions with Eastman PETG. The screw design
depicted in Figure 1 had a couple of limitations as it resulted in higher torque even at
lower feed rate and higher temperature. The throughput yield that could be delivered
was maximum of 10Kgs/Hr.</p><p num="0050">The limitations of the screw design depicted in Figure 1 was overcome by modifying
the screw as shown in Figure 2. When 75% by weight of Polycarbonate (GE-100,
105,175) and 25% by weight of PETG (SK S2008 or Eastman) were extruded on ZSK
25 mm co rotating twin screw extruder on modified screw design S3 (Figure 2), that
has two vacuum ports at barrel No.4 and barrel No.8, a clear composition was
produced, having a correlated haze of 0.93-1.12%, and 88.7% of light transmission
with Yellowness Index of 12.088. This screw design has been found give clear
transparent blends of PC/PETG irrespective of the PETG employed. The modified
screw design therefore worked well for both the grades of PETG i.e. SK and Eastman
grades and did not require addition of any catalyst and quencher to obtain clear
blends. In addition the torque produced is much lower about 65% even at higher
output of 18Kgs/Hr.</p><p num="0051">The environmental stress cracking resistance was found to be dependant on the
molecular weight of the blends. The blends displayed good environmental stress
cracking resistance with very less and in some cases negligible crack when exposed to
butter. Similarly improved edge cracking resistance was also observed in the resin
composition of the present invention.</p><p num="0052">While the invention has been illustrated and described in typical embodiments, it is
not intended to be limited to the details shown, since various modifications and
substitutions can be made without departing in any way from the scope of the present
invention. As such, further modifications and equivalents of the invention herein
disclosed may occur to persons skilled in the art using no more than routine
experimentation, and all such modifications and equivalents are believed to be within
the scope of the invention as defined by the following claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An optically clear thermoplastic resin composition comprising: structural units
derived from substituted or unsubstituted polycarbonate and substituted or
unsubstituted polyester, wherein said polyester comprises structural units derived
from terephthalic acid and a mixture of 1,4-cyclohexane dimethanol and ethylene
glycol, wherein said ethylene glycol is greater than about 60 mole percent based on
total moles of 1,4-cyclohexane dimethanol and ethylene glycol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1, wherein said polycarbonate comprises repeating
units of the formula:

wherein D is a divalent aromatic radical derived from a dihydroxyaromatic compound
of the formula HO-D-OH, wherein D has the structure of formula:

wherein A1 represents an aromatic group; E comprises a sulfur-containing linkage,
sulfide, sulfoxide, sulfone; a phosphorus-containing linkage, phosphinyl, phosphonyl;
an ether linkage; a carbonyl group; a tertiary nitrogen group; a silicon-containing
linkage; silane; siloxy; a cycloaliphatic group; cyclopentylidene, cyclohexylidene,
3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexylidene, methylcyclohexylidene, 2-[2.2.1] -bicycloheptylidene,
neopentylidene, cyclopentadecylidene, cyclododecylidene, adamantylidene; an
alkylene or alkylidene group, which group may optionally be part of one or more
fused rings attached to one or more aromatic groups bearing one hydroxy substituent;
an unsaturated alkylidene group; or two or more alkylene or alkylidene groups
connected by a moiety different from alkylene or alkylidene and selected from the
group consisting of an aromatic linkage, a tertiary nitrogen linkage; an ether linkage; a
carbonyl linkage; a silicon-containing linkage, silane, siloxy; a sulfur-containing
linkage, sulfide, sulfoxide, sulfone; a phosphorus-containing linkage, phosphinyl, and
phosphonyl;
R1 independently at each occurrence comprises a mono-valent hydrocarbon group,
alkenyl, allyl, alkyl, aryl, aralkyl, alkaryl, or cycloalkyl;
Y1 independently at each occurrence is selected from the group consisting of an
inorganic atom, a halogen; an inorganic group, a nitro group; an organic group, a
monovalent hydrocarbon group, alkenyl, allyl, alkyl, aryl, aralkyl, alkaryl, cycloalkyl,
and an alkoxy group;
the letter "m" represents any integer from and including zero through the number of
replaceable hydrogens on A1 available for substitution;
the letter "p" represents an integer from and including zero through the number of
replaceable hydrogens on E available for substitution;
the letter "t" represents an integer equal to at least one;
the letter "s" represents an integer equal to either zero or one; and
"u" represents any integer including zero.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The composition of claim 2, wherein the dihydroxyaromatic compound from
which D is derived is bisphenol A.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1, wherein said optically clear thermoplastic resin
composition comprises structural units derived from polyester and polycarbonate in a
range of about 10 - 90 percent by weight of polyester and 90 - 10 percent by weight
of polycarbonate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1, wherein said optically clear thermoplastic resin
composition comprises structural units derived from polyester and polycarbonate in a
range of about 25 - 75 percent by weight of polyester and 75 - 25 percent by weight
of polycarbonate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1, wherein said optically clear thermoplastic resin
composition comprises about 25 percent by weight of polyester and 75 percent by
weight of polycarbonate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1, wherein said optically clear resin composition has
a yellowness index of about less than 17.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1, wherein said optically clear resin composition
transmits about greater than 70 percent light in the region of about 250nm to about
300nm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1, wherein said optically clear resin composition has
a haze value about less than 30.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An article comprising the composition of claim 1.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>