<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2002053797-A1" country="WO" doc-number="2002053797" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25015780" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20020711"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2002053797-A1" status="new" fvid="78388904"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2002053797</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020711</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-0143844-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>0143844</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20011123</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-74992300-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>74992300</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001229</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>C23C  16/02</main-classification><further-classification>C23C  16/44</further-classification><further-classification>H01L  21/00</further-classification><further-classification>C23C  16/26</further-classification><further-classification>H01J  37/32</further-classification><further-classification>B01J  19/02</further-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  19/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  19/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B  31/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B  31/02        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/44        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/44        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01J  37/32        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01J  37/32        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/02        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">H01L  21/3065      20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  19/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  16/44A4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">H01J  37/32D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01J219:02B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01J219:02D10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01J219:02D12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01J219:02D6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">T01J237:32D4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">Y01N6:00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">FULLERENE COATED COMPONENT OF SEMICONDUCTOR PROCESSING EQUIPMENT</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">ELEMENT REVETU DE FULLERENE POUR EQUIPEMENT DE TRAITEMENT DE SEMI-CONDUCTEURS</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="CH-686438-A5" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>CH</country><doc-number>686438</doc-number><kind>A5</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="DE-19826681-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>19826681</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-5004810-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>5004810</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5876790-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5876790</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999020812-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999020812</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 017, no. 259 (C-1061), 21 May 1993 (1993-05-21) &amp; JP 05 004810 A (SEMICONDUCTOR ENERGY LAB CO LTD), 14 January 1993 (1993-01-14)</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHANG CHRISTOPHER C</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DAUGHERTY JOHN E</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LAM RES CORP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>O'DONNELL ROBERT J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook> </applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHANG, CHRISTOPHER, C.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DAUGHERTY, JOHN, E.</name> </addressbook> </applicant> <applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LAM RESEARCH CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>O'DONNELL, ROBERT, J.</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHANG CHRISTOPHER C</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DAUGHERTY JOHN E</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>O'DONNELL ROBERT J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHANG, CHRISTOPHER, C.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DAUGHERTY, JOHN, E.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>O'DONNELL, ROBERT, J.</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A corrosion resistant component of semiconductor processing equipment such as a plasma chamber includes a fullerene containing surface and process for manufacturing thereof.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>L'invention a trait à un élément résistant à la corrosion pour équipement de traitement de semi-conducteurs, p. ex. chambre à plasma, qui comporte une surface contenant du fullerène, et à un procédé de fabrication de celui-ci.</p></abstract><description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>--><p num="p0001"> FULLERENE COATED COMPONENT OF SEMICONDUCTOR PROCESSING EQUIPMENT</p><p num="p0002">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION Field of the Invention</p><p num="p0003">The present invention relates to semiconductor processing equipment and a method of improving corrosion resistance of such components.</p><p num="p0004">Description of the Related Art</p><p num="p0005">In the field of semiconductor processing, vacuum processing chambers are generally used for etching and chemical vapor deposition (CVD) of materials on substrates by supplying an etching or deposition gas to the vacuum chamber and application of an RF field to the gas to energize the gas into a plasma state. Examples of parallel plate, transformer coupled plasma (TCP™) which is also called inductively coupled plasma (ICP), and electron-cyclotron resonance (ECR) reactors and components thereof are disclosed in commonly owned U.S. Patent Nos.</p><p num="p0006">4,340,462; 4,948,458; 5,200,232 and 5,820,723. Because of the corrosive nature of the plasma environment in such reactors and the requirement for minimizing particle and/or heavy metal contamination, it is highly desirable for the components of such equipment to exhibit high corrosion resistance. During processing of semiconductor substrates, the substrates are typically held in place within the vacuum chamber by substrate holders such as mechanical clamps and electrostatic clamps (ESC). Examples of such clamping systems and components thereof can be found in commonly owned U.S. Patent Nos. 5,262,029 and 5,838,529. Process gas can be supplied to the chamber in various ways such as by gas nozzles, gas rings, gas distribution plates, etc. An example of a temperature controlled gas distribution plate for an inductively coupled plasma reactor and components thereof can be found in commonly owned U.S. Patent No. 5,863,376. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
In addition to the plasma chamber equipment, other equipment used in processing semiconductor substrates include transport mechanisms, gas supply systems, liners, lift mechanisms, load locks, door mechanisms, robotic arms, fasteners, and the like. The components of such equipment are subject to a variety of corrosive conditions associated with semiconductor processing. Further, in view of the high purity requirements for processing semiconductor substrates such as silicon wafers and dielectric materials such as the glass substrates used for flat panel displays, components having improved corrosion resistance are highly desirable in such environments. Aluminum and aluminum alloys are commonly used for walls, electrodes, substrate supports, fasteners and other components of plasma reactors. In order to prevent corrosion of such metal components, various techniques have been proposed for coating the aluminum surface with various coatings. For instance, U.S. Patent No. 5,641,375 discloses that aluminum chamber walls have been anodized to reduce plasma erosion and wear of the walls. The '375 patent states that eventually the anodized layer is sputtered or etched off and the chamber must be replaced. U.S. Patent No. 5,895,586 states that a technique for forming an erosion resistant film of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, A1C, TiN, TiC, A1N or the like on aluminum material can be found in Japanese Application Laid-Open No. 62-103379. U.S. Patent No. 5,680,013 states that a technique for flame spraying Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> on metal surfaces of an etching chamber is disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 4,491,496. The '013 patent states that the differences in thermal expansion coefficients between aluminum and ceramic coatings such as aluminum oxide leads to cracking of the coatings due to thermal cycling and eventual failure of the coatings in corrosive environments. In order to protect the chamber walls, U.S. Patent Nos. 5,366,585;</p><p num="p0007">5,798,016; and 5,885,356 propose liner arrangements. For instance, the '016 patent discloses a liner of ceramics, aluminum, steel and/or quartz with aluminum being preferred for its ease of machinability and having a coating of aluminum oxide, Sc<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> or Y<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, with Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> being preferred for coating aluminum to provide 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
protection of the aluminum from plasma. The '585 patent discloses a free standing ceramic liner having a thickness of at least 0.005 inches and machined from solid alumina. The '585 patent also mentions use of ceramic layers which are deposited without consuming the underlying aluminum can be provided by flame sprayed or plasma sprayed aluminum oxide. The '356 patent discloses a ceramic liner of alumina and a ceramic shield of aluminum nitride for the wafer pedestal. U.S. Patent No. 5,885,356 discloses ceramic liner materials for use in CVD chambers.</p><p num="p0008">Various coatings have been proposed for metal components of semiconductor processing equipment. For instance, U.S. Patent No. 5,879,523 discloses a sputtering chamber wherein a thermally sprayed coating of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is applied to a metal such as stainless steel or aluminum with an optional NiAl<sub>x</sub> bond coating therebetween. U.S. Patent Nos. 5,522,932 and 5,891,53 disclose a rhodium coating for metal components of an apparatus used for plasma processing of substrates with an optional nickel coating therebetween. U.S. Patent No. 5,680,013 discloses non-bonded ceramic protection for metal surfaces in a plasma processing chamber, the preferred ceramic material being sintered A1N with less preferred materials including aluminum oxide, magnesium fluoride, and magnesium oxide. U.S. Patent No. 5,904,778 discloses a SiC CVD coating on free standing SiC for use as a chamber wall, chamber roof, or collar around the wafer. With regard to plasma reactor components such as showerhead gas distribution systems, various proposals have been made with respect to the materials of the showerheads. For instance, commonly owned U.S. Patent No. 5,569,356 discloses a showerhead of silicon, graphite, or silicon carbide. U.S. Patent No. 5,494,713 discloses forming an alumite film on an aluminum electrode and a silicon coating film such as silicon oxide or silicon nitride over the alumite film. The '713 patent states that the thickness of the silicon coating film should be 10 μm or less, preferably about 5 μm, since the aluminum coating film, the alumite coating film and the silicon coating film have different coefficients of linear expansion and cracks are easily generated when the thickness of the silicon coating film is too 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
thick. A thickness below 5 μm, however, is stated to be unfavorable since the protection of the aluminum substrate is insufficient. U.S. Patent No. 4,534,516 discloses an upper showerhead electrode of stainless steel, aluminum, copper or the like. U.S. Patent No. 4,612,077 discloses a showerhead electrode of magnesium. U.S. Patent No. 5,888,907 discloses a showerhead electrode of amorphous carbon, SiC or Al. U.S. Patent Nos. 5,006,220 and 5,022,979 disclose a showerhead electrode either made entirely of SiC or a base of carbon coated with SiC deposited by CVD to provide a surface layer of highly pure SiC.</p><p num="p0009">In view of the need for high purity and corrosion resistance for components of semiconductor processing equipment, there is a need in the art for improvements in materials and/or coatings used for such components. Moreover, with regard to the chamber materials, any materials which can increase the service life of a plasma reactor chamber and thus reduce the down time of the apparatus, would be beneficial in reducing the cost of processing the semiconductor wafers. The above-description summarizes the general operation of vacuum processing chambers used for etching and CVD of materials on substrates by supplying an etching or deposition gas to the vacuum chamber and application of an RF field to the gas to energize the gas into a plasma state. With this as background, a second unrelated technology area important to an understanding of the present invention is the field of study relating to fullerenes. Fullerenes, sometimes referred to as buckyballs or buckminsterfullerenes, are a class of pure carbon molecules wherein the carbon atoms form a closed shell. The most commonly discussed fullerenes are C<sub>60</sub> and C<sub>70</sub>. A C<sub>60</sub> fullerene molecule consists of 60 carbon atoms joined together to form a cage structure with 20 hexagonal and 12 pentagonal faces symmetrically arrayed in a soccer ball-like structure. C<sub>60</sub> molecules form a close- packed solid molecular material having a face-centered cubic structure. The structure of C<sub>70</sub> has 25 hexagons, resulting in a shape reminiscent of a rugby ball.</p><p num="p0010">Since the discovery of fullerenes in 1985, researchers have investigated their properties and developed uses for the molecules. In this regard, there are numerous 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
patents detailing the use of fullerene containing films and coatings. See, for example, U.S. Patent Nos. 5,271,890; 5,310,699; 5,356,872; 5,368,890; 5,374,463; 5,380,595; 5,380,703; 5,395,496; 5,876,790; and 5,558,903.</p><p num="p0011">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION According to a first aspect of the invention a process for providing an erosion resistant fullerene containing coating on a surface of a semiconductor processing equipment component is provided. The process includes depositing a fullerene containing coating on a surface of a processing equipment component so as to form an outer erosion resistant surface. By erosion resistant surface, it is meant a surface coating that protects underlying materials from the corrosive effects of plasma chamber gases, while resisting erosion of the coating by the plasma chamber gases. The underlying surface of the process equipment component to be coated can comprise a metal, ceramic or polymer material. In fact, one or more intermediate metal, ceramic or polymer coatings may be used between the surface of the semiconductor processing equipment and the fullerene containing coating. Metal surfaces that may be coated include anodized or unanodized aluminum, stainless steel, a refractory metal such as molybdenum or other metal or alloy used in plasma chambers. Ceramic surfaces that may be coated include alumina, SiC, A1N, Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>, BC or other plasma compatible ceramic material. Polymeric surfaces that may be coated include fluoropolymers such as Teflon®, polyimides such as</p><p num="p0012">Vespel®, and other polymeric materials useful in a plasma chamber at temperatures up to 200°C.</p><p num="p0013">According to a second aspect of the invention, a metal component is provided. The component includes: (a) a metal surface; (b) an optional first intermediate coating on the metal surface; (c) an optional second intermediate coating on the first intermediate coating or on the metal surface; and (d) an outer fullerene containing coating on said component which provides a corrosion resistant 
<!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>-->
outer surface. Each of the first and second intermediate coatings may be a metal or alloy thereof, ceramic, polymer or mixture or composite of such materials.</p><p num="p0014">According to another aspect of the invention, there is provided a semiconductor processing equipment component made of a fullerene containing material. The component may include any one or more coatings employed in such equipment.</p><p num="p0015">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS The objects and advantages of the invention will become apparent from the following detailed description of the preferred embodiments thereof in connection with the accompanying drawing, in which:</p><p num="p0016">Figure 1 is a schematic cross-sectional view of a plasma reactor chamber having a component coated with a corrosion resistant coating in accordance with the present invention.</p><p num="p0017">Figure 2 shows details of the corrosion resistant coating in detail A of Figure 1.</p><p num="p0018">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS OF THE INVENTION</p><p num="p0019">The invention provides an effective way to provide corrosion resistance to metal, ceramic and polymer surfaces of components of semiconductor processing apparatus such as parts of a plasma processing reactor chamber by utilizing an erosion resistant coating. Such components include chamber walls, substrate supports, gas distribution systems including showerheads, baffles, rings, nozzles, etc., fasteners, heating elements, plasma screens, liners, transport module components, such as robotic arms, fasteners, inner and outer chamber walls, etc., and the like.</p><p num="p0020">Although the invention is applicable to any type of component having a metal surface, ceramic surface or polymer surface, for ease of illustration, the invention will be described in more detail with reference to the apparatus described 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>-->
in U.S. Patent No. 5,820,723 which is incorporated herein by reference in its entirety.</p><p num="p0021">Figure 1 illustrates a vacuum processing reactor chamber 10 that includes a substrate holder 70 providing an electrostatic clamping force to a substrate 60 as well as providing an RF bias to the substrate while it is He backcooled. A focus ring 72 confines plasma in an area above the substrate. A source of energy for maintaining a high density (e.g., 10"-10'<sup>2</sup> ions/cm<sup>3</sup>) plasma in the chamber such as an antenna 40 powered by a suitable RF source to provide a high density plasma is disposed at the top of reactor chamber 10. The chamber includes suitable vacuum pumping apparatus for maintaining the interior 30 of the chamber at a desired pressure (e.g., below 50 mTorr, typically 1-20 mTorr) by evacuating the chamber through the centrally located vacuum port 20 at the bottom of the chamber.</p><p num="p0022">A substantially planar dielectric window 50 of uniform thickness provided between the antenna 40 and the interior of the processing chamber 10 forms the vacuum wall at the top of the processing chamber 10. A gas distribution plate 52 is provided beneath window 20 and includes openings such as circular holes for delivering process gas from a gas supply to the chamber 10. A conical liner 54 extends from the gas distribution plate and surrounds the substrate holder 70. In operation, a semiconductor substrate such as a silicon wafer 60 is positioned on the substrate holder 70 and is typically held in place by an electrostatic clamp 74 while He backcooling is employed. Process gas is then supplied to the vacuum processing chamber 10 by passing the process gas through a gap between the window 50 and the gas distribution plate 52. Suitable gas distribution plate arrangements (i.e., showerhead) are disclosed in commonly owned U.S. Patent Application Serial Nos. 08/509,080; 08/658,258; and 08/658,259, the disclosures of which are hereby incorporated by reference. For instance, while the window and gas distribution plate arrangement in Figure 1 are planar and of uniform thickness, non-planar and/or non-uniform thickness geometries can be used for the window and/or gas distribution plate. A high density plasma is ignited in the space 
<!-- EPO <DP n="10"/>-->
between the substrate and the window by supplying suitable RF power to the antenna 40.</p><p num="p0023">Chamber walls 28 such as anodized or unanodized aluminum walls and metal, or ceramic or polymer components such as the substrate holder 70, fasteners 56, liners 54, etc., that are exposed to plasma and show signs of corrosion are candidates for coating according to the invention, thus avoiding the need to mask them during operation of the plasma chamber. Examples of metals and/or alloys that may be coated include anodized or unanodized aluminum and alloys thereof, stainless steel, refractory metals such as W and Mo and alloys thereof, copper and alloys thereof, etc. Examples of ceramic surfaces that may be coated include alumina, SiC, A1N, Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> and BC. Examples of commercially available polymer materials that may be coated include fluoropolymers such as Teflon®, polyimides such as Vespel®, and other polymeric materials useful in a plasma chamber at temperatures up to 200°C. In a preferred embodiment, the component to be coated is a chamber wall 28 having an anodized or unanodized aluminum surface 29. The coating according to the invention permits use of aluminum alloys without regard as to its composition (thus allowing use of more economical aluminum alloys in addition to highly pure aluminum), grain structure or surface conditions. In the following discussion, an example of a component to be coated is an aluminum chamber wall 28 having a first optional intermediate coating 80, a second optional intermediate coating 90, and a fullerene containing coating 100, as illustrated in Figure 2.</p><p num="p0024">In order to ensure good adhesion of the coated material, the surface of the aluminum substrate 28 is preferably thoroughly cleaned to remove surface material such as oxides or grease prior to coating. In addition, it is particularly desirable to roughen the substrate surface, anodize the substrate surface and again roughen the anodized substrate surface prior to application of any of the desired coatings.</p><p num="p0025">According to the invention, first intermediate coating 80 is optionally coated on the aluminum sidewall 28 by a conventional technique. The optional first 
<!-- EPO <DP n="11"/>-->
intermediate coating 80 is sufficiently thick to adhere to the substrate and to further allow it to be processed prior to forming the optional second intermediate coating 90 or the fullerene containing coating 100 described below. The first intermediate coating 80 can have any suitable thickness such as a thickness of at least about 0.001 inches, preferably from about 0.001 to about 0.25 inches, more preferably between 0.001 and 0.1 inches and most preferably from 0.001 inches to 0.05 inches.</p><p num="p0026">After depositing the optional first intermediate coating 80 onto aluminum substrate 28, the plating can be blasted or roughened by any suitable technique, and then overcoated with the second optional coating 90 or the fullerene containing coating 100. A roughened layer 80 provides a particularly good bond. Desirably, the second intermediate coating 90 imparts a high mechanical compression strength to the coating 80 and minimizes formation of fissures in the coating 90.</p><p num="p0027">The optional second intermediate coating 90 is sufficiently thick to adhere to the first intermediate coating 80 and to further allow it to be processed prior to forming any additional intermediate coatings or the outer fullerene containing coating 100 described below. The second intermediate coating 90 can have any suitable thickness such as a thickness of at least about 0.001 inches, preferably from about 0.001 to about 0.25 inches, more preferably between 0.001 and 0.1 inches and most preferably between 0.001 inches and 0.05 inches. The first and second intermediate coating may be made of any one or more materials employed in conventional plasma processing chambers. Examples of such materials include metals, ceramics and polymers. Particularly desirable metals include any one or more refractory metal composites or alloys containing such metals. Particularly desirable ceramics include Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, SiC, Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>, BC, A1N, TiO<sub>2</sub>, etc. Particularly desirable polymers include fiuoropolymers such as Teflon®, polyimides such as Vespel®, and other polymeric materials useful in a plasma chamber at temperatures up to 200°C. Specific materials contemplated for the intermediate layers also include fullerene containing materials; other hard carbon containing materials such as diamond and diamond-like materials; carbides, borides, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="12"/>-->
nitrides and/or carbonitrides of, for example, hafnium, tantalum, titanium and/or silicon; boron carbides; boron nitrides; boron carbonitrides; zirconia; yttria or mixtures of any of the above-mentioned materials.</p><p num="p0028">It is contemplated that the first and second intermediate layers 80 and 90, which are optional may be any one of the above-mentioned materials such that the coatings are the same or different depending on the desired properties. It is also anticipated that additional intermediate coatings such as a third, fourth or fifth intermediate coating of the same or different materials may be employed.</p><p num="p0029">The fullerene containing coating 100 is deposited on the optional second intermediate coating 90, or on the optional first intermediate coating 80, or directly on the aluminum substrate 28. The thickness of the fullerene containing coating is desirably at least 0.001 inches, preferably from about 0.001 to about 0.25 inches, more preferably from about 0.001 to about 0.2 inches, more preferably from about 0.001 to about 0.1 inches and most preferably 0.001 to 0.05 inches. The thickness of the fullerene containing coating 100 can be selected to be compatible with the plasma environment to be encountered in the reactor (e.g., etching, CVD, etc.). This layer of fullerene containing coating may be coated on all or part of the reactor chamber and components as discussed above.</p><p num="p0030">By fullerene containing coating, it is herein meant a coating containing or coating formed from doped or undoped carbon fullerenes sometimes referred to as buckyballs or buckminsterfullerenes. The most commonly discussed fullerenes are C<sub>60</sub> and C<sub>70</sub>. A C<sub>60</sub> fullerene molecule includes 60 carbon atoms joined together to form a cage structure with 20 hexagonal and 12 pentagonal faces symmetrically arrayed in a soccer ball-like structure. C<sub>60</sub> molecules form a close-packed solid molecular material having a face-centered cubic structure. The structure of C<sub>70</sub> has 25 hexagons, resulting in a shape reminiscent of a rugby ball.</p><p num="p0031">Preferred coatings include pure C<sub>60</sub> or C<sub>70</sub>, mixtures thereof, any one or more of the higher fullerenes such as C<sub>76</sub>, C<sub>7g</sub>, C<sub>g4</sub>, C<sub>92</sub> and so forth, or a mixture of C<sub>60</sub>, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="13"/>-->
C<sub>70</sub> and any one or more of the higher fullerenes. It is also contemplated that any one or more of the fullerenes are excluded from the fullerene containing coating. Also contemplated within the invention are the so called doped fullerenes. These molecules include fullerenes containing any one or more of a doping substance such as an alkali metal or a halogen atom. Doping concentrations are desirably less than or equal to one percent by weight of the fullerene coating, more desirably between about 100 parts per million and one percent by weight of the fullerene coating, and even more desirably between about 0.001 and 0.1 percent by weight of the fullerene coating. Alternatively, the fullerene containing coatings of the present invention may be a composite of any one of the above defined fullerenes with other materials or compounds that form a hard corrosion resistant surface. The composites desirably have a continuous matrix phase of the fullerene containing material. The composite may include other protective materials in amounts up to about 50 percent of the total composite and greater. More desirably, the composites of the present invention include between about one and 40 percent by weight additional material, and more preferably between about one and 20 percent by weight additional material and even more preferably between about one and 10 percent by weight additional material based upon the composite. In some instances, particularly where cost is significant, the percentage of fullerenes is very low, e.g., below 20, 10, 5 and one percent by weight of the coating.</p><p num="p0032">Such materials may include any one or more materials employed in plasma processing chambers. Examples of such materials include any one or more refractory metals, composites or alloys containing such metals. Particularly desirable ceramics include Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, SiC, Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>, BC, A1N, TiO<sub>2</sub>, etc. Particularly desirable polymers include fiuoropolymers such as Teflon®, polyimides such as Vespel®, and other polymeric materials useful in a plasma chamber at temperatures up to 200°C. It is believed that the most desirable materials would include the fullerenes alone or in combination with carbides, borides, nitrides and/or 
<!-- EPO <DP n="14"/>-->
carbonitrides of, for example, hafnium, tantatum, titanium and/or silicon; boron carbides; boron nitrides; boron carbonitride; zirconia; yttria or mixtures of any of the above-mentioned materials.</p><p num="p0033">The fullerene containing coating 100 of the present invention may be deposited onto the desired surface by any suitable technique such as chemical vapor deposition, thermal spraying, plasma spraying, sublimation, laser vaporization, sputtering, sputter deposition, ion beam coating, spray coating, dip coating, evaporation, roll-on coating, brush coating, etc. It is contemplated that one or multiple fullerene containing coatings with or without intermediate layers of other materials may be deposited onto the desired surface using such known techniques. In an alternative aspect of the invention, there is provided a semiconductor processing equipment component made of a fullerene containing material. The component may include any one or more coatings conventionally employed in such equipment. By use of the fullerene containing coatings or components of the present invention, it is preferred to obtain an ultrahard, erosion resistant surface. Such coating or component is desirably free of materials that adversely react with processing chamber gases and/or are chemically inert such that there is low or no particle contamination, little or no corrosion of the underlying substrate, little or no metal contamination and/or little or no volatile etch products that adversely affect the processed product or reactor equipment. Since the fullerenes are carbon based, they volatilize during plasma processing and can be removed from the chamber without contaminating the processed product, e.g., a silicon wafer.</p><p num="p0034">It is preferred that the fullerene containing coating or component be placed on or use in the regions that may or may not be exposed to the plasma environment such as parts in direct contact with the plasma or parts behind chamber components such as liners, etc., to minimize metal contamination of the semiconductor substrates processed in the reactor chamber. It is particularly preferred to limit or exclude transition metal dust; e.g., any one or more of elements 21 through 29 (scandium 
<!-- EPO <DP n="15"/>-->
through copper), 39 through 47 (yttbrium through silver), 57 through 79 (lanthanum through gold) and all known elements from 89 (actinium) on in the Periodic Table. Thereby, according to one advantage of the present invention, unsatisfactory etching or undesirable formation of pinholes in deposited films is reduced by suppressing occurrence of such dust by either erosion or corrosion.</p><p num="p0035">While the invention has been described in detail with reference to specific embodiments thereof, it will be apparent to those skilled in the art that various changes and modifications can be made, and equivalents employed, without departing from the scope of the appended claims. 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="16"/>--><claim-text/><claim-text>What Is Claimed Is:</claim-text><claim-text>1. A process for coating a surface of a component of semiconductor processing equipment, the process comprising:</claim-text><claim-text>(a) optionally depositing a first intermediate coating on a surface of a component of semiconductor processing equipment;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) optionally depositing a second intermediate coating on said first intermediate layer or on said surface; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) depositing a fullerene containing coating on said component to form an outer erosion resistant surface.</claim-text><claim-text>2. The process for coating according to Claim 1, wherein said surface of said component of semiconductor processing equipment comprises a metal, ceramic or polymer surface.</claim-text><claim-text>3. The process for coating according to Claim 2, wherein said first intermediate coating is not optional.</claim-text><claim-text>4. The process for coating according to Claim 3, wherein said first intermediate coating comprises a metal, ceramic or polymer coating.</claim-text><claim-text>5. The process for coating according to Claim 1, wherein said component comprises a chamber wall of a plasma etching chamber.</claim-text><claim-text>6. The process for coating according to Claim 1, further comprising forming a roughened surface on said component, said fullerene containing coating being deposited on said roughened surface. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="17"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>7. The process for coating according to Claim 1, wherein fullerenes present in said fullerene containing coating are C<sub>60</sub> fullerenes, C<sub>70</sub> fullerenes or mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>8. The process for coating according to Claim 1 , wherein said fullerene coating is deposited to a thickness ranging from about 0.001 to about 0.050 inches.</claim-text><claim-text>9. The process for coating according to Claim 1, wherein fullerenes present in said fullerene containing coating are doped fullerenes.</claim-text><claim-text>10. The process for coating according to Claim 1, wherein said fullerene containing coating is deposited by chemical vapor deposition, plasma spray coating, sublimation, laser vaporization, sputtering, sputtering deposition, ion beam coating, spray coating, dip coating, evaporation coating, roll-on coating or brush coating.</claim-text><claim-text>11. The process for coating according to Claim 1 , wherein one or more additional fullerene containing or intermediate coatings are applied to said component.</claim-text><claim-text>12. A component of semiconductor processing equipment comprising:</claim-text><claim-text>(a) a surface;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) an optional first intermediate coating on said surface;</claim-text><claim-text>(c) an optional second intermediate coating on said first intermediate coating or on said surface; and (d) a fullerene containing coating on said component that forms an outer corrosion resistant surface.</claim-text><claim-text>13. The component according to Claim 12, wherein said surface (a) is a metal, ceramic or polymer surface. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="18"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>14. The component according to Claim 12, wherein said first intermediate coating is not optional.</claim-text><claim-text>15. The component according to Claim 14, wherein said intermediate coating is a metal, ceramic or polymer coating.</claim-text><claim-text>16. The component according to Claim 12, wherein said component comprises a chamber wall of a plasma etching chamber.</claim-text><claim-text>17. The component according to Claim 12, wherein fullerenes present in said fullerene containing coating are C<sub>60</sub> fullerenes, C<sub>70</sub> fullerenes or mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>18. The component according to Claim 10, wherein said fullerene containing coating has a thickness ranging from about 0.001 to about 0.050 inches.</claim-text><claim-text>19. The component according to Claim 12, wherein fullerenes present in said fullerene containing coating are doped fullerenes.</claim-text><claim-text>20. The component according to Claim 12, further comprising one or more additional fullerene containing or intermediate coatings.</claim-text><claim-text>21. The component according to Claim 12, wherein fullerenes form a continuous matrix phase of said fullerene containing coating.</claim-text><claim-text>22. A component of semiconductor processing equipment having at least one surface exposed to plasma in the equipment, the component comprising a fullerene containing material forming a surface exposed to plasma in the equipment. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>