<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1403327-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1403327" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="31977915" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040331"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1403327-A1" status="new" fvid="24006434"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1403327</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040331</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03021688-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03021688</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030929</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-26014602-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>26014602</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020927</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B   1/514       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09B   1/514B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Farbstoffe</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Colorant compounds</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composés colorants</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1182232-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1182232</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-687807-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>687807</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-63223064-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>63223064</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 013, no. 015 (C-559), 13 January 1989 (1989-01-13) -&amp; JP 63 223064 A (MITSUI TOATSU CHEM INC), 16 September 1988 (1988-09-16)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>XEROX CORP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>XEROX CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Xerox Corporation</last-name><address><street>Patent Department, Xerox Square - 20 A, 100 Clinton Avenue South</street><city>Rochester, New York 14644</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BANNING JEFFERY H</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>JAEGER C WAYNE</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BANNING, JEFFERY H.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>JAEGER, C. WAYNE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BANNING, JEFFERY H.</last-name><address><street>484 NE 16th Avenue</street><city>Hillsboro OR 97124</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>JAEGER, C. WAYNE</last-name><address><street>15900 SW Raven Court</street><city>Beaverton OR 97007</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Grünecker, Kinkeldey, Stockmair &amp;amp; Schwanhäusser Anwaltssozietät</last-name><address><street>Maximilianstrasse 58</street><city>80538 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Disclosed are compounds of the formula 
<img id="img-80000001" orientation="unknown" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="80000001.tif" inline="no" he="48"/> 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom, n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, or 4, R<sub>1</sub> is 
an alkylene group or an arylalkylene group, and X is (a) a hydrogen atom, (b) a group of 
the formula 
<img id="img-80000002" orientation="unknown" wi="33" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="80000002.tif" inline="no" he="14"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl group, (c) 
an alkyleneoxy, aryleneoxy, arylalkyleneoxy, or alkylaryleneoxy group, or (d) a group of 
the formula 
<img id="img-80000003" orientation="unknown" wi="35" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="80000003.tif" inline="no" he="23"/> 
   wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl group. </p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">Cross-reference is made to the following copending 
applications: </p><p num="0002">Copending Application U.S. Serial No. (not yet assigned; 
Attorney Docket No. D/A2341 Q), filed concurrently herewith, entitled 
"Phase Change Inks," with the named inventors C. Wayne Jaeger and 
Jeffery H. Banning, the disclosure of which is totally incorporated herein 
by reference, discloses a phase change ink composition comprising a 
phase change ink carrier and a colorant compound of the formula 
<img id="img-00010001" orientation="unknown" wi="89" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00010001.tif" inline="no" he="49"/> 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom, n is an integer of 0, 1, 
2, 3, or 4, R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an arylalkylene group, and X is (a) a 
hydrogen atom, (b) a group of the formula 
<img id="img-00010002" orientation="unknown" wi="27" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00010002.tif" inline="no" he="15"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group, (c) an alkyleneoxy, aryleneoxy, arylalkyleneoxy, or 
alkylaryleneoxy group, or (d) a group of the formula  <img id="img-00020001" orientation="unknown" wi="39" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00020001.tif" inline="no" he="29"/> 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group. </p><p num="0003">Copending Application U.S. Serial No. (not yet assigned; 
Attorney Docket No. D/A2341Q1), filed concurrently herewith, entitled 
"Methods for Making Colorant Compounds," with the named inventors 
C. Wayne Jaeger and Jeffery H. Banning, the disclosure of which is 
totally incorporated herein by reference, discloses a process for 
preparing a colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-00020002" orientation="unknown" wi="93" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00020002.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
or 
<img id="img-00020003" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00020003.tif" inline="no" he="49"/> 
 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom, n is an integer of 0, 1, 
2, 3, or 4, R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an arylalkylene group, R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl 
group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl group, and R<sub>4</sub> is 
an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl group, 
can be prepared by a process which comprises (a) preparing a first 
reaction mixture by admixing (1) leucoquinizarin and, optionally, 
quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol group of 
the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, (3) boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent, and 
heating the first reaction mixture to prepare an alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-00030001" orientation="unknown" wi="81" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030001.tif" inline="no" he="49"/> 
followed by (b) converting the colorant thus prepared to either (i) an 
ester-substituted colorant by reaction with an esterification compound 
which is either (A) an anhydride of the formula 
<img id="img-00030002" orientation="unknown" wi="27" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030002.tif" inline="no" he="30"/> 
 
or (B) an acid of the formula R<sub>2</sub>COOH in the presence of an optional 
esterification catalyst, or (ii) a urethane-substituted colorant by reaction 
with an isocyanate compound of the formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>4</sub>-N̿C̿O,</st32:che> 
and (c) brominating the colorant thus prepared, wherein either 
conversion to ester or urethane can be performed before bromination 
or bromination can be performed before conversion to ester or 
urethane. </p><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0004">The present invention is directed to colorant compounds. 
More specifically, the present invention is directed to magenta colorant 
compounds particularly suitable for use in hot melt or phase change 
inks. One embodiment of the present invention is directed to 
compounds of the formula 
<img id="img-00040001" orientation="unknown" wi="89" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif" inline="no" he="49"/> 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom, n is an integer of 0, 1, 
2, 3, or 4, R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an arylalkylene group, and X is (a) a 
hydrogen atom, (b) a group of the formula  <img id="img-00050001" orientation="unknown" wi="25" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050001.tif" inline="no" he="18"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group, (c) an alkyleneoxy, aryleneoxy, arylalkyleneoxy, or 
alkylaryleneoxy group, or (d) a group of the formula 
<img id="img-00050002" orientation="unknown" wi="26" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050002.tif" inline="no" he="22"/> 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group. </p><p num="0005">In general, phase change inks (sometimes referred to as 
"hot melt inks") are in the solid phase at ambient temperature, but exist 
in the liquid phase at the elevated operating temperature of an ink jet 
printing device. At the jet operating temperature, droplets of liquid ink 
are ejected from the printing device and, when the ink droplets 
contact the surface of the recording substrate, either directly or via an 
intermediate heated transfer belt or drum, they quickly solidify to form a 
predetermined pattern of solidified ink drops. Phase change inks have 
also been used in other printing technologies, such as gravure printing, 
as disclosed in, for example, U.S. Patent 5,496,879 and German Patent 
Publications DE 4205636AL and DE 4205713AL, the disclosures of each of 
which are totally incorporated herein by reference. </p><p num="0006">Phase change inks for color printing typically comprise a 
phase change ink carrier composition which is combined with a phase 
change ink compatible colorant. In a specific embodiment, a series of 
colored phase change inks can be formed by combining ink carrier  
 
compositions with compatible subtractive primary colorants. The 
subtractive primary colored phase change inks can comprise four 
component dyes, namely, cyan, magenta, yellow and black, although 
the inks are not limited to these four colors. These subtractive primary 
colored inks can be formed by using a single dye or a mixture of dyes. 
For example, magenta can be obtained by using a mixture of Solvent 
Red Dyes or a composite black can be obtained by mixing several 
dyes. U.S. Patent 4,889,560, U.S. Patent 4,889,761, and U.S. Patent 
5,372,852, the disclosures of each of which are totally incorporated 
herein by reference, teach that the subtractive primary colorants 
employed can comprise dyes from the classes of Color Index (C.I.) 
Solvent Dyes, Disperse Dyes, modified Acid and Direct Dyes, and Basic 
Dyes. The colorants can also include pigments, as disclosed in, for 
example, U.S. Patent 5,221,335, the disclosure of which is totally 
incorporated herein by reference. U.S. Patent 5,621,022, the disclosure 
of which is totally incorporated herein by reference, discloses the use of 
a specific class of polymeric dyes in phase change ink compositions. </p><p num="0007">Phase change inks have also been used for applications 
such as postal marking and industrial marking and labelling. </p><p num="0008">Phase change inks are desirable for ink jet printers because 
they remain in a solid phase at room temperature during shipping, long 
term storage, and the like. In addition, the problems associated with 
nozzle clogging as a result of ink evaporation with liquid ink jet inks are 
largely eliminated, thereby improving the reliability of the ink jet 
printing. Further, in phase change ink jet printers wherein the ink 
droplets are applied directly onto the final recording substrate (for  
 
example, paper, transparency material, and the like), the droplets 
solidify immediately upon contact with the substrate, so that migration 
of ink along the printing medium is prevented and dot quality is 
improved. </p><p num="0009">Compositions suitable for use as phase change ink carrier 
compositions are known. Some representative examples of references 
disclosing such materials include U.S. Patent 3,653,932, U.S. Patent 
4,390,369, U.S. Patent 4,484,948, U.S. Patent 4,684,956, U.S. Patent 
4,851,045, U.S. Patent 4,889,560, U.S. Patent 5,006,170, U.S. Patent 
5,151,120, U.S. Patent 5,372,852, U.S. Patent 5,496,879, European Patent 
Publication 0187352, European Patent Publication 0206286, German 
Patent Publication DE 4205636AL, German Patent Publication 
DE 4205713AL, and PCT Patent Application WO 94/04619, the 
disclosures of each of which are totally incorporated herein by 
reference. Suitable carrier materials can include paraffins, 
microcrystalline waxes, polyethylene waxes, ester waxes, fatty acids 
and other waxy materials, fatty amide containing materials, 
sulfonamide materials, resinous materials made from different natural 
sources (tall oil rosins and rosin esters, for example), and many synthetic 
resins, oligomers, polymers, and copolymers. </p><p num="0010">U.S. Patent 6,395,078 (Jaeger), U.S. Patent 6,422,695 
(Jaeger), Canadian Patent Publication 2 355 533 (filed August 20, 2001, 
published February 23, 2002), European Patent Publication EP 1 182 232 
(filed August 17, 2001, published February 27, 2001), Japanese Patent 
Publication JP 2002129044 (filed August 8, 2001, published May 9, 2002), 
Brazilian Patent Publication PI01035819 (filed August 22, 2001, published  
 
March 26, 2002), and Mexican Patent Application 2001008418 (filed 
August 20, 2001), the disclosures of each of which are totally 
incorporated herein by reference, disclose a compound having the 
formula 
<img id="img-00080001" orientation="unknown" wi="73" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080001.tif" inline="no" he="58"/> 
wherein at least one Q<sub>1</sub>, Q<sub>2</sub>, Q<sub>3</sub>, and Q<sub>4</sub> is a halogen atom and any of 
Q<sub>1</sub>, Q<sub>2</sub>, Q<sub>3</sub> and Q<sub>4</sub> which is not a halogen atom is a hydrogen atom; 
and wherein R comprises at least two carbon atoms. The invention 
further encompasses inclusion of such compound into phase change 
ink carrier compositions, as well as printing methods utilizing such 
compound. </p><p num="0011">British Patent Publication GB 2 021 138 (Hohmann et al.), 
the disclosure of which is totally incorporated herein by reference, 
discloses mixtures of dyestuffs of the formula 
<img id="img-00080002" orientation="unknown" wi="82" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00080002.tif" inline="no" he="44"/> 
 
and of the formula 
<img id="img-00090001" orientation="unknown" wi="77" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00090001.tif" inline="no" he="48"/> 
wherein R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>, and R<sub>3</sub> denote C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> alkyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> alkoxy, or halogen, and 
n denotes 2 or 3, which are suitable for dyeing polyester fibers by the 
exhaustion process. Dark blue and navy blue dyeings with good 
fastness properties are obtained. </p><p num="0012">U.S. Patent 6,174,937 (Banning et al.), the disclosure of 
which is totally incorporated herein by reference, discloses a phase 
change ink comprising a material of the formula 
<img id="img-00090002" orientation="unknown" wi="67" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00090002.tif" inline="no" he="20"/> 
wherein X<sub>1</sub>, X<sub>2</sub>, X<sub>3</sub> and X<sub>4</sub> are segments comprising atoms selected from 
groups V and VI of the periodic table; wherein at least one R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>5</sub> 
comprises at least 37 carbon units; and wherein R<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>3</sub> and R<sub>4</sub> each 
comprise at least one carbon unit. The invention further encompasses 
a composition of matter, as well as methods of reducing coefficients of 
friction of phase change ink formulations. </p><p num="0013">U.S. Patent 5,507,864 (Jaeger et al.), the disclosure of which 
is totally incorporated herein by reference, discloses a phase change 
ink composition that includes a combination of different dye types such  
 
as an anthraquinone dye and a xanthene dye, which is most 
preferably a rhodamine dye. While each dye type is insufficiently 
soluble with respect to favored carrier compositions to preserve color 
saturation in reduced ink quantity prints, the dye type combination 
permits increased dye loading and maintains print quality. In a 
preferred embodiment of the invention, a favored carrier composition 
is adjusted to promote the colored form of a preferred rhodamine dye 
(C.I. Solvent Red 49) and mixed with a preferred anthraquinone dye 
(C.I. Solvent Red 172) whose concentration is kept below a critical level 
to prevent post printed blooming. The resulting preferred phase 
change ink compositions provide a magenta phase change ink with 
enhanced light fastness and color saturation, as well as good 
compatibility with preferred existing subtractive primary color phase 
change inks. </p><p num="0014">U.S. Patent 5,902,841 (Jaeger et al.), the disclosure of which 
is totally incorporated herein by reference, discloses a phase change 
ink composition wherein the ink composition utilizes a colorant in 
combination with a selected phase change ink carrier composition 
containing at least one hydroxy-functional fatty amide compound. </p><p num="0015">R. Butnaru et al., "Researches on Dyeing of Cotton Fabrics 
with Acid Dyestuffs, Concomitantly with Crease-Resist Treatments," 
<i>Cellulose Chem. Technol.,</i> 29, p. 471 (1995), the disclosure of which is 
totally incorporated herein by reference, discloses an analysis of the 
results obtained on dyeing of cotton cellulosic fabrics with acid 
dyestuffs, on employing crease-resist agents with polyfunctional 
structure. The conclusion was reached that no chemical or physical  
 
bonds occur between dyestuffs and the fiber, the dyestuffs being fixed 
onto the resin's aminic groups formed as a result of the thermal, crease-resist 
treatment. Washing resistance of the cellulosic materials thus 
dyed attained the values obtained as a result of dyeing with direct 
dyestuffs, specific for these types of fibers. </p><p num="0016">U.S. Patent 6,235,094 (Banning et al.), the disclosure of 
which is totally incorporated herein by reference, discloses a 
compound having the formula 
<img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="52" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="15"/> 
wherein R<sub>1</sub>, Z and the carbonyl can be comprised by a common ring,
 
wherein R<sub>1</sub> comprises a chromophore that absorbs light from the visible 
wavelength range, and wherein n is an integer that is at least 12. The 
invention also encompasses a solid phase change ink composition. 
Such composition includes a phase change ink carrier and a colorant. 
The colorant comprises a chromophore that absorbs light from the 
visible wavelength range, and has the formula 
<img id="img-00110002" orientation="unknown" wi="50" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110002.tif" inline="no" he="16"/> 
wherein R<sub>1</sub>, Z and the carbonyl can be comprised by a common ring,
 
wherein n is an integer that is at least 12. Additionally, the invention 
encompasses a method of forming a colorant. A first compound 
having the formula 
<img id="img-00110003" orientation="unknown" wi="29" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110003.tif" inline="no" he="17"/> 
 
is reacted with a second compound having the formula Z(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>,
 
wherein n is an integer that is at least 12, to form a third compound 
having the formula 
<img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="49" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="16"/> 
wherein the third compound comprises a chromophore that absorbs 
light from the visible wavelength range. </p><p num="0017">While known compositions and processes are suitable for 
their intended purposes, a need remains for improved colorant 
compounds. In addition, a need remains for colorant compositions 
particularly suitable for use in phase change inks. Further, a need 
remains for colorant compounds with a desirable magenta color. 
Additionally, a need remains for colorant compounds with desirable 
thermal stability. There is also a need for colorant compounds with 
good lightfastness. In addition, there is a need for colorant compounds 
that exhibit desirable solubility characteristics in phase change ink 
carrier compositions. Further, there is a need for colorant compounds 
that, when incorporated into phase change inks, exhibit reduced 
migration within a layer of printed ink. Additionally, there is a need for 
colorant compounds that, when incorporated into phase change inks, 
exhibit reduced crystallization within a layer of printed ink. A need also 
remains for colorant compounds that, when incorporated into phase 
change inks, enable production of prints that maintain uniform color 
over long periods of time without unevenness or blotching. In addition, 
a need remains for colorant compounds that, when incorporated into 
phase change inks, enable production of prints that retain their original  
 
color over long periods of time. Further, a need remains for colorant 
compounds that, when incorporated into phase change inks, enable 
production of prints that exhibit reduced sensitivity to image 
discoloration upon contact with human fingertips. Additionally, a need 
remains for colorant compounds that can be incorporated into phase 
change inks in desirably high concentrations. There is also a need for 
colorant compounds that can be manufactured easily and practically. 
In addition, there is a need for colorant compounds that can easily be 
converted to derivative molecules thereof.  </p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0018">The present invention provides: 
<sl><li>(1) compounds of the formula 
<img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="81" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="48"/> 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom, n is an integer of 0, 1, 
2, 3, or 4, R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an arylalkylene group, and X is (a) a 
hydrogen atom, (b) a group of the formula 
<img id="img-00140002" orientation="unknown" wi="30" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140002.tif" inline="no" he="14"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group, (c) an alkyleneoxy, aryleneoxy, arylalkyleneoxy, or 
alkylaryleneoxy group, or (d) a group of the formula 
<img id="img-00140003" orientation="unknown" wi="35" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140003.tif" inline="no" he="21"/> 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group; </li><li>(2) compounds according to (1) wherein Y is a 
hydrogen atom; </li><li>(3) compounds according to (1) wherein n is 0;  </li><li>(4) compounds according to (1) wherein n is 2; </li><li>(5) compounds according to (1 ) of the formula 
<img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="85" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="55"/></li><li>(6) compounds according to (1) of the formula 
<img id="img-00150002" orientation="unknown" wi="89" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150002.tif" inline="no" he="51"/></li><li>(7) compounds according to (1) of the formula 
<img id="img-00150003" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150003.tif" inline="no" he="53"/></li><li>(8) compounds according to (1) of the formula 
<img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/></li><li>(9) compounds according to (1) wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an 
unsubstituted alkylene group; </li><li>(10) compounds according to (1) wherein R<sub>1</sub> is a 
substituted alkylene group; </li><li>(11) compounds according to (1) wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an 
alkylene group wherein hetero atoms selected from oxygen, nitrogen, 
sulfur, silicon, or phosphorus are present in the alkylene group; </li><li>(12) compounds according to (1) wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an 
alkylene group wherein no hetero atoms are present in the alkylene 
group; </li><li>(13) compounds according to (1) wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an 
alkylene group having at least about 2 carbon atoms; </li><li>(14) compounds according to (1) wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an 
unsubstituted arylalkylene group; </li><li>(15) compounds according to (1) wherein R<sub>1</sub> is a 
substituted arylalkylene group;  </li><li>(16) compounds according to (1) wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an 
arylalkylene group wherein hetero atoms selected from oxygen, 
nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, or phosphorus are present in the arylalkylene 
group; </li><li>(17) compounds according to (1) wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an 
arylalkylene group wherein no hetero atoms are present in the 
arylalkylene group; </li><li>(18) compounds according to (1) wherein R<sub>1</sub> is of the 
formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">―CH<sub>2</sub>―CH<sub>2</sub>―;</st32:che></li><li>(19) compounds according to (1 ) wherein R<sub>1</sub> is of the 
formula 
<img id="img-00170001" orientation="unknown" wi="73" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170001.tif" inline="no" he="17"/> 
or 
<img id="img-00170002" orientation="unknown" wi="44" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170002.tif" inline="no" he="26"/></li><li>(20) compounds according to (1) wherein X is a 
hydrogen atom; </li><li>(21) compounds according to (1) wherein X is a group of 
the formula 
<img id="img-00170003" orientation="unknown" wi="31" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170003.tif" inline="no" he="13"/> 
 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group; </li><li>(22) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an 
unsubstituted alkyl group; </li><li>(23) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a 
substituted alkyl group; </li><li>(24) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl 
group wherein hetero atoms selected from oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, 
silicon, or phosphorus are present in the alkyl group; </li><li>(25) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl 
group wherein no hetero atoms are present in the alkyl group; </li><li>(26) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an 
unsubstituted aryl group; </li><li>(27) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a 
substituted aryl group; </li><li>(28) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an aryl 
group wherein hetero atoms selected from oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, 
silicon, or phosphorus are present in the aryl group; </li><li>(29) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an aryl 
group wherein no hetero atoms are present in the aryl group; </li><li>(30) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an 
unsubstituted arylalkyl group or an unsubstituted alkylaryl group; </li><li>(31) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a 
substituted arylalkyl group or a substituted alkylaryl group;  </li><li>(32) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an 
arylalkyl group or an alkylaryl group wherein hetero atoms selected 
from oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, or phosphorus are present in the 
arylalkyl group or alkylaryl group; </li><li>(33) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an 
arylalkyl group or an alkylaryl group wherein no hetero atoms are 
present in the arylalkyl group or alkylaryl group; </li><li>(34) compounds according to (21 ) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">―CH<sub>3</sub>;</st32:che></li><li>(35) compounds according to (21 ) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is 
<img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="47" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="22"/></li><li>(36) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is 
<img id="img-00190002" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00190002.tif" inline="no" he="58"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+m</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein m is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, or 10;  </li><li>(37) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is 
<img id="img-00200001" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00200001.tif" inline="no" he="61"/></li><li>(38) compounds according to (21) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear 
alkyl group having an average of about 50 carbon atoms; </li><li>(39) compounds according to (1) wherein X is an 
alkyleneoxy group, an aryleneoxy group, an arylalkyleneoxy group, or 
an alkylaryleneoxy group; </li><li>(40) compounds according to (1) wherein X is a group of 
the formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">―(C<sub>a</sub>H<sub>2a</sub>O)bR<sub>3</sub></st32:che> 
wherein a is an integer representing the number of carbon atoms in the 
alkyleneoxy group, b is an integer representing the number of repeat 
alkyleneoxy groups, and R<sub>3</sub> is a hydrogen atom, an alkyl group, an aryl 
group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl group; </li><li>(41 ) compounds according to (40) wherein a is 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 
28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48, 
49, or 50;  </li><li>(42) compounds according to (40) wherein a is 2; </li><li>(43) compounds according to (40) wherein a is 3; </li><li>(44) compounds according to (40) wherein a is 4; </li><li>(45) compounds according to (40) wherein b is at least 1; </li><li>(46) compounds according to (40) wherein b is at least 
about 2; </li><li>(47) compounds according to (40) wherein R<sub>3</sub> is a 
hydrogen atom; </li><li>(48) compounds according to (40) wherein X is 
<img id="img-00210001" orientation="unknown" wi="65" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00210001.tif" inline="no" he="25"/> 
or 
<img id="img-00210002" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00210002.tif" inline="no" he="35"/></li><li>(49) compounds according to (40) wherein X is 
<img id="img-00220001" orientation="unknown" wi="82" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00220001.tif" inline="no" he="132"/></li><li>(50) compounds according to (1) wherein X is a group of 
the formula 
<img id="img-00220002" orientation="unknown" wi="29" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00220002.tif" inline="no" he="22"/> 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group; </li><li>(51) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an 
unsubstituted alkyl group;  </li><li>(52) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is a 
substituted alkyl group; </li><li>(53) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkyl 
group wherein hetero atoms selected from oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, 
silicon, or phosphorus are present in the alkyl group; </li><li>(54) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkyl 
group wherein no hetero atoms are present in the alkyl group; </li><li>(55) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an 
unsubstituted aryl group; </li><li>(56) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is a 
substituted aryl group; </li><li>(57) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an aryl 
group wherein hetero atoms selected from oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, 
silicon, or phosphorus are present in the aryl group; </li><li>(58) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an aryl 
group wherein no hetero atoms are present in the aryl group; </li><li>(59) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an 
unsubstituted arylalkyl group or an unsubstituted alkylaryl group; </li><li>(60) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is a 
substituted arylalkyl group or a substituted alkylaryl group; </li><li>(61) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an 
arylalkyl group or an alkylaryl group wherein hetero atoms selected 
from oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, or phosphorus are present in the 
arylalkyl group or alkylaryl group;  </li><li>(62) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an 
arylalkyl group or an alkylaryl group wherein no hetero atoms are 
present in the arylalkyl group or alkylaryl group; </li><li>(63) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is 
<img id="img-00240001" orientation="unknown" wi="131" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240001.tif" inline="no" he="56"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+m</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein m is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, or 10; </li><li>(64) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is 
<img id="img-00240002" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240002.tif" inline="no" he="57"/></li><li>(65) compounds according to (50) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is 
<img id="img-00250001" orientation="unknown" wi="152" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250001.tif" inline="no" he="44"/></li><li>(66) compounds according to (1) of the formulae 
<img id="img-00250002" orientation="unknown" wi="93" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250002.tif" inline="no" he="51"/><img id="img-00250003" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250003.tif" inline="no" he="61"/><img id="img-00260001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00260001.tif" inline="no" he="97"/><img id="img-00260002" orientation="unknown" wi="123" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00260002.tif" inline="no" he="62"/><img id="img-00270001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00270001.tif" inline="no" he="99"/><img id="img-00270002" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00270002.tif" inline="no" he="44"/><img id="img-00270003" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00270003.tif" inline="no" he="60"/><img id="img-00280001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00280001.tif" inline="no" he="96"/><img id="img-00280002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00280002.tif" inline="no" he="70"/><img id="img-00290001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00290001.tif" inline="no" he="99"/><img id="img-00290002" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00290002.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-00290003" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00290003.tif" inline="no" he="58"/><img id="img-00300001" orientation="unknown" wi="103" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00300001.tif" inline="no" he="61"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 
carbon atoms, 
<img id="img-00300002" orientation="unknown" wi="81" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00300002.tif" inline="no" he="62"/><img id="img-00300003" orientation="unknown" wi="99" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00300003.tif" inline="no" he="70"/><img id="img-00310001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00310001.tif" inline="no" he="106"/><img id="img-00310002" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00310002.tif" inline="no" he="70"/><img id="img-00320001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00320001.tif" inline="no" he="109"/><img id="img-00320002" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00320002.tif" inline="no" he="60"/><img id="img-00330001" orientation="unknown" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00330001.tif" inline="no" he="65"/><img id="img-00330002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00330002.tif" inline="no" he="99"/><img id="img-00340001" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00340001.tif" inline="no" he="72"/><img id="img-00340002" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00340002.tif" inline="no" he="111"/><img id="img-00350001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350001.tif" inline="no" he="59"/><img id="img-00350002" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350002.tif" inline="no" he="60"/><img id="img-00350003" orientation="unknown" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350003.tif" inline="no" he="63"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 
carbon atoms,  <img id="img-00360001" orientation="unknown" wi="117" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00360001.tif" inline="no" he="69"/><img id="img-00360002" orientation="unknown" wi="116" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00360002.tif" inline="no" he="77"/><img id="img-00370001" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00370001.tif" inline="no" he="101"/><img id="img-00370002" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00370002.tif" inline="no" he="75"/><img id="img-00380001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00380001.tif" inline="no" he="100"/><img id="img-00380002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00380002.tif" inline="no" he="63"/><img id="img-00390001" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390001.tif" inline="no" he="73"/><img id="img-00390002" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390002.tif" inline="no" he="103"/><img id="img-00400001" orientation="unknown" wi="150" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400001.tif" inline="no" he="76"/><img id="img-00400002" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00400002.tif" inline="no" he="102"/><img id="img-00410001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/><img id="img-00410002" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410002.tif" inline="no" he="64"/><img id="img-00410003" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00410003.tif" inline="no" he="67"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 
carbon atoms,  <img id="img-00420001" orientation="unknown" wi="85" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420001.tif" inline="no" he="54"/><img id="img-00420002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420002.tif" inline="no" he="76"/><img id="img-00420003" orientation="unknown" wi="158" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00420003.tif" inline="no" he="78"/><img id="img-00430001" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430001.tif" inline="no" he="67"/><img id="img-00430002" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430002.tif" inline="no" he="61"/><img id="img-00430003" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00430003.tif" inline="no" he="66"/><img id="img-00440001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00440001.tif" inline="no" he="68"/><img id="img-00450001" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00450001.tif" inline="no" he="167"/> 
or mixtures thereof;  </li><li>(67) compounds according to (1) of the formulae 
<img id="img-00460001" orientation="unknown" wi="89" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00460001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/><img id="img-00460002" orientation="unknown" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00460002.tif" inline="no" he="60"/><img id="img-00460003" orientation="unknown" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00460003.tif" inline="no" he="62"/><img id="img-00470001" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00470001.tif" inline="no" he="63"/><img id="img-00470002" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00470002.tif" inline="no" he="56"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 
carbon atoms, or mixtures thereof; </li><li>(68) compounds according to (1) of the formulae 
<img id="img-00470003" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00470003.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-00480001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00480001.tif" inline="no" he="45"/><img id="img-00480002" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00480002.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-00480003" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00480003.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-00480004" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00480004.tif" inline="no" he="56"/><img id="img-00490001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00490001.tif" inline="no" he="63"/><img id="img-00490002" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00490002.tif" inline="no" he="58"/><img id="img-00490003" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00490003.tif" inline="no" he="67"/><img id="img-00500001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00500001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/><img id="img-00500002" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00500002.tif" inline="no" he="49"/><img id="img-00500003" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00500003.tif" inline="no" he="47"/><img id="img-00500004" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00500004.tif" inline="no" he="62"/><img id="img-00510001" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00510001.tif" inline="no" he="43"/><img id="img-00510002" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00510002.tif" inline="no" he="42"/> 
or mixtures thereof, wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+m</sub> is a branched alkylene group 
which may include unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein m is an 
integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, or 10; </li><li>(69) compounds according to (1) of the formula 
<img id="img-00510003" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00510003.tif" inline="no" he="57"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 
carbon atoms;  </li><li>(70) compounds of the formula 
<img id="img-00520001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00520001.tif" inline="no" he="49"/> 
wherein Y and Y' each, independently of the other, is a hydrogen atom 
or a bromine atom, n and n' each, independently of the other, is an 
integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, or 4, R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>1</sub>' each, independently of the other, is 
an alkylene group or an arylalkylene group, and X is (a) a group of the 
formula 
<img id="img-00520002" orientation="unknown" wi="36" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00520002.tif" inline="no" he="17"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkylene group, an arylene group, an arylalkylene 
group, or an alkylarylene group, (b) an alkyleneoxy group, an 
aryleneoxy group, an arylalkyleneoxy group, or an alkylaryleneoxy 
group, or (c) a group of the formula 
<img id="img-00520003" orientation="unknown" wi="54" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00520003.tif" inline="no" he="23"/> 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkylene group, an arylene group, an arylalkylene 
group, or an alkylarylene group;  </li><li>(71 ) compounds according to (70) wherein n and n' are 
each 0; </li><li>(72) compounds according to (70) wherein n and n' are 
each 2; </li><li>(73) compounds according to (70) wherein R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>1</sub>' 
each, independently of the other, is a substituted alkylene group or a 
substituted arylalkylene group; </li><li>(74) compounds according to (70) wherein R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>1</sub>' 
each, independently of the other, is an unsubstituted alkylene group or 
an unsubstituted arylalkylene group; </li><li>(75) compounds according to (70) wherein R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>1</sub>' are 
each of the formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">―CH<sub>2</sub>―CH<sub>2</sub>―;</st32:che></li><li>(76) compounds according to (70) wherein R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>1</sub>' are 
each of the formula 
<img id="img-00530001" orientation="unknown" wi="70" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00530001.tif" inline="no" he="18"/> 
or 
<img id="img-00530002" orientation="unknown" wi="41" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00530002.tif" inline="no" he="28"/></li><li>(77) compounds according to (70) wherein X is a group 
of the formula 
<img id="img-00540001" orientation="unknown" wi="37" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00540001.tif" inline="no" he="14"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkylene group, an arylene group, an arylalkylene 
group, or an alkylarylene group; </li><li>(78) compounds according to (77) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a 
substituted alkylene group, a substituted arylene group, a substituted 
arylalkylene group, or a substituted alkylarylene group; </li><li>(79) compounds according to (77) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an 
unsubstituted alkylene group, an unsubstituted arylene group, an 
unsubstituted arylalkylene group, or an unsubstituted alkylarylene 
group; </li><li>(80) compounds according to (77) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">―C<sub>36</sub> H<sub>62+ m</sub>―</st32:che> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+m</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein m is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, or 10; </li><li>(81) compounds according to (77) wherein R<sub>2</sub> is 
<img id="img-00540002" orientation="unknown" wi="145" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00540002.tif" inline="no" he="51"/></li><li>(82) compounds according to (70) wherein X is an 
alkyleneoxy group, an aryleneoxy group, an arylalkyleneoxy group, or 
an alkylaryleneoxy group; </li><li>(83) compounds according to (82) wherein X is of the 
formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">―R<sub>3</sub>(C<sub>a</sub>H<sub>2a</sub>O)bR<sub>3</sub>'―</st32:che> 
wherein a is an integer representing the number of carbon atoms in the 
alkyleneoxy, aryleneoxy, arylalkyleneoxy, or alkylaryleneoxy group, b is 
an integer representing the number of repeat alkyleneoxy, aryleneoxy, 
arylalkyleneoxy, or alkylaryleneoxy groups, and R<sub>3</sub> and R<sub>3</sub>' each, 
independently of the others, is an alkylene group, an arylene group, an 
arylalkylene group, or an alkylarylene group; </li><li>(84) compounds according to (70) wherein X is a group 
of the formula 
<img id="img-00550001" orientation="unknown" wi="55" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00550001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/> 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkylene group, an arylene group, an arylalkylene 
group, or an alkylarylene group; </li><li>(85) compounds according to (84) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is a 
substituted alkylene group, a substituted arylene group, a substituted 
arylalkylene group, or a substituted alkylarylene group; </li><li>(86) compounds according to (84) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an 
unsubstituted alkylene group, an unsubstituted arylene group, an 
unsubstituted arylalkylene group, or an unsubstituted alkylarylene 
group;  </li><li>(87) compounds according to (84) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">―C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+m</sub>―</st32:che> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+m</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein m is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, or 10; </li><li>(88) compounds according to (84) wherein R<sub>4</sub> is 
<img id="img-00560001" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00560001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/></li><li>(89) a compound comprising three or more moieties of 
the formula 
<img id="img-00570001" orientation="unknown" wi="83" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00570001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/> 
wherein each Y, independently of the others, is a hydrogen atom or a 
bromine atom, each n, independently of the others, is an integer of 0, 
1, 2, 3, or 4, and each R<sub>1</sub>, independently of the others, is an alkylene 
group or an arylalkylene group, said moieties being linked by a central 
atom or group of atoms or bonded to a polymeric chain; </li><li>(90) compounds according to (1) of the formula 
<img id="img-00570002" orientation="unknown" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00570002.tif" inline="no" he="56"/></li><li>(91 ) compounds according to (90) of the formula 
<img id="img-00580001" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00580001.tif" inline="no" he="47"/> 
wherein Y and Y' each, independently of the other, is a hydrogen atom 
or a bromine atom, n and n' each, independently of the other, is an 
integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, or 4, R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>1</sub>' each, independently of the other, is 
an alkylene group or an arylalkylene group, and X is (a) a group of the 
formula 
<img id="img-00580002" orientation="unknown" wi="41" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00580002.tif" inline="no" he="15"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkylene group, an arylene group, an arylalkylene 
group, or an alkylarylene group, (b) an alkyleneoxy group, an 
aryleneoxy group, an arylalkyleneoxy group, or an alkylaryleneoxy 
group, or (c) a group of the formula 
<img id="img-00580003" orientation="unknown" wi="60" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00580003.tif" inline="no" he="21"/> 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkylene group, an arylene group, an arylalkylene 
group, or an alkylarylene group;  </li><li>(92) compounds according to (90) of the formulae 
<img id="img-00590001" orientation="unknown" wi="101" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00590001.tif" inline="no" he="62"/><img id="img-00590002" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00590002.tif" inline="no" he="95"/><img id="img-00600001" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00600001.tif" inline="no" he="67"/><img id="img-00600002" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00600002.tif" inline="no" he="93"/><img id="img-00600003" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00600003.tif" inline="no" he="46"/><img id="img-00610001" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00610001.tif" inline="no" he="72"/><img id="img-00610002" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00610002.tif" inline="no" he="97"/><img id="img-00620001" orientation="unknown" wi="117" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00620001.tif" inline="no" he="76"/><img id="img-00620002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00620002.tif" inline="no" he="103"/><img id="img-00630001" orientation="unknown" wi="154" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00630001.tif" inline="no" he="65"/><img id="img-00630002" orientation="unknown" wi="123" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00630002.tif" inline="no" he="73"/><img id="img-00640001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00640001.tif" inline="no" he="103"/><img id="img-00640002" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00640002.tif" inline="no" he="82"/><img id="img-00650001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00650001.tif" inline="no" he="105"/><img id="img-00650002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00650002.tif" inline="no" he="59"/><img id="img-00660001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00660001.tif" inline="no" he="78"/><img id="img-00660002" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00660002.tif" inline="no" he="61"/> 
or mixtures thereof; and </li><li>(93) compounds according to (90) of the formulae 
<img id="img-00660003" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00660003.tif" inline="no" he="44"/><img id="img-00670001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00670001.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-00670002" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00670002.tif" inline="no" he="57"/><img id="img-00670003" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00670003.tif" inline="no" he="62"/><img id="img-00670004" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00670004.tif" inline="no" he="54"/><img id="img-00680001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00680001.tif" inline="no" he="51"/><img id="img-00680002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00680002.tif" inline="no" he="41"/> 
or mixtures thereof, wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+m</sub> is a branched alkylene group 
which may include unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein m is an 
integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, or 10. </li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0019">The present invention is directed to colorant compounds of 
the formula 
<img id="img-00680003" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00680003.tif" inline="no" he="50"/> 
 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom, n is an integer of 0, 1, 
2, 3, or 4, R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group (including linear, branched, saturated, 
unsaturated, cyclic, and unsubstituted alkylene groups, and wherein 
hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, phosphorus, and 
the like either may or may not be present in the alkylene group), in one 
embodiment with at least about 1 carbon atom, and in another 
embodiment with at least about 2 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 20 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with no more than about 6 carbon atoms, and in still 
another embodiment with no more than about 2 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
or an arylalkylene group (including unsubstituted and substituted 
arylalkylene groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, 
nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or may not 
be present in either or both of the alkyl portion and the aryl portion of 
the arylalkylene group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 
carbon atoms, and in another embodiment with at least about 7 
carbon atoms, and in one embodiment with no more than about 50 
carbon atoms, in another embodiment with no more than about 20 
carbon atoms, in yet another embodiment with no more than about 7 
carbon atoms, although the number of carbon atoms can be outside 
of these ranges, and X is (a) a hydrogen atom, (b) a group of the 
formula 
<img id="img-00690001" orientation="unknown" wi="25" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00690001.tif" inline="no" he="19"/> 
 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group (including linear, branched, saturated, 
unsaturated, cyclic, unsubstituted, and substituted alkyl groups, and
 
wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, 
phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in the alkyl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 1 carbon atom, in 
another embodiment with at least about 2 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 4 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in still another  
 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in still another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 70 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and in still 
another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
an aryl group (including unsubstituted and substituted aryl groups, and 
wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, 
phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in the aryl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in 
another embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with at least about 13 carbon atoms, in still 
another embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another  
 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in still another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 75 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and in still 
another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
an arylalkyl group (including unsubstituted and substituted arylalkyl 
groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, 
silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in 
either or both of the alkyl portion and the aryl portion of the arylalkyl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in 
another embodiment with at least about 7 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another  
 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 200 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and 
in still another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
or an alkylaryl group (including unsubstituted and substituted alkylaryl 
groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, 
silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in 
either or both of the alkyl portion and the aryl portion of the alkylaryl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in 
another embodiment with at least about 7 carbon atoms, in yet  
 
another embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 200 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and 
in still another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms,  
 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
(c) an alkyleneoxy group, an aryleneoxy group, an arylalkyleneoxy 
group, or an alkylaryleneoxy group, including (but not limited to) those 
of the formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">―(C<sub>a</sub>H<sub>2a</sub>O)bR<sub>3</sub></st32:che> 
wherein a is an integer representing the number of carbon atoms in the 
alkyleneoxy, aryleneoxy, arylalkyleneoxy, or alkylaryleneoxy group, 
being in various embodiments 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 
16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 
37, 38, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48, 49, or 50, although the value 
of a can be outside of these ranges, b is an integer representing the 
number of repeat alkyleneoxy, aryleneoxy, arylalkyleneoxy, or 
alkylaryleneoxy groups, being in one embodiment at least 1, in another 
embodiment at least about 2, in yet another embodiment at least 
about 5, and in still another embodiment at least about 10, and being 
in one embodiment no more than about 200, in another embodiment 
no more than about 150, in yet another embodiment no more than 
about 100, and in still another embodiment no more than about 50, 
although the value of b can be outside of these ranges, and R<sub>3</sub> is a 
hydrogen atom, an alkyl group (including linear, branched, saturated, 
unsaturated, cyclic, unsubstituted, and substituted alkyl groups, and 
wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, 
phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in the alkyl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 1 carbon atom, in 
another embodiment with at least about 2 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 4 carbon atoms, in yet another  
 
embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in still another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 70 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and in still  
 
another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
an aryl group (including unsubstituted and substituted aryl groups, and 
wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, 
phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in the aryl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in 
another embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with at least about 13 carbon atoms, in still 
another embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in still another  
 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 75 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and in still 
another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
an arylalkyl group (including unsubstituted and substituted arylalkyl 
groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, 
silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in 
either or both of the alkyl portion and the aryl portion of the arylalkyl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in 
another embodiment with at least about 7 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another  
 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 200 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and 
in still another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
or an alkylaryl group (including unsubstituted and substituted alkylaryl 
groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, 
silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in 
either or both of the alkyl portion and the aryl portion of the alkylaryl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in 
another embodiment with at least about 7 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another  
 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 200 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and 
in still another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
or (d) a group of the formula 
<img id="img-00800001" orientation="unknown" wi="33" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00800001.tif" inline="no" he="22"/> 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkyl group (including linear, branched, saturated, 
unsaturated, cyclic, unsubstituted, and substituted alkyl groups, and
 
 
wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, 
phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in the alkyl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 1 carbon atom, in 
another embodiment with at least about 2 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 4 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in yet another  
 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in still another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 70 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and in still 
another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
an aryl group (including unsubstituted and substituted aryl groups, and 
wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, 
phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in the aryl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in 
another embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with at least about 13 carbon atoms, in still 
another embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in another  
 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in still another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 75 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and in still 
another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
an arylalkyl group (including unsubstituted and substituted arylalkyl 
groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, 
silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in 
either or both of the alkyl portion and the aryl portion of the arylalkyl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in 
another embodiment with at least about 7 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another  
 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 200 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and 
in still another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
an alkylaryl group (including unsubstituted and substituted alkylaryl 
groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, 
silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in 
either or both of the alkyl portion and the aryl portion of the alkylaryl 
group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in 
another embodiment with at least about 7 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet another  
 
embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 200 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and 
in still another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
wherein the substituents on the substituted alkyl, alkylene, aryl, arylene,  
 
arylalkyl, arylalkylene, alkylaryl, and alkylarylene groups can be (but 
are not limited to) hydroxy groups, halogen atoms, amine groups, imine 
groups, ammonium groups, cyano groups, pyridine groups, pyridinium 
groups, ether groups, aldehyde groups, ketone groups, ester groups, 
amide groups, carbonyl groups, thiocarbonyl groups, sulfate groups, 
sulfonate groups, sulfide groups, sulfoxide groups, phosphine groups, 
phosphonium groups, phosphate groups, nitrile groups, mercapto 
groups, nitro groups, nitroso groups, sulfone groups, acyl groups, acid 
anhydride groups, azide groups, azo groups, cyanato groups, 
isocyanato groups, thiocyanato groups, isothiocyanato groups, mixtures 
thereof, and the like, wherein two or more substituents can be joined 
together to form a ring. </p><p num="0020">The above formula encompasses monomeric materials. In 
addition, the above formula encompasses dimeric materials containing 
two moieties of the formula 
<img id="img-00860001" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00860001.tif" inline="no" he="47"/> 
linked by a central X moiety, as follows:  <img id="img-00870001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00870001.tif" inline="no" he="53"/> 
wherein Y and Y' each, independently of the other, is a hydrogen atom 
or a bromine atom, n and n' each, independently of the other, is an 
integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, or 4, R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>1</sub>' each, independently of the other, is 
an alkylene group or an arylalkylene group as defined in further detail 
for the alkylene and arylalkylene R<sub>1</sub> groups hereinabove, and X is (a) a 
group of the formula 
<img id="img-00870002" orientation="unknown" wi="39" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00870002.tif" inline="no" he="15"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkylene group, an arylene group, an arylalkylene 
group, or an alkylarylene group as defined in further detail for the alkyl, 
aryl, arylalkyl, and alkylaryl R<sub>2</sub> groups hereinabove, (b) an alkyleneoxy 
group, an aryleneoxy group, an arylalkyleneoxy group, or an 
alkylaryleneoxy group as defined in further detail for the alkyleneoxy, 
aryleneoxy, arylalkyleneoxy, and alkylaryleneoxy R<sub>2</sub> groups 
hereinabove, or (c) a group of the formula 
<img id="img-00870003" orientation="unknown" wi="54" img-format="tif"  img-content="cf" file="00870003.tif" inline="no" he="23"/> 
 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkylene group, an arylene group, an arylalkylene 
group, or an alkylarylene group as defined in further detail for the alkyl, 
aryl, arylalkyl, and alkylaryl R<sub>4</sub> groups hereinabove. For example, when 
the colorant material is formed from a diacid starting material of the 
formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">HOOC-R<sub>2</sub>-COOH</st32:che> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is as defined hereinabove, X is of the formula 
<img id="img-00880001" orientation="unknown"  wi="40"  img-format="tif"  img-content="cf" file="00880001.tif" inline="no" he="17"/> 
When X is an alkyleneoxy group, an aryleneoxy group, an 
arylalkyleneoxy group, or an alkylaryleneoxy group, it can be of the 
formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">―R<sub>3</sub>(C<sub>a</sub>H<sub>2a</sub>O)bR<sub>3</sub>'―</st32:che> 
wherein a and b are as defined hereinabove when X is an alkyleneoxy 
group, an aryleneoxy group, an arylalkyleneoxy group, or an 
alkylaryleneoxy group and R<sub>3</sub> and R<sub>3</sub>' each, independently of the 
others, is an alkylene group (including linear, branched, saturated, 
unsaturated, cyclic, unsubstituted, and substituted alkylene groups, and 
wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, 
phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in the 
alkylene group), in one embodiment with at least about 1 carbon 
atom, in another embodiment with at least about 2 carbon atoms, in 
another embodiment with at least about 4 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with at least about 6 carbon atoms, in still 
another embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, in another  
 
embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in still another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 70 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and in still 
another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges,  
 
an arylene group (including unsubstituted and substituted arylene 
groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, 
silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or may not be present in 
the arylene group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 carbon 
atoms, in another embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in 
yet another embodiment with at least about 13 carbon atoms, in still 
another embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in still another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in another  
 
embodiment with no more than about 75 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and in still 
another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
an arylalkylene group (including unsubstituted and substituted 
arylalkylene groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, 
nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or may not 
be present in either or both of the alkyl portion and the aryl portion of 
the arylalkylene group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 
carbon atoms, in another embodiment with at least about 7 carbon 
atoms, in yet another embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, 
in another embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still 
another embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in yet another  
 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 200 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and 
in still another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
or an alkylarylene group (including unsubstituted and substituted 
alkylarylene groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, 
nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or may not 
be present in either or both of the alkyl portion and the aryl portion of 
the alkylarylene group), in one embodiment with at least about 6 
carbon atoms, in another embodiment with at least about 7 carbon 
atoms, in yet another embodiment with at least about 8 carbon atoms, 
in another embodiment with at least about 10 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with at least about 12 carbon atoms, in still 
another embodiment with at least about 14 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 16 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 18 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 20 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 22 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 24 carbon atoms, in still another  
 
embodiment with at least about 26 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 28 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 30 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 32 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 34 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 36 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 38 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 40 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 42 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with at least about 44 carbon atoms, in yet another 
embodiment with at least about 46 carbon atoms, in still another 
embodiment with at least about 48 carbon atoms, and in another 
embodiment with at least about 50 carbon atoms, and in one 
embodiment with no more than about 200 carbon atoms, in another 
embodiment with no more than about 100 carbon atoms, in yet 
another embodiment with no more than about 60 carbon atoms, and 
in still another embodiment with no more than about 50 carbon atoms, 
although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of these ranges, 
wherein the substituents on the substituted alkylene, arylene, 
arylalkylene, and alkylarylene groups can be (but are not limited to) 
hydroxy groups, halogen atoms, amine groups, imine groups, 
ammonium groups, cyano groups, pyridine groups, pyridinium groups, 
ether groups, aldehyde groups, ketone groups, ester groups, amide 
groups, carbonyl groups, thiocarbonyl groups, sulfate groups, sulfonate 
groups, sulfide groups, sulfoxide groups, phosphine groups, 
phosphonium groups, phosphate groups, nitrile groups, mercapto  
 
groups, nitro groups, nitroso groups, sulfone groups, acyl groups, acid 
anhydride groups, azide groups, azo groups, cyanato groups, 
isocyanato groups, thiocyanato groups, isothiocyanato groups, mixtures 
thereof, and the like, wherein two or more substituents can be joined 
together to form a ring. </p><p num="0021">When the colorant material is formed from a diisocyanate 
starting material of the formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">O=C=N―R<sub>4</sub>―N=C=O</st32:che> 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is as defined hereinabove, X is of the formula 
<img id="img-00940001" orientation="unknown" wi="55" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00940001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/> 
Similarly, the above formula encompasses trimeric, tetrameric, and 
higher moieties as well as oligomeric materials and polymeric materials, 
said materials containing three or more moieties of the formula 
<img id="img-00940002" orientation="unknown" wi="85" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00940002.tif" inline="no" he="50"/> 
wherein each Y, independently of the others, is a hydrogen atom or a 
bromine atom, each n, independently of the others, is an integer of 0, 
1, 2, 3, or 4, and each R<sub>1</sub>, independently of the others, is an alkylene 
group or an arylalkylene group, said moieties being linked by a central  
 
atom or group of atoms or bonded to a polymeric chain. These 
materials can be made by processes analogous to those illustrated 
herein for the monomeric and dimeric compounds of the present 
invention. </p><p num="0022">Colorant compounds of the present invention can be 
prepared by any desired or effective method. </p><p num="0023">In one embodiment, colorant compounds of the present 
invention are prepared by a process for preparing a colorant of the 
formula 
<img id="img-00950001" orientation="unknown" wi="95" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00950001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/> 
or 
<img id="img-00950002" orientation="unknown" wi="97" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00950002.tif" inline="no" he="55"/> 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom, n is an integer of 0, 1, 
2, 3, or 4, R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an arylalkylene group, R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl 
group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl group, and R<sub>4</sub> is  
 
an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl group, 
can be prepared by a process which comprises (a) preparing a first 
reaction mixture by admixing (1) leucoquinizarin and, optionally, 
quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol group of 
the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, (3) boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent, and 
heating the first reaction mixture to prepare an alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-00960001" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00960001.tif" inline="no" he="48"/> 
followed by (b) converting the colorant thus prepared to either (i) an 
ester-substituted colorant by reaction with an esterification compound 
which is either (A) an anhydride of the formula 
<img id="img-00960002" orientation="unknown" wi="34" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00960002.tif" inline="no" he="33"/> 
or (B) an acid of the formula R<sub>2</sub>COOH in the presence of an optional 
esterification catalyst, or (ii) a urethane-substituted colorant by reaction 
with an isocyanate compound of the formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>4</sub>―N=C=O</st32:che> 
 
and (c) brominating the colorant thus prepared, wherein either 
conversion to ester or urethane can be performed before bromination 
or bromination can be performed before conversion to ester or 
urethane. </p><p num="0024">In another embodiment, colorant compounds of the 
present invention are prepared by a process which comprises (a) 
preparing a first reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) leucoquinizarin and, 
optionally, quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol 
group of the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an 
arylalkylene group, (3) boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent, and 
heating the first reaction mixture to prepare an alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-00970001" orientation="unknown" wi="88" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00970001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
(b) preparing a second reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) the alcohol-substituted 
colorant, (2) a solvent, and (3) a first esterification 
compound which is either (i) an anhydride of the formula 
<img id="img-00970002" orientation="unknown" wi="35" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00970002.tif" inline="no" he="30"/> 
 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group, or (ii) an acid of the formula R<sub>2</sub>COOH in the presence of 
an optional esterification catalyst, and heating the second reaction 
mixture to form a first ester-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-00980001" orientation="unknown" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00980001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
(c) forming a third reaction mixture by admixing (1) the first ester-substituted 
colorant, (2) bromine, and (3) a solvent followed by 
quenching the third reaction mixture with water to form a brominated 
ester-substituted colorant and a salt thereof, of the formulae 
<img id="img-00980002" orientation="unknown" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00980002.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
and  <img id="img-00990001" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00990001.tif" inline="no" he="54"/> 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom and n is an integer of 
1, 2, 3, or 4; (d) preparing a fourth reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) the 
brominated ester-substituted colorant and the salt thereof, (2) a base, 
(3) water, and (4) a solvent and heating the fourth reaction mixture to 
form a brominated alcohol-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-00990002" orientation="unknown" wi="84" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00990002.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
and (e) preparing a fifth reaction mixture by admixing (1) the 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant, (2) a second esterification 
compound which is either (i) an anhydride of the formula 
<img id="img-00990003" orientation="unknown" wi="32" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00990003.tif" inline="no" he="33"/> 
 
wherein R<sub>2</sub>' is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group, and wherein R<sub>2</sub>' is different from R<sub>2</sub>, or (ii) an acid of the 
formula R<sub>2</sub>'COOH in the presence of an optional esterification catalyst, 
and (3) a solvent and heating the fifth reaction mixture to form a 
second ester-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01000001" orientation="unknown" wi="97" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01000001.tif" inline="no" he="53"/> 
In this embodiment, R<sub>2</sub>' has the same definitions as provided 
hereinabove for R<sub>2</sub> except that R<sub>2</sub>' is different from R<sub>2</sub>. </p><p num="0025">In yet another embodiment, colorant compounds of the 
present invention are prepared by a process which comprises (a) 
preparing a first reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) leucoquinizarin and, 
optionally, quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol 
group of the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an 
arylalkylene group, (3) boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent, and 
heating the first reaction mixture to prepare an alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formula  <img id="img-01010001" orientation="unknown" wi="95" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01010001.tif" inline="no" he="60"/> 
(b) preparing a second reaction mixture by admixing (1) the alcohol-substituted 
colorant, (2) a carboxylic acid of the formula R<sub>2</sub>COOH,
 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group, (3) an optional esterification catalyst, and (4) a solvent 
and heating the second reaction mixture to form an ester-substituted 
colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01010002" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01010002.tif" inline="no" he="51"/> 
and (c) forming a third reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) the ester-substituted 
colorant, (2) bromine, and (3) a solvent followed by 
quenching the third reaction mixture with water to form a brominated 
ester-substituted colorant and a salt thereof, of the formulae  <img id="img-01020001" orientation="unknown" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01020001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01020002" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01020002.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom and n is an integer of 
1, 2, 3, or 4. </p><p num="0026">In still another embodiment, colorant compounds of the 
present invention are prepared by a process which comprises (a) 
preparing a first reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) leucoquinizarin and, 
optionally, quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol 
group of the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an 
arylalkylene group, (3) boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent, and 
heating the first reaction mixture to prepare an alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formula  <img id="img-01030001" orientation="unknown" wi="85" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01030001.tif" inline="no" he="55"/> 
(b) preparing a second reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) the alcohol-substituted 
colorant, (2) bromine, and (3) a solvent followed by 
quenching the second reaction mixture with water to form a 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant and a salt thereof, of the 
formulae 
<img id="img-01030002" orientation="unknown" wi="77" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01030002.tif" inline="no" he="46"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01030003" orientation="unknown" wi="77" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01030003.tif" inline="no" he="55"/> 
 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom and n is an integer of 
0, 1, 2, 3, or 4; and (c) forming a third reaction mixture by admixing (1) 
the brominated alcohol-substituted colorant, (2) a carboxylic acid of 
the formula R<sub>2</sub>COOH, wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an 
arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl group, (3) an optional esterification 
catalyst, and (4) a solvent and heating the third reaction mixture to 
form a brominated ester-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01040001" orientation="unknown" wi="95" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01040001.tif" inline="no" he="51"/></p> <p num="0027">In yet still another embodiment, colorant compounds of 
the present invention are prepared by a process which comprises (a) 
preparing a first reaction mixture by admixing (1) leucoquinizarin and, 
optionally, quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol 
group of the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an 
arylalkylene group, (3) boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent, and 
heating the first reaction mixture to prepare an alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formula  <img id="img-01050001" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01050001.tif" inline="no" he="55"/> 
(b) preparing a second reaction mixture by admixing (1) the alcohol-substituted 
colorant, (2) an isocyanate of the formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>4</sub>―N̿C̿O</st32:che> 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group, and (3) an optional catalyst and heating the second 
reaction mixture to form a urethane-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01050002" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01050002.tif" inline="no" he="53"/> 
and (c) forming a third reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) the urethane-substituted 
colorant, (2) bromine, and (3) a solvent followed by 
quenching the third reaction mixture with water to form a brominated 
urethane-substituted colorant and a salt thereof, of the formulae  <img id="img-01060001" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01060001.tif" inline="no" he="57"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01060002" orientation="unknown" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01060002.tif" inline="no" he="53"/> 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom and n is an integer of 
1, 2, 3, or 4. </p><p num="0028">In still yet another embodiment, colorant compounds of 
the present invention are prepared by a process which comprises (a) 
preparing a first reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) leucoquinizarin and, 
optionally, quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol 
group of the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an 
arylalkylene group, (3) boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent, and 
heating the first reaction mixture to prepare an alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formula  <img id="img-01070001" orientation="unknown" wi="81" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01070001.tif" inline="no" he="58"/> 
(b) preparing a second reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) the alcohol-substituted 
colorant, (2) bromine, and (3) a solvent followed by 
quenching the second reaction mixture with water to form a 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant and a salt thereof, of the 
formulae 
<img id="img-01070002" orientation="unknown" wi="81" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01070002.tif" inline="no" he="48"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01070003" orientation="unknown" wi="81" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01070003.tif" inline="no" he="53"/> 
 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom and n is an integer of 
0, 1, 2, 3, or 4; and (c) forming a third reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) 
the brominated alcohol-substituted colorant, (2) an isocyanate of the 
formula 
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>4</sub>―N̿C̿O</st32:che> 
wherein R<sub>4</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group, and (3) an optional catalyst and heating the second 
reaction mixture to form a brominated urethane-substituted colorant 
and a salt thereof, of the formulae 
<img id="img-01080001" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01080001.tif" inline="no" he="51"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01080002" orientation="unknown" wi="108" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01080002.tif" inline="no" he="58"/></p><p num="0029">An alcohol-substituted colorant of the present invention of 
the formula  <img id="img-01090001" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01090001.tif" inline="no" he="54"/> 
can be prepared by admixing (1) leucoquinizarin and, optionally, 
quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol group of 
the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is as defined hereinabove, (3) boric acid, 
and (4) an optional solvent, followed by heating this reaction mixture to 
reflux temperature as follows (illustrated for an embodiment wherein 
the aminobenzene is substituted with the alcohol group in the 4- or 
para-position): 
<img id="img-01090002" orientation="unknown" wi="154" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01090002.tif" inline="no" he="50"/> 
While quinizarin is shown above as the starting material, the presence of 
leucoquinizarin, which is the reduced form of quinizarin, is needed to 
condense with the alcohol-substituted amine. The reaction between 
the amine and the leucoquinizarin further reduces some of the 
quinizarin present in the reaction mixture to leucoquinizarin, thereby 
rendering it capable of reacting with more of the amine and furthering  
 
the reaction to completion. If desired, the reaction can be carried out 
solely with leucoquinizarin and with no quinizarin, although for 
economical purposes such a procedure is often not desirable. In 
addition, instead of adding leucoquinizarin to a reaction mixture of 
quinizarin and the alcohol-substituted amine, leucoquinizarin can be 
generated in situ by preparing a reaction mixture of quinizarin and the 
alcohol-substituted amine and adding to the reaction mixture a 
reducing agent, as disclosed in, for example, Waring and Hallas, <i>The 
Chemistry and Application of Dyes,</i> ISBN 0-306-43278-1, Plenum 
Publishing Co. (New York 1990), the disclosure of which is totally 
incorporated herein by reference. </p><p num="0030">The quinizarin and the leucoquinizarin are present in any 
desired or effective relative amounts, in one embodiment at least 
about 5 moles of leucoquinizarin per every 95 moles of quinizarin, in 
another embodiment at least about 2 moles of leucoquinizarin per 
every 3 moles of quinizarin, and in yet another embodiment at least 
about 1 mole of leucoquinizarin per every 1 mole of quinizarin, and in 
one embodiment up to 100 percent leucoquinizarin and no quinizarin, 
although the relative amounts of quinizarin and leucoquinizarin can be 
outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0031">The alcohol-substituted aminobenzene is present in any 
desired or effective amount, in one embodiment at least about 0.95 
mole of alcohol-substituted aminobenzene per every one mole of 
(quinizarin plus leucoquinizarin), and in another embodiment at least 
about 1 mole of alcohol-substituted aminobenzene per every one 
mole of (quinizarin plus leucoquinizarin), and in one embodiment no  
 
more than about 1.05 moles of alcohol-substituted aminobenzene per 
every one mole of (quinizarin plus leucoquinizarin), and in another 
embodiment no more than about 1 mole of alcohol-substituted 
aminobenzene per every one mole of (quinizarin plus leucoquinizarin), 
although the amount of alcohol-substituted aminobenzene can be 
outside of these ranges. </p> <p num="0032">The boric acid, which functions as a catalyst in the reaction 
between the alcohol-substituted aminobenzene and the 
leucoquinizarin, is present in any desired or effective amount, in one 
embodiment about 1 mole of boric acid per every one mole of 
(quinizarin plus leucoquinizarin), although the amount of boric acid can 
be higher or lower than this amount. </p> <p num="0033">When the optional solvent is present, any desired or 
effective solvent can be used. Examples of suitable solvents include 
methanol, ethanol, isopropanol, butanol, ethylene glycol monomethyl 
ether, ethylene glycol dimethyl ether, and the like, as well as mixtures 
thereof. The reactants are present in the solvent in any desired or 
effective amount, in one embodiment at least about 25 grams of 
alcohol-substituted aminobenzene per every one liter of solvent, in 
another embodiment at least about 50 grams of alcohol-substituted 
aminobenzene per every one liter of solvent, and in another 
embodiment at least about 100 grams of alcohol-substituted 
aminobenzene per every one liter of solvent, and in one embodiment 
no more than about 500 grams of alcohol-substituted aminobenzene 
per every one liter of solvent, in another embodiment no more than 
about 250 grams of alcohol-substituted aminobenzene per every one  
 
liter of solvent, and in yet another embodiment no more than about 
125 grams of alcohol-substituted aminobenzene per every one liter of 
solvent, although the amount of solvent can be outside of these 
ranges. </p> <p num="0034">The reaction mixture containing (1) leucoquinizarin and, 
optionally, quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol 
group of the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is as defined hereinabove, (3) 
boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent is heated to any desirable or 
effective temperature, typically the reflux temperature of the selected 
solvent when a solvent is used, in one embodiment at least about 50°C, 
in another embodiment at least about 60°C, and in yet another 
embodiment at least about 75°C, and in one embodiment no more 
than about 150°C, in another embodiment no more than about 120°C, 
and in yet another embodiment no more than about 80°C, although 
the temperature can be outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0035">The reaction mixture containing (1 ) leucoquinizarin and, 
optionally, quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol 
group of the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is as defined hereinabove, (3) 
boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent is heated for any desirable or 
effective period of time, in one embodiment at least about 3 hours, 
and in another embodiment at least about 4 hours, and in one 
embodiment no more than about 24 hours, although the heating time 
can be outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0036">Upon completion of the reaction, the alcohol-substituted 
colorant according to the present invention is formed as a solid and 
can be recovered by cooling and filtering the reaction mixture.  </p><p num="0037">The alcohol-substituted colorant according to the present 
invention can be converted to an ester-substituted colorant according 
to the present invention of the formula 
<img id="img-01130001" orientation="unknown" wi="95" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01130001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
by preparing a reaction mixture by admixing (1) the alcohol-substituted 
colorant, (2) a solvent, and (3) an esterification compound such as an 
anhydride of the formula 
<img id="img-01130002" orientation="unknown" wi="30" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01130002.tif" inline="no" he="33"/> 
in which reaction mixture upon heating is formed an ester-substituted 
colorant according to the present invention as follows (illustrated for an 
embodiment wherein the alcohol-substituted colorant is substituted 
with the alcohol group in the 4- or para-position):  <img id="img-01140001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01140001.tif" inline="no" he="57"/></p><p num="0038">The alcohol-substituted colorant and the anhydride are 
present in any desired or effective relative amounts, in one 
embodiment at least about 1 mole of anhydride per every one mole of 
alcohol-substituted colorant, and in one embodiment no more than 
about 1.1 moles of anhydride per every one mole of alcohol-substituted 
colorant, although the amount of anhydride can be outside 
of these ranges. </p><p num="0039">Examples of suitable solvents include acetic acid, 
propionic acid, formic acid, butyric acid, dimethyl formamide, dimethyl 
sulfoxide, hexamethyl phosphorus triamide (HMPA), tetrahydrofuran, or 
the like, as well as mixtures thereof. The solvent is present in any desired 
or effective amount, in one embodiment at least about 25 grams of 
alcohol-substituted colorant per every one liter of solvent, and in 
another embodiment at least about 100 grams of alcohol-substituted 
colorant per every one liter of solvent, and in one embodiment no 
more than about 200 grams of alcohol-substituted colorant per every 
one liter of solvent, although the amount of solvent can be outside of 
these ranges. </p><p num="0040">The reaction mixture containing the alcohol-substituted 
colorant, the solvent, and the anhydride is heated to any desirable or  
 
effective temperature, in one embodiment at least about 25°C, and in 
another embodiment at least about 40°C, and in one embodiment no 
more than about 100°C, and in another embodiment no more than 
about 60°C, although the temperature can be outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0041">The reaction mixture containing the alcohol-substituted 
colorant, the solvent, and the anhydride is heated for any desirable or 
effective period of time, in one embodiment at least about 2.5 hours, 
and in another embodiment at least about 3 hours, and in one 
embodiment no more than about 5 hours, although the heating time 
can be outside of these ranges. Reaction completion can be 
determined by thin layer chromatography of the reaction mixture to 
detect the presence of unreacted reactants. </p><p num="0042">The ester-substituted colorant can be brominated to form 
a brominated ester-substituted colorant and its salt of the formulae 
<img id="img-01150001" orientation="unknown" wi="97" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01150001.tif" inline="no" he="51"/> 
and  <img id="img-01160001" orientation="unknown" wi="94" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01160001.tif" inline="no" he="54"/> 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom and n is 1, 2, 3, or 4. 
A reaction mixture is prepared by admixing (1 ) the ester-substituted 
colorant, (2) bromine, and (3) a solvent, followed by quenching the 
reaction mixture with water to form a mixture of a brominated ester-substituted 
colorant and its salt, as follows (illustrated for an 
embodiment wherein the ester-substituted colorant is substituted with 
the ester group in the 4- or para-position and wherein the resulting 
brominated ester-substituted colorant has Y=hydrogen and 2 bromine 
atoms in the ortho positions adjacent to the nitrogen atom):  <img id="img-01170001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01170001.tif" inline="no" he="100"/> 
The mixture of products contains both an amine compound and the 
HBr salt thereof. When it is desired to brominate an alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the present invention, it can be desirable in some instances 
to convert the alcohol-substituted colorant to the ester-substituted 
colorant, followed by bromination of the ester-substituted colorant and 
subsequent conversion of the brominated ester-substituted colorant to 
the brominated alcohol-substituted colorant, since the presence of the 
ester group protects the R<sub>1</sub>-containing moiety from undergoing 
reaction with HBr that is generated in the bromination reaction. </p><p num="0043">Bromine (Br<sub>2</sub>) can be provided by any desired or effective 
method, such as by adding elemental bromine, or by generating Br<sub>2</sub> in 
situ in the reaction mixture by the addition of a combination of a 
bromide salt and a bromate salt, as disclosed in, for example, <i>Kirk-Othmer 
Encyclopedia of Chemical Technology,</i> Vol. 4, 4<sup>th</sup> Edition, ISBN  
 
0-471-52672-X, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. (New York 1992), the disclosure of 
which is totally incorporated herein by reference, or the like. </p><p num="0044">The ester-substituted colorant and the bromine are present 
in any desired or effective relative amounts, in one embodiment at 
least about 2 moles of Br<sub>2</sub> per every one mole of ester-substituted 
colorant, in another embodiment at least about 2.5 moles of Br<sub>2</sub> per 
every one mole of ester-substituted colorant, and in yet another 
embodiment at least about 3 moles of Br2 per every one mole of ester-substituted 
colorant, and in one embodiment no more than about 4 
moles of Br<sub>2</sub> per every one mole of ester-substituted colorant, in 
another embodiment no more than about 3.5 moles of Br<sub>2</sub> per every 
one mole of ester-substituted colorant, and in yet another embodiment 
no more than about 3.25 moles of Br<sub>2</sub> per every one mole of ester-substituted 
colorant, although the amount of bromine can be outside 
of these ranges. Higher amounts of bromine lead to higher degrees of 
substitution with bromine atoms. Greater amounts of bromine and/or 
higher reaction temperatures are selected when it is desired to place a 
bromine atom in the Y position. </p><p num="0045">Examples of suitable solvents include acetic acid, 
propionic acid, formic acid, butyric acid, dimethyl formamide, dimethyl 
sulfoxide, hexamethyl phosphorus triamide (HMPA), tetrahydrofuran, or 
the like, as well as mixtures thereof. The solvent is present in any desired 
or effective amount, in one embodiment at least about 25 grams of 
ester-substituted colorant per every one liter of solvent, and in another 
embodiment at least about 100 grams of ester-substituted colorant per 
every one liter of solvent, and in one embodiment no more than about  
 
200 grams of ester-substituted colorant per every one liter of solvent, 
although the amount of solvent can be outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0046">In some instances, the esterification reaction between (1 ) 
the alcohol-substituted colorant, (2) a solvent, and (3) an anhydride to 
form the ester-substituted colorant is carried out immediately prior to 
the bromination reaction to convert the ester-substituted colorant to 
the brominated ester-substituted colorant. In this instance, the ester-substituted 
colorant need not be recovered from its reaction mixture; 
rather, the bromine can be added directly to this mixture upon 
completion of the esterification, and no additional solvent need be 
added. </p><p num="0047">The reaction mixture containing the ester-substituted 
colorant, the bromine, and the solvent generally can be initially heated 
to a temperature of about 30°C to about 40°C. The reaction of the 
ester-substituted colorant and the bromine tends to be exothermic, 
and the reaction mixture is generally maintained at a desirable 
temperature by controlling the rate of addition of bromine as well as by 
any desired external source, such as a heating mantle or the like. The 
reaction mixture containing the ester-substituted colorant, the bromine, 
and the solvent is maintained any desirable or effective temperature, in 
one embodiment at least about 25°C, and in another embodiment at 
least about 50°C, and in one embodiment no more than about 100°C, 
and in another embodiment no more than about 60°C, although the 
temperature can be outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0048">The reaction between the ester-substituted colorant and 
the bromine is allowed to proceed for any desirable or effective period  
 
of time, in one embodiment at least about 5 hours, and in one 
embodiment no more than about 24 hours, although the reaction time 
can be outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0049">Subsequent to completion of the reaction, the reaction 
mixture containing the ester-substituted colorant, the bromine, and the 
solvent can be poured into water to quench the reaction. Any desired 
or effective amount of water can be used, in one embodiment at least 
about 1.5 times as much water by volume as the volume of the 
reaction mixture, in another embodiment at least about 2 times as 
much water by volume as the volume of the reaction mixture, in yet 
another embodiment at least about 2 times as much water by volume 
as the volume of the reaction mixture, and in still another embodiment 
at least about 3 times as much water by volume as the volume of the 
reaction mixture, although the amount of water can be outside of 
these ranges. </p><p num="0050">The mixture of the brominated ester-substituted colorant 
and its salt can be recovered from the reaction mixture as a solid by 
filtration, washed, and dried. </p><p num="0051">The unbrominated alcohol-substituted colorant can also 
be converted to a brominated alcohol-substituted colorant by this 
same process, as follows (illustrated for an embodiment wherein the 
alcohol-substituted colorant is substituted with the ester group in the 4-or 
para-position and wherein the brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant has Y=hydrogen and 2 bromine atoms in the ortho positions 
adjacent to the nitrogen atom):  <img id="img-01210001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01210001.tif" inline="no" he="102"/></p><p num="0052">A brominated alcohol-substituted colorant of the present 
invention of the formula 
<img id="img-01210002" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01210002.tif" inline="no" he="48"/> 
can be prepared by admixing (1 ) a mixture of the brominated ester-substituted 
colorant and its salt, (2) a base, (3) water, and (4) a solvent 
and heating the reaction mixture thus formed to form a brominated 
alcohol-substituted colorant (and also to convert any of the 
ammonium salt form of the brominated ester-substituted colorant to  
 
the amine form), as follows (illustrated for an embodiment wherein the 
brominated ester-substituted colorant is substituted with the ester group 
in the 4- or para-position and wherein the brominated ester-substituted 
colorant has Y=hydrogen and 2 bromine atoms in the ortho positions 
adjacent to the nitrogen atom): 
<img id="img-01220001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01220001.tif" inline="no" he="108"/></p><p num="0053">The brominated ester-substituted colorant and its salt are 
added to a solvent, such as N-methyl pyrrolidinone, dimethyl sulfoxide, 
dimethyl formamide, or the like, as well as mixtures thereof, in any 
desired or effective amount, in one embodiment about 1 gram of 
brominated ester-substituted colorant plus salt thereof per every 4 
grams of solvent, although the amount of solvent can be higher or 
lower than this value.  </p><p num="0054">Any desired or effective base can be used. Examples of 
suitable bases include sodium hydroxide, potassium hydroxide, and the 
like, as well as mixtures thereof. The base is present in any desired or 
effective amount, in one embodiment at least about 1 mole of base 
per mole of (brominated ester-substituted colorant plus salt thereof), in 
another embodiment at least about 1.5 moles of base per mole of 
(brominated ester-substituted colorant plus salt thereof), and in yet 
another embodiment at least about 2 moles of base per mole of 
(brominated ester-substituted colorant plus salt thereof), and in one 
embodiment no more than about 5 moles of base per mole of 
(brominated ester-substituted colorant plus salt thereof), and in another 
embodiment no more than about 3 moles of base per mole of 
(brominated ester-substituted colorant plus salt thereof), although the 
amount of base can be outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0055">The water is present in any desired or effective amount. 
The amount of water added can depend on the solvent used. 
Addition of too much water can cause precipitation of the ester before 
it is hydrolyzed. Hydrolysis can be accomplished with as little as a mole 
of water for every mole of ester. Some water is generated in situ by the 
neutralization of the HBr salt by the base. In one embodiment, the 
water is added with the base, as a (for example) 50 percent aqueous 
solution of the base; for example, when the base is NaOH, every mole 
of NaOH comes with 2.2 moles of water, so that the addition of 1 mole 
of base is accompanied by the addition of 2.2 moles of water, the 
addition of 1.5 moles of base is accompanied by the addition of 3.3 
moles of water, the addition of 3 moles of base is accompanied by the  
 
addition of 6.6 moles of water, the addition of 5 moles of base is 
accompanied by the addition of 11.1 moles of water, and the like. </p><p num="0056">The reaction mixture containing the mixture of the 
brominated ester-substituted colorant and its salt, the base, the water, 
and the solvent is heated to any desirable or effective temperature, in 
one embodiment at least about 50°C, and in another embodiment at 
least about 60°C, and in one embodiment no more than about 70°C, 
and in another embodiment no more than about 60°C, although the 
temperature can be outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0057">The reaction mixture containing the mixture of the 
brominated ester-substituted colorant and its salt, the base, the water, 
and the solvent is heated for any desirable or effective period of time, 
in one embodiment at least about 45 minutes, and in one embodiment 
no more than about 90 minutes, although the heating time can be 
outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0058">Subsequent to completion of the reaction, the reaction 
mixture can be quenched by pouring it into water or by pouring water 
into the reaction mixture. Any desired or effective amount of water 
can be used, in one embodiment at least about 3 times as much water 
by volume as the volume of the reaction mixture, in another 
embodiment at least about 5 times as much water by volume as the 
volume of the reaction mixture, in yet another embodiment at least 
about 10 times as much water by volume as the volume of the reaction 
mixture, and in still another embodiment at least about 20 times as 
much water by volume as the volume of the reaction mixture, although 
the amount of water can be outside of these ranges.  </p><p num="0059">The pH of the quenched reaction mixture can then be 
adjusted by addition of an acid, such as acetic acid, hydrochloric acid, 
hydrobromic acid, sulfuric acid, or the like, as well as mixtures thereof, 
until the desired pH is reached, in one embodiment at least about 5, 
and in another embodiment at least about 7, and in one embodiment 
no more than about 8, although the pH can be outside of these 
ranges. </p><p num="0060">The brominated alcohol-substituted colorant can be 
recovered from the quenched reaction mixture as a solid by filtration, 
followed by washing and drying. </p><p num="0061">The brominated alcohol-substituted colorant can be 
converted to a brominated ester-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01250001" orientation="unknown" wi="93" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01250001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub>' is different from R<sub>2</sub> by admixing (1) the brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant, (2) an esterification compound such as a 
carboxylic acid of the formula R<sub>2</sub>'COOH, wherein R<sub>2</sub>' is as defined 
hereinabove, (3) a solvent, and (4) an optional esterification catalyst 
and heating the reaction mixture, as follows (illustrated for an 
embodiment wherein the brominated alcohol-substituted colorant is 
substituted with the ester group in the 4- or para-position and wherein  
 
the brominated ester-substituted colorant has Y=hydrogen and 2 
bromine atoms in the ortho positions adjacent to the nitrogen atom): 
<img id="img-01260001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01260001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/></p><p num="0062">The brominated alcohol-substituted colorant and the 
carboxylic acid are present in any desired or effective relative 
amounts, in one embodiment at least about 0.9 mole of carboxylic 
acid per every one mole of brominated alcohol-substituted colorant, in 
another embodiment at least about 0.95 mole of carboxylic acid per 
mole of brominated alcohol-substituted colorant, and in yet another 
embodiment at least about 1 mole of carboxylic acid per mole of 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant, and in one embodiment no 
more than about 2 moles of carboxylic acid per mole of brominated 
alcohol-substituted colorant, in another embodiment no more than 
about 1.05 moles of carboxylic acid per mole of brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant, and in yet another embodiment no more than 
about 1 mole of carboxylic acid per mole of brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant, although the relative amounts of carboxylic acid 
and brominated alcohol-substituted colorant can be outside of these 
ranges.  </p><p num="0063">When the optional esterification catalyst is present, any 
desired or effective esterification catalyst can be used, such as paratoluene 
sulfonic acid, dibutyl tin dilaurate, or the like, as well as mixtures 
thereof. The esterification catalyst is present in any desired or effective 
amount, in one embodiment at least about 0.05 mole of esterification 
catalyst per every one mole of brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant, and in one embodiment no more than about 0.5 mole of 
esterification catalyst per mole of brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant, although the amount of esterification catalyst can be outside 
of these ranges. </p><p num="0064">Any desired or effective solvent can be used. Examples of 
suitable solvents include xylene, toluene, benzene, chlorobenzene, 
nitrobenzene, dichlorobenzene, and the like, as well as mixtures 
thereof. The reactants are present in the solvent in any desired or 
effective amount, in one embodiment at least about 25 grams of 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant per every one liter of solvent, 
in another embodiment at least about 50 grams of brominated 
alcohol-substituted colorant per every one liter of solvent, and in yet 
another embodiment at least about 100 grams of brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant per every one liter of solvent, and in one 
embodiment no more than about 200 grams of brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant per every one liter of solvent, in another 
embodiment no more than about 150 grams of brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant per every one liter of solvent, and in yet another 
embodiment no more than about 100 grams of brominated alcohol-substituted  
 
colorant per every one liter of solvent, although the amount 
of solvent can be outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0065">The reaction mixture containing the brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant, the carboxylic acid, the solvent, and the optional 
esterification catalyst is heated to any desirable or effective 
temperature, typically the reflux temperature of the selected solvent, in 
one embodiment at least about 100°C, and in one embodiment no 
more than about 130°C, although the temperature can be outside of 
these ranges. </p><p num="0066">The reaction mixture containing the brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant, the carboxylic acid, the solvent, and the optional 
esterification catalyst is heated for any desirable or effective period of 
time, in one embodiment at least about 2 hours, in another 
embodiment at least about 24 hours, and in one embodiment no more 
than about 72 hours, and in another embodiment no more than about 
48 hours, although the heating time can be outside of these ranges. </p><p num="0067">The colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01280001" orientation="unknown" wi="94" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01280001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/> 
can be recovered from the reaction mixture as a solid by filtration, 
followed by washing and drying. If desired, purification can be carried 
out by filtration, redissolution in the solvent, heating, cooling,  
 
precipitating the colorant from the solution, filtering, washing the 
colorant with a solvent such as methanol, ethanol, or the like, and 
repeating this cycle until thin layer chromatography of the collected 
solid indicates that there is no detectable unreacted reactant present 
in the solid. </p><p num="0068">The unbrominated alcohol-substituted colorant can also 
be converted to an unbrominated ester-substituted colorant by this 
same process, as follows (illustrated for an embodiment wherein the 
alcohol-substituted colorant is substituted with the ester group in the 4-or 
para-position): 
<img id="img-01290001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01290001.tif" inline="no" he="55"/> 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom, n is an integer of 0, 1, 
2, 3, or 4, R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an arylalkylene group, and R<sub>2</sub> is an 
alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl group can  
 
be prepared by a process which comprises preparing a first reaction 
mixture by admixing (1) leucoquinizarin and, optionally, quinizarin, (2) an 
aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol group of the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, 
(3) boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent, and heating the first reaction 
mixture to prepare an alcohol-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01300001" orientation="unknown" wi="80" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01300001.tif" inline="no" he="49"/> 
followed by brominating and esterifying the alcohol-substituted 
colorant thus prepared, wherein either esterification can take place 
before bromination or bromination can take place before 
esterification. </p><p num="0069">In one specific embodiment, brominated ester-substituted 
colorants according to the present invention of the formula 
<img id="img-01300002" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01300002.tif" inline="no" he="50"/> 
can be prepared by a process which comprises (a) preparing a first 
reaction mixture by admixing (1) leucoquinizarin and, optionally,  
 
quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol group of 
the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an arylalkylene 
group, (3) boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent, and heating the first 
reaction mixture to prepare an alcohol-substituted colorant of the 
formula 
<img id="img-01310001" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01310001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
(b) preparing a second reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) the alcohol-substituted 
colorant, (2) a solvent, and (3) an anhydride of the formula 
<img id="img-01310002" orientation="unknown" wi="23" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01310002.tif" inline="no" he="31"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group and heating the second reaction mixture to form a first 
ester-substituted colorant of the formula  <img id="img-01320001" orientation="unknown" wi="99" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01320001.tif" inline="no" he="55"/> 
(c) forming a third reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) the first ester-substituted 
colorant, (2) bromine, and (3) a solvent followed by 
quenching the third reaction mixture with water to form a brominated 
ester-substituted colorant and a salt thereof, of the formulae 
<img id="img-01320002" orientation="unknown" wi="96" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01320002.tif" inline="no" he="51"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01320003" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01320003.tif" inline="no" he="51"/> 
 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom and n is an integer of 
1, 2, 3, or 4; (d) preparing a fourth reaction mixture by admixing (1) the 
brominated ester-substituted colorant and the salt thereof, (2) a base, 
(3) water, and (4) a solvent and heating the fourth reaction mixture to 
form a brominated alcohol-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01330001" orientation="unknown" wi="85" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01330001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/> 
and (e) preparing a fifth reaction mixture by admixing (1) the 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant, (2) a carboxylic acid of the 
formula R<sub>2</sub>'COOH, wherein R<sub>2</sub>' is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an 
arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl group, and wherein R<sub>2</sub>' is different from 
R<sub>2</sub>, (3) an optional esterification catalyst, and (4) a solvent and heating 
the fifth reaction mixture to form a second ester-substituted colorant of 
the formula 
<img id="img-01330002" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01330002.tif" inline="no" he="59"/> 
 
This process is particularly suitable for preparation of colorants wherein 
R<sub>2</sub> has 4 or fewer carbon atoms and wherein R<sub>2</sub>' has more than 4 
carbon atoms. </p><p num="0070">Brominated ester-substituted colorants according to the 
present invention of the formula 
<img id="img-01340001" orientation="unknown" wi="94" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01340001.tif" inline="no" he="51"/> 
can also be prepared by a process which comprises (a) preparing a 
first reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) leucoquinizarin and, optionally, 
quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol group of 
the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an arylalkylene 
group, (3) boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent, and heating the first 
reaction mixture to prepare an alcohol-substituted colorant of the 
formula 
<img id="img-01340002" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01340002.tif" inline="no" he="53"/> 
 
(b) preparing a second reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) the alcohol-substituted 
colorant, (2) a carboxylic acid of the formula R<sub>2</sub>COOH,
 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an 
alkylaryl group, (3) an optional esterification catalyst, and (4) a solvent 
and heating the second reaction mixture to form an ester-substituted 
colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01350001" orientation="unknown" wi="96" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01350001.tif" inline="no" he="51"/> 
and (c) forming a third reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) the ester-substituted 
colorant, (2) bromine, and (3) a solvent followed by 
quenching the third reaction mixture with water to form a brominated 
ester-substituted colorant and a salt thereof, of the formulae 
<img id="img-01350002" orientation="unknown" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01350002.tif" inline="no" he="50"/> 
and  <img id="img-01360001" orientation="unknown" wi="93" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01360001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom and n is an integer of 
1, 2, 3, or 4. </p><p num="0071">Brominated ester-substituted colorants according to the 
present invention of the formula 
<img id="img-01360002" orientation="unknown" wi="95" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01360002.tif" inline="no" he="49"/> 
can also be prepared by a process which comprises (a) preparing a 
first reaction mixture by admixing (1 ) leucoquinizarin and, optionally, 
quinizarin, (2) an aminobenzene substituted with an alcohol group of 
the formula -R<sub>1</sub>-OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is an alkylene group or an arylalkylene 
group, (3) boric acid, and (4) an optional solvent, and heating the first 
reaction mixture to prepare an alcohol-substituted colorant of the 
formula  <img id="img-01370001" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01370001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
(b) preparing a second reaction mixture by admixing (1) the alcohol-substituted 
colorant, (2) bromine, and (3) a solvent followed by 
quenching the second reaction mixture with water to form a 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant and a salt thereof, of the 
formulae 
<img id="img-01370002" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01370002.tif" inline="no" he="49"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01370003" orientation="unknown" wi="80" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01370003.tif" inline="no" he="56"/> 
 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom and n is an integer of 
0, 1, 2, 3, or 4; and (c) forming a third reaction mixture by admixing (1) 
the brominated alcohol-substituted colorant, (2) a carboxylic acid of 
the formula R<sub>2</sub>COOH, wherein R<sub>2</sub> is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an 
arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl group, (3) an optional esterification 
catalyst, and (4) a solvent and heating the third reaction mixture to 
form a brominated ester-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01380001" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01380001.tif" inline="no" he="49"/> 
One disadvantage of running the bromination on the unprotected 
alcohol is that from about 10 to about 20 percent of the alcohol can 
be converted by the evolved HBr to the alkylbromide derivative; this 
derivative generally is not believed to be convertd to the desired ester 
in the next step of the synthesis and generally is removed by 
recrystallization. Nevertheless, in some embodiments, bromination of 
the unprotected alcohol can also be desirable. </p><p num="0072">Urethane-substituted colorants according to the present 
invention of the formula  <img id="img-01390001" orientation="unknown" wi="94" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01390001.tif" inline="no" he="56"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01390002" orientation="unknown" wi="98" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01390002.tif" inline="no" he="54"/> 
can be prepared by any desired or effective method. One specific 
method entails the reaction of either an alcohol-substituted colorant 
according to the present invention of the formula 
<img id="img-01390003" orientation="unknown" wi="77" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01390003.tif" inline="no" he="49"/> 
or a brominated alcohol-substituted colorant according to the present 
invention of the formula  <img id="img-01400001" orientation="unknown" wi="83" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01400001.tif" inline="no" he="56"/> 
with an isocyanate. Isocyanates react with alcohols to form urethanes. 
For example, a monoisocyanate reacts with an alcohol to form a 
urethane as follows: 
<img id="img-01400002" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01400002.tif" inline="no" he="21"/> 
wherein R<sub>a</sub> and R<sub>b</sub> each, independently of the other, is an alkyl group 
(including linear, branched, saturated, unsaturated, cyclic, 
unsubstituted, and substituted alkyl groups, and wherein hetero atoms, 
such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, phosphorus, and the like either 
may or may not be present in the alkyl group), typically with from 
about 5 to about 100 carbon atoms, although the number of carbon 
atoms can be outside of this range, an aryl group (including 
unsubstituted and substituted aryl groups, and wherein hetero atoms, 
such as oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, phosphorus, and the like either 
may or may not be present in the aryl group), typically with from about 
5 to about 20 carbon atoms, although the number of carbon atoms 
can be outside of this range, an arylalkyl group (including unsubstituted 
and substituted arylalkyl groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as  
 
oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or 
may not be present in either or both of the alkyl portion and the aryl 
portion of the arylalkyl group), typically with from about 6 to about 50 
carbon atoms, although the number of carbon atoms can be outside 
of this range, or an alkylaryl group (including unsubstituted and 
substituted alkylaryl groups, and wherein hetero atoms, such as oxygen, 
nitrogen, sulfur, silicon, phosphorus, and the like either may or may not 
be present in either or both of the alkyl portion and the aryl portion of 
the alkylaryl group), typically with from about 6 to about 50 carbon 
atoms, although the number of carbon atoms can be outside of this 
range, and wherein the substituents on the substituted alkyl, alkylene, 
aryl, arylene, arylalkyl, arylalkylene, alkylaryl, and alkylarylene groups 
can be (but are not limited to) hydroxy groups, halogen atoms, amine 
groups, imine groups, ammonium groups, cyano groups, pyridine 
groups, pyridinium groups, ether groups, aldehyde groups, ketone 
groups, ester groups, amide groups, carbonyl groups, thiocarbonyl 
groups, sulfate groups, sulfonate groups, sulfide groups, sulfoxide 
groups, phosphine groups, phosphonium groups, phosphate groups, 
nitrile groups, mercapto groups, nitro groups, nitroso groups, sulfone 
groups, acyl groups, acid anhydride groups, azide groups, azo groups, 
cyanato groups, isocyanato groups, thiocyanato groups, 
isothiocyanato groups, mixtures thereof, and the like, wherein two or 
more substituents can be joined together to form a ring. Diisocyanates 
react similarly; for example, isophorone diisocyanate reacts with two 
moles of alcohol to form a diurethane as follows:  <img id="img-01420001" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01420001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/></p><p num="0073">Examples of suitable isocyanates include 
monoisocyanates, diisocyanates, triisocyanates, copolymers of a 
diisocyanate, copolymers of a triisocyanate, polyisocyanates (having 
more than three isocyanate functional groups), and the like, as well as 
mixtures thereof. Examples of monoisocyanates include 
octadecylisocyanate; hexadecylisocyanate; octylisocyanate; butyl 
and t-butylisocyanate; cyclohexyl isocyanate; adamantyl isocyanate; 
ethylisocyanatoacetate; ethoxycarbonylisocyanate; 
phenylisocyanate; alphamethylbenzyl isocyanate; 2-phenylcyclopropyl 
isocyanate; benzylisocyanate; 2-ethylphenylisocyanate; 
benzoylisocyanate; meta and paratolylisocyanate; 
2-, 3-, or 4-nitrophenylisocyanates; 2-ethoxyphenyl 
isocyanate; 3-methoxyphenyl isocyanate; 4-methoxyphenylisocyanate; 
ethyl 4-isocyanatobenzoate; 2,b-dimethylphenylisocyante; 1-naphthylisocyanate; 
(naphthyl)ethylisocyantes; and the like, as well as 
mixtures thereof. Examples of diisocyanates include isophorone 
diisocyanate (IPDI); toluene diisocyanate (TDI); diphenylmethane-4,4'-diisocyanate 
(MDI); hydrogenated diphenylmethane-4,4'-diisocyanate 
(H12MDI); tetra-methyl xylene diisocyanate (TMXDI); hexamethylene-1,6-diisocyanate 
(HDI); hexamethylene-1,6-diisocyanate; napthylene-1,5-diisocyanate; 
3,3'-dimethoxy-4,4'-biphenyldiisocyanate; 3,3'-dimethyl-4,4'-bimethyl-4,4'-biphenyldiisocyanate;  
 
phenylene 
diisocyanate; 4,4'-biphenyldiisocyanate; trimethylhexamethylene 
diisocyanate; tetramethylene xylene diisocyanate; 4,4'-methylenebis(2,6-diethylphenyl 
isocyanate); 1,12-diisocyanatododecane; 
1,5-diisocyanato-2-methylpentane; 1,4-diisocyanatobutane; 
dimer diisocyanate and cyclohexylene 
diisocyanate and its isomers; uretidione dimers of HDI; and the like, as 
well as mixtures thereof. Examples of triisocyanates or their equivalents 
include the trimethylolpropane trimer of TDI, and the like, isocyanurate 
trimers of TDI, HDI, IPDI, and the like, and biuret trimers of TDI, HDI, IPDI, 
and the like, as well as mixtures thereof. Examples of higher isocyanate 
functionalities include copolymers of TDI/HDI, and the like, and MDI 
oligomers, as well as mixtures thereof. </p><p num="0074">Any suitable reaction condition for making urethane 
compounds by condensing alcohols with isocyanates can be used to 
prepare urethane-substituted colorants according to the present 
invention. Typically (although not necessarily), the reaction is carried 
out at elevated temperatures (for example, from about 60 to about 
160°C) in the presence of an optional urethane reaction catalyst, such 
as dibutyl tindilaurate, bismuth tris-neodecanoate, cobalt benzoate, 
lithium acetate, stannous octoate, triethylamine, or the like. In a 
specific embodiment, the reaction conditions are conducted in an 
inert atmosphere, such as argon or nitrogen gas or other suitable gases, 
to prevent oxidizing or yellowing of the reaction products and to 
prevent undesirable side reactions. The reaction can employ an inert 
solvent, such as toluene or the like, or can be performed neat (i.e.,  
 
without a solvent). The mole ratio of reactants is adjusted so that the 
isocyanate functionalities are completely consumed in the reaction 
with a slight molar excess of alcohol-substituted colorant typically 
remaining. The reactants can be added together in any order and/or 
added to the reaction as physical mixtures. If desired, reaction 
conditions and the order of the addition of reactants can be controlled 
for several reasons, such as to provide a controlled exothermic 
reaction, to tailor the distribution of molecules in the antioxidant-containing 
material, or the like. When doing these adjustments, the 
different reactivities to isocyanates of alcohols versus amines can be 
employed, as well as the different reactivities of the two separate 
isocyanate groups on IPDI. See, for example, J. H. Saunders and K. C. 
Frisch's "Polyurethanes Part I, Chemistry" published by Interscience of 
New York, N.Y. in 1962 and Olin Chemicals' LUXATE® IM isophorone 
diisocyanate technical product information sheet, which provide 
further explanation of this chemistry. </p><p num="0075">Specific embodiments of the invention will now be 
described in detail. These examples are intended to be illustrative, and 
the invention is not limited to the materials, conditions, or process 
parameters set forth in these embodiments. All parts and percentages 
are by weight unless otherwise indicated.  </p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE I</u></heading><heading><u style="single">PART A</u></heading><p num="0076">In a glass reaction flask were combined 73 grams of 
sublimed quinizarin (obtained from Aceto Corp., Lake Success, NY), 49 
grams of leucoquinizarin (obtained from Aceto Corp.), 66 grams of 4-aminobenzene 
ethanol (obtained from Aceto Corp.), 31 grams of boric 
acid (obtained from Aldrich Chemical Co., Milwaukee, WI), and 780 
grams of methanol (obtained from JT Baker, Phillipsburg, NJ). The 
materials were mixed and heated until the solvent refluxed at about 
66°C. </p><p num="0077">After about 16 hours of reflux the reaction was complete, 
having generated an alcohol-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01450001" orientation="unknown" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01450001.tif" inline="no" he="54"/> 
The reaction mixture was cooled and filtered. The product filter cake 
was dried in air at ambient temperature. </p><p num="0078">The spectral strength of the alcohol-substituted colorant 
was determined using a spectrophotographic procedure based on the 
measurement of the colorant in solution by dissolving the colorant in 
toluene and measuring the absorbance using a Perkin Elmer Lambda 
2S UV/VIS spectrophotometer. The spectral strength of the alcohol-substituted 
colorant was measured as about 21,000 mL Absorbance  
 
Units per gram at absorption λ<sub>max</sub>, indicating a purity of about 80 
percent. </p><heading><u style="single">PART B-1</u></heading><p num="0079">In a glass reaction flask were combined 8 grams of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part A of this Example, 68 
grams of glacial acetic acid (obtained from JT Baker), 13 grams of 
propionic acid (obtained from Aldrich Chemical Co.), and 2.3 grams of 
acetic anhydride (obtained from Aldrich Chemical Co.). The materials 
were mixed and heated to a reflux temperature of about 121°C. After 
about 4 hours of reflux, the reaction was complete and the reaction 
mixture contained an ethyl acetate-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01460001" orientation="unknown" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01460001.tif" inline="no" he="61"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-2</u></heading><p num="0080">In a glass reaction flask were combined 12 grams of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part A of this Example, 10.2 
grams of dimer diisocyanate (obtained from Cognis; these materials 
are also described in, for example, <i>Kirk-Othmer Encyclopedia of 
Chemical Technology</i> 1979, volume 7,3<sup>rd</sup> edition, p. 768-782, John Wiley  
 
and Sons, Inc., the disclosure of which is totally incorporated herein by 
reference), and 1 drop of FASCAT 4202 catalyst (obtained from 
Atofina). The materials were mixed and heated to a temperature of 
about 120°C. After about 1 hour of heating, the reaction mixture 
became very thick, so the temperature was raised to about 150°C and 
stirred for 4 hours. IR analysis showed that the reaction was complete 
(no isocyanate peak) and the reaction mixture contained a dimer-diurethane-substituted 
colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01470001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01470001.tif" inline="no" he="44"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formula  <img id="img-01480001" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01480001.tif" inline="no" he="101"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-3</u></heading><p num="0081">In a glass reaction flask fitted with a Dean-Stark trap were 
combined 5 grams of the alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part 
A of this Example, 60 grams of xylenes (obtained from Aldrich Chemical 
Co.), 8.4 grams of the Guerbet acid 2-hexadecyl-1-eicosanoic acid 
(ISOCARB 36, obtained from Condea Vista, Austin, TX), and 0.25 grams 
of p-toluene sulfonic acid (obtained from Boliden Intertrade). The 
materials were mixed and heated to a reflux in an oil bath at 150°C. 
After about 19 hours of reflux, the reaction was complete and the 
reaction mixture contained an ISOCARB-36-ester substituted colorant of 
the formula  <img id="img-01490001" orientation="unknown" wi="122" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01490001.tif" inline="no" he="67"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-4</u></heading><p num="0082">In a glass reaction flask fitted with a Dean-Stark trap were 
combined 15 grams of the alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in 
Part A of this Example, 200 grams of xylenes (obtained from Aldrich 
Chemical Co.), 14.3 grams dimer acid hydrogenated (known as PRIPOL 
1006, obtained from Unichema International; these materials are also 
described in, for example, <i>Kirk-Othmer Encyclopedia of Chemical 
Technology</i> 1979, volume 7, 3<sup>rd</sup> edition, p. 768-782, John Wiley and Sons, 
Inc., the disclosure of which is totally incorporated herein by reference), 
and 0.5 grams of p-toluene sulfonic acid (obtained from Boliden 
Intertrade). The materials were mixed and heated to a reflux in an oil 
bath at 150°C. After about 19 hours of reflux, the reaction was 
complete and the reaction mixture contained a dimer acid disubstituted 
colorant of the formula  <img id="img-01500001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01500001.tif" inline="no" he="48"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formula 
<img id="img-01500002" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01500002.tif" inline="no" he="93"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-5</u></heading><p num="0083">In a glass reaction flask were combined 3.0 grams of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part A of this Example and 6.4 
grams of hydroabietyl alcohol (obtained as Abitol E from Hercules Inc., 
Wilmington DE). The mixture was heated to a temperature of about  
 
140°C until it was homogeneous. 1 drop of FASCAT 4202 catalyst 
(obtained from Atofina) and 3.2 grams of isophorone diisocyanate 
(DESMODUR I, obtained from Bayer Corp., Pittsburgh, PA) were then 
added and the materials were mixed and heated to a temperature of 
about 140°C. After about 5 hours of heating, IR analysis showed that 
the reaction was complete (no isocyanate peak) and the reaction 
mixture contained a diurethane-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01510001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01510001.tif" inline="no" he="44"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART C-1</u></heading><p num="0084">About 91 grams of the reaction mixture containing the 
ethyl acetate-substituted colorant from Part B-1 of this Example was 
charged into a glass reaction flask. The mixture was cooled to a 
minimum of 30°C. While mixing, about 9 grams of bromine (obtained 
from Aldrich Chemical Co.) was added to the mixture at a rate such 
that the temperature remained below about 40°C. The mixture was 
then heated to about 40°C. After about 24 hours of mixing the reaction 
was complete. </p><p num="0085">The reaction mixture was then quenched into 234 grams of 
deionized water and allowed to cool to room temperature. The 
reaction mixture was then filtered. The filter cake was reslurried and 
filtered twice in deionized water to remove most of the residual acetic  
 
acid. The filter cake was then dried in a 60°C oven. This filter cake 
contained a mixture of brominated ethyl acetate-substituted colorants 
of the formulae 
<img id="img-01520001" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01520001.tif" inline="no" he="60"/></p><p num="0086">The spectral strength of the brominated ethyl acetate-substituted 
colorant was determined using a spectrophotographic 
procedure based on the measurement of the colorant in solution by 
dissolving the colorant in toluene and measuring the absorbance using 
a Perkin Elmer Lambda 2S UV/VIS spectrophotometer. The spectral 
strength of the brominated ethyl acetate-substituted colorant was 
measured as about 15,000 mL Absorbance Units per gram at absorption 
λ<sub>max</sub>. This spectral strength indicated a purity of about 60 percent. </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-2</u></heading><p num="0087">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the 
colorant from Part B-2 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae  <img id="img-01530001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01530001.tif" inline="no" he="50"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01530002" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01530002.tif" inline="no" he="46"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formulae  <img id="img-01540001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01540001.tif" inline="no" he="98"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01540002" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01540002.tif" inline="no" he="93"/> 
will be obtained.  </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-3</u></heading><p num="0088">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the 
colorant from Part B-3 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae 
<img id="img-01550001" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01550001.tif" inline="no" he="57"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01550002" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01550002.tif" inline="no" he="61"/> 
will be obtained. </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-4</u></heading><p num="0089">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the  
 
colorant from Part B-4 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae 
<img id="img-01560001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01560001.tif" inline="no" he="41"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01560002" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01560002.tif" inline="no" he="42"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formula  <img id="img-01570001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01570001.tif" inline="no" he="98"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01570002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01570002.tif" inline="no" he="93"/> 
will be obtained.  </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-5</u></heading><p num="0090">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the 
colorant from Part B-5 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae 
<img id="img-01580001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01580001.tif" inline="no" he="43"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01580002" orientation="unknown" wi="148" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01580002.tif" inline="no" he="45"/> 
will be obtained. </p><heading><u style="single">PART D</u></heading><p num="0091">In a glass reaction flask were combined 18 grams of the 
mixture of the brominated ethyl acetate-substituted colorant and its 
salt prepared in Part C-1 of this Example, 72 grams of N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone 
(obtained from Aldrich Chemical Co.), 4 grams of sodium 
hydroxide (obtained from Aldrich Chemical Co.), and 4 grams of  
 
deionized water. The materials were mixed and heated to about 60°C. 
After about 3 hours the reaction was complete. </p><p num="0092">The reaction mixture was then quenched into 234 grams of 
deionized water and allowed to cool to room temperature. Glacial 
acetic acid was added until the solution reached a pH of between 6 
and 7. The reaction mixture was then filtered. The filter cake was 
reslurried and filtered twice in deionized water to remove most of the 
residual N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone. The filter cake was then dried in a 
60°C oven. This filter cake contained a brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01590001" orientation="unknown" wi="93" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01590001.tif" inline="no" he="51"/> 
The spectral strength of the brominated alcohol-substituted colorant 
was determined using a spectrophotographic procedure based on the 
measurement of the colorant in solution by dissolving the colorant in an 
equal mixture of toluene and tetrahydrofuran and measuring the 
absorbance using a Perkin Elmer Lambda 2S UV/VIS 
spectrophotometer. The spectral strength of the brominated alcohol-substituted 
colorant was measured as about 16,000 mL Absorbance 
Units per gram at absorption λ<sub>max</sub>. This spectral strength indicated a 
purity of about 60 percent.  </p><heading><u style="single">PART E</u></heading><p num="0093">In a glass reaction flask were combined 16 grams of the 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part D of this 
Example, 31 grams of UNICID® 700 (a material containing carboxylic 
acid of the formula R<sub>2</sub>COOH wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear alkyl group having an 
average of about 50 carbon atoms, also containing other 
unfunctionalized wax materials in an amount of up to about 25 percent 
by weight; obtained from Baker Petrolite, Sugarland, TX), 152 grams of 
xylene (obtained from Tarr, Inc., Portland, OR), and 0.6 grams of paratoluenesulfonic 
acid (obtained from Capital Resin Corp., Columbus, 
OH). The materials were mixed and heated to a reflux temperature of 
about 143°C. After about 7 hours, the reaction was complete. </p><p num="0094">The reaction mixture was then cooled to 40°C and filtered. 
The filter cake was reslurried and filtered two more times in methanol to 
remove residual xylene. The filter cake was then dried in air at ambient 
temperature. This filter cake contained a colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01600001" orientation="unknown" wi="106" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01600001.tif" inline="no" he="58"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 
carbon atoms.  </p><p num="0095">The spectral strength of the colorant was determined using 
a spectrophotographic procedure based on the measurement of the 
colorant in solution by dissolving the colorant in an equal mixture of 
toluene and tetrahydrofuran and measuring the absorbance using a 
Perkin Elmer Lambda 2S UV/VIS spectrophotometer. The spectral 
strength of the colorant was measured as about 5,000 mL Absorbance 
Units per gram at absorption λ<sub>max</sub>. This spectral strength indicated a 
purity of about 40 percent. </p><heading><u style="single">PART F</u></heading><p num="0096">Compounds of the formulae shown in Parts C-1 through 
C-5 of this Example are prepared by reversing steps B and C of this 
Example. More specifically, the alcohol-substituted colorant prepared 
in Part A of this Example is first subjected to bromination as described in 
Parts C-1 through C-5 of this Example, and the resulting brominated 
alcohol-substituted colorants are then subjected to esterification as 
described in Parts C-1 through C-5 of this Example. </p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE <b>II</b></u></heading><heading><u style="single">PART A</u></heading><p num="0097">In a glass reaction flask are combined 73 grams of 
sublimed quinizarin (available from Aceto Corp., Lake Success, NY), 49 
grams of leucoquinizarin (available from Aceto Corp.), 66 grams of 3-aminobenzene 
ethanol (available from Frinton Labs, Vineland, NJ), 31 
grams of boric acid (available from Aldrich Chemical Co., Milwaukee, 
WI), and 780 grams of methanol (available from JT Baker, Phillipsburg,  
 
NJ). The materials are mixed and heated until the solvent refluxes at 
about 66°C. After about 16 hours of reflux, it is believed that the 
reaction will be complete, having generated an alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01620001" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01620001.tif" inline="no" he="59"/> 
The reaction mixture is cooled and filtered. The product filter cake is 
dried in air at ambient temperature. The spectral strength of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant is determined using a 
spectrophotographic procedure based on the measurement of the 
colorant in solution by dissolving the colorant in toluene and measuring 
the absorbance using a Perkin Elmer Lambda 2S UV/VIS 
spectrophotometer. The spectral strength of the alcohol-substituted 
colorant is believed to be measured as about 21,000 mL Absorbance 
Units per gram at absorption λ<sub>max</sub>. </p><heading><u style="single">PART B-1</u></heading><p num="0098">In a glass reaction flask are combined 8 grams of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part A of this Example, 68 
grams of glacial acetic acid (available from JT Baker), 13 grams of 
propionic acid (available from Aldrich Chemical Co.), and 2.3 grams of  
 
acetic anhydride (available from Aldrich Chemical Co.). The materials 
are mixed and heated to a reflux temperature of about 121°C. After 
about 4 hours of reflux, the reaction is complete and the reaction 
mixture contains an ethyl acetate-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01630001" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01630001.tif" inline="no" he="67"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-2</u></heading><p num="0099">In a glass reaction flask are combined 12 grams of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part A of this Example, 10.2 
grams of dimer diisocyanate (available from Cognis; these materials 
are also described in, for example, <i>Kirk-Othmer Encyclopedia of 
Chemical Technology</i> 1979, volume 7, 3<sup>rd</sup> edition, p. 768-782, John Wiley 
and Sons, Inc., the disclosure of which is totally incorporated herein by 
reference), and 1 drop of FASCAT 4202 catalyst (available from 
Atofina). The materials are mixed and heated to a temperature of 
about 120°C. After about 1 hour of heating, the reaction mixture 
becomes very thick, so the temperature is raised to about 150°C and 
stirred for 4 hours. It is believed that IR analysis will show that the 
reaction is complete (no isocyanate peak), and that the reaction  
 
mixture will contain a dimer-diurethane-substituted colorant of the 
formula 
<img id="img-01640001" orientation="unknown" wi="154" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01640001.tif" inline="no" he="53"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formula 
<img id="img-01640002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01640002.tif" inline="no" he="102"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-3</u></heading><p num="0100">In a glass reaction flask fitted with a Dean-Stark trap are 
combined 5 grams of the alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part 
A of this Example, 60 grams of xylenes (available from Aldrich Chemical 
Co.), 8.4 grams of the Guerbet acid 2-hexadecyl-1-eicosanoic acid 
(ISOCARB 36, available from Condea Vista, Austin, TX), and 0.25 grams 
of p-toluene sulfonic acid (available from Boliden Intertrade). The 
materials are mixed and heated to a reflux in an oil bath at 150°C. 
After about 19 hours of reflux, it is believed that the reaction will be 
complete and that the reaction mixture will contain an ISOCARB-36-ester 
substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01650001" orientation="unknown" wi="108" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01650001.tif" inline="no" he="66"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-4</u></heading><p num="0101">In a glass reaction flask fitted with a Dean-Stark trap are 
combined 15 grams of the alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in 
Part A of this Example, 200 grams of xylenes (available from Aldrich 
Chemical Co.), 14.3 grams of dimer acid hydrogenated (known as 
PRIPOL 1006, available from Unichema International; these materials  
 
are also described in, for example, <i>Kirk-Othmer Encyclopedia of 
Chemical Technology</i> 1979, volume 7,3<sup>rd</sup> edition, p. 768-782, John Wiley 
and Sons, Inc., the disclosure of which is totally incorporated herein by 
reference), and 0.5 grams of p-toluene sulfonic acid (available from 
Boliden Intertrade). The materials are mixed and heated to a reflux in 
an oil bath at 150°C. After about 19 hours of reflux, it is believed that 
the reaction will be complete and that the reaction mixture will contain 
a dimer acid di-ester substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01660001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01660001.tif" inline="no" he="58"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formula  <img id="img-01670001" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01670001.tif" inline="no" he="113"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-5</u></heading><p num="0102">In a glass reaction flask are combined 3.0 grams of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part A of this Example and 6.4 
grams of hydroabietyl alcohol (available as Abitol E from Hercules Inc., 
Wilmington, DE) and the mixture is heated to a temperature of about 
140°C until it is homogeneous. 1 drop of FASCAT 4202 catalyst 
(available from Atofina) and 3.2 grams of isophorone diisocyanate 
(available as DESMODUR I from Bayer Corp., Pittsburgh, PA) are then 
added and the materials are mixed and heated to a temperature of 
about 140°C. After about 5 hours of heating, it is believed that IR 
analysis will show that the reaction is complete (no isocyanate peak)  
 
and that the reaction mixture will contain a diurethane-substituted 
colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01680001" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01680001.tif" inline="no" he="61"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART C-1</u></heading><p num="0103">About 91 grams of the reaction mixture containing the 
ethyl acetate-substituted colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is 
charged into a glass reaction flask. The mixture is cooled to a minimum 
of 30°C. While mixing, about 9 grams of bromine (available from 
Aldrich Chemical Co.) is added to the mixture at a rate such that the 
temperature remains below about 40°C. The mixture is then heated to 
about 40°C. After about 24 hours of mixing, the reaction is complete. 
The reaction mixture is then quenched into 234 grams of deionized 
water, allowed to cool to room temperature, and filtered. The filter 
cake is reslurried and filtered twice in deionized water to remove most 
of the residual acetic acid. The filter cake is then dried in a 60°C oven. 
It is believed that this filter cake will contain a mixture of brominated 
ethyl acetate-substituted colorants of the formulae  <img id="img-01690001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01690001.tif" inline="no" he="74"/> 
The spectral strength of the brominated ethyl acetate-substituted 
colorant is determined using a spectrophotographic procedure based 
on the measurement of the colorant in solution by dissolving the 
colorant in toluene and measuring the absorbance using a Perkin Elmer 
Lambda 2S UV/VIS spectrophotometer. It is believed that the spectral 
strength of the alcohol-substituted colorant will be measured as about 
21,000 mL Absorbance Units per gram at absorption λ<sub>max</sub>. </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-2</u></heading><p num="0104">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the 
colorant from Part B-2 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae  <img id="img-01700001" orientation="unknown" wi="158" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01700001.tif" inline="no" he="58"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01700002" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01700002.tif" inline="no" he="52"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formulae  <img id="img-01710001" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01710001.tif" inline="no" he="102"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01710002" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01710002.tif" inline="no" he="97"/> 
 
will be obtained. </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-3</u></heading><p num="0105">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the 
colorant from Part B-3 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae 
<img id="img-01720001" orientation="unknown" wi="118" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01720001.tif" inline="no" he="63"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01720002" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01720002.tif" inline="no" he="66"/> 
will be obtained.  </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-4</u></heading><p num="0106">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the 
colorant from Part B-4 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae 
<img id="img-01730001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01730001.tif" inline="no" he="59"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01730002" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01730002.tif" inline="no" he="58"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formula  <img id="img-01740001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01740001.tif" inline="no" he="107"/> 
and  <img id="img-01750001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01750001.tif" inline="no" he="111"/> 
will be obtained. </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-5</u></heading><p num="0107">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the 
colorant from Part B-5 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae  <img id="img-01760001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01760001.tif" inline="no" he="59"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01760002" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01760002.tif" inline="no" he="58"/> 
will be obtained. </p><heading><u style="single">PART D</u></heading><p num="0108">In a glass reaction flask are combined 18 grams of the 
mixture of the brominated ethyl acetate-substituted colorant and its 
salt prepared in Part C-1 of this Example, 72 grams of N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone 
(available from Aldrich Chemical Co.), 4 grams of sodium 
hydroxide (available from Aldrich Chemical Co.), and 4 grams of 
deionized water. The material is mixed and heated to about 60°C. 
After about 3 hours the reaction is complete. The reaction mixture is 
then quenched into 234 grams of deionized water and allowed to cool  
 
to room temperature. Glacial acetic acid is added until the solution 
reaches a pH of between 6 and 7. The reaction mixture is then filtered. 
The filter cake is reslurried and filtered twice in deionized water to 
remove most of the residual N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone. The filter cake is 
then dried in a 60°C oven. It is believed that this filter cake will contain 
a brominated alcohol-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01770001" orientation="unknown" wi="83" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01770001.tif" inline="no" he="59"/> 
The spectral strength of the brominated alcohol-substituted colorant 
can be determined using a spectrophotographic procedure based on 
the measurement of the colorant in solution by dissolving the colorant 
in an equal mixture of toluene and tetrahydrofuran and measuring the 
absorbance using a Perkin Elmer Lambda 2S UV/VIS 
spectrophotometer. It is believed that the spectral strength of the 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant will be measured as about 
16,000 mL Absorbance Units per gram at absorption λ<sub>max</sub>, which would 
indicate a purity of about 60 percent. </p><heading><u style="single">PART E</u></heading><p num="0109">In a glass reaction flask are combined 16 grams of the 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part D of this  
 
Example, 31 grams of UNICID® 700 (a material containing carboxylic 
acids of the formula R<sub>2</sub>COOH wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear alkyl group having 
an average of about 50 carbon atoms, also containing other 
unfunctionalized wax materials in an amount of up to about 25 percent 
by weight; available from Baker Petrolite, Sugarland, TX), 152 grams of 
xylene (available from Tarr, Inc., Portland, OR), and 0.6 grams of paratoluenesulfonic 
acid (available from Capital Resin Corp., Columbus, 
OH). The materials are mixed and heated to a reflux temperature of 
about 143°C. After about 7 hours, the reaction is complete. The 
reaction mixture is then cooled to 40°C and filtered. The filter cake is 
reslurried and filtered two more times in methanol to remove residual 
xylene. The filter cake is then dried in air at ambient temperature. It is 
believed that this filter cake will contain a colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01780001" orientation="unknown" wi="94" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01780001.tif" inline="no" he="65"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 
carbon atoms. </p><p num="0110">The spectral strength of the colorant can be determined 
using a spectrophotographic procedure based on the measurement of 
the colorant in solution by dissolving the colorant in an equal mixture of  
 
toluene and tetrahydrofuran and measuring the absorbance using a 
Perkin Elmer Lambda 2S UV/VIS spectrophotometer. It is believed that 
the spectral strength of the colorant will be measured as about 5,000 
mL Absorbance Units per gram at absorption λmax, which would 
indicate a purity of about 40 percent. </p><heading><u style="single">PART F</u></heading><p num="0111">Compounds of the formulae shown in Parts C-1 through 
C-5 of this Example are prepared by reversing steps B and C of this 
Example. More specifically, the alcohol-substituted colorant prepared 
in Part A of this Example is first subjected to bromination as described in 
Parts C-1 through C-5 of this Example, and the resulting brominated 
alcohol-substituted colorants are then subjected to esterification as 
described in Parts C-1 through C-5 of this Example. </p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE <b>III</b></u></heading><heading><u style="single">PART A</u></heading><p num="0112">In a glass reaction flask are combined 73 grams of 
sublimed quinizarin (available from Aceto Corp., Lake Success, NY), 49 
grams of leucoquinizarin (available from Aceto Corp.), 95.8 grams of 4-(4-hydroxybenzyl)aniline 
(which can be prepared as outlined in 
scheme 3 of de Groot et al., <i>J. Org. Chemistry</i> 2001, 66(26), p 8815-8830, 
the disclosure of which is totally incorporated herein by reference), 31 
grams of boric acid (available from Aldrich Chemical Co., Milwaukee, 
WI), and 780 grams of isopropyl alcohol (available from JT Baker, 
Phillipsburg, NJ). The materials are mixed and heated until the solvent  
 
refluxes at about 75°C. After about 16 hours of reflux it is believed that 
the reaction will be complete, having generated an alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01800001" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01800001.tif" inline="no" he="63"/> 
The reaction mixture is cooled and filtered. The product filter cake is 
dried in air at ambient temperature. The spectral strength of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant can be determined using a 
spectrophotographic procedure based on the measurement of the 
colorant in solution by dissolving the colorant in toluene and measuring 
the absorbance using a Perkin Elmer Lambda 2S UV/VIS 
spectrophotometer. </p><heading><u style="single">PART B-1</u></heading><p num="0113">In a glass reaction flask are combined 9.4 grams of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part A of this Example, 68 
grams of glacial acetic acid (available from JT Baker), 13 grams of 
propionic acid (available from Aldrich Chemical Co.), and 2.3 grams of 
acetic anhydride (available from Aldrich Chemical Co.). The materials 
are mixed and heated to a reflux temperature of about 121°C. After  
 
about 4 hours of reflux, the reaction is complete and it is believed that 
the reaction mixture will contain an ethyl acetate-substituted colorant 
of the formula 
<img id="img-01810001" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01810001.tif" inline="no" he="76"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-2</u></heading><p num="0114">In a glass reaction flask are combined 14.1 grams of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part A of this Example, 10.2 
grams of dimer diisocyanate (available from Cognis; these materials 
are also described in, for example, <i>Kirk-Othmer Encyclopedia of 
Chemical Technology</i> 1979, volume 7,3<sup>rd</sup> edition, p. 768-782, John Wiley 
and Sons, Inc., the disclosure of which is totally incorporated herein by 
reference), and 1 drop of FASCAT 4202 catalyst (available from 
Atofina). The materials are mixed and heated to a temperature of 
about 150°C and stirred for 4 hours. It is believed that IR analysis will 
show that the reaction is complete (no isocyanate peak) and that the 
reaction mixture will contain a dimer-diurethane-substituted colorant of 
the formula  <img id="img-01820001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01820001.tif" inline="no" he="46"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formula 
<img id="img-01820002" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01820002.tif" inline="no" he="96"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-3</u></heading><p num="0115">In a glass reaction flask fitted with a Dean-Stark trap are 
combined 5.9 grams of the alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in 
Part A of this Example, 60 grams of xylenes (available from Aldrich 
Chemical Co.), 8.4 grams of the Guerbet acid 2-hexadecyl-1-eicosanoic  
 
acid (ISOCARB 36, available from Condea Vista, Austin, TX), 
and 0.25 grams of p-toluene sulfonic acid (available from Boliden 
Intertrade). The materials are mixed and heated to reflux in an oil bath 
at 150°C. After about 19 hours of reflux, the reaction is complete and it 
is believed that the reaction mixture will contain an ISOCARB-36-substituted 
colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01830001" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01830001.tif" inline="no" he="72"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-4</u></heading><p num="0116">In a glass reaction flask fitted with a Dean-Stark trap are 
combined 17.6 grams of the alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in 
Part A of this Example, 200 grams of xylenes (available from Aldrich 
Chemical Co.), 14.3 grams of dimer acid hydrogenated (known as 
PRIPOL 1006, available from Unichema International; these materials 
are also described in, for example, <i>Kirk-Othmer Encyclopedia of 
Chemical Technology</i> 1979, volume 7,3<sup>rd</sup> edition, p. 768-782, John Wiley 
and Sons, Inc., the disclosure of which is totally incorporated herein by 
reference), and 0.5 grams of p-toluene sulfonic acid (available from  
 
Boliden Intertrade). The material is mixed and heated to reflux in an oil 
bath at 150°C. After about 19 hours of reflux, it is believed that the 
reaction will be complete and that the reaction mixture will contain a 
dimer acid di-ester substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01840001" orientation="unknown" wi="152" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01840001.tif" inline="no" he="47"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formula 
<img id="img-01840002" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01840002.tif" inline="no" he="97"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B-5</u></heading><p num="0117">In a glass reaction flask are combined 3.5 grams of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part A of this Example and 6.4 
grams of hydroabietyl alcohol (available as Abitol E from Hercules Inc. 
of Wilmington Del.) and the mixture is heated to a temperature of 
about 140°C until it is homogeneous. 1 drop of FASCAT 4202 catalyst 
(available from Atofina) and 3.2 grams of isophorone diisocyanate 
(available as DESMODUR I from Bayer Corp., Pittsburgh, PA) are added. 
The materials are mixed and heated to a temperature of about 140°C. 
After about 5 hours of heating it is believed that IR analysis will show 
that the reaction is complete (no isocyanate peak) and that the 
reaction mixture will contain a diurethane-substituted colorant of the 
formula 
<img id="img-01850001" orientation="unknown" wi="158" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01850001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART C-1</u></heading><p num="0118">About 107 grams of the reaction mixture containing the 
ethyl acetate-substituted colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is 
charged into a glass reaction flask. The mixture is cooled to a minimum 
of 30°C. While mixing, about 9 grams of bromine (available from 
Aldrich Chemical Co.) is added to the mixture at a rate such that the  
 
temperature remaines below about 40°C. The mixture is then heated 
to about 40°C. After about 24 hours of mixing the reaction is complete. 
The reaction mixture is then quenched into 234 grams of deionized 
water and allowed to cool to room temperature. The reaction mixture 
is then filtered and the filter cake is reslurried and filtered twice in 
deionized water to remove most of the residual acetic acid. The filter 
cake is then dried in a 60°C oven. It is believed that this filter cake will 
contain a mixture of brominated ethyl acetate-substituted colorants of 
the formulae 
<img id="img-01860001" orientation="unknown" wi="120" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01860001.tif" inline="no" he="69"/> 
and  <img id="img-01870001" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01870001.tif" inline="no" he="73"/> 
The spectral strength of the brominated ethyl acetate-substituted 
colorant can be determined using a spectrophotographic procedure 
based on the measurement of the colorant in solution by dissolving the 
colorant in toluene and measuring the absorbance using a Perkin Elmer 
Lambda 2S UV/VIS spectrophotometer. </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-2</u></heading><p num="0119">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the 
colorant from Part B-2 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae 
<img id="img-01870002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01870002.tif" inline="no" he="44"/> 
and  <img id="img-01880001" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01880001.tif" inline="no" he="45"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formulae 
<img id="img-01880002" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01880002.tif" inline="no" he="95"/> 
and  <img id="img-01890001" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01890001.tif" inline="no" he="96"/> 
will be obtained. </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-3</u></heading><p num="0120">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the 
colorant from Part B-3 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae  <img id="img-01900001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01900001.tif" inline="no" he="67"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01900002" orientation="unknown" wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01900002.tif" inline="no" he="69"/> 
will be obtained. </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-4</u></heading><p num="0121">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the 
colorant from Part B-4 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae  <img id="img-01910001" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01910001.tif" inline="no" he="53"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01910002" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01910002.tif" inline="no" he="47"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formulae  <img id="img-01920001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01920001.tif" inline="no" he="98"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01920002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01920002.tif" inline="no" he="99"/> 
will be obtained.  </p><heading><u style="single">PART C-5</u></heading><p num="0122">The process of Part C-1 of this Example is repeated except 
that the colorant from Part B-1 of this Example is replaced with the 
colorant from Part B-5 of this Example. It is believed that a colorant of 
the formulae 
<img id="img-01930001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01930001.tif" inline="no" he="51"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01930002" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01930002.tif" inline="no" he="53"/> 
will be obtained. </p><heading><u style="single">PART D</u></heading><p num="0123">In a glass reaction flask are combined 18 grams of the 
mixture of the brominated ethyl acetate-substituted colorant and its 
salt prepared in Part C-1 of this Example, 72 grams of N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone  
 
(available from Aldrich Chemical Co.), 4 grams of sodium 
hydroxide (available from Aldrich Chemical Co.), and 4 grams of 
deionized water. The material is mixed and heated to about 60°C. 
After about 3 hours the reaction is complete. The reaction mixture is 
then quenched into 234 grams of deionized water and allowed to cool 
to room temperature. Glacial acetic acid is added until the solution 
reaches a pH of between 6 and 7. The reaction mixture is then filtered 
and the filter cake is reslurried and filtered twice in deionized water to 
remove most of the residual N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone. The filter cake is 
then dried in a 60°C oven. It is believed that this filter cake will contain 
a brominated alcohol-substituted colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01940001" orientation="unknown" wi="105" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01940001.tif" inline="no" he="62"/> 
The spectral strength of the brominated alcohol-substituted colorant 
can be determined using a spectrophotographic procedure based on 
the measurement of the colorant in solution by dissolving the colorant 
in an equal mixture of toluene and tetrahydrofuran and measuring the 
absorbance using a Perkin Elmer Lambda 2S UV/VIS 
spectrophotometer.  </p><heading><u style="single">PART E</u></heading><p num="0124">In a glass reaction flask are combined 18.8 grams of the 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part D of this 
Example, 31 grams of UNICID® 700 (a material containing carboxylic 
acids of the formula R<sub>2</sub>COOH wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear alkyl group having 
an average of about 50 carbon atoms, also containing other 
unfunctionalized wax materials in an amount of up to about 25 percent 
by weight; obtained from Baker Petrolite, Sugarland, TX), 152 grams of 
xylene (obtained from Tarr, Inc., Portland, OR), and 0.6 grams of paratoluenesulfonic 
acid (obtained from Capital Resin Corp., Columbus, 
OH). The materials are mixed and heated to a reflux temperature of 
about 143°C. After about 7 hours, the reaction is complete. The 
reaction mixture is then cooled to 40°C and filtered and the filter cake 
is reslurried and filtered two more times in methanol to remove residual 
xylene. The filter cake is then dried in air at ambient temperature. It is 
believed that this filter cake will contain a colorant of the formula 
<img id="img-01950001" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01950001.tif" inline="no" he="67"/> 
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 
carbon atoms.  </p><heading><u style="single">PART F</u></heading><p num="0125">Compounds of the formulae shown in Parts C-1 through 
C-5 of this Example are prepared by reversing steps B and C of this 
Example. More specifically, the alcohol-substituted colorant prepared 
in Part A of this Example is first subjected to bromination as described in 
Parts C-1 through C-5 of this Example, and the resulting brominated 
alcohol-substituted colorants are then subjected to esterification as 
described in Parts C-1 through C-5 of this Example. </p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE <b>IV</b></u></heading><heading><u style="single">PART A</u></heading><p num="0126">In a 500 milliliter round bottom flask equipped with 
magnetic stirrer were combined 24.6 grams of 3-(1-hydroxyethyl) 
aniline, of the formula 
<img id="img-01960001" orientation="unknown" wi="55" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01960001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/> 
(obtained from Aldrich Chemical Co., Milwaukee, WI), 17.4 grams of 
leucoquinizarin (obtained from Aceto Corp., Lake Success, NY), 25.9 
grams of quinizarin (obtained from Aceto Corp.), 10.9 grams of boric 
acid (obtained from Aldrich Chemical Co.), and 275.5 grams of 
methanol. The flask was placed under stirring and a condenser in a hot 
oil bath at about 120°C for 19 hours. Thereafter the reaction mixture  
 
was poured hot into a 1 liter beaker and allowed to cool in a 
refrigerator. Thereafter, precipitated solids were collected by vacuum 
filtration, rinsing, and washing with cold methanol. The collected solids 
were dried overnight in a vacuum oven at about 50°C to yield 58.5 
grams of the product, believed to be of the formula 
<img id="img-01970001" orientation="unknown" wi="83" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01970001.tif" inline="no" he="53"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B</u></heading><p num="0127">In a glass reaction flask are combined 12 grams of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant prepared as described in Part A of this 
Example, 10.2 grams of dimer diisocyanate (available from Cognis), 
and 1 drop of FASCAT 4202 catalyst (available from Atofina). The 
materials are mixed and heated to a temperature of about 120°C. 
After about 1 hour of heating, the reaction mixture becomes very thick, 
so the temperature is raised to about 150°C and the reaction mixture 
stirred for 4 hours. It is believed that at this point IR analysis will show 
that the reaction is complete (no isocyanate peak) and that the 
reaction mixture will contain a dimer-diurethane-substituted colorant of 
the formula  <img id="img-01980001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01980001.tif" inline="no" he="44"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formula 
<img id="img-01980002" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01980002.tif" inline="no" he="76"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART C</u></heading><p num="0128">In a glass reaction flask are combined the dimer 
diurethane-substituted colorant prepared as described in Part B of this 
Example, 68 grams of glacial acetic acid (available from JT Baker), and 
13 grams of propionic acid (available from Aldrich Chemical Co). The 
mixture is cooled to a minimum of 30°C. While mixing, about 6.1 grams 
of bromine (available from Aldrich Chemical Co.) are added to the 
mixture at a rate such that the temperature remains below about 40°C.  
 
The mixture is then heated to about 40°C. After about 24 hours of 
mixing the reaction is complete. The reaction mixture is then quenched 
into about 250 grams of deionized water, allowed to cool to room 
temperature, and filtered. The product is reslurried and filtered twice in 
deionized water to remove most of the residual acetic acid. The 
product is then dried in a 60°C oven. It is believed that this product will 
contain a mixture of brominated ethyl acetate-substituted colorants of 
the formulae 
<img id="img-01990001" orientation="unknown" wi="158" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01990001.tif" inline="no" he="39"/> 
and 
<img id="img-01990002" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="01990002.tif" inline="no" he="39"/> 
wherein C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>62+n</sub> is a branched alkylene group which may include 
unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5; 
6, 7, 8, 9, or 10, one isomer of which is believed to be of the formulae  <img id="img-02000001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02000001.tif" inline="no" he="78"/> 
and 
<img id="img-02000002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02000002.tif" inline="no" he="72"/></p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE <b>V</b></u></heading><heading><u style="single">PART A</u></heading><p num="0129">In a 100 milliliter glass reaction flask equipped with a 
magnet and a stirring oil bath at about 130°C were combined 30 grams 
(representing a large excess) of fresh (unopened jar) benzaldehyde  
 
(obtained from Aldrich Chemical Co.), 10.7 grams of 4-aminobenzene 
ethanol (obtained from Aceto Corp.), and about 35 grams of butanol 
(obtained from JT Baker, Phillipsburg, NJ). The materials were mixed 
and heated until the solvent refluxed and the mixture was then held at 
reflux. </p><p num="0130">After about 4 hours of reflux, a distillation column was 
attached and the excess benzaldehyde and the butanol were distilled 
off. To ensure that the benzaldehyde and the butanol were 
completely removed, a vacuum was applied and the temperature 
was held at about 130°C for 1 hour. The reaction had generated a 
protected alcohol-substituted aniline of the formula 
<img id="img-02010001" orientation="unknown" wi="94" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02010001.tif" inline="no" he="22"/> 
The benzaldehyde protected 4-aminobenzene ethanol was cooled to 
room temperature with a nitrogen gas blanket. The neat product was 
then dissolved in about 100 milliliters of HPLC grade acetonitrile and 
transferred to a 250 milliliter 1 neck roundbottom flask with magnet and 
a reflux condenser with a nitrogen blanket on the top of the 
condenser. About 3 milliliters of BF3-etherate (available from the 
Aldrich Chemical Co., of the formula BF<sub>3•</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-O-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>3</sub>) was then 
added and 39.0 grams of propylene oxide (available from Adrich 
Chemical Co.) was added over 1 hour while keeping the reaction flask 
at room temperature. A hot water bath was then added and stirring 
continued. The resulting product, while not characterized, is believed 
to be a slightly viscous liquid of the formula  <img id="img-02020001" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02020001.tif" inline="no" he="33"/> 
After heating for an hour, about 30 grams of 6 Molar hydrochloric acid 
is added to the reaction mixture and heating/stirring is continued for an 
additional hour. The acetonitrile, the liberated benzaldehyde, and the 
water (from the HCl) are then distilled off and the resultant liquid is 
believe to be of the formula: 
<img id="img-02020002" orientation="unknown" wi="113" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02020002.tif" inline="no" he="33"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART B</u></heading><p num="0131">In a glass reaction flask are combined 73 grams of 
sublimed quinizarin (available from Aceto Corp., Lake Success, NY), 49 
grams of leucoquinizarin (available from Aceto Corp.), 289 grams of 
propoxylated 4-aminobenzene ethanol (prepared as described in Part 
A of this Example), 31 grams of boric acid (available from Aldrich 
Chemical Co., Milwaukee, WI), and 780 grams of isopropanol 
(available from JT Baker, Phillipsburg, NJ). The materials are mixed and 
heated until the solvent refluxes. After about 16 hours of reflux the 
reaction is complete, having generated an alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formula  <img id="img-02030001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02030001.tif" inline="no" he="62"/> 
The reaction mixture is cooled and filtered and the product filter cake is 
dried in air at ambient temperature. </p><p num="0132">The spectral strength of the alcohol-substituted colorant 
can be determined using a spectrophotographic procedure based on 
the measurement of the colorant in solution by dissolving the colorant 
in toluene and measuring the absorbance using a Perkin Elmer Lambda 
2S UV/VIS spectrophotometer. </p><heading><u style="single">PART C</u></heading><p num="0133">In a glass reaction flask are combined 18.3 grams of the 
alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part B of this Example, 68 
grams of glacial acetic acid (available from JT Baker), 13 grams of 
propionic acid (available from Aldrich Chemical Co.), and 2.3 grams of 
acetic anhydride (available from Aldrich Chemical Co.). The materials 
are mixed and heated to a reflux temperature of about 121°C. After 
about 4 hours of reflux, the reaction is complete and it is believed that 
the reaction mixture will contain an ethyl acetate-substituted colorant 
of the formula  <img id="img-02040001" orientation="unknown" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02040001.tif" inline="no" he="64"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART D</u></heading><p num="0134">About 91 grams of the reaction mixture containing the 
acetylated colorant from Part C of this Example is charged into a glass 
reaction flask. The mixture is cooled to a minimum of 30°C. While 
mixing, about 8 grams of bromine (available from Aldrich Chemical 
Co.) is added to the mixture at a rate such that the temperature 
remains below about 40°C. The mixture is then heated to about 40°C. 
After about 24 hours of mixing, the reaction is complete. The reaction 
mixture is then quenched into 234 grams of deionized water and 
allowed to cool to room temperature. The liquid contains a mixture of 
brominated acetylated propoxylated-colorants of the formulae  <img id="img-02050001" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02050001.tif" inline="no" he="63"/> 
and 
<img id="img-02050002" orientation="unknown" wi="147" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02050002.tif" inline="no" he="60"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART E</u></heading><p num="0135">In a glass reaction flask are combined 18 grams of the 
mixture of the aqueous brominated, acetylated, propoxylated colorant 
and its salt prepared in Part D of this Example and 4 grams of sodium 
hydroxide (available from Aldrich Chemical Co.). The materials are 
mixed and heated to about 60°C. After about 3 hours the reaction is 
complete. The reaction mixture is then allowed to cool to room 
temperature. Glacial acetic acid is added until the solution reaches a  
 
pH of between 6 and 7. The aqueous, neutralized reaction product is 
then heated with stirring to about 95°C (above the cloud point of the 
product). It is then transferred to a separatory funnel and allowed to 
cool and separate. The salt water layer is removed and the product 
layer (still containing some water) is then transferred to a one neck 
round bottom flask and placed on a rotary evaporator. The water is 
then removed under vacuum. It is believed that the remaining viscous 
liquid will contain a brominated, propoxylated, alcohol-substituted 
colorant of the formulae 
<img id="img-02060001" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02060001.tif" inline="no" he="58"/> 
and 
<img id="img-02060002" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02060002.tif" inline="no" he="60"/></p><heading><u style="single">PART F</u></heading><p num="0136">In a glass reaction flask are combined 12 grams of the 
brominated alcohol-substituted colorant prepared in Part E of this 
Example, 3.6 grams of octadecyl isocyanate (Mondur O, available from 
Bayer Corp), and 1 drop of FASCAT 4202 catalyst (available from 
Atofina). The materials are mixed and heated to a temperature of 
about 120°C. After about 4 hours of heating, it is believed that IR 
analysis will show that the reaction is complete (no isocyanate peak) 
and that the reaction mixture will contain an octadecyl urethane-substituted 
colorant of the formula  <img id="img-02080001" orientation="unknown" wi="152" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="02080001.tif" inline="no" he="170"/></p><p num="0137">Other embodiments and modifications of the present 
invention may occur to those of ordinary skill in the art subsequent to a 
review of the information presented herein; these embodiments and 
modifications, as well as equivalents thereof, are also included within 
the scope of this invention.  </p><p num="0138">The recited order of processing elements or sequences, or 
the use of numbers, letters, or other designations therefor, is not 
intended to limit a claimed process to any order except as specified in 
the claim itself. </p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>Compounds of the formula 
 
wherein Y is a hydrogen atom or a bromine atom, n is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 
or 4, R1 is an alkylene group or an arylalkylene group, and X is (a) a hydrogen 
atom, (b) a group of the formula 
 
wherein R2 is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl 
group, (c) an alkyleneoxy, aryleneoxy, arylalkyleneoxy, or alkylaryleneoxy 
group, or (d) a qroup of the formula 
 
wherein R4 is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl 
group. </claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>Compounds according to claim 1 wherein Y is a hydrogen 
atom. </claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>Compounds according to claim 1 wherein X is a group of 
the formula 
 
wherein R2 is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl 
group. </claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>Compounds according to claim 1 wherein X is a group of 
the formula 
 
wherein R4 is an alkyl group, an aryl group, an arylalkyl group, or an alkylaryl 
group. </claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>Compounds according to claim 1 of the formulae 
 
wherein R2 is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 carbon 
atoms, 
 
wherein R2 is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 carbon 
atoms, 
 
wherein R2 is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 carbon 
atoms, 
 
or mixtures thereof. </claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>Compounds according to claim 1 of the formulae 
 
wherein R2 is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 carbon 
atoms, or mixtures thereof. </claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>Compounds according to claim 1 of the formulae 
 
or mixtures thereof, wherein C36H62+m is a branched alkylene group which 
may include unsaturations and cyclic groups, wherein m is an integer of 0, 1, 
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, or 10. </claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>Compounds according to claim 1 of the formula 
 
wherein R2 is a linear alkyl group having an average of about 50 carbon 
atoms. </claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>Compounds of the formula 
 
wherein Y and Y' each, independently of the other, is a hydrogen atom or a 
bromine atom, n and n' each, independently of the other, is an integer of 0, 
1, 2, 3, or 4, R1 and R1' each, independently of the other, is an alkylene group 
or an arylalkylene group, and X is (a) a group of the formula 
 
wherein R2 is an alkylene group, an arylene group, an arylalkylene group, or 
an alkylarylene group, (b) an alkyleneoxy group, an aryleneoxy group, an 
arylalkyleneoxy group, or an alkylaryleneoxy group, or (c) a group of the 
formula 
 
wherein R4 is an alkylene group, an arylene group, an arylalkylene group, or 
an alkylarylene group. </claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A compound comprising three or more moieties of the 
formula 
 
wherein each Y, independently of the others, is a hydrogen atom or a 
bromine atom, each n, independently of the others, is an integer of 0, 1, 2, 3, 
or 4, and each R1, independently of the others, is an alkylene group or an 
arylalkylene group, said moieties being linked by a central atom or group of 
atoms or bonded to a polymeric chain. </claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>