<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1816177-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1816177" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="36227527" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20070808"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1816177-A1" status="new" fvid="24963250"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1816177</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20070808</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04792917-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04792917</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20041025</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2004015780-W" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2004015780</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20041025</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   5/00        20060101CFI20060509BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   5/08        20060101AFI20060509BHEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   5/10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   5/20</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23F  11/18M</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23F  11/18M2</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">GEFRIERSCHUTZ- UND KÜHLMITTEL</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">ANTI-FREEZE SOLUTION/COOLANT COMPOSITION</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">MÉLANGE D'UNE SOLUTION ANTIGEL ET D'UN FLUIDE DE REFROIDISSEMENT</invention-title><citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>See references of WO  2006046275A1</text><sources><source name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HONDA MOTOR CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SHISHIAI KK</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HONDA MOTOR CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SHISHIAI-KABUSHIKIGAISHA</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HONDA MOTOR CO., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>1-1, Minamiaoyama 2-chome, Minato-ku</street><city>Tokyo 107-8556</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Shishiai-Kabushikigaisha</last-name><address><street>12 Shin-hazama</street><city>Seki-shi, Gifu 501-32</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>EGAWA HIROSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HORI MICHIHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KADO HIDEMI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MORITA YOSHIYUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OMORI AYAKO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OSAWA MITSURU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>EGAWA, HIROSHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HORI, MICHIHIRO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KADO, HIDEMI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MORITA, YOSHIYUKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OMORI, AYAKO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OSAWA, MITSURU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>EGAWA, Hiroshi c/o SHISHIAI-KABUSHIKIGAISHA</last-name><address><street>12, Shin-hazama</street><city>Seki-shi, Gifu 5013923</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HORI, Michihiro c/o SHISHIAI-KABUSHIKIGAISHA</last-name><address><street>12, Shin-hazama</street><city>Seki-shi, Gifu 5013923</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KADO, Hidemi c/o SHISHIAI-KABUSHIKIGAISHA</last-name><address><street>12, Shin-hazama</street><city>Seki-shi, Gifu 5013923</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MORITA, Yoshiyuki c/o HONDA R &amp; D CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>4-1, Chuou 1-chome</street><city>Wako-shi, Saitama 3510193</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OMORI, Ayako c/o HONDA R &amp; D CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>4-1, Chuou 1-chome</street><city>Wako-shi, Saitama 3510193</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OSAWA, Mitsuru c/o HONDA R &amp; D CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>4-1, Chuou 1-chome</street><city>Wako-shi, Saitama 3510193</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Ratcliffe, Susan Margaret</last-name><address><street>Urquhart-Dykes &amp; Lord LLP Churchill House Churchill Way</street><city>Cardiff CF10 2HH</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><pct-or-regional-filing-data ucid="JP-2004015780-W" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2004015780</doc-number><kind>W</kind></document-id></pct-or-regional-filing-data><pct-or-regional-publishing-data ucid="WO-2006046275-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2006046275</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20060504</date></document-id></pct-or-regional-publishing-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country> <country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country> <country>GB</country> <country>GR</country> <country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="pa01">This invention provides an anti-freeze solution/coolant composition suitable for use, for example, in a cooling system of internal combustion engines such as engines. The anti-freeze solution/coolant composition comprises a base comprising one or a mixture of two or more members selected from the group consisting of water, alcohols, glycols, and glycol ethers, and a fluoro compound and an inorganic acid compound contained in the base. The anti-freeze solution/coolant composition can effectively suppress the corrosion of magnesium or a magnesium alloy constituting a coolant system.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>Technical Field</heading><p num="p0001">The present invention relates to an antifreeze/coolant composition for use in cooling systems for internal combustion engines such as car engines, and in particular to an antifreeze/coolant composition which effectively prevents corrosion of magnesium or magnesium alloy parts used in cooling systems.</p><heading>Background Art</heading><p num="p0002">Metals such as aluminum, aluminum alloys, cast iron, steel, brass, solder and copper are used in cooling systems for internal combustion engines such as car engines. These metals can corrode by contacting water or air. Therefore, antifreeze/coolant compositions for use in cooling systems contain a metal corrosion inhibitor to prevent corrosion of such metals.</p><p num="p0003">In recent years, automobiles are becoming lighter in order to conserve natural resources and energy. Because of this trend, materials used in cooling systems for car engines are also becoming lighter. Magnesium and magnesium alloys which are lighter than most other popularly used metals and excellent in terms of recyclability have come into the spotlight.</p><p num="p0004">Magnesium and magnesium alloys have lower standard electrode potentials than most other popularly used metals. Therefore, it was difficult to effectively prevent corrosion of such metals when used in a solution.</p><p num="p0005">In recent years, compositions containing a compound which effectively prevents corrosion of magnesium and magnesium alloys have been proposed. Fluorides, for example, are known as rust inhibitors for magnesium (see Non-Patent Document 1).</p><p num="p0006">In Patent Document 1, a coolant composition is proposed where carboxylic acid is added together with a fluoride or a fluorocarboxylic acid (see Patent Document 1).</p><p num="p0007">In addition, a coolant composition where amide carboxylate or amide sulfonate is used to prevent corrosion of magnesium and magnesium alloys has also been proposed (see Patent Document 2).</p><p num="p0008">Although such coolant compositions including these compounds are effective of reducing corrosion of magnesium, the corrosion prevention<!-- EPO <DP n="2"> --> effect is insufficient for coolant compositions for engine cooling systems and therefore, a composition having a greater effect in preventing corrosion is in demand.

Non-Patent Document 1: SAE Technical Paper Series 850418

Patent Document 1: International Unexamined Patent Publication <patcit id="pcit0001" dnum="WO2002527619A" status="new"><text>2002-527619</text></patcit>

Patent Document 2: International Unexamined Patent Publication <patcit id="pcit0002" dnum="WO2004506091A" status="new"><text>2004-506091</text></patcit></p><heading>Disclosure of the Invention</heading><heading>Problem to Be Solved by the Invention</heading><p num="p0009">The present inventors conducted a diligent research to develop an antifreeze/coolant composition which provides sufficient corrosion prevention in an engine cooling system and the like comprising of magnesium or a magnesium alloy, and discovered that combinations of fluorine compounds and inorganic acids are highly effective for preventing corrosion of magnesium and magnesium alloys.</p><p num="p0010">Accordingly, an object of the present invention is to provide an antifreeze/coolant composition which can effectively prevent corrosion of magnesium or magnesium alloy of a cooling system.</p><heading>Means for Solving Problem</heading><p num="p0011">In order to achieve the above object, the present invention provides an antifreeze/coolant composition comprised of a mixture of a base material selected from water, alcohol, glycol and glycol ether and a fluorine compound and an inorganic acid.</p><p num="p0012">The antifreeze/coolant composition according to the present invention provides a function of effectively preventing corrosion of magnesium and/or magnesium alloys for a cooling system. The base material of this composition is one or more materials selected from among water, alcohol, glycol and glycol ether.</p><p num="p0013">Such alcohol may be methanol, ethanol, propanol, butanol, pentanol, hexanol, heptanol or octanol.</p><p num="p0014">Such glycol may be ethylene glycol, diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol, propylene glycol, 1, 3-propanediol, 1, 3-butanediol, 1, 5-pentanediol and hexylene glycol.</p><p num="p0015">Such glycol ether may be ethylene glycol monomethyl ether, diethylene glycol monomethyl ether, triethylene glycol monomethyl ether, tetraethylene glycol monomethyl ether, ethylene glycol monoethyl ether,<!-- EPO <DP n="3"> --> diethylene glycol monoethyl ether, triethylene glycol monoethyl ether, tetraethylene glycol monoethyl ether, ethylene glycol monobutyl ether, diethylene glycol monobutyl ether, triethylene glycol monobutyl ether or tetraethylene glycol monobutyl ether.</p><p num="p0016">The antifreeze/coolant composition according to the present invention is characterized by containing both a fluorine compound and an inorganic acid in the base material. A fluorine compound collaborates with an inorganic acid to effectively prevent corrosion of magnesium or magnesium alloys of cooling systems. Such fluorine compound may be hydrogen fluoride, potassium fluoride, sodium fluoride, ammonium fluoride, lithium fluoride, sodium fluorocarboxylate or potassium fluorocarboxylate. Among these, fluorides selected from among hydrogen fluoride, potassium fluoride, sodium fluoride and ammonium fluoride are particularly preferable for their excellent corrosion preventive effects on magnesium or magnesium alloys.</p><p num="p0017">Such fluorine compound is preferably contained from 0.01 mass % to 5.0 mass %. In the case where a fluorine compound is contained below this range, corrosion prevention of magnesium and magnesium alloys will be insufficient while in the case where a fluorine compound is contained above this range, no additional effects can be expected, which is uneconomical.</p><p num="p0018">An inorganic acid and a fluorine compound collaborate and effectively prevent corrosion of magnesium or magnesium alloys of cooling systems. Such inorganic acid may be phosphoric acid, silicic acid, boric acid, nitric acid, nitrous acid, molybdic acid, carbonic acid, sulfuric acid, titanic acid, vanadic acid, manganic acid, germanic acid, tungstic acid or their salts. When such an acid or acids are included, corrosion of magnesium or magnesium alloys is excellently prevented.</p><p num="p0019">Of these inorganic acids, such phosphoric acid may be orthophosphoric acid, pyrophosphoric acid, trimetaphosphoric acid or tetrametaphosphoric acid. Such silicic acid may be sodium metasilicate, potassium metasilicate and sodium silicate (Na<sub>2</sub>O/XSiO<sub>2</sub> X is 0.5 to 3.3). Such salts of boric acid, nitric acid, nitrous acid, molybdic acid, carbonic acid, sulfuric acid, titanic acid, vanadic acid, manganic acid, germanic acid or tungstic acid may be sodium salts, potassium salts or ammonium salts.</p><p num="p0020">Among such inorganic acids, phosphoric acid and/or a salt thereof, silicic acid and/or a salt thereof, and a combination of two or more selected from among phosphoric acid and salts thereof and silicic acid<!-- EPO <DP n="4"> --> and salts thereof may be preferably used. Thus, a combination of phosphoric acid and silicic acid, a combination of phosphoric acid and a silicate, a combination of a phosphate and silicic acid, a combination of a phosphate and a silicate, a combination of phosphoric acid, silicic acid and a silicate, a combination of phosphoric acid, a phosphate and silicic acid, a combination of phosphoric acid, a phosphate and a silicate, a combination of a phosphate, a silicate and silicic acid, and a combination of phosphoric acid, a phosphate, silicic acid and a silicate may be effectively used.</p><p num="p0021">Preferably, such inorganic acid is contained within the range from 0.01 mass % to 10.0 mass %. In the case where an inorganic acid is contained below this range only little effect of preventing corrosion of magnesium and magnesium alloys is expected, while in the case where an inorganic acid is contained above this range, no additional effects may be expected, thus, uneconomical.</p><p num="p0022">In the case where phosphoric acid and/or a salt thereof is used as an inorganic acid, or in the case where silicic acid and/or a salt thereof is used, a fluorine compound is preferably contained within the range from 0.01 mass % to 5.0 mass % in the composition, and the phosphoric acid and/or salt thereof or silicic acid and/or salt thereof is contained within the range from 0.01 mass % to 5.0 mass %. The contents of the fluorine compound and the phosphoric acid and/or salt thereof or silicic acid and/or salt thereof should be such that sufficient effects of preventing corrosion of magnesium and magnesium alloys may be achieved, and use of a fluorine compound and a phosphoric acid and/or salt thereof or silicic acid and/or salt thereof should be economically determined.</p><p num="p0023">In the case where a combination of phosphoric acid and/or a salt thereof and silicic acid and/or a salt thereof is used as the inorganic acid, preferably a fluorine compound is contained within the range from 0.01 mass % to 5.0 mass % in the composition, and a phosphoric acid and/or salt thereof and silicic acid and/or salt thereof is contained within the range from 0.01 mass % to 5.0 mass %. The content should be such that sufficient effects of preventing corrosion of magnesium and magnesium alloys may be achieved, and use of a fluorine compound and a phosphoric acid and/or salt thereof and silicic acid and/or salt thereof should be economically determined.</p><p num="p0024">The antifreeze/coolant composition according to the present invention may further include one or more selected from among aromatic monobasic acids, aromatic dibasic acids, aliphatic monobasic acides,<!-- EPO <DP n="5"> --> aliphatic dibasic acids and their salts.</p><p num="p0025">Such aromatic monobasic acides and their salts may be benzoic acids, such as benzoic acid, nitrobenzoic acid and hydroxybenzoic acid, alkylbenzoic acids, such as p-toluic acid, p-ethylbenzoic acid, p-propylbenzoic acid, p-isopropylbenzoic acid and p-tert butylbenzoic acid, alkoxybenzoic acids (RO-C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>4</sub>-COOH:R is an alkyl group with C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>5</sub>), cinnamic acids (R-C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>4</sub>-CH=COOH:R is an alkyl group or an alkoxy group with C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>5</sub>), alkyl cinnamic acids or alkoxy cinnamic acids, or their alkaline metal salts, ammonium salts or amine salts. Benzoic acid, p-toluic acid and p-tert butylbenzoic acid are excellent in corrosion prevention for aluminum based and iron based metals, and therefore, it is desirable that at least one of these compounds is included.</p><p num="p0026">Such aromatic dibasic acids and their salts may be, phthalic acid, isophthalic acid or terephthalic acid or their alkaline metal salts and ammonium salts.</p><p num="p0027">Preferably, such aromatic monobasic or aromatic dibasic acids are contained within the range from 0.1 mass % to 10 mass %. In the case where an aromatic monobasic or aromatic dibasic acid is contained less than 0.1 mass %, only little effects of preventing corrosion of aluminum based and iron based metals is expected, while in the case of more than 10 mass % is contained, no additional effects may be expected, which is uneconomical.</p><p num="p0028">Such aliphatic monobasic acids and their salts may be, pentanoic acid, hexanoic acid, heptanoic acid, octanoic acid, 2-ethyl hexanoic acid, nonanoic acid, decanoic acid, undecanoic acid, dodecanoic acid, oleic acid, linoleic acid, linolenic acid, ricinoleic acid or stearic acid, or their alkaline metal salts and ammonium salts of these can be used.</p><p num="p0029">Such aliphatic dibasic acids and their salts may be, oxalic acid, malonic acid, succinic acid, glutaric acid, adipic acid, piperinic acid, suberic acid, azelaic acid, sebacic acid, undecanedioic acid, dodecanedioic acid, brassylic acid or taptic acid or their alkaline metal salts amine salts or ammonium salts. Among these, suberic acid, azelaic acid, sebacic acid, undecanediouic acid and dodecanedioic acid are preferred.</p><p num="p0030">Preferably, such aliphatic monobasic acid, aliphatic dibasic acid or salt thereof is included within the range from 0.1 mass % to 10 mass %. In the case where such aliphatic monobasic acid, aliphatic dibasic acid or salt thereof is contained less than 0.1 mass %, only little effects<!-- EPO <DP n="6"> --> of preventing corrosion of aluminum based and iron based metals is expected, while in the case where the content exceeds 10 mass %, no additional effects may be expected and thus uneconomical.</p><p num="p0031">In addition, the antifreeze/coolant composition according to the present invention may include one or more selected from among triazoles and thiazoles. Benzotriazole, tolyltriazole, 4-phenyl-1, 2, 3-triazole, 2-naphtotriazole and 4-nitrobenzo triazole may be used as triazoles, and among these, benzotriazole and tolyltriazole are particularly preferred. In addition, benzothiazole and mercaptobenzothiazole may be used as thiazoles.</p><p num="p0032">When these triazoles or thiazoles are added, the effects of preventing corrosion of copper based metals, such as brass and copper, will be improved. Preferably, a triazole is contained within the range from 0.01 mass % to 1.0 mass %. Preferably, such thiazole is contained within the range from 0.01 mass % to 1.0 mass %.</p><p num="p0033">In addition, it is desirable that the antifreeze/coolant composition according to the present invention has a pH within the range from 9 to 13. In the case where the pH value is within the above described range, the effects of preventing corrosion of magnesium and magnesium alloys will further be improved.</p><p num="p0034">The antifreeze/coolant composition according to the present invention may include a conventional antifoaming agent, coloring agent and/or conventional corrosion inhibitor in addition to the above described materials.</p><p num="p0035">The present invention should not be limited by the following embodiments, and modifications within the scope of the appended claims are possible.</p><heading>Effects of the Invention</heading><p num="p0036">The antifreeze/coolant composition according to the present invention contains a base material comprising one or more selected from among water, alcohol, glycol and glycol ether as well as and contains a fluorine compound and an inorganic acid in such base material. The composition will effectively prevent corrosion of the magnesium or magnesium alloys of cooling systems.</p><heading>Best Mode for Carrying Out the Invention</heading><heading>Embodiments:</heading><p num="p0037">Embodiment 1 comprising potassium fluoride and a phosphate,<!-- EPO <DP n="7"> --> Embodiment 2 comprising potassium fluoride and a silicate, and Embodiment 3 comprising potassium fluoride, a phosphate and a silicate were prepared (Table 1). In addition, Comparative 1 free of any rust inhibiting additive, Comparative 2 including only potassium fluoride, Comparative 3 including only a phosphate, and Comparative 4 including only a silicate were also prepared (Table 1). A metal corrosion test was conducted on the respective samples of the Embodiments 1 to 3 and Comparatives 1 to 4 to measure and evaluate changes in weight and appearance of test metal pieces. The results of the test are shown in Table 2. The metal corrosion test was performed according to the standard of JIS K 2234 (Metal Corrosiveness Property Test), and Mg alloy (AZ91D) was used as the test metal pieces.<!-- EPO <DP n="8"> --><tables id="tabl0001" num="0001"><table frame="all"><title>Table 1</title><tgroup cols="8"><colspec colwidth="31mm" colnum="1" colname="col1"/><colspec colwidth="25mm" colnum="2" colname="col2"/><colspec colwidth="25mm" colnum="3" colname="col3"/><colspec colwidth="25mm" colnum="4" colname="col4"/><colspec colwidth="25mm" colnum="5" colname="col5"/><colspec colwidth="25mm" colnum="6"  colname="col6"/><colspec colwidth="25mm" colnum="7" colname="col7"/><colspec colwidth="25mm" colnum="8" colname="col8"/><thead><row><entry align="center"  valign="middle">Component</entry><entry align="center"  valign="middle">Embodiment 1</entry><entry align="center"  valign="middle">Embodiment 2</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Embodiment 3</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Comparative 1</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Comparative 2</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Comparative 3</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Comparative 4</entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry valign="middle">Ethylene glycol</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">100</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">100</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">100</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">100</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">100</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">100</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">100</entry></row><row><entry valign="middle">Potassium fluoride</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">0.5</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">0.5</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">0.5</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">-</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">0.5</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">-</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">-</entry></row><row><entry>Phosphate</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="center">-</entry></row><row><entry>Silicate</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables id="tabl0002" num="0002"><table frame="all"><title>Table 2</title><tgroup cols="8"><colspec colwidth="30mm" colnum="1" colname="col1"/><colspec colwidth="30mm" colnum="2" colname="col2"/><colspec colwidth="30mm" colnum="3" colname="col3"/><colspec colwidth="32mm" colnum="4" colname="col4"/><colspec colwidth="30mm" colnum="5" colname="col5"/><colspec colwidth="30mm" colnum="6" colname="col6"/><colspec colwidth="30mm" colnum="7" colname="col7"/><colspec colwidth="30mm" colnum="8" colname="col8"/><thead><row><entry align="center" valign="middle">Item</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Embodiment 1</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Embodiment 2</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Embodiment 3</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Comparative 1</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Comparative 2</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Comparative 3</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Comparative 4</entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry>change of test piece</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Slight change in color</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Slight change in color</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Slight change in color</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Color changed to black; corrosion on entire surface</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Color changed to white; porous corrosion</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Color changed to black; corrosion on entire surface</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">Color changed to black; corrosion on entire surface</entry></row><row><entry>change in mass mg/cm<sup>2</sup></entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">+0.14</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">+0.18</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">+0.22</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">+2.28</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">+0.36</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">+3.45</entry><entry align="center" valign="middle">+2.94</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><!-- EPO <DP n="9"> --></p><p num="p0038">Table 2 shows that Comparatives 1 to 4, which did not contain both or none of a fluorine compound and an inorganic acid, exhibited a large change in weight and showed inferior corrosion prevention for Mg alloy, while all of the samples of Embodiments 1 to 3, which contained both a fluorine compound and an inorganic acid, exhibited little change in weight and provided excellent corrosion prevention for Mg alloy.</p><heading>Industrial Applicability</heading><p num="p0039">The present invention provides an antifreeze/coolant composition for use in cooling systems of internal combustion engines such as car engines, and in particular, in cooling systems comprising magnesium or magnesium alloy parts.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="c-en-0001" num="0001"><claim-text>An antifreeze/coolant composition, comprising a base material selected from water, alcohol, glycol and glycol ether, further comprising a fluorine compound and an inorganic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0002" num="0002"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to Claim 1, wherein the fluorine compound is contained between 0.01 mass % and 5.0 mass % and the inorganic acid is contained between 0.01 mass % and 10.0 mass %.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0003" num="0003"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to Claim 1, wherein the fluorine compound is one or more compounds selected from hydrogen fluoride, potassium fluoride, sodium fluoride and ammonium fluoride.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0004" num="0004"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to Claim 1, wherein the inorganic acid is one or more compounds selected from phosphoric acid, silicic acid, boric acid, nitric acid, nitrous acid, molybdic acid, carbonic acid, sulfuric acid, titanic acid, vanadic acid, manganic acid, germanic acid, tungstic acid and salts thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0005" num="0005"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to Claim 4, wherein the inorganic acid is phosphoric acid and/or a salt thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0006" num="0006"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to Claim 5, wherein the fluorine compound is contained between 0.01 mass % to 5.0 mass % and the phosphoric acid and/or a salt thereof is contained between 0. 01 mass % to 5.0 mass %.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0007" num="0007"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to Claim 4, wherein the inorganic acid is silicic acid and/or a salt thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0008" num="0008"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to Claim 7, wherein the fluorine compound is contained between 0.01 mass % and 5.0 mass % and the silicic acid and/or a salt thereof is contained between 0.01 mass % and 5.0 mass %.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0009" num="0009"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to Claim 4, wherein the inorganic acid is a combination of a phosphoric acid and/or a salt thereof and a silicic acid and/or a salt thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0010" num="0010"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to Claim 9, wherein the fluorine compound is contained between 0.01 mass % and 5.0 mass %, the phosphoric acid and/or a salt thereof is contained between 0.01 mass % and 5.0 mass %, and the silicic acid and/or a salt thereof is contained between 0.01 mass % and 5.0 mass %.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0011" num="0011"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to Claim 1, further<!-- EPO <DP n="11"> --> comprising one or more compounds selected from aromatic monobasic acids, aromatic dibasic acids, aliphatic monobasic acids, aliphatic dibasic acids and salts thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0012" num="0012"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to Claim 1, further comprising one or more compounds selected from triazoles and thiazoles.</claim-text></claim><claim id="c-en-0013" num="0013"><claim-text>The antifreeze/coolant composition according to any of Claims 1 to 12 whose pH is from 9 to 13.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>