<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1239032-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1239032" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="8176657" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020911"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1239032-A1" status="new" fvid="23536676"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1239032</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020911</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01105138-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01105138</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010302</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-01105138-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01105138</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010302</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23C   9/152       20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23C   9/152       20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/18        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23L   1/30        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23L   1/30        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  35/66        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  35/74        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  39/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  39/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  39/395       20060101ALI20050410BMRU        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  39/395       20060101CLI20050410BMRU        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  29/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  29/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  37/00        20060101C I20060521RMWO        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  37/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  37/08        20060101A I20060521RMWO        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  16/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  16/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  16/42        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  16/42        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   1/21        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   1/21        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N  15/09        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N  15/09        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A23K   1/00C2B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A23K   1/18N</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07K  16/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07K  16/42M10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61K39:52C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61K39:54A1</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Milchsäurebakterien als Mitteln zur Behandlung und Vorbeugung von Allergie</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Lactic acid bacteria as agents for treating and preventing allergy</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Bactéries lactiques en tant qu'agents pour le traitement et la prévention des allergies</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="WO-1997031948-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997031948</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000063252-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000063252</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>BOERSMA W J A ET AL: "LACTOBACILLUS AS VECTORS WITH INTRINSIC ADJUVANTICITY FOR SAFE LIVE MUCOSAL VACCINES" JOURNAL OF CELLULAR BIOCHEMISTRY - SUPPLEMENT,US,WILEY-LISS, vol. 19A, no. SUPPL. O, 16 January 1995 (1995-01-16), page 255 XP002027111 ISSN: 0730-2312</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>POUWELS P H ET AL: "The potential of Lactobacillus as a carrier for oral immunization: Development and preliminary characterization of vector systems for targeted delivery of antigens" JOURNAL OF BIOTECHNOLOGY,NL,ELSEVIER SCIENCE PUBLISHERS, AMSTERDAM, vol. 44, no. 1, 26 January 1996 (1996-01-26), pages 183-192, XP000921209 ISSN: 0168-1656</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NESTLE SA</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SOCIETE DES PRODUITS NESTLE S.A.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Société des Produits Nestlé S.A.</last-name><address><street>P.O.Box 353</street><city>1800 Vevey</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>FRITSCHE RODOLPH</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GERMOND JAQUES-EDOUARD</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>STADLER BEDA M PROF DR</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VOGEL MONIQUE</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>FRITSCHE, RODOLPH</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GERMOND, JAQUES-EDOUARD</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>STADLER, BEDA M., PROF. DR.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VOGEL, MONIQUE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>FRITSCHE, RODOLPH</last-name><address><street>Vers-Chez-Les-Blanc</street><city>1000 Lausanne 26</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GERMOND, JAQUES-EDOUARD</last-name><address><street>Ch. des Cèdres 18</street><city>1023 Crissier</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor> <inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>STADLER, BEDA M., PROF. DR.</last-name><address><street>Bubenbergplatz 4</street><city>3011 Bern</city><country>CH</country></address> </addressbook> </inventor> <inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VOGEL, MONIQUE</last-name><address><street>Heckenweg 8</street><city>3007 Bern</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Becker Kurig Straus</last-name><address><street>Patentanwälte Bavariastrasse 7</street><city>80336 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention pertains to novel strains of lactic acid bacteria capable of reducing an
individual's tendency to react allergic against a variety of different allergens. In particular, the
present invention relates to recombinant strains of lactic acid bacteria that express surface
polypeptides which include peptides or antibody fragments acting as mimic for at least a part of
the F<sub>c</sub> region of IgE-molecules. The invention also pertains to food or pharmaceutical
compositions containing said micro-organisms or active fractions thereof.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="130" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="108"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention pertains to novel strains of lactic acid bacteria capable of reducing an
individual's tendency to develop allergic reactions. In particular, the present invention relates to
recombinant strains of lactic acid bacteria expressing surface polypeptides which include small
and larger peptides acting as mimic for at least a part of the F<sub>c</sub> region of IgE-molecules. The
invention also pertains to food or pharmaceutical compositions containing said micro-organisms
or active fractions thereof.</p><p num="0002">The immune system is a complex and multifactorial defense system that protects the body from
any invasive biological or chemical agent, such as viruses, bacteria, parasites and fungi or simply
larger chemical substances. Although being indispensable for maintaining the body's integrity,
the immune system may in certain cases be the cause of the illness itself, such as in autoimmune
diseases, inflammation or allergies.</p><p num="0003">Allergies are inappropriate reactions of the immune system to a variety of substances (allergens).
Generally, individuals do not generate a significant immune reaction against substances regularly
encountered in the environment, such as pollen or food material, which non-reactivity is deemed to
be mainly due to a suppressing mechanism of the immune system itself. However, in an impaired
condition the immune system does not fulfil said suppressing activity resulting in a specific
immune reaction against the allergen - the allergic reaction.</p><p num="0004">A generally established mechanism of allergic reactions involves a sequence of events beginning
with the uptake of the allergen which needs to pass the epithelial barrier to reach and activate
effector cells, located in the lamina propria or epithelium below the level of the tight junctions.
The clinical symptoms associated with allergic reactions are basically the result of an early
specific immune response and a late inflammatory reaction. During the early phase
immunoglobulines E (IgE) against the allergenic substance are produced by the host's immune 
system, which are subsequently bound via a receptor protein to e.g. mast cells and basophils.
Upon binding and crosslinking the IgE molecules on their surface the cells release histamine and
cytokines, which then mediate the late phase by recruiting inflammatory cells into the nasal and
upper respiratory tract passages. The influx of eosinophils, macrophages, lymphocytes,
neutrophils and platelets subsequently starts the inflammatory cycle amplifying the initial
immune response which in turn triggers the release of more inflammatory cells.</p><p num="0005">In the past, the number of individuals suffering from allergy has increased, which is frequently
attributed to an ever increasing atmospheric pollution caused by e.g. exhaust gases. Also, an
extended consumption of proteinaceous material is deemed to contribute to said development, in
particular to the growing occurrence of food allergy. Further, the deficit in microbial infections
encountered in developed countries has also been suggested as another possible cause for the
increase of atopic diseases.</p><p num="0006">Therefore, there exists a need in the art to treat allergy, for which different approaches have been
proposed so far.</p><p num="0007">As for the treatment of food allergy some methods rely on modifying the food material itself such
that its allergenic potential is reduced. This may be achieved by altering the chemical structure
thereof, or by limiting or banning the food material or components thereof, respectively, which
would be the cause of such trouble. Yet, a problem involved often resides in that the specific
allergenic substance in the respective food material is frequently not known so that in most cases
it is not clear which component should be selectively removed or altered.</p><p num="0008">A different approach of treating food allergy and food intolerance is directed to restoring and
maintaining the intestine's integrity such that food allergens essentially may not pass. In this
respect US 5,192,750 describes the use of N-acetyl glucosamine to enable the mucosa to form the
necessary barrier to transmission of food allergens and to maintain normal function.</p><p num="0009">A most general approach of treating allergy is an immunotherapy which involves repeated
injection of the allergen, over a period of several years, to desensitize a patient to the allergen.
Proceeding accordingly is, however, time consuming, involves years of treatment, and often fails 
to achieve its goal of desensitizing the patient.</p><p num="0010">According to a more recent approach, vaccination of individuals against IgE molecules is
suggested which inhibits triggering of mast cells and basophils. To this end, WO 97/31948 proposes
specific peptides for vaccination that resemble in their three dimensional conformation parts of
the IgE molecule, i.e. the immunoglobulines involved in the release of mediators, that play a part
in the regulation of allergic and inflammatory reactions. It is conceived that the individual's own
immune system will eventually form antibodies directed to said IgE molecules such that said IgE
immunoglobulines are scavenged.</p><p num="0011">However, said method harbours the disadvantage common to normal vaccination procedures in
that the biologically active substance has to be administered by invasive methods, such as e.g. by
intraveneous injection, which route of administration is generically disliked by patients. On the
other hand, when choosing the oral route, suitable galenic formulas have to be designed to allow
the biologically active substance to pass the gastro-intestinal tract without getting destroyed.
Another problem encountered in this method resides in that the mimotopes are, in most of the
cases, short length peptides, that on their own will not elicit a substantial immune response so that
apart from carriers and excipients adjuvantia have to be included in the composition.</p><p num="0012">Therefore, there is a need in the art to provide improved means for treating allergy. In particular,
an object of the present invention resides in providing means that allow treatment of allergy in an
efficient, easy and cost effective manner preferably without requiring a physician and without
bringing about the negative associations linked with such treatments.</p><p num="0013">The above object has been solved by providing novel lactic acid bacteria strains that express on
their surface a polypeptide containing at least one peptide sequence mimicking at least part of a
conformational epitope (mimotope) of an IgE molecule.</p><p num="0014">In the figures,
<sl><li>Fig. 1 shows a protein stain and Immunoblot analysis of Lactobacillus johnsonii recombinants. (A)
Protein stain of La1 wild type (lane 1), La1 carrying pMD112TT (La1TT, lane 2) or pMD112ε4 
(La1ε4, lane 3). (B) Expression of proteinase PrtB on La1TT (lane 2) and La1ε4 (lane 3).
Approximately 10<sup>8</sup> bacteria were analyzed by immunoblot using anti-PrtB serum diluted 1:2000.
Wild type La1 was loaded as a negative control (lane 1). Binding antibodies were detected with
horseradish peroxidase conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG (Fc) antibodies. (C) Expression of tetanus
mimotope on the surface of La1TT (lane 2). Approximately 10<sup>8</sup> bacteria per slot were analyzed by
immunoblot using anti-TT serum diluted 1:1000. La1 (lane 1) and La1E4 (lane 3) were used as
negative controls. Binding antibodies were detected with horseradish peroxidase conjugated goat
anti-rabbit IgG (Fc) antibodies. (D) Expression of ε4 mimotope on the surface of La1ε4 (lane 3).
Approximately 10<sup>8</sup> bacteria per slot were analyzed by immunoblot using anti-E4 serum (SDS280)
at a concentration of 10µg/ml. La1 (lane 1) and La1TT (lane 2) were used as negative controls.
Binding antibodies were detected with horseradish peroxidase conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG (Fc)
antibodies. The arrow indicates the height of the proteinase band seen in A-D.</li><li>Fig. 2 shows the result of an binding assay of anti TT IgG to surface displayed epsilon mimotopes
on lactic acid bacteria in ELISA.</li><li>Fig. 3 shows the result of an binding assay of anti-ε4 IgG to surface displayed epsilon mimotopes
on lactic acid bacteria in ELISA.</li></sl></p><p num="0015">In the studies leading to the present invention it has now been found that by providing a lactic acid
bacterium containing a recombinant surface polypeptide comprising a peptide sequence as defined
above a specific immunization of an individual against IgE may be obtained, with the result that
allergic reactions of said individuals to essentially all antigens are suppressed.</p><p num="0016">Without wishing to be bound to any theory it is presently envisaged that the lactic acid bacteria,
that upon ingestion remain in the gastro-intestinal tract for a period of time, are capable to present
the antigen to an individual's immune system such that an effective immune reaction takes place
leading to the formation of anti-IgE antibodies in the individual. This fact is all the more
surprising, since it could not be predicted, whether administration of a bacterium to an individual,
which is effected via the gastro-intestinal route, containing such a surface protein, would
eventually present the corresponding antigen - the mimotope - to the individual's immune system
such that the immune system will be capable of recognizing the antigen and elicit an immune 
response thereto. What is more, obviously the biological environment, wherein the mimotope is
presented to the immune system is such that the use of adjuvantia for eliciting an immune response
against the antigen is not required.</p><p num="0017">According to a preferred embodiment the lactic acid bacterium containing a surface polypeptide
containing the mimotope belongs to the Lactobacillus group or Bifidobacterium group or
Lactococcus group, and is more preferably derived from the groups of <i>L. acidophilus, L.
johnsonii, L. gasseri, L. casei, L. paracasei or L. reuteri</i>, all of human or animal origin.
According to a more preferred embodiment the lactic acid bacterium is a probiotic lactic acid
bacterium. As probiotics micro-organisms shall be understood capable to pass the gastro-intestinal
tract in an essentially viable and live form and optionally also be capable of stimulating
the host's immune system. According to a most preferred embodiment the lactic acid bacteria is
<i>Lactobacillus johnsonii.</i></p><p num="0018">The nature of the surface polypeptide is not crucial with the proviso that the "mimotope peptide
sequence" may be inserted such that it is accessible for the immune system. According to a
preferred embodiment the surface polypeptide/protein, into which a sequence mimicking a
conformational epitope of an IgE immuno-globuline is inserted, is the cell surface anchored
protease of Lactobacillus bulgaricus the sequence of which was published in Gilbert et al., (1996)
J. Bacteriol, <b>178</b>, 3059-3065. This protein was characterized as a 2000 amino acids protein, being
composed of a leader peptide of 33 amino acids (pre-region) responsible for cell export of the
enzyme, followed by a series of 154 amino acids (pro-region) which is responsible, upon
cleavage, for the activation of the proteolytic activity of the enzyme and 700-800 amino acids for
the active site. The subsequent region (around 1000 amino acids) has been suggested to play a
role in the specificity of cleavage and transport in the cell of the generated peptides and to also
span the cell wall. The protease is cell wall anchored by its carboxyl end with the last 200 amino
acids being responsible for the specific covalent binding to the cell wall peptidoglycan structure.</p><p num="0019">The polypeptide may be expressed in the lactic acid bacterium according to methods well known
in the art. For example the commercially available vectors pNZ124 (Platteuw et al., (1994) Appl.
Env. Microbiol. <b>60</b>, 587), pGK12 (Walke et al., (1996) FEMS Microbiol. <b>138</b>, 233,) or pG+host9
(Maguin et al., (1996) J. Bacteriol <b>178</b>, 931) maybe used for episomal expression. Yet, having in 
mind the superior stability of chromosome integration, this way of doing could be preferred for
the recombinant gene coding for the respective polypeptide. For integration into the chromosome
homologous recombination may be applied by e.g. using an recombinant gene from lactic acid
bacteria, containing the tolerogenic peptide and replacing the endogenous gene. Yet, methods for
introducing recombinant genes into a host's chromosome are well within the skilled person's
skill.</p><p num="0020">The peptide sequences (Seq. Id. No.1-17) and the anti-idiotypic VH and VL sequence (Seq. Id.
No. 18-19) mimicking a conformational epitope of an IgE may be found by screening random
peptide and human Fab antibodies phage display libraries with an antibody directed to the Fc part
of IgE. Preferred mimotope and anti-idiotypic Fab sequences are selected from the group
consisting of:
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="147" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="7"/><img id="img-00060002" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060002.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060003" orientation="unknown" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060003.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060004" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060004.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060005" orientation="unknown" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060005.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060006" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060006.tif" inline="no" he="5"/><img id="img-00060007" orientation="unknown" wi="137" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060007.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060008" orientation="unknown" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060008.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060009" orientation="unknown" wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060009.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060010" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060010.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060011" orientation="unknown"  wi="145" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060011.tif" inline="no"  he="4"/><img id="img-00060012"  orientation="unknown"  wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060012.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060013" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060013.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060014" orientation="unknown" wi="141" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060014.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060015" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060015.tif" inline="no" he="10"/><img id="img-00060016" orientation="unknown" wi="147" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060016.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060017" orientation="unknown" wi="148" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060017.tif" inline="no" he="4"/><img id="img-00060018" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00060018.tif" inline="no" he="23"/><img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-00070002" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00070002.tif" inline="no" he="67"/></p><p num="0021">For more detailed information regarding the isolation and/or preparation of peptide and anti-idiotypic
VH and VL sequences mimicking part of an IgE constant region in general, reference is
made to WO 97/31948, the teaching of which is incorporated herein by way of reference.</p><p num="0022">The present invention also relates to a food and pharmaceutical composition, in particular
vaccines, containing at least one such lactic acid bacterium as described above.</p><p num="0023">The bacterial strain may be included in the composition in an amount ranging from 10<sup>5</sup> to 10<sup>12</sup>
cfu (colony forming unit) per g of the material. The food composition may be milk, yoghurt,
curd, cheese, fermented milks, milk based fermented products, ice cream, fermented cereal based
products, milk based powders, infant formulae or, in case of animals, pet food and the
pharmaceutical composition may be in the form of tablets, liquid bacterial suspensions, dried oral
supplements, wet oral supplements, dry tube feeding or wet tube-feeding.</p><p num="0024">The lactic acid bacterium and the food/pharmaceutical composition of the present invention may 
be used for treating any disease condition associated with allergic reactions, wherein an immune
reaction involving IgE antibodies are involved, such as e.g. rhinitis, atopic dermatitits, erythema
etc.. Likewise, it will be appreciated that the bacteria/compositions of the present invention are
well suited for being used as a "vaccination agent", preventing the onset of allergy in an
individual in general. This may easily be accomplished by simply feeding the person in need of a
treatment against allergy with a food composition or a pharmaceutical composition according to
the present invention. Upon ingestion the bacteria will colonize the intestine for a certain period
of time so that depending on the amount of bacterial cell counts and the time period during which
the compositions of the present invention are administered, the mimotope is presented to he
individual, so that he may form an immune response against the mimotope(s). It will be
appreciated that in addition to the lactic acid bacterium contained in the compositions of the
present invention agents known to stimulate the immune system may be administered as well, so
as to improve the immune response against the mimotope.</p><p num="0025">The following examples further illustrate the invention without limiting it thereto.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 1</u></b></heading><heading>Construction of recombinant polypeptide</heading><p num="0026">Two peptides were fused with the cell surface anchored protease of L. bulgaricus to be displayed
on the surface of the bacterium La1 (CNCM I-1225), i.e. the peptide ε4 (Seq. Id. No. 1) and
another peptide (used as a control) derived from Tetanus Toxin (termed TT in the following;
sequence see below).</p><p num="0027">The mimotope (ε4) was fused in frame to the cell surface proteinase (PrtB) from Lactobacillus
bulgaricus (Gilbert et al., (1996) J. Bacteriol, <b>178</b>, 3059-3065).</p><p num="0028">The protease gene was first amplified with its promoter by using the following two primers: <img id="img-00090001" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00090001.tif" inline="no" he="14"/><img id="img-00090002" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00090002.tif" inline="no" he="17"/></p><p num="0029">The amplification product was cleaved with BamHI and XbaI and cloned in the lactic acid
bacteria vector pNZ124, that had been digested with the same restriction enzymes, and
eventually introduced by electroporation into plasmid-free (beta-galactosidase and protease
negative) <i>Lactococcus lactis.</i></p><p num="0030">The region of the active site of the cloned protease was replaced by the sequence of the TT and
the ε4 peptides flanked by two cysteines residues at both ends. The cysteine residues were added
becauses these two peptides were isolated from phage display libraries as circular peptides
flanked by two cysteine residues. As these peptides do not represent the natural epitopes but
rather mimic them, they are called mimotopes:
<img id="img-00090003" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00090003.tif" inline="no" he="24"/><img id="img-00090004" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00090004.tif" inline="no" he="25"/></p><p num="0031">To achieve this, the cloned protease was cleaved with NheI which is located 50bp downstream
the sequence of the cleavage site of the leader peptide and PvuI, 800 bp further downstream. The
DNA sequence coding for the peptide of interest (supra) was inserted between the two restriction
sites as two oligonucleotides, which were designed such as to generate the two restriction sites at
their ends once they are hybridized. The design of the oligonucleotides took into account that
upon ligation to the protease gene the reading frame of the recombinant protein remains open. </p><p num="0032">The amplification product was cleaved with the restriction enzymes. In both cases the DNA
fragments were ligated to the protease gene and introduced by electroporation into <i>Lactobacillus
johnsonii.</i></p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 2</u></b></heading><heading>Transformation of <i>Lactobacillus johnsonii</i></heading><p num="0033">For transformation purposes <i>Lactobacillus johnsonii</i> strain La1 (available from the Institute
Pasteur under the accession no. CNCM I-1225) was grown overnight in MRS broth at 37 °C in
anaerobic conditions. An aliquot of this culture was used to inoculate (1:10) another culture broth
(MRS) containing 0.5 M sucrose. After an additional re-inoculation at 2 % into 200 ml MRS +
0.5 M sucrose the culture was grown to an OD<sub>595</sub> of 0.6. The cells were collected by centrifuging
at 5000 rpm at 4 °C for 10 min, the pellet was washed twice with ½ volume of a solution
containing 1 M sucrose and 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> , once with ¼ volume of a solution containing 1 M
sucrose, 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>) and the pellet obtained after centrifugation was resuspended in 3.5 ml of
a solution of 1 M sucrose, 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> + 0.459 ml 87 % glycerol (10 % final concentration).
The cells were either directly used for transformation or frozen at -80°C.</p><p num="0034">For the electroporation 40 µl of cells were mixed with 10 - 100 ng of DNA (in &lt;5 µl volume) and
transferred into an ice-cold 0.2 cm electroporation cuvette. Pulses at 200 Ω, 25 µF, 2.5 kV in ice-cold
0.2 cm electroporation cuvette were applied. To the cuvette 1 ml of MRS + 20 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> ,
2mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> was added and the suspension was incubated for 2-3 hours at 37°C. 10 µl and 100 µl
aliquots, respectively, were plated on MRS agar plates containing the appropriate antibiotic. The
plates were incubated anaerobically for 24-48 h at the same temperature as above. As a selection
medium MRS with chloramphenicol (10µg/ml) was used.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 3</u></b></heading><heading>Generation of antisera against the proteinase PrtB</heading><p num="0035">To generate antisera against the PrtB rabbits were immunized subcutaneously with <i>Lactobacillus
delbrueckii</i> subsp <i>bulgaricus</i> strain ATCC11842 expressing proteinase B (PrtB). Bacteria were
grown overnight in MRS broth at 42 °C in a GasPak anaerobic system. An aliquot of this culture
was used to inoculate another culture broth (MRS) containing 0.5 M sucrose and the culture was 
grown for 5 hours at 42°C until an OD<sub>595</sub> of 0.6. The cells were collected by centrifuging at 5000
rpm at 4°C for 10 min, the pellet was washed twice with 10ml PBS and then resuspended in 2 ml
PBS. Rabbits were immunized three times at two weeks intervals with 1.5 ml PBS resuspended
cells and seven days after the last feeding rabbits were bled. Serum was purified six times on
2x10<sup>9</sup><i>Lactobacillus johnsonii</i> (La1).</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 4</u></b></heading><heading>Generation of antisera against the TT and the ε4 mimotopes</heading><p num="0036">To generate sera against the TT and the ε4 mimotopes rabbits were immunised subcutaneously
with either polyoxime-TT mimotope construct or with ε4 mimotope conjugated with keyhole
limpet hemocyanin (KLH). Rabbits were immunized four times at two weeks intervals and
animals were bled seven days after the last injection. The anti-ε4 serum was purified by
immunoaffinity chromatography on CH-Sepharose 4B coupled to ε4 mimotope.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 5</u></b></heading><heading>Detection of mimotope-PrtB fusion proteins by antibodies</heading><p num="0037">In order to determine, whether the lactic acid bacteria express the mimotopes in a manner so as to
be accessible by and recognized by antibodies, bacteria either containing the PrtB gene without
any modification, or containing the recombinant gene (coding either for the ε4 or the TT
mimotope respectively) were grown in 25ml medium containing 10µg/ml chloramphenicol.
Bacterial cells were harvested by centrifugation at 3000 x g for 15 min at 4°C, washed with 5ml
TBS and recentrifuged. Finally the bacterial pellet was resuspended in 450 µl Tris-buffered saline
(TBS: 25mM Tris/HCl pH 7.5, 0.8% NaCl, 0.02% KCl) and 150µl 4x non-reducing sample
buffer (80mM Tris/HCl pH 6.8, 2.5% SDS, 0.15% glycerol, 0.05% bromophenol blue). 20µl
aliquots were separated by SDS- polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) (6% acryl-amide-Bis,
0.5M Tris-HCl pH 8.8) and run in a 25mM Tris, 192mM glycine buffer (pH 8.3) at
100V for 60 min. The gels were stained with BM Fast stain (Boehringer Mannheim, Germany) or
transferred electrophoretically onto nitrocellulose membranes (Protran BA 83, Schleicher &amp;
Schuell, Dassel, Germany). After transfer the membranes were blocked with PBS/5%BSA for
2hrs at RT. Immunoblots were incubated with either rabbit anti-TT serum (1:1000) or anti-PrtB 
serum (1:2000) overnight at RT and incubated for 3hrs at RT with a 1:1000 dilution of horseradish
peroxidase conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG. Immunoblots were developed with 4-chloro-1-naphtol
for 2 minutes.</p><p num="0038">As shown in Fig. 1, it could be observed that recombinant <i>Lactobacillus johnsonii</i> showed
specific bands using the appropriate antibodies for detection, indicating that the ε4 and the TT
mimotopes as well as the proteinase PrtB was produced by the recombinant bacteria in the
correct conformation.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 6</u></b></heading><heading>ELISA to detect surface antigen expression on Lactobacillus johnsonii (La1)</heading><p num="0039">Transformed bacteria were grown overnight in 50ml medium containing 10µg/ml
chloramphenicol. Bacterial cells were harvested by centrifugation at 3000 x g for 15 min at 4°C,
washed with 5ml TBS and recentrifuged. Finally the bacterial pellet was resuspended in 900µl
TBS and 100µl 0.5M bicarbonate buffer pH9.6. Costar EIA/RIA half-well plates (Costar,
Cambridge, MA) were coated overnight at 37°C with 50 µl bacterial solution per well
(approximately 10<sup>8</sup> bacteria). Coating efficiency was assessed using TTd at a concentration of
10µg/ml as coating antigen. Plates were extensively washed with PBS/0.1% Tween-20 until no
bacteria were left. Wells were blocked in PBS/5%BSA for 2h at 37°C and incubated with 50 µl
of either rabbit anti-TT serum or affinity purified rabbit anti-ε4 serum IgG antibodies at a
concentration of 10 µg/ml for 4h at 37°C. After washing six times with PBS/0.1% Tween-20
plates were incubated 1.5h at 37°C with a 1:1000 dilution of horseradish peroxidase conjugated
goat anti-rabbit IgG. Plates were washed six times with PBS/0.1% Tween-20 and developed with
tetramethylbenzidine (TMB; Fluka Chemie AG, Buchs, Switzerland). The reaction was stopped
with 1M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and absorbance values were measured at 450 nm using an ELISA reader
(Molecular devices, Basel, Switzerland).</p><p num="0040">As are illustrated in Fig. 2 and 3 anti-TT and anti-ε4 antibodies specifically recognized the live
recombinant La1 expressing TT and ε4 mimotopes indicating that the two mimotopes were
expressed and dispoayed on the cell surface of the bacteria. <img id="img-00130001" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/><img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="89" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="229"/><img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="87" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="229"/><img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="129" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="232"/><img id="img-00170001" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00170001.tif" inline="no" he="232"/><img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="25"/></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A bacterial strain of the lactic acid bacterium group, expressing a surface polypeptide
which contains a peptide sequence mimicking at least part of a conformational epitope of
an IgE molecule.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The bacterial strain according to claim 1, which is selected from Lactobacillus group or
Bifidobacterium group or Lactococcus group, and is more preferably derived from the
groups of L. acidophilus, L. johnsonii, L. gasseri, L. casei, L. paracasei or L. reuteri.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The bacterial strain according to claim 1 or claim 2, wherein the surface polypeptide is
the cell surface anchored protease of L. bulgaricus.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The bacterial strain according to any of the preceding claims, wherein the peptide
sequence is derived from a sequence selected from SEQ. ID. No. 1 to SEQ. ID. No. 19.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A food composition containing a bacterial strain according to any of the preceding claims
or a supernatant thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The food composition according to claim 5, which is selected from the group consisting
of milk, yoghurt, curd, cheese, fermented milks, milk based fermented products, ice
cream, fermented cereal based products, milk based powders, infant formulae or pet food.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The food material according to any of the claims 5 or 6, wherein the bacterial strain is
contained therein in an amount ranging from 107 to 1012 cfu / dosage form.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A pharmaceutical composition containing a bacterial strain according to any of the claims
1 to 4.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The pharmaceutical composition according to claim 8, wherein the bacterial strain is
contained therein in an amount ranging from 1010 to 1012 cfu / dosage form.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>Use of a bacterial strain according to any of the claims 1 to 4 for the preparation of an
ingestable carrier for the treatment of allergy and/or prevention of the onset of allergic
reactions.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>Use of a food or pharmaceutical composition according to any of the claims 6 to 9 for the
preparation of an ingestable carrier for the treatment of allergy and/or prevention of the
onset of allergic reactions.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>