<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1536041-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1536041" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="34468584" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050601"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1536041-A2" status="new" fvid="24366290"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1536041</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20050601</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04105829-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04105829</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20041117</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2003393793-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2003393793</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031125</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2003424403-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2003424403</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031222</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2003424404-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2003424404</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031222</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2003424405-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2003424405</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031222</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2004058681-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2004058681</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040303</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2004058684-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2004058684</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040303</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2004058685-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2004058685</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040303</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2004172510-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2004172510</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040610</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2004175038-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2004175038</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040614</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2004178074-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2004178074</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040616</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2004178075-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2004178075</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040616</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/30        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/30        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/40        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/40        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  30/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  30/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  16/02H</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  16/30</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  16/40</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  16/40D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  30/00B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Beschichteter Cermet Schneideinsatz mit harter, gegen Abschiefern beständiger Beschichtung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Coated cermet cutting tool with a chipping resistant, hard coating layer</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Outil de coupe en cermet revêtu d'une couche de revêtement dure résistante à l'écaillement</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1247789-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1247789</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1288335-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1288335</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>A.A. LAYYOUS, D.M. FREINKEL, R. ISRAEL: "Al2O3 coated cemented carbides: optimization structure, number of layers and type of interlayer" SURFACE AND COATINGS TECHNOLOGY, vol. 56, 1992, pages 89-95, XP002362565</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>M. KATHREIN, W. SCHINTLMEISTER, W. WALLGRAM, U. SCHLEINKOFER:  "Doped CVD Al2O3 coatings for high performance cutting tools" SURFACE AND COATINGS TECHNOLOGY, vol. 163, 1 January 2003 (2003-01-01), pages 181-188, XP002362564</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI MATERIALS CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI MATERIALS CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MITSUBISHI MATERIALS CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>5-1, Otemachi 1-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HAYAHI TAKUYA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OSHIKA TAKATOSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TSUSHIMA FUMIO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HAYAHI, TAKUYA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OSHIKA, TAKATOSHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TSUSHIMA, FUMIO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hayahi, Takuya Mitsubishi Materials Corporation</last-name><address><street>Cen. Res. Inst. Naka Res. Centre 1002-14 Mukaiyama</street><city>Naka-cho, Naka-gun, Ibaraki</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Oshika, Takatoshi Mitsubishi Materials Corporation</last-name><address><street>Cen. Res. Inst. Naka Res. Centre 1002-14 Mukaiyama</street><city>Naka-cho, Naka-gun, Ibaraki</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Tsushima, Fumio Mitsubishi Materials Corporation</last-name><address><street>Cen. Res. Inst. Naka Res. Centre 1002-14 Mukaiyama</street><city>Naka-cho, Naka-gun, Ibaraki</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Türk, Gille, Hrabal, Leifert</last-name><address><street>Patentanwälte Brucknerstrasse 20</street><city>40593 Düsseldorf</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A surface-coated cermet cutting tool with a hard-coating
layer having excellent chipping resistance, in which
the hard coating layer formed on a surface of a tool
substrate that constitutes the surface-coated cermet cutting
tool is composed of the following upper and lower layers (a)
and (b):
<sl><li>(a) as the lower layer, a titanium compound layer
having at least one or two of a titanium carbide layer, a
titanium nitride layer, a titanium carbonitride layer, a
titanium carboxide layer and a titanium oxycarbonitride
layer, all of which are deposited by chemical vapor
deposition, the titanium compound layer having a total
average layer thickness of 3 to 20 µm, and</li><li>(b) as the upper layer, a heat-transformed α-type Al-Zr
oxide layer formed by carrying out a heat-transforming
treatment in a state that a titanium oxide layer satisfying
the composition formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub>, (where value Y is 1.2 to 1.9
in an atomic ratio to Ti when measured by Auger Electron
Spectroscopy) and having an average layer thickness of 0.05
to 1.5 µm is chemically deposited on a surface of an Al-Zr
oxide layer having a κ-type or -type crystal structure
deposited by chemical vapor deposition and satisfying the
composition formula: (Al<sub>1-X</sub>Zr<sub>X</sub>)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (where value X is 0.003 to 
0.05 in an atomic ratio when measured by an electron probe
micro-analyzer (EPMA)) to thereby transform the crystal
structure of the Al-Zr oxide layer having the κ-type or -type
crystal structure into an α-type crystal structure.
The heat-transformed α-type Al-Zr oxide layer shows an
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which a
highest peak appears in an inclination angle interval in a
range of 0 to 10 degrees and the sum of frequencies in a
range of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or more of the total
sum of frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph, in which the inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph is obtained from the results of
radiating electron beam onto crystal grains having a
hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring range of surfaces
to be polished using a field-emission-type scanning electron
microscope, measuring an inclination angle of a normal line
of the plane (0001) as a crystal plane in which each of the
crystal grains is formed with respect to each of the
polished surfaces, sorting the measured inclination angles
in a range of 0 to 45 degrees among all the measured
inclination angles into several intervals at a pitch of 0.25
degrees, and summing up the frequencies in each of the
intervals. The heat-transformed α-type Al-Zr oxide layer
has an average layer thickness of 1 to 15 µm.</li></sl><img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="150" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="220"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><heading>1. Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a surface-coated
cermet cutting tool (hereinafter referred to as a coated
cermet tool) of which a hard coating layer exhibits
excellent chipping resistance, in particular, during high-speed
intermittent cutting of steel, cast iron, etc.</p><heading>2. Description of the Related Art</heading><p num="0002">Conventionally, a coated cermet tool is known, which is
generally formed by coating, on a surface of a substrate
(hereinafter, generally referred to as a tool substrate)
made of tungsten carbide (hereinafter, referred to as WC)-based
cemented carbide or titanium carbonitride (hereinafter,
referred to as TiCN)-based cermet, a hard-coating layer
composed of the following upper and lower layers (a) and
(b) :
<sl><li>(a) as the lower layer, a titanium compound layer
having at least one or two of titanium carbide (hereinafter,
referred to as TiC) layer, a titanium nitride (hereinafter,
referred to as TiN) layer, a titanium carbonitride
(hereinafter, referred to as TiCN) layer, a titanium
carboxide (hereinafter, referred to as TiCO) layer, and a 
titanium oxycarbonitride (hereinafter, referred to as TiCNO)
layer, all of which are formed by chemical vapor deposition,
the titanium compound layer having a total average layer
thickness of 3 to 20 µm, and</li><li>(b) as the upper layer, a deposited α-type aluminum
oxide (hereinafter referred to as Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) layer having an α-type
crystal structure deposited by chemical vapor
deposition and an average layer thickness of 1 to 15 µm.
The coated cermet tool is widely used for, for example,
continuous or intermittent cutting of steel or cast iron.</li></sl></p><p num="0003">Generally, it is also well known that a titanium
compound layer or deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer constituting
the hard-coating layer of a coated cermet tool has a
granular crystal structure, and further a TiCN layer
constituting the titanium compound layer has a lengthwise
growth crystal structure formed by carrying out chemical
vapor deposition in a moderate temperature range of 700 to
950°C using as a reaction gas a mixed gas which includes
organic carbonitride, for example, CH<sub>3</sub>CN in a conventional
chemical vapor deposition reactor for increasing the
strength of the layer, as disclosed in Japanese Unexamined
Patent Application Publications Nos. 6-31503 and 6-8010.</p><p num="0004">In recent years, the performance of cutting tools has
been markedly enhanced, and demands for labor saving and
energy saving in cutting work and cost reduction have been 
increased. Accordingly, the cutting work is more often
carried out at a higher speed range. The conventional
coated cermet tools generally present no problem when they
are used in the continuous cutting or intermittent cutting
of steel, cast iron or the like under normal conditions.
And, when the conventional cutting tools are used in a high-speed
intermittent cutting under the severest cutting
condition, i.e., in the high-speed intermittent cutting
where mechanical and thermal impacts are repeatedly applied
to the cutting edge at very short pitches, a titanium
compound layer which is typically the lower layer of a hard-coating
layer has high strength and exhibits excellent
impact resistance. However, the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
that constitutes the upper layer of a hard-coating layer,
despite its hardness in high temperature and excellent heat
resistance, is very brittle against the mechanical and
thermal impacts. As a result, chipping (fine crack) easily
occurs in the hard-coating layer, consequently shortening
the usable life of cermet cutting tools.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0005">The present invention is made to solve the above
problems, and it is therefore an object of the present
invention to provide a surface-coated cermet cutting tool
with a hard-coating layer having excellent chipping 
resistance.</p><p num="0006">Considering the above problems, the inventors have
conducted studies for improving the chipping resistance of a
deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer that constitutes the upper layer
of the hard-coating layer of the coated cermet tools, and
have obtained the following results (a) to (c) described
below.
<sl><li>(a) On a surface of a tool substrate, the titanium
compound layer as a lower layer is formed under normal
conditions using a conventional chemical vapor deposition
reactor. An Al-Zr oxide layer [hereinafter, referred to as
an (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having a κ-type or -type crystal
structure and satisfying the composition formula: (Al<sub>1</sub>-<sub>x</sub>Zr<sub>x</sub>)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
(where value X is 0.003 to 0.05 in an atomic ratio
when measured by an electron probe micro-analyzer (EPMA)] is
deposited under the same normal conditions.
Next, the surface of the (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is processed
using the chemical vapor deposition reactor under the
following conditions:
<sl><li>Composition of a reaction gas: in volume%, TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.2 to
3%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 0.2 to 10%, Ar: 5 to 50%, and H<sub>2</sub>: balance,</li><li>Temperature of reaction atmosphere: 900 to 1020°C,</li><li>Pressure of reaction atmosphere: 7 to 30 kPa, and</li><li>Time: 25 to 100 min.</li></sl>
Then, a titanium oxide layer satisfying the composition 
formula: TiO<sub>y</sub>, (wherein value Yis 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic
ratio to Ti when measured by Auger Electoron Spectroscopy)
and having an average layer thickness 0.05 to 1.5 µm are
formed on the surface of the (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer.In this state, by carrying out a heat-transforming
treatment in an atmosphere of Ar gas, preferably, under the
following conditions: a pressure of 7 to 50 kPa, a
temperature of 1000 to 1200°C, and a holding duration of 10
to 120 minutes, to transform the (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having the
κ-type or -type crystal structure into the (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
having an α-type crystal structure. Then, by the operation
of the titanium oxide layer formed on the surface of the (Al,
Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer before the transformation the κ-type or -type
crystal structure is wholly and simultaneously transformed
into the α-type crystal structure and the progress of the
heat transformation is markedly promoted. Thus, cracks
generated at the time of the transformation become extremely
fine and the titanium oxide particulates are uniformly and
dispersedly distributed. Further, the high temperature
strength of the (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer itself is markedly enhanced
by the effect of Zr as a constituent element of the (Al,
Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. As a result, the heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer has a uniformed structure in which cracks
generated by the transformation process has fine
characteristics over the entire length, in addition to high 
strength, very strong resistance against mechanical and
thermal impacts and excellent chipping resistance.
Accordingly, in the coated cermet tool having a hard-coating
layer composed of the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer as the upper layer and the titanium compound layer
(this titanium compound layer does not exhibit any change
during heat-transforming treatment under the above-mentioned
conditions) as the lower layer, the heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer exhibits excellent chipping resistance,
even in a high-speed intermittent cutting accompanied with
severe mechanical and thermal impacts, while it has the same
high temperature hardness and heat resistance as the
excellent high temperature hardness and heat resistance
inherent to an α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. Thus, with the presence
of the titanium compound layer having high strength, the
occurrence of chipping in the hard-coating layer is markedly
suppressed and an excellent wear resistance is exhibited for
a prolonged period of time.</li><li>(b) As for the conventional α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer and the
above heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, when an
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph is obtained
from the results of radiating electron beam onto crystal
grains having a hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring
range of surfaces to be polished using a field-emission-type
scanning electron microscope, as shown in schematic 
explanatory views of Figs. 1(a) and 1(b), measuring an
inclination angle of a normal line of a plane (0001) as a
crystal plane in which each of the crystal grains is formed
with respect to each of the polished surfaces, sorting the
measured inclination angles in a range of 0 to 45 degrees
among all the measured inclination angles into several
intervals at a pitch of 0.25 degrees, and summing up the
frequencies in each of the intervals, the conventional
deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, as illustrated in Fig. 6, shows
an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which
the distribution of measured inclination angles of the plane
(0001) is unbiased in a range of 0 to 45 degrees, whereas
the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, as illustrated
in Fig. 2, shows an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which a sharp and highest peak appears at a certain
position in an inclination angle interval, and the position
of the sharp and highest peak appearing in the inclination
angle interval on an X-axis of the graph varies depending on
the variation of value Y in the composition formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub> of
the titanium oxide layer.</li><li>(c) According to the test results, when value Y in the
composition formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub> of the titanium oxide layer is set
to 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic ratio as described above, there
is obtained an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which the sharp and highest peak appears in an 
inclination angle range of 0 to 10 degrees, and the sum of
frequencies in the range of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or
more of the total sum of frequencies on the inclination
angle frequency-distribution graph. In a coated cermet tool
of the present invention deposited using, as the upper layer
of the hard coating layer, a heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer which shows the resulting inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph on which the inclination angle
frequency in the range of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or
more, and the highest peak appears in the inclination angle
interval in the range of 0 to 10 degrees with the presence
of the titanium compound layer as the lower layer, the
coated cermet tools of the present invention exhibit more
excellent wear resistance without causing chipping in the
cutting edge, in particular, in the high-speed intermittent
cutting, as compared to the conventional cermet tool.</li></sl></p><p num="0007">The present invention has been achieved based on the
above research results (a) to (c).</p><p num="0008">According to the present invention, there is provided a
surface-coated cermet cutting tool with a hard-coating layer
exhibiting excellent chipping resistance, the surface-coated
cermet cutting tool being formed by coating, on a surface of
a tool substrate made of tungsten-carbide-based cemented
carbide or titanium-carbonitride-based cermet, the hard-coating
layer composed of the following upper and lower 
layers (a) and (b):
<sl><li>(a) as the lower layer, a titanium compound layer
having at least one or two of a titanium carbide layer, a
titanium nitride layer, a titanium carbonitride layer, a
titanium carboxide layer and a titanium oxycarbonitride
layer, all of which are deposited by chemical vapor
deposition, the titanium compound layer having a total
average layer thickness of 3 to 20 µm, and</li><li>(b) as the upper layer, a heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer formed by carrying out a heat-transforming
treatment in a state that a titanium oxide layer satisfying
the composition formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub>, (where value Y is 1.2 to 1.9
in an atomic ratio to Ti when measured by Auger Electron
Spectroscopy) and having an average layer thickness of 0.05
to 1.5 µm is chemically deposited on a surface of an (Al,
Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having a κ-type or -type crystal structure
deposited by chemical vapor deposition and satisfying the
composition formula: (Al<sub>1-x</sub>Zr<sub>x</sub>)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (where value X is 0.003 to
0.05 in an atomic ratio when measured by an electron probe
micro-analyzer (EPMA)) to thereby transform the crystal
structure of the (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having the κ-type or -type
crystal structure into an α-type crystal structure,</li></sl>
   the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer showing an
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which a
highest peak appears in an inclination angle interval in a 
range of 0 to 10 degrees and the sum of frequencies in a
range of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or more of the total
sum of frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph, wherein the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph is obtained from results of radiating
electron beam onto crystal grains having a hexagonal crystal
lattice in a measuring range of surfaces to be polished
using a field-emission-type scanning electron microscope,
measuring an inclination angle of a normal line of the plane
(0001) as a crystal plane in which each of the crystal
grains is formed with respect to each of the polished
surfaces, sorting the measured inclination angles in a range
of 0 to 45 degrees among all the measured inclination angles
into several intervals at a pitch of 0.25 degrees, and
summing up the frequencies in each of the intervals,

   and the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having
an average layer thickness of 1 to 15 µm.</p><p num="0009">The reasons for limiting the numerical values in the
layers constituting the hard coating layer of the coated
cermet layer of the present invention as described above
will be described below.</p><heading>(a) Average layer thickness of the lower layer (Ti
compound layer)</heading><p num="0010">A titanium compound layer inherently has excellent high
temperature strength, and the hard-coating layer has high 
temperature strength by virtue of the existence of the
titanium compound layer. In addition, the titanium compound
layer is firmly adhered to both of the tool substrate and
the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer that is the
upper layer. Accordingly, it contributes to improving the
adherence of the hard-coating layer to the tool substrate.
However, when the total average layer thickness is less than
3 µm, the above function cannot be sufficiently obtained.
On the other hand, when the total average layer thickness
exceeds 20 µm, thermal plastic deformation is apt to occur,
particularly in a high-speed intermittent cutting
accompanied by the generation of high heat, which causes
partial wear. Accordingly, the average layer thickness of a
lower layer is preferably set to 3 to 20 µm.</p><heading>(b) Composition and average layer thickness of titanium
oxide layer (value Y)</heading><p num="0011">As described above, by the operation of the titanium
compound layer a deposited κ-type or -type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
is wholly and simultaneously transformed into a heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer to thereby make cracks
generated at the time of heating transformation fine and
uniform. In addition, the titanium compound layer functions
to promote the heating transformation and to suppress the
growth of crystal grains by shortening the processing time.
Moreover, when value Y in the composition formula: TiO<sub>y</sub> of 
the titanium compound layer is set to 1.2 to 1.9 as
described above, according to the test results, the titanium
compound layer functions to show an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph on which a highest peak of
inclination angle frequency appears in an inclination angle
interval range of 0 to 10 degrees, and the ratio of the sum
of frequencies in the inclination angle frequency range of 0
to 10 degrees occupies 45% of the total sum of frequencies
on the inclination angle frequency-distribution graph.
Accordingly, when value Y is less than 1.2, the highest peak
appears less in the range of 0 to 10 degrees on the
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph of the heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. In other words, the
ratio of the sum of frequencies in the range of 0 to 10
degrees may become less than 45% of the total sum of
frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph. In this case, as described above, a desired
excellent high temperature strength cannot be secured in the
heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, which leads to the
failure in obtaining a desired chipping resistance. On the
other hand, when value Y exceeds 1.9, the inclination angle
interval in which the highest peak appears may deviates out
of the range of 0 to 10 degrees. In this case, the desired
high temperature strength cannot be secured in the heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. Thus, value Y is set 
to 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic ratio to Ti.</p><p num="0012">Further, in this case, when the average layer thickness
of the titanium oxide layer is less than 0.05 µm, the above-mentioned
functions cannot be sufficiently obtained. On the
other hand, since the above functions can be sufficiently
obtained only with an average layer thickness of 1.5 µm, and
the thickness beyond the limit is unnecessary, the average
layer thickness of the titanium oxide layer is preferably
set to 0.05 to 1.5 µm.</p><heading>(c) Content ratio of Zr in the upper layer [a heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer] and average layer
thickness of the upper layer</heading><p num="0013">The heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer has
excellent high temperature hardness and heat resistance by
the presence of Al as a constituent element thereof, and has
high temperature strength by the presence of Zr as a
constituent element thereof. Thus, the heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer exhibits excellent wear resistance and
chipping resistance. However, when the content ratio (value
X) of Zr is less than 0.003 in an atomic ratio occupied in
the total amount with Al (this is true of the following
ratios), a sufficiently enhanced high temperature strength
cannot be secured. On the other hand, when the content
ratio of Zr exceeds 0.05, instability is caused in the
hexagonal crystal lattice, which makes it difficult to 
sufficiently transform an κ-type or -type crystal structure
into an α-type crystal structure during the heat-transforming
treatment. Thus, the content ratio (value X)
of Zr is preferably set to 0.003 to 0.05.</p><p num="0014">Further, when the average layer thickness of the heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is less than 1 µm, the
hard coating layer cannot be allowed to sufficiently exhibit
wear resistance. On the other hand, when the average layer
thickness of the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is
greater than 15 µm, chipping is apt to occur. Thus, the
average layer thickness of the heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is preferably set to 1.15 µm.</p><p num="0015">Furthermore, for the purpose of identifying the cutting
tool before and after the use thereof, a TiN layer having a
gold color tone may be deposited, if desired. In this case,
the average layer thickness of the TiN layer is preferably
0.1 to 1 µm. This is because, when the average layer
thickness is less than 0.1 µm, a sufficient identification
cannot be achieved, whereas the identification due to the
TiN layer is sufficient with an average layer thickness of
up to 1 µm.</p><p num="0016">Further, the inventors have obtained the following
results (a) to (c) described below.
<sl><li>(a) On a surface of a tool substrate, the titanium
compound layer as a lower layer is formed under normal 
conditions using a conventional chemical vapor deposition
reactor. An Al-Cr oxide [hereinafter, referred to as an (Al,
Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having a κ-type or -type crystal structure and
satisfying the composition formula: (Al<sub>1-x</sub>Cr<sub>x</sub>)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (where value
X is 0.005 to 0.04 in an atomic ratio when measured by an
electron probe micro-analyzer (EPMA)] is deposited under the
same normal conditions.
Next, the surface of the (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is processed
using the chemical vapor deposition reactor under the
following conditions:
<sl><li>Composition of a reaction gas: in volume%, TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.2 to
3%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 0.2 to 10%, Ar: 5 to 50%, and H<sub>2</sub>: balance,</li><li>Temperature of reaction atmosphere: 900 to 1020°C,</li><li>Pressure of reaction atmosphere: 7 to 30 kPa, and</li><li>Time: 25 to 100 min.</li></sl>
Then, a titanium oxide layer satisfying the composition
formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub>, (wherein value Y is 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic
ratio to Ti when measured by Auger Electoron Spectroscopy)
and having an average layer thickness 0.1 to 2 µm are formed
on the surface of the (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer.In this state, by carrying out a heat-transforming
treatment in an atmosphere of Ar gas, preferably, under the
following conditions: a pressure of 7 to 50 kPa, and a
temperature of 1000 to 1200°C, to transform the (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer having the κ-type or -type crystal structure into the 
(Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having an α-type crystal structure. Then,
by the operation of the titanium oxide layer formed on the
surface of the (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer before the transformation
the κ-type or -type crystal structure is wholly and
simultaneously transformed into the α-type crystal structure
and the progress of the heat transformation is markedly
promoted. Thus, since cracks generated at the time of the
transformation are simultaneously generated, the titanium
oxide particulates are extremely finely, uniformly and
dispersedly distributed, and the fineness of the cracks
generated due to transformation is further promoted by the
effect of Cr as a constituent element of the (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer. As a result, since the formed heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer has a uniformed structure in which
cracks generated by transformation process and crystal
grains has fine characteristics over the entire layer, it
has a very strong resistance against mechanical and thermal
impacts and consequently excellent chipping resistance.
Accordingly, in the coated cermet tool having a hard-coating
layer composed of the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer as the upper layer and the titanium compound layer
(this titanium compound layer does not exhibit any change
during heat-transforming treatment under the above-mentioned
conditions) as the lower layer, the heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer exhibits excellent chipping resistance, 
even in the high-speed intermittent cutting accompanied with
severe mechanical and thermal impacts, while it has the same
high temperature hardness and heat resistance as the
excellent high temperature hardness and heat resistance
inherent to an α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. Thus, with the presence
of the titanium compound layer having high strength, the
occurrence of chipping in the hard-coating layer is markedly
suppressed and the excellent wear resistance is exhibited
for a prolonged period of time.</li><li>(b) As for the conventional α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer and the
above heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, when an
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph is obtained
from the results of radiating electron beam onto crystal
grains having a hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring
range of surfaces to be polished using a field-emission-type
scanning electron microscope, as shown in schematic
explanatory views of Figs. 1(a) and 1(b), measuring an
inclination angle of a normal line of the plane (0001) as a
crystal plane in which each of the crystal grains is formed
with respect to each of the polished surfaces, sorting the
measured inclination angles in a range of 0 to 45 degrees
among all the measured inclination angles into several
intervals at a pitch of 0.25 degrees, and summing up the
frequencies in each of the intervals, the conventional
deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, as illustrated in Fig. 6, shows 
an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which
the distribution of measured inclination angles of the plane
(0001) is unbiased in a range of 0 to 45 degrees, whereas
the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, as illustrated
in Fig. 3, shows an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which a sharp and highest peak appears at a certain
position in an inclination angle interval and the position
of the sharp and highest peak appearing in the inclination
angle interval on an X-axis of the graph varies depending on
the variation of value Y in the composition formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub> of
the titanium oxide layer.</li><li>(c) According to the test results, when value Y in the
composition formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub> of the titanium oxide layer is set
to 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic ratio to Ti as described above,
there is obtained an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which the sharp and highest peak
appears in an inclination angle range of 0 to 10 degrees,
and the sum of frequencies (the sum of frequencies is
proportional to the height of the highest peak) in the range
of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or more of the total sum of
frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph. In a coated cermet tool of the present invention
deposited using, as the upper layer of the hard coating
layer, a heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer which
shows the resulting inclination angle frequency-distribution 
graph on which the inclination angle frequency in the range
of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or more, and the highest
peak appears in the inclination angle interval in the range
of 0 to 10 degrees with the presence of the titanium
compound layer as a lower layer, the coated cermet tools of
the present invention exhibit more excellent wear resistance
without causing chipping in a cutting edge, in particular,
in the high-speed intermittent cutting, as compared to the
conventional cermet tool.</li></sl></p><p num="0017">The present invention has been achieved based on the
above research results (a) to (c).</p><p num="0018">According to the present invention, there is provided a
surface-coated cermet cutting tool with a hard-coating layer
exhibiting excellent chipping resistance, the surface-coated
cermet cutting tool being formed by coating, on a surface of
a tool substrate made of tungsten carbide-based cemented
carbide or titanium carbonitride-based cermet, the hard-coating
layer composed of the following upper and lower
layers (a) and (b):
<sl><li>(a) as the lower layer, a titanium compound layer
having at least one or two of a titanium carbide layer, a
titanium nitride layer, a titanium carbonitride layer, a
titanium carboxide layer and a titanium oxycarbonitride
layer, all of which are deposited by chemical vapor
deposition, the titanium compound layer having a total 
average layer thickness of 3 to 20 µm, and</li><li>(b) as the upper layer, a heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer formed by carrying out a heat-transforming
treatment in a state that a titanium oxide layer satisfying
the composition formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub>, (where value Y is 1.2 to 1.9
in an atomic ratio to Ti when measured by Auger Electorn
Spectroscopy) and having an average layer thickness of 0.1
to 2 µm is chemically deposited on a surface of an (Al,
Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having a κ-type or -type crystal structure
deposited by chemical vapor deposition and satisfying the
composition formula: (Al<sub>1-x</sub>Cr<sub>x</sub>)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (where value X is 0.005 to
0.04 in an atomic ratio when measured by an electron probe
micro-analyzer (EPMA)) to thereby transform the crystal
structure of the (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having the κ-type or -type
crystal structure into an α-type crystal structure,</li></sl>
   the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer showing an
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which a
highest peak appears in an inclination angle interval in a
range of 0 to 10 degrees and the sum of frequencies in a
range of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or more of the total
sum of frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph wherein the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph is obtained from the results of radiating
electron beam onto crystal grains having a hexagonal crystal
lattice in a measuring range of surfaces to be polished 
using a field-emission-type scanning electron microscope,
measuring an inclination angle of a normal line of the plane
(0001) as a crystal plane in which each of the crystal
grains is formed with respect to each of the polished
surfaces, sorting the measured inclination angles in a range
of 0 to 45 degrees among all the measured inclination angles
into several intervals at a pitch of 0.25 degrees, and
summing up the frequencies in each of the intervals,

   and the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having
an average layer thickness of 1 to 15 µm.</p><p num="0019">The reasons for limiting the numerical values in the
layers constituting the hard coating layer of the coated
cermet layer of the present invention as described above
will be described below.</p><heading>(a) Average layer thickness of the lower layer (a
titanium compound layer)</heading><p num="0020">A titanium compound layer inherently has excellent high
temperature strength, and the hard-coating layer has high
temperature strength by virtue of the existence of the
titanium compound layer. In addition, the titanium compound
layer is firmly adhered to both of the tool substrate and
the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer that is the
upper layer. Accordingly, it contributes to improving the
adherence of the hard-coating layer to the tool substrate.
However, when the total average layer thickness is less than 
3 µm, the above function cannot be sufficiently obtained.
On the other hand, when the total average layer thickness
exceeds 20 µm, thermal plastic deformation is apt to occur,
particularly in the high-speed intermittent cutting
accompanied by the generation of high heat, which causes
partial wear. Accordingly, the average layer thickness of a
lower layer is preferably set to 3 to 20 µm.</p><heading>(b) Composition and average layer thickness of titanium
oxide layer (value Y)</heading><p num="0021">As described above, by the operation of the titanium
compound layer a deposited κ-type or -type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
is wholly and simultaneously transformed into a heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer to thereby make cracks
generated at the time of heating transformation fine and
uniform. In addition, the titanium compound layer functions
to promote the heating transformation and to suppress the
growth of crystal grains by shortening the processing time.
Moreover, when value Y in the composition formula: TiO<sub>y</sub> of
the titanium compound layer is set to 1.2 to 1.9 as
described above, according to the test results, the titanium
compound layer functions to show an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph on which a highest peak of
inclination angle frequency appears in an inclination angle
interval range of 0 to 10 degrees, and the ratio of the sum
of frequencies in the inclination angle frequency range of 0 
to 10 degrees occupies 45% of the total sum of frequencies
on the inclination angle frequency-distribution graph.
Accordingly, when value Y is less than 1.2, the highest peak
appear less in the range of 0 to 10 degrees on the
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph of the heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. In other words, the
ratio of the sum of frequencies in the range of 0 to 10
degrees may become less than 45% of the total sum of
frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph. In this case, as described above, a desired
excellent high temperature strength cannot be secured in the
heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, which leads to the
failure in obtaining a desired chipping resistance. On the
other hand, when value Y exceeds 1.9, the inclination angle
interval in which the highest peak appears may deviates out
of the range of 0 to 10 degrees. In this case, the desired
high temperature strength cannot be secured in the heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. Thus, value Y is
preferably set to 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic ratio to Ti.</p><p num="0022">Further, in this case, when the average layer thickness
of the titanium oxide layer is less than 0.1 µm, the above-mentioned
functions cannot be sufficiently obtained. On the
other hand, since the above functions can be sufficiently
obtained only with an average layer thickness of 2 µm, and
the thickness beyond the limit is unnecessary, the average 
layer thickness of the titanium oxide layer is preferably
set to 0.1 to 2 µm.</p><heading>(c) Content ratio and average layer thickness of Cr in
the upper layer [heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer]</heading><p num="0023">The heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer has
excellent high temperature hardness and heat resistance by
the presence of Al as a constituent element thereof. On the
other hand, when Cr as a constituent element coexists with
the titanium oxide layer, it functions to still further
promote the fineness of fine cracks due to transformation,
which is generated at the time of a deposited α-type (Al,
Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer into a heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer.
However, when the content ratio (value X) of Cr is less than
0.005 in an atomic ratio occupied in the total amount with
Al (this is true of the following ratios), an effect to
further promote the fineness of cracks due to transformation
cannot be secured. On the other hand, when the content
ratio of Cr exceeds 0.04, instability is caused in the
hexagonal crystal lattice, which makes it difficult to
sufficiently perform a κ-type or -type crystal structure
into an α-type crystal structure during the heat-transforming
treatment. Thus, the content ratio (value X)
of Cr is set to 0.005 to 0.04, preferably, 0.012 to 0.035.</p><p num="0024">Further, when the average layer thickness of the heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is less than 1 µm, the 
hard coating layer cannot be allowed to sufficiently exhibit
wear resistance. On the other hand, when the average layer
thickness of the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is
greater than 15 µm, chipping is apt to occur. Thus, the
average layer thickness of the heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is preferably set to 1 to 15 µm.</p><p num="0025">Furthermore, for the purpose of identifying the cutting
tool before and after the use thereof, a TiN layer having a
gold color tone may be deposited, if desired. In this case,
the average layer thickness of the TiN layer is preferably
0.1 to 1 µm. This is because, when the average layer
thickness is less than 0.1 µm, sufficient identification
cannot be achieved, whereas the identification due to the
TiN layer is sufficient with an average layer thickness of
up to 1 µm.</p><p num="0026">Further, the inventors have obtained the following
results (a) to (c) described below.
<sl><li>(a) On a surface of a tool substrate, the titanium
compound layer as a lower layer is formed under normal
conditions using a conventional chemical vapor deposition
reactor. An Al-Ti oxide layer [hereinafter, referred to as
an (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having a κ-type or -type crystal
structure and satisfying the composition formula:
(Al<sub>1-x</sub>Ti<sub>x</sub>)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (where value X is 0.01 to 0.05 in an atomic ratio
when measured by an electron probe micro-analyzer (EPMA)] is 
deposited under the same normal conditions.
Next, the surface of the (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is processed
using the chemical vapor deposition reactor under the
following conditions:
<sl><li>Composition of a reaction gas: in volume%, TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.2 to
3%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 0.2 to 10%, Ar: 5 to 50%, and H<sub>2</sub>: balance,</li><li>Temperature of reaction atmosphere: 900 to 1020°C,</li><li>Pressure of reaction atmosphere: 7 to 30 kPa, and</li><li>Time: 25 to 100 min.</li></sl>
Then, a titanium oxide layer satisfying the composition
formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub>, (wherein value Y is 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic
ratio to Ti when measured by Auger Electron Spectroscopy)
and having an average layer thickness 0.05 to 1.5 µm are
formed on the surface of the (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. In this
state, by carrying out a heat-transforming treatment in an
atmosphere of Ar gas, preferably, under the following
conditions: a pressure of 7 to 50 kPa, a temperature of 1000
to 1200°C, and a holding duration of 10 to 120 minutes, to
transform the (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having the κ-type or -type
crystal structure into the (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having an α-type
crystal structure. Then, by the operation of the titanium
oxide layer formed on the surface of the (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
before the transformation the κ-type or -type crystal
structure is wholly and simultaneously transformed into the
α-type crystal structure and the progress of the heat 
transformation is markedly promoted. Thus, since cracks
generated at the time of the transformation are
simultaneously generated, the titanium oxide particulates
are extremely finely, uniformly and dispersedly distributed,
and the crystal growth at the time of the heat
transformation is suppressed by the effect of Ti as a
constituent element of the (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer and the crystal
becomes preferably fine. As a result, since the formed
heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer has a uniformed
structure in which cracks generated by the transformation
process and crystal grains become fine over the entire layer,
it has a very strong resistance against mechanical and
thermal impacts and consequently excellent chipping
resistance. Accordingly, in the coated cermet tool having a
hard-coating layer composed of the heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer as the upper layer and the titanium
compound layer (this titanium compound layer does not
exhibit any change by heat-transforming treatment under the
above-mentioned conditions) as the lower layer, the heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer exhibits excellent
chipping resistance, even in the high-speed intermittent
cutting accompanied with severe mechanical and thermal
impacts, while it has the same high temperature hardness and
heat resistance as the excellent high temperature hardness
and heat resistance inherent to the α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. Thus, 
with the presence of the titanium compound layer having high
strength, the occurrence of chipping in the hard-coating
layer is markedly suppressed and the excellent wear
resistance is exhibited for a prolonged period of time.</li><li>(b) As for the conventional α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer and the
above heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, when an
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph is obtained
from the results of radiating electron beam onto crystal
grains having a hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring
range of surfaces to be polished using a field-emission-type
scanning electron microscope, as shown in schematic
explanatory views of Figs. 1(a) and 1(b), measuring an
inclination angle of a normal line of the plane (0001) as a
crystal plane in which each of the crystal grains is formed
with respect to each of the polished surfaces, sorting the
measured inclination angles in a range of 0 to 45 degrees
among all the measured inclination angles into several
intervals at a pitch of 0.25 degrees, and summing up the
frequencies in each of the intervals, the conventional
deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, as illustrated in Fig. 6, shows
an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which
the distribution of measured inclination angles of the plane
(0001) is unbiased in a range of 0 to 45 degrees, whereas
the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, as illustrated
in Fig. 4, shows an inclination angle frequency-distribution 
graph on which a sharp and highest peak appears at a certain
position in an inclination angle interval and the position
of the sharp and highest peak appearing in the inclination
angle interval on an X-axis of the graph varies depending on
the variation of value Y in the composition formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub> of
the titanium oxide layer.</li><li>(c) According to the test results, when value Y in the
composition formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub> of the titanium oxide layer is set
to 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic ratio to Ti as described above,
there is obtained an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which the sharp and highest peak
appears in an inclination angle range of 0 to 10 degrees,
and the sum of frequencies (the sum of frequencies is
proportional to the height of the highest peak) in the range
of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or more of the total sum of
frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph. In a coated cermet tool of the present invention
deposited using, as the upper layer of the hard coating
layer, a heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer which
shows the resulting inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which the inclination angle frequency in the range
of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or more, and the highest
peak appears in the inclination angle interval in the range
of 0 to 10 degrees with the presence of the titanium
compound layer as the lower layer, the coated cermet tool of 
the present invention exhibits more excellent wear
resistance without causing chipping in a cutting edge, in
particular, in the high-speed intermittent cutting, as
compared to the conventional cermet tool.</li></sl></p><p num="0027">The present invention has been achieved based on the
above research results (a) to (c).</p><p num="0028">According to the present invention, there is provided a
surface-coated cermet cutting tool with a hard-coating layer
exhibiting excellent chipping resistance, the surface-coated
cermet cutting tool being formed by coating, on a surface of
a tool substrate made of tungsten carbide-based cemented
carbide or titanium carbonitride-based cermet, the hard-coating
layer composed of the following upper and lower
layers (a) and (b):
<sl><li>(a) as the lower layer, a titanium compound layer
having at least one or two of a titanium carbide layer, a
titanium nitride layer, a titanium carbonitride layer, a
titanium carboxide layer and a titanium oxycarbonitride
layer, all of which are deposited by chemical vapor
deposition, and the titanium compound layer having a total
average layer thickness of 3 to 20 µm, and</li><li>(b) as the upper layer, a heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer formed by carrying out a heat-transforming
treatment in a state that a titanium oxide layer satisfying
the composition formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub>, (where value Y is 1.2 to 1.9 
in an atomic ratio to Ti when measured by Auger Electron
Spectroscopy) and having an average layer thickness of 0.05
to 1.5 µm is chemically deposited on a surface of an (Al-Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer having a κ-type or -type crystal structure
deposited by chemical vapor deposition and satisfying the
composition formula: (Al<sub>1-x</sub>Ti<sub>x</sub>)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (where value X is 0.01 to
0.05 in an atomic ratio when measured by an electron probe
micro-analyzer (EPMA)) to thereby transform the crystal
structure of the (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having the κ-type or -type
crystal structure into an α-type crystal structure,</li></sl>
   the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer showing an
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which a
highest peak appears in an inclination angle interval in a
range of 0 to 10 degrees and the sum of frequencies in a
range of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or more of the total
sum of frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph wherein the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph is obtained from results of radiating
electron beam onto crystal grains having a hexagonal crystal
lattice in a measuring range of surfaces to be polished
using a field-emission-type scanning electron microscope,
measuring an inclination angle of a normal line of the plane
(0001) as a crystal plane in which each of the crystal
grains is formed with respect to each of the polished
surfaces, sorting the measured inclination angles in a range 
of 0 to 45 degrees among all the measured inclination angles
into several intervals at a pitch of 0.25 degrees, and
summing up the frequencies in each of the intervals,

   and the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti) oxide layer
having an average layer thickness of 1 to 15 µm.</p><p num="0029">The reason for limiting the numerical values in the
layers constituting a hard coating layer of the coated
cermet layer of the present invention as described above
will be described below.</p><heading>(a) Average layer thickness of the lower layer
(titanium compound layer)</heading><p num="0030">A titanium compound layer inherently has excellent high
strength, and the hard-coating layer has high strength by
virtue of the existence of the titanium compound layer. In
addition, the titanium compound layer is firmly adhered to
both of the tool substrate and the heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer that is the upper layer. Accordingly, it
contributes to improving the adherence of the hard-coating
layer to the tool substrate. However, when the total
average layer thickness is less than 3 µm, the above
function cannot be sufficiently obtained. On the other hand,
when the total average layer thickness exceeds 20 µm,
thermal plastic deformation is apt to occur, particularly in
a high-speed intermittent cutting accompanied by the
generation of high heat, which causes partial wear. 
Accordingly, the total average layer thickness is preferably
set to 3 to 20 µm.</p><heading>(b) Composition and average layer thickness of titanium
oxide layer (value Y)</heading><p num="0031">As described above, by the operation of the titanium
compound layer a deposited κ-type or -type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
is wholly and simultaneously transformed into a heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer to thereby make cracks
generated at the time of heating transformation fine and
uniform. In addition, the titanium compound layer functions
to promote the heating transformation and to suppress the
growth of crystal grains by shortening the processing time.
Moreover, when value Y in the composition formula: TiO<sub>Y</sub> of
the titanium compound layer is set to 1.2 to 1.9 as
described above, according to the test results, the titanium
compound layer functions to show an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph on which a highest peak of
inclination angle frequency appears in an inclination angle
interval range of 0 to 10 degrees, and the ratio of the sum
of frequencies in the inclination angle frequency range of 0
to 10 degrees occupies 45% of the total sum of frequencies
on the inclination angle frequency-distribution graph.
Accordingly, when value Y is less than 1.2, the highest peak
appears less in the range of 0 to 10 degrees on the
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph of the heat-transformed 
α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. In other words, the
ratio of the sum of frequencies in the range of 0 to 10
degrees may become less than 45% of the total sum of
frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph. In this case, as described above, a desired
excellent high temperature strength cannot be secured in the
heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, which leads to the
failure in obtaining a desired chipping resistance. On the
other hand, when value Y exceeds 1.9, the inclination angle
interval in which the highest peak appears may deviates out
of the range of 0 to 10 degrees. In this case, desired
excellent high temperature strength cannot be secured in the
heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. Thus, value Y is
set to 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic ratio to Ti.</p><p num="0032">Further, in this case, when the average layer thickness
of the titanium oxide layer is less than 0.05 µm, the above-mentioned
functions cannot be sufficiently obtained. On the
other hand, since the above functions can be sufficiently
obtained only with an average layer thickness of 1.5 µm, and
the thickness beyond the limit is unnecessary, the average
layer thickness of the titanium oxide layer is preferably
set to 0.05 to 1.5 µm.</p><heading>(c) Content ratio of Ti in the upper layer [a heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer] and average layer
thickness of the upper layer</heading><p num="0033">The heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer has
excellent high temperature hardness and heat resistance by
the presence of Al as a constituent element thereof, and has
high temperature strength by the presence of Ti as a
constituent element thereof. Thus, the heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer exhibits excellent wear resistance and
chipping resistance. However, when the content ratio (value
X) of Ti is less than 0.01 in an atomic ratio (this is true
of the following ratios) occupied in the total amount with
Al, an effect to make crystal sufficiently fine cannot be
exhibited. On the other hand, when the content ratio of Ti
exceeds 0.05, instability is caused in the hexagonal crystal
lattice, which makes it difficult to sufficiently transform
a κ-type or -type crystal structure into an α-type crystal
structure during the heat-transforming treatment. Thus, the
content ratio (value X) of Ti is preferably set to 0.01 to
0.05.</p><p num="0034">Further, when the average layer thickness of the heat-transformed
α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is less than 1 µm, the
hard coating layer cannot be allowed to sufficiently exhibit
wear resistance. On the other hand, when the average layer
thickness of the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is
greater than 15 µm, chipping is apt to occur. Thus, the
average layer thickness of the heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is preferably set to 1.15 µm. </p><p num="0035">Furthermore, for the purpose of identifying the cutting
tool before and after the use thereof, a TiN layer having a
gold color tone may be deposited, if desired. In this case,
the average layer thickness of the TiN layer is preferably
0.1 to 1 µm. This is because, when the average layer
thickness is less than 0.1 µm, a sufficient identification
cannot be achieved, whereas the identification due to the
TiN layer is sufficient with an average layer thickness of
up to 1 µm.</p><p num="0036">Further, the inventors have obtained the following
results (a) to (c) described below.
<sl><li>(a) On a surface of a tool substrate, the titanium
compound layer as a lower layer is formed under normal
conditions using a conventional chemical vapor deposition
reactor. An Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (hereinafter, referred to as a deposited κ,
-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) layer having a κ-type or -type crystal structure in
a state formed by vapor deposition is formed under the same
normal conditions.
Next, the surface of the deposited κ, -Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is
processed using the chemical vapor deposition reactor under
the following conditions:
<sl><li>Composition of a reaction gas: in volume%, TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.2 to
3%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 0.2 to 10%, Ar: 5 to 50%, and H<sub>2</sub>: balance,</li><li>Temperature of reaction atmosphere: 800 to 1100°C,</li><li>Pressure of reaction atmosphere: 4 to 70 kPa, and </li><li>Time: 15 to 60 min.</li></sl>
Then, a titanium oxide layer satisfying the composition
formula: TiO<sub>x</sub>, (where value X to Ti is 1.2 to 1.9 in an
atomic ratio when measured by Auger Electron Spectroscopy)
and having an average layer thickness 0.05 to 1 µm are
formed on the surface of the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer.In this state, heat-transforming treatment is carried
out in an atmosphere of Ar gas, preferably, under the
following conditions: a pressure of 7 to 50 kPa and a
temperature of 1000 to 1200°C, to transform the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
having the deposited κ, -Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer into an Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
having an α-type crystal structure. Then, by the operation
of the titanium oxide layer formed on the surface of the
deposited κ, -Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer before the transformation the
transformation of the κ-type or -type crystal structure is
wholly and simultaneously transformed into the α-type
crystal structure and the progress of the heat
transformation is markedly promoted. Thus, since cracks
generated at the time of the transformation are
simultaneously formed, the titanium oxide particulates are
extremely finely, uniformly and dispersedly distributed, and
the growth of crystal grains is markedly suppressed by the
shortening of the heat-transforming treatment time. As a
result, since the formed heat-transformed α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
has a uniformed structure in which cracks generated by the 
transformation and crystal grains becomes fine over the
entire layer, it has very strong resistance against
mechanical and thermal impacts. Accordingly, in the coated
cermet tool having a hard-coating layer composed of the
transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer as the upper layer and the titanium
compound layer (this titanium compound layer does not
exhibit any change during heat-transforming treatment under
the above-mentioned conditions) as the lower layer, the
transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer exhibits excellent chipping
resistance with the presence of the titanium compound layer
having high strength. Thus, the occurrence of chipping in
the hard-coating layer is markedly suppressed and the
excellent wear resistance is exhibited for a prolonged
period of time.</li><li>(b) As for the conventional α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer known as
the upper layer of a hard coating layer and the transformed
α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer described in (a), when an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph is obtained from results of
radiating electron beam onto crystal grains having a
hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring range of surfaces
to be polished using a field-emission-type scanning electron
microscope, as shown in schematic explanatory views of Figs.
1(a) and 1(b), measuring an inclination angle of a normal
line of the plane (0001) as a crystal plane in which each of
the crystal grains is formed with respect to each of the 
polished surfaces, sorting the measured inclination angles
in a range of 0 to 45 degrees among all the measured
inclination angles into several intervals at a pitch of 0.25
degrees, and summing up the frequencies in each of the
intervals, the conventional deposited α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, as
illustrated in Fig. 6, shows an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which the distribution of measured
inclination angles of the plane (0001) is unbiased in a
range of 0 to 45 degrees, whereas the transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer, as illustrated in Fig. 5, shows an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph on which a sharp and highest
peak appears at a certain position in an inclination angle
interval and the position of the sharp and highest peak
appearing in the inclination angle interval on an X-axis of
the graph varies depending on the variation of value X in
the composition formula: TiO<sub>x</sub> of the titanium oxide layer.</li><li>(c) According to the test results, when value X to Ti
in the composition formula: TiO<sub>x</sub> of the titanium oxide layer
is set to 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic ratio as described above,
there is obtained an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which the sharp and highest peak
appears in an inclination angle range of 0 to 10 degrees,
and the sum of frequencies in the range of 0 to 10 degrees
occupies 45% or more of the total sum of frequencies on the
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph. In a coated 
cermet tool of the present invention deposited using, as the
upper layer of the hard coating layer, a transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer which shows the resulting inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which the inclination angle frequency
in the range of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or more, and
the highest peak appears in the inclination angle interval
in the range of 0 to 10 degrees with the presence of the
titanium compound layer as the lower layer, the coated
cermet tool of the present invention exhibits more excellent
wear resistance without causing chipping in a cutting edge,
in particular, in the high-speed cutting, as compared to the
conventional cermet tool.</li></sl></p><p num="0037">The present invention has been achieved based on the
above research results.</p><p num="0038">According to the present invention, there is provided a
surface-coated cermet cutting tool with a hard-coating layer
exhibiting excellent chipping resistance, the surface-coated
cermet cutting tool being formed by coating, on a surface of
a tool substrate made of tungsten carbide-based cemented
carbide or titanium carbonitride-based cermet, the hard-coating
layer composed of the following upper and lower
layers (a) and (b):
<sl><li>(a) as the lower layer, a titanium compound layer
having at least one or two of a titanium carbide layer, a
titanium nitride layer, a titanium carbonitride layer, a 
titanium carboxide layer and a titanium oxycarbonitride
layer, all of which are deposited by chemical vapor
deposition, and the titanium compound layer having a total
average layer thickness of 3 to 20 µm, and</li><li>(b) as the upper layer, a transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
formed by carrying out a heat-transforming treatment in a
state that a titanium oxide layer satisfying the composition
formula: TiO<sub>x</sub>, (where value X is 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic
ratio to Ti when measured by Auger Electron Spectroscopy) is
chemically deposited on a surface of a deposited κ, -Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer to thereby transform the crystal structure of the
deposited κ, -Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer into an α-type crystal structure,</li></sl>
   the transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer showing an inclination
angle frequency-distribution graph on which a highest peak
appears in an inclination angle interval in a range of 0 to
10 degrees and the sum of frequencies in a range of 0 to 10
degrees occupies 45% or more of the total sum of frequencies
on the inclination angle frequency-distribution graph
wherein the inclination angle frequency-distribution graph
is obtained from results of radiating electron beam onto
crystal grains having a hexagonal crystal lattice in a
measuring range of surfaces to be polished using a field-emission-type
scanning electron microscope, measuring an
inclination angle of a normal line of the plane (0001) as a
crystal plane in which each of the crystal grains is formed 
with respect to each of the polished surfaces, sorting the
measured inclination angles in a range of 0 to 45 degrees
among all the measured inclination angles into several
intervals at a pitch of 0.25 degrees, and summing up the
frequencies in each of the intervals,

   and the transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer having an average
layer thickness of 1 to 15 µm.</p><p num="0039">The reasons for limiting the numerical values in the
layers constituting a hard coating layer of the coated
cermet layer of the present invention as described above
will be described below.</p><heading>(a) Average layer thickness of a lower layer (Ti
compound layer)</heading><p num="0040">A titanium compound layer inherently has excellent high
temperature strength, and the hard-coating layer has high
temperature strength by virtue of the existence of the
titanium compound layer. In addition, the titanium compound
layer is firmly adhered to both of the tool substrate and
the transformed α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer that is the upper layer.
Accordingly, it contributes to improving the adherence of
the hard-coating layer to the tool substrate. However, when
the total average layer thickness is less than 3 µm, the
above function cannot be sufficiently obtained. On the
other hand, when the total average layer thickness exceeds
20 µm, thermal plastic deformation is apt to occur, 
particularly in a high-speed intermittent cutting
accompanied by the generation of high heat, which causes
partial wear. Accordingly, the total average layer
thickness is preferably set to 3 to 20 µm.</p><heading>(b) Composition and average layer thickness of titanium
oxide layer (value X)</heading><p num="0041">As described above, by the operation of the titanium
compound layer the heating transformation of a deposited κ,
-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is wholly and simultaneously transformed into
an α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer to thereby make cracks generated at the time
of heating transformation fine and uniform. In addition,
the titanium compound layer has a functions to promote the
heating transformation and to suppress the growth of crystal
grains by shortening the processing time. Moreover, when
value X in the composition formula: TiO<sub>x</sub> of the titanium
compound layer is set to 1.2 to 1.9 as described above,
according to the test results, the titanium compound layer
functions to show an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which a highest peak of inclination
angle frequency appears in an inclination angle interval
range of 0 to 10 degrees, and the ratio of the sum of
frequencies in the inclination angle frequency range of 0 to
10 degrees occupies 45% of the total sum of frequencies on
the inclination angle frequency-distribution graph.
Accordingly, when value X is less than 1.2, the highest peak 
appears less in the range of 0 to 10 degrees on the
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph of the
transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer. In other words, the ratio of the
sum of frequencies in the range of 0 to 10 degrees may
become less than 45% of the total sum of frequencies on the
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph. In this
case, as described above, desired excellent high temperature
strength cannot be secured in the transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer,
which leads to the failure in obtaining a desired chipping
resistance. On the other hand, when value X exceeds 1.9,
the inclination angle interval in which the highest peak
appears may deviates out of the range of 0 to 10 degrees.
In this case, desired excellent high temperature strength
cannot also be secured in the transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer.
Therefore, value X to Ti is preferably set to 1.2 to 1.9 in
an atomic ratio.</p><p num="0042">Further, in this case, when the average layer thickness
of the titanium oxide layer is less than 0.05 µm, the above-mentioned
functions cannot be sufficiently obtained. On the
other hand, since the above functions can be sufficiently
obtained only with an average layer thickness of 1 µm, and
the thickness beyond the limit is unnecessary, the average
layer thickness of the titanium oxide layer is preferably
set to 0.05 to 1 µm.</p><heading>(c) Average layer thickness of an upper layer (a 
transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer)</heading><p num="0043">The transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer functions to improve the
wear resistance of the hard coating layer by virtue of the
high temperature hardness and excellent heat resistance
possessed by Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> itself and to markedly suppress the
occurrence of chipping in the hard coating layer even in the
high-speed cutting by virtue of its inherent excellent
resistance against thermal or mechanical impacts (chipping
resistance), as described above. However, when the average
layer thickness of the transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is less than
1 µm, the above function cannot be sufficiently obtained.
On the other hand, when the average layer thickness of the
transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer exceeds 15 µm, chipping is apt to
occur. Accordingly, the average layer thickness of the
transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer is preferably set to 1 to 15 µm.</p><p num="0044">Furthermore, for the purpose of identifying the cutting
tool before and after the use thereof, a TiN layer having a
gold color tone may be deposited, if desired. In this case,
the average layer thickness of the TiN layer is preferably
0.1 to 1 µm. This is because, when the average layer
thickness is less than 0.1 µm, a sufficient identification
cannot be obtained, whereas the identification due to the
TiN layer is sufficient with an average layer thickness of
up to 1 µm.</p><p num="0045">In the coated cermet tool according to the present 
invention, the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
constituting the upper layer of the hard-coating layer
exhibits excellent high temperature hardness and heat
resistance, and further excellent chipping resistance even
in the high-speed intermittent cutting of steel or cast iron
accompanied with very high mechanical and thermal impacts.
Thus, the excellent wear resistance is exhibited without
causing chipping in the hard coating layer.</p><p num="0046">In the coated cermet tool according to the present
invention, the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
constituting the upper layer of the hard-coating layer
exhibits excellent high temperature hardness and heat
resistance, and further excellent chipping resistance even
in the high-speed intermittent cutting of steel or cast iron
accompanied with very high mechanical and thermal impacts.
Thus, the excellent wear resistance is exhibited without
causing chipping in the hard coating layer.</p><p num="0047">In the coated cermet tool according to the present
invention, the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
constituting the upper layer of the hard-coating layer
exhibits excellent high temperature hardness and heat
resistance, and further excellent chipping resistance even
in the high-speed intermittent cutting of steel or cast iron
accompanied with very high mechanical and thermal impacts.
Thus, the excellent wear resistance is exhibited without 
causing chipping in the hard coating layer.</p><p num="0048">In the coated cermet tool according to the present
invention, the transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer constituting the
upper layer of the hard-coating layer exhibits excellent
chipping resistance even in the high-speed intermittent
cutting of steel or cast iron accompanied very high
mechanical and thermal impacts and high heat generation.
Thus, the excellent wear resistance is exhibited for a
prolonged period of time.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0049"><sl><li>Fig. 1 is a schematic explanatory view illustrating a
measuring range of an inclination angle of the plane (0001)
of crystal grains in various kinds of a heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, a heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer, a heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, a
transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer and a deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer,
which constitute a hard coating layer;</li><li>Fig. 2 is an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph of the plane (0001) of a heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer which constitutes a hard coating layer of a
coated cermet tool 2 of the present invention as shown in
Table 5;</li><li>Fig. 3 is an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph of the plane (0001) of a heat-transformed α-type (Al, 
Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer which constitutes a hard coating layer of a
coated cermet tool 2 of the present invention as shown in
Table 9;</li><li>Fig. 4 is an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph of the plane (0001) of a heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer which constitutes a hard coating layer of a
coated cermet tool 2 of the present invention as shown in
Table 13;</li><li>Fig. 5 is an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph of the plane (0001) of a transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
which constitutes a hard coating layer of a coated cermet
tool 2 of the present invention as shown in Table 17; and</li><li>Fig. 6 is an inclination angle distribution graph of
the plane (0001) of a deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer which
constitutes a hard coating layer of a conventional coated
cermet tool.</li></sl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading><p num="0050">Hereinafter, coated cermet tools according to the
present invention will be described in detail by examples
with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p><heading>[Example 1]</heading><p num="0051">The following powders, each having a mean particle size
in a range of 1 to 3 µm, were prepared as raw materials for
substrates: WC powder, TiC powder, ZrC powder, VC powder, 
TaC powder, NbC powder, Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> powder, TiN powder, TaN powder
and Co powder. Those raw powders were compounded with each
other based on the compounding compositions shown in Table 1,
mixed with each other in an acetone solution having wax
added thereto for 24 hours using a ball mill and were dried
under reduced pressure. Thereafter, the resulting powder
mixtures were press-formed into green compacts having
predetermined shape at a pressure of 98 Mpa. The green
compacts were then sintered in a vacuum under the following
conditions: a pressure of 5 Pa, a predetermined temperature
in a range of 1370 to 1470°C, and a holding duration of 1
hour. After sintering, cutting edges were subjected to
horning (R: 0.07 mm) to manufacture tool substrates A to F
made of WC-based cemented carbide and having throwaway tip
shapes defined in ISO·CNMG120408.</p><p num="0052">Further, the following powders, each having a mean
particle size in a range of 0.5 to 2 µm, were prepared as
raw materials for substrates: TiCN (TiC/TiN=50/50 in weight
ratio) powder, Mo<sub>2</sub>C power, Zrc power, NbC powder, TaC powder,
WC power, Co powder and Ni powder. Those raw powders were
compounded with each other based on the compounding
composition shown in Table 2, wet-mixed with each other for
24 hours using a ball mill and were dried. Thereafter, the
resulting powder mixtures were press-formed into green
compacts at a pressure of 98 MPa. The green compacts were 
then sintered in a nitrogen atmosphere under the following
conditions: a pressure of 1.3 kPa, a temperature of 1540°C,
and a holding duration of 1 hour. After sintering, cutting
edges were subjected to horning (R:0.07 mm) to manufacture
tool substrates a to f made of TiCN-based cermet and having
tip shapes defined in ISO Standard-CNMG120412.</p><p num="0053">Next, by using a general chemical vapor deposition
reactor, on the surfaces of the tool substrates A to F and a
to f, titanium compound layers as lower layers of the hard-coating
layers were deposited with combinations and target
layer thickness shown in Table 5 under conditions shown in
Table 3 (in Table 3, 1-TiCN represents formation conditions
of TiCN layers having a lengthwise growth crystal structure
described in Japanese Unexamined Patent Application
Publication No. 6-8010, and the others represent formation
conditions of general granular crystal structure). Next,
similarly, (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having a κ-type or -type
crystal structure were deposited with combinations and
target layer thickness shown in Table 5 under conditions
shown in Table 3. Subsequently, on a surface of each of the
(Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having κ-type or -type crystal structure,
a titanium oxide layer was deposited with a combination
shown in Table 5 under conditions shown in Table 4. In this
state, heat-transforming treatment was performed in an Ar
atmosphere under the following conditions: a pressure of 30 
kPa, a temperature of 1100°C, and a predetermined holding
duration in a range of 20 to 100 minutes to transform the
(Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having a κ-type or -type crystal
structure into (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having an α-type crystal
structure. As a result, coated cermet tools 1 to 13 of the
present invention having the heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers as upper layers of the hard-coating layers were
manufactured, respectively.</p><p num="0054">Furthermore, in manufacturing the coated cermet tools 1
to 13 of the present invention, separate test pieces are
prepared, and those test pieces were loaded into the same
chemical vapor deposition reactor. The test pieces were
taken out of the chemical vapor deposition reactor at the
time when the titanium oxide layers are formed on the
surfaces of the test pieces, and compositions (value Y) and
layer thickness of the titanium oxide layers were measured
(the longitudinal sections of the layers were measured)
using Auger Electron Spectroscopy or a scanning electron
microscope. As a result, all the coated cermet tools showed
substantially the same compositions and average layer
thickness (the average value of values measured at five
points) as the target compositions and target layer
thickness.</p><p num="0055">For the purpose of comparison, as shown in Table 6, the
deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers as upper layers of the hard-coating 
layers with target layer thickness shown in Table 6
were formed under the same conditions as those shown in
Table 3. Then, the conventional cermet tools 1 to 13 were
manufactured under the same conditions as the above ones
except that the formation of the titanium oxide layers and
the heat-transforming treatment under the conditions
mentioned above were not performed.</p><p num="0056">Next, an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph
of the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers and the
deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers that constitute the hard-coating
layers of the coated cermet tools of the present
invention and conventional cermet tools was drawn up using a
field-emission-type scanning electron microscope.</p><p num="0057">Specifically, the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs were drawn up through the following
steps. First, the test pieces are set in a lens-barrel of a
field-emission-type scanning electron microscope, using the
surfaces of the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers
and deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers thereof as surfaces to be
polished. Then, electron beam having an acceleration
voltage of 15 kV are individually radiated on crystal grains
having the hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring range of
the polished surfaces with an irradiating current of 1 nA at
an incidence angle of 70 degrees with respect to the
polished surfaces. Next, an inclination angle of a normal 
line of the plane (0001) as a crystal plane in which each of
the crystal grains is formed with respect to a normal line
of each of the polished surface was measured at an interval
of 0.1 µm/step for an area of 30 x 50 µm, using an electron
backscattering diffraction image device. Based on these
measurement results, among all the measured inclination
angles, the measured inclination angles in a range of 0 to
45 degrees are sorted into several intervals at a pitch of
0.25 degrees, and the frequencies in each sorted interval
are summed up.</p><p num="0058">In the resulting inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs of the various heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers and deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers, an
inclination angle interval in which the plane (0001) shows
the highest peak, and the ratio occupied by the inclination
angle frequencies in an inclination angle interval ranging
from 0 to 10 degrees to all the inclination angle
frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph is shown in Tables 5 and 6, respectively.</p><p num="0059">In the above various inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs, as shown in Tables 5 and 6,
respectively, all the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers of the coated cermet tool of the present invention
show an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on
which the measured inclination angle distribution of the 
plane (0001) shows the highest peak in the inclination angle
interval in a range of 0 to 10 degrees and on which the
ratio of the inclination angle frequencies in the
inclination angle interval ranging from 0 to 10 degrees is
45% or more. To the contrary, all the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers of the conventional coated cermet tools 1 to 13 show
an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which
the distribution of measured inclination angles of the plane
(0001) is unbiased in a range of 0 to 45 degrees, the
highest peak does not appear, and the ratio of the
inclination angle frequencies in the inclination angle
interval ranging from 0 to 10 degrees is 23% or less.</p><p num="0060">In addition, Fig. 2 illustrates an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph of the heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer of the coated cermet tool 2 of the present
invention, and Fig. 6 illustrates an angle frequency-distribution
graph of the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer of the
conventional coated cermet tool 10.</p><p num="0061">Moreover, as for the coated cermet tools 1 to 13 of the
present invention and the conventional coated cermet tools 1
to 13, when the layers that constitute the hard coating
layers of the coated cermet tools are observed using an
electron probe micro-analyzer (EPMA) or the Auger Electron
Spectroscopy (when the longitudinal sections of the layers
are observed), it was found that all the coated cermet tools 
1 to 13 of the present invention are composed of a Ti
compound layer and a heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer, which have substantially the same compositions as the
target compositions, and the Ti compound layer deposited
before heat-transforming treatment also exists in the
surfaces of the tools. On the other hand, it was found that
all the conventional cermet tools 1 to 13 are composed of a
Ti compound layer and a deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, which
have substantially the same compositions as the target
compositions. Further, when the thickness of layers
constituting the hard-coating layers of the coated cermet
tools was measured by using a scanning electron microscope
(similarly, the longitudinal sections of the layers were
measured), all the coated cermet tools had substantially the
same average layer thickness (the average value of values
measured at five points) as the target layer thickness.</p><p num="0062">Next, in a state in which each of the above-mentioned
various coated cermet tools was screw-fixed to a tip of a
bite made of tool steel with a fixing jig, the coated cermet
tools 1 to 13 of the present invention and the conventional
coated cermet tools 1 to 13 were subjected to the following
tests:
<sl><li>(1) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of
alloyed steel (normal cutting speed is 200 m/min) under the
following conditions: <sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS·SCM 420 round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 450 m/min,</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.5 mm,</li><li>Feed rate: 0.3 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 5 min,</li></sl></li><li>(2) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of
carbon steel (normal cutting speed is 250 m/min) under the
following conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS·S25C round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 450 m/min,</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.5 mm,</li><li>Feed rate: 0.35 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 5 min,</li></sl></li><li>(3) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of cast
iron (normal cutting speed is 250 m/min) under the following
conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS·FC250 round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 500 m/min,</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.5 mm, </li><li>Feed rate: 0.3 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 5 min,</li></sl></li></sl>
Then, the width of flank wear of a cutting edge was measured
in each test. The measurement results are shown in Table 7. <img id="img-00580001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00580001.tif" inline="no" he="97"/><img id="img-00590001" orientation="unknown" wi="133" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00590001.tif" inline="no" he="103"/><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="center" namest="1">Layer Constituting Hard Coating Layer</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">Formation Condition (kPa denotes pressure of reaction atmosphere, and °C denotes temperature thereof)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Type</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">Target Composition (atomic ratio)</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">Reaction Gas Composition (volume %)</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4">Reaction Atmosphere</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Pressure</entry><entry align="center">Temperature</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiC</entry><entry align="center">TiC</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 8.5%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiN (First Layer)</entry><entry align="center">TiN</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 30%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">900</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiN (Other Layers)</entry><entry align="center">TiN</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 35%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">1040</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1-TiCN</entry><entry align="center">1-TiC<sub>0.5</sub>N<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 20%, CH<sub>3</sub>CN: 0.6%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">900</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCN</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.5</sub>N<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>:20%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 4%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCO</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.5</sub>O<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CO: 4%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCNO</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.3</sub>N<sub>0.3</sub>O<sub>0.4</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CO: 3%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 3%, N<sub>2</sub>: 20%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 2.2%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1000 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:A</entry><entry align="center">Zr (Value X) : 0.003</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.7%, ZrCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.03%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -type MO:B</entry><entry align="center">Zr (Value X): 0.01</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.6%, ZrCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.1%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:C</entry><entry align="center">Zr (Value X): 0.017</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.53% ZrCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.17%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -type MO:D</entry><entry align="center">Zr (Value X): 0.024</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.46%, ZrCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.24%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:E</entry><entry align="center">Zr (Value X): 0.03</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.4%, ZrCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.3%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -type MO:F</entry><entry align="center">Zr (Value X): 0.037</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.33%, ZrCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.37%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:G</entry><entry align="center">Zr (Value X): 0.043</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.27%, ZrCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.43%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -type MO:H</entry><entry align="center">Zr (Value X): 0.05</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.2%, ZrCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.5%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row><row><entry>(In Table 3, MO denotes (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="center" namest="1">Thin Ti Oxide Layer</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">Formation Condition</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Type</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">Target Composition (atomic ratio)</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">Reaction Gas Composition (volume %)</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4">Reaction Atmosphere</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Pressure (kPa)</entry><entry align="center">Temperature (°C)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">TiO<sub>1.20</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.5%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 0.2%, Ar: 40%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">TiO<sub>1.35</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 3%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5%, Ar: 40%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">TiO<sub>1.50</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 3%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 10%, Ar: 50%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">14</entry> <entry align="center">1000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">TiO<sub>1.60</sub></entry> <entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 1%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 4.5%, Ar: 40%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry> <entry align="center">7</entry> <entry align="center">1000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">TiO<sub>1.75</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 1%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 8%, Ar: 10%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">TiO<sub>1.90</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.2%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5%, Ar: 5%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">900</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-00630001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00630001.tif" inline="no" he="195"/><img id="img-00640001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00640001.tif" inline="no" he="202"/> 
inclination angle interval in which the plane (0001) shows the highest peak;
Frequency Ratio represents a frequency ratio in an inclination angle interval of
0 to 10 degrees] <img id="img-00660001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00660001.tif" inline="no" he="202"/><img id="img-00670001" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00670001.tif" inline="no" he="225"/> 
in which the plane (0001) shows the highest peak; Frequency Ratio represents a
frequency ratio in an inclination angle interval of 0 to 10 degrees] <img id="img-00690001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00690001.tif" inline="no" he="201"/><img id="img-00700001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00700001.tif" inline="no" he="214"/><img id="img-00710001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00710001.tif" inline="no" he="138"/></p><p num="0063">As apparent from the results shown in Tables 5 to 7, in
all the cermet tools 1 to 13 of the present invention in
which the upper layers of the hard coating layers are
composed of a heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> showing an
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which the
inclination angle of the plane (0001) shows the highest peak
in an inclination angle interval in a range of o to 10
degrees and the ratio of the sum of frequencies in the
inclination angle interval ranging from 0 to 10 degrees
occupy 45% or more, the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Zr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers exhibit excellent chipping resistance in high-speed
intermittent cutting of steel or cast iron accompanied with
very high mechanical and thermal impacts and high heat
generation. As a result, occurrence of chipping in cutting
edges is suppressed markedly and the excellent wear
resistance is exhibited. To the contrary, in all the
conventional coated cermet tools 1 to 13 in which the upper
layers of the hard coating layers are composed of a
deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer showing an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph on which the distribution of
measured inclination angles of the plane (0001) is unbiased
in a range from 0 to 45 degrees, and the highest peak does
not appear, the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers could not
resist to severe mechanical and thermal impacts in high-speed
intermittent cutting to generate chipping in the 
cutting edges, consequently shortening the usable life of
the conventional cermet cutting tools.</p><heading>[Example 2]</heading><p num="0064">The following powders, each having a mean particle size
in a range of 1 to 3 µm, were prepared as raw materials for
substrates: WC powder, TiC powder, ZrC powder, VC powder,
TaC powder, NbC powder, Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> powder, TiN powder, TaN powder
and Co powder. Those raw powders were compounded with each
other based on the compounding compositions shown in Table 1,
mixed with each other in an acetone solution having wax
added thereto for 24 hours using a ball mill and were dried
under reduced pressure. Thereafter, the resulting powder
mixtures were press-formed into green compacts having
predetermined shape at a pressure of 98 Mpa. The green
compacts were then sintered in a vacuum under the following
conditions: a pressure of 5 Pa, a predetermined temperature
in a range of 1370 to 1470°C, and a holding duration of 1
hour. After sintering, cutting edges were subjected to
horning (R: 0.07 mm) to manufacture tool substrates A to F
made of WC-based cemented carbide and having throwaway tip
shapes defined in ISO·CNMG120408.</p><p num="0065">Further, the following powders, each having a mean
particle size in a range of 0.5 to 2 µm, were prepared as
raw materials for substrates: TiCN (TiC/TiN=50/50 in weight
ratio) powder, Mo<sub>2</sub>C power, ZrC power, NbC powder, TaC powder, 
WC power, Co powder and Ni powder. Those raw powders were
compounded with each other based on the compounding
composition shown in Table 2, wet-mixed with each other for
24 hours using a ball mill and were dried. Thereafter, the
resulting powder mixtures were press-formed into green
compacts at a pressure of 98 MPa. The green compacts were
then sintered in a nitrogen atmosphere under the following
conditions: a pressure of 1.3 kPa, a temperature of 1540°C,
and a holding duration of 1 hour. After sintering, cutting
edges were subjected to horning (R: 0.07 mm) to manufacture
tool substrates a to f made of TiCN-based cermet and having
tip shapes defined in ISO Standard·CNMG120412.</p><p num="0066">Next, by using a general chemical vapor deposition
reactor, on the surfaces of the tool substrates A to F and a
to f, titanium compound layers as lower layers of the hard-coating
layers were deposited with combinations and target
layer thickness shown in Table 9 under conditions shown in
Table 8 (in Table 8, 1-TiCN represents formation conditions
of TiCN layers having a lengthwise growth crystal structure
described in Japanese Unexamined Patent Application
Publication No. 6-8010, and the others represent formation
conditions of general granular crystal structure). Next,
similarly, (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having a κ-type or -type
crystal structure were deposited with combinations and
target layer thickness shown in Table 9 under conditions 
shown in Table 8. Subsequently, on the surfaces of the (Al,
Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having a κ-type or -type crystal structure, a
titanium oxide layer was deposited with combinations shown
in Table 9 under conditions shown in Table 4. In this state,
heat-transforming treatment was performed in an Ar
atmosphere under the following conditions: a pressure of 30
kPa, a temperature of 1100°C, and a predetermined holding
duration in a range of 20 to 100 minutes to transform the
(Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having a κ-type or -type crystal
structure into (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having an α-type crystal
structure. As a result, coated cermet tools 1 to 13 of the
present invention having the heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers as upper layers of the hard-coating layers were
manufactured, respectively.</p><p num="0067">Furthermore, in manufacturing the coated cermet tools 1
to 13 of the present invention, separate test pieces are
prepared, and those test pieces were loaded into the same
chemical vapor deposition reactor. The test pieces were
taken out of the chemical vapor deposition reactor at the
time when the titanium oxide layers are formed on the
surfaces of the test pieces, and compositions (value Y) and
layer thickness of the titanium oxide layers were measured
(the longitudinal sections of the layers were measured)
using Auger Electron Spectroscopy or a scanning electron
microscope. As a result, all the coated cermet tools showed 
substantially the same compositions and average layer
thickness (the average value of values measured at five
points) as the target compositions and target layer
thickness.</p><p num="0068">For the purpose of comparison, as shown in Table 10,
the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers as upper layers of the
hard-coating layers with target layer thickness shown in
Table 10 were formed under the same conditions as those
shown in Table 8. Then, conventional cermet tools 1 to 13
were manufactured under the same conditions as the above
ones except that the formation of the titanium oxide layer
and the heat-transforming treatment under the conditions
mentioned above were not performed.</p><p num="0069">Next, an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph
of the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers and the
deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers that constitute the hard-coating
layers of the coated cermet tools of the present
invention and conventional cermet tools was drawn up using a
field-emission-type scanning electron microscope.</p><p num="0070">Specifically, the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs were drawn up through the following
steps. First, the test pieces tools are set in a lens-barrel
of a field-emission-type scanning electron microscope,
using the surfaces of the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers and deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers thereof as surfaces 
to be polished. Then, electron beam having an acceleration
voltage of 15 kV are individually radiated on crystal grains
having the hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring range of
the polished surfaces with an irradiating current of 1 nA at
an incidence angle of 70 degrees with respect to the
polished surfaces. Next, an inclination angle of a normal
line of the plane (0001) as a crystal plane in which each of
the crystal grains is formed with respect to a normal line
of each of the polished surface was measured at an interval
of 0.1 µm/step for an area of 30 x 50 µm, using an electron
backscattering diffraction image device. Based on these
measurement results, among all the measured inclination
angles, the measured inclination angles in a range of 0 to
45 degrees are sorted into several intervals at a pitch of
0.25 degrees, and the frequencies in each sorted interval
are summed up.</p><p num="0071">In the resulting inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs of the various heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers and deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers, an
inclination angle interval in which the plane (0001) shows
the highest peak, and the ratio occupied by the inclination
angle frequencies in an inclination angle interval ranging
from 0 to 10 degrees to all the inclination angle
frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph is shown in Tables 9 and 10, respectively. </p><p num="0072">In the above various inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs, as shown in Tables 9 and 10,
respectively, all the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers of the coated cermet tool of the present invention
show an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on
which the measured inclination angle distribution of the
plane (0001) shows the highest peak in the inclination angle
interval in a range of 0 to 10 degrees and on which the
ratio of the inclination angle frequencies in the
inclination angle interval ranging from 0 to 10 degrees is
45% or more. To the contrary, all the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers of the conventional coated cermet tools 1 to 13 show
an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which
the distribution of measured inclination angles of the plane
(0001) is unbiased in a range of 0 to 45 degrees, the
highest peak does not appear, and the ratio of the
inclination angle frequencies in the inclination angle
interval ranging from 0 to 10 degrees is 25% or less.</p><p num="0073">In addition, Fig. 3 illustrates an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph of the heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer of the coated cermet tool 2 of the present
invention, and Fig. 6 illustrates an angle frequency-distribution
graph of the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer of the
conventional coated cermet tool 10.</p><p num="0074">Moreover, as for the coated cermet tools 1 to 13 of the 
present invention and the conventional coated cermet tools 1
to 13, when the layers that constitute the hard coating
layers of the coated cermet tools are observed using an
electron probe micro-analyzer (EPMA) or the Auger electron
Spectroscopy (when the longitudinal sections of the layers
are observed), it was found that all the coated cermet tools
1 to 13 of the present invention are composed of a Ti
compound layer and a heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer, which have substantially the same compositions as the
target compositions, and the Ti compound layer deposited
before heat-transforming treatment also exists in the
surface of the tools. On the other hand, it was found that
all the conventional cermet tools 1 to 13 are composed of a
Ti compound layer and a deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, which
have substantially the same compositions as the target
compositions. Further, when the thickness of layers
constituting the hard-coating layers of the coated cermet
tools was measured by using a scanning electron microscope
(similarly, the longitudinal sections of the layers were
measured), all the coated cermet tools had substantially the
same average layer thickness (the average value of values
measured at five points) as the target layer thickness.</p><p num="0075">Next, in a state in which each of the above-mentioned
various coated cermet tools was screw-fixed to a tip of a
bite made of tool steel with a fixing jig, the coated cermet 
tools 1 to 13 of the present invention and the conventional
coated cermet tools 1 to 13 were subjected to the following
tests:
<sl><li>(1) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of
alloyed steel (normal cutting speed is 200 m/min) under the
following conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS·SCM 440 round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 350 m/min,</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.5 mm,</li><li>Feed rate: 0.2 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 10 min,</li></sl></li><li>(2) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of
carbon steel (normal cutting speed is 250 m/min) under the
following conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS·S30C round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 450 m/min,</li><li>Depth of cut: 2.0 mm,</li><li>Feed rate: 0.3 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 10 min,</li></sl></li><li>(3) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of cast
iron (normal cutting speed is 250 m/min) under the following 
conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS·FC300 round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 400 m/min,</li><li>Depth of cut: 2.5 mm,</li><li>Feed rate: 0.25 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 10 min,</li></sl></li></sl>
Then, the width of flank wear of a cutting edge was measured
in each test. The measurement results are shown in Table 11. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="center" namest="1">Layer Constituting Hard Coating Layer</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">Formation Condition (kPa denotes pressure of reaction atmosphere, and °C denotes temperature thereof)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Type</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">Target Composition (atomic ratio)</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">Reaction Gas Composition (volume %)</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4">Reaction Atmosphere</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Pressure</entry><entry align="center">Temperature</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiC</entry><entry align="center">TiC</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 8.5%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiN (First Layer)</entry><entry align="center">TiN</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 30%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">900</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiN (Other Layers)</entry><entry align="center">TiN</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 35%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">1040</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1-TiCN</entry><entry align="center">1-TiC<sub>0.5</sub>N<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 20%, CH<sub>3</sub>CN: 0.6%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">900</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCN</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.5</sub>N<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>:20%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 4%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCO</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.5</sub>O<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CO: 4%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCNO</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.3</sub>N<sub>0.3</sub>O<sub>0.4</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CO: 3%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 3%, N<sub>2</sub>: 20%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 2.2%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1000 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:A</entry><entry align="center">Cr (Value X): 0.005</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 2.5%, CrCl<sub>3</sub>: 0.05%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 2.2%, HCl: 3%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.1%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -type MO:B</entry><entry align="center">Cr (Value X): 0.012</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 2.5%, CrCl<sub>3</sub>: 0.08%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 2.2%, HCl: 3%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.3%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:C</entry><entry align="center">Cr (Value X): 0.02</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 2.3% CrCl<sub>3</sub>: 0.08%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 2.2%, HCl: 3%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.1%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -type MO:D</entry><entry align="center">Cr (Value X): 0.025</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 2.3%, CrCl<sub>3</sub>: 0.1%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 2.2%, HCl: 3%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.3%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:E</entry><entry align="center">Cr (Value X): 0.03</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 2.2%, CrCl<sub>3</sub>: 0.1%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 2%, HCl: 3%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.1%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -type MO:F</entry><entry align="center">Cr (Value X): 0.035</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 2.2%, CrCl<sub>3</sub>: 0.12%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 2%, HCl: 3%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.3%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:G</entry><entry align="center">Cr (Value X): 0.04</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 2.2%, CrCl<sub>3</sub>: 0.15%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 2%, HCl: 3%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.1%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry>[In Table 8, MO denotes (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>]</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-00840001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00840001.tif" inline="no" he="213"/><img id="img-00850001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00850001.tif" inline="no"  he="213"/><img id="img-00860001" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="tb"  file="00860001.tif"  inline="no"  he="37"/><img id="img-00870001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00870001.tif" inline="no" he="225"/><img id="img-00880001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00880001.tif" inline="no" he="220"/><img id="img-00890001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00890001.tif" inline="no" he="48"/><img id="img-00900001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00900001.tif" inline="no" he="191"/><img id="img-00910001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00910001.tif" inline="no" he="208"/><img id="img-00920001" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00920001.tif" inline="no" he="135"/></p><p num="0076">As apparent from the results shown in Tables 9 to 11,
in all the cermet tools 1 to 13 of the present invention in
which the upper layers of the hard coating layers are
composed of a heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> showing an
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which the
inclination angle of the plane (0001) shows the highest peak
in an inclination angle interval in a range of 0 to 10
degrees and the ratio of the sum of frequencies in the
inclination angle interval ranging from 0 to 10 degrees
occupy 45% or more, the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Cr)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers exhibit excellent chipping resistance in high-speed
intermittent cutting of steel or cast iron accompanied with
very high mechanical and thermal impacts and high heat
generation. As a result, occurrence of chipping in cutting
edges is suppressed markedly and the excellent wear
resistance is exhibited. To the contrary, in all the
conventional coated cermet tools 1 to 13 in which the upper
layers of the hard coating layers are composed of a
deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer showing an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph on which the distribution of
measured inclination angles of the plane (0001) is unbiased
in a range from 0 to 45 degrees, and the highest peak does
not appear, the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers could not
resist to severe mechanical and thermal impacts in high-speed
intermittent cutting to generate chipping in the 
cutting edges, consequently shortening the usable life of
the conventional cermet cutting tools.</p><heading>[Example 3]</heading><p num="0077">The following powders, each having a mean particle size
in a range of 1 to 3 µm, were prepared as raw materials for
substrates: WC powder, TiC powder, ZrC powder, VC powder,
TaC powder, NbC powder, Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> powder, TiN powder, TaN powder
and Co powder. Those raw powders were compounded with each
other based on the compounding compositions shown in Table 1,
mixed with each other in an acetone solution having wax
added thereto for 24 hours using a ball mill and were dried
under reduced pressure. Thereafter, the resulting powder
mixtures were press-formed into green compacts having
predetermined shape at a pressure of 98 Mpa. The green
compacts were then sintered in a vacuum under the following
conditions: a pressure of 5 Pa, a predetermined temperature
in a range of 1370 to 1470°C, and a holding duration of 1
hour. After sintering, cutting edges were subjected to
horning (R: 0.07 mm) to manufacture tool substrates A to F
made of WC-based cemented carbide and having throwaway tip
shapes defined in ISO.CNMG120408.</p><p num="0078">Further, the following powders, each having a mean
particle size in a range of 0.5 to 2 µm, were prepared as
raw materials for substrates: TiCN (TiC/TiN=50/50 in weight
ratio) powder, Mo<sub>2</sub>C power, Zrc power, NbC powder, TaC powder, 
WC power, Co powder and Ni powder. Those raw powders were
compounded with each other based on the compounding
composition shown in Table 2, wet-mixed with each other for
24 hours using a ball mill and were dried. Thereafter, the
resulting powder mixtures were press-formed into green
compacts at a pressure of 98 MPa. The green compacts were
then sintered in a nitrogen atmosphere under the following
conditions: a pressure of 1.3 kPa, a temperature of 1540°C,
and a holding duration of 1 hour. After sintering, cutting
edges were subjected to horning (R: 0.07 mm) to manufacture
tool substrates a to f made of TiCN-based cermet and having
tip shapes defined in ISO·Standard CNMG120412.</p><p num="0079">Next, by using a general chemical vapor deposition
reactor, on the surfaces of the tool substrates A to F and a
to f, titanium compound layers as lower layers of the hard-coating
layers were deposited with combinations and target
layer thickness shown in Table 13 under conditions shown in
Table 12 (in Table 12, 1-TiCN represents formation
conditions of TiCN layers having a lengthwise growth crystal
structure described in Japanese Unexamined Patent
Application Publication No. 6-8010, and the others represent
formation conditions of general granular crystal structure).
Next, similarly, (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having a κ-type or -type
crystal structure were deposited with combinations and
target layer thickness shown in Table 13 under conditions 
shown in Table 12. Subsequently, on the surfaces of the (Al,
Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having a κ-type or -type crystal structure, a
titanium oxide layer was deposited with combinations shown
in Table 13 under conditions shown in Table 4. In this
state, heat-transforming treatment was performed in an Ar
atmosphere under the following conditions: a pressure of 30
kPa, a temperature of 1100°C, and a predetermined holding
duration in a range of 20 to 100 minutes to transform the
(Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having a κ-type or -type crystal
structure into (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having an α-type crystal
structure. As a result, coated cermet tools 1 to 13 of the
present invention having the heat-transformed α-type (Al,
Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers as upper layers of the hard-coating layers were
manufactured, respectively.</p><p num="0080">Furthermore, in manufacturing the coated cermet tools 1
to 13 of the present invention, separate test pieces are
prepared, and those test pieces were loaded into the same
chemical vapor deposition reactor. The test pieces were
taken out of the chemical vapor deposition reactor at the
time when the titanium oxide layers are formed on the
surfaces of the test pieces, and compositions (value Y) and
layer thickness of the titanium oxide layers were measured
(the longitudinal sections of the layers were measured)
using Auger Electron Spectroscopy or a scanning electron
microscope. As a result, all the coated cermet tools showed 
substantially the same compositions and average layer
thickness (the average value of values measured at five
points) as the target compositions and target layer
thickness.</p><p num="0081">For the purpose of comparison, as shown in Table 14,
the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers as upper layers of the
hard-coating layers with target layer thickness shown in
Table 14 were formed under the same conditions as those
shown in Table 12. Then, conventional cermet tools 1 to 13
were manufactured under the same conditions as the above
ones except that the formation of the titanium oxide layer
and the heat-transforming treatment under the conditions
mentioned above were not performed.</p><p num="0082">Next, an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph
of the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers and the
deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers that constitute the hard-coating
layers of the coated cermet tools of the present
invention and conventional cermet tools was drawn up using a
field-emission-type scanning electron microscope.</p><p num="0083">Specifically, the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs were drawn up through the following
steps. First, the test pieces tools are set in a lens-barrel
of a field-emission-type scanning electron microscope,
using the surfaces of the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers and deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers thereof as surfaces 
to be polished. Then, electron beam having an acceleration
voltage of 15 kV are individually radiated on crystal grains
having the hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring range of
the polished surfaces with an irradiating current of 1 nA at
an incidence angle of 70 degrees with respect to the
polished surfaces. Next, an inclination angle of a normal
line of the plane (0001) as a crystal plane in which each of
the crystal grains is formed with respect to a normal line
of each of the polished surface was measured at an interval
of 0.1 µm/step for an area of 30 x 50 µm, using an electron
backscattering diffraction image device. Based on these
measurement results, among all the measured inclination
angles, the measured inclination angles in a range of 0 to
45 degrees are sorted into several intervals at a pitch of
0.25 degrees, and the frequencies in each sorted interval
are summed up.</p><p num="0084">In the resulting inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs of the various heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers and deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers, an
inclination angle interval in which the plane (0001) shows
the highest peak, and the ratio occupied by the inclination
angle frequencies in an inclination angle interval ranging
from 0 to 10 degrees to all the inclination angle
frequencies on the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph is shown in Tables 13 and 14, respectively. </p><p num="0085">In the above various inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs, as shown in Tables 13 and 14,
respectively, all the heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers of the coated cermet tool of the present invention
show an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on
which the measured inclination angle distribution of the
plane (0001) shows the highest peak in the inclination angle
interval in a range of 0 to 10 degrees and on which the
ratio of the inclination angle frequencies in the
inclination angle interval ranging from 0 to 10 degrees is
45% or more. To the contrary, all the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers of the conventional coated cermet tools 1 to 13 show
an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which
the distribution of measured inclination angles of the plane
(0001) is unbiased in a range of 0 to 45 degrees, the
highest peak does not appear, and the ratio of the
inclination angle frequencies in the inclination angle
interval ranging from 0 to 10 degrees is 25% or less.</p><p num="0086">In addition, Fig. 4 illustrates an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph of the heat-transformed α-type
(Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer of the coated cermet tool 2 of the present
invention, and Fig. 6 illustrates an angle frequency-distribution
graph of the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer of the
conventional coated cermet tool 10.</p><p num="0087">Moreover, as for the coated cermet tools 1 to 13 of the 
present invention and the conventional coated cermet tools 1
to 13, when the layers that constitute the hard coating
layers of the coated cermet tools are measured using an
electron probe micro-analyzer (EPMA) or the Auger Electron
Spectroscopy (when the longitudinal sections of the layers
are observed), it was found that all the coated cermet tools
1 to 13 of the present invention are composed of a Ti
compound layer and a heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layer, which have substantially the same compositions as the
target compositions, and the Ti compound layer deposited
before heat-transforming treatment also exists in the
surfaces of the tools. On the other hand, it was found that
all the conventional cermet tools 1 to 13 are composed of a
Ti compound layer and a deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, which
have substantially the same compositions as the target
compositions. Further, when the thickness of layers
constituting the hard-coating layers of the coated cermet
tools was measured by using a scanning electron microscope
(similarly, the longitudinal sections of the layers were
measured), all the coated cermet tools had substantially the
same average layer thickness (the average value of values
measured at five points) as the target layer thickness.</p><p num="0088">Next, in a state in which each of the above-mentioned
various coated cermet tools was screw-fixed to a tip of a
bite made of tool steel with a fixing jig, the coated cermet 
tools 1 to 13 of the present invention and the conventional
coated cermet tools 1 to 13 were subjected to the following
tests:
<sl><li>(1) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of
alloyed steel (normal cutting speed is 200 m/min) under the
following conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS·SCM 415 round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 400 m/min,</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.5 mm,</li><li>Feed rate: 0.35 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 5 min,</li></sl></li><li>(2) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of
carbon steel (normal cutting speed is 250 m/min) under the
following conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS·S35C round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 450 m/min,</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.5 mm,</li><li>Feed rate: 0.25 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 5 min,</li></sl></li><li>(3) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of cast
iron (normal cutting speed is 250 m/min) under the following 
conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS·FC150 round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 550 m/min,</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.5 mm,</li><li>Feed rate: 0.3 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 5 min,</li></sl></li></sl>
Then, the width of flank wear of a cutting edge was measured
in each test. The measurement results are shown in Table 15. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="center" namest="1">Layer Constituting Hard Coating Layer</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">Formation Condition (kPa denotes pressure of reaction atmosphere, and °C denotes temperature thereof)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Type</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">Target Composition (atomic ratio)</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">Reaction Gas Composition (volume %)</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4">Reaction Atmosphere</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Pressure</entry><entry align="center">Temperature</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiC</entry><entry align="center">TiC</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 8.5%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiN (First Layer)</entry><entry align="center">TiN</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 30%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">900</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiN (Other Layers)</entry><entry align="center">TiN</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 35%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">1040</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1-TiCN</entry><entry align="center">1-TiC<sub>0.5</sub>N<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 20%, CH<sub>3</sub>CN: 0.6%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">900</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCN</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.5</sub>N<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>:20%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 4%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCO</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.5</sub>O<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CO: 4%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCNO</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.3</sub>N<sub>0.3</sub>O<sub>0.4</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CO: 3%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 3%, N<sub>2</sub>: 20%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 2.2%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1000 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:A</entry><entry align="center">Ti (Value X): 0.01</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.27%, TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.03%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -type MO:B</entry><entry align="center">Ti (Value X): 0.015</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 4.24%, TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.07%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:C</entry><entry align="center">Ti (Value X): 0.02</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.23% TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.07%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -type MO:D</entry><entry align="center">Ti (Value X): 0.025</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 4.19%, TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.11%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:E</entry><entry align="center">Ti (Value X): 0.03</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.20%, TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.10%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -type MO:F</entry><entry align="center">Ti (Value X): 0.035</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 4.15%, TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.15%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-type MO:G</entry><entry align="center">Ti (Value X): 0.04</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.17%, TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.13%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -type MO:H</entry><entry align="center">Ti (Value X): 0.05</entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 4.09%, TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 0.22%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row><row><entry>[In Table 12, MO denotes (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>]</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-01050001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01050001.tif" inline="no" he="195"/><img id="img-01060001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01060001.tif" inline="no" he="207"/><img id="img-01070001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01070001.tif" inline="no" he="38"/><img id="img-01080001" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01080001.tif" inline="no" he="215"/><img id="img-01090001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01090001.tif" inline="no" he="218"/><img id="img-01100001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01100001.tif" inline="no" he="32"/><img id="img-01110001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01110001.tif" inline="no" he="208"/><img id="img-01120001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01120001.tif" inline="no" he="216"/><img id="img-01130001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01130001.tif" inline="no" he="121"/></p><p num="0089">As apparent from the results shown in Tables 13 to 15,
in all the cermet tools 1 to 13 of the present invention in
which the upper layers of the hard coating layers are
composed of a heat-transformed α-type (Al, Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> showing an
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on which the
inclination angle of the plane (0001) shows the highest peak
in an inclination angle interval in a range of 0 to 10
degrees and the ratio of the sum of frequencies in the
inclination angle interval ranging from 0 to 10 degrees
occupy 45% or more, the heat-transformed α-type (Al-Ti)<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers exhibit excellent chipping resistance in high-speed
intermittent cutting of steel or cast iron accompanied with
very high mechanical and thermal impacts and high heat
generation. As a result, occurrence of chipping in cutting
edges is suppressed markedly and the excellent wear
resistance is exhibited. To the contrary, in all the
conventional coated cermet tools 1 to 13 in which the upper
layers of the hard coating layers are composed of a
deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer showing an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph on which the distribution of
measured inclination angles of the plane (0001) is unbiased
in a range from 0 to 45 degrees, and the highest peak does
not appear, the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers could not
resist to severe mechanical and thermal impacts in high-speed
intermittent cutting to generate chipping in the 
cutting edges, consequently shortening the usable life of
the conventional cermet cutting tools.</p><heading>[Example 4]</heading><p num="0090">The following powders, each having a mean particle size
in a range of 1 to 3 µm, were prepared as raw materials for
substrates: WC powder, TiC powder, ZrC powder, VC powder,
TaC powder, NbC powder, Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> powder, TiN powder, TaN powder
and Co powder. Those raw powders were compounded with each
other based on the compounding compositions shown in Table 1,
mixed with each other in an acetone solution having wax
added thereto for 24 hours using a ball mill and were dried
under reduced pressure. Thereafter, the resulting powder
mixtures were press-formed into green compacts having
predetermined shape at a pressure of 98 Mpa. The green
compacts were then sintered in a vacuum under the following
conditions: a pressure of 5 Pa, a predetermined temperature
in a range of 1370 to 1470°C, and a holding duration of 1
hour. After sintering, cutting edges were subjected to
horning (R: 0.07 mm) to manufacture tool substrates A to F
made of WC-based cemented carbide and having throwaway tip
shapes defined in ISO·CNMG120408.</p><p num="0091">Further, the following powders, each having a mean
particle size in a range of 0.5 to 2 µm, were prepared as
raw materials for substrates: TiCN (TiC/TiN=50/50 in weight
ratio) powder, Mo<sub>2</sub>C power, Zrc power, NbC powder, TaC powder, 
WC power, Co powder and Ni powder. Those raw powders were
compounded with each other based on the compounding
composition shown in Table 2, wet-mixed with each other for
24 hours using a ball mill and were dried. Thereafter, the
resulting powder mixtures were press-formed into green
compacts at a pressure of 98 MPa. The green compacts were
then sintered in a nitrogen atmosphere under the following
conditions: a pressure of 1.3 kPa, a temperature of 1540°C,
and a holding duration of 1 hour. After sintering, cutting
edges were subjected to horning (R: 0.07 mm) to manufacture
tool substrates a to f made of TiCN-based cermet and having
tip shapes defined in ISO Standard·CNMG120412.</p><p num="0092">Next, by using a general chemical vapor deposition
reactor, on the surfaces of the tool substrates A to F and a
to f, titanium compound layers as lower layers of the hard-coating
layers were deposited with combinations and target
layer thickness shown in Table 17 under conditions shown in
Table 16 (in Table 16, 1-TiCN represents formation
conditions of TiCN layers having a lengthwise growth crystal
structure described in Japanese Unexamined Patent
Application Publication No. 6-8010, and the others represent
formation conditions of general granular crystal structure).
Next, similarly, the deposited κ, -Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers were
deposited with combinations and target layer thickness shown
in Table 17 under conditions shown in Table 16. 
Subsequently, on the surfaces of the deposited κ, -Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers, a titanium oxide thin layer was deposited with
combinations shown in Table 17 under conditions shown in
Table 4. Heat-transforming treatment was performed in an Ar
atmosphere under the following conditions: a pressure of 30
kPa, a temperature of 1100°C, and a predetermined holding
duration in a range of 10 to 60 minutes to transform the
deposited κ, -Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers into Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers having an α-type
crystal structure. As a result, coated cermet tools 1 to 13
of the present invention having the transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers as upper layers of the hard coating layers were
manufactured, respectively.</p><p num="0093">Furthermore, in manufacturing the coated cermet tools 1
to 13 of the present invention, separate test pieces are
prepared, and those test pieces were loaded into the same
chemical vapor deposition reactor. The test pieces were
taken out of the chemical vapor deposition reactor at the
time when the thin titanium oxide thin layers are formed on
the surfaces of the test pieces, and compositions (value X)
and average layer thickness (µm) of the thin titanium oxide
thin layer were measured (the longitudinal sections of the
layers were measured) using Auger Electron Spectroscopy or a
transmission electron microscope.</p><p num="0094">For the purpose of comparison, as shown in Table 18,
the deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers as upper layers of the 
hard-coating layers with target layer thickness shown in
Table 18 were formed under the same conditions as those
shown in Table 16. Then, conventional cermet tools 1 to 13
were manufactured under the same conditions as the above
ones except that the formation of the titanium oxide thin
layer and the heat-transforming treatment under the
conditions mentioned above were not performed.</p><p num="0095">Next, an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph
of the heat-transformed α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers and the deposited
α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers that constitute the hard-coating layers
of the coated cermet tools of the present invention and
conventional cermet tools was drawn up using a field-emission-type
scanning electron microscope.</p><p num="0096">Specifically, the inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs were drawn up through the following
steps. First, the test pieces tools are set in a lens-barrel
of a field-emission-type scanning electron microscope,
using the surfaces of the transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers and
deposited α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers thereof as surfaces to be polished.
Then, electron beam having an acceleration voltage of 15 kV
are individually radiated on crystal grains having the
hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring range of the
polished surfaces with an irradiating current of 1 nA at an
incidence angle of 70 degrees with respect to the polished
surfaces. Next, an inclination angle of a normal line of 
the plane (0001) as a crystal plane in which each of the
crystal grains is formed with respect to a normal line of
each of the polished surface was measured at an interval of
0.1 µm/step for an area of 30 x 50 µm, using an electron
backscattering diffraction image device. Based on these
measurement results, among all the measured inclination
angles, the measured inclination angles in a range of 0 to
45 degrees are sorted into several intervals at a pitch of
0.25 degrees, and the frequencies in each sorted interval
are summed up.</p><p num="0097">In the resulting inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs of the various heat-transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
layers and deposited α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers, an inclination angle
interval in which the plane (0001) shows the highest peak,
and the ratio occupied by the inclination angle frequencies
in an inclination angle interval ranging from 0 to 10
degrees to all the inclination angle frequencies on the
inclination angle frequency-distribution graph is shown in
Tables 17 and 18, respectively.</p><p num="0098">In the above various inclination angle frequency-distribution
graphs, as shown in Tables 17 and 18,
respectively, all the α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers of the coated cermet
tool of the present invention show an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph on which the measured
inclination angle distribution of the plane (0001) shows the 
highest peak in the inclination angle interval in a range of
0 to 10 degrees and on which the ratio of the inclination
angle frequencies in the inclination angle interval ranging
from 0 to 10 degrees is 45% or more. To the contrary, all
the deposited α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers of the conventional coated
cermet tools 1 to 13 show an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which the distribution of measured
inclination angles of the plane (0001) is unbiased in a
range of 0 to 45 degrees, the highest peak does not appear,
and the ratio of the inclination angle frequencies in the
inclination angle interval ranging from 0 to 10 degrees is
25% or less.</p><p num="0099">In addition, Fig. 5 illustrates an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph of the transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer
of the coated cermet tool 9 of the present invention, and
Fig. 6 illustrates an angle frequency-distribution graph of
the deposited α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer of the conventional coated cermet
tool 10.</p><p num="0100">Moreover, as for the resulting coated cermet tools 1 to
13 of the present invention and the resulting conventional
coated cermet tools 1 to 13, when the layers that constitute
the hard coating layers of the coated cermet tools are
measured using the Auger Electron Spectroscopy (when the
longitudinal sections of the layers are observed), it was
found that all the coated cermet tools 1 to 13 of the 
present invention are composed of a Ti compound layer and a
transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, which have substantially the same
compositions as the target compositions, and the Ti compound
layer deposited in the surfaces of the tools before heat-transforming
treatment also has the substantially the same
compositions in the above measurement as the target
compositions. On the other hand, it was found that all the
conventional cermet tools 1 to 13 are composed of a Ti
compound layer and a deposited α-type Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer, which have
substantially the same compositions as the target
compositions. Moreover, when the thickness of layers
constituting the hard coating layers of the coated cermet
tools was measured by using a scanning electron microscope
(similarly, the longitudinal sections of the layers were
measured), all the coated cermet tools had substantially the
same average layer thickness (the average value of values
measured at five points) as the target layer thickness.</p><p num="0101">Next, in a state in which each of the above-mentioned
various coated cermet tools was screw-fixed to a tip of a
bite made of tool steel with a fixing jig, the coated cermet
tools 1 to 13 of the present invention and the conventional
coated cermet tools 1 to 13 were subjected to the following
tests:
<sl><li>(1) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of
alloyed steel (normal cutting speed is 200 m/min) under the 
following conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS·SCr 420H round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 380 m/min,</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.5 mm,</li><li>Feed rate: 0.2 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 10 min,</li></sl></li><li>(2) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of
carbon steel (normal cutting speed is 200 m/min) under the
following conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS.S40C round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 350 m/min,</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.0 mm,</li><li>Feed rate: 0.25 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 10 min,</li></sl></li><li>(3) a dry high-speed intermittent cutting test of cast
iron (normal cutting speed is 200 m/min) under the following
conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece: a JIS·FCD450 round bar having four
longitudinal grooves equidistantly arranged in the
longitudinal direction,</li><li>Cutting speed: 400 m/min, </li><li>Depth of cut: 1.5 mm,</li><li>Feed rate: 0.3 mm/rev,</li><li>Cutting time: 10 min,</li></sl></li></sl>
Then, the width of flank wear of a cutting edge was measured
in each test. The measurement results are shown in Table 19. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="center" namest="1">Layer Constituting Hard Coating Layer</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">Formation Condition (kPa denotes pressure of reaction atmosphere, and °C denotes temperature thereof)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Type</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">Target Composition (atomic ratio)</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">Reaction Gas Composition (volume %)</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4">Reaction Atmosphere</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Pressure</entry><entry align="center">Temperature</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiC</entry><entry align="center">TiC</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 8.5%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiN (First Layer)</entry><entry align="center">TiN</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 30%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">900</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiN (Other Layers)</entry><entry align="center">TiN</entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 35%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">1040</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1-TiCN</entry><entry align="center">1-TiC<sub>0.5</sub>N<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>: 20%, CH<sub>3</sub>CN: 0.6%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">900</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCN</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.5</sub>N<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, N<sub>2</sub>:20%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 4%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCO</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.5</sub>O<sub>0.5</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CO: 4%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">TiCNO</entry><entry align="center">TiC<sub>0.3</sub>N<sub>0.3</sub>O<sub>0.4</sub></entry><entry align="center">TiCl<sub>4</sub>: 4.2%, CO: 3%, CH<sub>4</sub>: 3%, N<sub>2</sub>: 20%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 2.2%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>:</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">1000 </entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">Balance</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited κ-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">κ-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 3.3%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 2.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">950</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Deposited -Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="center">AlCl<sub>3</sub>: 4.3%, CO<sub>2</sub>: 5.5%, HCl: 1.2%, H<sub>2</sub>S: 0.2%, H<sub>2</sub>: Balance</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">800</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-01260001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01260001.tif" inline="no" he="199"/><img id="img-01270001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01270001.tif" inline="no" he="193"/><img id="img-01280001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01280001.tif" inline="no" he="207"/><img id="img-01290001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01290001.tif" inline="no" he="226"/><img id="img-01300001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01300001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/><img id="img-01310001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01310001.tif" inline="no" he="203"/><img id="img-01320001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01320001.tif" inline="no" he="210"/><img id="img-01330001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="01330001.tif" inline="no" he="133"/></p><p num="0102">As apparent from the results shown in Tables 17 to 19,
in all the cermet tools 1 to 13 of the present invention in
which the upper layers of the hard coating layers are
composed of a transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> showing an inclination
angle frequency-distribution graph on which the inclination
angle of the plane (0001) shows the highest peak in an
inclination angle interval in a range of 0 to 10 degrees and
the ratio of the sum of frequencies in the inclination angle
interval ranging from 0 to 10 degrees occupy 45% or more,
the transformed α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers exhibit excellent chipping
resistance in high-speed intermittent cutting of steel or
cast iron accompanied with very high mechanical and thermal
impacts and high heat generation. As a result, occurrence
of chipping in cutting edges is suppressed markedly and the
excellent wear resistance is exhibited. To the contrary, in
all the conventional coated cermet tools 1 to 13 in which
the upper layers of the hard coating layers are composed of
a deposited α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer showing an inclination angle
frequency-distribution graph on which the distribution of
measured inclination angles of the plane (0001) is unbiased
in a range from 0 to 45 degrees, and the highest peak does
not appear, the deposited α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers could not resist to
severe mechanical and thermal impacts in high-speed
intermittent cutting to generate chipping in the cutting
edges, consequently shortening the usable life of the 
conventional cermet cutting tools.</p><p num="0103">As described above, the coated cermet tools of the
present invention exhibit excellent chipping resistance not
only in continuous cutting or intermittent cutting of
various materials such as steel and cast iron under normal
conditions but also in high-speed intermittent cutting work
having severe cutting conditions, and exhibit excellent
cutting performance for a prolonged period of time.
Accordingly, it is possible to sufficiently and
satisfactorily cope with the demand for high performance of
a cutting device, labor saving and energy saving in cutting
work, and cost reduction.</p><p num="0104">Further, the coated cermet tools of the present
invention exhibit excellent chipping resistance not only in
continuous cutting or intermittent cutting of various
materials such as steel and cast iron under normal
conditions but also in high-speed intermittent cutting under
the severest cutting condition accompanied with very high
mechanical and thermal impacts and high heat generation, and
exhibit excellent cutting performance for a prolonged period
of time. Accordingly, it is possible to sufficiently and
satisfactorily cope with the demand for high performance of
a cutting device, labor saving and energy saving in cutting
work, and cost reduction. </p><heading>[Name of Document] DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0105"><sl><li>[Fig. 1] (a)
<sl><li>NORMAL LINE OF POLISHED SURFACE</li><li>NORMAL LINE OF PLANE (0001)</li><li>INCLINATION ANGLE OF PLANE (0001): 0 DEGREE</li><li>POLISHED SURFACE</li></sl></li><li>[Fig. 1] (b)
<sl><li>NORMAL LINE OF POLISHED SURFACE</li><li>NORMAL LINE OF PLANE (0001)</li><li>INCLINATION ANGLE OF PLANE (0001): 45 DEGREES</li><li>POLISHED SURFACE</li></sl></li><li>[Fig. 2]
<sl><li>INCLINATION ANGLE INTERVAL (DEGREES)</li><li>SUMMED FREQUENCY</li></sl></li><li>[Fig. 3]
<sl><li>INCLINATION ANGLE INTERVAL (DEGREES)</li><li>SUMMED FREQUENCY</li></sl></li><li>[Fig. 4]
<sl><li>INCLINATION ANGLE INTERVAL (DEGREES)</li><li>SUMMED FREQUENCY</li></sl></li><li>[Fig. 5]
<sl><li>INCLINATION ANGLE INTERVAL (DEGREES)</li><li>SUMMED FREQUENCY</li></sl></li><li>[Fig. 6]
<sl><li>INCLINATION ANGLE INTERVAL (DEGREES)</li><li>SUMMED FREQUENCY</li></sl></li></sl></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A surface-coated cermet cutting tool with a hard-coating
layer having excellent chipping resistance,
   wherein the surface-coated cermet cutting tool is
formed by coating, on a surface of a tool substrate made of
tungsten carbide-based cemented carbide or titanium
carbonitride-based cermet, a hard-coating layer composed of
the following upper and lower layers (a) and (b):
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) as the lower layer, a titanium compound layer
having at least one or two of a titanium carbide layer, a
titanium nitride layer, a titanium carbonitride layer, a
titanium carboxide layer and a titanium oxycarbonitride
layer, all of which are deposited by chemical vapor
deposition, the titanium compound layer having a total
average layer thickness of 3 to 20 µm, and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) as the upper layer, a heat-transformed α-type Al-Zr
oxide layer formed by carrying out a heat-transforming
treatment in a state that a titanium oxide layer satisfying
the composition formula: TiOY, (where value Y is 1.2 to 1.9
in an atomic ratio to Ti when measured by Auger Electron
Spectroscopy) and having an average layer thickness of 0.05
to 1.5 µm is chemically deposited on a surface of an Al-Zr
oxide layer having a κ-type or -type crystal structure
deposited by chemical vapor deposition and satisfying the
composition formula: (Al1-xZrx)2O3 (where value X is 0.003 to
0.05 in an atomic ratio when measured by an electron probe
micro-analyzer (EPMA)) to thereby transform the crystal
structure of the Al-Zr oxide layer having the κ-type or -type
crystal structure into an α-type crystal structure,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the heat-transformed α-type Al-Zr oxide layer
shows an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on
which a highest peak appears in an inclination angle
interval in a range of 0 to 10 degrees and the sum of
frequencies in a range of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or
more of the total sum of frequencies on the inclination
angle frequency-distribution graph, in which the inclination
angle frequency-distribution graph is obtained from results
of radiating electron beam onto crystal grains having a
hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring range of surfaces
to be polished using a field-emission-type scanning electron
microscope, measuring an inclination angle of a normal line
of the plane (0001) as a crystal plane in which each of the
crystal grains is formed with respect to each of the
polished surfaces, sorting the measured inclination angles
in a range of 0 to 45 degrees among all the measured
inclination angles into several intervals at a pitch of 0.25
degrees, and summing up the frequencies in each of the
intervals, and
   wherein the heat-transformed α-type Al-Zr oxide layer
has an average layer thickness of 1 to 15 µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A surface-coated cermet cutting tool with a hard-coating
layer having excellent chipping resistance,
   wherein the surface-coated cermet cutting tool is
formed by coating, on a surface of a tool substrate made of
tungsten carbide-based cemented carbide or titanium
carbonitride-based cermet, the hard-coating layer composed
of the following upper and lower layers (a) and (b):
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) as the lower layer, a titanium compound layer
having at least one or two of a titanium carbide layer, a
titanium nitride layer, a titanium carbonitride layer, a
titanium carboxide layer and a titanium oxycarbonitride
layer, all of which are deposited by chemical vapor
deposition, and the titanium compound layer having a total
average layer thickness of 3 to 20 µm, and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) as the upper layer, a heat-transformed α-type Al-Cr
oxide layer formed by carrying out a heat-transforming
treatment in a state that a titanium oxide layer satisfying
the composition formula: TiOY, (where value Y is 1.2 to 1.9
in an atomic ratio to Ti when measured by Auger Electron
Spectroscopy) and having an average layer thickness of 0.1
to 2 µm is chemically deposited on a surface of an Al-Cr
oxide layer having a κ-type or -type crystal structure
deposited by chemical vapor deposition and satisfying the
composition formula: (Al1-xCrx)2O3 (where value X is 0.005 to
0.04 in an atomic ratio when measured by an electron probe
micro-analyzer (EPMA)) to thereby transform the crystal
structure of the Al-Cr oxide layer having the κ-type or -type
crystal structure into an α-type crystal structure,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the heat-transformed α-type Al-Cr oxide layer
shows an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on
which a highest peak appears in an inclination angle
interval in a range of 0 to 10 degrees and the sum of
frequencies in a range of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or
more of the total sum of frequencies on the inclination
angle frequency-distribution graph, in which the inclination
angle frequency-distribution graph is obtained from the
results of radiating electron beam onto crystal grains
having a hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring range of
surfaces to be polished using a field-emission-type scanning
electron microscope, measuring an inclination angle of a
normal line of the plane (0001) as a crystal plane in which
each of the crystal grains is formed with respect to each of
the polished surfaces, sorting the measured inclination
angles in a range of 0 to 45 degrees among all the measured
inclination angles into several intervals at a pitch of 0.25
degrees, and summing up the frequencies in each of the
intervals, and wherein the heat-transformed α-type Al-Cr
oxide layer has an average layer thickness of 1 to 15 µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A surface-coated cermet cutting tool with a hard-coating
layer having excellent chipping resistance,
   wherein the surface-coated cermet cutting tool is
formed by coating, on a surface of a tool substrate made of
tungsten carbide-based cemented carbide or titanium
carbonitride-based cermet, the hard-coating layer composed
of the following upper and lower layers (a) and (b):
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) as the lower layer, a titanium compound layer
having at least one or two of a titanium carbide layer, a
titanium nitride layer, a titanium carbonitride layer, a
titanium carboxide layer and a titanium oxycarbonitride
layer, all of which are deposited by chemical vapor
deposition, and the titanium compound layer having a total
average layer thickness of 3 to 20 µm, and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) as the upper layer, a heat-transformed α-type Al-Ti
oxide layer formed by carrying out a heat-transforming
treatment in a state that a titanium oxide layer satisfying
the composition formula: TiOY, (where value Y is 1.2 to 1.9
in an atomic ratio to Ti when measured by Auger Electron
Spectroscopy) and having an average layer thickness of 0.05
to 1.5 µm is chemically deposited on a surface of an Al-Ti
oxide layer having a κ-type or -type crystal structure
deposited by chemical vapor deposition and satisfying the
composition formula: (Al1-xTix)2O3 (where value X is 0.01 to
0.05 in an atomic ratio when measured by an electron probe
micro-analyzer (EPMA)) to thereby transform the crystal
structure of the Al-Ti oxide layer having the κ-type or -type
crystal structure into an α-type crystal structure,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the heat-transformed α-type Al-Ti oxide layer
shows an inclination angle frequency-distribution graph on
which a highest peak appears in an inclination angle
interval in a range of 0 to 10 degrees and the sum of
frequencies in a range of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or
more of the total sum of frequencies on the inclination
angle frequency-distribution graph, in which the inclination
angle frequency-distribution graph is obtained from the
results of radiating electron beam onto crystal grains
having a hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring range of
surfaces to be polished using a field-emission-type scanning
electron microscope, measuring an inclination angle of a
normal line of the plane (0001) as a crystal plane in which
each of the crystal grains is formed with respect to each of
the polished surfaces, sorting the measured inclination
angles in a range of 0 to 45 degrees among all the measured
inclination angles into several intervals at a pitch of 0.25
degrees, and summing up the frequencies in each of the
intervals, and
   wherein the heat-transformed α-type Al-Ti oxide layer
has an average layer thickness of 1 to 15 µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A surface-coated cermet cutting tool with a hard-coating
layer having excellent chipping resistance,
   wherein the surface-coated cermet cutting tool being
formed by coating, on a surface of a tool substrate made of
tungsten carbide-based cemented carbide or titanium
carbonitride-based cermet, the hard-coating layer composed
of the following upper and lower layers (a) and (b):
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) as the lower layer, a titanium compound layer
having at least one or two of a titanium carbide layer, a
titanium nitride layer, a titanium carbonitride layer, a
titanium carboxide layer and a titanium oxycarbonitride
layer, all of which are deposited by chemical vapor
deposition, the titanium compound layer having a total
average layer thickness of 3 to 20 µm, and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) as the upper layer, a heat-transformed α-type
aluminum oxide layer formed by carrying out a heat-transforming
treatment in a state that a titanium oxide thin
layer satisfying the composition formula: TiOx, (where value
X to Ti is 1.2 to 1.9 in an atomic ratio when measured by
Auger Electron Spectroscopy) and having an average layer
thickness of 0.05 to 1.0 µm is chemically deposited on a
surface of a heat-transformed aluminum oxide layer having a
κ-type or -type crystal structure deposited by chemical
vapor deposition to thereby transform the crystal structure
of the aluminum oxide layer having the κ-type or -type
crystal structure into an α-type crystal structure,</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the heat-transformed α-type aluminum oxide
layer shows an inclination angle frequency-distribution
graph on which a highest peak appears in an inclination
angle interval in a range of 0 to 10 degrees and the sum of
frequencies in a range of 0 to 10 degrees occupies 45% or
more of the total sum of frequencies on the inclination
angle frequency-distribution graph, in which the inclination
angle frequency-distribution graph is obtained from results
of radiating electron beam onto crystal grains having a
hexagonal crystal lattice in a measuring range of surfaces
to be polished using a field-emission-type scanning electron
microscope, measuring an inclination angle of a normal line
of the plane (0001) as a crystal plane in which each of the
crystal grains is formed with respect to each of the
polished surfaces, sorting the measured inclination angles
in a range of 0 to 45 degrees among all the measured
inclination angles into several intervals at a pitch of 0.25
degrees, and summing up the frequencies in each of the
intervals, and wherein the heat-transformed α-type
aluminum oxide layer has an average layer thickness of 1 to
15 µm.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>