<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1054071-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1054071" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="20415442" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20001122"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1054071-A2" status="new" fvid="23009576"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1054071</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20001122</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00109343-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00109343</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000502</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="SE-9901590-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>SE</country><doc-number>9901590</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990504</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22F   7/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22F   7/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C   1/05        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C   1/05        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  29/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  29/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22C   1/05B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22C  29/08</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L22F998:00+B22F9/02S</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L22F999:00+B22F1/00A+B22F9/04</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung eines verbesserten fein körnigen Sinterkarbidkörper aus WC-Co</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method of manfacturing an improved fine-grained WC-Co cemented carbide</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé de fabrication d'un corp de carbure cémenté de WC-Co à grain fin</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-4950328-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4950328</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998003690-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998003690</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998003691-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998003691</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999013120-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999013120</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DAUB, H.W. (WIDIA) ET AL: "Performance potentials of super-fine and ultra-fine grained hard alloys and their manufacture.ÄLeistungspotentiale von Feinst- und Ultrafeinstkorn-Hartmetallen und ihre Herstellung.Ü." DEUTSCHE GESELLSCHAFT FUR METALLKUNDE. ADENSAUERALLEE 21, OBERURSEL 1, 6370, GERMANY. 1995. 285-306, NUMERICAL DATA, GRAPHS, 13 REF. CONFERENCE: POWDER TECHNOLOGY PATHS TO THE FUTURE (PULVERTECHNOLOGISCHE WEGE IN DIE ZUKUNFT), HAGEN, GERMANY, 16-17 N, XP002149436</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>LEIDERMAN, M. (TECHNION) ET AL: "Sintering, microstructure and properties of submicron cemented carbides." PLANSEE PROCEEDINGS. VOLUME 2. CEMENTED CARBIDES AND HARD MATERIALS (1997), 718-729, NUMERICAL DATA, GRAPHS, 19 REF. PLANSEE AG. REUTTE, TYROL, AUSTRIA CONFERENCE: 14TH INTERNATIONAL PLANSEE SEMINAR '97, TIROL, AUSTRIA, 12-16 MAY 1997, XP002145388</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>SCHUBERT, W.D. (TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITAT WIEN) ET AL: "Hardness to toughness relationship of fine-grained WC-Co hardmetals." INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF REFRACTORY METALS &amp; HARD MATERIALS (1998) 16, (2), 133-142, GRAPHS, NUMERICAL DATA, 9 REF. ISSN: 0263-4368, XP002145389</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SANDVIK AB</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SANDVIK AKTIEBOLAG</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SANDVIK AKTIEBOLAG</last-name><address><street/><city>811 81 Sandviken</city><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OSKARSSON ROLF</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OSKARSSON, ROLF</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OSKARSSON, ROLF</last-name><address><street>Svampstigen B2</street><city>14440 Rönninge</city><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Taquist, Lennart</last-name><address><street>Sandvik AB Patent Department</street><city>811 81 Sandviken</city><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties> <international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country> <country>DK</country> <country>ES</country> <country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention relates to a method of making a WC-Co-based
cemented carbide with a fine WC-grain size. The cemented
carbide is produced from well deagglomerated or easy to
deagglomerate WC powder with round morphology, a Co powder also
well deagglomerated or easy to deagglomerate and with a grain size
equal to or smaller than the WC grain size and grain growth
inhibitors. According to the invention the metal part of the grain
growth inhibitors is added as part of the binder phase i.e. is
included in the Co powder and alloyed therewith.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to an improved method of making
fine-grained WC-Co cemented carbide.</p><p num="0002">Cemented carbides for metal cutting have been used for almost
70 years. All the time improvements have been made and higher
productivity has been achieved. One of the biggest inventions in
this area was the coatings with thin layers of TiC, TiN, Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>
etc., which have increased the metal removal rate considerably.
The coatings have also been developed from the initial high
temperature chemical vapour deposition (HT-CVD) towards lower
deposition temperature (MT-CVD) and also Physical Vapour
Deposition (PVD). The thickness and the adherence of the coatings
have been improved as well which have changed the compositions for
the cemented carbide substrates. Previously these substrates were
more cutting tool materials than today when they are often just
substrates adapted for optimum performance when combined with a
coating. When the coating is worn through the cutting edge is
changed.</p><p num="0003">Substrate development has included reducing the content of
cubic carbides in the WC-Co-based cemented carbide substrates.
These developments lead to a demand for finer WC grain size in the
sintered cemented carbide than previously.</p><p num="0004">Extremely fine-grained WC-Co cemented carbides have been
developed for drilling of composite printed circuit boards and
similar applications. Here not only submicron but also so-called
'nano-sized' materials are available. The limit for 'nano-sized'
is not defined in detail, but often up to 200 nm (0.2 µm) is
considered as nano-size. Special production methods are used for
these types of material.</p><p num="0005">The present invention relates to WC-Co-based cemented
carbides produced from raw materials made via 'traditional' ways,
i.e. tungsten carbide powder produced separately by carburizing
tungsten metal powder or tungsten oxide with carbon and cobalt
powder. Gas carburizing is of course included. The precipitation
of a cobalt salt on the surface of tungsten carbide followed by
reduction to metallic cobalt is consequently excluded.</p><p num="0006">The sintered WC mean grain sizes for alloys with improved
properties if produced via the present invention are in the area
0.6-1.6 µm, preferably 0.6-1.4 µm. Also 0.4 µm WC alloys can 
advantageously be produced this way but here there are not so many
applications for ordinary metal cutting so far.</p><p num="0007">For submicron material grain growth inhibitors are used as a
rule: Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> and/or combinations of VC+Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> are used for finer
grain sizes.</p><p num="0008">All cubic carbides in Groups IV and V of the periodic table
act as grain growth inhibitors for WC-Co-alloys: TiC, ZrC, HfC,
VC, NbC, TaC but also the hexagonal Mo<sub>2</sub>C and the orthorombic Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>
of Group VI. For WC-Co-alloys with a sintered mean grain size of
1.0-1.6 µm for the tungsten carbide, TaC is a very common grain
size stabilizer/grain growth inhibitor, but also NbC is used often
in combination with TaC. Mo<sub>2</sub>C can be used as well, both in the
submicron and micron grain size area (0.8-1.6 µm).</p><p num="0009">The traditional way to produce cemented carbide is to wet
mill the desired proportions of WC, Co and grain growth
inhibitors, if any, and pressing agent like PEG or A-wax, in a
ball mill with milling bodies of WC-Co (in order to avoid unwanted
impurities in the material) extensively in alcohol/water or any
other milling liquid. The final grain size of the tungsten carbide
is determined during this process. The tungsten carbide is often
strongly agglomerated and this is also valid for the cobalt
powder. The milling process is often very long in order to:
<sl><li>1. Determine the final grain size of the tungsten carbide.</li><li>2. Get an even dispersion of the grain growth inhibitors to
avoid grain growth in any part.</li><li>3. Have the cobalt evenly dispersed to avoid porosity and
cobalt lakes in the sintered material.</li></sl></p><p num="0010">This long milling time is detrimental to:
<sl><li>1) Wear of the milling bodies</li><li>2) Wear of the inner walls of the mills (high
maintenance cost)</li><li>3) Investment costs in a lot of mills to produce the
wanted amount of material</li></sl></p><p num="0011">A long milling time will also create a very wide distribution
in grain size of the milled WC particles. The numerous
consequences of this broad distribution include: high compaction
pressure with high deflection at unloading of the punch and high
risk for cracks with modern complex geometries and the formation
of unfavourable morphologies of the sintered WC grains 
(triangular, prismatic etc) resulting in low toughness (transverse
rupture strength).</p><p num="0012">After milling, the slurry must be dried, often in a
spraydrier, to get a free-flowing powder. This powder is then
pressed and sintered to blanks followed by grinding to the final
dimensions and often coated.</p><p num="0013">The object of the present invention is to avoid the
production disadvantages described above and also to increase the
performance level for the sintered material, mainly the toughness.</p><p num="0014">The invention consists of the following basic concepts:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>A well defined, narrow grain size distributed WC raw
material with rounded morphology is used in which its final
(sintered) grain size is already determined when it is produced
via reduction and carburization. The WC must be deagglomerated
into single grains or be easy to deagglomerate. If a cemented
carbide with a sintered WC mean grain size of 1.3 µm is wanted the
original WC must have a mean grain size of about (1.0-) 1.2 µm
because a certain small, but controlled, grain growth can never be
avoided.</li><li>A well defined, narrow grain sized Co raw material, also
with rounded morphology and with a mean grain size equivalent to
or smaller than the mean WC grain size with which it will be mixed
is selected. The cobalt powder must also be easy to deagglomerate.
Advantageously, this Co raw material already includes at least the
metal part of the grain growth inhibitors, i.e. the addition of
the grain growth inhibitor is part of the Co powder production
process. This means that also the cobalt is 'tailor made' for the
final sintered alloy, because the amount and type of grain growth
inhibitor additions are dependent on both final (sintered) WC
grain size and the amount of binder phase desired.</li><li>A short milling time which is rather a blending and mixing
than a traditional milling.</li></ul></p><p num="0015">The use of the concepts listed above gives a cemented carbide
with better production economy combined with better compacting
properties (less cracks and better tolerances i.e. better shape
stability) and increased toughness. The toughness increase is due
to a better morphology with more rounded and less triangular and
prismatic WC grains. With the grain growth inhibitors present
where they are wanted/needed, i.e. the contact surfaces between Co
and WC, the amount of grain growth inhibitors can often be 
decreased. Because these inhibitors, especially VC, are well known
to decrease the toughness, a decrease of these elements but still
the same effect because they are placed where they are needed, a
better toughness can be obtained.</p><p num="0016">The invention is suitable for additions of up to 3,
preferably up to 2, weight-% of V and/or Cr, Ti and Ta and/or Nb.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0017">Two powder batches were produced, one according to
established technology and one according to the invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Known technique</u>:</heading><p num="0018"><sl><li>89.5 w/o WC, 0.8 µm (FSSS)</li><li>10.0 w/o Co standard (1.5 µm)</li><li>0.5 w/o Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub></li><li>Milling time: 30 h</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Invention:</u></heading><p num="0019"><sl><li>89.5 w/o WC, 0.70 µm (FSSS)</li><li>10.43 w/o Co-Cr (0.65 µm)</li><li>0.07 w/o C (carbon compensation)</li><li>Milling time: 3 h</li></sl></p><p num="0020">The Co-Cr alloy according to the invention contains Co and Cr
in the proportions 10/0.43 and is easy to deagglomerate as well as
the WC according to the invention.</p><p num="0021">The mills were identical as well as the total amount of
powder in the mills. The slurries were spray dried with the same
process parameters.</p><p num="0022">The two powders were pressed to insert blanks, SNUN 120308,
in tools for 18% shrinkage when sintering.</p><p num="0023">The compacting pressure was 145 MPa for the powder produced
according to existing technique and 110 MPa for powder according
to the invention.</p><p num="0024">Desired compacting pressure is 100±20 MPa.</p><p num="0025">The pressed compacts were then sintered in the same batch and
had the same hardness in as-sintered condition, 1600±25 HV3.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 2</heading><p num="0026">Of the same powders as in example 1, test pieces 5.5x6.5x21
mm were produces. They were sintered together and then tested in a
3-point bending test with the following results, mean values: <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Known technique</entry><entry align="left">Invention</entry></row><row><entry align="right">2725±300 MPa</entry><entry align="right">3250±200 MPa</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>EXAMPLE 3</heading><p num="0027">Two alloys with the same composition were made, one according
to the present invention and one according to known technique.</p><heading><u style="single">Known technique</u></heading><p num="0028"><sl><li>93.5 w/o WC   1.2 µm FSSS</li><li>6.0 w/c Co standard (1.5 µm)</li><li>0.5 w/o TaC</li><li>Milling time: 40 h</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Invention</u></heading><p num="0029"><sl><li>93.5 w/o WC   1.0 µm (FSSS)</li><li>6.4 w/o Co-Ta 0.8 µm</li><li>0.1 w/o C (carbon compensation)</li><li>Milling time: 4 h</li></sl></p><p num="0030">The two variants were produced according to example 1. When
pressing the same test inserts, SNUN 120308, the compacting
pressure for 18% shrinkage was 160 MPa for the powder according to
existing technique and 115 MPa for the powder according to the
invention. After sintering both variants had the same hardness,
1750±25 HV3.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>Method of making a WC-Co-based cemented carbide with a
fine WC grain size using at least one grain growth inhibitor by
mixing a well deagglomerated or easy to deagglomerate WC powder
with round morphology, a Co powder also well deagglomerated or
easy to deagglomerate characterised in that said at
least one grain growth inhibitor is added as part of the Co powder
i.e. is included in the Co powder and alloyed therewith.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>Method according to claim 1 characterised in
that the Co-powder has a mean grain size equal to or smaller than
the WC-powder mean grain size.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>Method according to any of the preceding claims
characterised in that the sintered mean WC grain size
is 0.6-1.4 µm.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>