<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1209255-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1209255" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="20281913" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020529"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1209255-A2" status="new" fvid="23440572"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1209255</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20020529</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01126183-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01126183</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011105</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="SE-0004272-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>SE</country><doc-number>0004272</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001122</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23B  27/14        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23B  27/14        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23C   5/16        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23C   5/16        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23P  15/28        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23P  15/28        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/40        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/40        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/44        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/44        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/455       20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  16/455       20060101C I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  30/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  30/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  16/40D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  16/455F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  30/00B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Oxidbeschichtetes Schneidwerkzeug</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Oxide coated cutting tool</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Outil de coupe revêtu d'oxyde</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0753602-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0753602</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4984940-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4984940</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5589223-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5589223</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1995019457-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1995019457</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>SANDVIK AB</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SANDVIK AKTIEBOLAG</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SANDVIK AKTIEBOLAG</last-name><address><street/><city>811 81 Sandviken</city><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BUDZYNSKI LARS-ANDERS</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LJUNGBERG BJOERN</name><address><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BUDZYNSKI, LARS-ANDERS</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LJUNGBERG, BJOERN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BUDZYNSKI, LARS-ANDERS</last-name><address><street>Dalhemsvägen 4</street><city>14146 Huddinge</city><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Ljungberg, Björn</last-name><address><street>Kulstötarvägen 96</street><city>12244 Enskede</city><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Taquist, Lennart</last-name><address><street>Sandvik AB Patent Department</street><city>811 81 Sandviken</city><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data> </bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>According to the present invention there is provided a body at
least partially coated with one or more refractory layers of which
at least one layer essentially consist of α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>. Said α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer
consists of essentially equiaxed grains with an average
grain size of &lt; 1 µm and with a bimodal grain size distribution
with coarser grains with an average grainsize in the interval 0.5
- 1 µm and finer grains with an average grainsize of &lt;0.5 µm. The
Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer further contains striated zones containing titanium
(&gt;5 at %) but no nitrogen or carbon. This particular microstructure
is obtained by temporarily stopping the gases needed for the
growth of the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer and introducing TiCl<sub>4</sub>.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="77" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="109"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a coated cutting tool for
chipforming machining. The coating includes at least one alumina
(Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) layer characterized by fine, equiaxed grains.</p><p num="0002">Cemented carbide cutting tools coated with various types of
Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layers using Chemical Vapour Deposition (CVD), e.g., pure κ-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>,
mixtures of κ-and α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> coarse grained α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and fine
grained textured α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> have been commercially available for
years generally in multilayer combinations with other metal carbide
and/or nitride-layers, the metal being selected from transition
metals of the IVB, VB and VIB groups of the Periodic Table.</p> <p num="0003">Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> crystallises in several different phases: α, κ, γ, δ, 
etc. The two most frequently occurring phases of CVD-produced wear
resistant Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layers are the thermodynamically stable, α-phase
and the metastable κ-phase or a mixture thereof. Generally, the K-phase
exhibits a grainsize in the range 0.5-3.0 µm and the grains
predominately grow through the whole coating forming a columnar
type coating morphology. Furthermore, the κ-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layers are free
from crystallographic defects and also free from micropores and
voids.</p> <p num="0004">Coarsegrained (3-6 µm) α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> often possesses porosity and
crystallographic defects, while finegrained textured α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> are
free of defects with very pronounced columnar-shaped grains.</p> <p num="0005">In US 5,674,564 is disclosed a method of growing a finegrained
κ-alumina-layer by employing a low deposition temperature
and a high concentration of a sulphur dopant.</p><p num="0006">In US 5,487,625 a method is disclosed for obtaining a fine
grained, (012)-textured α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer consisting of columnar
grains with a small cross section (about 1 µm).</p><p num="0007">In US 5,766,782 a method is disclosed for obtaining a finegrained
(104)-textured α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer.</p><p num="0008">As mentioned above, all Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layers produced by the CVD technique
possess a more or less columnarlike grainstructure. An
Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer with an equiaxed grainstructure is, however, expected
to show some favourable mechanical properties, e g resistance to
crack propagation, as compared to a layer with a columnar grainstructure.
One well-known and possible technique to avoid columnar
grain growth is to deposit a so-called multilayer structure in
which the columnar growth of e g Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is periodically interrupted 
by the growth of a thin, 0.1-1 µm second layer such as disclosed in
US 4,984,940. The second layer should preferably have a different
crystal structure or at least different lattice spacings in order
to be able to initiate renucleation of the first layer. One example
of such a technique is when the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> growth periodically is
interrupted by a short TiN deposition process resulting in a
(Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>+TiN)xn multilayer structure with a thickness of the individual
TiN-layers of about 0.1-1 µm e g see Proceedings of the
12:th European CVD Conference page pr.8-349. However, such multilayer
structures very often suffer from a low adherence between
the two different types of layers.</p><p num="0009">It is the object of the present invention to provide onto a
hard substrate, or preferably onto a hard substrate coated with a
TiC<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>O<sub>z</sub>-layer, at least one single phase α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer with a microstructure
which is different from the prior art columnar α- or
κ-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> CVD layers mentioned above. It is also the object of the
present invention to provide a high performance tool coating comprising
the invented Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer.</p><p num="0010">It is a further object of the invention to provide an alumina
coated cutting tool insert with improved cutting performance in
steel, stainless steel, cast iron and in particular nodular cast
iron.</p><p num="0011">Figure 1a is a Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM) micrograph
of an Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer according to the present invention.</p><p num="0012">Figure 1b is a SEM micrograph at high magnification of a polished
cross-section of an Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer according to the present invention.</p><p num="0013">Figure 2a is a SEM micrograph prior art Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer.</p><p num="0014">Figure 2b is a SEM micrograph at high magnification of a polished
cross-section of an Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer according to the prior art.</p><p num="0015">Figure 3a is a SEM micrograph of a prior art multilayer
Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>/TiN coating.</p><p num="0016">Figure 3b is a SEM micrograph at high magnification of a polished
cross-section of an Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>/TiN multilayer according to the
prior art.</p><p num="0017">Surprisingly it has been found that a non-columnar α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer
can be deposited by interrupting the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> growth process by
obstructing the flow of the CO<sub>2</sub>, AlCl<sub>3</sub>, HCl and H<sub>2</sub>S gases to the
reactor chamber and then immediately introducing TiCl<sub>4</sub> (H<sub>2</sub> is already
present in the reactor) for a short period of time. When the 
reactant gases AlCl<sub>3</sub>, HCl, CO<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>S are allowed to reenter the
reactor again in that mentioned order, renucleation of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> will
take place. The duration of the TiCl<sub>4</sub> treatment as well as the
TiCl<sub>4</sub> concentration are important parameters which must be optimized
in order to obtain the desired result. If the TiCl<sub>4</sub> concentration
is too low or/and treatment time is too short, the renucleation
of the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer will not be sufficiently dense to
cover a sufficient portion of the whole coating surface. If, on
the other hand, the TiCl<sub>4</sub> concentration is too high and/or the
treatment time is too long, the cohesion between the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> grains
will be too weak resulting in a low quality coating.</p><p num="0018">The method of the present invention thus relates to the coating
of a body with an α-alumina-layer during which the body is
brought in contact with a hydrogen carriergas containing one or
more halides of aluminium and a hydrolysing and/or oxidising agent
at temperature of the body between 950 and 1000 °C. The oxidation
potential of the CVD-reactor atmosphere prior to the nucleation of
Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is kept at a low level keeping the total concentration of
H<sub>2</sub>O, water vapour, or other oxidising species, preferably less
than 5 ppm. The Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> growth is started by sequencing the following
gases AlCl<sub>3</sub>, HCl and CO<sub>2</sub> (H<sub>2</sub> is already present in the reactor)
into the reaction chamber in that mentioned order or by using
the start-up procedures described in any of the prior art patents,
US 5,487,625 and US 5,766,782, in order to achieve different textures
of the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer. After 10-60 minutes a sulphur dopant,
preferably H<sub>2</sub>S, is added to the gas mixture. The flow of the CO<sub>2</sub>,
AlCl<sub>3</sub>, HCl gases and the sulphur dopant are periodically interrupted
at intervals of 10-50 minutes and 1-10 % (of the hydrogen
flow) TiCl<sub>4</sub> is allowed to enter the reactor for a period of 1-10
minutes and then again replaced by AlCl<sub>3</sub>, HCl, CO<sub>2</sub> and the sulphur
dopant in that mentioned order. This procedure is repeatedly carried
out in order to obtain a striated, bimodal α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer-structure
with the desired grainsize and texture.</p><p num="0019">In contrast to the columnar grains of prior art Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layers,
the grains of the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layers according to the present invention
are essentially equiaxed with a bimodal structure which is a mixture
of small and large grains. The obtained grainsize and the
distribution of the same are dependent on the number of TiCl<sub>4</sub>
treatments carried out. The more frequently the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> process is
interrupted and the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> surface is treated with TiCl<sub>4</sub>, the 
smaller the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> grains will be. The coarser Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> grains have an
average grain size d<sub>c</sub>≤1 µm and the finer Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> grains 0.1≤d<sub>f</sub>≤d<sub>c</sub>/3.</p><p num="0020">The grainsize in the α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer can be determined from a
SEM top-view micrograph at about 4000X magnification. Such a micrograph
of an Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer surface according to the present invention
is shown in Fig 1a. In Fig 2a and 3a, the micrographs of
prior art Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layers are shown. The size and the shape of the
grains can easily be observed. Furthermore, the striated zones in
the α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer which contain titanium and oxygen are visible in
a polished cross section at 4000-6000 X magnification. These striated
zones which do not contain any carbon or nitrogen may also
contain some aluminium. The striated zones are preferably &lt;0.2 µm
thick and the number of striated zones per µm Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer should be
1-10. They may be closely linked together but in some cases almost
resembling a multilayer structure. The presence of these striated
zones in the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> structure evidently limits the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> grain
growth and makes renucleation possible without the negative effect
of fully intermediate or intervening layers.</p><p num="0021">By selecting appropriate conditions for the initial growth of
the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer, e g according to the procedures in patents US
5,487,625 and US 5,766,782, Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layers textured in the (012)-,
(024)- or (104)-directions with a texture coefficient TC&gt;1.3 can
be deposited.</p><p num="0022">The texture Coefficient, TC, is defined as:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">TC(hkl) = <st32:frac align="centre">I (hkl)<st32:over>I<st32:sub pos="post">o</st32:sub> (hkl)</st32:over></st32:frac> {<st32:frac align="centre">1<st32:over>n</st32:over></st32:frac> Σ <st32:frac align="centre">I (hkl)<st32:over>I<st32:sub pos="post">o</st32:sub> (hkl)</st32:over></st32:frac>} <st32:sup pos="post">-1</st32:sup></st32:df>
   where
<sl><li>I(hkl) = measured intensity of the (hkl) reflection</li><li>I<sub>o</sub>(hkl) = standard intensity of the ASTM standard powder
pattern diffraction data</li><li>n = number of reflections used in the calculation, (hkl)
reflections used are: (012), (104), (110), (113), (024),
(116)</li></sl></p><p num="0023">More specifically, the coated body comprises a cutting tool
with a substrate of cemented carbide, cermet, ceramic or superhard
material and with at least on the functioning parts of the surface
thereof a coating consisting of a hard wear resistant material. In
said coating at least one layer is a single phase α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer 
according to the present invention, and said single phase α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer
having a thickness in the range 0.5-25 µm. The other layers
in the coating structure may be TiC or related carbide, nitride,
carbonitride, oxycarbide and oxycarbonitride of a metal selected
from the Groups IVB, VB, and VIB of the Periodic Table, the elements
B, Al and Si and/or mixtures thereof. Such other layers may
be deposited by CVD, PACVD (Plasma CVD), PVD (Physical Vapour
Deposition) or MT-CVD (Moderate Temperature CVD). At least one of
such other layers is in contact with the substrate. The total
thickness of the coating of the cutting tool can vary between 1
and 30 µm.</p><heading><u style="single">Example</u></heading><p num="0024"><sl><li>A) Cemented carbide cutting inserts in style CNMG 120412-KM
with the composition 6 weight-% Co and balance WC were coated with
a 5 µm thick layer of Ti(C,N) using the MTCVD-technique with TiCl<sub>4</sub>,
H<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>2</sub> and CH<sub>3</sub>CN as process gases. In subsequent process steps
during the same coating cycle, a 0.5 µm TiC<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>O<sub>z</sub>-layer with an approximate
composition corresponding to x=0.5, y=0.3 and z=0.2 was
deposited followed by a 6 µm thick layer of α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> deposited according
to the invented coating process. Prior to the nucleation
of the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> the oxidation potential of the carrier gas H<sub>2</sub> (only
gas present in the reactor) i.e. the water vapour concentration,
was explicitly set to a low level, less than 5 ppm.
Then the first Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer step 1 was started up. The process
conditions during the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> deposition were as below:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Step</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">CO<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="left">4%</entry><entry align="left">4%</entry><entry align="left">0%</entry><entry align="left">4%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">AlCl<sub>3</sub></entry><entry align="left">4%</entry><entry align="left">4%</entry><entry align="left">0%</entry><entry align="left">4%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">H<sub>2</sub>S</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">0.2%</entry><entry align="left">0%</entry><entry align="left">0.2%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">HCl</entry><entry align="left">1.5%</entry><entry align="left">5%</entry><entry align="left">0%</entry><entry align="left">5%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">H<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="left">balance</entry><entry align="left">balance</entry><entry align="left">balance</entry><entry align="left">balance</entry></row><row><entry align="left">TiCl<sub>4</sub></entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">-</entry><entry align="left">5%</entry><entry align="left">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pressure</entry><entry align="left">60 mbar</entry><entry align="left">60 mbar</entry><entry align="left">60 mbar</entry><entry align="left">60 mbar</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Temperature</entry><entry align="left">1000°C</entry><entry align="left">1000°C</entry><entry align="left">1000°C</entry><entry align="left">1000°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Duration</entry><entry align="left">30 min</entry><entry align="left">20 min</entry><entry align="left">5 min</entry><entry align="left">20 min</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables> The Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer was deposited by proceeding through step 1, 2
and 3 and then looping between step 3 and step 2 nine times and
finishing the process by step 4. Hence, the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-process was interrupted
and treated with TiCl<sub>4</sub>/H<sub>2</sub> altogether ten times.XRD-analysis of the deposited α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> showed a strongly textured
structure with a texture coefficient TC(012) of 1.7 of the
(012) planes and TC(024) of 1.5 of the (024) planes.From the SEM-micrographs taken from the top surface, similar
to Fig 1a, the grainsize was determined. The coarse grains had an
average grainsize of 0.9 µm and the fine grains had an average
grainsize of 0.3 µm.</li><li>B) The cemented carbide substrate of A) was coated with
Ti(C,N) (5 µm), a 0.5 µm TiC<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>O<sub>z</sub>-layer and Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (6 µm) as set
forth in A) except for that the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> process was carried out according
to prior art technique i.e. the same process as described
under A) except for that the TiCl<sub>4</sub>/H<sub>2</sub>-treatments were excluded and
an Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> process time of 290 min. This resulted in an Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer
consisting essentially of the κ-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> phase with an average grainsize
of about 2 µm, Fig 2a.</li><li>C) The cemented carbide substrate of A) was coated with
Ti(C,N) (5 µm), a 0.5 µm TiC<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>O<sub>z</sub>-layer and a 6 µm of multilayered
Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> coating on top as set forth in A) except for that step 3 was
substituted by a prior art TiN-process step. The process parameters
for this TiN-step were as follow: 2 % TiCl<sub>4</sub>, 40 % N<sub>2</sub>, 58 % H<sub>2</sub>
and a process time of 3 min. This resulted in a multilayer coating
consisting of eleven layers of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and ten thin layers of TiN.
The Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer was determined to consist of the κ-phase.</li></sl></p><p num="0025">Coated tool inserts from A), B) and C) were all wet blasted
with 150 mesh Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> powder in order to smooth the coating surfaces.</p><p num="0026">The cutting inserts were then tested with respect to edge line
and rake face flaking in a facing operation in nodular cast iron.
The shape of the machined work piece was such that the cutting
edge is intermitted twice during each revolution.

Cutting data:

   Speed = 170 m/min,

   Cutting depth = 2.0 mm and

   Feed = 0.1 mm/rev. </p><p num="0027">The inserts were run one cut over the face of the work piece.
This test is very decisive and demanding when cutting nodular cast
iron.</p><p num="0028">The percentage of the edge line in cut that obtained flaking
into the carbide substrate was recorded for each insert tested as
well as to what extent flaking occurred on the rake phase of the
cutting insert.</p><p num="0029">The results are expressed in the table below as an average
value of the four inserts.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="4" align="center" namest="3">Flaking</entry></row><row><entry nameend="2" align="center" namest="1"/><entry align="center" namest="3">Edge line</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">Rake face</entry></row><row><entry align="center">A)</entry><entry align="left">α-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>

single phase/striated (acc. to invention)</entry><entry align="left">0 %</entry><entry align="left">only spot-wise flaking of the Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-layer</entry></row><row><entry align="center">B)</entry><entry align="left">κ-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>

(prior art)</entry><entry align="left">90 %</entry><entry align="left">severe Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-flaking</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C)</entry><entry align="left">multilayer Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>/TiN

(prior art)</entry><entry align="left">70 %</entry><entry align="left">Flaking between TiN and Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layers</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>Cutting tool comprising a body on which at least on the
functioning parts of the surface thereof, a hard and wear resistant
coating is applied characterized in said coating
comprising a structure of one or more refractory layers of which
at least one layer essentially consist of α-Al2O3in that said α-Al2O3-layer
consists of essentially equiaxed grains with an average
grainsize of &lt;1 µm and further containing striated zones containing
&gt;5 at % titanium but no nitrogen or carbon.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>Cutting tool according to claim 1 characterised
in that said Al2O3-layer has a bimodal grainsize distribution with
coarser grains with an average grain size dc≤1 µm and the finer
grains df in the interval 0.1≤df≤dc/3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>Cutting tool according to any of the preceding claims
characterised in that said striated zones are &lt;0.2 µm
thick and the number thereof per µm Al2O3-layer 1-10.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>Cutting tool according to any of the preceding claims
characterized in that said alumina layer is textured
in at least one of the directions (012), (104) or (024) with a
texture coefficient larger than 1.3, the texture coefficient being
defined as:
TC(hkl) = I (hkl)Io (hkl) {1n Σ I (hkl)Io (hkl)} -1
   where
<claim-text><claim-text>I(hkl) = measured intensity of the (hkl) reflection</claim-text><claim-text>Io(hkl) = standard intensity of the ASTM standard powder pattern
diffraction data</claim-text><claim-text>n = number of reflections used in the calculation</claim-text><claim-text>(hkl) reflections used are: (012), (104), (110),
(113), (024), (116).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>Cutting tool according to any of the preceding claims
characterized in having at least one layer in contact
with the substrate, said layer comprising of a nitride, carbide,
carbonitride, oxycarbide and/or oxycarbonitride of a metal selected
from the Groups IVB, VB and VIB of the Periodic Table, B,
Al, and Si and/or mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>Method of coating a body with an α-alumina layer at which
the body is brought in contact with a hydrogen carrier gas containing
one or more halides of aluminium and a hydrolysing and/or
oxidising agent at 950-1000 °C wherein the oxidation potential of
the CVD-reactor atmosphere prior to the nucleation of Al2O3 is
kept at a low level using a total concentration of H2O or other
oxidising species preferably below 5 ppm, the Al2O3 growth being
started up by entering the following gases into the reaction chamber:
AlCl3, HCl and CO2 and after 20-60 min a sulphur dopant,
preferably H2S, is added characterized in that during
the growth, the CO2, AlCl3, HCl and the sulphur dopant are repeatedly
stopped with intervals of 10-50 min and TiCl4 is allowed to
enter the reactor for 1-10 min in a concentration of 1-10% then
replaced by AlCl3, HCl, CO2 and the sulphur dopant in the mentioned
order.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>