<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1582549-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1582549" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34890641" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20051005"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1582549-A1" status="new" fvid="24449281"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1582549</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20051005</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-05251952-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>05251952</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20050330</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-81588004-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>81588004</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040331</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-92504104-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>92504104</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040824</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 209/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 209/46        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  64/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  64/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  51/00        20060101C N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  51/06        20060101A N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  55/00        20060101C N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  55/02        20060101A N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  69/00        20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  69/00        20060101C I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101AFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101CFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07D 209/46</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  64/12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  69/00+B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07D209:46</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L51:06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L55:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L69:00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Flammhemmende Harzmischungen auf Basis von 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-Bis(4-Hydroxyaryl)Phthalimidin-Monomere enthaltende Polymeren</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Flame retardant resin blends based on polymers derived from 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-Bis(4-Hydroxyaryl)Phthalimidine monomers</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Mélanges ignifuges de résine à base de polymères dérivés des monoméres de la 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-Bis(4-Hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0025859-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0025859</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0129824-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0129824</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0617070-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0617070</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0633292-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0633292</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2002050185-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2002050185</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>LIN; PEARCE:  "Polymers with improved flammability characteristics. I. Phenolphthalein-related homopolymers" JOURNAL OF POLYMER SCHIENCE: POLYMER CHEMISTRY EDITION, vol. 19, 1981, pages 2659-2670, XP009050158</text><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>R. ALBERT:  "Phenolphtaleinanilid und Orcinphtaleinanilid" CHEM. BER., vol. 26, 1893, pages 3077-3079, XP009050294</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEN ELECTRIC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1 River Road</street><city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DHANABALAN ANANTHARAMAN</name><address><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LINGANNAIAH CHANDRASHEKHAR</name><address><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SRINIVASAN VEERARAGHAVAN</name><address><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DHANABALAN, ANANTHARAMAN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LINGANNAIAH, CHANDRASHEKHAR</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SRINIVASAN, VEERARAGHAVAN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DHANABALAN, ANANTHARAMAN</last-name><address><street>7 5th Cross, Vignana Nagar New Thippasandra</street><city>Bangalore, 560075</city><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>LINGANNAIAH, CHANDRASHEKHAR</last-name><address><street>No. 11, 10th Cross 1st Main, Prashanthnaar</street><city>Bangalore, 560079</city><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SRINIVASAN, VEERARAGHAVAN</last-name><address><street>1470 E Block AECS Layout, Kundalahalli</street><city>Bangalore, 560037</city><country>IN</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Szary, Anne C.</last-name><address><street>London Patent Operation General Electric International, Inc. 15 John Adam Street</street><city>London WC2N 6LU</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IS</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LT</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Methods for producing a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine, and
polymer blends consisting essentially of at least one thermoplastic polymer, and a
polymer comprise structural units derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.
An exemplary method comprises forming a reaction
mixture comprising at least one substituted or unsubstituted phenolphthalein, at least
one substituted or unsubstituted primary hydrocarbyl amine, and an acid catalyst; and
heating the reaction mixture to a temperature of less than 180 °C to remove a distillate
comprising water and form a crude 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
product; where the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
has a formula:
<img id="img-80000001" orientation="unknown" wi="48" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="80000001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/>
where R<sup>1</sup> is selected from the group consisting of a hydrogen and a hydrocarbyl group,
and R<sup>2</sup> is selected from the group consisting of a hydrogen, a hydrocarbyl group, and a
halogen.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present disclosure generally relates to resin blends and articles comprising
thermoplastic polymers derived from 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
monomers. More particularly, the present disclosure
relates to resin blends and articles comprising a polycarbonate comprising structural
units derived from phenolphthalein derivatives, such as 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
monomer and an ABS (acrylonitrile - butadiene - styrene)
resin. Still more particularly, the present disclosure relates to resin blends and articles
comprising a polycarbonate comprising structural units derived from relatively pure 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.</p><p num="0002">It is well known that plastic substrates are rendered fire-retardant by the use of fire-retardant
additives. Polymer blends comprising an ABS resin, such as for example, a
polycarbonate - ABS blend are particularly challenging substrates due to the
inherently high flammability of the ABS resin component. Blends of polycarbonates
with styrenic polymers, such as the ABS resins mentioned above are typically
rendered fire-retardant by the addition of organic phosphorus compounds, such as
resorcinol 1,3-diphenylphosphate (abbreviated as "RDP" throughout this disclosure)
and bisphenol A bis(diphenyl)phosphate (abbreviated as "BPADP"), which are
generally believed to act in a vapor phase by quenching free radicals that can be
responsible for the propagation of the fire. It is also known that an effective amount
of the organic phosphorus compound necessary for achieving a given degree of fire
retardance can be reduced by employing appropriate synergists, such as siloxanes,
inorganic fillers, etc.</p><p num="0003">Further, for resin blends comprising highly flammable polymers, such as the ABS
resins, it is necessary to add relatively large amounts, sometimes as high as the
amount of the ABS resin present in the resin blend to achieve robust flame
performance (such as for example, the Underwriter Laboratories' rating of "V0" as
defined in a UL94 standard) for molded parts having relatively thin walls (example, 
less than or equal to 2 millimeters wall thickness. However, the addition of relatively
high amounts of the fire-retardant additives based on organic phosphorus compounds
can lead to number of disadvantages in the final blend, such as for example, inferior
heat characteristics (heat distortion temperature) due to the plasticizing effect of the
organic phosphorus compounds; poor mechanical properties, such as room
temperature impact and tensile modulus, among others. Also, these additives are
known to bloom to the surface during aging, thereby resulting in poor aesthetics.
Further, there are environmental health and safety concerns during operations, such as
for example, during processing, incineration, or recycling of plastic materials
containing organic phosphorus-based compounds as fire-retardants. These concerns
have prompted the industry to seek alternative, "greener", or more environmentally
friendly fire-retardants. Due to the wide applications of fire-retardant plastics for
modem day living, a safer and more environmentally friendly non-phosphorus fire-retardant
additive would be greatly beneficial to the plastics manufacturing and
processing industries. In particular, such a fire-retardant additive will be able to
enhance the utility (for example, in the consumer products industry) of polymer blends
based on ABS resins, such as for example, the polycarbonate - ABS blend.</p><p num="0004">Therefore, there is a need for fire-retardant polymer blends containing effective fire-retardant
additives that not only are phosphorus-free, but also do not affect the desired
physical properties of the blends, such as for example, impact, tensile modulus, and
the like. Further, there is a need for polymeric fire-retardant additives that can help
retain the properties of the polymer blend, as compared to the low molecular weight
fire-retardant additives, such as RDP and BPADP, which act as plasticizers, as
described previously.</p><p num="0005">Phenolphthalein has been used as an aromatic dihydroxy compound monomer for
preparing polycarbonates, which are generally characterized with excellent ductility
and high glass transition temperatures. Certain derivatives of phenolphthalein have
also been used as aromatic dihydroxy compound monomers to prepare polycarbonate
resins as well as polyarylate resins. For example, polycarbonate homopolymers have
been prepared by an interfacial polycondensation method using phosgene and
monomers such as 3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine and 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine 
(hereinafter sometimes referred to as "para,para-PPPBP").</p><p num="0006">Lin and Pearce (Journal of Polymer Science: Polymer Chemistry Edition, (1981) Vol.
19, pp. 2659 - 2670) reported the synthesis of para, para-PPPBP for preparing
polycarbonates and other polymers by refluxing phenolphthalein and aniline
hydrochloride in aniline for 6 hours, followed by recrystallization from ethanol.
During this reaction, side products are created which, if not removed, can result in
para, para-PPPBP having an unacceptable purity for use as a monomer or as a
comonomer. The undesirable side products or impurities generally include both
inorganic and organic species. With regard to the manufacture of polycarbonate, the
impurities can hinder polymerization and result in low weight average molecular
weight polycarbonates, for example, less than about 22,000 Daltons for melt
polymerization and less than about 50,000 Daltons for an interfacial polymerization
that exhibit undesirable physical properties, such as increased brittleness, that is, poor
ductility properties. Furthermore, the impurities in the para, para-PPPBP monomer
include, for example, trace (parts per million) levels of phenolphthalein or
phenolphthalein residues that can undesirably produce discoloration in the
polycarbonates and other polymers derived therefrom, thereby affecting the
transparency of the polymer product. Coloration is not desirable for many commercial
applications. U.S. Patent No. 5,344,910 discloses that copolymers of para, para-PPPBP
were found to have poor melt stability resulting in foamy polymer melts and
moldings, and discoloration of the resin during melt processing.</p><p num="0007">It would therefore be desirable to develop a process for preparing relatively pure
phenolphthalein derivatives such as 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine,
which can then be used for producing polycarbonates and
other polymers having improved properties, such as lower color, e.g., a low
yellowness index (YI) of less than about 10, and higher weight average molecular
weight. Further still, there is a need for such resin blends and articles having excellent
fire retardance and improved physical properties. </p><heading>BRIEF SUMMARY</heading><p num="0008">In one embodiment the present invention provides a method for producing a 2-hydrocarbyl
-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine, comprising:
<sl><li>forming a reaction mixture comprising at least one substituted or unsubstituted
phenolphthalein, at least one substituted or unsubstituted primary hydrocarbyl amine,
and an acid catalyst; and</li><li>heating the reaction mixture to a temperature of less than 180 °C to remove a distillate
comprising water and form a crude 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
product;</li></sl>
wherein said 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine has a formula:
<img id="img-00040001" orientation="unknown" wi="55" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif" inline="no" he="40"/>
wherein R<sup>1</sup> is selected from the group consisting of a hydrogen and a hydrocarbyl
group, and R<sup>2</sup> is selected from the group consisting of a hydrogen, a hydrocarbyl
group, and a halogen.</p><p num="0009">One aspect of the disclosure is a polymer blend consisting essentially of at least one
thermoplastic polymer and a polymer comprising structural units derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.</p><p num="0010">A second aspect of the disclosure is a molded article comprising a polymer blend, the
polymer blend consisting essentially of at least one thermoplastic polymer in an
amount of 5 to 98 weight percent, a rubber-modified graft copolymer in an amount of
75 to 1 weight percent, and a polycarbonate comprising structural units derived from a
2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine in an amount of 20 to 1 weight
percent, wherein the weight percents are based on the overall weight of the polymer 
blend. The at least one thermoplastic polymer can be selected from the group
consisting of vinyl polymers, acrylic polymers, polyacrylonitrile, polystyrenes,
polyolefins, polyesters, polyurethanes, polyamides, polysulfones, polyimides,
polyetherimides, polyphenylene ethers, polyphenylene sulfides, polyether ketones,
polyether ether ketones, polyethersulfones, poly(alkenylaromatic) polymers,
polybutadiene, polyacetals, polycarbonates, polyphenylene ethers, ethylene-vinyl
acetate copolymers, polyvinyl acetate, liquid crystal polymers, aromatic polyesters,
polyestercarbonate, copolymers comprising aromatic ester, estercarbonate, and
carbonate repeat units, mixtures; and blends comprising at least one of the foregoing
polymers.</p><p num="0011">A third aspect of the disclosure is a molded article comprising a polymer blend, where
the polymer blend consists essentially of: of a bisphenol A polycarbonate in an
amount of 5 to 98 weight percent of an acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene resin in an
amount of 75 to 1 weight percent, and a polycarbonate comprising structural units
derived from a 2-phenyl-3-{(4-hydroxyphenyl)(2-hydroxyphenyl)}phthalimidine in an
amount of 20 to 1 weight percent, wherein the weight percents are based on an overall
weight of the polymer blend.</p><p num="0012">A fourth aspect of the disclosure is a polymer blend comprising at least one
thermoplastic polymer, and a 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine/BPA
polycarbonate copolymer in an amount greater than 7 weight percent of the total
weight of the blend, wherein the polymer blend is free of a fire retardant phosphorous
containing compound, and has at least a V-1 fire rating as measured in accordance
with Underwriter Laboratories UL-94 Vertical Burn Test procedure dated, July 29,
1997.</p><p num="0013">A fifth aspect of the disclosure is a polycarbonate-acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene
polymer blend comprising a bisphenol A polycarbonate; an acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene
resin; and a 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine/bisphenol A
polycarbonate copolymer in an amount greater than 7 weight percent of the total
weight of the polymer blend, wherein the polymer blend is free of a fire retardant
phosphorous containing compound and has a V-O fire rating as measured in 
accordance with Underwriter Laboratories UL-94 Vertical Burn Test procedure dated
July 29, 1997.</p><p num="0014">A sixth aspect of the disclosure is a polymer blend comprising at least one
thermoplastic polymer and a polymer comprising structural units derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine,
where the blend does not comprise
a flame retardant.</p><p num="0015">The above described and other features are exemplified by the following detailed
description.</p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading><p num="0016">For the purposes of this disclosure, the term "hydrocarbyl" is defined herein as a
monovalent moiety formed by removing a hydrogen atom from a hydrocarbon.
Representative hydrocarbyls are alkyl groups having 1 to 25 carbon atoms, such as
methyl, ethyl, propyl, butyl, pentyl, hexyl, heptyl, octyl, nonyl, undecyl, decyl,
dodecyl, octadecyl, nonadecyl, eicosyl, heneicosyl, docosyl, tricosyl, and the isomeric
forms thereof; aryl groups having 6 to 25 carbon atoms, such as ring-substituted and
ring-unsubstituted forms of phenyl, tolyl, xylyl, naphthyl, biphenyl, tetraphenyl, and
the like; aralkyl groups having 7 to 25 carbon atoms, such as ring-substituted and ring-unsubtituted
forms of benzyl, phenethyl, phenpropyl, phenbutyl, naphthoctyl, and the
like; and cycloalkyl groups, such as cyclopropyl, cyclobutyl, cyclopentyl, cyclohexyl,
cycloheptyl, cyclooctyl, and the like. The term "aryl' as used herein refers to various
forms of aryl groups that have been described hereinabove for the "hydrocarbyl"
group.</p><p num="0017">The present disclosure is generally directed to producing and purifying
phenophthalein derivatives, which are suitable for use as monomers for preparing
polymers. Further, the prepared polymers are used in blends with other thermoplastic
polymers, such as an ABS resin, to form molding compositions, which are in turn
valuable for producing articles having excellent fire retardance and physical
properties. </p><p num="0018">Exemplary phenophthalein derivatives are 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidines
of formula (I):
<img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="93" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="40"/>
wherein R<sup>1</sup> is selected from a group consisting of a hydrogen and a hydrocarbyl group,
and R<sup>2</sup> is selected from the group consisting of a hydrogen, a hydrocarbyl group, and a
halogen. By way of example, 2-aryl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidines can
generally be prepared by reaction of an aromatic amine (also referred to herein as "aryl
amine"), e.g., an aniline, of formula (II):
<img id="img-00070002" orientation="unknown" wi="97" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070002.tif" inline="no" he="30"/>
wherein R<sup>1</sup> is as defined above; with a phenolphthalein of formula (III):
<img id="img-00070003" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070003.tif" inline="no" he="48"/>
wherein R<sup>2</sup> is as previously defined. An acid catalyst is generally used to facilitate
formation of the phthalimidine product. Suitable acid catalysts that can be used
include amine salts of mineral acids. Examples of suitable mineral acids include
hydrochloric acid, sulfuric acid, and nitric acid. Examples of suitable amines include
primary, secondary, and tertiary amines having any combination of aliphatic and
aromatic groups bonded to the amine nitrogen. Suitable examples of amine salt 
catalysts include primary, secondary, and tertiary amine hydrochlorides.
Hydrochloride salts of the primary aromatic amines of formula (II) are preferred since
the amines of formula (II) also serve as the starting material for preparing the
phthalimidines of formula (I). In one embodiment, the catalyst is introduced as a preformed
salt into the reactor. In another embodiment, the catalyst is generated in the
reactor by first charging the amine of formula (II) into the reactor, and then adding
about 1/3 to about 1 part by weight of an appropriate mineral acid to phenolphthalein.
In still another embodiment, about 0.1 parts to about 0.3 parts by weight of hydrogen
chloride gas is introduced into a reactor charged with the aryl amine to form an
appropriate amount of the aryl amine hydrochloride catalyst. More hydrochloric acid
or more hydrogen chloride gas can also used, but is generally not required. A solvent
can optionally be employed to form the aryl amine hydrochloride. The solvent can
then be removed (if necessary), and the aryl amine of formula (II) can be added,
followed by addition of phenolphthalein (III). The reaction of phenolphthalein (III)
with the aryl amine (II) proceeds by a condensation reaction to form the desired
phthalimidine product (I). An excess of the aryl amine over the phenolphthalein may
be used to keep the reaction proceeding in the forward direction. Likewise, a higher
reaction temperature with or without removal of water by-product also facilitates
product formation. However, in order to enhance the selectivity of 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)
phthalimidine (I), and suppress the formation of undesired (2-hydroxyaryl)(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
by-products, for example, it is preferred to
control the temperature of the reaction mixture, and the rate of removal of water as
well. The temperature of the reaction mixture and rate of water removal is controlled
such that the crude 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl) phthalimidine product is at
least 97.5 area percent pure 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine in one
embodiment, and at least 98 area percent pure in another embodiment. The chemical
structure of (2-hydroxyaryl)(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine by-product is shown in
formula (IV) below. <img id="img-00090001" orientation="unknown" wi="108" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00090001.tif" inline="no" he="41"/>
wherein R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup> are as previously described.</p><p num="0019">In one embodiment, the reaction temperature is controlled such that the water by-product
(calculated based on the moles of the phenolphthalein (III) which is preferably
the limiting reagent) distills over a period of about 12 hours to about 20 hours. If the
reaction mixture is heated such that the amount of water by-product distills within
about 6 hours, the phthalimidine product of formula (I) has a relatively greater amount
of the (2-hydroxyaryl)(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine impurity shown in formula (IV).
Therefore, although a higher reaction temperature ensures a quicker consumption of
the phenolphthalein (III), it also leads to formation of a higher amount of the impurity
of formula (IV). If the reaction temperature is not sufficiently high, and water by-product
is not removed, a relatively large amount of the phenolphthalein remains
unreacted, thereby leading to an inferior product, e.g., forms colored byproducts
during melt mixing, forms low molecular weight polymers, and the like. Thus, in one
embodiment, the reaction mixture is heated to a temperature of about 150°C to about
175°C to remove water by-product and form the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
product. In another embodiment, the reaction mixture is
heated to a temperature of about 150°C to about 170°C.</p><p num="0020">By way of example, phenolphthalein (R<sup>2</sup> is H, R<sup>3</sup> is phenyl in formula (III)) was
reacted with aniline (R<sup>3</sup> is H in formula (II)) in the presence of aniline hydrochloride
as the catalyst to form 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine (i.e.,
para,para-PPPBP), as shown in formula (V). <img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="97" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="44"/></p><p num="0021">As will be discussed in the Example Section, the so-formed para, para-PPPBP was
produced at high yields and was used to produce polycarbonates with a YI of less than
about 10 and high weight average molecular weights. Moreover, the reaction did not
produce any detectable (and undesirable) isomers of para, para-PPPBP such as the
ortho, para-PPPBP isomer shown in Formula (VI) below.
<img id="img-00100002" orientation="unknown" wi="94"  img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00100002.tif" inline="no" he="43"/></p><p num="0022">Isolation of the desired phenolphthalein derivative from the reaction mixture includes
quenching the mixture with an aqueous mineral acid, such as aqueous hydrochloric
acid, and precipitating the crude 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.
The crude product is then dissolved in an aqueous inorganic base comprising an alkali
metal or alkaline earth metal hydroxide, carbonate, or bicarbonate to provide a first
solution. Aqueous sodium hydroxide can be used. Next, the first solution of the
crude product is treated with a suitable solid adsorbent that can remove color-forming
species present in the solution. In one embodiment, commercially available activated
carbon can be used. Treatment with the activated carbon removes color-forming
species present in the solution. Suitable activated carbon include, but are not intended
to be limited to, the NORIT series of activated carbon available from Norit
Corporation, and those activated carbons commercially available from E. Merck
Company. The decolorizing efficiency of the activated carbon is indicated by its
methylene blue number. Generally, an activated carbon with a relatively higher
methylene blue number is less expensive than an activated carbon having a relatively 
lower methylene blue number. Applicants find that even activated carbons having
relatively higher methylene blue numbers are effective decolorizing agents. After
treatment with the activated carbon, the resulting mixture is filtered to provide a
second solution.</p><p num="0023">In addition to functioning as a decolorizing agent, the activated carbon treatment also
aids in selectively adsorbing the 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine
isomeric impurity. Thus, one method for purifying a
crude 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine product comprises
contacting an aqueous base solution of the crude product with the activated carbon
and filtering off the carbon to provide a second solution. The second solution may
again be treated in the same manner, if desired, to provide further reductions in the
levels of the 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine
impurity. In an embodiment, the step of treating and filtering the first solution is done
such that it is effective to reduce an amount of 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine
to less than or equal to 1,000 parts per million relative to
an overall weight of the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.</p><p num="0024">The decolorized and purified solution is next treated with an aqueous mineral acid,
such as aqueous hydrochloric acid to precipitate 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.
The precipitate is then finally stirred with an aliphatic
alcohol to remove any trace of the phenolphthalein that may still be present and
subsequently filtered to furnish purified 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.
Suitable aliphatic alcohols include any aliphatic
monohydric or dihydric alcohol. Non-limiting examples of suitable aliphatic alcohols
include methanol, ethanol, iso-propanol, iso-butanol, n-butanol, tertiary butanol, n-pentanol,
iso-pentanol, cyclohexanol, ethylene glycol, propylene glycol, neopentyl
glycol and the like. In a particular embodiment, aliphatic monohydric alcohols that
are miscible with water, such as methanol, ethanol, and isopropanol are used.
Methanol is the preferred aliphatic alcohol for removing phenolphthalein. The so-produced
and purified 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine preferably
comprises less than or equal to 1,000 parts per million of the 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine
isomeric impurity. Further, the purified 
2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine preferably comprises less than or
equal to 1,000 parts per million of the phenolphthalein starting material.</p><p num="0025">In another embodiment, a method for purifying crude 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
product comprises dissolving the crude product in an
aqueous base solution, treating the aqueous base solution of the crude product with the
activated carbon, filtering off the carbon to provide a second solution, and acidifying
the second solution with an aqueous acid to precipitate the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine,
which has a relatively low level of the 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine
impurity, e.g., less than 1,000 parts
per million. The resulting product can then be contacted with an aliphatic alcohol in
the manner previously described.</p><p num="0026">The general methods described hereinabove can advantageously be applied for
preparing para, para-PPPBP having an undetectable level of ortho, para-PPPBP (as
measured by HPLC technique). In one embodiment, the purified para,para-PPPBP
may also comprise up to 1,000 parts per million of phenolphthalein.</p><p num="0027">The 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl) phthalimidines, including the exemplary 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine,
are commercially valuable monomers
or comonomers for producing a variety of polymers and polymer compositions formed
by reactions of the phenolic OH groups of the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidines.
Suitable polymers that can be produced are polymers
selected from the group consisting of homopolymers and copolymers of a
polycarbonate, a polyestercarbonate, a polyester, a polyesteramide, a polyimide, a
polyetherimide, a polyamideimide, a polyether, a polyethersulfone, a polycarbonate-polyorganosiloxane
block copolymer, a copolymer comprising aromatic ester,
estercarbonate, and carbonate repeat units; and a polyetherketone. A suitable example
of a copolymer comprising aromatic ester, estercarbonate, and carbonate repeat units
is the copolymer produced by the reaction of a hydroxy-terminated polyester, such as
the product of reaction of isophthaloyl chloride, and terephthaloyl chloride with
resorcinol, with phosgene and an aromatic dihydroxy compound, such as bisphenol A. </p><p num="0028">In one embodiment, polycarbonates having desirable properties are synthesized,
wherein the polycarbonates include structural units of formula (VII):
<img id="img-00130001"  orientation="unknown"  wi="107"  img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="45"/>
which are derived from 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine; wherein
R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup> are as described previously; and the C=O structural units are derived from a
C=O donor such as phosgene or a carbonic acid diester; where the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
comprises less than or equal to 1,000 parts per
million of a 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine relative
to an overall weight of said 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.</p><p num="0029">The polycarbonate composition may further comprise structural units derived from at
least one other aromatic dihydroxy compound such as is represented by the general
formula (VIII):
<img id="img-00130002" orientation="unknown" wi="110" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130002.tif" inline="no" he="22"/>
wherein each G<sup>1</sup> is an independently aromatic group; E is selected from the group
consisting of an alkylene group, an alkylidene group, a cycloaliphatic group, a sulfur-containing
linkage group, a phosphorus-containing linkage group, an ether linkage
group, a carbonyl group, a tertiary nitrogen group, and a silicon-containing linkage
group; R<sup>3</sup> is a hydrogen or a monovalent hydrocarbon group each; Y<sup>1</sup> is independently
selected from the groups consisting of a monovalent hydrocarbyl group, an alkenyl
group, an allyl group, a halogen, an oxy group and a nitro group; each m is
independently a whole number from zero through the number of positions on each
respective G<sup>1</sup> available for substitution; p is a whole number from zero through the 
number of positions on E available for substitution; t is a natural number greater than
or equal to one; s is either zero or one; and u is a whole number.</p><p num="0030">Suitable examples of E include cyclopentylidene, cyclohexylidene, 3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexylidene,
methylcyclohexylidene, 2-[2.2.1]-bicycloheptylidene,
neopentylidene, cyclopentadecylidene, cyclododecylidene, and adamantylidene; a
sulfur-containing linkage such as sulfide, sulfoxide or sulfone, a phosphorus-containing
linkage such as phosphinyl, phosphonyl, an ether linkage, a carbonyl
group, a tertiary nitrogen group, and a silicon-containing linkage such as a silane or
siloxy linkage.</p><p num="0031">In the aromatic dihydroxy comonomer compound shown in Formula (VIII), when
more than one Y<sup>1</sup> substituent is present, they may be the same or different. The same
holds true for the R<sup>3</sup> substituent. Where "s" is zero in formula (VIII) and "u" is not
zero, the aromatic rings are directly joined with no intervening alkylidene or other
bridge. The positions of the hydroxyl groups and Y<sup>1</sup> on the aromatic nuclear residues
G<sup>1</sup> can be varied in the ortho, meta, or para positions and the groupings can be in
vicinal, asymmetrical or symmetrical relationship, where two or more ring carbon
atoms of the hydrocarbon residue are substituted with Y<sup>1</sup> and hydroxyl groups. In
some embodiments, the parameters "t", "s", and "u" are each one; both G<sup>1</sup> radicals are
unsubstituted phenylene radicals; and E is an alkylidene group such as isopropylidene.
In particular embodiments, both G<sup>1</sup> radicals are p-phenylene, although both may be
ortho- or meta-phenylene or one ortho- or meta-phenylene and the other para-phenylene.</p><p num="0032">Some illustrative, non-limiting examples of aromatic dihydroxy compounds of
formula (VIII) include the dihydroxy-substituted aromatic hydrocarbons disclosed by
name or formula (generic or specific) in U.S. Patent 4,217,438. Some particular
examples of aromatic dihydroxy compound comonomers include, but are not intended
to be limited to, 2,4'-dihydroxydiphenylmethane, bis(2-hydroxyphenyl)methane,
bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)methane, bis(4-hydroxy-5-nitrophenyl)methane, bis(4-hydroxy-2,6-dimethyl-3-methoxyphenyl)methane,
1,1-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)ethane, 1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-2-chlorophenyl)ethane,
2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)propane (bisphenol A); 2,2-bis(3-chloro-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane; 
2,2-bis(3-bromo-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3-methylphenyl)propane; 2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3-isopropylphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(3-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane; 2,2-bis(3-phenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(3,5-dichloro-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(3,5-dibromo-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane; 2,2-bis(3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-methylphenyl)propane; 2,2-bis(3-bromo-4-hydroxy-5-methylphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-isopropylphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(3-bromo-4-hydroxy-5-isopropylphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(3-t-butyl-5-chloro-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane; 2,2-bis(3-bromo-5-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(3-chloro-5-phenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane; 2,2-bis(3-bromo-5-phenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(3,5-disopropyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(3,5-di-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane; 2,2-bis(3,5-diphenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-2,3,5,6-tetrachlorophenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-2,3,5,6-tetrabromophenyl)propane; 2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-2,3,5,6-tetramethylphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(2,6-dichloro-3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(2,6-dibromo-3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3-ethylphenyl)propane, 2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3,5-dimethylphenyl)propane,
2,2-bis(3,5,3',5'-tetrachloro-4,4'-dihydroxyphenyl)propane,
bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexylmethane, 2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1-phenylpropane,
1,1-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane; 1,1-bis(3-chloro-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-bromo-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-3-methylphenyl)cyclohexane; 1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-3-isopropylphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-phenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane; 1,1-bis(3,5-dichloro-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3,5-dibromo-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(4'-hydroxy-3'methylphenyl) cyclohexane
(DMBPC), 1,1-bis(3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane; 4,4'-[1-methyl-4-(1-methyl-ethyl)-1,3-cyclohexandiyl]bisphenol
(1,3 BHPM), 4-[1-[3-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-4-methylcyclohexyl]-1-methyl-ethyl]-phenol
(2,8 BHPM), 3,8-dihydroxy-5a,10b-diphenylcoumarano-2',3',2,3-coumarane
(DCBP), 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine,
1,1-bis(3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-methylphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-bromo-4-hydroxy-5-methylphenyl)cyclohexane; 
1,1-bis(3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-isopropylphenyl)cyclohexane; 1,1-bis(3-bromo-4-hydroxy-5-isopropylphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-t-butyl-5-chloro-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1 -bis(3-bromo-5-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1 -bis(3-chloro-5-phenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1 -bis(3-bromo-5-phenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3,5-disopropyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3,5-di-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane; 1,1-bis(3,5-diphenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-2,3,5,6-tetrachlorophenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-2,3,5,6-tetrabromophenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1 -bis(4-hydroxy-2,3,5,6-tetramethylphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1 -bis(2,6-dichloro-3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(2,6-dibromo-3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexane;
1,1-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-chloro-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane; 1,1-bis(3-bromo-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-3-methylphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-3-isopropylphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-phenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1 -bis(3,5-dichloro-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1 -bis(3,5-dibromo-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-methylphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-bromo-4-hydroxy-5-methylphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-isopropylphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-bromo-4-hydroxy-5-isopropylphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3-t-butyl-5-chloro-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1 -bis(3-bromo-5-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
bis(3-chloro-5-phenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1 -bis(3-bromo-5-phenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3,5-disopropyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3,5-di-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(3,5-diphenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane; 
1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-2,3,5,6-tetrachlorophenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-2,3,5,6-tetrabromophenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-2,3,5,6-tetramethylphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1, 1-bis(2,6-dichloro-3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
1, 1-bis(2,6-dibromo-3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)-3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexane;
4,4-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)heptane, 4,4'dihydroxy-1,1-biphenyl;
4,4'-dihydroxy-3, 3'-dimethyl-1,1-biphenyl; 4,4'-dihydroxy-3,3'-dioctyl-1,1 -biphenyl;
4,4'-(3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexylidene)diphenol, 4,4'-bis(3,5-dimethyl)diphenol, 4,4'-dihydroxydiphenylether;
4,4'-dihydroxydiphenylthioether; 1,3-bis(2-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-2-propyl)benzene;
1,3-bis(2-(4-hydroxy-3-methylphenyl)-2-propyl)benzene;
1,4-bis(2-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-2-propyl)benzene, 1,4-bis(2-(4-hydroxy-3-methylphenyl)-2-propyl)benzene
2,4'-dihydroxyphenyl sulfone, 4,4'-dihydroxydiphenylsulfone
(BPS), bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)methane, 2,6-dihydroxy
naphthalene; hydroquinone; resorcinol, C1-3 alkyl-substituted resorcinols, 3-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1,1,3-trimethylindan-5-ol,
1-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1,3,3-trimethylindan-5-ol,
and 2,2,2',2'-tetrahydro-3,3,3',3'-tetramethyl-1,1'-spirobi[1H-indene]-6,6'-diol.
The most typical aromatic dihydroxy compound is Bisphenol A (BPA).</p><p num="0033">In some embodiments, an isosorbide comonomer can be used with the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
monomer to produce polycarbonate copolymers.
Isosorbide, sometimes also called 1,4:3,6-dianhydo-D-glucitol, is a rigid, chemically,
and thermally stable aliphatic diol that tends to produce copolymers having higher
glass transition temperatures, as compared to comonomer compositions which do not
include isosorbide.</p><p num="0034">The carbonic acid diester described above has the general formula (IX):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">(ZO)<sub>2</sub>C=O</st32:che>
wherein each Z is independently an unsubstituted or substituted alkyl radical, or an
unsubstituted or substituted aryl radical. Suitable examples of carbonic acid diesters
include, but are not intended to be limited to, ditolyl carbonate, m-cresyl carbonate,
dinaphthyl carbonate, diphenyl carbonate, diethyl carbonate, dimethyl carbonate,
dibutyl carbonate, dicyclohexyl carbonate, and combinations of two or more carbonic 
acid diesters thereof. Diphenyl carbonate is widely used as a carbonic acid diester due
to its low cost and ready availability on a commercial scale. If two or more of the
carbonic acid diesters listed above are utilized, preferably one of the carbonic acid
diesters is diphenyl carbonate.</p><p num="0035">Suitable carbonic acid diesters include the group of "activated aromatic carbonates".
As used herein, the term "activated aromatic carbonate" is defined as a diaryl
carbonate that is more reactive than diphenyl carbonate in a transesterification
reaction. Such activated aromatic carbonates can also be represented by formula (IX),
wherein each Z is an aryl radical having 6 to 30 carbon atoms. More specifically, the
activated carbonates have the general formula (X):
<img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="26"/>
wherein Q and Q' are each independently an ortho-positioned activating group; A and
A' are each independently aromatic rings which can be the same or different
depending on the number and location of their substituent groups, and a and a' is zero
to a whole number up to a maximum equivalent to the number of replaceable
hydrogen groups substituted on the aromatic rings A and A' respectively, provided a +
a' is greater than or equal to 1. R and R' are each independently substituent groups
such as alkyl, substituted alkyl, cycloalkyl, alkoxy, aryl, alkylaryl, cyano, nitro, or
halogen. The term b is zero to a whole number up to a maximum equivalent to the
number of replaceable hydrogen atoms on the aromatic ring A minus the number a,
and the number b' is zero to a whole number up to a maximum equivalent to the
number of replaceable hydrogen atoms on the aromatic ring A' minus the number a'.
The number, type and location of R or R' on the aromatic ring is not intended to be
limited unless they deactivate the carbonate and lead to a carbonate that is less
reactive than diphenyl carbonate.</p><p num="0036">Non-limiting examples of suitable ortho-positioned activating groups Q and Q'
include (alkoxycarbonyl)aryl groups, (arylketone)aryl groups, halogens, nitro groups, 
amide groups, sulfone groups, sulfoxide groups, or imine groups with structures
indicated below:
<img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="109" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/>
wherein X is halogen or NO<sub>2</sub>; M and M' independently comprises N-dialkyl, N-alkyl
aryl, alkyl, or aryl; and R<sup>4</sup> is alkyl or aryl.</p><p num="0037">Specific non-limiting examples of activated aromatic carbonates include bis(o-methoxycarbonylphenyl)carbonate,
bis(o-chlorophenyl)carbonate, bis(o-nitrophenyl)carbonate,
bis(o-acetylphenyl)carbonate, bis(o-phenylketonephenyl)carbonate,
bis(o-formylphenyl)carbonate. Unsymmetrical
combinations of these structures, wherein the substitution number and type on A and
A' are different, are also contemplated. A preferred structure for the activated
aromatic carbonate is an ester-substituted diaryl carbonate having the formula (XI):
<img id="img-00190002" orientation="unknown" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00190002.tif" inline="no" he="37"/>
wherein R<sup>5</sup> is independently at each occurrence a C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub>
cycloalkyl radical, or C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> aromatic radical; R<sup>6</sup> is independently at each occurrence
a halogen atom, cyano group, nitro group, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> cycloalkyl
radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> aromatic radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkoxy radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> cycloalkoxy radical,
C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> aryloxy radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkylthio radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> cycloalkylthio radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub>
arylthio radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkylsulfinyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> cycloalkylsulfinyl radical,
C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> arylsulfinyl radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkylsulfonyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> cycloalkylsulfonyl
radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> arylsulfonyl radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkoxycarbonyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> 
cycloalkoxycarbonyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> aryloxycarbonyl radical, C<sub>2</sub> - C<sub>60</sub> alkylamino
radical, C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>60</sub> cycloalkylamino radical, C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>60</sub> arylamino radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>40</sub>
alkylaminocarbonyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>40</sub> cycloalkylaminocarbonyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>40</sub>
arylaminocarbonyl radical, or C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> acylamino radical; and c is independently at
each occurrence an integer 0-4. At least one of the substituents CO<sub>2</sub>R<sup>5</sup> is preferably
attached in the ortho position of formula (XI).</p><p num="0038">Examples of preferred ester-substituted diaryl carbonates include, but are not limited
to, bis(methylsalicyl)carbonate (CAS Registry No. 82091-12-1) (also known as
BMSC or bis(o-methoxycarbonylphenyl)carbonate), bis(ethyl salicyl)carbonate,
bis(propyl salicyl) carbonate, bis(butylsalicyl) carbonate, bis(benzyl salicyl)carbonate,
bis(methyl 4-chlorosalicyl)carbonate and the like. Preferably, BSMC is used in melt
polycarbonate synthesis due to its lower molecular weight and higher vapor pressure.</p><p num="0039">Some non-limiting examples of non-activating groups which, when present in an
ortho position, would not be expected to result in activated carbonates are alkyl,
cycloalkyl or cyano groups. Some specific and non-limiting examples of non-activated
carbonates include bis(o-methylphenyl)carbonate, bis(p-cumylphenyl)carbonate,
bis(p-(1,1,3,3-tetramethyl)butylphenyl)carbonate and bis(o-cyanophenyl)carbonate.
Unsymmetrical combinations of these structures are also
expected to result in non-activated carbonates.</p><p num="0040">Unsymmetrical diaryl carbonates, wherein one aryl group is activated and one aryl is
inactivated, are useful if the activating group renders the diaryl carbonate more
reactive than diphenyl carbonate.</p><p num="0041">One method for determining whether a certain diaryl carbonate is activated or is not
activated is to carry out a model melt transesterification reaction between the
particular diaryl carbonate and a phenol such as para - (1,1,3,3-tetramethyl)butyl
phenol (and comparing the relative reactivity against diphenyl carbonate). This
phenol is preferred because it possesses only one reactive site, possesses a low
volatility, and possesses a similar reactivity to bisphenol-A. The model melt
transesterification reaction is carried out at temperatures above the melting points of
the particular diaryl carbonate and phenol in the presence of a transesterification 
catalyst, which is usually an aqueous solution of sodium hydroxide or sodium
phenoxide. Preferred concentrations of the transesterification catalyst are at about
0.001 mole percent based on the number of moles of the phenol or diaryl carbonate.
Although a preferred reaction temperature is 200 °C, the choice of reaction conditions
as well as catalyst concentration can be adjusted depending on the reactivity and
melting points of the reactants to provide a convenient reaction rate. The reaction
temperature is preferably maintained below the degradation temperature of the
reactants. Sealed tubes can be used if the reaction temperatures cause the reactants to
volatilize and affect the reactant molar balance. A determination of an equilibrium
concentration of the reactants is accomplished through reaction sampling during the
course of the reaction with subsequent analysis of the reaction mixture using well-known
detection methods such as HPLC (high pressure liquid chromatography).
Particular care needs to be taken so that the reaction does not continue after the
sample has been removed from the reaction vessel. This is accomplished by cooling
down the sample in an ice bath and by employing a reaction quenching acid, such as
acetic acid in the water phase of the HPLC solvent system. It may also be desirable to
introduce the reaction quenching acid directly into the reaction sample in addition to
cooling the reaction mixture. A preferred concentration for the reaction quenching
acid, e.g., acetic acid in the water phase of the HPLC solvent system, is about 0.05
mole percent. The equilibrium constant is then determined from the concentration of
the reactants and product after equilibrium is reached. Equilibrium is assumed to have
been reached when the concentration of components in the reaction mixture reach a
point of little or no change on sampling of the reaction mixture. The equilibrium
constant can be determined from the concentration of the reactants and products by
methods well known to those skilled in the art. A diaryl carbonate which possesses a
relative equilibrium constant (K<sub>diarylcarbonate</sub> / K<sub>diphenylcarbonate</sub>) of greater than 1 is
considered to possess a greater reactivity than diphenyl carbonate and is a suitable
activated aromatic carbonate for use in the present disclosure, whereas a diaryl
carbonate which possesses an equilibrium constant of 1 or less is considered to
possess the same or have less reactivity than diphenyl carbonate and is considered not
to be activated. It is generally preferred to employ an activated aromatic carbonate
with very high reactivity compared to diphenyl carbonate when conducting 
transesterification reactions. Preferred are activated aromatic carbonates with an
equilibrium constant greater than at least 1,000 times that of diphenyl carbonate.</p><p num="0042">Polycarbonate compositions comprising the structural unit of formula (VII) and
carbonate units derived from the activated carbonate preferably comprise at least one
end group derived from the activated carbonate. In one embodiment, the end groups
which are indicative of the activated aromatic carbonate has a structure of formula
(XII):
<img id="img-00220001" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00220001.tif" inline="no" he="19"/>
wherein Q is an ortho-positioned activating group; A is an aromatic ring, n is a whole
number of 1 to the number of replaceable hydrogen groups substituted on the aromatic
ring A; R is a substituent group selected from the group consisting of alkyl,
cycloalkyl, alkoxy, aryl, cyano, nitro, and halogen; and b is zero to a whole number to
the number of replaceable hydrogen groups on the aromatic ring minus n. Q is
preferably a radical independently selected from the group consisting of
(alkoxycarbonyl)aryl groups, halogens, nitro groups, amide groups, sulfone groups,
sulfoxide groups, or imine groups with structures
<img id="img-00220002" orientation="unknown" wi="116" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00220002.tif" inline="no" he="37"/>
wherein X comprises halogen or NO<sub>2</sub>, M and M' independently comprises N-alkyl, N-aryl,
or N-alkyl aryl; R<sup>4</sup> comprises alkyl or aryl when n is 1; and n has a value of 0 or
1.</p><p num="0043">Polycarbonates prepared using ester-substituted diaryl carbonates, such
as for example BMSC, may further comprise very low levels of structural features,
which arise from side reactions taking place during the melt polymerization reaction
between an ester-substituted diaryl carbonate of structure (XI) and dihydroxy aromatic 
compounds of structure (VIII). One such structural feature has a structure of formula
(XIII):
<img id="img-00230001" orientation="unknown" wi="101" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00230001.tif" inline="no" he="32"/>
wherein R<sup>7</sup> is a halogen atom, cyano group, nitro group, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub>
cycloalkyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> aromatic radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkoxy radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub>
cycloalkoxy radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> aryloxy radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkylthio radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub>
cycloalkylthio radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> arylthio radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkylsulfinyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub>
cycloalkylsulfinyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> arylsulfinyl radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub> alkylsulfonyl radical,
C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> cycloalkylsulfonyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> arylsulfonyl radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub>
alkoxycarbonyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> cycloalkoxycarbonyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> aryloxycarbonyl
radical, C<sub>2</sub> - C<sub>60</sub> alkylamino radical, C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>60</sub> cycloalkylamino radical, C<sub>5</sub>-C<sub>60</sub>
arylamino radical, C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>40</sub> alkylaminocarbonyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>40</sub>
cycloalkylaminocarbonyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>40</sub> arylaminocarbonyl radical, or C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>20</sub>
acylamino radical; and c is a whole number of 1-4. Typically such kinks are present
only to a minor extent (e.g., 0.2 to 1 mole percent).</p><p num="0044">Structure (XIII) is termed an internal ester-carbonate linkage or kink. Without wishing
to be bound by any theory, it is thought that structure (XIII) may arise by reaction of
an ester-substituted phenol by-product, for example methyl salicylate, at its ester
carbonyl group with a dihydroxy aromatic compound or a hydroxyl group of a
growing polymer chain. Further reaction of the ester-substituted phenolic hydroxy
group leads to formation of a carbonate linkage. Thus, the ester-substituted phenol by-product
of reaction of an ester-substituted diaryl carbonate with a dihydroxy aromatic
compound may be incorporated into the main chain of a linear polycarbonate, for
example.</p><p num="0045">Another structural feature present in melt transesterification polymerization reactions
between ester-substituted diaryl carbonates and dihydroxy aromatic compounds is the 
ester-linked terminal end group having a free hydroxyl group and have the structure
(XIV):
<img id="img-00240001" orientation="unknown" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240001.tif" inline="no" he="19"/>
wherein R<sup>7</sup> and c are as defined above. Without wishing to be bound by any theory, it
is believed that structure (XIV) may arise in the same manner as structure (XIII), but
without further reaction of the ester-substituted phenolic hydroxy group. In the
structures provided herein, the wavy line represents the polycarbonate polymer chain
structure. End capping of the polymer chains made by this method may be only
partial. In typical embodiments of polycarbonates prepared by the methods described
herein, the free hydroxyl group content is from 7 percent to 50 percent. This number
may be varied by changing reaction conditions or by adding additional end-capping
agents. In one embodiment, wherein the activated carbonate used is BMSC, there will
be an ester linked end group of structure (XV):
<img id="img-00240002" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00240002.tif" inline="no" he="26"/>
which possesses a free hydroxyl group. Thus, for example, if the terminal group of
structure (XV) is attached to a para, para-PPPBP unit in the polycarbonate chain then
it is designated hereinafter as "p,p-PPPBP-salicyl-OH end", and if the terminal group
of structure (XV) is attached to a BPA unit in the polycarbonate chain, it is hereinafter
designated as "BPA-salicyl-OH end".</p><p num="0046">The polycarbonates comprise structural units indicative of the activated carbonate.
These structural units may be end groups produced when activated carbonate
fragments act as end capping agents or may be kinks introduced into the copolymer by
incorporation of activated carbonate fragments.</p><p num="0047">The polycarbonate made, using the activated aromatic carbonate as described above,
may also have end-groups having structure (XVI): <img id="img-00250001" orientation="unknown" wi="90" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250001.tif" inline="no" he="23"/>
where R, b, A, Q, and n are defined in the preceding sections.</p><p num="0048">In one embodiment the terminal end group having structure (XVI) is a methyl salicyl
group of structure (XVII):
<img id="img-00250002" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00250002.tif" inline="no" he="28"/></p><p num="0049">It could also include other salicyl groups such as the ethylsalicyl, isopropylsalicyl, and
butylsalicyl groups.</p><p num="0050">A number of polymerization methods can be used for producing a polymer, such as a
homopolycarbonate or a copolycarbonate, comprising structural units derived from a
2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine, wherein the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
comprises less than or equal to about 1,000 parts per
million of a 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine relative
to an overall weight of the purified 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.
Suitable methods for fabricating polycarbonates, for
example, include a melt transesterification polymerization method, an interfacial
polymerization method, and a bischloroformate polymerization method.</p><p num="0051">As used herein, the term "structural units derived from" when used in the context of
describing the portions of the copolycarbonates derived from the aliphatic diol and the
aromatic dihydroxy compounds refers to the fact that both such monomers lose their
respective hydrogen atoms upon incorporation in the polymer.</p><p num="0052">As used herein the term "activated carbonate" refers to a diaryl carbonate which is
typically more reactive (either kinetically or thermodynamically) toward aromatic
dihydroxy compounds than diphenyl carbonate under identical conditions. Activated
carbonates are typically (but not necessarily) substituted diaryl carbonates. </p><p num="0053">As used herein the term "structural units indicative of the activated carbonate" means
either internal "kinks" in the copolycarbonate or end groups caused by incorporation
of a fragment of an activated carbonate such as bismethylsalicyl carbonate (sometimes
hereinafter referred to as "BMSC").</p><p num="0054">The melt transesterification polymerization method is generally carried out by
combining a catalyst and a reactant composition to form a reaction mixture; and
mixing the reaction mixture under reactive conditions for a time period effective to
produce a polycarbonate product, wherein the reactant composition generally
comprises a carbonic acid diester of the formula (ZO)<sub>2</sub>C=O, wherein each Z is
independently an unsubstituted or a substituted alkyl radical, or an unsubstituted or a
substituted aryl radical and the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine,
wherein the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine comprises less than or
equal to about 1,000 parts per million of a 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine
relative to an overall weight of said 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.</p><p num="0055">During the manufacture of the polycarbonates by the melt transesterification method
using the activated or unactivated carbonic acid diester, the amount of the carbonic
acid diester comprises about 0.8 moles to about 1.30 moles, and more specifically
about 0.9 moles to about 1.2 moles, based on one mole of the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
or any combination of the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
and at least one aromatic dihydroxy comonomer.</p><p num="0056">Suitable melt transesterification catalysts include alkali metal compounds, alkaline
earth metal compounds, tetraorganoammonium compounds, and
tetraorganophosphonium compounds, combinations comprising at least one of the
foregoing catalysts.</p><p num="0057">Specific examples of alkali metal compounds or alkaline earth metal compounds
include organic acid salts, inorganic acid salts, oxides, hydroxides, hydrides, and
alcoholates of alkali metals and alkaline earth metals. Preferably, the catalyst is an
alkali metal compound of the formula M<sub>1</sub>X<sub>1</sub>, wherein M<sub>1</sub> is selected from the group 
consisting of lithium, sodium, and potassium; and X<sub>1</sub> is selected from the group
consisting of hydroxide and OAr, wherein Ar is a monovalent aromatic radical.</p><p num="0058">More specifically, examples of suitable alkali metal compounds include, but are not
limited to, sodium hydroxide, potassium hydroxide, lithium hydroxide, calcium
hydroxide, magnesium hydroxide, sodium bicarbonate, potassium bicarbonate, lithium
bicarbonate, sodium carbonate, potassium carbonate, lithium carbonate, sodium
acetate, potassium acetate, lithium acetate, lithium stearate, sodium stearate,
potassium stearate, lithium hydroxyborate, sodium hydroxyborate, sodium
phenoxyborate, sodium benzoate, potassium benzoate, lithium benzoate, disodium
hydrogen phosphate, dipotassium hydrogen phosphate, dilithium hydrogen phosphate,
disodium salts, dipotassium salts, and dilithium salts of bisphenol A, and sodium
salts, potassium salts, lithium salts of phenol, and the like.</p><p num="0059">Specific examples of alkaline earth metal compounds include, but are not limited to,
calcium hydroxide, barium hydroxide, magnesium hydroxide, strontium hydroxide,
calcium bicarbonate, barium bicarbonate, magnesium bicarbonate, strontium
bicarbonate, calcium carbonate, barium carbonate, magnesium carbonate, strontium
carbonate, calcium acetate, barium acetate, magnesium acetate, strontium acetate,
strontium stearate, and the like.</p><p num="0060">Exemplary tetraorganoammonium compounds include compounds comprising
structure (XVIII):
<img id="img-00270001" orientation="unknown" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00270001.tif" inline="no" he="25"/>
wherein R<sup>8</sup> -R<sup>11</sup> are independently a C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> alkyl radical, C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> cycloalkyl radical or
a C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>20</sub> aryl radical and X<sup>-</sup> is an organic or inorganic anion. Suitable anions (X<sup>-</sup>)
include hydroxide, halide, carboxylate, sulfonate, sulfate, carbonate and bicarbonate.
In one embodiment, the transesterification catalyst comprises tetramethyl ammonium
hydroxide. </p><p num="0061">In still other embodiments, the catalyst is a tetraorganophosphonium compound.
Exemplary quaternary phosphonium compounds include compounds comprising
structure (XIX):
<img id="img-00280001" orientation="unknown" wi="85" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00280001.tif" inline="no" he="29"/>
wherein R<sup>8</sup> -R<sup>11</sup> and X<sup>-</sup> are as previously described. Illustrative anions include
hydroxide, halide, carboxylate, sulfonate, sulfate, carbonate, and bicarbonate.</p><p num="0062">Where X<sup>-</sup> is a polyvalent anion such as carbonate or sulfate it is understood that the
positive and negative charges in structures (XVIII) and (XIX) are properly balanced.
For example, when R<sup>9</sup> -R<sup>12</sup> in structure (XVIII) are each methyl groups and X- is
carbonate, it is understood that X<sup>-</sup> represents ½ (CO<sub>3</sub><sup>-2</sup>) as will be appreciated by
those skilled in the art.</p><p num="0063">Specific examples of tetraorganoammonium compounds and tetraorganophosphonium
compounds include, but are not limited to tetramethylammonium hydroxide,
tetrabutylammonium hydroxide, tetraethylphosphonium hydroxide,
tetrabutylphosphonium acetate, tetrabutylphosphonium hydroxide, and the like.</p><p num="0064">In one embodiment, the catalyst comprises tetrabutylphosphonium acetate. In an
alternate embodiment, the catalyst comprises a mixture of an alkali metal salt or
alkaline earth metal salt with at least one quaternary ammonium compound, at least
one quaternary phosphonium compound, or a mixture thereof. For example, the
catalyst may be a mixture of sodium hydroxide and tetrabutylphosphonium acetate. In
another embodiment, the catalyst is a mixture of sodium hydroxide and tetramethyl
ammonium hydroxide.</p><p num="0065">In another embodiment, the catalyst comprises an alkaline earth metal salt of an
organic acid, an alkali metal salt of an organic acid, or a salt of an organic acid
comprising both alkaline earth metal ions and alkali metal ions. Alkali metal and
alkaline earth metal salts of organic acids, such as for example, formic acid, acetic 
acid, stearic acid and ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid can also be used. In one
embodiment, the catalyst comprises magnesium disodium ethylenediamine
tetraacetate (EDTA magnesium disodium salt).</p><p num="0066">In yet another embodiment, the catalyst comprises the salt of a non-volatile inorganic
acid. By "non-volatile" it is meant that the referenced compounds have no
appreciable vapor pressure at ambient temperature and pressure. In particular, these
compounds are not volatile at temperatures at which melt polymerizations of
polycarbonate are typically conducted. The salts of non-volatile acids are alkali metal
salts of phosphites; alkaline earth metal salts of phosphites; alkali metal salts of
phosphates; and alkaline earth metal salts of phosphates. Suitable salts of non-volatile
acids include NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>3</sub>, NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, Na<sub>2</sub>H<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>3</sub>, KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, CsH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, Cs<sub>2</sub>H<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, or a
mixture thereof In one embodiment, the transesterification catalyst comprises both
the salt of a non-volatile acid and a basic co-catalyst such as an alkali metal
hydroxide. This concept is exemplified by the use of a combination of NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> and
sodium hydroxide as the transesterification catalyst.</p><p num="0067">Any of the catalysts disclosed above may be used as combinations of two or more
substances. The catalyst may be added in a variety of forms. The catalyst may be
added as a solid, for example as a powder, or it may be dissolved in a solvent, for
example, in water or alcohol. The total catalyst composition is preferably about 1 X
10<sup>-7</sup> to about 2 X 10<sup>-3</sup> moles, and with about 1 X 10<sup>-6</sup> to about 4 X 10<sup>-4</sup> moles more
preferred for each mole of the combination of the purified para, para-PPPBP and the
aromatic dihydroxy compound comonomer.</p><p num="0068">Any of the catalysts described above for use in polycarbonate melt transesterification
reactions may be used in reactions involving activated carbonates. It is often
advantageous to use a combination of some amount of a salt of an alkaline earth metal
and/or an alkali metal (i.e., an "alpha" catalyst) that does not degrade at temperatures
used throughout the reaction together with a quaternary ammonium and/or a
quaternary phosphonium compound that does degrade at a temperature used in the
reaction (i.e., a "beta" catalyst). The total amount of catalyst employed is about 1 x
10<sup>-7</sup> to about 1 x 10<sup>-2</sup>, and preferably about 1 x 10<sup>-7</sup> to about 2 x 10<sup>-3</sup> moles catalyst per 
total moles of the mixture of para, para-PPPBP and aromatic dihydroxy compound
employed.</p><p num="0069">The reactants for the polymerization reaction using an activated aromatic carbonate
can be charged into a reactor either in the solid form or in the molten form. Initial
charging of reactants into a reactor and subsequent mixing of these materials under
reactive conditions for polymerization may be conducted in an inert gas atmosphere
such as a nitrogen atmosphere. The charging of one or more reactant may also be done
at a later stage of the polymerization reaction. Mixing of the reaction mixture is
accomplished by any methods known in the art, such as by stirring. Reactive
conditions include time, temperature, pressure and other factors that affect
polymerization of the reactants. Typically, the activated aromatic carbonate is added at
a mole ratio of about 0.8 to about 1.3, and more specifically, 0.9 to about 1.2 and all
sub-ranges there between, relative to the total moles of aromatic dihydroxy compound
and aliphatic diol.</p><p num="0070">The melt polymerization reaction using the activated aromatic carbonate is conducted
by subjecting the above reaction mixture to a series of temperature-pressure-time
protocols. In some embodiments, this involves gradually raising the reaction
temperature in stages while gradually lowering the pressure in stages. In one
embodiment, the pressure is reduced from about atmospheric pressure at the start of
the reaction to about 0.01 millibar (1 Pascal) or in another embodiment to 0.05
millibar (5 Pascals) in several steps as the reaction approaches completion. The
temperature may be varied in a stepwise fashion beginning at a temperature of about
the melting temperature of the reaction mixture and subsequently increased to about
320 °C. In one embodiment, the reaction mixture is heated from about ambient (about
21 - 23 °C) temperature to about 150 °C. The polymerization reaction starts at a
temperature of about 150 °C to about 220 °C, then is increased to about 220 °C to
about 250 °C and is then further increased to a temperature of about 250 °C to about
320 °C and all sub-ranges there-between. The total reaction time is about 30 minutes
to about 200 minutes and all sub-ranges there between. This procedure will generally
ensure that the reactants react to give polycarbonates with the desired molecular
weight, glass transition temperature and physical properties. The reaction proceeds to 
build the polycarbonate chain with production of a by-product such as, for example an
ester-substituted alcohol e.g., methyl salicylate. Efficient removal of the by-product
may be achieved by different techniques such as reducing the pressure. Generally the
pressure starts relatively high in the beginning of the reaction, such as atmospheric
pressure in one embodiment, and is lowered progressively throughout the reaction and
temperature is raised throughout the reaction. Experimentation is needed to find the
most efficient conditions for particular production equipment.</p><p num="0071">The progress of the reaction may be monitored by measuring the melt viscosity or the
weight average molecular weight of the reaction mixture using techniques known in
the art such as gel permeation chromatography. These properties may be measured by
taking discreet samples or may be measured on-line. After the desired melt viscosity
and/or molecular weight is reached, the final polycarbonate product may be isolated
from the reactor in a solid or molten form. It will be appreciated by a person skilled in
the art, that the method of making polycarbonates as described in the preceding
sections may be made in a batch or a continuous process and the process disclosed
herein is essentially preferably carried out in a solvent free mode. Reactors chosen
should ideally be self-cleaning and should minimize any "hot spots."</p><p num="0072">In one embodiment, the aliphatic homopolycarbonate and aliphatic-aromatic
copolycarbonate may be prepared in an extruder in presence of one or more catalysts,
wherein the carbonating agent is an activated aromatic carbonate. The reactants for the
polymerization reaction can be fed to the extruder in powder or molten form. In one
embodiment, the reactants are dry blended prior to addition to the extruder. The
extruder may be equipped with pressure reducing devices (e.g., vents), which serve to
remove the activated phenol by-product and thus drive the polymerization reaction
toward completion. The molecular weight of the polycarbonate product may be
manipulated by controlling, among other factors, the feed rate of the reactants, the
type of extruder, the extruder screw design and configuration, the residence time in
the extruder, the reaction temperature and the pressure reducing techniques present on
the extruder. The molecular weight of the polycarbonate product may also depend
upon the structures of the reactants, such as, activated aromatic carbonate, aliphatic
diol, dihydroxy aromatic compound, and the catalyst employed. Many different screw 
designs and extruder configurations are commercially available that use single screws,
double screws, vents, back flight and forward flight zones, seals, side-streams and
sizes. One skilled in the art may have to experiment to find the best designs using
generally known principals of commercial extruder design. Vented extruders similar
to those that are commercially available may also be used.</p><p num="0073">The process disclosed herein can be used to prepare PPPBP homopolycarbonate and
copolycarbonates having a weight average molecular weight (Mw) of about 3,000 to
about 150,000 and a glass transition temperature (Tg) of about 80 °C to about 300 °C.
The number average molecular weights (Mn) of the homopolycarbonate and
copolycarbonates is from about 1,500 to about 75,000. The transparency of cast films
made from the polycarbonate or copolycarbonates prepared in accordance with the
present disclosure is greater than about 85 percent, as determined by a Haze Guard
Instrument.</p><p num="0074">In monitoring and evaluating polycarbonate synthesis, it is of particular interest to
determine the concentration of Fries product present in the polycarbonate. The
generation of significant Fries product can lead to polymer branching, resulting in
uncontrollable melt behavior. In the process of preparing polycarbonates described
herein, some branching reaction (Fries reaction) takes place (especially at higher
temperatures and exacerbated by alpha catalysts) resulting in a Fries product. Fries
products are defined as structural units of the product polycarbonate which upon
hydrolysis of the product polycarbonate affords a carboxy-substituted dihydroxy
aromatic compound bearing a carboxy group adjacent to one or both of the hydroxy
groups of the carboxy-substituted dihydroxy aromatic compound. For example, in
bisphenol A polycarbonate prepared by a melt polymerization method in which Fries
reaction occurs, the Fries product comprises structure (XX) below, which affords 2-carboxy
bisphenol A upon complete hydrolysis of the product polycarbonate. As
indicated, the Fries product may serve as a site for polymer branching, the wavy lines
of structure (XX) indicating a polymer chain structure. <img id="img-00330001" orientation="unknown" wi="107" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00330001.tif" inline="no" he="31"/></p><p num="0075">The polycarbonates prepared using the activated carbonate by the disclosed method
have a concentration of Fries product of less than about 500 parts per million (ppm) as
measured by high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC). The Fries
concentration is much less than what is obtained in a conventional melt
polymerization process that uses diphenyl carbonate as the carbonic acid diester. Fries
products are generally undesirable for certain polycarbonates because excessive levels
can adversely affect certain physical properties.</p><p num="0076">In the interfacial polymerization method, 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine,
with or without one or more comonomers, and phosgene
are reacted in the presence of an acid acceptor and an aqueous base to produce said
polycarbonate. Tertiary amines, such as for example, trialkylamines are preferably
used as acid acceptors. An exemplary trialkylamine is triethylamine. Suitable
aqueous bases include, for example, the alkali metal hydroxides, such as sodium
hydroxide. The interfacial method can be used for producing polycarbonates
comprising structural units derived from 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine,
and preferably having molecular weights greater than
about 50,000, relative to polystyrene standard.</p><p num="0077">The interfacial method described above can be suitably adapted to produce
polycarbonates through the intermediate formation of 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
bischloroformate. This method is sometimes called the
bischloroformate polymerization method. In one embodiment, the method comprises
reacting a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine with phosgene in an
organic solvent, and then reacting the bischloroformate either with a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine,
or an aromatic dihydroxy compound in the
presence of an acid acceptor and an aqueous base to form the polycarbonate. </p><p num="0078">The interfacial polymerization method and the bischloroformate polymerization
method can be carried in a batch or a continuous mode using one or more reactor
systems. To carry out the process in a continuous mode, one or more continuous
reactors, such as for example, a tubular reactor can be used. In one embodiment, the
continuous method comprises introducing into a tubular reactor system phosgene, at
least one solvent (example, methylene chloride), at least one bisphenol, aqueous base,
and optionally one or more catalysts (example, a trialkylamine) to form a flowing
reaction mixture. The flowing mixture is then passed through the tubular reactor
system until substantially all of the phosgene has been consumed. The resulting
mixture is next treated with a mixture comprising an aqueous base, at least one end-capping
agent, optionally one or more solvents, and at least one catalyst. The end-capped
polycarbonate thus formed is continuously removed from the tubular reactor
system. The process can be used for preparing end-capped polycarbonate oligomers
(generally polycarbonates having a weight average molecular weight of less than or
equal to 10,000 daltons) or polymers having a weight average molecular weight of
greater than 10,000 daltons. The processes outlined hereinabove can also be suitably
adapted, for example, to produce end-capped polycarbonates via the intermediate
formation of a mixture comprising a bisphenol monochloroformate or a bisphenol
bischloroformate.</p><p num="0079">In another embodiment, polymer blends comprise the polymers described previously
and at least one thermoplastic polymer. The at least one thermoplastic polymer is
selected from the group consisting of vinyl polymers, acrylic polymers,
polyacrylonitrile, polystyrenes, polyolefins, polyesters, polyurethanes, polyamides,
polysulfones, polyimides, polyetherimides, polyphenylene ethers, polyphenylene
sulfides, polyether ketones, polyether ether ketones, ABS resins, ASA resins,
polyethersulfones, poly(alkenylaromatic) polymers, polybutadiene, polyacetals,
polycarbonates, polyphenylene ethers, ethylene-vinyl acetate copolymers, polyvinyl
acetate, liquid crystal polymers, ethylene-tetrafluoroethylene copolymer, aromatic
polyesters, polyvinyl fluoride, polyvinylidene fluoride, polyvinylidene chloride,
tetrafluoroethylene, polycarbonate - polyorganosiloxane block copolymers, 
copolymers comprising aromatic ester, estercarbonate, and carbonate repeat units;
mixtures, and blends comprising at least one of the foregoing polymers.</p><p num="0080">The polymers and polymer blends described hereinabove are valuable for producing
articles. In one embodiment, an article comprises a polymer comprising structural
units derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine, which
comprises less than or equal to about 1,000 parts per million of a 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine,
relative to an overall weight of the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.
In another embodiment, an article
comprises a polymer comprising structural units derived from a 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine,
which comprises less than or equal to about 1,000 parts
per million of 2-phenyl-3-{(4-hydroxyphenyl)(2-hydroxyphenyl)}phthalimidine,
relative to an overall weight of said 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine.</p><p num="0081">Polymers, particularly polycarbonate homopolymers and copolymers comprising
structural units derived from the high purity 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
in general, and para,para-PPPBP in particular have a
yellowness index (YI) of less than 10 as measured on a 3 millimeter thick plaque in
accordance with ASTM D1925 in one embodiment, a YI of less than 5 in another
embodiment, and a YI of less than 2 in still another embodiment. Hence, these
polycarbonate polymers are useful for producing articles having a number of useful
properties, such as a low residual color. The articles also exhibit excellent heat aging.
Thus, extruded articles have low color values (as measured by yellowness index, YI)
even after heat aging, such as, for example, a YI of less than about 2 after heat aging
in air at 155 °C - 160 °C for about 500 hours in one embodiment, and a YI of less than
about 0.5 after heat aging in air at 120 °C for about 500 hours in another embodiment.
The polycarbonate homopolymers and copolymers have high glass transition
temperatures of higher than or equal to about 180 °C. One of the unique properties of
these polycarbonates, especially those that have glass transition temperatures of
greater than or equal to about 180 °C is that during melt processing they exhibit a
shear-thinning behavior. That is, the polymers have the ability to flow under an
applied shear. Therefore, standard melt processing equipment used for BPA
polycarbonates can advantageously be used for producing articles. The 
polycarbonates also have high transparency, as measured by percent light
transmission, of greater than or equal to about 85 percent. Moreover, the
copolycarbonate is especially useful for articles that are preferably made form a
polymer having transparency and the other advantageous properties of a BPA
homopolycarbonate, but with a significantly higher Tg. Lenses in applications where
they are exposed to heat are a good example of such an application.</p><p num="0082">The polycarbonate compositions disclosed herein are particularly valuable for
producing a variety of lenses suitable for diverse applications. In an embodiment, the
lens comprises a polycarbonate, which comprises structural units of formula (VII)
derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine comprising less
than or equal to about 1,000 parts per million of a 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine
relative to an overall weight of said 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine;
and a yellowness index of less than
10 as measured on a 3 millimeter thick plaque in accordance with ASTM D1925 in
one embodiment, and less than 2 in another embodiment. Non-limiting examples of
suitable articles include an automotive headlamp inner lens, an automotive headlamp
outer lens, an automotive fog lamp lens, an automotive bezel, a medical device, a
display device, electrical connectors, under the hood automotive parts, and projector
lens. Examples of suitable display devices include a laptop computer screen, a liquid
crystal display screen, and an organic light-emitting diode display screen.</p><p num="0083">The polycarbonates disclosed herein may also be combined with effective amounts of
one or more of various types of additives used selected from the group consisting of
fillers, fire retardants, drip retardants, antistatic agents, UV stabilizers, heat stabilizers,
antioxidants, plasticizers, dyes, pigments, colorants, processing aids, and mixtures
thereof. These additives are known in the art, as are their effective levels and methods
of incorporation. Effective amounts of the additives vary widely, but they are usually
present in an amount up to about 50% or more by weight, based on the weight of the
entire composition. Especially preferred additives include hindered phenols, thio
compounds and amides derived from various fatty acids. The preferred amounts of
these additives generally ranges up to about 2% total combined weight based on the
total weight of the composition. </p><p num="0084">In another embodiment, polymer blends consisting essentially of at least one
thermoplastic polymer and a polymer comprising structural units derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine,
such as 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine,
but which do not contain a fire retardant additive, such
as a phosphorus-containing compound (which is traditionally for preparing fire-retardant
polymer compositions), surprisingly exhibit excellent fire retardance (a V-0
or V-1 rating in accordance with the standards set forth by Underwriter Laboratories)
without compromising on the other desirable physical properties, such as room
temperature impact, tensile modulus, heat distortion temperature or glass transition
temperature. Accordingly, one can prepare fire-retardant compositions, molding
compositions, and molded articles comprising any polymer that has structural units
derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine. Further, without
wishing to be bound by any theory, it is believed that the presence of the impurities in
the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine monomer, such as the 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine,
or the substituted or
the unsubstituted phenolphthalein , will not affect the fire-retardance of compositions
consisting essentially of flammable thermoplastic polymers and the polymer
comprising structural units derived from the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.
However, depending upon the end-use applications
and/or the relative amounts of such a polymer in a final resin blend, the presence of
impurities such as the ones described above in the starting monomer may or may not
be critical. For other applications, such as for example, molding compositions having
a low color, a yellowness index of less than or equal to about 10 (as measured on a 3
millimeter thick plaque in accordance with ASTM D1925) can be obtained without
any significant loss in other physical properties by employing a polymer prepared
from 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine monomer having less than
about 1,000 parts per million of the 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine,
and/or less than or equal to about 1,000 parts per million
of the phenolphthalein compound.</p><p num="0085">Suitable thermoplastic polymers for producing flame retardant compositions include
one or more polymers each having structural units derived from one or more 
monomers selected from the group consisting of vinyl aromatic monomers,
monoethylenically unsaturated nitrile monomers, and C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>12</sub> alkyl (meth)acrylate
monomers. In an embodiment, rubber-modified graft copolymers and polymers
comprising such copolymers are suitable for producing the flame retardant
compositions.</p><p num="0086">Suitable vinyl aromatic monomers include, but are not intended to be limited to,
styrene and substituted styrenes having one or more alkyl, alkoxyl, hydroxyl or halo
substituent group attached to the aromatic ring, Exemplary vinyl aromatic monomers
include, for example, alpha- methyl styrene, p-methyl styrene, vinyl toluene, vinyl
xylene, trimethyl styrene, butyl styrene, chlorostyrene, dichlorostyrene, bromostyrene,
p- hydroxystyrene, methoxystyrene and vinyl-substituted condensed aromatic ring
structures, such as, e.g., vinyl naphthalene, vinyl anthracene, as well as mixtures of
vinyl aromatic monomers, among others.</p><p num="0087">As used in the present context the term "monoethylenically unsaturated nitrile
monomer" means an acyclic compound that comprises a single nitrile group and a
single site of ethylenic unsaturation per molecule. Suitable monoethylenically
unsaturated nitrile monomers include, but are not intended to be limited to,
acrylonitrile, methacrylonitrile, and alpha- chloro acrylonitrile.</p><p num="0088">The terminology "(meth)acrylate monomers" refers collectively to acrylate monomers
and methacrylate monomers. Suitable C<sub>1</sub>- C<sub>12</sub> alkyl (meth)acrylate monomers include,
but are not intended to be limited to, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub> alkyl acrylate monomers, e.g., ethyl
acrylate, butyl acrylate, iso-pentyl acrylate, n-hexyl acrylate, 2-ethyl hexyl acrylate,
and their C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub> alkyl methacrylate analogs, e.g., methyl methacrylate, ethyl
methacrylate, propyl methacrylate, isopropyl methacrylate, butyl methacrylate, hexyl
methacrylate, and decyl methacrylate.</p><p num="0089">In one embodiment, the thermoplastic polymer comprises a vinyl aromatic polymer
having structural units derived from one or more vinyl aromatic monomers, for
example styrene, and having structural units derived from one or more
monoethylenically unsaturated nitrile monomers, for example acrylonitrile. In another
embodiment, the thermoplastic polymer comprises from about 55 to about 99 weight 
percent, and in other embodiments, from about 60 to about 90 weight percent of
structural units derived from styrene; and in other embodiments, from about 1 to about
45 weight percent, and in still other embodiments from about 10 to about 40 weight
percent of structural units derived from acrylonitrile. In one embodiment, the weight
average molecular weight of such types of thermoplastic polymer is from about
50,000 to about 100,000 daltons, relative to polystyrene standards.</p><p num="0090">The thermoplastic polymer can also comprise at least one rubber modified graft
copolymer comprising a discontinuous rubber phase dispersed in a continuous rigid
thermoplastic phase, wherein at least a portion of the rigid thermoplastic phase is
chemically grafted to the rubber phase. Hereinafter the term "rubber modified graft
copolymer" is sometimes referred to as a rubber modified thermoplastic resin. In one
embodiment, rubber modified graft copolymers comprise those made by a bulk or,
synonymously, a mass polymerization process. In another embodiment, rubber
modified graft copolymers comprise those made by emulsion polymerization.
Suitable rubbers for use in making the rubber phase comprise those having a glass
transition temperature (T<sub>g</sub>) of less than or equal to 25 °C in one embodiment, less than
or equal to 0 °C in another embodiment., and less than or equal to minus 30 °C in yet
another embodiment. The rubber comprises a polymer, often a linear polymer, having
structural units derived from one or more conjugated diene monomers. Suitable
conjugated diene monomers include, but are not intended to be limited to, 1,3-butadiene,
isoprene, 1,3-heptadiene, methyl-1,3-pentadiene, 2,3-dimethylbutadiene, 2-ethyl-1,3-pentadiene,
1,3-hexadiene, 2,4-hexadiene, dichlorobutadiene,
bromobutadiene, and dibromobutadiene; as well as mixtures of conjugated diene
monomers. In other embodiments, the conjugated diene monomer comprises at least
one of 1,3-butadiene or isoprene.</p><p num="0091">In other embodiments, the rubber may optionally include structural units derived from
one or more copolymerizable monoethylenically unsaturated monomers selected from
C<sub>2</sub> - C<sub>8</sub> olefin monomers, vinyl aromatic monomers, monoethylenically unsaturated
nitrile monomers, and C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>12</sub> alkyl (meth)acrylate monomers. As used herein, the
term "C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>8</sub> olefin monomers" means a compound having from 2 to 8 carbon atoms
per molecule and having a single site of ethylenic unsaturation per molecule. Suitable 
C<sub>2</sub> - C<sub>8</sub> olefin monomers comprise, example, ethylene, propene, 1-butene, 1-pentene,
and heptene. Suitable vinyl aromatic monomers, monoethylenically unsaturated
nitrile monomers, and C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub> alkyl (meth)acrylate monomers comprise those
previously described.</p><p num="0092">In one embodiment, the rubber is a polybutadiene homopolymer. In another
embodiment, the rubber is a copolymer, for example, a block copolymer comprising
structural units derived from one or more conjugated diene monomers and up to 50
percent by weight of structural units derived from one or more monomers selected
from vinyl aromatic monomers and monoethylenically unsaturated nitrile monomers,
such as, for example, a styrene-butadiene copolymer, an acrylonitrile- butadiene
copolymer or a styrene-butadiene-acrylonitrile copolymer. More specifically, the
rubber can be a styrene-butadiene block copolymer that contains from about 50 to
about 95 weight percent of structural units derived from butadiene, and from about 5
to about 50 weight percent of structural units derived from styrene. Suitable rubber
polymers may also comprise structural units derived from butyl acrylate. In another
embodiment, the rubber is an ethylene-propylene-diene modified rubber.</p><p num="0093">The elastomeric rubber phase may be made by aqueous emulsion polymerization in
the presence of a free radical initiator, a polyacid surfactant, and optionally, a chain
transfer agent. The resulting polymer emulsion can be coagulated to form particles of
the elastomeric phase material. Suitable free radical include, but are not intended to
be limited to, an organic peroxide compound, such as benzoyl peroxide; a persulfate
compound, such as potassium persulfate; an azonitrile compound, such as, 2,2' -
azobis-2,3,3-trimethylbutyronitrile (sometimes abbreviated in common parlance as
"AIBN"); or a redox initiator system, such as a combination of cumene
hydroperoxide, ferrous sulfate, tetrasodium pyrophosphate, and a reducing sugar or
sodium formaldehyde sulfoxylate. Suitable chain transfer agents include, but are not
intended to be limited to, a C<sub>9</sub> - C<sub>13</sub> alkyl mercaptan compound, such as nonyl
mercaptan, tertiary dodecyl mercaptan, or the like.</p><p num="0094">The emulsion polymerized particles of the elastomeric rubber phase material can have
a weight average particle size in one embodiment of about 50 to about 1,000 
nanometers ("nm"), in another embodiment of about 50 to about 800 nm, and in yet
another embodiment of from 100 to 500 nm, as measured by light transmission. The
size of emulsion polymerized elastomeric particles may optionally be increased by
mechanical, colloidal or chemical agglomeration of the emulsion-polymerized
particles according to known techniques.</p><p num="0095">Specific thermoplastic polymers that can be used in a polymer blend with a polymer
comprising structural units derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
can be selected from the group consisting of ABS resins,
ASA (acrylate - styrene - acrylonitrile) resins, acrylonitrile - butadiene copolymer,
styrene-butadiene copolymers, ethylene - propylene - diene copolymers, and
polyacrylates, such as those comprising poly(butyl acrylate) and poly(2-ethylhexyl
acrylate).</p><p num="0096">Examples of suitable bisphenol compounds used for producing the polycarbonate
block of formula (XXII) include, but are not intended to be limited to, 4,4'-(3,3,5-trimethylcyclohexylidene)diphenol,
4,4'-bis(3,5-dimethyl)diphenol, 1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-3-methylphenyl)cyclohexane,
4,4-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)heptane, 2,4'-dihydroxydiphenylmethane,
bis(2-hydroxyphenyl)methane, bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)methane,
bis(4-hydroxy-5-nitrophenyl)methane, bis(4-hydroxy-2,6-dimethyl-3-methoxyphenyl)methane,
1,1 -bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)ethane, 1,1-bis(4-hydroxy-2-chlorophenyl)ethane,
2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)propane, 2,2-bis(3-phenyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane,
2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3-methylphenyl)propane, 2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3-ethylphenyl)propane,
2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3-isopropylphenyl)propane, 2,2-bis(4-hydroxy-3,5-dimethylphenyl)propane,
2,2-bis(3,5,3',5'-tetrachloro-4,4'-dihydroxyphenyl)propane,
bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)cyclohexylmethane, 2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1-phenylpropane,
2,4'-dihydroxyphenyl sulfone, 2,6-dihydroxy
naphthalene; hydroquinone; resorcinol, C<sub>1-3</sub> alkyl-substituted resorcinols, 3-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1,1,3-trimethylindan-5-ol,
1-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1,3,3-trimethylindan-5-ol,
2,2,2',2'-tetrahydro-3,3,3',3'-tetramethyl-1,1'-spirobi[1H-indene]-6,6'-diol, 1-methyl-1,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)-3-isopropylcyclohexane,
1-methyl-2-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-3-[1-(4-hydroxyphenyl)isopropyl]cyclohexane,
and combinations
thereof; and combinations comprising at least one of the foregoing bisphenols. </p><p num="0097">Non-limiting examples of antioxidants that can be used in molding compositions, for
example, include tris(24-di-tert-butylphenyl) phosphite, 3,9-di(2,4-di-tert-butylphenoxy)-2,4,8,10-tetraoxa-3,9-
diphosphaspiro[5.5]undecane, 3,9-di(2,4-dicumylphenoxy)-2,4,8,10-tetraoxa-3,9-diphosphaspiro[5.5]undecane,
tris(p-nonylphenyl)
phosphite, 2,2',2"-nitrilo[triethyl-tris[3,3',5,5'-tetra-tertbutyl-1,1'-biphenyl-2'-diyl]phosphite],
3,9-distearyloxy-2,4,8,10-tetraoxa-3,9-diphosphaspiro[5.
5]undecane, dilauryl phosphite, 3,9-di[2,6-di-tert-butyl-4-methyl- phenoxy]-2,4,8,10-tetraoxa-3,9-diphosphaspiro[5.5]undecane
and tetrakis(2,4-di-tert-butylphenyl) 4,4'-bis(diphenylene)phosphonite,
distearyl pentaerythritol diphosphite, diisodecyl
pentaerythritol diphosphite, 2,4,6-tri-tert-butylphenyl-2-butyl-2-ethyl-1,3-propanediol
phosphite, tristearyl sorbitol triphosphite, tetrakis(2,4-di-tert-butylphenyl)4,4'-biphenylene
diphosphonite, (2,4,6-tri-tert-butylphenyl)-2-butyl-2-ethyl-1, 3-propanediolphosphite,
tri-isodecylphosphite, and mixtures of phosphites containing at
least one of the foregoing. Of these, tris(2,4-di-tert-butylphenyl) phosphite, 2,4,6-tri-tert-butylphenyl-2-butyl-2-ethyl-1,3-propanediol
phosphite, bis(2,4-di-tert-butylphenyl)pentaerythritol
diphosphite are preferred for some applications, as well as
mixtures of phosphites containing at least one of the foregoing phosphites, and the
like.</p><p num="0098">Non-limiting examples of processing aids include Doverlube® FL-599 (available
from Dover Chemical Corporation), Polyoxyter® (available from Polychem Alloy
Inc.), Glycolube P (available from Lonza Chemical Company), pentaerythritol
tetrastearate, Metablen A-3000 (available from Mitsubishi Rayon), neopentyl glycol
dibenzoate, and the like.</p><p num="0099">Non-limiting examples of UV stabilizers include 2-(2'-Hydroxyphenyl)-benzotriazoles,
e.g., the 5'-methyl-, 3',5'-di- tert.-butyl-, 5'-tert.-butyl-, 5'-(1,1,3,3-tetramethylbutyl)-,
5-chloro- 3',5'-di-tert.-butyl-, 5-chloro-3'-tert.-butyl-5'-methyl-, 3'-sec.-butyl-
5'-tert.-butyl-, 3'-alpha -methylbenzyl -5'-methyl, 3'- alpha- methylbenzyl-5'-methyl-5-chloro-,
4'-hydroxy-, 4'-methoxy-, 4'-octoxy-, 3',5'-di-tert.-amyl-, 3'-methyl-5'-carbomethoxyethyl-,
5-chloro-3',5'- di-tert.-amyl-derivative, and Tinuvin®
234 (available from Ciba Specialty Chemicals); 2,4-bis-(2'-hydroxyphenyl)-6-alkyl-s-triazines,
e.g., the 6-ethyl-, 6- heptadecyl- or 6-undecyl-derivative; 2-hydroxybenzophenones 
e.g., the 4-hydroxy-, 4-methoxy-, 4-octoxy-, 4- decyloxy-, 4-dodecyloxy-,
4-benzyloxy-, 4,2',4'-trihydroxy-, 2,2',4,4'- tetrahydroxy- or 2'-hydroxy-4,4'-dimethoxy-derivative;
1,3-bis-(2'-hydroxybenzoyl)-benzenes, e.g., 1,3-bis-(2'-hydroxy-4'-
hexyloxy-benzoyl)-benzene, 1,3-bis-(2'-hydroxy-4'-octyloxy-benzoyl)-benzene
or 1,3-bis-(2'-hydroxy-4'-dodecyloxybenzoyl)-benzene; esters of optionally
substituted benzoic acids, e.g., phenylsalicylate octylphenylsalicylate,
dibenzoylresorcin, bis-(4-tert.-butylbenzoyl)resorcin, benzoylresorcin, 3,5-di-tert.-butyl-4-hydroxybenzoic
acid-2,4- di-tert.-butylphenyl ester or -octadecyl ester or -2-methyl-4,6-di-tert.-
butyl ester; acrylates, e.g., alpha -cyano- beta, beta -
diphenylacrylic acid-ethyl ester or isooctyl ester, alpha -carbomethoxycinnamic acid
methyl ester, alpha-cyano-beta-methyl-p-methoxycinnamic acid methyl ester or -butyl
ester or N(beta-carbomethoxyvinyl)-2-methyl-indoline; oxalic acid diamides, e.g.,
4,4'-di-octyloxy-oxanilide, 2,2'-di- octyloxy-5,5'-di-tert.-butyl-oxanilide, 2,2'-di-dodecyloxy-5,5-di-tert.-
butyl-oxanilide, 2-ethoxy-2'-ethyl-oxanilide, N,N'-bis-(3-dimethyl-
aminopropyl)-oxalamide, 2-ethoxy-5-tert.-butyl-2'-ethyloxanilide and the
mixture thereof with 2-ethoxy-2'-ethyl-5,4'-di-tert-butyl-oxanilide, or mixtures of
ortho- and para-methoxy- as well as of ortho- and para-ethoxy di-substituted
oxanilides. In one embodiment, the ultraviolet light absorber can be selected from the
group of 2-(2-hydroxy-5-methylphenyl)-2H-benzotriazole; 2-(2- hydroxy-3,5-di-tert-amylphenyl)-2H-benzotriazole;
2-[2-hydroxy-3,5-di- (alpha,alphadimethylbenzyl)phenyl]-2H-benzotriazole;
2-(2-hydroxy-5-tert- octylphenyl)-2H-benzotriazole;
2-hydroxy-4-octyloxybenzophenone; nickel bis(O-ethyl 3,5-di-tert-butyl-4-hydroxybenzylphosphonate);
2,4- dihydroxybenzophenone; 2-(2-hydroxy-3-tert-butyl-5-methylphenyl)-2H-
benzotriazole;and a nickel butylamine complex with
2,2'-thiobis(4-tert- butylphenol), 2-ethoxy-2'-ethyloxanilide or 2-ethoxy-2'-ethyl-5,5'-ditert-
butyloxanilide.</p><p num="0100">In other embodiments, the fire retardant polymer blends comprise at least one
thermoplastic polymer and a 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine/BPA
polycarbonate copolymer in an amount greater than 7 weight percent of the total
weight of the blend, wherein the polymer blend is free of a fire retardant phosphorous
containing compound, and has at least a V-1 fire rating, as measured in accordance 
with Underwriter Laboratories UL-94 Vertical Burn Test procedure dated July 29,
1997. In other embodiments, depending upon the relative composition of the
thermoplastic polymer and the 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine/BPA
polycarbonate copolymer, such polymer blends also have a V-1 fire rating, as
measured in accordance with Underwriter Laboratories UL-94 Vertical Burn Test
procedure dated July 29, 1997. Polymer blends having a V-1 fire rating are also
valuable for many commercial applications. An exemplary polymer blend comprises
a blend of bisphenol A polycarbonate and an acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene
copolymer as the thermoplastic polymer component. As described in this
embodiment, the polymer blend is free of a fire retardant phosphorous containing
compound such as, for example, polymeric or non-polymeric organic phosphorus
species selected from the group consisting of phosphate esters, thiophosphate esters,
phosphonate esters, thiophosphonate esters, phosphinate esters, thiophosphinate
esters; phosphines, including triphenylphosphine; phosphine oxides, including
triphenylphosphine oxide and tris(2-cyanoethyl)phosphine oxide, thiophosphine
oxide; and phosphonium salts. Other organic phosphorus species include, but are not
intended to be limited to, non-polymeric phosphate esters including, for example,
alkyl phosphate esters, aryl phosphate esters, resorcinol-based phosphate esters, and
bisphenol- based phosphate esters. Exemplary organic phosphorus species are
aromatic phosphate esters, non-limiting examples of which includes
triphenylphosphate, tricresylphosphate, resorcinol bis(diphenylphosphate), bisphenol
A bis(diphenylphosphate), tris(nonyl)phenylphosphate, mixtures of the foregoing
aromatic phosphate esters, and other aromatic phosphate esters known in the art. In
summary, the polymer blend in this embodiment can be free of any phosphorous
containing compounds that function as fire retardants. As such, the polymer blend
may include phosphorous containing compounds that do not function as fire
retardants, e.g., phosphite based additives, and the like.</p><p num="0101">The fire-retardant compositions may further comprise one or more fluoropolymers in
an amount that is effective to provide anti-drip properties to the compositions.
Suitable fluoropolymers and methods for making such fluoropolymers are known,
such as for example, U.S. Patent Nos. 3,671,487 and 3,723,373. Suitable 
fluoropolymers include homopolymers and copolymers that comprise structural units
derived from one or more fluorinated alpha-olefin monomers. The term "fluorinated
alpha-olefin monomer" means an alpha-olefin monomer that includes at least one
fluorine atom substituent. Suitable fluorinated alpha-olefin monomers include, e.g.,
fluoroethylenes such as, tetrafluoroethylene, trifluoroethylene, 1,1-difluoroethylene,
fluoroethylene, 1,1-difluoro-2-chloroethylene, 1,1-difluoro-1,1-dichloroethylene, 1,2-difluoro-1,2-dichloroethylene,
1-fluoro-2,2-dichloroethylene, 1-chloro-1-fluoroethylene,
and 1,1,2-trichloro-2-fluoroethylene; and fluoropropylenes, such as
e.g., hexafluoropropylene, 1,1,1,3-tetrafluoropropylene, 1,1,1,3,3-pentafluoropropylene,
and 1,1,1,2-tetrafluoropropylene. In other embodiments
suitable fluorinated alpha-olefin copolymers include copolymers comprising structural
units derived from two or more fluorinated alpha-olefin copolymers such as, e.g.,
poly(tetrafluoroethylene-hexafluoropropylene), and copolymers comprising structural
units derived from one or more fluorinated monomers and one or more non-fluorinated
monoethylenically unsaturated monomers that are copolymerizable with
the fluorinated monomers such as, e.g., poly(tetrafluoroethylene-ethylene-propylene)
copolymers. Suitable non- fluorinated monoethylenically unsaturated monomers
include e.g., alpha- olefin monomers such as, e.g., ethylene, propylene, butene,
acrylate monomers such as e.g., methyl methacrylate, butyl acrylate, vinyl ethers, such
as, e.g., cyclohexyl vinyl ether, ethyl vinyl ether, n-butyl vinyl ether, vinyl esters such
as, e.g., vinyl acetate, and vinyl versatate. In a particular embodiment the
fluoropolymer is a poly(tetrafluoroethylene) homopolymer ("PTFE"). The
fluoropolymer can be incorporated in the polymer blends by any of the methods
known in the art, such as those disclosed in commonly owned U.S. Patent Application
US 2003/0109650 (published on June 12, 2003).</p><p num="0102">The flame retardant resinous compositions may optionally comprise at least one
impact modifier, which is different from any rubber modified graft copolymer and any
rubber in the rubber modified graft copolymer, as described above. In various
embodiments, suitable impact modifiers comprise at least one core - shell type impact
modifiers comprising a poly(alkyl acrylate) or poly(alkyl methacrylate) shell. In other
embodiments, suitable impact modifiers comprise core - shell type impact modifiers 
comprising a poly(methylmethacrylate) shell. In still other embodiments, suitable
impact modifiers comprise those which are core-shell type impact modifiers including
a shell comprising poly(methylmethacrylate) and a core comprising a polybutadiene
rubber. In still other embodiments, suitable impact modifiers comprise those which
are core-shell type impact modifiers including a shell comprising
poly(methylmethacrylate) and a core comprising a silicone rubber. Illustrative
silicone rubbers may comprise poly(diorganosiloxanes) such as
poly(dimethylsiloxane). In other embodiments, suitable impact modifiers comprising
those which are core-shell type impact modifiers including a shell comprising
poly(methylmethacrylate) and a core comprising a silicone rubber and at least one
other polymer with a glass transition temperature higher than that of the silicone
rubber. In still other embodiments, suitable impact modifiers comprise those which
are core-shell type impact modifiers including a shell comprising
poly(methylmethacrylate) and a core comprising a silicone rubber and at least one
poly(alkylacrylate) with a glass transition temperature higher than that of the silicone
rubber. In a particular embodiment, a suitable impact modifier is a core-shell type
impact modifier, such as those which include a shell comprising
poly(methylmethacrylate) and a core comprising a silicone rubber and
poly(butylacrylate). One type of suitable core-shell impact modifier can be prepared
in accordance with the method of Sasaki et al. as taught in U.S. Pat. No. 5,132,359. In
some embodiments, suitable impact modifiers include those sold under the trade name
METABLEN by Mitsubishi Rayon Co., Ltd.</p><p num="0103">The fire-retardant compositions described hereinabove are valuable for producing
articles. The use of copolymers comprising structural units derived from 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
monomers, such as p,p-PPPBP as a
phosphorus-free fire-retardant additive is useful for producing articles, particularly
thin-walled fire-retardant articles having a wall thickness of about 1 to about 2
millimeters in one embodiment, and about 2 to about 5 millimeters in another
embodiment. Generally, the lower the wall thickness of a molded article, the more
difficult it is to achieve effective fire-retardance (e.g., a V-0 UL94 rating), or a desired
"flame out time" (abbreviated in this disclosure as "FOT"). An exemplary copolymer, 
which is very effective as such a polymeric fire-retardant additive is a material
comprising structural units derived from a monomer mixture of 75 weight percent of
bisphenol A and 25 weight percent of p,p-PPPBP. Such a copolymer can be prepared
by any method known in the art for producing polycarbonates (discussed previously).</p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0104">In the following examples, molecular weights were measured by gel permeation
chromatography using a polystyrene standard. Glass transition temperatures of the
polycarbonates were measured by differential scanning calorimetry by heating the
sample at the rate of 10°C to 20°C per minute under nitrogen. Yellow index was
measured using ASTM D1925 test method on plaques of 3 millimeter thickness and
on films of 0.2 millimeter thickness. Films were prepared in a petri dish by casting
from a solution of 1.1 grams of a polycarbonate in about 10 milliliters of chloroform.</p><p num="0105">HPLC analysis was generally carried out by using a solution of about 50 milligrams of
the sample dissolved in about 10 milliliters of methanol. The HPLC instrument was
equipped with a C18 (reverse phase) column maintained at a temperature of 40 °C,
and an ultraviolet detector capable of detecting components at a wavelength of 230
nanometers. A solvent mixture of methanol and water of varying relative proportions
was used. The flow rate was maintained at 1 milliliter per minute. Area percent assay
was computed from the area value for each peak detected in the chromatogram
divided by the total area from all peaks detected. To measure weight percent assay,
calibration curves for p,p-PPPBP, o,p-PPPBP, and phenolphthalein were first
generated. Then, the weight percent of a given component in a sample was calculated
using these calibration curves.</p><p num="0106">All melt transesterification polymerizations were carried out using either diphenyl
carbonate or bismethylsalicyl carbonate. The catalyst for all of the polymerization
runs was prepared by taking appropriate aliquots of a stock solution of aqueous
sodium hydroxide and a 25 weight percent aqueous tetramethylammonium hydroxide.
Molded articles were prepared by first preparing pellets of the molding compositions
using a 25 millimeter ZSK twin-screw extruder, followed by injection molding using a 
L&amp;T DEMAG 60 molding machine having a clamping capacity of 60 ton, a screw
diameter of 25 millimeters, and shot capacity of 58 grams of polystyrene.</p><p num="0107">Reference to the polymer blends as shown in Table 4 included one or more of the
following materials. Bisphenol A polycarbonate (PC-105), made by an interfacial
process and having a weight average molecular weight of 64,000 (polystyrene
standard, methylene chloride solvent) was obtained from GE Plastics, Mt. Vernon,
Indiana. Acrylonitrile - Butadiene - Styrene (ABS) terpolymer resin made by a bulk
process was used. The resin has an acrylonitrile content of 21.5 - 22.5 weight percent,
butadiene rubber content of 11 - 12.5 weight percent, and styrene content of 66 - 66.5
weight percent. TSAN (Teflon-grafted Styrene-Acrylonitrile copolymer) was used as
an anti-drip agent. TSAN was prepared by polymerizing styrene and acrylonitrile in
an emulsion of Teflon so as to get partially SAN-encapsulated Teflon particles. The
TSAN so prepared typically contains about 50 weight percent of Teflon and about 50
weight percent of styrene and acrylonitrile. Liquid BPADP {(bisphenol A
bis(diphenylphosphate)} was purchased from Albermarle Fine and Specialty
Chemicals.</p><p num="0108">In Table 4, "PC-ST" refers to the polyorganosiloxane-polycarbonate block copolymer
having a weight average molecular weight of about 57,000 and represented by formula
XXI:
<img id="img-00480001" orientation="unknown" wi="145" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00480001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
where "c" has a value of about 20 to about 60, "d" has a value from about 2 to about
3; "e" has a value from about 170 to about 180, and the siloxane blocks comprise
from about 5 to about 10 percent by weight of the block copolymer..</p><p num="0109">The PPPBP/BPA PC copolymer refers to the polycarbonate copolymer prepared using
a monomer mixture consisting of 75 mole percent of BPA and 25 mole percent of
para,para-PPPBP, and has a glass transition temperature (T<sub>g</sub>) of 189 °C. The
BHPM/BPA PC copolymer refers to a polycarbonate copolymer prepared using a 
monomer mixture consisting of 46 mole percent of 1-methyl-1,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)-3-isopropylcyclohexane
(abbreviated as "1,3-BHPM") and 54 mole
percent of BPA, and has T<sub>g</sub> of 191 °C.</p><p num="0110">All the ingredients in the formulation shown in Table 4 were weighed into a
polyethylene bag using a digital weighing balance. All the ingredients were
thoroughly mixed in the bag for 5 minutes. The mixed formulation was then melt
mixed between 280-295 deg C using an intermeshing, twin screw extruder
(Coperion Model ZSK-25) equipped with a 25 millimeter diameter screw. The screw
revolution was maintained at 500 RPM during the melt mixing. All the formulations
were extruded into strands, which were subsequently cut into cylindrical shaped
pellets using an in-line strand cutter.</p><p num="0111">The compounded pellets were dried at 80 °C for a minimum of 6 hours in a hot air
circulated oven. Compounded pellets were then injection molded into standard test
specimens using LT Demag 60 injection molding machine of L&amp;T Make. The
machine had a screw clamming capacity of 60 tons, a diameter of 25 mm and a shot
capacity of 58 grams of polystyrene. Barrel zones were electrically heated and were
maintained between 280-300 °C and the screw speed was 100 RPM. The mold was
maintained at 70 °C using an oil heated mold temperature controller.</p><p num="0112">All the test specimens were conditioned at 23 °C and 50 percent relative humidity for
a minimum of 48 hours before performing the testing. For impact testing, specimens
were conditioned for a minimum of 24 hours after the notch cutting. Uni-axial tensile
testing was done using an Instron Universal Testing Machine (Model No 5566, motor-driven
test frame) in accordance with ISO 527 test method. Notched izod impact
(NII) was determined in accordance with ISO 180A test protocol. The test was done
using a CEAST Impact Tester using a 5.5 joule hammer. Values reported are in
kilojoules per meter square. Heat distortion temperature (HDT) determination was
carried out. HDT was measured in accordance with ISO 75 test method, by applying
the load (1.8 MPa) edgewise on the sample after measuring the sample dimensions. A
CEAST Heat Distortion Temperature Tester (Model No-6921) equipped with a
circulating silicone oil as the heating medium was used to measure HDT. The values 
are reported in °C. Char content analysis was done using a Thermo gravimetric
Analyzer by heating the sample from room temperature to 800 °C at a rate of 20 °C
per minute under nitrogen. The weight of the sample at 750 °C (that is, the
temperature at which the plot of sample weight versus temperature levels off) was
taken as the final char content.</p><p num="0113">Melt volumetric flow rate (abbreviated as MVR) was measured in accordance with
ISO 1133 test protocol using a CEAST Melt volumetric flow rate/melt flow rate
testing machine. The processibility of a thermoplastic polymer composition can be
expressed, for example, by its melt volume rate (hereinafter sometimes referred to as
"MVR") value. In the present disclosure, MVR is defined as the volume of a sample
that passes though an orifice with a piston when a sample of about 6 - 7 grams of the
sample is placed under a constant load of 1.2 kilograms at about 300 °C and a dwell
time of about of 5 minutes. A higher value generally means the polymer composition
is easier to process. MVR test samples were pre-dried for a minimum of 3 hours at 80
°C in a hot air circulated oven. MVR values are reported in cubic centimeters per 10
minutes.</p><p num="0114">Total flame out time (FOT) measurements were carried out on the molded specimens
(1.6 millimeters thick, 13 millimeters wide, and 125 millimeters in length) in
accordance with Underwriter Laboratories UL-94 Vertical Burn Test procedure dated,
July 29, 1997 as follows.</p><p num="0115">Molded specimens were clamped vertically with the help of a stand and on the rear
side of which a mirror is placed to observe if the bars are burning at the backside so
that the total flame out time is captured. A cotton layer was placed under the clamped
bar as per the test protocol to check if any of the drips ignited the cotton layer. The
test burner was applied to the bottom of the bar for 10 seconds. Then the flame was
removed and burning time (T<sub>1</sub>) (that is, the time required for the sample to self-extinguish)
was recorded. As soon as the flame extinguished, the flame was reapplied
immediately for another 10 seconds. Again the burning time (T2) was
recorded. The FOT is then given by (T<sub>1</sub>+T<sub>2</sub>). The burning time after each flame
application and ignition of the cotton layer was interpreted into a UL-94 flammability 
rating. A V-O rating or an average FOT of less than 10 seconds indicates that the
material has the best flame retardance. A V-1 rating is assigned for an average FOT
value of between 10 to less than 30 seconds. When the specimen exhibits both
dripping characteristics and ignition of the cotton, then the fire retardance is rated as
V-2. Any specimen that could not be rated as per the above interpretation has been
designated as "NR (not rated)".</p><p num="0116">Comparative Example 1. In this example, a prior art process was employed to isolate
a para, para-PPPBP product.</p><p num="0117">The prior art process included refluxing a mixture of phenolphthalein (20 grams (g)),
aniline hydrochloride (20 g), and 60 ml of aniline at a temperature from about 180 °C
to about 185 °C for 5 hours under nitrogen. The dark solution was then stirred into a
mixture of 100 grams of ice and 70 grams of concentrated HCl. The violet crystalline
product was filtered off and washed with water. The crystals were then dissolved in
ice-cold 10% sodium hydroxide solution. The solution was treated with 0.2 g active
carbon, and then filtered. By drop-wise addition of concentrated HCl into the stirred
batch, the color changed to a bright pink, then to a pure white, thick slurry with a pH
of 3-4. The precipitated phenolphthalein anilide was then washed neutral with water
and dried under vacuum at 70°C. The crude crystals gave a melting point of 288 -
291°C with a yield of 79%. Double recrystallization from ethanol, followed by
drying the crystals under vacuum at 150°C gave the product. The results are shown in
Table 1.</p><p num="0118">Comparative Example 2. The procedure described in Comparative Example 1 was
repeated except that the water by-product was removed. The results are shown in
Table 1.</p><p num="0119">Comparative Example 3. In this Example, phenolphthalein and aniline were reacted
in the presence of hydrochloric acid. The reaction was carried out without removing
the water by-product.</p><p num="0120">Phenolphthalein (38.1 grams), aniline (65 milliliters), and concentrated hydrochloric
acid (20.5 milliliters) were charged into a reaction vessel and heated such that the 
temperature of the reaction mixture was 155 °C - 165 °C. The temperature of the
reaction was adjusted to 155-165 C. After being heated for about 14 - 15 hours, the
reaction mixture was poured into a mixture of hydrochloric acid and water. The solid
product, which precipitated, was collected by filtration. Analysis of the solid product
by HPLC indicated about 6 area percent of para,para-PPPBP and about 93 area
percent of phenolphthalein, wherein ortho, para-PPPBP was not detected (less than 10
parts per million, the detection limit of the HPLC method). The results are shown in
Table 1.</p><p num="0121">Comparative Examples 4 and 5. Polymerization runs were carried out using the
procedure described in Example 2 below with the para,para-PPPBP prepared in
accordance with Comparative Examples 1 and 2, respectively. The molecular weights
of the polycarbonate prepared by this method and the YI of films prepared by solution
casting of the polycarbonates are shown in Table 2.</p><p num="0122">Comparative Example 6. This Example describes the preparation of a polycarbonate
copolymer using the same method as disclosed in Example 4 below, with a para, para-PPPBP
monomer prepared in accordance with Comparative Example 2.</p><p num="0123">Comparative Examples 7-10. These examples illustrate the various polymer blend
formulations that did not include the para,para-PPPBP/BPA polycarbonate. The
formulations and results are shown in Table 4.</p><p num="0124">Example 1. This Example describes the preparation of para,para-PPPBP containing
less than or equal to about 1,000 parts per million of ortho, para-PPPBP isomer
impurity.</p><p num="0125">Phenolphthalein (31. 8 grams), aniline (65 milliliters), and concentrated hydrochloric
acid (20.5 milliliters) were taken in a reaction flask fitted with a Dean Stark
condenser. The reaction mass was heated to an internal temperature of 155 °C - 165
°C. Water was collected during the course of the reaction. After being heated at this
temperature for 14 - 15 hours, the reaction mixture was poured into a mixture of
hydrochloric acid and water. The crude product, which precipitated, was collected by
filtration and dissolved in an aqueous sodium hydroxide solution containing activated 
charcoal. After being stirred for about 30 minutes, the mixture was then filtered to
remove the charcoal. The charcoal treatment step was repeated once more, and the
resulting filtrate was treated with concentrated hydrochloric acid to precipitate para,
para-PPPBP as a white solid, which was then filtered. The solid product was refluxed
in methanol (approximately four volumes of methanol were taken relative to the
volume of the solid product) for about an hour, cooled, and filtered to provide the
final product which was found by HPLC analysis to have a para, para-PPPBP purity of
99.9 area percent. The yield of the isolated product was 80 to 82 percent of theory.
The results are shown in Table 1, where "ND" indicates, "not detected".</p><p num="0126">Example 2. This Example describes the general melt transesterification method used
for preparing polycarbonate copolymers using 47 weight percent of diphenyl
carbonate and 53 weight percent of a monomer mixture consisting of 75 weight
percent of BPA and 25 weight percent of the purified para,para-PPPBP prepared in
accordance with Example 1.</p><p num="0127">A glass polymerization reactor was passivated by soaking the reactor in a bath
containing 1 molar aqueous hydrochloric acid solution. After 24 hours, the reactor
was thoroughly rinsed with demineralized water, and finally, with deionized water to
ensure that all traces of acid and other contaminants were removed. The reactor was
then thoroughly dried and charged with the appropriate amounts of the purified
para,para-PPPBP monomer or a monomer mixture comprising the purified para,para-PPPBP
and diphenyl carbonate monomers. The reactor was then mounted in a
polymerization assembly and checked to ensure that no leaks were present. The
catalyst solutions (2.5 X 10<sup>-4</sup> mol of aqueous tetramethylammonium hydroxide and 5
X 10<sup>-6</sup> mole of aqueous sodium hydroxide), as prepared above, were then introduced
into the reactor using a syringe. The atmosphere inside the reactor was then evacuated
using a vacuum source and purged with nitrogen. This cycle was repeated 3 times
after which the contents of the reactor were heated to melt the monomer mixture.
When the temperature of the mixture reached about 180°C to about 190 °C, the stirrer
in the reactor was turned on and adjusted to about 40 to about 80 revolutions per
minute (rpm) to ensure that the entire solid mass fully melted, a process that usually
took about 15 to about 20 minutes. Next, the reaction mixture was heated to a 
temperature of about 230°C, while the pressure inside the reactor was adjusted to
about 170 millibar using a vacuum source. This temperature-pressure-time regime
was designated as P1. After stirring the reaction mass at this condition for about 1
hour, the reaction temperature was raised to about 270°C while readjusting the
pressure to around 20 millibar. After being maintained at this condition, designated as
P2, for about 30 minutes, the temperature of the reaction mixture was raised to 300°C
while bringing the pressure down to less than or equal to about 1 millibar. After being
maintained at this condition, designated as P3, for about 30 minutes, the temperature
of the reaction mixture was raised to 300°C while bringing the pressure down to less
than or equal to about 1 millibar. After being maintained at this condition, designated
as P4, for about 30 minutes, the temperature of the reaction mixture was raised to
about 315°C while bringing the pressure down to less than or equal to about 1
millibar. After allowing the reaction to proceed under these conditions, designated as
P5, for about 10 minutes to about 20 minutes, the pressure inside the reactor was
brought to atmospheric pressure and the reactor was vented to relieve any excess
pressure. Product isolation was accomplished by breaking the glass nipple at the
bottom of the reactor and collecting the material. In the cases where the product was
of a very high molecular weight, the hot molten polymer was dropped down by
pressurizing the reactor with nitrogen gas.</p><p num="0128">Example 3. This Example describes the melt transesterification method used for
preparing polycarbonate copolymer using 55 weight percent of bismethylsalicyl
carbonate and 45 weight percent of a monomer mixture comprising 75 weight percent
of BPA and 25 weight percent of purified para,para-PPPBP (prepared as described in
Example 1).</p><p num="0129">The same procedure as described above was used to charge the necessary reaction
ingredients into the reactor. However, after the heating step to fully melt the
monomer, the reaction mixture was heated to a temperature of about 210°C at
atmospheric pressure (about 910 millibar). After stirring the reaction mass at this
condition for about 10 minutes, the pressure was reduced to about 100 millibars, and
maintained at this condition for about 15 minutes. Next, the reaction mixture was
heated to a temperature of about 310 °C while bring the pressure down to less than or 
equal to about 1 millibar. After being stirred under these conditions for about 15
minutes, the pressure inside the reactor was brought to atmospheric pressure and the
reactor was vented to relieve any excess pressure. Product isolation was
accomplished using the same procedure as described in Example 2.</p><p num="0130">The procedure described hereinabove was used to prepare polycarbonate copolymers
having M<sub>w</sub> from about 45,000 to about 75,000.</p><p num="0131">Example 4. This Example describes the general procedure for the interfacial
polymerization method using a monomer mixture comprising a 75 : 25 mole ratio of
purified para,para-PPPBP (prepared in accordance with method described in Example
1) and BPA, respectively. The procedure used here is as described in U.S. Patent
5,804,525, where the monomer mixture (as described above) and para-cumylphenol
was reacted with phosgene in methylene chloride in the presence of
tetrabutylammonium bromide. During addition of phosgene, the pH of the reaction
mixture was maintained at about 10.5 by slow addition of aqueous sodium hydroxide.
After phosgene addition, triethylamine was added to react out trace levels of
chloroformate derivatives present in the reaction mixture. The polycarbonate thus
prepared had the following physical properties: YI (yellowness index, ASTM D1925):
9; Notched izod at ambient temperature (ASTM D256): 4.9 foot-pound per inch;
Glass transition temperature: 191 °C; Delta YI (ASTM D1925) of molded article after
heat aging in air in an oven maintained at 155 °C - 160 °C for 500 hours: less than 2;
Delta YI (ASTM D1925) after heat aging in air in an oven maintained at 120 °C for
500 hours: less than 0.5.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="left" namest="1">Example</entry><entry nameend="4" align="left" namest="2">HPLC analysis (Area percent)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">para,para-PPPBP</entry><entry align="left">Phenolphthalein</entry><entry align="left">ortho,para-PPPBP</entry></row> <row><entry align="left">1 <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">97.5</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="left">2</entry></row> <row><entry align="left">2 <!--footnotes removed--></entry> <entry align="center">98.5</entry> <entry align="center">0.11</entry><entry align="left">1.35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3 <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">6.2</entry><entry align="center">93.1</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">99.9</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry><entry align="left">ND<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Polymerization Run Example Number</entry><entry align="left">para,para-PPPBP Example Number</entry><entry align="left">M<sub>w</sub> of polycarbonate (Daltons)</entry><entry align="left">YI of polycarbonate (article)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">1<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">21,000</entry><entry align="left">6.3 (film)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">5<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">2<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">19,000</entry><entry align="left">4.3 (film)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">30,000</entry><entry align="left">0.8 (film)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">63,000</entry><entry align="left">0.6 (film)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">62,000</entry><entry align="left">&lt; 1 (film); 9 (molded plaque)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">6<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">2<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">44,000</entry><entry align="left">59 (molded plaque)<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0132">Table 1 shows the effect of the purity of the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidines
on the molecular weight and yellowness indices of films
of the polymers derived using these phthalimidines as a comonomer with bisphenol A.
Comparative Examples 1 and 2 indicate that a higher level of the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine
impurity (or sometimes herein
generally referred to as "ortho, para-PPPBP impurity") in the para,para-PPPBP
comonomer results in a lower molecular weight and a relatively higher film
yellowness index for the polymer. Without wishing to be bound by theory, it is
believed that the ortho, paraPPPBP impurity, being relatively more sterically hindered
than the corresponding para,para-phthalimidine isomer acts as a chain termination
agent, thereby limiting polymer chain length and molecular weight. However,
Example 1 shows that when para,para-PPPBP with no detectable (by HPLC) level of
the ortho, para-impurity is copolymerized with BPA, the polymer weight average
molecular weight is substantially higher (31,000). Furthermore, the polymer film has
a relatively much lower yellowness index of 0.8. Comparative Example 3 shows that
even if the reaction temperature is maintained at about 155 °C to 165 °C, if water is
not removed during the reaction to form para,para-PPPBP, the reaction gives a very
poor yield (about 6 area percent) of para,para-PPPBP. </p><p num="0133">Moreover, when the compound (IV) was prepared in accordance with the procedure of
Comparative Example 1, wherein phenolphthalein and excess aniline are heated under
reflux in a nitrogen atmosphere for about 5 hours without removal of water, such that
the reaction temperature is about 180 °C to about 185 °C, the para, para-PPPBP that
was isolated after the double crystallization from ethanol contained about 2.5 area
percent of an undesired side-product that has been analytically determined to be
isomeric ortho, para-PPPBP.</p><p num="0134">On the other hand, if the reaction is carried out in the same manner as described in
Comparative Example 1, but the water by-product is distilled out over the same period
of about 5 hours, HPLC analysis indicated that the isolated product contains about
98.5 area percent of para,para-PPPBP, about 0.11 area percent of phenolphthalein, and
about 1.35 area percent of the impurity compound (IV). This indicates that water
removal is necessary to lower the formation of compound (IV). However, when the
reaction is conducted using a reaction temperature of about 160 °C to about 165 °C,
water removal takes about 14 hours, and the impurity (IV) was undetectable in the
isolated para, para-PPPBP product relative to the measurement sensitivity of the
HPLC method (detection limit of 10 parts per million for compound (IV)).
Furthermore, the product only contains about 0.05 area percent of phenolphthalein. In
contrast, when the reaction was conducted at a reaction temperature of about 160 °C to
about 165 °C, but the water was not removed, HPLC analysis of the reaction mixture
after 14 hours of heating indicated formation of only about 6.2 area percent of para,
para-PPPBP with the majority (about 92 area percent) of phenolphthalein starting
material remaining unreacted. These results clearly indicate that the preferred method
for forming para, para-PPPBP in high isolated yield and high isomeric purity is to
maintain the reaction temperature at about 160 °C to about 165 °C with water removal
over a period of about 14 hours. Under such conditions, utilization of phenolphthalein
for selectively forming para, para-PPPBP is enhanced, and formation of the ortho,
para-PPPBP is minimized. These techniques can be suitably adapted to prepare the
other 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidines described previously.</p><p num="0135">The results shown in Table 1 (Example 1), and Table 2, (Examples 2 and 4) clearly
indicate that purified para,para-PPPBP is useful for preparing polycarbonates of high 
molecular weight (e.g., M<sub>w</sub> of 62,000), which are valuable for producing films and
molded articles having a yellowness index of less than 10. Moreover, the molded
articles show excellent resistance to heat aging, as shown in Example 4, thus making
such polycarbonates valuable for high heat applications.</p><p num="0136">Examples 5-7. These examples illustrate the various polymer blend formulations that
included varying amounts of the para,para-PPPBP/BPA polycarbonate. The
formulations and results are shown in Table 4. <tables><table><tgroup cols="9"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="9" align="left" namest="2">Compositions and Examples</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Raw materials</entry><entry align="left">A</entry><entry align="left">B</entry><entry align="left">C</entry><entry align="left">D</entry><entry align="left">E</entry><entry align="left">F</entry><entry align="left">G</entry><entry align="left">H</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">6<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">7<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">8<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">9<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">10<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="left">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PC-105</entry><entry align="left">80.4</entry><entry align="left">90.4</entry><entry align="left">94.4</entry><entry align="left">92.4</entry><entry align="left">80.4</entry><entry align="left">80.4</entry><entry align="left">87.4</entry><entry align="left">84.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Liquid BPADP</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Bulk ABS</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Anti-drip additive</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Anti-oxidant</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pentaerythritol tetrastearate</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PC-ST</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PPPBP/BPA PC copolymer</entry><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="left">10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">BHPM/BPA PC copolymer</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">14</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Property Measured</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Average FOT</entry><entry align="left">2.6</entry><entry align="left">2.68</entry><entry align="left">14.24</entry><entry align="left">9.4</entry><entry align="left">16.1</entry><entry align="left">32.2</entry><entry align="left">10.6</entry><entry align="left">4.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UL94 rating</entry><entry align="left">V0</entry><entry align="left">V0</entry><entry align="left">V1</entry><entry align="left">V1</entry><entry align="left">V1</entry><entry align="left">NR</entry><entry align="left">V1</entry><entry align="left">V0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">NII (kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</entry><entry align="left">25.6</entry><entry align="left">16.8</entry><entry align="left">71.5</entry><entry align="left">25.5</entry><entry align="left">79.5</entry><entry align="left">65.3</entry><entry align="left">31.3</entry><entry align="left">28.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Modulus (MPa)</entry><entry align="left">2338</entry><entry align="left">2573</entry><entry align="left">2417</entry><entry align="left">2373</entry><entry align="left">2279</entry><entry align="left">2495</entry><entry align="left">2314</entry><entry align="left">2330</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Strength (MPa)</entry><entry align="left">62.1</entry><entry align="left">63.83</entry><entry align="left">58.3</entry><entry align="left">60.3</entry><entry align="left">57.5</entry><entry align="left">63.9</entry><entry align="left">60.5</entry><entry align="left">60.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Yield Strain %</entry><entry align="left">6.1</entry><entry align="left">5.8</entry><entry align="left">5.9</entry><entry align="left">5.6</entry><entry align="left">6.0</entry><entry align="left">7.1</entry><entry align="left">6.0</entry><entry align="left">5.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Break Stress (MPa)</entry><entry align="left">49</entry><entry align="left">65.3</entry><entry align="left">59.3</entry><entry align="left">61.7</entry><entry align="left">62.2</entry><entry align="left">64.5</entry><entry align="left">53.3</entry><entry align="left">57.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Break Strain (percent)</entry><entry align="left">41</entry><entry align="left">101.7</entry><entry align="left">95</entry><entry align="left">94.6</entry><entry align="left">103.9</entry><entry align="left">90.1</entry><entry align="left">72.4</entry><entry align="left">85.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MVR</entry><entry align="left">6.3</entry><entry align="left">5.9</entry><entry align="left">6.1</entry><entry align="left">5.5</entry><entry align="left">6.3</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">11.2</entry><entry align="left">10.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Char Yield (weight percent)</entry><entry align="left">25.7</entry><entry align="left">20.1</entry><entry align="left">19.9</entry><entry align="left">19.7</entry><entry align="left">21.3</entry><entry align="left">19.6</entry><entry align="left">22.1</entry><entry align="left">20.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">HDT (°C)</entry><entry align="left">124</entry><entry align="left">109.1</entry><entry align="left">121.8</entry><entry align="left">114.4</entry><entry align="left">117.2</entry><entry align="left">124.7</entry><entry align="left">121</entry><entry align="left">121.6<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0137">The data as presented in Table 4 shows that addition of 10 to 14 weight percent of the
para, para-PPPBP/BPA polycarbonate copolymer to a BPA polycarbonate - ABS 
resin blend advantageously and unexpectedly leads to a V-0 fire-retardant
composition, most notably achieved without the use of any phosphorus-containing
compound (such as BPADP) as a fire retardant additive. Use of 10 weight percent of
the polycarbonate copolymer also gives V-0 fire retardance (see Example 7), however,
use of 7 weight percent of the para,para-PPPBP/BPA polycarbonate copolymer to the
polycarbonate - ABS resin blend leads to a V-1 fire retardant composition (See
Example 6). Therefore, it appears that for polycarbonate - ABS resin blends, the
transition from V-0 to V-1 fire retardance occurs when the amount of the para,para-PPPBP/BPA
polycarbonate copolymer is varied from 7 - 10 weight percent. Further,
comparison of Example 5 and Comparative Example 6 shows that use of the
para,para-PPPBP/BPA polycarbonate as a fire retardant additive gives an increase in
the HDT of about 15 °C, thereby clearly showing the plasticizing effect of the BPADP
type fire retardant additive. Additionally, the composition of Example 5 shows a
significantly improved NII (at ambient temperature) value of 25.6 kilojoules per meter
square, as compared to the value of 16.8 kilojoules per meter square for the
composition of Comparative Example 7.</p><p num="0138">Comparative Example 10 indicates that if the 1,3-BHPM/BPA polycarbonate
copolymer with a T<sub>g</sub> of about 191°C, which is comparable to the T<sub>g</sub> (189 °C) of the
para,para-PPPBP/BPA polycarbonate copolymer is used, poor fire-retardance was
observed, and therefore the result could not be classified under the UL94 rating
system. Hence, the fire retardant activity cannot be generalized to any polycarbonate
polymer having a relatively high T<sub>g</sub>, such as those polymers having a T<sub>g</sub> of around
190°C. Comparing the data obtained from Comparative Example 9 and Example 5, it
can be seen that the use of para,para-PPPBP/BPA polycarbonate copolymer as a
polymeric fire retardant additive gives superior fire retardance, as compared with
using the PC - ST copolymer, but without an added organic phosphorus compound.
Organosiloxane - polycarbonate block copolymer, such as PC - ST have previously
been used as a synergist in conjunction with an organic phosphorus compound for
preparing fire-retardant polymer compositions.</p><p num="0139">It also appears that when polycarbonates comprising structural units derived from
para,para-PPPBP are incorporated in the BPA polycarbonate - ABS resin blend, the 
resulting compositions show a surprisingly higher MVR (6.3 in Example 5), as
compared to compositions which do not contain the para,para-PPPBP/BPA
polycarbonate (5.1 in Comparative Example 6). Therefore, the present disclosure
enables one to produce V-0 fire-retardant polymer blends that not only have higher
HDT values, but also are relatively easier to process.</p><p num="0140">While the disclosure has been described with reference to a preferred embodiment, it
will be understood by those skilled in the art that various changes may be made and
equivalents may be substituted for elements thereof without departing from the scope
of the disclosure. In addition, many modifications may be made to adapt a particular
situation or material to the teachings of the disclosure without departing from essential
scope thereof. Therefore, it is intended that the disclosure not be limited to the
particular embodiment disclosed as the best mode contemplated for carrying out this
invention, but that the disclosure will include all embodiments falling within the scope
of the appended claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for producing a 2- hydrocarbyl -3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine,
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>forming a reaction mixture comprising at least one substituted or unsubstituted
phenolphthalein, at least one substituted or unsubstituted primary hydrocarbyl amine,
and an acid catalyst; and</claim-text><claim-text>heating the reaction mixture to a temperature of less than 180 °C to remove a distillate
comprising water and form a crude 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
product;</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein said 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine has a formula:

wherein R1 is selected from the group consisting of a hydrogen and a hydrocarbyl
group, and R2 is selected from the group consisting of a hydrogen, a hydrocarbyl
group, and a halogen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method of Claim 1, further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>dissolving said crude 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine product in
an aqueous base to provide a first solution;</claim-text><claim-text>treating and filtering said first solution with a solid adsorbent to provide a second
solution; and</claim-text><claim-text>treating said second solution with an aqueous acid to precipitate said 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine comprising less than or
equal to 1,000 parts per million of a 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine
relative to an overall weight of said 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine,
wherein said 2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine
has a formula of:

wherein R1 is selected from the group consisting of a hydrogen and a hydrocarbyl
group, and R2 is selected from the group consisting of a hydrogen, a hydrocarbyl
group, and a halogen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A polycarbonate comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>structural units of formula derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine:
</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein R1 is selected from the group consisting of a hydrogen and a hydrocarbyl
group, and R2 is selected from the group consisting of a hydrogen, a hydrocarbyl
group, and a halogen; and further wherein the 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine
comprises less than or equal to 1,000 parts per million of a
2-hydrocarbyl-3-{(4-hydroxyaryl)(2-hydroxyaryl)}phthalimidine relative to an overall
weight of said 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A polymer blend consisting essentially of at least one thermoplastic polymer
and a polymer comprising structural units derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A molded article comprising a polymer blend, said polymer blend consisting
essentially of:
<claim-text><claim-text>at least one thermoplastic polymer in an amount of 5 to 98 weight percent based on a
total weight of the polymer blend, wherein the at least one thermoplastic polymer
comprises vinyl polymers, acrylic polymers, polyacrylonitrile, polystyrenes,
polyolefins, polyesters, polyurethanes, polyamides, polysulfones, polyimides,
polyetherimides, polyphenylene ethers, polyphenylene sulfides, polyether ketones,
polyether ether ketones, polyethersulfones, poly(alkenylaromatic) polymers,
polybutadiene, polyacetals, polycarbonates, polyphenylene ethers, ethylene-vinyl
acetate copolymers, polyvinyl acetate, liquid crystal polymers, aromatic polyesters,
polyestercarbonate, copolymers comprising aromatic ester, estercarbonate, and
carbonate repeat units, mixtures; and blends comprising at least one of the foregoing
polymers;</claim-text><claim-text>at least one rubber-modified graft copolymer in an amount of 75 to 1 weight percent
based on a total weight of the polymer blend; and</claim-text><claim-text>a polycarbonate in an amount of 20 to 1 weight percent based on a total weight of the
polymer blend, wherein the polycarbonate comprises structural units derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A molded article comprising a polymer blend, said polymer blend consisting
essentially of:
<claim-text><claim-text>a bisphenol A polycarbonate in an amount of 5 to 98 weight percent based on a total
weight of the polymer blend;</claim-text><claim-text>an acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene resin in an amount of 75 to 1 weight percent based
on a total weight of the polymer blend; and</claim-text><claim-text>polycarbonate in an amount of 20 to 1 weight percent based on a total weight of the
polymer blend, wherein the polycarbonate comprises structural units derived from a 2-phenyl-3-{(4-hydroxyphenyl)(2-hydroxyphenyl)}phthalimidine.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A polymer blend comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>at least one thermoplastic polymer, and</claim-text><claim-text>a 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine/BPA polycarbonate copolymer in
an amount greater than 7 weight percent of the total weight of the blend, wherein the
polymer blend is free of a fire retardant phosphorous containing compound, and has at
least a V-1 fire rating as measured in accordance with Underwriter Laboratories UL-94
Vertical Burn Test procedure dated July 29, 1997.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A polycarbonate-acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene polymer blend comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a bisphenol A polycarbonate;</claim-text><claim-text>an acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene; and</claim-text><claim-text>a 2-phenyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)phthalimidine/BPA polycarbonate copolymer in
an amount greater than 7 weight percent of the total weight of the blend, wherein the
polycarbonate-acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene polymer blend is free of a phosphorous
containing compound and has a V-O fire rating as measured in accordance with
Underwriter Laboratories UL-94 Vertical Burn Test procedure dated July 29, 1997.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A polymer blend comprising at least one thermoplastic polymer and a polymer
comprising structural units derived from a 2-hydrocarbyl-3,3-bis(4-hydroxyaryl)phthalimidine,
wherein the blend does not comprise a flame retardant.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>