<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1408100-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1408100" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="32028530" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040414"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1408100-A1" status="new" fvid="24035630"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1408100</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040414</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03021731-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03021731</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030925</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-6537602-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6537602</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021010</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J   8/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J   8/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J   8/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J   8/18        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J   8/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J   8/24        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  38/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  38/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  38/12        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  38/30        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10G  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10G  11/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J   8/00F6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J   8/18G</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J   8/24F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10G  11/18A</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Katalysator Regeneration mit Mittelrohr</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Catalyst regenerator with a centerwell</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Régénératuer de catalysateur avec un conduit central</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0413062-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0413062</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3661800-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3661800</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4615992-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4615992</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5043522-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5043522</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5171921-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5171921</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6118035-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6118035</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1993000674-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1993000674</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>KELLOG BROWN &amp; ROOT INC</last-name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>KELLOG BROWN &amp; ROOT, INC.</last-name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kellog Brown &amp;amp; Root, Inc.</last-name><address><street>4100 Clinton Drive</street><city>Houston, Texas 77020</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>PETERSON ROBERT B</last-name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>SANTNER CHRIS</last-name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>TALLMAN MICHAEL</last-name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>PETERSON, ROBERT B.</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>SANTNER, CHRIS</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>TALLMAN, MICHAEL</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PETERSON, ROBERT B.</last-name><address><street>602 Santa Maria</street><city>Sugar Land Texas 77478</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SANTNER, CHRIS</last-name><address><street>15943 Ivy Bridge Lane</street><city>Houston Texas 77095</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TALLMAN, MICHAEL</last-name><address><street>7311 Redding Road</street> <city>Houston Texas 77036</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor> </inventors> <agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Weiss, Wolfgang, Dipl.-Chem. Dr.</last-name> <address><street>Weickmann &amp;amp; Weickmann Patentanwälte Postfach 86 08 20</street><city>81635 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>BE</country><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A catalyst regenerator for regenerating spent light FCC catalyst
and heating the catalyst to supply heat to an FCC reactor. The
regenerator has discharge outlets for catalyst and off gas and a valve
for introducing spent catalyst through a central stand pipe portion.
The regenerator houses a dense phase catalyst bed. A centerwell
receives a lower end of the standpipe portion and defines an annulus
therebetween. The spent catalyst is introduced through the standpipe
portion into the annulus. A fuel distributor introduces fuel into the
centerwell for mixing with the catalyst in the annulus. A fluidization
distributor introduces fluidization gas into the centerwell for fluidizing
the catalyst in the annulus. A radial slot in the centerwell introduces
the catalyst and fuel mixture from the annulus below the upper
surface of the dense phase bed. An air distributor located below the
radial slot introduces combustion air into the dense phase bed.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to catalyst recovery from a light
FCC-type effluent, and also to regeneration of the recovered
catalyst.</p><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0002">It has been proposed to produce light olefins such as ethylene
and propylene from mixtures of heavier paraffin and olefins using a
fluid catalytic cracking (FCC) system with the reaction conditions
described, for example, in US Patents 5,043,522 to Leyshon et al.;
5,171,921 to Gaffney et al.; and 6,118,035 Fung et al. In this
system, particulated catalyst and feedstock enter a reactor under
specific reaction conditions. The reactor effluent is processed in a
series of cyclone separators, usually housed in a vessel, that
separate most of the catalyst from the effluent to be regenerated for
recycle to a regenerator and then to the reactor, in a manner similar
to conventional refinery FCC operations. The catalyst-lean hot
effluent gases from the cyclones are then cooled and separated by
fractional distillation, for example, into the product constituents.</p><p num="0003">There are, however, some significant differences between the
light olefin FCC process and conventional refinery FCC operations.
Conventional FCC processes produce an effluent that has significant
quantities of heavier hydrocarbons that are condensed in a quench
tower. There is also a minor amount of residual catalyst entrained in
the effluent, that is not removed by the cyclones, which is collected
with the heavier hydrocarbons condensed in the quench tower to
form slurry oil. Slurry oil from the quench tower is often difficult to 
process and/or dispose of; frequently it is burned as a fuel oil. In the
light olefin FCC process, there are only very minor quantities of
heavier hydrocarbons in the effluent gas, i.e. a relatively high ratio of
catalyst to fuel oil, so the removal of the catalyst fines becomes
problematic because there is very little heavy oil recovered and any
'slurry oil' would have a much higher catalyst loading than in the
case of the conventional refinery FCC process.</p><p num="0004">Another issue in the light olefin FCC process is the
regeneration of the catalyst recovered from the riser effluent by the
cyclones. In the conventional refinery FCC unit, significant quantities
of coke are formed in the riser and deposit on the catalyst particles.
In the regenerator, this coke can be used as a fuel source for
combustion with oxygen in the regenerator vessel to supply the heat
needed to heat-balance the unit. Frequently, the regenerator may
need to be cooled to prevent the catalyst from getting too hot,
particularly when the feedstock deposits a lot of carbon on the
catalyst. On the other hand, the prior art light olefin FCC process
generally has insufficient coke deposition in the light olefin FCC
process to support catalyst regeneration and the heat of reaction.</p><p num="0005">In a conventional gasoline FCC process, it has been
suggested that supplemental fuel such as fuel gas or fuel oil (torch
oil) can be introduced into the regenerator to achieve the
temperatures required for catalyst regeneration and the heat of
reaction during non-steady state operations, for example, when
starting-up the unit, to achieve an adequate regenerator
temperature. However, as far as applicant is aware, there are no
adequate systems known for introducing fuel into the dense phase 
bed of a FCC regenerator processing low-carbon catalyst, for
continuous operation.</p><p num="0006">Further, there is a need for a light olefin FCC process and
system capable of processing a light feedstock that conventionally
yields inadequate coke formation, yet improved somehow to achieve
the heat of reaction required in the reactor.</p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0007">The present invention addresses the catalyst handling
problems in the light olefin FCC process noted above, preferably by
using a fuel oil addition to the quench tower and recirculation of the
quench tower oil to wash catalyst from the effluent gases, by
recovering a slurry of the catalyst in the fuel oil from the recirculating
quench oil, and by continuously introducing the slurry into the
regenerator to recover the catalyst and supply the heat requirements
for catalyst regeneration and the heat of reaction. In this manner,
the fuel oil supplied for catalyst washing from the effluent gas can
preferably be used to supply the heat requirements of the
regenerator, and at the same time can eliminate catalyst losses in
the effluent gas.</p><p num="0008">The present invention is a method and system for recovering
fines from a light FCC-type effluent gas. The feedstock for such a
light FCC unit is a feedstock that conventionally yields inadequate
coke formation, for example, a C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>12</sub> feedstock, preferably a C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>8</sub>
feedstock. Cracked gases from the reactor are cooled by direct
contact with circulating oil, for example, in an oil quench tower. The
catalyst fines carried with the reactor effluent are washed out from
the gases. A circulating oil pump-around loop cools the gases and 
removes the fines. A slipstream of quench oil is sent to a catalyst
separation system for separation of the catalyst fines. Catalyst
removal can be achieved, for example, via filtration, hydroclonic
separation, electrostatic precipitation, and a combination thereof.
For example, when catalyst filtration is utilized, a slipstream of the
quench oil can be sent through one of at least two filters to remove
fines. Another filter is in backwash operation using compressed gas
to remove the collected fines. The recovered fines are combined
with quench oil to form a slurry that carries the fines to the FCC
regenerator. The quench oil in the slurry is combusted in the
regenerator to provide a convenient way of supplying FCC system
heat requirements, while at the same time returning the catalyst fines
recovered from the reactor effluent gas to the FCC system. In this
manner, catalyst losses can be limited to any fines entrained in the
regenerator exhaust from the dilute phase. Since there is a
minimum amount of oil generated in the FCC, the quench oil is
imported to inventory the quench tower and provide the heat
required in the regenerator.</p><p num="0009">In one aspect, the present invention broadly provides a
method for recovering catalyst fines from a light FCC-type effluent
gas. The method includes the steps of:
<sl><li>(a) supplying quench oil to maintain a steady state
inventory thereof;</li><li>(b) contacting the effluent gas with the quench oil to cool
the effluent gas and wash out catalyst fines to obtain a cooled
effluent gas essentially free of fines; </li><li>(c) returning the quench oil from the contacting step to
the inventory;</li><li>(d) continuously recirculating quench oil from the
inventory to the contacting step;</li><li>(e) separating fines from a stream of the quench oil from
the inventory to recover the fines and keep the fines from
building up in the inventory; and</li><li>(f) slurrying the fines recovered from the separation
step.</li></sl></p><p num="0010">In the method, the contacting and collecting steps can be
effected in a quench tower comprising vapor-liquid contact elements
and a bottoms zone that holds the inventory of quench oil. The
recirculated quench oil can be cooled before the contacting step.
The separation can be effected by any suitable means, for example,
filtration, electrostatic separation and use of hydroclones, and the
separation is preferably continuous.</p><p num="0011">When using filtration, the separation is preferably effected
using at least two filters, wherein a first filter is in a filtration mode
while a second filter in parallel is used for backwashing to remove
the collected fines. The filtrate can be returned to the inventory. The
filtration and backwashing can also include periodically alternating
the first and second filters between filtration and backwashing
modes. The backwashing preferably includes at least one
compressed gas pulse through the at least one filter that is in the
backwashing mode in the reverse flow direction to remove the
separated fines, and collecting the separated fines in a holdup 
vessel. The separated fines are combined with a heavy oil, such as
fuel oil or quench oil, to form a slurry, preferably in the holdup vessel.</p><p num="0012">The electrostatic precipitation process is similar to the filtration
procedure insofar as multiple units are on-line, collecting catalyst
fines, while one or more are being backwashed. This backwash step
utilizes clean fuel oil or circulating quench oil. The separation is
accomplished by inducing an electrical field across a packing
medium. Catalyst particles are ionized and/or polarized and
collected at contact points in the packing medium. Removal of the
particles is accomplished by deactivating the electrodes and backflushing
the freed particles.</p><p num="0013">The hydroclone separation process preferably has at least two
stages of hydroclones in series with each stage containing multiple,
small diameter hydroclones in parallel. The hydroclone operates by
the same principal as a cyclone; specifically, centrifugal force is used
to separate the oil and catalyst particles. Two stages are necessary
at a minimum to concentrate the underflow stream. Typically, the
underflow from the hydroclone is 20 to 40 percent of the total flow.
The requirements of this process dictate that the solids be
concentrated in the underflow stream which is 5 to 10 percent of the
total inlet flow. By example, if the circulating oil is 50,000 lbs/hr and
the net fuel oil is 5,000 lbs/hr, then the net underflow must be 10
percent of the total flow or 31.6 percent from each stage (0.316 x
0.316 = 0.1). It is not necessary that the underflows from each stage
be identical, but the net underflow must satisfy the fuel oil
requirement. The underflow quantity is typically controlled by control
valves on the outlets of the overflow and underflow streams. </p><p num="0014">A slurry is formed by combining the fines with a quench oil.
Sometimes steam is added to further distribute the fines in the
quench oil. The slurry from the holdup vessel is preferably
introduced into a catalyst regenerator in a light FCC unit for
combustion to supply the heat requirement of the FCC process.
Slurry in excess of that required for combustion can be introduced
into the reactor in the FCC unit where it is vaporized into the effluent
gas. The makeup quench oil can be added directly to the inventory,
the recirculation loop or as the filter backwash.</p><p num="0015">In another aspect, the present invention provides a system for
recovering fines from a light FCC-type effluent gas. The system
includes means for supplying quench oil to maintain a steady state
inventory thereof, means for contacting the effluent gas with the
quench oil to cool the effluent gas and wash out catalyst fines to
obtain a cooled effluent gas essentially free of fines, means for
returning the quench oil from the contacting step to the inventory,
means for continuously recirculating quench oil from the inventory to
the contacting step, means for separating fines from a stream of the
quench oil from the inventory to recover the fines and keep the fines
from building up in the inventory, and means for slurrying the fines
recovered from the separation step.</p><p num="0016">A further aspect of the invention is a system for recovering
fines from a light FCC-type effluent gas that includes a quench tower
having an inlet for receiving the effluent gas, vapor-liquid contacting
elements disposed above the inlet for cooling the effluent gas and
washing out the fines, a gas outlet above the contacting elements for
discharging cooled effluent gas essentially free of entrained fines, 
and a liquid holdup zone below the inlet for collecting quench oil from
the contacting elements. A recirculation loop is provided for
continuously recirculating the quench oil from the liquid holdup zone
to the contacting elements. At least two filters are alternatingly
operable in filtration and backwashing modes. A filtration loop is
provided for circulating quench oil from the liquid holdup zone
through a filtration-mode filter and returning filtrate to the liquid
holdup zone. A backwashing loop is provided for removing the fines
collected in the filter and passing the collected fines to a slurry
collection zone. A heavy oil, for example, fuel oil or quench oil from
inventory, is added to the slurry collection zone to form a slurry of the
collected fines therein.</p><p num="0017">The system can also include a quench line for introducing the
effluent gas into the inlet, the quench line including a mixing zone for
receiving quench oil to cool the effluent gas, and a filtrate line from
the filtration-mode filter to the mixing zone for supplying the filtrate as
the quench oil. A line can be provided for supplying makeup quench
oil to the quench tower or to the recirculation loop. Valves can be
used in the backwash and recirculation loops for selectively placing
the filters in filtration and backwash modes. The system can also
include a source of compressed gas, a line from the source to the
backwashing loop, and a valve in the line for pulsing the compressed
gas into the backwashing loop to facilitate fines removal from the
backwashing-mode filter.</p><p num="0018">The system, alternatively or additionally, includes a line for
supplying the slurry from the slurry collection zone to the reactor in
the FCC unit. Preferably, the system can include a line for supplying 
the slurry from the slurry collection zone into a dense phase bed of a
regenerator for receiving and regenerating catalyst from the stripper
for recirculation to a FCC reactor that supplies the effluent to the
stripper. Preferably, the regenerator includes a mixing zone for
mixing the slurry and the catalyst from the stripper and a discharge
zone for introducing the mixture from the mixing zone within the
dense phase bed, preferably below the top of the dense phase bed.
The mixing zone is preferably an annulus centrally disposed within
the dense phase bed. The regenerator can have a subjacent air
distributor for introducing an oxygen-containing gas adjacent the
discharge zone, preferably in the form of a pipe ring with perforations
or multiple nozzles or, alternatively, a pipe grid with multiple branch
arms around the annulus and below the discharge zone.</p><p num="0019">Still further, the present invention provides a catalyst
regenerator for regenerating spent light FCC catalyst. The
regenerator includes a regenerator vessel housing a dense phase
catalyst bed, a central upright standpipe portion for receiving the
spent catalyst to be regenerated, and a centerwell receiving a lower
end of the standpipe portion and defining an annulus between the
standpipe portion and an inside diameter of the centerwell. There is
a valve for controlling the introduction of spent catalyst from the
standpipe portion into the annulus. In one embodiment useful in an
FCC unit having a central vertical standpipe configuration, the valve
is located at a lower end of the standpipe portion, which is at the
lower end of the vertical standpipe. In another embodiment, the FCC
unit is of a side by side design and the valve is a catalyst slide valve
located in the pipe angled into the side of the regenerator. The 
angled pipe extends to the center of the regenerator and the
standpipe portion is attached to or formed as part of the end thereof.
A fuel distributor is provided for introducing fuel into the centerwell
for mixing with the catalyst in the annulus. A fluidization distributor is
provided for introducing fluidization gas into the centerwell for
fluidizing the catalyst in the annulus. A radial slot is formed in the
centerwell for introducing the catalyst and fuel mixture from the
annulus into the dense phase bed below an upper surface thereof.
An air distribution ring or pipe distributor is disposed in the dense
phase bed about the centerwell subjacent to the radial slot for
introducing combustion air into the dense phase bed. A catalyst
discharge outlet is in fluid communication with the dense phase bed.
An off gas discharge outlet is in fluid communication with a dilute
phase above the dense phase bed. The regenerator can also
include a source of fuel oil for supplying the fuel oil to the fuel
distributor, a fluidization medium source for supplying a fluidization
medium which is not an oxygen-containing gas, for example, steam,
an inert gas, and fuel gas to the fluidization distributor, and/or a
steam source for optionally supplying steam to the fuel distributor.
The regenerator can further include an air preheater for heating air
prior to introduction through the air distributor, for example, during a
start-up.</p><p num="0020">Another aspect of the present invention is providing a method
of converting an original FCC unit of side by side configuration to a
converted FCC unit for processing light feedstock. In this method,
the original FFC unit has at least an original regenerator, an angled
spent catalyst supply line attached to the spent catalyst inlet, and a 
catalyst slide valve in the angled supply line. The regenerator has a
spent catalyst inlet, an air inlet and an air distribution assembly
attached to the air inlet within and near the bottom of the
regenerator. The conversion involves replacing the original
regenerator with a regenerator according to the present invention.</p><p num="0021">In one embodiment of such a conversion according to the
present invention, the method includes removing the air supply
assembly of the regenerator. A centerwell is installed on the interior
bottom of the regenerator. A fluidization gas inlet and at least one
fuel inlet is provided through the bottom of the regenerator within the
centerwell. A fluidization gas distribution ring is installed and
connected to the fluidization gas inlet. At least one fuel distribution
nozzle is connected to a corresponding fuel inlet at the interior
bottom of the regenerator within the centerwell. An air inlet is
provided through the regenerator outside of the centerwell. A
deflector plate is installed within the centerwell. An internal pipe is
installed and connected to the spent catalyst supply inlet. The
internal pipe has an angled portion at a similar angle to that of the
angled spent catalyst supply line, a standpipe portion and an annular
plate attached to the standpipe portion. The lower end of the
standpipe portion extends into the centerwell creating a radial slot
between the annular plate and the top edge of the centerwell. The
lower end of the standpipe portion is spaced above the deflector
plate to allow flow of spent catalyst through the standpipe portion
and provide deflection of the spent catalyst flow direction for mixing
the spent catalyst with fuel oil that is vaporized within the centerwell
when the modified FCC unit is operated. An air distribution pipe is 
installed around the centerwell and below the radial slot and
connected to the air inlet.</p><heading><u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u></heading><p num="0022"><sl><li>Fig. 1 is a simplified schematic process flow diagram of an
FCC unit, including an oil quench tower, used to crack light
hydrocarbons, according to one embodiment of the invention.</li><li>Fig. 2 is an enlarged elevation of a lower portion of the
regenerator of Fig. 1 for regenerating catalyst in a light FCC unit
using slurry of the fines from the filter backwash of the oil quench
tower according to the present invention.</li><li>Fig. 3 is a plan of the regenerator of Fig. 2 as seen along the
lines 3-3 in Fig. 2.</li><li>Fig. 4 (prior art) is an enlarged elevation of a lower portion of a
regenerator having a side entry for catalyst used for regenerating
catalyst in a conventional side by side FCC unit.</li><li>Fig. 5 is an enlarged elevation of a lower portion of another
embodiment of a regenerator according to the present invention for
regenerating catalyst in a light or conventional FCC unit in a side by
side configuration.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0023">The present invention is a method and system for recovering
fines from the light FCC effluent and regenerating spent catalyst. As
used in the specification and claims, a light FCC unit or process is
one in which the hydrocarbon feedstock to the FCC riser has a very
low resid content such that there is insufficient carbon deposited on
the catalyst to sustain combustion for regeneration without a
supplemental fuel source, and there is insufficient fuel oil in the riser 
effluent for conventional slurry oil recovery, i.e. less than 2 weight
percent of the hydrocarbons in the reactor effluent gases from the
riser have an atmospheric boiling point above 550°F (288°C).
However, if this amount is greater than 2 weight percent, the filters
can optionally be bypassed and this material used as the slurry. The
FCC process encompasses a fluidized catalytic reaction system,
converting a light hydrocarbon feed stream preferably having a high
olefin content to a product slate rich in propylene and ethylene. The
typical propylene/ethylene product ratio from the reactor can be
approximately 2.0. The FCC reactor is very flexible in that it can
process many olefin-rich streams which may be available from an
olefins plant or a refinery, such as, for example, olefins plant C<sub>4</sub>/C<sub>5</sub>
streams, refinery C<sub>4</sub>'s, light naphtha produced in thermal or catalytic
cracking processes, or the like.</p><p num="0024">With reference to Fig. 1, a superheated feed, typically at
800°F, is introduced via line 100 to the riser 102 where it is mixed
with hot regenerated catalyst supplied via line 104. If desired, steam
can also be injected into the riser 102 at this point. Reaction
conditions in the riser 102 are maintained as described in U.S.
Patents 5,043,522; 5,171,921; and 6,118,035; each of which is
hereby incorporated herein by reference in its entirety. The
hydrocarbon gases and catalyst flow upward in the riser 102, where
the cracking reactions take place. The hydrocarbon gases and
catalyst are separated in a series of conventional cyclones 106, 108,
and the product gases at a typical temperature of 1100-1200°F are
routed out of the top of the stripper vessel 110 via line 112. </p><p num="0025">The effluent gases in line 112 can be cooled to generate
steam in a waste heat boiler (not shown), and then are routed to a
quench tower 114 where entrained catalyst is washed from the
gases by contact with circulating quench oil. Overhead vapor from
the tower 114 in line 116 at a typical temperature of 200-400°F is
then routed to conventional product recovery facilities such as
distillation towers (not shown) for recovery of ethylene, propylene
and other products.</p><p num="0026">Catalyst separated by the cyclones 106,108 is collected at the
bottom of the stripper 110 and contacted with steam (not shown) to
strip residual hydrocarbon gas from the catalyst. The steam and
hydrocarbons exit the stripper 110 with the other effluent gases
through the cyclone 108 and line 112 as previously mentioned.</p><p num="0027">The catalyst then flows down through standpipe 118 into the
subjacent regenerator 120. In the regenerator 120, the small
amount of coke that has formed on the catalyst is burned in the
dense phase bed 122 and catalyst activity is restored for
recirculation to the riser 102 via line 104 as previously mentioned.
Because there is insufficient coke to provide the necessary heat of
reaction to sustain regeneration at a typical regeneration
temperature of 1250-1350°F, additional fuel is necessary to
complete the heat balance on the reactor system. The fuel is
preferably in the form of fuel oil, e.g. pyrolysis fuel oil, that contains
catalyst fines from the quench tower 114 as described in more detail
below, but capability for adding fuel gas can also be provided to
supplement the heating if desired. The slurry is continuously 
supplied to the regenerator 120 from the slurry surge drum 124 via
line 126, which is designed for mitigating potential erosion.</p><p num="0028">Accessory systems include conventional FCC systems such
as, for example, air supply, catalyst hoppers and flue gas handling
and heat recovery. An air compressor (not shown) supplies air via
line 128 for regeneration of the catalyst. An air heater (not shown)
can be provided for startup. Fresh and spent catalyst hoppers (not
shown) are provided for storage of makeup and used/equilibrium
catalyst that is typically respectively added to or taken from the
regenerator, as is well known in the art.</p><p num="0029">In the regenerator 120, catalyst is separated from the flue gas
in one or more cyclones 130. If desired, a conventional third stage
separator cyclone (not shown) can be used to minimize catalyst
losses. The flue gases are typically cooled by superheating high
pressure steam and vented. Spent catalyst, including fines from the
third stage separator, contain no or only trace amounts of poisons
found in typical refinery FCC catalyst due to the relatively cleaner
feedstocks used in the light olefin FCC process, and can be used as
an adjunct in concrete or brick manufacture or disposed in landfill.</p><p num="0030">The quench tower 114 includes a vapor-liquid contacting zone
130, which can include conventional packing or trays, disposed
above a liquid holdup zone 132. Effluent gas from line 112 is
introduced below the contacting zone 130. A recirculation loop 134
includes pump 136, heat exchanger 138 and return line 140 to
introduce a continuous supply of quench oil to liquid distributor 142
above the contacting zone 130. In the contacting zone 130, the
catalyst fines in the effluent gas are washed into the quench oil, and 
the effluent gas is cooled. The effluent gas typically enters the
quench tower 114 at 800-1000°F, and exits at 200-400°F. The
quench oil can be maintained in holdup zone 132 at a temperature of
350-700°F, and cooled to 300-550°F in exchanger 138 against a
feedstock stream or steam.</p><p num="0031">If desired, the quench tower 114 can include a secondary
cooling zone 144 above the primary contacting zone 130, similarly
configured with pumparound loop 146 that includes exchanger 148
for further cooling the quench oil to 200-450°F, for example. A
portion of the quench oil from collection zone 150 can be introduced
via line 152 into line 112 to provide initial cooling of the effluent
gases in mixing zone 154 upstream from the quench tower 114. For
example, 500-550°F quench oil in line 152 can cool the effluent
gases to 800-1000°F in the mixing zone 154.</p><p num="0032">A filtration loop 156 includes pump 158, filters 160a, 160b and
line 162 for returning filtrate to the quench tower 114, either directly
or via the recirculation loop 134. Backwash gaseous medium is
provided via line 164 to pressurize and flush the collected fines into
line 166 and slurry drum 124. The backwash gaseous medium can
be selected from an inert gas, air and fuel gas. One of the filters
160a or 160b is in filter mode, while the other is in backwash mode.
For example, valves 168, 170, 172 and 174 are open and valves
175, 176, 180 and 182 are closed when filter 160a is filtering and
filter 160b is being backwashed; the valves are switched after the
fines have accumulated in filter 160a and it is ready for backwashing.
The filtration is preferably continuous and should be at a rate that
keeps the fines level from building to excessive levels in the quench 
oil, preferably no more than 0.5 weight percent fines, more preferably
no more than 0.2 weight percent, and yet more preferably no more
than 0.1 weight percent fines in the quench oil. As an illustrative
example, in a quench tower receiving 50 to 200 lbs/hr catalyst fines
in the effluent gas, for example, 100 lbs/hr, then 50,000 lbs/hr of
quench oil must be filtered in order to maintain a catalyst
concentration of 0.2 weight percent in the recirculation loop 134</p><p num="0033">The backwash contains a high concentration of catalyst fines,
on the order of 10 to 20 weight percent. This concentration is
reduced to a manageable level, for example, 2 to 4 weight percent,
by dilution with fuel oil and/or circulating quench oil in the slurry drum
124. The amount of dilution oil is preferably equal to that required
for combustion in the regenerator. If the fines concentration is in
excess of a manageable level, additional fuel oil and/or quench oil
can be introduced to the slurry drum 124 and this excess can be
recycled to the riser via line 127.</p><p num="0034">If desired, the compressed gas can conveniently pressurize
the drum 124 so that it is not necessary to employ a pump to transfer
the slurry into the regenerator 120 via line 126. As mentioned,
quench oil slurry from the drum 124 is supplied to the regenerator
120 for combustion to supply the heating requirements and return
the catalyst to the regenerator-riser system; however, if there is
excess slurry, it can also be introduced to the riser 102 via line 127.
In this manner, the quench oil in the slurry supplied to the riser 102 is
added to the effluent gases via cyclones 106, 108 and subsequently
condensed in the quench tower 114, whereas the entrained catalyst 
is eventually transferred into the regenerator 120 with the other
catalyst recovered from the cyclones 106, 108.</p><p num="0035">In the regenerator 120 (see Figs. 2 and 3), there is a standpipe
118 and plug valve 200. Spent catalyst flows down the standpipe
118 and passes through the catalyst plug valve 200. After passing
through the plug valve 200, the catalyst changes direction and flows
upwardly through the annulus 202 of the spent catalyst centerwell
204 using a fluidization gas introduced via line 125 to distribution ring
204b positioned in the centerwell 204 below the valve 200. The
fluidization medium or gas can be, for example, steam, an inert gas,
and fuel gas. Slurry oil (line 126) and a fluidization gas (line 123) are
introduced through nozzles 204a. The fluidization gas, for example,
steam, facilitates dispersion and atomization of the slurry oil as it
discharges into the catalyst in the centerwell 204. The dispersion
steam and the slurry oil, which vaporizes on contact with the hot
spent catalyst, provide additional fluidization for the catalyst. At this
point, vaporization of the slurry oil is required. An oxygen-containing
gas is preferably not used as the fluidization gas here in order to
avoid, or at least minimize, combustion within the centerwell 204.
The catalyst is diverted outwardly into the dense phase bed 122 from
the circular slot 206 defined by the upper terminus of the centerwell
204 and an outer periphery of annular plate 208. The annular plate
208 is secured about the standpipe 118 and preferably has an outer
diameter at least that of the centerwell 204. In this manner the
catalyst is distributed radially outwardly into the dense phase catalyst
bed 122 well below its upper surface 209. </p><p num="0036">The dense fluidized bed 122 is aerated by air provided by an
air grid that preferably takes the form of air distribution ring 210. The
ring 210 has a diameter between the outer diameter of the centerwell
204 and the outer diameter of the dense phase bed 122 in the
regenerator 120. As the aeration air travels upward from
perforations or nozzles 211 into the dense phase bed 122, the slurry
oil and the carbon on the catalyst are burned to form CO<sub>2</sub>. It is
important to introduce the slurry oil/catalyst mixture into the dense
phase bed 122 in relatively close proximity to the air and below the
upper surface 209 of the bed 122 to ensure good combustion and
heat generation within the bed 122. Typically, the regenerator 120 is
operated at 1250 to 1350°F, preferably from 1275 to 1325°F. The
convergence of the air from the ring 210 and the catalyst/oil mixture
from the slot 206 at relatively high velocities within the dense phase
bed 122 facilitates good mixing in a combustion zone within the bed
122 to provide uniform heating and regeneration of the catalyst. The
regenerator bed should be designed for a superficial vapor velocity
of between 0.5 and 7 ft/s, preferably between 1.5 and 5 ft/s, and
more preferably between 2 and 3 ft/s. The volume of the bed 122
above the air ring 210 should be designed for sufficient residence
time to ensure essentially complete regeneration of the catalyst.</p><p num="0037">Off gas is conventionally recovered overhead from the
regenerator 120 via separator cyclones 130 and an overhead line
212 (see Fig. 1). Since the regenerator 120 is operated in a
complete combustion mode, there is generally no need for a CO
burner to convert the CO to CO<sub>2</sub> before discharge to the
atmosphere, but one can be included if desired. More heat of 
combustion is generated, and hence less fuel oil is needed, when
complete combustion is achieved. Excess air is generally avoided,
but as a practical matter a slight excess is needed to achieve
complete combustion.</p><p num="0038">The regenerator 120 can be operated with or without a CO
promoter, typically a catalyst such as platinum, which is commonly
added to promote the conversion of CO to CO<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0039">The lower portion of a prior art side by side conventional FCC
regenerator is shown in Fig. 4. Catalyst is fed to the regenerator via
an angled pipe 414, a catalyst slide valve 416, and an inlet 420. The
ends of a pair of hydroclones 430 extend below the upper surface
209 of the dense bed 122. Combustion air is fed into the dense bed
122 via an air feed apparatus 409.</p><p num="0040">The regenerator 400 shown in Fig. 5 is according to the
present invention and is useful in a FCC unit having a side by side
configuration and can be substituted for the regenerator shown in
Fig.4. Whether in a new installation or as part of a retrofit, such a
regenerator 400 provides greater feed versatility to accept
conventional or light feeds, since a fuel oil, quench oil or slurry oil
feed capability is provided when processing light FCC feeds in order
to provide the necessary heat of reaction.</p><p num="0041">The angled pipe 414 for catalyst feed no longer terminates at
the inlet 420 as shown in Fig. 4. Rather, angled pipe 414 is coupled
via the catalyst slide valve 416 to angled pipe 417 that extends
therefrom substantially to the vertical center axis of the regenerator
400 and has a vertical stand portion 418 extending therefrom into the
centerwell 204. A circular deflection plate 450 is located below the 
lower end of the stand portion 418 to redirect the catalyst flowing
therethrough. The remaining components having like reference
numerals are as in the previous figures.</p><p num="0042">Further, an FCC unit of side-by-side configuration having a
conventional regenerator, for example, the regenerator shown in Fig.
4, can be converted to be a converted FCC unit having a regenerator
400 as shown in Fig. 5, thereby reducing the capital costs associated
with the fabrication of a new regenerator. The air supply assembly
460 would be removed. The centerwell 204, fluidization medium
distribution ring 204b and fuel distribution nozzles 204a would be
installed at the interior base of the regenerator within the centerwell
204. The air distribution pipe 210 would be installed around the
centerwell 204 and below the radial slot 206. The deflector plate 450
would be installed within the centerwell 204. Pipe 417 with the
standpipe portion 418 and annular plate 208 would be installed such
that the end of the stand portion 418 extends into the centerwell 204
a sufficient distance above the deflector plate 450 to allow flow of the
catalyst and provide adequate deflection of the catalyst flow direction
for mixing the catalyst with the fuel oil vaporized within the centerwell
204. The hydroclones 430 may or may not have to be replaced or
reconditioned or repositioned within the regenerator 400 such that
their ends extend below the upper surface 209 of the dense bed 122.</p><p num="0043">The present invention is illustrated above with respect to
specific embodiments. Various changes and modifications will occur
to the skilled artisan in view thereof. It is intended that all such
modifications within the scope and spirit of the appended claims be
embraced thereby. </p><p num="0044">A catalyst regenerator for regenerating spent light FCC catalyst
and heating the catalyst to supply heat to an FCC reactor. The
regenerator has discharge outlets for catalyst and off gas and a valve
for introducing spent catalyst through a central stand pipe portion.
The regenerator houses a dense phase catalyst bed. A centerwell
receives a lower end of the standpipe portion and defines an annulus
therebetween. The spent catalyst is introduced through the standpipe
portion into the annulus. A fuel distributor introduces fuel into the
centerwell for mixing with the catalyst in the annulus. A fluidization
distributor introduces fluidization gas into the centerwell for fluidizing
the catalyst in the annulus. A radial slot in the centerwell introduces
the catalyst and fuel mixture from the annulus below the upper
surface of the dense phase bed. An air distributor located below the
radial slot introduces combustion air into the dense phase bed.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A catalyst regenerator for regenerating spent light FCC catalyst
and heating the catalyst to supply heat to an FCC reactor,
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a regenerator vessel housing a dense phase catalyst
bed;</claim-text><claim-text>a central upright standpipe portion for receiving the spent
catalyst to be regenerated;</claim-text><claim-text>a centerwell receiving a lower end of the standpipe
portion and defining an annulus between the standpipe portion
and an inside diameter of the centerwell;</claim-text><claim-text>a valve for introducing spent catalyst through the
standpipe portion into the annulus;</claim-text><claim-text>a fuel distributor for introducing fuel into the centerwell for
mixing with the catalyst in the annulus;</claim-text><claim-text>a fluidization distributor for introducing fluidization gas
into the centerwell for fluidizing the catalyst in the annulus;</claim-text><claim-text>a radial slot formed in the centerwell for introducing the
catalyst and fuel mixture from the annulus into the dense phase
bed below an upper surface thereof;</claim-text><claim-text>an air distributor disposed in the dense phase bed
subjacent to the radial slot for introducing combustion air into
the dense phase bed;</claim-text><claim-text>a catalyst discharge outlet in fluid communication with the
dense phase bed; and</claim-text><claim-text>an off gas discharge outlet in fluid communication with a
dilute phase above the dense phase bed.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The regenerator of claim 1 wherein the air distributor is an air
distribution ring disposed in the dense phase bed about the
centerwell subadjacent to the radial slot.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The regenerator of claim 1 wherein the fuel distributor is at least
one nozzle.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The regenerator of claim 1 further comprising a source of fuel
oil for supplying fuel oil to the fuel distributor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The regenerator of claim 1 further comprising a fluidization gas
source for supplying fluidization gas to the fluidization
distributor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The regenerator of claim 5 wherein the fluidization gas is steam.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The regenerator of claim 1 further comprising a steam source
for supplying steam to the fuel distributor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The regenerator of claim 1 wherein the valve is located at a
lower end of the standpipe portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The regenerator of claim 8 wherein the standpipe portion is a
lower end of a central vertical standpipe located within the
regenerator.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The regenerator of claim 1, wherein the regenerator has an
angled spent catalyst supply line extending into the regenerator
and the valve is located in the angled spent catalyst line prior to
entering the regenerator and the standpipe portion extends from
the angled spent catalyst supply line within the regenerator.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The regenerator of claim 10 wherein the standpipe portion is
attached to the end of angled spent catalyst line.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A method of converting an original FCC unit of side by side
configuration to a converted FCC unit for processing light
feedstock comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing the original FFC unit having at least
   an original regenerator having
      a spent catalyst inlet,
      an air inlet and
      an air distribution assembly attached to the air inlet
within and near a bottom of the regenerator,
      an angled spent catalyst supply line attached to the
spent catalyst inlet, and
      a catalyst slide valve in the angled supply line, and</claim-text><claim-text>replacing the original regenerator with a regenerator
according to Claim 1.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A method of converting an original FCC unit of side by side
configuration to a converted FCC unit for processing light
feedstock comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing the original FFC unit having at least
   an original regenerator having
      a spent catalyst inlet,
      an air inlet and
      an air supply assembly attached to the air inlet
within and near a bottom of the regenerator,
   an angled spent catalyst supply line attached to the
spent catalyst inlet, and
   a catalyst slide valve in the angled supply line;</claim-text><claim-text>removing the air supply assembly;</claim-text><claim-text>installing a centerwell to the interior bottom of the
regenerator;</claim-text><claim-text>providing a fluidization gas inlet and at least one fuel inlet
through the bottom of the regenerator within the
centerwell;</claim-text><claim-text>installing a fluidization gas distribution ring connected to
the fluidization gas inlet and at least one fuel
distribution nozzle connected to the corresponding at
least one fuel inlet at the interior bottom of the
regenerator within the centerwell;</claim-text><claim-text>providing an air inlet through the regenerator outside of
the centerwell;</claim-text><claim-text>installing a deflector plate within the centerwell;</claim-text><claim-text>installing an internal pipe connected to the spent catalyst
supply inlet,
   wherein the internal pipe has an angled portion at a
similar angle to that of the angled spent catalyst
supply line, a standpipe portion and an annular
plate attached to the standpipe portion,
   wherein a lower end of the standpipe portion extends
into the centerwell creating a radial slot between
the annular plate and a top edge of the centerwell,
and
   wherein the lower end of the standpipe portion is
spaced above the deflector plate to allow flow of
spent catalyst through the standpipe portion and
provide deflection of the spent catalyst flow
direction for mixing the spent catalyst with fuel oil
that is vaporized within the centerwell when the
modified FCC unit is operated; and</claim-text><claim-text>installing an air distribution pipe around the centerwell
and below the radial slot and connected to the air
inlet.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>