<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1334710-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1334710" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="27609590" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030813"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1334710-A1" status="new" fvid="23819830"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1334710</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030813</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02255880-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02255880</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020822</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-5845502-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5845502</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020129</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   6/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   6/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   6/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   6/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   6/083       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K   6/00B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K   6/00B3</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K   6/083B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Wässrige enzymatische Haftmittel für Zahnprothesen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Aqueous enzymatic denture adhesives</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Compositions adhesives pour prothese dentaire aqueuses et enzymatiques</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-4564519-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4564519</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5176899-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5176899</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5453284-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5453284</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5989526-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5989526</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LACLEDE INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LACLEDE, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Laclede, Inc.</last-name><address><street>2030 East University Drive</street><city>Rancho Dominguez, California 90220</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KANG HARJINDER</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PELLICO MICHAEL A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KANG, HARJINDER</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PELLICO, MICHAEL A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KANG, HARJINDER</last-name><address><street>c/0 Laclede 2030 East University Drive</street><city>Rancho Dominguez CA 90220</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PELLICO, MICHAEL A.</last-name><address><street>314 Palisades Avenue</street><city>Santa Monica, CA 90402</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Matthews, Howard Nicholas</last-name><address><street>Prentice &amp;amp; Matthews, Calvert's Buildings, 52 B Borough High Street</street><city>London SE1 1XN</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Hydro-activated and/or oxygen activated aqueous, enzymatic,
antimicrobial denture adhesive compositions are stabilized against enzymatic
action prior to oral application of the adhesive by incorporating a thickener into
the adhesive formulation so as to provide the forrmulation with an enzyme
immobilizing viscosity which inhibits enzymatic action during processing and in
the adhesive package. An illustrative, thickened, enzymatic adhesive with this
enhancement contains glucose oxidase, glucose, lactoperoxidase and
potassium thiocyanate together with a mixture of polyacrylic acid and
polyvinylpyrrolidone in an amount to provide the adhesive with a viscosity of at
least about 300,000 centipoises.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>1. <u style="single">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to enzymatic denture adhesive compositions and,
more particulary, to stabilized, aqueous, enzymatic denture adhesives, which,
upon oral application, produce an anti-bacterial and bacteriostatic effect in the
oral cavity by activation of the enzyme system within the adhesive.</p><p num="0002">Denture adhesives are used by denture wearers to secure loose fitting
dentures. When a denture is first made, it fits tightly in the mouth. However, with
the passage of time, the mouth changes and the denture often becomes less
secure, with loss of the initial tight fit.</p><p num="0003">When this occurs, the patient has three choices: (a) obtain a new
denture, (b) reline the old denture, or (c) use a denture adhesive. For those who
choose denture adhesives, there are diverse products from which a selection
can be made. These include powders, gels, pastes, and sheets. The adhesives
are based on water soluble gums and polymers such as carboxymethyl
cellulose, gum arcacia, gum tragacanth, poly(ethylene oxide),
polyvinylpyrrolidone, vinyl methyl ether maleic anhydride, polyacrylamides,
acetic polyvinyl compounds, polyacrylic acid derivates and the like.</p><p num="0004">The most common denture adhesives are those sold as pastes. The
pastes are usually a combination of gums and powders combined with oil
and/or other vehicle. The denture wearer squeezes the paste from a dispensing
tube onto the denture which is then fitted into the mouth. Denture powders
based on gums and/or polymers are also widely used by sprinkling the powder
onto the denture which is then positioned in the mouth. Denture adhesives are
also sold as sheets or films prepared from gums or polymers. </p><p num="0005">Regardless of the physical form of these adhesives, they all require
contact with water to become effective. It is only when the gums and polymers
become wet that they develop their adhesive properties. Normally, these
adhesives work very well in the mouth. However, for denture wearers who
suffer from dry mouth (xerostomia), dentures adesives work poorly or not at all
because there is insufficient saliva to activate these adhesives, Also, because
saliva is naturally antibacterial, people who suffer from dry mouth have an
increased risk of periodontal disease, cavities and mouth odors.</p><p num="0006">The invention herein is directed to water-based denture adhesive
compositions which incorporate (a) a hydro-activated anti-bacterial enzyme
system and (b) a thickener so as to provide the composition with an enzyme
immobilizing visvosity to inhibit enzymatic action during processing and in the
denture adhesive package prior to oral application. The aqueous denture
adhesive, with its anti-bacterial system, is particularly well suited for denture
wearers who suffer from impaired saliva flow and provides those denture users
with oral protection that would otherwise be present with normal saliva flow.</p><heading>2. <u style="single">RELATED ART</u></heading><heading>2A. <u style="single">ENZYME SYSTEMS</u></heading><p num="0007">It is disclosed in the prior art that enzymatic anti-bacterial systems,
predicated on oxidoreductase enzymes such as glucose oxidase, can be
incorporated into oral care products and other products such as powder milk
(U.S. Patent No. 4,617,190) and bandages (U.S. Patent No. 4,576,817) for
producing an anti-bacterial effect in a defined environment.</p><p num="0008">U.S. Pat. No. 4,150,113 (Hoogendoorn et al., 1979) and U.S. Pat. No.
4,178,362 (Hoogendorn et al., 1979) disclose, respectively, an enzymatic
toothpaste and an enzymatic chewable dentifrice containing glucose oxidase 
which acts on glucose present in saliva and tooth plaque to produce hydrogen
peroxide. The patentees note that oral bacteria, through enzyme systems
having SH-Groups, effect glycolysis of food products containing sugars and
point out that lactoperoxidase, which is present in saliva, provides the means
for transferring oxygen from hydrogen peroxide to oral bacteria resulting in the
oxidation of the SH-containing enzymes into inactive disulfide enzymes. It is
further disclosed that the dentifrice may be formulated with potassium
thiocyanate.</p><p num="0009">U.S. Pat. No. 4,269, 822 (Pellico et al., 1981) discloses an antiseptic
dentifrice containing an oxidizable amino acid substrate and an oxidoreductase
enzyme specific to such substrate for producing hydrogen peroxide and
ammonia upon oral application of the dentifrice, with pre-application stability
being maintained by limiting the quantity of any water present in the dentifrice.</p><p num="0010">U.S. Pat No. 4, 537, 764 (Pellico et al., 1985) discloses an enzymatic
dentifrice containing Beta-D-glucose and glucose oxidase for producing
hydrogen peroxide upon oral application of the dentifrice, with pre-application
stability being maintained by limiting any water in the dentifrice to not more than
about 10 wt.% based on the weight of the dentifrice.</p><p num="0011">U.S. Pat. No. 4,564,519 (Pellico et al., 1986) discloses a di-enzymatic
chewable dentifrice which contains, for example, glucose and glucose oxidase
for producing hydrogen peroxide upon chewing the dentifrice and further
contains a thiocyanate salt and lactoperoxidase for interacting with hydrogen
peroxide to produce a hypothiocyanate (sic) bacterial inhibitor, with pre-application
stability being maintained by limiting any unbound water in the
chewable dentifrice to an amount not more than about 1.0 wt.% and limiting the
total water, bound and unbound, to not more than about 10 wt.%. </p><p num="0012">U.S. Pat. No. 4,578,365 (Pellico et al., 1986) discloses a di-enzymatic
dentifrice which contains, for example, glucose and glucose oxidase for
producing hydrogen peroxide upon oral application of the dentifrice and further
contains a thiocyanate salt and lactoperoxidase for interacting with hydrogen
peroxide to produce a hypothiocyanate (sic) with pre-application stability being
maintained by limiting any water in the dentifrice to not more than about 10
wt.% based on the weight of the dentifrice.</p><p num="0013">U. S. Patent No. 5,176,899 (Montgomery, 1993) discloses an aqueous
enzymatic dentifrice which contains, for example, Beta-D-Glucose and glucose
oxidase for producing hydrogen peroxide upon oral application of the dentifrice
and, optionally, contains a thiocyanate salt and lactoperoxidase for interacting
with hydrogen peroxide to produce a hypothiocyanite (OSCN-) bacteriostatic
agent, with pre-application stability being maintained by processing and
packaging the dentifrice under vacuum conditions so as to limit the level of
dissolved oxygen in the dentifrice.</p><p num="0014">U.S. Pat. No. 5,336,494 (Pellico, 1994) discloses an orally chewable,
enzymatically coated pet product which contains, for example, Beta-D-glucose
and glucose oxidase for producing hydrogen peroxide upon oral chewing of the
product and may further contain a peroxidase and an alkali metal salt of an
oxygen accepting anion such as potassium iodide for interacting with hydrogen
peroxide to produce hypoiodite, an anionic bacterial inhibitor.</p><p num="0015">U.S. Pat. No. 5,453,284 (Pellico, 1995) discloses an aqueous enzymatic
dentifrice having a water content in excess of 10 wt. % and which contains, for
example, Beta-D-glucose and glucose oxidase for producing hydrogen
peroxide upon oral application of the dentifrice and may further contain a
peroxidase and an oxidizable alkali metal salt such as the thiocyanate, 
chloride or iodide salt of sodium or potassium for interacting with hydrogen
peroxide to produce an anionic bacterial inhibitor, with pre-application stability
being maintained by the addition of a water soluble thickener in an amount to
provide the dentifrice with a viscosity from about 800 to about 75,000
centipoises.</p><heading>2B. <u style="single">DENTURE ADHESIVES</u></heading><p num="0016">U.S. Patent No. 4,518,721 (Dhabhar et al., 1985) discloses a
hydrophillic denture adhesive containing sodium carboxymethylcellulose,
poly(ethylene oxide), polyethylene glycol and glycerin.</p><p num="0017">U.S. Patent No. 4,804,412 (Komiyama, 1989) discloses a denture
adhesive containing polyvinyl acetate and polypropylene oxide and which may
further include other ingredients such as enzymes, as for example, dextranase,
mutanase, levanase and in(s)ulinase.</p><p num="0018">U.S. Patent No. 5,760,102 (Hall et al., 1998) discloses an aqueous
denture adhesive containing aloe extract, polyvinylpyrrolidone,
hydroxyethylcellulose, hydrogen peroxide and water.</p><p num="0019">U.S. Patent No. 6,294,594 (Borja, 2001) discloses a denture cream
formulation containing polyvinylpyrrolidone, poly(ethylene oxide),
carboxymethylcellulose, mineral oil, petrolatum, polyacrylic acid derivative,
silicon dioxide, flavor and dye.</p><p num="0020">Each of the foregoing patent references is incorporated herein by
reference thereto.</p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0021">In accordance with this invention, there is provided an aqueous
enzymatic denture adhesive having a water content of at least about 10 wt. % and
containing, per gram of adhesive, from about 0.015 to about 0.6 millimole of 
oxidizable substrate and from about 0.5 to about 5,000 International Units of
oxidoreductase enzyme specific to such substrate for producing hydrogen
peroxide upon oral application of the adhesive, and further containing non-toxic,
ambient, water soluble thickener in an amount to provide the adhesive
with a viscosity from about 300,000 to about 1,900,000 to therby stabilize the
adhesive against the production of hydrogen peroxide prior to oral application
of the adhesive.</p><heading><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</u></heading><p num="0022">The invention described herein is directed to the use of thickener in
aqueous denture adhesive compositions containing hydro-activated and/or
oxygen activated anti-bacterial enzyme system to thereby provide a viscosity
which inhibits the enzymatic reaction prior to oral application of the adhesive.</p><p num="0023">The thickeners which can be used in the practice of this invention
comprise non-toxic, water soluble hydrocolloids and synthetic polymers as, for
example, (a) water soluble gums such as gum arabic, gum tragacanth, gum
karaya or gum guar; (b) microbial fermentation hydrocolloids such as xanthan
gum; (c) starch derivatives such as high viscosity starch or hydrogenated starch;
(d) cellulose derivatives such as sodium carboxymethylcellulose or
hydroxymethylcellulose; and (e) synthetic polymers/gums including (i) vinyl
polymers such as polyvinylpyrrolidone, polyviny lalcohol and carboxyvinyl
polymer, (ii) acrylic polymers such as polyacrylic acid and polyacrylamide, and
(iii) ethylene oxide polymers. A particular effective thickener is a combination of
polyacrylic acid and polyvinylpyrrolidone which may be further enhanced by the
presence of hydrogenated starch.</p><p num="0024">The thickener is generally present in an amount to provide the enzymatic
denture adhesive with a viscosity from about 300,000 to about 1,900,000 
centipoises, with an intermediate amount being so selected as to provide the
adhesive with a viscosity from about 400,000 to about 1,750,000 centipoises,
and a preferred amount being so selected as to provide the adhesive with a
viscosity from about 600,000 to about 1,600,000 centipoises. Viscosity
determinations can be made by utilizing a suitable viscometer in accordance
with applicable procedures well known in the art.</p><p num="0025">The enzymatic component of the therapeutic composition comprises a
first enzyme system containing an oxidizable substrate and an
oxidoreductase enzyme specific to such substrate for producing hydrogen
peroxide upon oral application of the adhesive, with the chemical environment
of the oral cavity providing the source of additional reactant (oxygen) or
reactants (oxygen, water) to effect the enzymatic reaction. Illustrative examples
of oxidoreductase enzymes and their corresponding oxidizable substrates are
set forth in the following table:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">OXIDOREDUCTASE ENZYME</entry><entry align="left">OXIDIZABLE SUBSTRATE</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glucose oxidase</entry><entry align="left">B-D-glucose</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hexose Oxidase</entry><entry align="left">Hexose</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Galactose Oxidase</entry><entry align="left">D-galactose</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pyranose Oxidase</entry><entry align="left">Pyranose</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pyruvate Oxidase</entry><entry align="left">Pyruvate</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oxalate Oxidase</entry><entry align="left">Oxalate</entry></row><row><entry align="left">DL-Aminoacid Oxidase</entry><entry align="left">DL-Aminoacid</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0026">In an illustrative reaction, glucose oxidase catalyzes the interaction of
Beta-D-glucose, water and oxygen during oral application of the adhesive 
to produce hydrogen peroxide and gluconic acid.</p><p num="0027">Glucose oxidase is characterized in the literature as a glycoprotein
containing two molecules of flavine-adenine dinucleotide which has a
molecular weight of approximately 150,000, an isoelectric point at pH 4.2 and
an optimum pH at 5.5 with a broad pH range from 4 through 7.</p><p num="0028">The oxidizable substrate is generally present in the adhesive
composition in an amount from about 0.015 to about 0.6 millimole per gram of
adhesive composition and, preferably, in an amount from about
0.025 to about 0.1 millimole per gram of adhesive composition while the
oxidoreductase enzyme specific to the substrate is generally present in the
composition in an amount from about 0.5 to about 500 International Units
(herein sometimes abbreviated IU) per gram of composition, and, preferably, in
an amount from about 10 to about 40 IU per gram of composition. The term
millimole identifies that quantity in grams corresponding to the molecular weight
of the composition divided by one thousand. The term International Unit(s)
identifies that amount of enzyme that will effect catalysis of 1.0 micromole of
substrate per unit at pH 7.0 and 25 C. Oxidoreductase enzymes are supplied in
dry or liquid form with the label specifying the concentration in International
Units on a per gram or per milliliter, as appropriate.</p><p num="0029">In addition to the first enzyme system comprising oxidizable substrate
and oxidoreductase enzyme specific to such substrate for producing hydrogen
peroxide, the enzymatic adhesive composition of this invention is provided with
a second enzyme system containing a peroxidatic peroxidase and an alkali
metal salt of an oxygen accepting anion for interacting with hydrogen peroxide
to produce an oxidized anionic bacterial inhibitor.</p><p num="0030">Peroxidases which can be used in the practice of this invention include 
lactoperoxidase, horseradish peroxidase, iodide peroxidase, and
myeloperoxidase. Oxidizable salts which can be used in the practice of this
invention include, for example, the thiocyanate, chloride or iodide salt of
sodium, potassium, ammonium, calcium or magnesium or mixtures of such
salts. In the presence of hydrogen peroxide, the oxygen accepting anion of the
aforesaid salts, namely, thiocyanate, chloride or iodide, are oxidized to
hypothiocyanite, hypochlorite and hypoiodite, respetively.</p><p num="0031">Lactoperoxidase is a glycoprotein which, in one commercial
embodiment, is a lyophilized powder derived from milk. This commercial
peroxidase has an activity of 80 IU/mg and a projected molecular weight of
93,000 for L-Tyrosine lodination. The physical-chemical properties reported for
lactoperoxidase include: molecular weight 78,000; partial specific volume 0.74;
and heme/mole 1.0.</p><p num="0032">The peroxidase is generally present in the adhesive composition in an
amount from about 0.05 to about 20 International Units per gram of composition
and, preferably, in an amount from about 0.1 to about 1.0 International Units
per gram of composition while the oxidizable salt is generally present in the
composition in an amount from about 0.0001 to about 0.01 millimole per gram
of composition and, preferably, in an amount from about 0.001 to about 0.006
millimole per gram of composition.</p><p num="0033">The operable integrity of the enzymatic system can be affected by
catalase which is present in commercial glucose oxidase as well as mucous
membrane tissue. Catalase, which is extraneous to the enzymatic system of this
invention, competes with peroxidatic peroxidase for hydrogen peroxide. In
order to reduce loss of hydrogen peroxide through the presence of catalase, an
effective amount of enzymatic inhibitor specific to catalase can be 
advantageously incorporated into the enzymatic adhesive. An ascorbic salt
such as sodium ascorbate, potassium ascorbate, ascorbyl palmitate, or
mixtures thereof can be used as an enzymatic inhibitor which is specific to
catalase. An effective amount of ascorbate salt for catalase inhibition is from
about 0.000001 to about 0.0001 millimole per gram of adhesive composition.
Iron salts such as ferrous sulfate can be incorporated the enzymatic
composition as a potentiator for ascorbate salt in its role as catalase inhibitor.</p><p num="0034">The enzymatic adhesive compositions of this invention may
advantageously be formulated with an aminohexose as, for example, an
aminoglucose such as glucosamine, N-actyl glucosamine or mixtures thereof in
order to increase the yield or accumulation of oxidized anionic bacterial
inhibitor. The aminoglucose is generally present in the enzymatic composition
in an amount from about 0.0001 to about 0.002 millimole per gram of adhesive
and, preferably, in amount from about 0.003 to about 0.001 millimole per gram
of adhesive.</p><p num="0035">As As a result of the high viscosity of the enzymatic adhesives provided
by the thickeners, the adhesives can be formulated with water in excess of 10
wt. % without initiating an enzymatic reaction prior to oral application of the
adhesive. Water is generally present in the enzymatic adhesive in an amount
from about 10 wt. % to about 60 wt. %, with an intermediate amount being from
about 10 wt. % to about 50 wt. % and a preferred amount being from about 15
wt. % to about 35 wt. %.</p><p num="0036">In addition to the thickeners, enzyme system and water, the adhesive
compositions of this invention may contain typical formulating ingredients such
as humectants, buffering agents, fluorides, flavors, colors and sweeteners as
well as a variety of auxiliary adhesive components as described in the above 
identified patents, the disclosures of which are incorporated by reference,
together with the limitations as specified therein.</p><p num="0037">The enzymztic adhesives, in the form of a paste or gel, can be prepared
in any suitable manner as, for example, by blending the dry ingredients into the
liquid ingredients, with agitation, until a smooth mixture is obtained, with the
proviso that shear sensitive ingredients, which include the enzymes, are added
last to minize shear impact on such ingredients.</p><p num="0038">In accordance with this invention, it has now been found that
oxidoreductase enzyme stability can be maintained in an aqueous denture
adhesive that contains in excess of 10 wt. % water, as shown by the examples
hereinafter set forth, when a thickener is used in the aqueous adhesive so as to
provide a viscosity of at least about 300,000 centipoises.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0039">This example illustrates an aqueous, enzymatic denture adhesive
containing 10 wt. % water together with an enzyme system containing Beta-D-glucose,
glucose oxidase, lactoperoxidase and potassium thiocyanate.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Composition</entry><entry align="center">Weight, grams</entry></row> <row><entry align="left">Glycerine</entry><entry align="center">77.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">D.I. Water</entry><entry align="center">10.0000</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">Xanthan gum</entry> <entry align="center">4.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carboxymethylcellulose</entry><entry align="center">8.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lactoperoxidase (100 IU/mg)</entry><entry align="center">0.0005 (50 IU)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Beta-D-glucose</entry><entry align="center">1.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glucose oxidase (100 IU)</entry><entry align="center">0.0010 (100 IU)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium thiocyanate</entry><entry align="center">0.1500</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="center"><o ostyle="single">100.1515</o></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0040">The viscosity of this enzymatic adhesive is 300,000 centipoises
and the adhesive has an enzymatic shelf life in excess of 2 years. </p><heading>EXAMPLE 2</heading><p num="0041">This example illustrates an aqueous, enzymatic denture adhesive
containing 15 wt. % water together with an enzyme system containing Beta-D-glucose,
glucose oxidase, lactoperoxidase and potassium thiocyanate wherein
the thickener is a combination of polyacrylic acid (Carbopol 980) and
hydroxymethyl cellulose.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Composition</entry><entry align="left">Weight, grams</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glycerine</entry><entry align="center">42.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sorbitol (70 % solids, 30 % water)</entry><entry align="center">50.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbopol 980</entry><entry align="center">3.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hydroxymethylcellulose</entry><entry align="center">3.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Beta-D-glucose</entry><entry align="center">1.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lactoperoxidase (100 IU/mg)</entry><entry align="center">0.0005 (50 IU)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glucose oxidase (100 IU)</entry><entry align="center">0.0010 (100 IU)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium thiocyanate</entry><entry align="center">0.1500</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium hydroxide</entry><entry align="center">1.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="center"><o ostyle="single">100.1515</o></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0042">The viscosity of this enzymatic adhesive is 400,000 centipoises
and the adhesive has an enzymatic shelf life in excess of 3 years.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 3</heading><p num="0043">This example illustrates an aqueous, enzymatic denture adhesive
containing 10 wt. % water together with an enzyme system containing hexose,
hexose oxidase, myeloperoxidase and potassium thiocyanate wherein the
thickener is a combination of polyacrylic acid (Carbopol 980) and hydrogenated
starch.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Composition</entry><entry align="center">Weight, grams</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glycerine</entry><entry align="center">10.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">D.I. Water</entry><entry align="center">10.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hydrogenated starch</entry><entry align="center">67.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbopol 980</entry><entry align="center">4.0000 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hexose (100 IU/mg)</entry><entry align="center">7.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hexose oxidase (100 IU/mg)</entry><entry align="center">0.0001 (10 IU)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Myeloperoxidase (100 IUmg)</entry><entry align="center">0.0002 (100 IU)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium thiocyanate</entry><entry align="center">0.1500</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium hydroxide</entry><entry align="center">2.0000</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="center"><o ostyle="single">100.1503</o></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0044">The viscosity of this enzymatic adhesive is 600,000 centipoises
and the adhesive has an enzymatic shelf life in excess of 2 years.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 4</heading><p num="0045">This example illustrates an aqueous, enzymatic denture adhesive
containing 57 wt. % water together with an enzyme system containing Beta-D-glucose,
glucose oxidase, myeloperoxidase and potassium thiocyanate
wherein the thickener is a combination of polyacrylic acid (Carbopol 980) and
hydrogenated starch.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Composition</entry><entry align="center">Weight, grams</entry></row><row><entry align="left">D.I. Water</entry><entry align="center">57.000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hydrogenated starch</entry><entry align="center">27.000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbopol 980</entry><entry align="center">2.000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyvinylpyrrolidone</entry><entry align="center">8.000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Beta-D-glucose</entry><entry align="center">5.000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glucose oxidase (100/IU/mg)</entry><entry align="center">0.005 (500 IU)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Myeloperoxidase (100</entry><entry align="center">0.001 (100 IU)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium thiocyanate</entry><entry align="center">0.150</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium hydroxide</entry><entry align="center"><u style="single">1.000</u></entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="center">100.150</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0046">The viscosity of this enzymatic adhesive is 900,000 centipoises and the
adhesive has an enzymatic shelf life in excess of 2 years. </p><heading>EXAMPLE 5</heading><p num="0047">This example illustrates an aqueous, enzymatic denture adhesive
containing 14 wt. % water together with an enzyme system containing Beta-D-glucose,
glucose oxidase, lactoperoxidase and potassium iodide wherein the
thickener is a combination of hydrogenated starch, polyacrylic acid (Carbopol
980), and polyvinylpyrrolidone.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Composition</entry><entry align="center">Weight, grams</entry></row><row><entry align="left">D.I. Water</entry><entry align="center">14.000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glycerine</entry><entry align="center">14.000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hydrogenated starch</entry><entry align="center">62.500</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbopol 980</entry><entry align="center">1.000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyvinylpyrollidone</entry><entry align="center">8.000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium hydroxide</entry><entry align="center">0.050</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Beta-D-glucose</entry><entry align="center">0.050</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Glucose oxidase (100 IU/mg)</entry><entry align="center">0.008</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lactoperoxidase (100 IU/gm)</entry><entry align="center">0.010</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Potassium iodide</entry><entry align="center">0.004</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="center"><o ostyle="single">99.6184</o></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0048">The viscosity of this enzymatic adhesive is 1,900,000 centipoises
and the adhesive has an enzymatic shelf life in excess of 3 years.</p><p num="0049">Adjunct antibacterial agents such as the enzyme lysozyme and the
protein lactoferrin can also be added to the enzymatic formulations of this
invention.</p><p num="0050">In view of the foregoing description and examples, it will become
apparent to those of ordinary skill in the art that equivalent modifications thereof
may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of this invention.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An aqueous, enzymatic denture adhesive composition having a water
content of at least about 10 wt. % and containing, per gram of adhesive, from
about 0.015 to about 0.6 millimole of oxidizable substrate and from about 0.5
to about 5,000 International Units of oxidreductase enzyme specific to such
substrate for producing hydrogen peroxide upon oral application of the
adhesive; and
   further containing non-toxic, ambient, water soluble thickener in an
amount to provide the adhesive with a viscosity from about 300,000 to about
1,900,000 centipoises to thereby stabilize the adhesive against the production
of hydrogen peroxide prior to oral application of the adhesive.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 wherein the amount of water soluble
thickener is so selected as to provide the adhesive with a viscosity from about
400,000 to about 1,750,000 centipoises.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 wherein the amount of water soluble
thickener is so selected as to provide the adhesive with a viscosity from about
600,000 to about 1,600,000 centipoises.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 wherein the upper limit of the water
content is about 60 wt. %.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 wherein the water content is from
about 10 wt. % to about 50 wt. %.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 wherein the water content is from
about 15 wt. % to about 35 wt. %.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 wherein the water soluble thickener is
selected from natural and synthetic hydrolloids and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 wherein the water soluble thickener is
a member selected from the group consisting of gum arabic, gum tragacanth,
gum karaya, gum guar, xanthan gum, high viscosity starch, hydrogenated
starch, carboxymethylcellulose, hydroxymethylcellulose, polyvinylpyrrolidone,
polvinyl alcohol, carboxyvinyl polymer, polyacrylic acid, polyacrylamide,
ethylene oxide polymers and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 wherein the oxidizable substrate is
Beta-D-glucose and the oxidoreductase enzyme is glucose oxidase.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 wherein the oxidizable substrate is
hexose and the oxidoreductase enzyme is hexose oxidase.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 wherein the oxidizable substrate is
present in an amount from about 0.025 to about 0.1 millimole per gram of
adhesive and the oxidoreductase enzyme specific to the substrate is present in
an amount from about 10 to about 1,000 International Units per gram of
adhesive.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 which further contains an effective
amount of an augmenting anti-bacterial agent selected from the group
consisting of lysozyme, lactoferrin and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 1 which also contains, per gram of
adhesive, from about 0.1 to about 10,000 International Units of peroxidatic
peroxidase selected from the group consisting of lactoperoxidase, horse
raddish peroxidase, iodide peroxidase, chloride peroxidase, myeloperoxidase
and mixtures thereof, and from about 0.0001 to about 0.01 millimole of an alkali
metal salt of an oxygen accepting anion selected from the group consisting of
thiocyanate, chloride, and iodide and mixtures of such salts for interacting with
hydrogen peroxide to produce oxidized anionic bacterial inhibitor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 13 wherein the peroxidase is present
in an amount from about 10 to about 1,500 International Units per gram of
adhesive and the oxidizable salt is present in an amount from about 0.001 to
about 0.006 millimole per gram of adhesive.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 13 wherein the peroxidase is
lactoperoxidase and the alkali metal salt is alkali metal thiocyanate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The denture adhesive of claim 13 wherein the oxidizable substrate is
Beta-D- glucose, the oxidoreductase enzyme is glucose oxidase, the peroxide
is lactoperoxidase, the oxidizable salt is potassium thiocyanate, and the
thickener is a combination of polyvinylpyrrolidone and polyacrylic acid.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>