<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1561729-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1561729" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34673715" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050810"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1561729-A1" status="new" fvid="24403445"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1561729</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050810</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04075384-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04075384</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040205</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-04075384-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04075384</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040205</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   1/28        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   1/28        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   1/58        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C02F   1/58        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C02F   1/28B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C02F   1/58F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M02F101:30B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M02F101:36</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M02F103:38</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Entfernung von fluorierten Tensiden aus Abwasser</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Removal of fluorinated surfactants from waste water</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Elimination de tensioactifs fluorés présents dans les eaux usées</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-5442097-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5442097</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000035971-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000035971</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2003099879-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2003099879</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PABON M ET AL:  "Fluorinated surfactants: synthesis, properties, effluent treatment" JOURNAL OF FLUORINE CHEMISTRY, ELSEVIER SEQUOIA, LAUSANNE, CH, vol. 114, no. 2, 28 April 2002 (2002-04-28), pages 149-156, XP004351169 ISSN: 0022-1139</text><sources><source category="Y"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>3M INNOVATIVE PROPERTIES CO</last-name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>3M INNOVATIVE PROPERTIES COMPANY</last-name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>3M Innovative Properties Company</last-name><address><street>P.O.Box 33427</street><city>St. Paul, Minnesota 55133-3427</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>HINTZER KLAUS</last-name><address><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>OBERMAIER EGON</last-name><address><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>SCHWERTFEGER WERNER</last-name><address><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>HINTZER, KLAUS</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>OBERMAIER, EGON</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>SCHWERTFEGER, WERNER</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hintzer, Klaus c/o 3M Europe s.a.</last-name><address><street>Hermeslaan 7</street><city>1831 Diegem</city><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Obermaier, Egon c/o 3M Europe s.a.</last-name><address><street>Hermeslaan 7</street><city>1831 Diegem</city><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Schwertfeger, Werner c/o 3M Europe s.a.</last-name> <address><street>Hermeslaan 7</street><city>1831 Diegem</city><country>BE</country></address></addressbook> </inventor> </inventors> <agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Voortmans, Gilbert J.L.</last-name><address><street>3M Europe S.A./N.V. Hermeslaan 7</street><city>1831 Diegem</city><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention provides a method of removing a fluorinated surfactant from waste
water comprising fluoropolymer particles. The method comprises (i) adding a non-fluorinated
surfactant to the waste water (ii) contacting the thus obtained waste water with
adsorbent particles to adsorb at least a portion of the fluorinated surfactant to the adsorbent
particles and (iii) separating the waste water and the adsorbent particles.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>1. Field of the invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to the removal and/or recovery of fluorinated surfactant from
waste water, in particular from waste water that contains fluoropolymer particles.</p><heading>2. Background of the invention</heading><p num="0002">Fluoropolymers, i.e. polymers having a fluorinated backbone, have been long known and
have been used in a variety of applications because of several desirable properties such as
heat resistance, chemical resistance, weatherability, UV-stability etc... The various
fluoropolymers are for example described in "Modem Fluoropolymers", edited by John
Scheirs, Wiley Science 1997. The fluoropolymers may have a partially fluorinated
backbone, generally at least 40% by weight fluorinated, or a fully fluorinated backbone.
Particular examples of fluoropolymers include polytetrafluoroethylene (PTFE), copolymers
of tetrafluoroethylene (TFE) and hexafluoropropylene (HFP) (FEP polymers),
perfluoroalkoxy copolymers (PFA), ethylene-tetrafluoroethylene (ETFE) copolymers,
terpolymers of tetrafluoroethylene, hexafluoropropylene and vinylidene fluoride (THV) and
polyvinylidene fluoride polymers (PVDF).</p><p num="0003">A frequently used method for producing fluoropolymers involves aqueous emulsion
polymerization of one or more fluorinated monomers resulting in an aqueous dispersion of
the fluoropolymer. The aqueous emulsion polymerization of fluorinated monomers
generally involves the use of a fluorinated surfactant. Frequently used fluorinated
surfactants include perfluorooctanoic acids and salts thereof, in particular ammonium
perfluorooctanoic acid. Further fluorinated surfactants used include perfluoropolyether
surfactants such as disclosed in EP 1059342, EP 712882, EP 752432, EP 816397, US
6,025,307, US 6,103,843 and US 6,126,849. Still further surfactants that have been used are
disclosed in US 5,229,480, US 5,763,552, US 5,688,884, US 5,700,859, US 5,804,650, US
5,895,799, WO 00/22002 and WO 00/71590.</p><p num="0004">Perfluorocarboxylic acids (PFCA) are the preferred emulsifiers for making fluorinated
polymers, e.g. perfluorinated polymers like PTFE, FEP, PFA, perfluorinated elastomers, and 
others. Especially perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) in form of its salts (e.g.ammonium salt,
APFO) is widely used. But, APFO and other fluorinated surfactants, in particular
perfluorinated surfactants have raised environmental concerns. Another important aspect is
the fact that these surfactants are expensive materials and any losses thereof from the
production process should be minimized. Until now, these emulsifiers, especially APFO are
indispensable because they do not display chain transfer properties. So PFOA or APFO
respectively are just a prominent example for a whole class of fluorinated surfactants, in
particular fluorinated surfactants with carboxylic acid groups.</p><p num="0005">The fluoropolymers may be used to coat substrates to provide desirable properties thereto
such as for example chemical resistance, weatherability, water- and oil repellency etc... For
example aqueous dispersions of fluoropolymer may be used to coat kitchen ware, to
impregnate fabric or textile e.g. glass fabric, to coat paper or polymeric substrates. For sake
of economy and convenience, the fluoropolymer dispersions will typically have between
35% by weight and 70% by weight of fluoropolymer solids, which is typically attained using
an upconcentration process. Alternatively, for some applications, the fluoropolymers are
provided in granular or powder form. To obtain fluoropolymer granulate or powder, the
fluoropolymer is typically coagulated and the resulting coagulate may be washed with water
one or more times to obtain a desired level of purity.</p><p num="0006">During the production of fluoropolymers to their final commercial form, waste water
streams are created that contain fluorinated surfactant. For example, waste water streams
may result from upconcentration of the dispersion, cleaning of the polymerization vessel and
equipment, coagulation of the dispersion and washing to obtain fluoropolymer granulate or
powder. Additionally, waste water containing fluorinated surfactant may result during
application of the fluoropolymers. Frequently, the waste water streams not only contain
fluorinated surfactant but also other components such as a small amount of fluoropolymer
particles.</p><p num="0007">Several methods for the removal of PFCAs from aqueous media are known. For example, a
method employing reverse osmosis is described in WO 02/139593. A combined process of
extracting PFCA from aqueous solutions at low pH levels using chlorinated hydrocarbons 
and contacting the organic layer with alumina to recover the PFCA is described in EP
194692 and EP 194691. DE 2407834 discloses the use of silica gel to separate PFCAs from
aqueous solutions.</p><p num="0008">Treatment of PFCA contaminated water can be done by applying reverse osmosis followed
by an active carbon bed absorption including the regeneration thereof with ethanol as
described by G. A. Bystrov et al, Plasticheskie Massy, (1990), (4), 75-8 (CA 113, 11571).
As reported by the Russian Authors, the PFCA contaminated water (40-4000 mg of PFCA
per liter) is purified by reverse osmosis in an initial step, resulting in water containing less
than 20 mg per liter of PFCA. This level can be further reduced in an additional purification
step using an active carbon bed. At break through of PFCA, the loaded active carbon bed is
regenerated. Although several different methods were tried, the Soxhlet extraction with
solvents, especially a ethanol - water mixture, showed the best results. But even in this case
only 65 % of the absorbed PFCA could be removed. The thus regenerated active carbon
showed a decrease of activity in the range of 25 - 40 %. Based on this result it is stated that
the active carbon can be reused only 2-3 times before it has to be discarded.</p><p num="0009">While the aforementioned methods can be applied to remove fluorinated surfactants, in
particular PFCAs from water, the methods cannot be readily applied to complicated
industrial waste waters that contain further contaminants, in particular fluoropolymer
particles. These particles may interfere with the removal process. In particular, the
efficiency of adsorbent particles such as carbon black or silica gel is drastically reduced due
to clogging of the adsorbent particles with the fluoropolymer particles.</p><p num="0010">Moreover, it will generally be desired to recover the fluorinated surfactant from the
adsorbent particles such that the expensive fluorinated surfactant can be reused in a
polymerization process and the adsorbent particles can be reused in a purification of waste
water. While the efficiency of the adsorbent particles may decrease after re-generation, it
would be desirable to regenerate the adsorbent particles such that they can be reused more
frequently before they have to be discarded because of unacceptable low efficiency levels. </p><p num="0011">Accordingly, the use of adsorbent particles such as carbon black or silica gel for the recovery
or removal of fluorinated surfactant from waste water containing fluoropolymer particles has
not found practical applications. Instead, the use of an anion exchange resin to recover
PFCAs from fluoropolymer particle containing waste water has been disclosed in WO
99/62858 and WO 99/62830. According to WO 99/62858, the fluoropolymer particles are
removed from the waste water before contacting the waste water with the anion exchange
resin. According to WO 99/62830, a non-ionic surfactant is added to the waste water before
contacting the latter with the exchange resin.</p><p num="0012">It would now be desirable to find a further process for the removal and/or recovery of
fluorinated surfactants, in particular carboxylic acid group containing fluorinated
surfactants, from waste water containing fluoropolymer particles.</p><heading>3. Summary of the invention.</heading><p num="0013">The present invention provides a method of removing a fluorinated surfactant from waste
water comprising fluoropolymer particles. The method comprises (i) adding a non-fluorinated
surfactant to the waste water (ii) contacting the thus obtained waste water with
adsorbent particles to adsorb at least a portion of the fluorinated surfactant to the adsorbent
particles and (iii) separating the waste water and the adsorbent particles.</p><p num="0014">By the term 'absorbent particles' in connection with the present invention is meant particles
that are capable of physically adsorbing the fluorinated surfactant. However, the term
'adsorbent particles' is not intended to include ion exchange resins, which typically bind
fluorinated surfactants having ionic groups as a result an ion exchange process
notwithstanding the fact that the adsorption to the exchange resin may also occur by a
physical adsorption process other than the ion exchange process.</p><p num="0015">Surprisingly, it has been found that notwithstanding the fact that the adsorbent particles
typically also adsorb non-fluorinated surfactants, the fluorinated surfactant amount in the
waste water containing fluoropolymer particles can be effectively reduced without risks of
clogging of the adsorbent particles with the fluoropolymer particles. </p><heading>4. Detailed description of the invention.</heading><p num="0016">Any waste water resulting from the handling, use or production of fluoropolymers can be
treated using the method of the present invention. Typically, such waste water will contain
fluoropolymer particles in addition to some fluorinated surfactant. The quantity of
fluoropolymer particles in the waste water is generally limited and is typically less than 5%
by weight or less than 2% by weight based on the amount of water. A common amount of
fluoropolymer particles in the waste water is less than 1% by weight, e.g. between 0.01 and
0.5% by weight. The fluoropolymer particles may have any shape although they are
generally spherical and they may vary widely in size. Typically the fluoropolymer particles
will have a diameter between 10nm and 1000nm, commonly between 30 and 500nm.</p><p num="0017">The nature of the fluoropolymer particles is not critical and any fluoropolymer as well as
mixtures of different fluoropolymers may be contained in the waste water. For example the
fluoropolymer particles may be particles of non-melt processible fluoropolymers such as
PTFE and modified PTFE or particles of melt-processible fluoropolymers including
fluoroplastics and fluoroelastomers. Examples of melt-processible fluoropolymers include
ETFE, FEP, PFA and THV polymers.</p><p num="0018">In addition to containing fluorinated surfactant and fluoropolymer particles, the waste water
may contain other components such as residual ingredients from the polymerization process,
e.g. salts, initiators, chain transfer agents etc...</p><p num="0019">In accordance with the present invention, a non-fluorinated surfactant should be added to the
waste water before contacting the latter with the adsorbent particles. Although the non-fluorinated
surfactant may get adsorbed to the adsorbent particles, it has been found that the
use of the non-fluorinated surfactant nevertheless prevents or reduces the problem of
clogging of the adsorbent particles with fluoropolymer particles. The amount of the non-fluorinated
surfactant needed will typically depend on the nature of the adsorbent particles
used as well as on the amount of fluoropolymer particles in the dispersion. The appropriate
amount can be readily determined by one skilled in the art through routine experimentation.
Generally, the amount of non-fluorinated surfactant will be between 1 and 1000 ppm based 
on the amount of fluoropolymer particles in the waste water. A convenient amount is
between 5 and 500 ppm.</p><p num="0020">The non-fluorinated surfactant may be selected from anionic, amphoteric and non-ionic
surfactants, with the latter being preferred. Examples of suitable non-ionic non-fluorinated
surfactants include surfactants that contain one or more saturated or unsaturated aliphatic
moieties linked to one or more non-ionic hydrophilic groups. The saturated or unsaturated
aliphatic moieties may include linear, branched and/or cyclic structures and they can be
linked to the non-ionic hydrophilic group through a functional group such as an ester, ether
linkage, amide linkage etc.. The non-ionic hydrophilic group generally comprises
oxyalkylene groups in which the alkylene group has 2, 3 or 4 carbon atoms. For example,
the non-ionic hydrophilic group may be a polyoxyethylene group, a polyoxypropylene group
or a copolymer, including block-copolymers, comprising oxyethylene and oxypropylene
groups.</p><p num="0021">Particular examples of non-ionic surfactants include polyoxyalkylene alkyl ether surfactants,
polysorbates and alkoxylated acetylenic diols, preferably ethoxylated acetylenic diols.
Commercially available ethoxylated acetylenic diols that may be used include those
available under the SURFYNOL™ brand from Air Products, in particular SURFYNOL™
465.</p><p num="0022">According to a particular embodiment in connection with the present invention, the non-ionic
surfactant corresponds to the formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sup>1</sup>-O-[CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>O]<sub>n</sub>-[R<sup>2</sup>O]<sub>m</sub>-R<sup>3</sup></st32:che>
   wherein R<sup>1</sup> represents an aromatic or aliphatic hydrocarbon group having at least 8
carbon atoms, R<sup>2</sup> represents an alkylene having 3 carbon atoms, R<sup>3</sup> represents hydrogen
or a C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>3</sub> alkyl group, n has a value of 0 to 40, m has a value of 0 to 40 and the sum of
n+m being at least 2.

It will be understood that in the above formula (I), the units indexed by n and m may appear
as blocks or they may be present in an alternating or random configuration. </p><p num="0023">Examples of non-ionic surfactants according to formula (I) above include alkylphenol oxy
ethylates of the formula:
<img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="28"/>
wherein R is an alkyl group of 4 to 20 carbon atoms and r represents a value of 4 to 20.
Examples of surfactants according to formula (II) include ethoxylated p-isooctylphenol
commercially available under the brand name TRITON™ such as for example TRITON™
X 100 wherein the number of ethoxy units is about 10 or TRITON™ X 114 wherein the
number of ethoxy units is about 7 to 8.</p><p num="0024">Still further examples include those in which R<sup>1</sup> in the above formula (I) represents an alkyl
group of 4 to 20 carbon atoms, m is 0 and R<sup>3</sup> is hydrogen. An example thereof includes
isotridecanol ethoxylated with about 8 ethoxy groups and which is commercially available
as GENAPOL® X 080 from Clariant GmbH. Non-ionic surfactants according to formula (I)
in which the hydrophilic part comprises a block-copolymer of ethoxy groups and propoxy
groups may be used as well. Such non-ionic surfactants are commercially available from
Clariant GmbH under the trade designation GENAPOL® PF 40 and GENAPOL® PF 80.</p><p num="0025">Particular examples of anionic hydrocarbon surfactants for use in this invention include
alkyl sulfonates such as lauryl sulfonate, alkyl sulfates such as lauryl sulfate,
alkylarylsulfonates and alkylarylsulfates, fatty (carboxylic) acids and salts thereof such as
lauric acids and salts thereof and phosphoric acid alkyl or alkylaryl esters and salts thereof.
Commercially available anionic hydrocarbon surfactants that can be used include Polystep™
A16 (sodium dodecylbenzyl sulphonate) from Stepan Company, Hostapur™ SAS 30
(secondary alkyl sulphonate sodium salt), Emulsogen™ LS (sodium lauryl sulfate) and
Emulsogen™ EPA 1954 (mixture of C<sub>12</sub> to C<sub>14</sub> sodium alkyl sulfates) available from
Clariant GmbH and TRITON™ X-200 (sodium alkylsulfonate) available from Union
Carbide. Preferred are anionic hydrocarbon surfactants having a sulfonate group. </p><p num="0026">The fluorinated surfactant contained in the waste water may be any fluorinated surfactant,
i.e. the method of the present invention can be widely practiced to remove a variety of
fluorinated surfactants, including mixtures thereof, from waste water. However, the method
of the present invention is particularly suitable to remove and/or recover (per)fluorinated
aliphatic acid surfactants or salts thereof. The method of the present invention can
conveniently be used to remove fluorinated surfactants according to the following formula
from waste water:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Q-R<sub>f</sub>-Z-M<sup>a</sup></st32:che>
wherein Q represents hydrogen, Cl or F whereby Q may be present in terminal position or
not; R<sub>f</sub> represents a linear or branched perfluorinated alkylene having 4 to 15 carbon atoms;
Z represents COO<sup>-</sup>, M<sup>a</sup> represents a cation including an alkali metal ion or an ammonium
ion. Representative examples of fluorinated surfactants according to above formula (III) are
perfluoroalkanoic acids and salts thereof such as perfluorooctanoic acid and its salts in
particular ammonium salts.</p><p num="0027">The amount of fluorinated surfactant contained in the waste water is not particularly critical
but is typically between 5 and 10 000ppm, generally between 100 and 5000 ppm. Also, the
waste water may contain a mixture of fluorinated surfactants although such will generally
not be preferred.</p><p num="0028">In accordance with the method of the present invention, the waste water is contacted with
adsorbent particles. Suitable adsorbent particles include carbon black, silica gel, clays and
zeolites. Conveniently used are carbon black particles. The shape of the adsorbent particles
is not particularly critical. For example, the adsorbent particles may have a plate shape, can
be spherical, cylindrical or they can be rods. Also, adsorbent particles having a variety of
different shapes may be used as a mixture. The size of the adsorbent particles is typically
between 0.05mm and 20mm, generally between 0.1 and 10mm. A practical range is
between 0.5 and 5mm. The adsorbent particles typically adsorb the fluorinated acid
surfactant on their surface and it will thus generally be preferred to optimize the specific
surface area of the particles, i.e. the amount of surface per unit of weight. Typically, the 
specific surface area of the adsorbent particles will be between 10 and 5000 m<sup>2</sup>/g, generally
between 100 and 3000 m<sup>2</sup>/g with a practical range being from 300 to 2000 m<sup>2</sup>/g.</p><p num="0029">The amount of adsorbent particles used to remove fluorinated surfactant will generally
depend on the nature of the adsorbent particles used as well as on the composition of the
waste water, in particular the amount of fluorinated surfactant contained therein. Suitable
amounts of the adsorbent particles may be determined by one skilled in the art through
routine experimentation.</p><p num="0030">According to a preferred embodiment of the present invention, the adsorbent particles
having adsorbed on them fluorinated surfactant are regenerated so that they can be reused
multiple times to remove fluorinated surfactant from waste water, rather than having to be
disposed of when they have been loaded to their maximum capacity.</p><p num="0031">A particularly useful way of regenerating the adsorbent particles that have been loaded with
an acid group containing fluorinated surfactant such as for example perfluoroaliphatic acid
surfactants or salts thereof or surfactants of the formula (III) above, involves mixing the
absorbent particles loaded with the fluorinated surfactant with a regeneration fluid
comprising an alcohol, optionally an acid and generally also water. In the thus obtained
mixture to esterification of the acid group containing fluorinated surfactant with the alcohol
is caused, generally by heating the mixture, so as to produce the ester derivative of the
fluorinated acid surfactant. The order of addition of the components of the regeneration
fluid is not critical although it will generally be preferred to first add the alcohol and then the
optional acid to the adsorbent particles. It is of course also possible to prepare the
regeneration fluid in advance by mixing the alcohol and optional acid and then mixing this
as an integral fluid with the adsorbent particles. Preferably, the regeneration fluid will also
contain water. The addition of an acid is not mandatory as the fluorinated acid surfactant
may autocatalyse the esterification with the alcohol. Nevertheless, typically an acid is added
in the regeneration fluid. </p><p num="0032">Suitable alcohols that may be used include in particular lower aliphatic alcohols having 1 to
5 carbon atoms such as methanol, ethanol and propanol. However aromatic alcohols may be
used as well. Additionally, the alcohol may be added under the form of a precursor of the
alcohol. Such a precursor should however form an alcohol under the conditions used to
cause the esterification. Suitable precursors of the alcohol may include compound such as
ketals that readily form a corresponding alcohol under the acidic conditions existing in the
regeneration fluid or mixture thereof with the adsorbent particles. The optional acid when
used with the regeneration fluid is preferably an inorganic acid but the use of organic acids
is not excluded. Also, the acid is preferably a strong acid such as for example sulphuric
acid, hydrochloric acid, phosphoric acid or nitric acid. The amount and nature of the acid
used is typically such that a pH of less than 4, preferably not more than 3 and more
preferably not more than 2 is attained in the mixture of regeneration fluid and adsorbent
particles.</p><p num="0033">The regeneration process can be carried out at ambient pressure, positive pressure, and under
reduced pressure. Typically, the process is carried out at a pressure between 0.1 and 2 atm,
conveniently at ambient pressure, i.e. about 1 atm. The mixture will typically be heated to
the boiling point of the mixture but lower temperatures can be used for the reaction as well.
Typically, the process is carried out at a temperature of between 30 and 100°C.</p><p num="0034">The total amount of regeneration fluid and its composition is typically determined on basis
of the amount of loaded adsorbent particles to be regenerated and the actual loading of the
particles. Generally, the regeneration fluid should contain the alcohol in a stoichiometric
amount or stoichiometric excess of the amount of fluorinated acid surfactant loaded on the
adsorbent particles offered for regeneration. If this data is not available, one should
generally apply a large excess of the regeneration liquid. This does not adversely affect the
regeneration process but has the disadvantage that a non-optimal amount of regeneration
liquid is used. The excess regeneration liquid can easily be drained from the regenerated
adsorbent particles after the regeneration process is finished. The drained liquid can be
weighed and analyzed to determine the actual amount and composition of the drained
regeneration liquid. The composition and amount of the drained regeneration liquid can
than be adjusted by adding appropriate amounts of its components so that the drained 
regeneration liquid may be re-used. Reuse of the regeneration liquid will create less waste, is
environmentally friendly, and reduces the costs.</p><p num="0035">The volume ratio of regeneration fluid to adsorbent particles is preferably at least 2 although
lower volume ratios may be used as well. However, lower volume ratios may cause damage
to the adsorbent particles because of stresses generated at lower volume ratios. Higher
volume ratios can be practiced but too large volume ratios will generally be uneconomical.
Typically the volume ratio will be between 2 and 4.</p><p num="0036">The mixture containing the adsorbent particles and ester derivative of the fluorinated acid
surfactant may be distilled. The distillate that forms contains the ester derivative. With a
sufficient amount of water present in the distillate the ester derivative will generally easily
separate out as a separate phase from the remainder of the distillate. The distillate will
typically contain sufficient water if a substantial amount of water is contained in the
regeneration fluid, e.g. at least 10% by weight. Alternatively, water may be added to
distillate to cause separation. Typically, the ester derivative will form the lower phase.
Thus, the ester derivative can be easily separated from the distillate and the remainder of the
distillate may be re-introduced into the mixture being distilled. Such a regeneration process
thus allows for convenient regeneration of the adsorbent particles with a minimal amount of
regeneration fluid being needed.</p><p num="0037">Furthermore, it has been found that the regeneration process is highly effective and allows
for re-use of the adsorbent particles multiple times, i.e. they can be regenerated several times
before their efficiency drops below an uneconomical level at which point the adsorbent
particles need to be disposed of. Furthermore, the process is highly efficient in removing
fluorinated surfactant from the adsorbent particles such that even when the adsorbent
particles need to be disposed of, because of their lost efficiency, the remaining levels of
fluorinated surfactant in the adsorbent particles is very low. Also, despite the addition of the
non-fluorinated surfactant to the waste water, some fluoropolymer particles contained
therein may still adsorb to the adsorbent particles without however causing clogging of the
adsorbent particles. It was found that the regeneration process is capable of releasing also 
these fluoropolymer particles completely or at least to a large extent from the adsorbent
particles.</p><p num="0038">As will be appreciated by one skilled in the art, the regeneration process not only results in
regenerated adsorbent particles but also the ester derivative of fluorinated acid surfactant.
This ester derivative can be converted back into the corresponding fluorinated acid
surfactant or salt thereof by hydrolysing the ester derivative as is known to those skilled in
the art. The thus obtained fluorinated acid surfactant or salt thereof can then be reused in the
polymerization of fluorinated monomers to make fluoropolymers.</p><p num="0039">The invention will now be further described with reference to the following examples
without however the intention to limit the invention thereto.</p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0040">Two glass columns (diameter 4.5 cm) were loaded with dry active carbon (particle size 1.5
mm ; available from Merck). The first column contained 201 g and the second column 205 g
active carbon. The volume of each bed was ca. 400 ml. The columns were connected and
water was pumped through until all gas was removed. Waste water obtained from several
fluoropolymer emulsion polymerisations of a production plant was filtered to remove visible
solids. 30 ppm Genapol™ X080 (non-ionic surfactant available from Clariant GmbH) were
added to the filtered waste water that contained emulsified microparticles of fluoropolymers
and 210-240ppm of ammonium perfluorooctanoic acid (APFOA). This mixture was passed
over the columns from the bottom to the top. The flow rate was initially adjusted to one bed
volume per hour but was increased to 2.5 bed volumes per hour after a loading of 4.8g of
APFOA. No clogging of the active carbon bed could be seen during the loading process. At
break through of perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) after the first column (PFOA level 45
ppm), 68.3 g APFO had adsorbed to the carbon bed. The columns were washed with 5 liter
deionised water and the contents of the first column were transferred to a distillation
apparatus consisting of a flask equipped with a mechanical stirrer, thermometer, vapor line
and a condenser. The regeneration liquid, consisting of methanol, water and sulfuric acid 
(60/20/20 ratio) was added. The mixture was heated at a temperature between 70-85°C to
allow distillation. The condensed vapor separated in two liquid phases. The lower phase,
consisting of methyl perfluorooctanoate was removed while the upper phase was sent back
to the distillation flask. The distillation was finished as soon as no increase of the lower
phase was observed. A total of 68.1 g methyl perfluorooctanoate was recovered (100%).</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>Method of removing a fluorinated surfactant from waste water comprising
fluoropolymer particles, said method comprising (i) adding a non-fluorinated
surfactant to said waste water (ii) contacting the thus obtained waste water with
adsorbent particles to adsorb at least part of the fluorinated surfactant to said
adsorbent particles and (iii) separating the waste water and the adsorbent particles.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>Method according to claim 1 wherein said adsorbent particles comprise carbon
black.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>Method according to claim 1 or 2 wherein said non-fluorinated surfactant comprises
a non-ionic surfactant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>Method according to any of the previous claims wherein said fluorinated surfactant
comprises a fluorinated acid or salt thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>Method according to claim 4 wherein said fluorinated surfactant comprises a
perfluoroaliphatic acid or salt thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>Method according to any of the previous claims wherein the amount of non-fluorinated
surfactant is between 1 and 1000ppm based on the amount of
fluoropolymer particles in the waste water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>Method according to any of the previous claims further comprising the step of
regenerating the adsorbent particles.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>Method according to claim 7 wherein said fluorinated surfactant comprises a
perfluoroaliphatic acid or salt thereof and wherein the step of regenerating comprises
mixing the adsorbent particles with an alcohol and an acid and heating the thus
obtained mixture to cause esterification of said perfluoroaliphatic acid or salt thereof
with said alcohol so as to produce an ester derivative of said perfluoroaliphatic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>Method according to claim 8 further comprising distilling the mixture, thereby
forming a distillate containing said ester derivative, and separating said ester
derivative from the distillate thereby yielding said ester derivative of said
perfluoroaliphatic acid and a remainder of the distillate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>Method according to claim 9 wherein the remainder of the distillate is re-introduced
in said mixture.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>