<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1277775-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1277775" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26618943" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030122"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1277775-A1" status="new" fvid="23654946"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1277775</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030122</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02015683-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02015683</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020717</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2001218348-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2001218348</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010718</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002032839-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002032839</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020208</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/40        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/48        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/63        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/76        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  65/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  65/26        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  65/28        20060101AFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  18/08D2B5C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  18/40A13</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  18/48M</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  18/76A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  65/26R</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08G101:00B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08G101:00K3</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08G101:00P</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung eines polymerdispergierten Polyols</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Methods for producing a polymer dispersed polyol</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé de production de polyol dispersé dans un polymère</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0677543-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0677543</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0807651-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0807651</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0992523-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0992523</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1022300-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1022300</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5605939-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5605939</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6066683-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6066683</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1991018909-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1991018909</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>ASAHI GLASS CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ASAHI GLASS COMPANY LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ASAHI GLASS COMPANY LTD.</last-name><address><street>12-1, Yurakucho 1-chome, Chiyoda-ku</street><city>Tokyo 100-8405</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>AKAGI ETSUKO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HORIE AKIO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SUGIYAMA KAYOKO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TOYOTA YOSHINORI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WADA HIROSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AKAGI, ETSUKO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HORIE, AKIO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SUGIYAMA, KAYOKO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TOYOTA, YOSHINORI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WADA, HIROSHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>AKAGI, ETSUKO</last-name><address><street>19-30-204, Mitsuzawashimomachi, Kanagawa-ku</street><city>Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Horie, Akio c/o Asahi Glass Urethane Co., Ldt.</last-name><address><street>25, Oaza-towada, Kamisu-machi</street><city>Kashima-gun, Ibaraki</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SUGIYAMA, KAYOKO</last-name><address><street>1-633-2-801, Marukodori, Nakahara-ku</street><city>Kawasaki-shi, Kanagawa</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Toyota, Yoshinori c/o Asahi Glass Com.,Ltd.</last-name><address><street>1150, Hazawa-cho, Kanagawa-ku</street><city>Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Wada, Hiroshi c/o Asahi Glass Urethane Co., Ldt.</last-name><address><street>25, Oaza-towada, Kamisu-machi</street><city>Kashima-gun, Ibaraki</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Müller-Boré &amp;amp; Partner Patentanwälte</last-name><address><street>Grafinger Strasse 2</street><city>81671 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A method for producing a polyoxyalkylene polyol
which comprises subjecting propylene oxide and ethylene
oxide to ring-opening addition polymerization with an
initiator in the presence of a catalyst,

   wherein the polyoxyalkylene polyol is a
polyoxyalkylene polyol obtained by subjecting propylene
oxide to ring-opening addition polymerization with an
initiator in the presence of a double metal cyanide
complex catalyst to form an oxypropylene block chain,
subjecting ethylene oxide and propylene oxide to ring-opening
addition polymerization randomly to form an
oxyalkylene random chain, changing the catalyst and
subjecting ethylene oxide to ring-opening addition
polymerization in the presence of an alkali metal
catalyst to form an oxyethylene block chain,

   and the polyoxyalkylene polyol is a polyoxyalkylene
polyol having a hydroxyl value of from 5 to 56 mgKOH/g, a
proportion of an initiator residue of at most 25 mass%, a
proportion of the oxypropylene block chain of from 5 to
50 mass%, a total oxyethylene group content of from 5 to
60 mass%, and a ratio of primary hydroxyl groups among
terminal hydroxyl groups of at least 60 mol%.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to methods for
producing a polyoxyalkylene polyol and a polymer
dispersed polyol. The polyoxyalkylene polyol and the
polymer dispersed polyol obtained by the production
methods of the present invention are widely used as a
material of an elastomer, a synthetic resin, a coating
and a sealing material, or as a surfactant, a lubricant,
a diluent, a plasticizer, etc. Particularly when they
are used as a material for producing a flexible
polyurethane foam (hereinafter referred to as flexible
foam), a flexible foam having improved mechanical
properties such as hardness, moldability, vibrating
property and durability can be obtained.</p><p num="0002">Heretofore, various studies have been conducted to
improve properties of a flexible foam. For example, in
order to improve comfort of a seat cushion of e.g. an
automobile to sit on, improvement of e.g. impact
resilience, vibrating property and durability has been 
desired. Further, in recent years, along with a change
in taste of users for comfort to sit on, a flexible foam
having a low impact resilience coefficient has been
desired. With regard to the vibrating property, it is
considered to be effective to make decrement in a
frequency region to which human is sensitive (considered
to be from 4 to 8 Hz for example, or from 6 to 20 Hz)
particularly significant. In order to improve such
properties, it is considered to be effective to produce a
seat cushion by employing a polyoxyalkylene polyol having
a higher molecular weight.</p><p num="0003">A polyoxyalkylene polyol (hereinafter referred to as
polyol) used as a material of a flexible foam is usually
produced by subjecting an alkylene oxide such as
propylene oxide to ring-open addition polymerization with
e.g. a polyhydric alcohol as an initiator by using a
sodium type catalyst such as sodium hydroxide or a
potassium type catalyst such as potassium hydroxide. By
this production method, a monool having unsaturated bonds
(unsaturated monool) is formed as a by-product, and the
formation amount of the unsaturated monool increases
along with decrease in the hydroxyl value (increase in
the molecular weight) of the polyol.</p> <p num="0004">In production of a polyol having a hydroxyl value at
a level of 56 mgKOH/g which is widely used as a material
of a flexible foam, the formation amount of the
unsaturated monool is not so large as to be a serious 
problem. However, in production of a polyol having a
high molecular weight and a low hydroxyl value, the
formation amount of the unsaturated monool tends to be
problematic. In a case where a flexible foam is produced
by using a polyol having a high degree of total
unsaturation, problems such as decrease in hardness,
deterioration of permanent compression set and
deterioration of curing property at the time of molding
tend to occur. Further, in a case where a polyol having
a low hydroxyl value is produced by using a sodium type
catalyst or a potassium type catalyst, the degree of
total unsaturation tends to be remarkably high, and the
production is very difficult.</p><p num="0005">As a method of producing a polyol having a low
degree of total unsaturation and a low hydroxyl value, a
production method of subjecting an alkylene oxide to
ring-opening addition polymerization by using a double
metal cyanide complex as a catalyst is proposed in JP-A-2-276821.
Although comfort to sit on remarkably improves
when a high molecular weight polyol obtained by this
production method is used, there may be a problem in
moldability such as air flow, required in addition to
comfort to sit on, in some cases. Practically, such a
polyol alone is used to produce a flexible foam, degree
of closed-cell tends to be relatively high, thus leading
to a defect at the time of crushing treatment in some
cases. </p><p num="0006">As a method to overcome the problem of moldability,
a method for producing a flexible foam by using as the
material a polyol mixture comprising a polyol produced by
using a double metal cyanide complex catalyst and a
polyol produced by using potassium hydroxide is proposed
in JP-A-8-231676. However, in this method, as the polyol
produced by using a double metal cyanide complex
catalyst, a polyoxyalkylene polyol produced by subjecting
propylene oxide alone to ring-opening addition
polymerization with an initiator and then subjecting
ethylene oxide alone to ring-opening addition
polymerization, is used, and further, the degree of
unsaturation of the polyol produced by using a potassium
hydroxide catalyst is high, and the degree of
unsaturation of the entire polyol mixture is thereby
high, whereby durability of the foam tends to be
insufficient.</p><p num="0007">Further, as another method, a method of using a
double metal cyanide complex catalyst, subjecting a
mixture of ethylene oxide with another alkylene oxide to
ring-opening addition polymerization reaction system with
an initiator to produce a polyol having a random addition
structure of ethylene oxide with another alkylene oxide
in the molecule of the polyol, and using this polyol to
form a flexible foam having favorable moldability, is
proposed in U.S.P. 5,605,939 and U.S.P. 5,648,559.
However, the present inventors have tried to produce a 
flexible foam for an automobile seat by using a polyol in
Examples as disclosed in the above patents, but a foam
could not be produced as depressions (collapses) were
formed in the inside and on the surface of the foam.</p><p num="0008">Under these circumstances, the present invention has
been made to overcome the above problems, and it is an
object of the present invention to provide methods for
producing a material polyol and a polymer dispersed
polyol, which provide, in production of a flexible foam
using as the material a polyol produced by using a double
metal cyanide complex catalyst, a flexible foam having
favorable foam moldability maintained, having good
physical properties such as hardness and vibrating
property, and having favorable durability particularly
heat and humidity permanent compression set.</p> <p num="0009">The present invention provides a method for
producing a polyoxyalkylene polyol, which comprises
subjecting propylene oxide and ethylene oxide to ring-opening
addition polymerization with an initiator in the
presence of a catalyst, wherein the polyoxyalkylene
polyol is a polyoxyalkylene polyol obtained by subjecting
propylene oxide to ring-opening addition polymerization
with an initiator in the presence of a double metal
cyanide complex catalyst to form an oxypropylene block
chain, subjecting ethylene oxide and propylene oxide to
ring-opening addition polymerization randomly to form an
oxyalkylene random chain, changing the catalyst and 
subjecting ethylene oxide to ring-opening addition
polymerization in the presence of an alkali metal
catalyst to form an oxyethylene block chain, and the
polyoxyalkylene polyol is a polyoxyalkylene polyol having
a hydroxyl value of from 5 to 56 mgKOH/g, a proportion of
an initiator residue of at most 25 mass%, a proportion of
the oxypropylene block chain of from 5 to 50 mass%, a
total oxyethylene group content of from 5 to 60 mass%,
and a ratio of primary hydroxyl groups among terminal
hydroxyl groups of at least 60 mol%.</p> <p num="0010">The present invention further provides a method for
producing a polymer dispersed polyol, which comprises
polymerizing a monomer having polymerizable unsaturated
groups employing the polyoxyalkylene polyol obtained by
the above production method as a dispersion medium.</p> <p num="0011">Now, the present invention will be described in
detail with reference to the preferred embodiment.</p><heading><u style="single">Structure of polyol (1)</u></heading><p num="0012">The polyoxyalkylene polyol (hereinafter referred to
as polyol (1)) of the present invention is a
polyoxyalkylene polyol obtained in such a manner that
propylene oxide is subjected to ring-opening addition
polymerization with an initiator in the presence of a
double metal cyanide complex catalyst to form an
oxypropylene block chain, ethylene oxide and propylene
oxide are subjected to ring-opening addition
polymerization randomly to form an oxyalkylene random 
chain, then the catalyst is changed, and ethylene oxide
is subjected to ring-opening addition polymerization in
the presence of an alkali metal catalyst to form an
oxyethylene block chain.</p><p num="0013">Namely, the polyol (1) has an initiator residue (i),
an oxypropylene block chain (ii), an oxyalkylene random
chain (iii) and an oxyethylene block chain (iv) in its
molecule.</p><heading><u style="single">Initiator residue (i)</u></heading><p num="0014">As the initiator for the polyol (1) of the present
invention, an active hydrogen compound such as a
polyhydric alcohol, an amine or a condensed type compound
may be used. Here, the initiator residue (i) is a moiety
in the polyol (1) derived from the initiator. The
proportion of the initiator residue (i) is preferably at
most 25 mass% based on the entire polyol (1), preferably
from 2 to 20 mass%.</p><p num="0015">Specific examples of the initiator include
polyhydric alcohols such as ethylene glycol, propylene
glycol, 1,4-butanediol, glycerol, trimethylolpropane,
pentaerythritol, diglycerol, meso-erythritol, methyl
glucoside, glucose, sorbitol and sucrose; amines such as
ethylenediamine, diethylenediamine, triethylenediamine,
diaminodiphenylmethane, hexamethylenediamine and
propylenediamine; and condensed type compounds such as
phenol resins and novolac resins.</p><p num="0016">Such active hydrogen compounds may be used in 
combination of at least two. Among these active hydrogen
compounds, preferred is a polyhydric alcohol.
Particularly, an at least trivalent polyhydric alcohol is
preferred in such a viewpoint that hardness of a flexible
foam employing as the material a polyol produced by using
such a polyhydric alcohol as the initiator is likely to
be obtained.</p><p num="0017">Further, as the initiator, a compound obtained by
subjecting an alkylene oxide in a small amount to ring-opening
addition polymerization with the above compound
may also be used. The alkylene oxide is preferably
propylene oxide. The molecular weight of the obtained
compound is preferably at least 650.</p><p num="0018">Most preferred as the initiator is a compound having
a hydroxyl value of from 150 to 250 mgKOH/g, obtained by
subjecting propylene oxide to ring-opening addition
polymerization with an at least trivalent polyhydric
alcohol.</p><heading><u style="single">Oxypropylene block chain (ii)</u></heading><p num="0019">The polyol (1) of the present invention has an
oxypropylene block chain (ii) formed by using a double
metal cyanide complex catalyst, adjacent to the initiator 
residue (i). The proportion of the oxypropylene block
chain (ii) is from 5 to 50 mass% based on the entire
polyol (1), preferably from 10 to 40 mass%. The
proportion of the oxypropylene block chain (ii) is
particularly preferably from 20 to 30 mass%, whereby
hardness of the flexible foam can be controlled high. If
the oxypropylene block chain exceeds 50 mass%, degree of
closed-cell of the flexible foam tends to be high,
whereby moldability tends to deteriorate, and the curing
property tends to deteriorate, whereby hardness is less
likely to be obtained. Further, if the oxypropylene
block chain (ii) is less than 5 mass%, hardness of the
flexible foam is less likely to be obtained.</p><p num="0020">Here, in a case where a compound obtained by
subjecting propylene oxide to ring-opening addition
polymerization with an at least trivalent polyhydric
alcohol is used as the initiator, the oxypropylene block
chain in the initiator residue (i) and the oxypropylene
block chain (ii) formed by using a double metal cyanide
complex catalyst can not be distinguished even when the
obtained polyol (1) is analyzed. Accordingly, in a case
of verification as the polyol (1), the oxypropylene block
chain of the initiator residue (i) and the oxypropylene
block chain (ii) formed by using a double metal cyanide
complex catalyst are not distinguished. Namely, the
total proportion of the initiator residue (i) and the
oxypropylene block chain (ii) is preferably from 5 to 75 
mass%, more preferably from 12 to 60 mass%, based on the
entire polyol (1).</p><p num="0021">Further, when the polyol (1) wherein the
oxypropylene block chain (ii) is adjacent to the
initiator residue (i) and another polyol are compared,
the former is preferred, which has favorable moldability.
Further, the oxypropylene block chain (ii) is produced by
using the above double metal cyanide complex catalyst,
whereas if another catalyst is used, an unsaturated
monool is produced as a by-product, and durability of a
flexible foam employing the obtained polyol as the
material tends to deteriorate, such being unfavorable.</p><heading><u style="single">Oxyalkylene random chain (iii)</u></heading><p num="0022">The polyol (1) of the present invention has an
oxyalkylene random chain (iii) formed by using a double
metal cyanide complex catalyst adjacent to the
oxypropylene block chain (ii). The oxyalkylene random
chain is a structure obtained by supplying ethylene oxide
and propylene oxide in a predetermined proportion to the
reaction system, and subjecting to ring-opening addition
polymerization randomly. The proportion of the
oxyalkylene random chain (iii) is preferably from 5 to 90
mass% based on the entire polyol (1), preferably from 10
to 80 mass%.</p><p num="0023">The content of oxyethylene groups in the oxyalkylene
random chain (iii) in the polyol (1) of the present
invention is preferably from 3 to 35 mass%, more 
preferably from 5 to 30 mass%, based on the oxyalkylene
random chain (iii). Namely, the proportion of ethylene
oxide to propylene oxide supplied to the reaction system
is preferably from 3/97 to 35/65, more preferably from
5/95 to 30/70, in a mass ratio (ethylene oxide/propylene
oxide). In a case where the oxyethylene group in the
oxyalkylene random chain (iii) is less than this range or
exceeds this range, degree of closed-cell of the flexible
foam tends to be high, and the moldability may
deteriorate in some cases, such being unfavorable.</p><p num="0024">Further, when ethylene oxide and propylene oxide are
supplied to the reaction system in a predetermined
proportion, the proportion may be changed during the
supplying. By such a method, the content of oxyethylene
groups in the oxyalkylene random chain (iii) can be
controlled in the desired portion of the molecule. For
example, in a case where the proportion of ethylene oxide
is increased in stages, a polyol (1) wherein the content
of oxyethylene groups becomes high towards the terminal
of the molecule of the polyol (1) can be produced.</p><heading><u style="single">Oxyethylene block chain (iv)</u></heading><p num="0025">The polyol (1) of the present invention has an
oxyethylene block chain (iv) produced by using an alkali
metal catalyst adjacent to the oxyalkylene random chain
(iii) i.e. at the terminal of the molecule. The content
of this oxyethylene block chain (iv) is preferably from 3
to 40 mass%, more preferably from 5 to 30 mass%, based on 
the entire polyol (1). If the oxyethylene block chain
(iv) exceeds 40 mass%, shrinkage is likely to occur even
after crushing treatment, such being unfavorable.
Further, if the oxyethylene block chain (iv) is less than
3 mass%, e.g. collapses of the foam are likely to occur
in production of the flexible foam, and the production
tends to be difficult.</p><heading><u style="single">Composite metal cyanide complex catalyst</u></heading><p num="0026">The polyol (1) of the present invention is obtained
by subjecting the above-described specific alkylene
oxides to ring-opening addition polymerization with an
initiator in the presence of the double metal cyanide
complex catalyst. As the double metal cyanide complex
catalyst, compounds as disclosed in JP-B-46-27250 may,
for example, be mentioned. Particularly, a complex
containing zinc hexacyanocobaltate as the main component
is preferred, and its ether and/or alcohol complexes are
more preferred. By using such a double metal cyanide
complex catalyst, the amount of by-product unsaturated
monool can be suppressed, and durability of the flexible
foam employing the obtained polyol as the material tends
to improve.</p><p num="0027">Further, the above ether is not particularly
limited, but is preferably a compound of the following
formula (hereinafter referred to as compound (X)):
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sup>1</sup>-C(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(OR<sup>0</sup>)<sub>n</sub>OH</st32:che>
wherein R<sup>1</sup> is a methyl group or an ethyl group, R<sup>0</sup> is an 
ethylene group or a group having a hydrogen atom of an
ethylene group substituted with a methyl group or an
ethyl group, and n is an integer of from 1 to 3. R<sup>0</sup> is
particularly preferably a group selected from an ethylene
group, a propylene group, an ethylethylene group, a 1,2-dimethylethylene
group and a 1,1-dimethylethylene group.</p><p num="0028">As the compound (X), specifically, compounds as
disclosed in WO00/02951 may be mentioned. Specifically,
the following compounds are preferred.</p><p num="0029">In a case where n is 1, preferred are ethylene
glycol mono-tert-butyl ether, propylene glycol mono-tert-butyl
ether, ethylene glycol mono-tert-pentyl ether and
propylene glycol mono-tert-pentyl ether. In a case where
n is 2, diethylene glycol mono-tert-butyl ether and
diethylene glycol mono-tert-pentyl ether are preferred.
In a case where n is 3, triethylene glycol mono-tert-butyl
ether and triethylene glycol mono-tert-pentyl ether
are preferred. Further, as the compound (X), a compound
wherein n is 1 is particularly preferred, and a compound
wherein R<sup>1</sup> is a methyl group is most preferred. Further,
as the compound (X), at least two compounds may be used
together.</p><p num="0030">The above alcohol is not particularly limited and
methanol, ethanol, 1-propanol, 2-propanol, 1-butanol, 2-butanol,
tert-butyl alcohol, pentanol and octanol may,
for example, be mentioned, and among them, it is
preferred to use tert-butyl alcohol. </p><p num="0031">In a case where the compound (X) and another
compound are used together as organic ligands, the
compound to be used together is preferably one or at
least two compounds selected from the group consisting of
tert-butyl alcohol, 1-butanol, 2-butanol, tert-pentyl
alcohol, isopentyl alcohol, N,N-dimethylacetoamide, glyme
(ethylene glycol dimethyl ether), diglyme (diethylene
glycol dimethyl ether) triglyme (triethylene glycol
dimethyl ether), 2-propanol and dioxane. The dioxane may
be either 1,4-dioxane or 1,3-dioxane, and 1,4-dioxane is
preferred. As the compound to be used together, tert-butyl
alcohol, tert-pentyl alcohol or glyme is
particularly preferred, and tert-butyl alcohol is most
preferred.</p><p num="0032">Namely, specific examples of the double metal
cyanide complex to be used in the present invention
include a zinc hexacyanocobaltate-ethylene glycol mono-tert-butyl
ether complex, a zinc hexacyanocobaltate-ethylene
glycol mono-tert-butyl ether/tert-butyl alcohol
complex, a zinc hexacyanocobaltate-tert-butyl alcohol
complex and a zinc hexacyanocobaltate-glyme complex.
Among them, particularly preferred are a zinc
hexacyanocobaltate-ethylene glycol mono-tert-butyl ether
complex and a zinc hexacyanocobaltate-ethylene glycol
mono-tert-butyl ether/tert-butyl alcohol complex.</p><heading><u style="single">Alkali metal catalyst</u></heading><p num="0033">The alkali metal catalyst to be used for formation 
of the oxypropylene block chain (iv) may be a sodium type
catalyst, a potassium type catalyst or a cesium type
catalyst. The sodium type catalyst may, for example, be
a sodium metal, a sodium alkoxide such as sodium
methoxide, sodium hydroxide or sodium carbonate. The
same applies to the potassium type catalyst and the
cesium type catalyst.</p><p num="0034">In production of the polyol (1) of the present
invention, as the method of changing the double metal
cyanide complex catalyst to the alkali metal catalyst,
the alkali metal catalyst may be added to the reaction
system after the double metal cyanide complex catalyst is
deactivated, or the alkali metal catalyst may be added to
the reaction system without deactivation. In the latter
case, the double metal cyanide complex catalyst is
deactivated by addition of the alkali metal catalyst. As
the deactivation method, a treatment by putting water, an
acid or an alkali, or a treatment by putting an adsorbent
may, for example, be mentioned.</p><heading><u style="single">Properties of polyol (1)</u></heading><p num="0035">The hydroxyl value of the polyol (1) of the present
invention is from 5 to 56 mgKOH/g, more preferably from
10 to 42 mgKOH/g. If the hydroxyl value exceeds 56
mgKOH/g and the molecular weight is low, elasticity of
the obtained flexible foam tends to be insufficient.
Further, if the hydroxyl value is less than 5 mgKOH/g,
hardness of the obtained flexible foam is less likely to 
be obtained.</p><p num="0036">The number of hydroxyl groups in the polyol (1) of
the present invention is preferably from 2 to 8, more
preferably from 2.7 to 7, most preferably from 2.8 to
5.2. Here, the number of hydroxyl groups is an average
number of active hydrogen in the initiator. If the
number of hydroxyl groups is less than 2, the obtained
flexible foam tends to be soft, and the durability tends
to deteriorate. If the number of hydroxyl groups exceeds
8, the obtained flexible foam tends to be hard, and
mechanical properties such as elongation tend to
deteriorate.</p><p num="0037">The degree of unsaturation of the polyol (1) of the
present invention is preferably at most 0.03 meq/g, more
preferably at most 0.025 meq/g. If the degree of
unsaturation exceeds 0.03 meq/g, i.e. if the amount of
the unsaturated monool is large, durability and comfort
to sit on of the obtained flexible foam tend to
deteriorate. As the index of the durability of the
flexible foam, dry heat permanent compression set and
heat and humidity permanent compression set may be
mentioned. The higher the degree of unsaturation, the
higher the value of the permanent compression set, and
the poorer the durability tends to be. Further, as the
index of the comfort to sit on of the flexible foam, the
resonance frequency may be mentioned. Such a correlation
that as the resonance frequency decreases, 
transmissibility at 6 Hz at which human feels most
uncomfortable tends to decrease, and thus the resonance
frequency is suitable as the index.</p><p num="0038">The total oxyethylene group content (i.e. the
content of all oxyethylene groups contained in the
initiator residue (i), oxyalkylene random chain (iii) and
oxyethylene block chain (iv)) in the polyol (1) of the
present invention is from 5 to 60 mass%, more preferably
from 10 to 40 mass%. Further, the proportion of primary
hydroxyl groups among terminal hydroxyl groups of the
polyol, derived from the oxyethylene block chain (iv) at
the terminal of the molecule of the polyol (1) of the
present invention, i.e. the ratio of primary hydroxyl
groups among terminal hydroxyl groups is preferably at
least 60 mol%, more preferably from 80 to 95 mol%.</p><heading><u style="single">Polymer dispersed polyol</u></heading><p num="0039">The present invention further provides a method for
producing a polymer dispersed polyol wherein polymer fine
particles are stably dispersed in the polyol (1). The
polymer dispersed polyol is a dispersion system wherein
polymer fine particles (dispersoid) are stably dispersed
in the base polyol (dispersion medium). Namely, the
polymer dispersed polyol of the present invention is a
polymer dispersed polyol wherein the above-described
polyol (1) is employed as the base polyol.</p><p num="0040">The polymer as the polymer fine particles may be an
addition polymerization type polymer or a condensation 
polymerization type polymer. The addition polymerization
type polymer may be obtained, for example, by
homopolymerizing or copolymerizing a monomer such as
acrylonitrile, styrene, a methacrylate ester or an
acrylate ester. The condensation polymerization type
polymer may, for example, be polyester, polyurea,
polyurethane or melamine.</p><p num="0041">Presence of polymer fine particles in the polyol
suppresses the hydroxyl value of the polyol low, and is
effective to improve physical properties such as hardness
and air flow of the flexible foam. The content of the
polymer fine particles in the polymer dispersed polyol is
not particularly limited, but is preferably at most 50
mass%, more preferably from 3 to 40 mass%. In a case
where the mass of the polyol is employed for calculation,
the mass of the polymer fine particles is not included.</p><heading><u style="single">Use of polyol (1)</u></heading><p num="0042">The polyol (1) and the polymer dispersed polyol of
the present invention are widely used as a material of a
flexible foam, an elastomer, a synthetic resin, a coating
and a sealing material, or as a surfactant, a lubricant,
a diluent, a plasticizer, etc. They are particularly
preferably used as a material for producing a flexible
foam, whereby moldability of the foam, and vibrating
property and physical properties such as hardness of the
flexible foam to be obtained tend to improve. As a
method for producing a flexible foam, a method may 
usually be mentioned wherein a polyol compound and a
polyisocyanate compound are reacted in the presence of a
blowing agent and a catalyst, and in the presence of a
foam stabilizer, a crosslinking agent or a cell opener as
the case requires.</p><p num="0043">As the polyol compound (including a polymer
dispersed polyol) to be reacted in production of the
flexible foam, a polyol mixture containing the polyol (1)
of the present invention and/or the polymer dispersed
polyol of the present invention is preferably used. As
the polyol mixture, the polyol (polyol (1) or polymer
dispersed polyol) of the present invention alone may be
used, or another polyol may be used together. The
another polyol is not particularly limited so long as it
is a polyol used for production of the flexible foam, but
is preferably a polyoxyalkylene polyol, preferably a
polyoxyalkylene polyol having a total oxypropylene group
content of at least 40 mass%. Among polyols to be
reacted in production of the flexible foam, the content
of the polyol of the present invention is preferably at
least 20 mass%, more preferably at least 30 mass%,
particularly preferably at least 50 mass%. Further, at
least two polyols of the present invention as mixed may
be used. However, the polyol compound (mixture) does not
include a crosslinking agent and a cell opener as
mentioned hereinafter.</p><p num="0044">The hydroxyl value of the polyol mixture is 
preferably from 5 to 56 mgKOH/g, more preferably from 10
to 42 mgKOH/g. Further, the degree of total unsaturation
of the polyol mixture is preferably at most 0.05 meq/g,
more preferably at most 0.03 meq/g, most preferably at
most 0.025 meq/g. Further, the average ratio of primary
hydroxyl groups among terminal hydroxyl groups of the
polyol mixture is preferably at least 60 mol%.</p><p num="0045">The polyisocyanate compound is not particularly
limited, and aromatic, alicyclic and aliphatic
polyisocyanates having at least two isocyanate groups; a
mixture of at least two of the above polyisocyanates; and
a modified polyisocyanate obtained by modification
thereof may, for example, be mentioned. Specific
examples thereof include polyisocyanates such as tolylene
diisocyanate (TDI), diphenylmethane diisocyanate (MDI),
polymethylene polyphenyl isocyanate (common name: crude
MDI), xylylene diisocyanate (XDI), isophorone
diisocyanate (IPDI) and hexamethylene diisocyanate
(HMDI), and prepolymer type modified products,
isocyanurate type modified products, urea type modified
products and carbodiimide type modified products thereof.
Among them, preferred are TDI, MDI, crude MDI and
modified product thereof.</p><p num="0046">The amount of the polyisocyanate compound used is
usually represented by isocyanate index (a value
represented by 100 times the proportion of the number of
isocyanate groups based on the total number of active 
hydrogen of e.g. polyol, crosslinking agent, cell opener
and water). The amount of the polyisocyanate compound
used in the present invention is preferably from 80 to
120, more preferably from 85 to 110, as represented by
the isocyanate index.</p><p num="0047">The blowing agent is not particularly limited, but
is preferably at least one member selected from water and
inert gases. As the inert gas, the air, nitrogen or
carbon dioxide gas may, for example, be mentioned. Among
them, water is preferred. The amount of the blowing
agent is not particularly limited, and in a case where
water is used, it is preferably at most 10 parts by mass,
more preferably from 0.1 to 8 parts by mass, per 100
parts by mass of the polyol compound.</p><p num="0048">The above catalyst is not particularly limited so
long as it is a catalyst which accelerates a urethanating
reaction, and it may, for example, be a tertiary amine
such as triethylenediamine, bis(2-dimethylaminoethyl)ether
or N,N,N',N'-tetramethylhexamethylenediamine; a metal carboxylate such
as potassium acetate or potassium 2-ethylhexanoate; or an
organic metal compound such as dibutyltin dilaurate.</p><p num="0049">The foam stabilizer is not particularly limited, and
it may, for example, be a silicone type foam stabilizer
or a fluorine type foam stabilizer, and a silicone type
foam stabilizer is preferred. By using such a foam
stabilizer, homogeneous cell structure can be formed. </p><p num="0050">As the crosslinking agent, preferred is a compound
having at least two functional groups having active
hydrogen such as a hydroxyl group, a primary amino group
or a secondary amino group. The hydroxyl value of the
crosslinking agent is preferably at least 100 mgKOH/g,
more preferably 150 mgKOH/g, particularly preferably at
least 200 mgKOH/g. Further, at least two crosslinking
agents may be used together.</p><p num="0051">Specific examples thereof include compounds such as
ethylene glycol, propylene glycol, 1,4-butanediol,
neopentyl glycol, 1,6-hexanediol, diethylene glycol,
triethylene glycol, dipropylene glycol, glycerol,
trimethylol propane, pentaerythritol, diglycerol,
dextrose, sorbitol, sucrose, monoethanolamine,
diethanolamine, triethanolamine, bisphenol A,
ethylenediamine, 3,5-diethyl-2,4 (or 2,6)-diaminotoluene
(DETDA), 2-chloro-p-phenylenediamine (CPA), 3,5-bis(methyithio)-2,4
(or 2,6)-diaminotoluene, 1-trifluoromethyl-3,5-diaminobenzene,
1-trifluoromethyl-4-chloro-3,5-diaminobenzene,
2,4-toluenediamine, 2,6-toluenediamine,
bis(3,5-dimethyl-4-aminophenyl)methane,
4,4'-diaminodiphenylmethane, m-xylylenediamine, 1,4-diaminohexane,
1,3-bis(aminomethyl)cyclohexane and
isophorone diamine, and compounds obtained by adding a
relatively small amount of an alkylene oxide thereto.</p><p num="0052">The cell opener is preferably a polyoxyalkylene
polyol having a number of hydroxyl group of at least 2, a 
hydroxyl value of from 20 to 180 mgKOH/g and an
oxyethylene group content exceeding 60 mass%. By using
such a cell opener, moldability of the flexible foam
tends to be improved, specifically, the crushing load
tends to be suppressed low. The amount of the cell
opener used is preferably from 0.1 to 5 parts by mass per
100 parts by mass of the polyol compound.</p><p num="0053">In production of the flexible foam, in addition to
the above components, a surfactant such as an emulsifying
agent or a foam stabilizer; an aging preventing agent
such as an antioxidant or a ultraviolet ray absorbent; a
filler such as calcium carbonate or barium sulfate; or a
known additive or assistant such as a flame retardant, a
plasticizer, a colorant or an antifungal agent, may be
used as the case requires.</p><p num="0054">As the method of forming a flexible foam, a method
of pouring a reactive mixture directly into a mold by
means of a low pressure foaming machine or a high
pressure foaming machine is preferred. Particularly
preferred is a method of molding in a closed mold
(molding method). In the present invention, the flexible
foam may be produced either by a cold curing method or a
hot curing method, but a cold curing method is preferred.</p><p num="0055">The flexible foam produced by using as the material
the polyol (1) or the polymer dispersed polyol of the
present invention, is useful for e.g. a cushion, a
mattress or a seat. It is particularly suitable as a 
seat for vehicles such as automobiles.</p><p num="0056">Now, the present invention will be described in
further detail with reference to Examples. However, it
should be understood that the present invention is by no
means restricted to such specific Examples.</p><p num="0057">Values in foaming formulation in Examples and
Comparative Examples represent parts by mass.</p><p num="0058">Examples X1 to X11 are Production Examples of
polyoxyalkylene polyols of the present invention
(Examples of the present invention), Examples X12 to X17
are Production Examples of comparative polyoxyalkylene
polyols (Comparative Examples), and Example X18 is a
Production Example of a polyol used as a cell opener.</p><p num="0059">Properties of polyols obtained in Production
Examples are shown in Table 1. As properties, the
following items are shown. The proportion (unit: mass%)
of an oxypropylene block chain adjacent to the initiator,
(hereinafter referred to as "PO part (1)") the proportion
(unit: mass%) of an oxypropylene block chain not directly
connected to the initiator (hereinafter referred to as
"PO part (2)"), the proportion (unit: mass%) of an
oxyalkylene random chain (hereinafter referred to as
"random portion (1), random portion (2)"), the
oxyethylene group content (unit: mass%) at each of the
random part (1) and the random part (2) (hereinafter
referred to as EO amount), the proportion (unit: mass%)
of the oxyethylene block chain at the terminal 
(hereinafter referred to as "EO part"), the hydroxyl
value (unit: mgKOH/g), the ratio of primary hydroxyl
groups among terminal hydroxyl groups (unit: mol%) and
the degree of unsaturation (unit: meq/g).</p><p num="0060">The hydroxyl value and the degree of unsaturation
were measured by a method in accordance with JIS K-1557.
In Production Examples, a DMC-METB complex catalyst is
meant for a zinc hexacyanocobaltate-ethylene glycol mono-tert-butyl
ether complex catalyst, a DMC-METB/TBA complex
catalyst is meant for a zinc hexacyanocobaltate-ethylene
glycol mono-tert-butyl ether/tert-butyl alcohol complex
catalyst, a DMC-TBA complex catalyst is meant for a zinc
hexacyanocobaltate-tert-butyl alcohol complex catalyst,
and a DMC-glyme complex catalyst is meant for a zinc
hexacyanocobaltate-glyme complex catalyst.</p><p num="0061">The initiator 1 is a compound having a hydroxyl
value of 168 mgKOH/g obtained by adding propylene oxide
to glycerol, and the initiator 2 is a compound having a
hydroxyl value of 234 mgKOH/g obtained by adding
propylene oxide to glycerol.</p><heading>POLYOL PRODUCTION EXAMPLES</heading><heading>EXAMPLE X1</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol A1</u></heading><p num="0062">1,525 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a
reaction by using a DMC-METB complex catalyst in the
presence of 1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 120°C,
and then 2,833 g of an ethylene oxide/propylene oxide 
mixture containing 11.6 mass% of ethylene oxide was
reacted therewith at about 120°C. Then, potassium
hydroxide was added to the reaction system to change the
catalyst to potassium hydroxide, and using this potassium
hydroxide catalyst, 1,097 g of ethylene oxide was reacted
therewith at about 120°C, and the production was
completed. After the reaction, a treatment with an
adsorbent (synthetic magnesium silicate) and filtration
were carried out to obtain polyol A1 having a hydroxyl
value of 27.3 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X2</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol A2</u></heading><p num="0063">Polyol A2 having a hydroxyl value of 27.8 mgKOH/g
was obtained in the same manner as in the production of
polyol A1 except that 2,833 g of an ethylene
oxide/propylene oxide mixture having an ethylene oxide
content of 23.2 mass% was used.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X3</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol B1</u></heading><p num="0064">2,279 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a
reaction by using a DMC-METB complex catalyst in the
presence of 1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 120°C,
and then 2,278 g of an ethylene oxide/propylene oxide
mixture containing 14.4 mass% of ethylene oxide was
reacted therewith at about 120°C, then 905 g of ethylene
oxide was reacted by using a sodium methoxide catalyst at
about 120°C, and the production was completed. After the 
reaction, a treatment with an adsorbent (synthetic
magnesium silicate) and filtration were carried out to
obtain polyol B1 having a hydroxyl value of 27.6 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X4</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol B2</u></heading><p num="0065">Polyol B2 having a hydroxyl value of 27.8 mgKOH/g
was obtained in the same manner as in the production of
polyol B1 except that a DMC-METB/TBA complex catalyst was
used instead of the DMC-METB complex catalyst.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X5</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol B3</u></heading><p num="0066">Polyol B3 having a hydroxyl value of 27.7 mgKOH/g
was obtained in the same manner as in the production of
polyol B1 except that a DMC-glyme complex catalyst was
used instead of the DMC-METB complex catalyst.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X6</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol C</u></heading><p num="0067">2,473 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a
reaction by using a DMC-METB complex catalyst in the
presence of 1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 120°C,
and then 2,174 g of an ethylene oxide/propylene oxide
mixture containing 14.4 mass% of ethylene oxide was
reacted therewith at about 120°C, then 627 g of ethylene
oxide was reacted therewith by using a sodium methoxide
catalyst at about 120°C, and the production was
completed. After the reaction, a treatment with an
adsorbent (synthetic magnesium silicate) and filtration 
were carried out to obtain polyol C having a hydroxyl
value of 28.1 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X7</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol D</u></heading><p num="0068">3,137 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a
reaction by using a DMC-METB complex catalyst in the
presence of 1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 120°C,
and then 1,259 g of an ethylene oxide/propylene oxide
mixture containing 14.4 mass% of ethylene oxide was
reacted therewith at about 120°C, then 878 g of ethylene
oxide was reacted therewith by using a potassium
hydroxide catalyst at about 120°C, and the production was
completed. After the reaction, a treatment with an
adsorbent (synthetic magnesium silicate) and filtration
were carried out to obtain polyol D having a hydroxyl
value of 28.3 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X8</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol E</u></heading><p num="0069">630 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a reaction
by using a DMC-METB complex catalyst in the presence of
1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 120°C, and then 4,014
g of an ethylene oxide/propylene oxide mixture containing
11 mass% of ethylene oxide was reacted therewith at about
120°C, then 691 g of ethylene oxide was reacted therewith
by using a potassium hydroxide catalyst at about 120°C,
and the production was completed. After the reaction, a
treatment with an adsorbent (synthetic magnesium 
silicate) and filtration were carried out to obtain
polyol E having a hydroxyl value of 27.8 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X9</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol F1</u></heading><p num="0070">2,833 g of an ethylene oxide/propylene oxide mixture
containing 11.6 mass% of ethylene oxide was subjected to
a reaction by using a DMC-METB complex catalyst in the
presence of 1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 120°C,
and then 1,525 g of propylene oxide was reacted therewith
at about 120°C, then 1,097 g of ethylene oxide was
reacted therewith by using a potassium hydroxide catalyst
at about 120°C, and the production was completed. After
the reaction, a treatment with an adsorbent (synthetic
magnesium silicate) and filtration were carried out to
obtain polyol F1 having a hydroxyl value of 27.9 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X10</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol F2</u></heading><p num="0071">Polyol F2 having a hydroxyl value of 26.9 mgKOH/g
was obtained in the same manner as in the production of
polyol F1 except that 2,833 g of an ethylene
oxide/propylene oxide mixture having an ethylene oxide
content of 23.2 mass% was used.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X11</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol G</u></heading><p num="0072">3,817 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a
reaction by using a DMC-METB complex catalyst in the
presence of 1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 120°C, 
and then 591 g of an ethylene oxide/propylene oxide
mixture containing 21.4 mass% of ethylene oxide was
reacted therewith at about 120°C, then 953 g of ethylene
oxide was reacted therewith by using a potassium
hydroxide catalyst at about 120°C, and the production was
completed. After the reaction, a treatment with an
adsorbent (synthetic magnesium silicate) and filtration
were carried out to obtain polyol G having a hydroxyl
value of 28.1 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X12</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol H</u></heading><p num="0073">253 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a reaction
by using a DMC-METB complex catalyst in the presence of
1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 120°C, and then 4,387
g of an ethylene oxide/propylene oxide mixture containing
11 mass% of ethylene oxide was reacted therewith at about
120°C, then 695 g of ethylene oxide was reacted therewith
by using a potassium hydroxide catalyst at about 120°C,
and the production was completed. After the reaction, a
treatment with an adsorbent (synthetic magnesium
silicate) and filtration were carried out to obtain
polyol H having a hydroxyl value of 27.9 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X13</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol J</u></heading><p num="0074">252 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a reaction
by using a DMC-TBA complex catalyst in the presence of
720 g of the initiator 2 at about 120°C, and then 4,487 g 
of an ethylene oxide/propylene oxide mixture containing
13 mass% of ethylene oxide was reacted therewith at about
120°C, then 813 g of an ethylene oxide/propylene oxide
mixture containing 40 mass% of ethylene oxide was reacted
therewith at about 120°C, and the production was
completed. After the reaction, a treatment with an
adsorbent (synthetic magnesium silicate) and filtration
were carried out to obtain polyol J having a hydroxyl
value of 27.9 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X14</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol K</u></heading><p num="0075">5,550 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a
reaction by using a DMC-METB complex catalyst in the
presence of 1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 120°C,
and then 1,103 g of an ethylene oxide was reacted
therewith by using a potassium hydroxide catalyst at
about 120°C, and the production was completed. After the
reaction, a treatment with an adsorbent (synthetic
magnesium silicate) and filtration were carried out to
obtain polyol K having a hydroxyl value of 23.9 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X15</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol L1</u></heading><p num="0076">6,467 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a
reaction by using a potassium hydroxide catalyst in the
presence of 1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 110°C,
and then 1,423 g of ethylene oxide was reacted therewith
at about 110°C, and the production was completed. After 
the reaction, a treatment with an adsorbent (synthetic
magnesium silicate) and filtration were carried out to
obtain polyol L1 having a hydroxyl value of 24 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X16</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol L2</u></heading><p num="0077">5,378 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a
reaction by using a potassium hydroxide catalyst in the
presence of 1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 110°C,
and then 1,257 g of ethylene oxide was reacted therewith
at about 110°C, and the production was completed. After
the reaction, a treatment with an adsorbent (synthetic
magnesium silicate) and filtration were carried out to
obtain polyol L2 having a hydroxyl value of 27.9 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X17</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol L3</u></heading><p num="0078">4,416 g of propylene oxide was subjected to a
reaction by using a potassium hydroxide catalyst in the
presence of 1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 110°C,
and then 904 g of ethylene oxide was reacted therewith at
about 110°C, and the production was completed. After the
reaction, a treatment with an adsorbent (synthetic
magnesium silicate) and filtration were carried out to
obtain polyol L3 having a hydroxyl value of 35.5 mgKOH/g.</p><heading>EXAMPLE X18</heading><heading><u style="single">Production of polyol T</u></heading><p num="0079">5,000 g of an ethylene oxide/propylene oxide mixture
containing 80 mass% of ethylene oxide was subjected to a 
reaction by using a potassium hydroxide catalyst in the
presence of 1,000 g of the initiator 1 at about 120°C,
and the production was completed. After the reaction, a
treatment with an adsorbent (synthetic magnesium
silicate) and filtration were carried out to obtain
polyol T having a hydroxyl value of 27.9 mgKOH/g. <img id="img-00340001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00340001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Crosslinking agent a1</entry><entry align="left">Propylene oxide/ethylene oxide addition product of sorbitol, hydroxyl value: 450 mgKOH/g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Crosslinking agent a2</entry><entry align="left">Diethanolamine</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Catalyst b1</entry><entry align="left">Dipropylene glycol (DPG) solution of triethylenediamine (TEDA L-33, tradename, manufactured by TOSOH CORPORATION)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Catalyst b2</entry><entry align="left">DPG solution of bis-[(2-dimethylamino)ethyl]ether (TOYOCAT ET, tradename, manufactured by TOSOH CORPORATION)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Foam stabilizer c</entry><entry align="left">Silicone foam stabilizer (SRX-274C, tradename, manufactured by TORAY SILICONE)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cell opener</entry><entry align="left">Polyol T</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Blowing agent</entry><entry align="left">Water</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyol N</entry><entry align="left">Polymer dispersed polyol wherein acrylonitrile/styrene copolymer particles (20 mass%) are dispersed in polyol A1 (80 mass%) as a dispersion medium</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyol P</entry><entry align="left">Polymer dispersed polyol wherein acrylonitrile/styrene copolymer particles (20 mass%) are dispersed in polyol C (80 mass%) as a dispersion medium</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyol Q</entry><entry align="left">Polymer dispersed polyol wherein acrylonitrile/styrene copolymer particles (20 mass%) are dispersed in polyol K(80 mass%) as a dispersion medium</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyol R</entry><entry align="left">Polymer dispersed polyol wherein acrylonitrile/styrene copolymer particles (20 mass%) are dispersed in polyol L2 (80 mass%) as a dispersion medium</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyol S</entry><entry align="left">Polymer dispersed polyol wherein acrylonitrile/styrene copolymer particles (22 mass%) are dispersed in polyol L3 (78 mass%) as a dispersion medium</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyisocyanate</entry><entry align="left">Mixture of TDI-80 (mixture of 2,4-TDI/2,6-TDI=80/20 mass%)/crude MDI=80/20 mass%, isocyanate group content: 44.8 mass% (Coronate 1021, tradename, manufactured by NIPPON POLYURETHANE INDUSTRY CO., LTD.)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0080">A flexible polyurethane foam was produced by using
materials shown in Table 2 in an amount shown in Table 3 
or 4. A mixture of all the materials except for
polyisocyanate (polyol system) and a polyisocyanate
compound were respectively adjusted to have a liquid
temperature of 25±1°C, the polyisocyanate compound was
added to the polyol system, followed by mixing with
stirring by a high-speed mixer for 5 seconds, and the
mixture was immediately poured and closed in an aluminum
mold in a size of 400 mm lengthwise and breadthwise and
100 mm in height, heated to 60°C. After curing for 6
minutes, a polyurethane foam was taken out and left to
stand for at least 24 hours, and then various physical
properties were measured. The results are shown in
Tables 3 and 4.</p><p num="0081">The crushing property was evaluated as the
characteristics of the moldability. The crushing
property was evaluated by productivity when the foam was
compressed up to 25% of the thickness of the foam and the
foam cells were released, immediately after the foam was
taken out from the mold (400 mm × 400 mm × 100 mm), and
evaluated in accordance with such evaluation standards
that ○: good, Δ: rather poor. Further, the load applied
to the surface of 400 mm × 400 mm at the time of
compression was evaluated as the crushing load (unit: N).
Here, the measurement methods of the foam physical
properties were in accordance with the following methods,
and with regard to the core density, one cut into a size
of 100 mm lengthwise and breadthwise and 50 mm in height, 
having the skin portion removed from the center portion
of the foam, was used for measurement.</p><p num="0082">With regard to the resonance frequency, there is a
correlation between the molded foam for test piece having
a size of 400 mm × 400 mm × 100 mm and an actual molded
foam for a seat cushion, and the actual molded foam tends
to have a resonance frequency higher than that of the
test piece by from about 0.2 to about 1 Hz, depending
upon e.g. the thickness and shape in general.</p><p num="0083">The degree of unsaturation in Tables 3 and 4 is the
degree of total unsaturation (unit: meq/g) of the polyol
or the base polyol in the polymer dispersed polyol.</p><p num="0084">Now, standards used for measurement of the physical
properties of the flexible foam are shown below.</p><p num="0085">Overall density (unit: kg/m<sup>3</sup>), core density (unit:
kg/m<sup>3</sup>), 25%-ILD hardness (unit: N/314 cm<sup>2</sup>), core impact
resilience coefficient (unit: %), tear strength (N/cm),
tensile strength (kPa), elongation (%), dry heat
permanent compression set (unit: %) and heat and humidity
permanent compression set (unit: %) were measured by
methods in accordance with JIS K6400. Hysteresis loss
(unit: %) was measured by a method in accordance with
JASO B407-87. Resonance frequency (unit: Hz) and
transmissibility at 6 Hz were measured by methods in
accordance with JASO B407-87 (excitation amplitude: ±2.5
mm, pressing plate: iron abrasive plate, load: 490 N). <img id="img-00380001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00380001.tif" inline="no" he="229"/><img id="img-00390001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00390001.tif" inline="no" he="232"/></p><p num="0086">Examples 1 to 11 in Tables 3 and 4 are Examples of
the present invention. As the polyol (1) produced in
such a manner that propylene oxide is subjected to a
reaction continuously in an amount of from 5 to 50 mass%
adjacent to the initiator by using the double metal
cyanide complex catalyst, ethylene oxide and propylene
oxide are randomly reacted therewith, and then ethylene
oxide is reacted therewith by using an alkali metal
catalyst, is used as the material, a foam having
favorable moldability, favorable physical properties such
as hardness and vibrating property, and favorable
durability particularly heat and humid permanent
compression set can be obtained. Particularly in
Examples 10 and 11, as the polyol T is used as the cell
opener, the crushing load can be suppressed low, and
favorable moldability is obtained.</p><p num="0087">Examples 12 to 18 in Table 4 are Comparative
Examples.</p><p num="0088">In Examples 12 and 18, puncture was formed on the
foam at the time of crushing treatment, whereby physical
properties could not be measured.</p><p num="0089">In Examples 13, in order to make up for failure in
moldability caused by the polyol K used as the material
produced by using the double metal cyanide complex
catalyst not having an oxyalkylene random chain, the
polyol L2 synthesized by using a potassium hydroxide
catalyst is mixed and used as the material, whereby the 
degree of total unsaturation of the polyol is high, and
the durability is insufficient. Further, the moldability
is not sufficient.</p><p num="0090">In Example 14, the polyol produced with a potassium
hydroxide catalyst is used, whereby the durability is
poor.</p><p num="0091">In Example 15, a polyol wherein the oxypropylene
block chain adjacent to the initiator is 60 mass% based
on the entire polyol is used, whereby the reactivity with
the polyisocyanate is insufficient, and the hardness is
low.</p><p num="0092">In Example 16, a polyol wherein the oxypropylene
block chain adjacent to the initiator is 4 mass% based on
the entire polyol is used, whereby the hardness is
insufficient.</p><p num="0093">In Example 17, at the terminal of the polyol L
produced by using the double metal cyanide complex
catalyst, production was not terminated with the reaction
of ethylene oxide, whereby collapses were generated and a
foam could not be formed, and physical properties could
not be measured.</p><p num="0094">By employing a polyol having a specific structure of
the present invention, a flexible polyurethane foam
having improved moldability, and favorable physical
properties such as hardness and vibrating property can be
obtained. Further, the polyol (1) of the present
invention is produced by using a double metal cyanide 
complex catalyst, whereby physical properties such as
durability particularly heat and humidity permanent
compression set are also excellent.</p><p num="0095">The entire disclosure of Japanese Patent Application
No. 2001-218348 filed on July 18, 2001 and Japanese
Patent Application No. 2002-32839 filed on February 8,
2002 including specification, claims and summary are
incorporated herein by reference in its entirety.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for producing a polyoxyalkylene polyol which
comprises subjecting propylene oxide and ethylene oxide
to ring-opening addition polymerization with an initiator
in the presence of a catalyst,
   wherein the polyoxyalkylene polyol is a
polyoxyalkylene polyol obtained by subjecting propylene
oxide to ring-opening addition polymerization with an
initiator in the presence of a double metal cyanide
complex catalyst to form an oxypropylene block chain,
subjecting ethylene oxide and propylene oxide to ring-opening
addition polymerization randomly to form an
oxyalkylene random chain, changing the catalyst and
subjecting ethylene oxide to ring-opening addition
polymerization in the presence of an alkali metal
catalyst to form an oxyethylene block chain,
   and the polyoxyalkylene polyol is a polyoxyalkylene
polyol having a hydroxyl value of from 5 to 56 mgKOH/g, a
proportion of an initiator residue of at most 25 mass%, a
proportion of the oxypropylene block chain of from 5 to
50 mass%, a total oxyethylene group content of from 5 to
60 mass%, and a ratio of primary hydroxyl groups among
terminal hydroxyl groups of at least 60 mol%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method for producing a polyoxyalkylene polyol
according to Claim 1, wherein in the formation of the
oxyalkylene random chain, the proportion of ethylene
oxide to propylene oxide to be subjected to the ring-opening
addition polymerization is within a range of from
3/97 to 35/65 in a mass ratio.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method for producing a polyoxyalkylene polyol
according to Claim 1 or 2, wherein the double metal
cyanide complex catalyst has a compound of the following
formula as at least part of organic ligands:
R1-C(CH3)2(OR0)nOH
wherein R1 is a methyl group or an ethyl group, R0 is an
ethylene group or a group having a hydrogen atom of an
ethylene group substituted with a methyl group or an
ethyl group, and n is an integer of from 1 to 3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method for producing a polyoxyalkylene polyol
according to Claim 1, 2 or 3, wherein the proportion of
the oxyethylene block chain in the polyoxyalkylene polyol
is from 3 to 40 mass%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method for producing a polyoxyalkylene polyol
according to Claim 1, 2, 3 or 4, wherein the proportion
of the oxyalkylene random chain in the polyoxyalkylene
polyol is from 5 to 90 mass%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method for producing a polymer dispersed polyol,
which comprises polymerizing a monomer having
polymerizable unsaturated groups by employing the
polyoxyalkylene polyol obtained by the production method
as defined in any one of Claims 1 to 5 as a dispersion
medium.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method for producing a flexible polyurethane foam
which comprises reacting a polyol compound and a
polyisocyanate compound in the presence of a blowing
agent and a catalyst, wherein as the polyol compound, a
polyol mixture containing the polyoxyalkylene polyol
obtained by the production method as defined in any one
of Claims 1 to 5 and/or the polymer dispersed polyol
obtained by the production method as defined in Claim 6,
is used.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method for producing a flexible polyurethane foam
according to Claim 7, wherein the degree of total
unsaturation of the polyol compound is at most 0.05 meq/g.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method for producing a flexible polyurethane foam
according to Claim 7 or 8, wherein a cell opener is added
to produce the flexible polyurethane foam.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method for producing a flexible polyurethane
foam according to Claim 7, 8 or 9, wherein the flexible
polyurethane foam is produced in a sealed mold.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>