<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1006151-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1006151" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22744266" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000607"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1006151-A1" status="new" fvid="22834639"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1006151</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000607</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99123473-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99123473</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991125</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-20105098-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20105098</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981130</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   8/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   8/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   8/18        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   8/42        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 210/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 210/10        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/24        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/24        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/10        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/12        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/22        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  51/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  51/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/05        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F   8/42</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  51/06+B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L23:10</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Thermoplastische Vulkanisate von Vernetzung mittels Hydrosilylierung von acrylmodifiziertem Bromparamethylstyrol-Isobutylen Kautschuk</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Themoplastic vulcanisate from hydrosilylation crosslinking of acrylic modified bromoparamethylstyrene-isobutylene rubber</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Vulcanisé thermoplastique de réticulation par hydrosilylation de bromoparaméthylstyrène-isobutylène caoutchouc modifié par un composé acrylique</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0651009-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0651009</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1995009197-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1995009197</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1996040800-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1996040800</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ADVANCED ELASTOMER SYSTEMS</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ADVANCED ELASTOMER SYSTEMS, L.P.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Advanced Elastomer Systems, L.P.</last-name><address><street>388 South Main Street</street><city>Akron, Ohio 44311-1059</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MEDSKER ROBERT E</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PATEL RAMAN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WANG DONALD S T</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MEDSKER, ROBERT E.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PATEL, RAMAN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WANG, DONALD S.T.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MEDSKER, ROBERT E.</last-name><address><street>13145 Kaufman Avenue</street><city>Hartville, Ohio 44632</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PATEL, RAMAN</last-name><address><street>578 Sun Valley Drive</street><city>Akron, Ohio 4431</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WANG, DONALD S.T.</last-name><address><street>402 Misty Lane</street><city>Akron, Ohio 44333</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Weber, Thomas, Dr.</last-name><address><street>Patentanwälte von Kreisler-Selting-Werner, Deichmannhaus am Dom</street><city>50667 Köln</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An improved process for the preparation of thermoplastic vulcanizates
from butyl rubbers by hydrosilylation crosslinking of acrylic or alkacrylic
functionalized copolymers of isobutylene and paramethylstyrene is disclosed.
The functionalization results in lower compression and tension set than when
using conventional butyl rubbers. Other physical properties of the
thermoplastic vulcanizate are improved consistent with more efficient
crosslinking of the functionalized copolymer.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep"  status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to thermoplastic vulcanizate compositions
prepared using hydrosilylation crosslinking of the rubber component of the
composition. A thermoplastic vulcanizate is generally defined as a polymer or
blend of polymers that can be processed and recycled in the same way as a
conventional thermoplastic material, yet has properties and functional
performance similar to that of vulcanized rubber at service temperatures.
Blends or alloys of plastic and rubber have become increasingly important in
the production of high performance thermoplastic vulcanizates, particularly for
the replacement of thermoset rubbers in various applications. The acrylic
modification of the butyl rubber results in faster, more efficient crosslinking of
butyl rubber with hydrosilylation crosslinking.</p><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0002">Polymer blends which have a combination of both thermoplastic and
elastic properties are generally obtained by combining a thermoplastic resin
with an elastomeric composition in a way such that the elastomer component
is intimately and uniformly dispersed as a discrete particulate phase within a
continuous phase of the thermoplastic. Early work with vulcanized rubber
components is found in U.S. Pat. No. 3,037,954 which discloses both static
vulcanization of the rubber, as well as the technique of dynamic vulcanization
wherein a vulcanizable elastomer is dispersed into a molten resinous
thermoplastic polymer and the elastomer is cured while continuously mixing 
and shearing the blend. The resulting composition is a micro-gel dispersion of
cured elastomer in an uncured matrix of thermoplastic polymer.</p><p num="0003">In U.S. Pat. No. Re. 32,028 polymer blends comprising an olefin
thermoplastic resin and an olefin copolymer are described, wherein the rubber
is dynamically vulcanized to a state of partial cure. The resulting
compositions are reprocessible. U.S. Pat. Nos. 4,130,534 and 4,130,535
further disclose thermoplastic vulcanizates comprising butyl rubber and
polyolefin resin, and olefin rubber and polyolefin resin, respectively. The
compositions are prepared by dynamic vulcanization and the rubber
component is cured to the extent that it is essentially insoluble in conventional
solvents. A range of crosslinking, or curing, agents for the vulcanization of
the rubber are described in the early art, including peroxides, sulfurs, phenolic
resins, radiation, and the like.</p><p num="0004">U.S. Pat. No. 4,803,244 generally discusses the use of multifunctional
organosilicon compounds in conjunction with a catalyst as an agent for
crosslinking the rubber component of a thermoplastic elastomer by
hydrosilylation. Hydrosilylation involves the addition of a silicon hydride
across a multiple bond, often with a transition metal catalyst. This patent
describes a rhodium catalyzed hydrosilylation of EPDM rubber in a blend with
polypropylene.</p><p num="0005">A further modification of hydrosilylation crosslinking of the rubber in
a thermoplastic elastomer composition is disclosed in European Patent
Application No. 651,009. A compatibilizing agent containing in the same
molecule a component having an affinity for the rubber and a component 
having an affinity for the thermoplastic resin is incorporated into the
composition, and is said to improve adhesion between the rubber and resin in
order to prevent agglomeration.</p><p num="0006">U.S. Patent 5,672,660 generally describes thermoplastic elastomers
prepared by hydrosilylation crosslinking of rubbers polymerized from
monomers including specific dienes. The use of lower amounts of platinum
catalysts was also described.</p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0007">The present invention is based on the discovery that the process for
hydrosilylation crosslinking of the rubber in a thermoplastic vulcanizate
wherein the rubber is a copolymer of at least isobutylene and
paramethyltyrene which was post polymerization functionalized with a
carbon-carbon double bond from an acrylic or alkacrylic group. This
combination provides rapid crosslinking of the rubber to a fully vulcanized
state, yet requires an unexpectedly low concentration of the catalyst in order to
achieve the cure. In the instant invention no compatibilizer is required in order
to produce compositions with excellent mechanical properties, no bubble
formation and very good colorability, due to the extremely low levels of
catalyst concentration. Surprisingly, lower catalyst concentrations also
produce compositions with much improved heat aging characteristics,
resistance to degradation by ultraviolet light and having a non-hygroscopic
character.</p><p num="0008">The compositions produced by the improved process have utility as
replacements for thermoset rubber compounds in a variety of applications, 
particularly where molding or extrusion is involved and the combination of
thermoplastic and elastomeric properties provides an advantage. Typical uses
include molded articles for automobile underhood parts, engineering and
construction materials, mechanical rubber goods, industrial parts such as hose,
tubing and gaskets, electrical applications and household goods.</p><heading><b>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</b></heading><p num="0009">Thermoplastic vulcanizate compositions may generally be prepared by
blending a thermoplastic resin and a rubber, then melting the thermoplastic
component and mixing the melt until the blend is homogeneous. If a
composition of vulcanized rubber in a thermoplastic matrix is desired,
crosslinking agents (also referred to as curatives or vulcanizing agents) are
added to the blend and crosslinking occurs during the mixing. This latter
process is described as dynamic vulcanization.</p><p num="0010">A wide range of thermoplastic resins and rubbers and/or their mixtures
have been used in the preparation of thermoplastic elastomers, including
polypropylene, HDPE, LDPE,VLDPE, LLDPE, cyclic olefin homopolymers
or copolymes as well as olefinic block copolymers, polystyrene,
polyphenylene sulfide, polyphenylene oxide and ethylene propylene
copolymer (EP) thermoplastics, with ethylene propylene diene rubber
(EPDM), acrylonitrile butadiene rubber (NBR) and natural rubber (NR) as the
elastomers. When the elastomer component is crosslinked, agents such as
sulfur, peroxide, phenolics and ionic compounds are often used. </p><heading><u style="single">Hydrosilylation Agents</u></heading><p num="0011">Hydrosilylation has also been disclosed as a crosslinking method. In
this method a silicon hydride having at least two SiH groups in the molecule is
reacted with the carbon-carbon multiple bonds of the unsaturated (i.e.
containing at least one carbon-carbon double bond) rubber component of the
thermoplastic elastomer, in the presence of the thermoplastic resin and a
hydrosilylation catalyst. Silicon hydride compounds useful in the process of
the invention include methylhydrogen polysiloxanes, methylhydrogen
dimethyl-siloxane copolymers, alkyl methyl polysiloxanes,
bis(dimethylsilyl)alkanes and bis(dimethylsilyl)benzene.</p><p num="0012">Preferred silicon hydride compounds may be described by the formula
<img id="img-00050001" orientation="unknown" wi="115" img-format="tif"  img-content="cf"  file="00050001.tif"  inline="no" he="39"/>
where each R is independently selected from the group consisting of alkyls
comprising 1 to 20 carbon atoms, cycloalkyls comprising 4 to 12 carbon atoms
and aryls. In formula (1) it is preferred that each R be independently selected
from a group consisting of alkyls comprising 1 to 6 carbon atoms. Even more
preferred is R = methyl. R' represents a hydrogen atom, an alkyl or alkoxy
group having from 1 to about 24 carbon atoms. R'' represents R or a hydrogen
atom. <sl><li>D represents the group
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="41" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="45"/></li><li>D' represents the group
<img id="img-00060002" orientation="unknown" wi="52" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060002.tif" inline="no" he="49"/></li><li>T represents the group
<img id="img-00060003" orientation="unknown" wi="39" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060003.tif" inline="no" he="48"/></li><li>m is an integer having a value ranging from 1 to 50,</li><li>n is an integer having a value ranging from 1 to 50, and</li><li>p is an integer having a value ranging from 0 to 6.</li></sl></p><p num="0013">Particularly preferred polyorganosiloxanes are those in which the
silicon atom of the silicon hydride functionality is bound by
heteroatoms/atoms having lone pairs of electrons. The preferred 
polyorganosiloxanes may also be substituted with appropriate functionality
permitting solubility in the reaction media. A type of this functionalization is
described in U.S. Pat. No. 4,046,930 which teaches alkylation of
polyorganosiloxanes. Weight percent of alkylation should not exceed a level
that does not permit adequate reaction rates due to steric constraints.</p><p num="0014">The amount of silicon hydride compound useful in the process of the
present invention can range from about 0.1 to about 10.0 mole equivalents of
SiH per carbon-carbon double bond in the rubber, and preferably is in the
range of about 0.5 to about 5.0 mole equivalents of SiH per carbon-carbon
double bond in the rubber component of the thermoplastic elastomer.</p><heading><u style="single">Thermoplastic Resins</u></heading><p num="0015">Thermoplastic resins useful in the compositions produced by the
invention include crystalline polyolefin homopolymers and copolymers. They
are desirably prepared from monoolefin monomers having 2 to 20 carbon
atoms, such as ethylene, propylene, 1-butene, 1-pentene and the like, as well
as copolymers derived from linear and cyclic olefins, with propylene being
preferred. As used in the specification and claims the term polypropylene
includes homopolymers of propylene as well as reactor copolymers of
polypropylene which can contain about 1 to about 20 wt% of ethylene or an -
olefin comonomer of 4 to 20 carbon atoms, and mixtures thereof. The
polypropylene can be crystalline, isotactic or syndiotactic polypropylene.
Commercially available polyolefins may be used in the practice of the
invention. Other thermoplastic resins which are substantially inert to the 
rubber, the silicon hydride and the hydrosilylation catalyst would also be
suitable. Blends of thermoplastic resins may also be used.</p><p num="0016">The amount of thermoplastic resin found to provide useful
compositions is generally from about 5 to about 90 weight percent, based on
the weight of the rubber and resin. Preferably, the thermoplastic resin content
will range from about 20 to about 80 percent by weight of the total polymer.
This can also be expressed as a weight ratio of the thermoplastic resin to the
rubber(s) of 5:95 to 90:10 more desirably 20:80 to 80:20.</p><heading><u style="single">Rubbers</u></heading><p num="0017">Desirably the rubber is an acrylic or alkacrylic group functionalized
(modified by adding the functional group) copolymer of at least isobutylene
and paramethylstyrene. By the term acrylic or alkacrylic group, applicant
means acrylic or aklacrylic or combinations thereof. The term alkacrylic is
intended to express that the acrylic can have an alkyl or alkenyl substituent
thereon of 1 to 5 carbon atoms, preferably methyl or ethyl. The
functionalization reaction involves halogenating the copolymer of isobutylene
and paramethyl styrene as set forth in EP publication no. 0 344 021 (preferably
by bromination) and then reacting the brominated polymer with <img id="img-00090001" orientation="unknown" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00090001.tif" inline="no" he="107"/>
where R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> are H or an alkyl of 1 to 5 carbon atoms and R<sub>3</sub> is H, an alkyl
or an alkenyl of 1 to 5 carbon atoms. The amount of acrylic or alkacrylic
groups per polymer chain can vary depending on the properties desired.
Desirably, the number of moles of acrylic or alkacrylic or combinations
thereof, if both are present, is from about 0.1 to about 5 moles %, more
desirably from about 0.3 to about 1.5 moles % based upon the total moles of
repeat units..</p><p num="0018">Desirably, the copolymer of isobutylene and paramethylstyrene
comprises repeat units from at least isobutylene and paramethyltyrene. Other
copolymerizable monomers can be present in small amounts. The amount of
repeating units from isobutylene is desirably from about 80 to about 99 weight
percent, more desirably from about 90 to about 99 weight percent and the 
amount of repeat units from paramethylstyrene is from about 1 to about 20
weight percent and more desirably from about 1 to about 10 weight percent.</p><p num="0019">While a preferred embodiment is using the acrylic or alkacrylic group,
or combinations thereof functionalized copolymer of isobutylene and
paramethylstyrene as the entire rubber component, it is possible to use a blend
of said copolymer with the rubbers listed below. Desirably in a blend of the
copolymer with other rubbers the copolymer is a majority by weight of the
total rubbers in the thermoplastic vulcanizate.</p><p num="0020">Unsaturated rubbers useful to prepare thermoplastic vulcanizates
include monoolefin copolymer rubbers comprising non-polar, rubbery
copolymers of two or more -monoolefins, preferably copolymerized with at
least one polyene, usually a diene. However, unsaturated monoolefin rubber
such as EPDM rubber is more suitable. EPDM is a polymer of ethylene,
propylene and one or more non-conjugated diene or non-conjugated dienes,
and the monomer components may be polymerized using Ziegler-Natta or
metallocene catalyzed reactions, among others. Satisfactory non-conjugated
dienes include 5-ethylidene-2-norbornene (ENB); 1,4-hexadiene (HD); 5-methylene-2-norbornene
(MNB); 1,6-octadiene; 5-methyl-1,4-hexadiene; 3,7-dimethyl-1,6-octadiene;
1,3-cyclopentadiene; 1,4-cyclohexadiene;
dicyclopentadiene (DCPD); 5-vinyl-2-norbornene (VNB) and the like, or a
combination thereof.</p><p num="0021">It has been found that rubber having a structure in which the diene
monomer has carbon-carbon multiple bonds which are predominately
unencumbered, i.e. bonds which are sterically unhindered such as terminal or 
pendant double bonds, provide a greatly improved rate of cure in the
hydrosilylation curing process of the invention. Structures in which the bonds
either normally are unencumbered or are easily isomerized to form a sterically
unencumbered double bond, are rapidly hydrosilated, e.g. 1,4-hexadiene or
ENB. This use of sterically unhindered carbon-carbon multiple bonds is
particularly beneficial where a fully cured rubber component is desired. The
use of an additional rubber in which the diene component is selected from the
group consisting of 5-ethylidene-2-norbornene, 5-methyl-1,4-hexadiene, 1,4-hexadiene
and 5-vinyl-2-norbomene is preferred. 5-vinyl-2-norbomene is
particularly preferred as a diene component of such rubber.</p><p num="0022">Butyl rubbers are also useful as additional rubbers in the compositions
of the invention. As used in the specification and claims, the term "butyl
rubber" includes copolymers of an isoolefin and a conjugated monoolefin,
terpolymers of an isooolefin, a conjugated monoolefin and divinyl aromatic
monomers, and the halogenated derivatives of such copolymers and
terpolymers. The useful butyl rubber copolymers comprise a major portion of
isoolefin and a minor amount, usually less than 30 wt%, of a conjugated
multiolefin. The preferred copolymers comprise about 85-99.5 wt% of a C<sub>4-7</sub>
isoolefin such as isobutylene and about 15-0.5 wt% of a multiolefin of 4-14
carbon atoms, such as isoprene, butadiene, dimethyl butadiene, 4-methyl-1,4-pentadiene
and piperylene. Commercial butyl rubber, useful in the invention,
is a copolymer of isobutylene and minor amounts of isoprene. Other butyl co-and
terpolymer rubbers are illustrated by the description in U.S. Pat. No. 
4,916,180. Isobutylene/divinylbenzene is particularly preferred as an
elastomer suitable for hydrosilylation crosslinking.</p><p num="0023">A further rubber suitable in the invention is natural rubber. The main
constituent of natural rubber is the linear polymer cis-1,4-polyisoprene. It is
normally commercially available in the form of smoked sheets and crepe.
Synthetic polyisoprene can also be used with the particularly preferred
synthetic polyisoprene elastomers being those that contain vinyl functionality
pendant to the main polymer chain, i.e. 1,2-enchainments.</p><p num="0024">Polybutadiene is also a suitable elastomer for hydrosilylation curing
with polybutadienes that contain vinyl functionality being the most preferred.</p><p num="0025">In preparing the compositions of the invention, the amount of rubber
generally ranges from about 95 to about 10 weight percent, based on the
weight of the rubber and thermoplastic resin. Preferably, the rubber content
will be in the range of from about 80 to about 20 weight percent of total
polymer.</p><heading><u style="single">Hydrosilylation Catalysts</u></heading><p num="0026">It has previously been understood that any catalyst, or catalyst
precursor capable of generating a catalyst in situ, which will catalyze the
hydrosilylation reaction with the carbon-carbon bonds of the rubber can be
used. Such catalysts have included transition metals of Group VIII such as
palladium, rhodium, platinum and the like, including complexes of these
metals. Chloroplatinic acid has been disclosed as a useful catalyst in U.S. Pat.
No. 4,803,244 and European Application No. 651,009, which further disclose
that the catalyst may be used at concentrations of 5 to 10,000 parts per million 
by weight and 100 to 200,000 parts per million by weight based on the weight
of rubber, respectively.</p><p num="0027">It has been found in the process of the present invention that
significantly lower concentrations of platinum-containing catalyst can be
used, while obtaining improvement in both the speed of the reaction and the
efficiency of the crosslinking. Concentrations of catalyst in the range of about
0.1 to about 10, 20, or 40 parts per million by weight, expressed as platinum
metal, are effective in rapidly and completely curing the rubber in the process
of dynamically vulcanizing blends of thermoplastic resin and rubber. These
low catalyst concentrations are particularly effective in combination with
acrylic or alkacrylic or combinations thereof functionalized copolymer of
isobutylene and paramethyl styrene having carbon-carbon multiple bonds
which are predominately sterically unhindered Catalyst concentrations of
about 1 to about 25 parts per million by weight based on the weight of rubber,
expressed as platinum metal, are particularly preferred.</p><p num="0028">Platinum-containing catalysts which are useful in the process of the
invention are described, for example, in U.S. Pat. No. 4,578,497; U.S. Pat. No.
3,220,972; and U.S. Patent No. 2,823,218 all of which are incorporated herein
by this reference. These catalysts include chloroplatinic acid, chloroplatinic
acid hexahydrate, complexes of chloroplatinic acid with symdivinyltetramethyldisiloxane,
dichloro-bis(triphenylphosphine) platinum (II),
cis-dichloro-bis(acetonitrile) platinum (II), dicarbonyldichioroplatinum (II),
platinum chloride and platinum oxide. Zero valent platinum metal complexes
such as Karstedt's catalyst are particularly preferred, as described in U.S. Pat. 
No. 3,775,452; U.S. Pat. No. 3,814,730; and U.S. Pat. No. 4,288,345 all of
which are incorporated herein by this reference.</p><p num="0029">In order for the catalyst to function most efficiently in the dynamic
vulcanization environment, it is important that it is inherently thermally stable,
or that its activity is inhibited to prevent too rapid a reaction or catalyst
decomposition. Appropriate catalyst inhibitors that are suitable to stabilize the
platinum catalyst at high temperatures include 1,3,5,7-tetravinyl-1,3,5,7-tetramethylcyclotetrasiloxane
and its higher analogs such as methylvinyl
cyclic pentamer. However, other olefins that provide stable, yet catalytically
active platinum metal complexes include maleates, fumarates, and substituted
alkynes. It is also particularly preferred in the invention to use a catalyst that
remains soluble in the reaction medium.</p><heading><u style="single">Additives</u></heading><p num="0030">The thermoplastic elastomer may contain conventional additives,
which can be introduced into the composition in the thermoplastic resin, the
rubber, or in the blend either before, during or after the hydrosilylation and
curing. Examples of such additives are antioxidants, processing aids,
reinforcing and nonreinforcing fillers, pigments, waxes, rubber processing oil,
extender oils, antiblocking agents, antistatic agents, ultraviolet stabilizers,
plasticizers (including esters), foaming agents, flame retardants and other
processing aids known to the rubber compounding art. Such additives may
comprise from about 0.1 to about 300 percent by weight based on the weight
of the final thermoplastic elastomer product. Fillers and extenders which can
be utilized include conventional inorganics such as calcium carbonate, clays, 
silica, talc, titanium dioxide, carbon black and the like. Additives, fillers or
other compounds which may interfere with the hydrosilylation should be
added after curing reaches the desired level.</p><p num="0031">In another embodiment, it has been found that the heat aging properties
of compositions prepared according to the invention can be greatly improved
by the addition of a metal chelating agent to the blend. This effect is believed
to be due to the fact that the hydrosilylation catalyst is in an active valence
state. This form of the platinum metal accelerates degradation of the
thermoplastic elastomer, particularly under conditions of elevated temperature
over an extended time. Chelation prevents the metal from causing
degradation.</p><p num="0032">Typical chelating agents useful for this purpose include materials such
as 1,2-bis(3,5-di-ter-butyl-4-hydroxyhydrocinnamoyl)hydrazine and the like.
Surprisingly, these agents may be incorporated into the composition prior to or
after the hydrosilylation curing. Amounts of chelating agent ranging from
about 0.025 parts per hundred parts of rubber (phr) to about 10 phr have been
found to be useful, and amounts in the range of about 0.1 phr to 2 phr are
preferred.</p><p num="0033">In a further embodiment of the invention, it has been demonstrated that
reducing residual or unreacted silicon hydride functionality in the
thermoplastic elastomer products results in compositions which have
improved heat stability. Unreacted silicon hydride may be reduced or
eliminated by reacting the silicon hydride with compounds containing active
hydrogen, carbon-carbon multiple bonds, carbon-oxygen double bonds or 
carbon-nitrogen double bonds and the like. The residual silicon hydride reacts
with these compounds to eliminate silicon hydride functionality and form
silicon-oxygen or carbon-silicon bonds.</p><p num="0034">Typical compounds useful for this purpose are silica and water.
These agents are incorporated into the composition after the hydrosilylation
cure is complete. Water may be introduced as steam anytime after cure in a
single or two pass operation. Amounts of such compounds may be estimated
by measuring residual silicon hydride and adding a stoichiometric amount of
the compound. One may also desire to add a stoichiometric excess if
necessary to eliminate a sufficient amount of the residual silicon hydride in
order to realize the desired improvement in heat aging properties. Amounts of
such compounds ranging from about one mole equivalent to about 10 mole
equivalents have been found to be useful, and amounts in the range of about 1
to 3 mole equivalents are preferred.</p><heading><u style="single">Extender Oil</u></heading><p num="0035">The rubber processing or extender oils used in thermoplastic
elastomers generally are paraffinic, naphthenic or aromatic oils derived from
petroleum fractions. The type will be that ordinarily used in conjunction with
the specific rubber or rubbers present in the composition, and the quantity
based on the total rubber content of the thermoplastic elastomer may range
from zero to several hundred pans per hundred rubber. Important to the
efficiency of the catalyst is that the oils and other additives contain no or very
low concentrations of compounds that are catalyst inhibitors or that interfere
with the activity of the catalyst. These compounds include phosphines, 
amines, sulfides, thiols or other compounds that may be classified as Lewis
bases. Lewis bases, or other compounds that have a pair of electrons available
for donation, will react with the platinum catalyst, effectively neutralizing its
activity. It has been discovered that the presence of such compounds has a
surprisingly detrimental impact on hydrosilylation curing in the process of
dynamic vulcanization of the rubber component of the thermoplastic elastomer
compositions. If the concentration of compounds which have the chemical
reactivity of Lewis bases, such as compounds containing sulfur or nitrogen, is
maintained at or below a level which provides less than about 1000 ppm and
300 ppm of sulfur and nitrogen respectively, then the amount of platinum
catalyst required to promote efficient hydrosilylation curing in dynamic
vulcanization can be substantially reduced, usually to the range of about 4 ppm
or less, without impact on the cure state of the rubber or the tensile properties
of the thermoplastic elastomer product. Concentrations of sulfur and nitrogen
below about 500 and 200 ppm respectively are, more preferred, and
concentrations of less than about 30 ppm sulfur and less than about 100 ppm
nitrogen are most preferred. It has been discovered that, even at catalyst
concentrations as low as 0.25 ppm, full cure of the elastomer can be achieved
if the concentration of sulfur and nitrogen is within the most preferred ranges.</p><p num="0036">Most paraffinic petroleum oils for the rubber industry are derived from
a crude oil distillation stream. A typical refining history would include some
type of dewaxing to reduce the pour point, a solvent extraction to physically
remove aromatic compounds and a hydrotreating process to chemically
modify aromatic structures. Both extraction and hydrotreating result in a net 
increase in the total concentration of saturated hydrocarbon structures and a
net decrease in the total aromatic, sulfur and nitrogen-containing compound
concentration. The degree of reduction in concentration of these compounds
in the oil is dependent upon the type and severity of the refining employed,
and the nature of the crude oil. White and paraffinic oils have been treated
more extensively than aromatic and napthenic oils and would contain a smaller
concentration of aromatic, sulfur and/or nitrogen compounds. It is difficult to
elucidate the exact chemical structure of these compounds due to their
complexity. The tendency of an oil to interfere with platinum catalyzed
hydrosilylation is directly related to the concentration of sulfur and nitrogen
containing compounds, as well as compounds which contain phosphorus, tin,
arsenic, aluminum and iron.</p><heading><u style="single">Processing</u></heading><p num="0037">The rubber component of the thermoplastic elastomer is generally
present as small, i.e. micro-size, particles within a continuous thermoplastic
resin matrix, although a co-continuous morphology or a phase inversion is also
possible depending upon the amount of rubber relative to plastic and the
degree of cure of the rubber. The rubber is desirably at least partially
crosslinked, and preferably is completely or fully crosslinked. It is preferred
that the rubber be crosslinked by the process of dynamic vulcanization. As
used in the specification and claims, the term "dynamic vulcanization" means
a vulcanization or curing process for a rubber blended with a thermoplastic
resin, wherein the rubber is vulcanized under conditions of shear at a
temperature at which the mixture will flow. The rubber is thus simultaneously 
crosslinked and dispersed as fine particles within the thermoplastic resin
matrix, although as noted above other morphologies may exist. Dynamic
vulcanization is effected by mixing the thermoplastic elastomer components at
elevated temperatures in conventional mixing equipment such as roll mills,
Banbury mixers, Brabender mixers, continuous mixers, mixing extruders and
the like. The unique characteristic of dynamically cured compositions is that,
notwithstanding the fact that the rubber component is partially or hilly cured,
the compositions can be processed and reprocessed by conventional plastic
processing techniques such as extrusion, injection molding and compression
molding. Scrap or flashing can be salvaged and reprocessed.</p><p num="0038">The terms "fully vulcanized" and "fully cured" or "fully crosslinked" as
used in the specification and claims means that the rubber component to be
vulcanized has been cured or crosslinked to a state in which the elastomeric
properties of the crosslinked rubber are similar to those of the rubber in its
conventional vulcanized state, apart from the thermoplastic elastomer
composition. The degree of cure can be described in terms of gel content, or
conversely, extractable components. Gel content reported as percent gel (based
on the weight of crosslinkable rubber) is determined by a procedure which
comprises determining the amount of insoluble polymer by soaking the
specimen for 48 hours in organic solvent at room temperature, weighing the
dried residue and making suitable corrections based upon knowledge of the
composition. Thus, corrected initial and final weights are obtained by
subtracting from the initial weight the weight of soluble components, other
than rubber to be vulcanized, such as extender oils, plasticizers and 
components of the composition soluble in organic solvent, as well as that
rubber component of the product which is not intended to be cured. Any
insoluble polyolefins, pigments, fillers, and the like are subtracted from both
the initial and final weights. The rubber component can be described as fully
cured when less than about 5%, and preferably less than 3%, of the rubber
which is capable of being cured by hydrosilylation is extractable from the
thermoplastic elastomer product by a solvent for that rubber. Alternatively the
degree of cure may be expressed in terms of crosslink density. All of these
descriptions are well known in the art, for example in U.S. Pat. Nos.
4,593,062, 5,100,947 and 5,157,081, all of which are fully incorporated herein
by this reference.</p><p num="0039">The following general procedure was used in the preparation of
thermoplastic elastomers by the process of the invention, as set forth in the
examples. The thermoplastic resin, oil and rubber were placed in a heated
internal mixer, with the hydrosilylation agent and hydrosilylation catalyst.
The hydrosilylation agent and catalyst can be incorporated into the
composition by any suitable technique, for example by injection as solutions
in oil or as neat components, although a dilute hydrosilylation crosslinker and
catalyst solutions are preferred. Additives such as antioxidants, ultraviolet
stabilizers and fillers may also be added as a slurry in oil. Masterbatches of
the components may also be prepared to facilitate the blending process. The
mixture was heated to a temperature sufficient to melt the thermoplastic
component, and the mixture was masticated, with added processing oil if
desired, until a maximum in the mixing torque indicated that vulcanization had 
occurred. Mixing was continued until the desired degree of vulcanization was
achieved.</p><p num="0040">The order of addition of the hydrosilylation agent and hydrosilylation
catalyst was found to be important. Maximum catalyst efficiency was
obtained when the hydrosilylation agent was added first to the blend, followed
by the hydrosilylation catalyst. The mechanical properties of the thermoplastic
elastomer products, as well as the degree of cure, were improved when this
order of addition was followed.</p><p num="0041">The invention will be better understood by reference to the following
examples which serve to illustrate but not limit the present process. In the
examples, the following test methods were used to determine the properties of
the thermoplastic elastomer products.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Hardness (Shore A)</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 2240</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ultimate tensile strength (UTS - psi)</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 412</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ultimate elongation (UE - %)</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 412</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Modulus at 100% elongation (M100 - psi)</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 412</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tear Strength pli</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 412</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tension set (TS - %)</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 412</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Compression Set</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D 395, Method B</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0042">The components used in the compositions prepared according to the
examples are further identified as follows. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Copolymer A</entry><entry align="left">Methacrylate grafted XP-50 Butyl Rubber (0.35 mole methacrylic groups)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Copolymer B</entry><entry align="left">Methacrylate grafted XP-50 Butyl Rubber (0.51 mole methacrylic groups)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Copolymer C</entry><entry align="left">Methacrylate grafted XP-50 Butyl Rubber (0.73 mole methacrylic groups)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Butyl Rubber B</entry><entry align="left">Butyl 268 from Exxon</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polypropylene A</entry><entry align="left">Homopolypropylene MFI = 2600(LMW)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polypropylene B</entry><entry align="left">Copolymer of propylene and ethylene MFI = 4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polypropylene C</entry><entry align="left">Homopolypropylene MFI = 14</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Si-H "A"</entry><entry align="left">2-2822 from Dow Corning hydrosilylation crosslinker</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Catalyst A</entry><entry align="left">PC-085 1.0 wt % in paraffinic oil from Dow Corning (platinum containing catalyst)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil (paraffinic) A</entry><entry align="left">Britol 20T mineral oil from Witco</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil (polybutene) B</entry><entry align="left">Exxon Parapol 950</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil (polybutene) C</entry><entry align="left">Exxon Parapol 450</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0043">Compositions Ia, Ib, Ic, and Id were prepared to compare the properties
of thermoplastic vulcanizates from methacrylate functionalized copolymers of
isobutylene and paramethyistyrene (Copolymer A) to the controls from
thermoplastic vulcanizates from conventional butyl rubber, Compositions IIc
and IId (using Butyl rubber B, a copolymer of isobutylene and a conventional
diene for butyl rubber). Compositions Ia through Id using the methacrylate
functionalized copolymers had higher UE, M-100, and Tear Strength and
lower Tension Set and Compression Set than the control examples IIc and IId.
It was generally observed that the Butyl Rubber "B" did not cure under the
reaction conditions. Compositions Ia - Id vary. Composition Ia used 2.84 wt
% Si-H "A", 4.74 wt % Catalyst "A" and 23.7 wt % Oil "A" while Ib uses the 
same amounts but substitutes Oil "B" (a polybutene oil) for an Oil "A" (a
mineral oil). Composition Ic varies from the first two compositions in that it
uses only 1.48 wt % Si-H "A", 2.46 wt % Catalyst "A" and uses the Oil "B"
(polybutene similar to Composition Ib). Composition Id uses the lower
amounts of Si-H and Catalyst (similar to composition Ic) and then substitutes
Oil "C" (a polybutene oil). The properties of the thermoplastic vulcanizates
did not change much going from Composition Ia to Composition Ib indicating
the oil type had little effect other than possibly matching the refractive index
of the rubber and plastic phases. The properties only changed slightly going to
Composition Ic and Composition Id indicating that smaller amounts of
hydrosilylation agent (Si-H) and catalyst are nearly as effective as higher
amounts of the same components. The physical properties of the two control
(Compositions IIc and IId) indicate that complete curing of the conventional
butyl rubber does not occur even when nearly twice as much hydrosilylation
agent and catalyst are used as compared to the lowest levels used to cure a
methacrylate functionalized copolymer of isobutylene and paramethylstyrene.
The properties of the two controls (especially the compression set and tension
set) are generally unsuitable for most thermoplastic vulcanizate applications. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1"><b>HYDROSILYLATION CURED THERMOPLASTIC VULCANIZATES</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Composition</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Ia</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Ib</b> </entry><entry align="left"><b>Ic</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>IIc</b></entry> <entry align="left"><b>Id</b> </entry> <entry align="left"><b>IId</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ingredients</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Copolymer A</entry><entry align="center">47.39</entry><entry align="center">47.39</entry><entry align="center">49.26</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">49.26</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Butyl Rubber</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">49.26</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">47.39</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polypropylene A</entry><entry align="center">2.37</entry><entry align="center">2.37</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polypropylene B</entry><entry align="center">9.48</entry><entry align="center">9.48</entry><entry align="center">12.32</entry><entry align="center">12.32</entry><entry align="center">12.32</entry><entry align="center">11.85</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polypropylene C</entry><entry align="center">9.48</entry><entry align="center">9.48</entry><entry align="center">9.85</entry><entry align="center">9.85</entry><entry align="center">9.85</entry><entry align="center">9.48</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Si-H A</entry><entry align="center">2.84</entry><entry align="center">2.84</entry><entry align="center">1.48</entry><entry align="center">1.48</entry><entry align="center">1.48</entry><entry align="center">2.84</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Catalyst A</entry><entry align="center">4.74</entry><entry align="center">4.74</entry><entry align="center">2.46</entry><entry align="center">2.46</entry><entry align="center">2.46</entry><entry align="center">4.74</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil (paraffinic) A</entry><entry align="center">23.70</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil (polybutene) B</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">23.70</entry><entry align="center">24.63</entry><entry align="center">24.63</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil (polybutene) C</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">24.63</entry><entry align="center">23.70</entry></row><row><entry align="left">TOTAL</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1"><b>ROOM TEMPERATURE PROPERTY</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hardness A, 5 sec</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">53</entry><entry align="center">36</entry><entry align="center">52</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UE, %</entry><entry align="center">279</entry><entry align="center">277</entry><entry align="center">386</entry><entry align="center">737</entry><entry align="center">375</entry><entry align="center">124</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UTS, psi</entry><entry align="center">698</entry><entry align="center">660</entry><entry align="center">695</entry><entry align="center">128</entry><entry align="center">589</entry><entry align="center">112</entry></row><row><entry align="left">M-100, psi</entry><entry align="center">310</entry><entry align="center">324</entry><entry align="center">284</entry><entry align="center">122</entry><entry align="center">248</entry><entry align="center">112</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tear Strength, pli</entry><entry align="center">112</entry><entry align="center">145</entry><entry align="center">137</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">102</entry><entry align="center">39</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tension Set, %</entry><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">55</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comp. Set, 22 hrs, 70C</entry><entry align="center">24</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="center">81</entry><entry align="center">34</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1"><b>ORGANOSILOXANE CURED ACRYLIC MODIFIED Br-XP-50
BUTYL TPV</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Composition</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>IIIa</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Ie</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>IVa</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Va</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Via</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ingredients</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Copolymer A</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">56.09</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">60.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Copolymer B</entry><entry align="center">55.00</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">60.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Copolymer C</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">57.64</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polypropylene MFI=0.7</entry><entry align="center">36.67</entry><entry align="center">37.40</entry><entry align="center">38.43</entry><entry align="center">40.00</entry><entry align="center">40.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SiH A</entry><entry align="center">1.67</entry><entry align="center">1.73</entry><entry align="center">1.78</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Catalyst A</entry><entry align="center">6.67</entry><entry align="center">4.78</entry><entry align="center">2.15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">TOTAL</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry><entry align="center">100.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hardness A, 5 sec</entry><entry align="center">92</entry><entry align="center">88</entry><entry align="center">87</entry><entry align="center">86</entry><entry align="center">87</entry></row><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1"><b>ROOM TEMPERATURE PROPERTY</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">UE, %</entry><entry align="center">420</entry><entry align="center">340</entry><entry align="center">170</entry><entry align="center">170</entry><entry align="center">220</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UTS, psi</entry><entry align="center">2900</entry><entry align="center">1960</entry><entry align="center">1220</entry><entry align="center">1020</entry><entry align="center">730</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="1">698 660</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="1">695 128</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="1">589 112</entry></row><row><entry align="left">M-100, psi</entry><entry align="center">1400</entry><entry align="center">1190</entry><entry align="center">1100</entry><entry align="center">990</entry><entry align="center">720</entry></row><row><entry align="left">M-300,psi</entry><entry align="center">2300</entry><entry align="center">1770</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tension Set, %</entry><entry align="center">24</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">34</entry><entry align="center">Break</entry><entry align="center">78</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comp. Set, 22 hrs, 100°C</entry><entry align="center">47</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gel %</entry><entry align="center">97</entry><entry align="center">88</entry><entry align="center">85</entry><entry align="center">23</entry><entry align="center">8</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0044">The examples in Table 2 further illustrate the desirability of
crosslinking acrylic or methacrylic functionality on an isobutylene-p-methylstyrene
copolymer.

None of the compositions of Table 2 include oil so they have higher Shore A
hardness. Composition IIIa is derived from a copolymer with a higher amount
of methacrylic functionality (0.51 mole %) than previous examples.
Composition Ie is similar to previous compositions but has no oil.
Composition IVa is similar to earlier compositions but uses a copolymer with
0.73 mole % methacrylic functionality. Composition Va (control) is similar to
IIIa but lacks silicon hydride crosslinker and catalyst. Composition VIa
(control) is similar to Ie but lacks silicon hydride crosslinker and a catalyst.</p><p num="0045">While the best mode and preferred embodiment of the invention have
been set forth in accord with the Patent Statutes, the scope of the invention is
not limited thereto, but rather is defined by the attached claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A thermoplastic vulcanizate comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) a thermoplastic resin and</claim-text><claim-text>b) a butyl rubber copolymer of isobutylene and paramethylstyrene
containing acrylic and/or alkacrylic groups pendant on repeat units from
paramethylstyrene via a carboxyl linkage to the paramethyl group, said butyl
rubber copolymer being crosslinked via the reaction product of a
hydrosilylation crosslinking agent and a carbon-carbon double bond of said
acrylic and/or alkacrylic groups.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A thermoplastic vulcanizate according to claim 1, wherein said
butyl rubber is the reaction product of acrylate modification of a brominated
copolymer of at least isobutylene and paramethylstyrene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A thermoplastic vulcanizate according to claim 2, wherein said
alkacrylic group is derived from metal salt of acrylic or methacrylic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A thermoplastic vulcanizate according to claim 2, wherein said
butyl rubber less said acrylic and/or alkacrylic group is a copolymer of from
about 80 to about 99 weight percent isobutylene and from about 1 to about 20
weight percent paramethylstyrene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A thermoplastic vulcanizate according to claim 2, wherein said copolymer
includes from about 0.1 to about 5 mole % acrylic or alkacrylic group or a
combination thereof if both of them are present.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A thermoplastic vulcanizate according to claim 2, wherein said
thermoplastic resin and said butyl rubber are present in ratios by weight of
from about 20:80 to about 80:20.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A thermoplastic vulcanizate according to claim 6, wherein said
butyl rubber copolymer comprises from about 80 to about 99 weight percent
repeat units from isobutylene and from about 1 to about 20 weight percent
repeat units from paramethylstyrene and from about 0.1 to about 5 mole %
acrylic or alkacrylic groups.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A thermoplastic vulcanizate according to claim 7, wherein said
thermoplastic resin comprises polyethylene or polypropylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A thermoplastic vulcanizate according to claim 8 further including
residual platinum from a platinum containing hydrosilylation catalyst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A process for forming a thermoplastic vulcanizate, said process
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) blending
<claim-text><claim-text>1) a thermoplastic resin</claim-text><claim-text>2) a butyl rubber copolymer of isobutylene and
paramethylstyrene having acrylic or alkacrylic groups, or combinations thereof
pendant from at least some of the repeat units from paramethylstyrene via a
carboxyl linkage from the acrylic or alkacrylic group.</claim-text><claim-text>3) a hydrosilylation crosslinking agent and,</claim-text><claim-text>4) a catalyst for hydrosilylation crosslinking,</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>b) crosslinking said butyl rubber copolymer with said hydrosilylation
crosslinking agent.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A process according to claim 10, wherein the weight ratio of
thermoplastic resin to butyl rubber copolymer is from about 20:80 to about
80:20 respectively.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A process according to claim 11, wherein said thermoplastic resin
comprises polyethylene or polypropylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A process according to claim 12, wherein said acrylic or
alkacrylic, or combinations thereof comprise acrylic, methacrylic, or ethacrylic
or combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A process according to claim 12, wherein said catalyst comprises
platinum containing catalyst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A process according to claim 12, wherein said copolymer of
isobutylene and paramethylstyrene comprises from about 80 to about 99
weight percent isobutylene, and from 1 to about 20 weight percent
paramethylstyrene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A process according to claim 12, wherein said acrylic or alkacrylic
groups or combinations thereof, if both are present, are present in an amount
from about 0.1 to about 5 mole %.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="156" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="239" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="238" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>