<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1308484-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1308484" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="8181160" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030507"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1308484-A1" status="new" fvid="23750647"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1308484</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030507</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01204141-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01204141</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011030</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-01204141-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01204141</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011030</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   5/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   5/16        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   7/12        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   7/12        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 183/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 183/04        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 193/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 193/04        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D   5/16C7</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D   5/16H</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verwendung von Kolophonium-silylester in selbstpolierenden, fäulnisverhindernden Anstrichen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Use of silylesters of rosin in self-polishing antifouling paints</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Emploi des esters silyliques de la colophane dans des peintures auto-polissantes et antisalissures</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0802243-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0802243</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1016681-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1016681</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-2007691-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2007691</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SIGMA COATINGS BV</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SIGMA COATINGS B.V.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SIGMA COATINGS B.V.</last-name><address><street>Amsterdamseweg, 14</street><city>1422 AD Uithoorn</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GILLART MICHEL</name><address><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VOS MARCEL</name><address><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GILLART, MICHEL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VOS, MARCEL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GILLART, MICHEL</last-name><address><street>rue J. Froissart 6/102</street><city>1348 Louvain-la-Neuve</city><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VOS, MARCEL</last-name><address><street>Rue du Cheval Godet 78</street><city>1400 Nivelles</city><country>BE</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Walsh, David Patrick</last-name><address><street>Appleyard Lees, Enterprise House 12 St Pauls Street</street><city>Leeds LS1 2LE</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Silylesters of rosin are used in self-polishing antifouling paints alone or in
combination with other binder components.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to binders for self-polishing antifouling paints.
More particularly, it relates to the use of silylesters as binder in self-polishing
antifouling paints.</p><p num="0002">Many existing antifouling paints used for ships to prevent barnacles and
other marine life from attaching to the ships' hulls work by slowly leaching
metallic compounds into the sea. But studies have shown that these
compounds persist in the water, killing sea life, harming the environment
and possibly entering the food chain. One of the most effective types of
antifouling paint, developed in the 1960s, contains the organotin tributyltin
(TBT), which has been proven to cause deformations in oysters and sex
changes in whelks.</p><p num="0003">The International Maritime Organization (IMO), a unit of the United Nations,
adopted on 5 October 2001 an International Convention on the Control of
Harmful Antifouling Systems at the end of a five-day Diplomatic Conference
held in London.</p><p num="0004">The proposed antifouling convention comes in response to Assembly
resolution A.895 (21) (Antifouling systems used on ships, adopted by IMO
in November 1999, which called on IMO's Marine Environment Protection
Committee ( MEPC) to develop an instrument, legally binding throughout
the world, to address the harmful effects of antifouling systems used on
ships).</p><p num="0005">The resolution calls for a global prohibition on the application of organotin
compounds which act as biocides in antifouling systems on ships by 1
January 2003, and a complete prohibition on the presence of organotin 
compounds which act as biocides in antifouling systems on ships by 1
January 2008.</p><p num="0006">The harmful environmental effects of organotin compounds were
recognized by IMO in 1990, when the MEPC adopted a resolution which
recommended that Governments adopt measures to eliminate the use of
antifouling paint containing TBT on non-aluminium hulled vessels of less
than 25 meters in length and eliminate the use of antifouling paints with a
leaching rate of more than 4 micrograms of TBT per day. Some countries,
such as Japan, have already banned TBT in antifouling paint for most
ships.</p><p num="0007">There is therefore a need in the art for improved erodable antifouling paint
compositions containing no organotin compound, while retaining the good
antifouling and self-polishing properties of the tin-containing antifouling
paints of the prior art.</p><p num="0008">Tin-free systems are well known in the art:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>Antifouling paints containing rosin and similarly soluble salts thereof
exist for many years. Rosin is slightly soluble in seawater (8.6 x 10<sup>-5</sup> mol/L
at pH = 8.1). Due to its low molecular weight, rosin is blended with another
binder to provide an appropriate film-forming performance.</li><li>Paints based on a combination of wood rosin with copper- or zinc-pyrithione
have been found to thicken or gel unacceptably within a few
days. US 5,112,397 (Olin Corp.) discloses paints containing an amine
compound or esterified wood rosin to impart desired gelation-inhibition.</li><li>EP 289481 and EP 526441 (Sigma Coatings), WO 9744401
(Hempel's) disclose systems based on rosin in combination with a film 
forming binder. However, the coatings produced in accordance with these
specifications suffer from the technical problem that their coatings are
nowadays classified as "ablative" since the erosion is not based on a real
chemical hydrolysis but well on a complex process which weakens the
surface layer by a combination of dissolving and leaching followed by
frictional abrasives forces leading to higher surface roughness (at micron
scale ablative pattern) and an irregular erosion rate of the coating.</li><li>Systems based on copper (or zinc) acrylates are described in EP
342276 (Nippon Paint), GB 2 311 070 (Kansaï Paint), US 5 545 823 and
US 5 382 281 (Yung Chi Paint). Based on cheap raw materials these tin-free
systems suffer from several drawbacks. Indeed, their production
requires a dedicated equipment and their composition is very difficult to
assess by chemical analysis. Further, the use of copper in antifouling
systems will certainly be restricted in the forthcoming years. An example of
that trend is the Dutch ban on the application of copper-containing
antifouling paints on yachts smaller than 25 meters.</li><li>Systems based on silyl acrylates were disclosed by M&amp;T (WO
8402915, EP 00131621), and further developed by Chugoku ( EP 775733
), Nippon Oils &amp; Fats ( EP 297505, EP 646630, EP 714957, EP 802243 )
and Sigma Coatings (WO 0162811 and WO 0162858)</li></ul></p><p num="0009">It is known in the art that rosin or rosin derivatives may be used in
combination with hydrolysable acrylates in order to improve some of their
properties.</p><p num="0010">EP 530205 (Courtaulds) discloses the use of rosin amine D in combination
with copper acrylates .

WO 0043460 (Akzo Nobel) discloses some advantages of using blends of
rosin (and its derivatives) with zinc/copper acrylates. </p><p num="0011">EP 1016681 (Chugoku) discloses that the blending of rosin (and its
derivatives) with trialkylsilyl(meth)acrylate co-polymers improve the ability
to erode at static conditions (e.g. during the outfitting period in the building
of new ships) and by this having a superior antifouling performance. The
recoatability and the resistance to cracking and detachment were also
claimed to be improved by this blending</p><p num="0012">EP 802243 (Nippon Oils &amp; Fats) discloses blends of at least one compound
selected from rosin, rosin derivatives and rosin metal salts with certain
polymers containing organosilyl ester groups as binder in self-polishing
antifouling paints, leading to improved properties after long-term
immersion.

Nowadays, the ship owners continue to request an excellent performance
over increasingly longer periods of time, in order to reduce the frequency of
dry-docking the ships to apply a fresh coating on their hulls. There is thus
a continuous need in the art for alternative and improved self-polishing
antifouling paint compositions.</p><p num="0013">The inventor has surprisingly found that the "ablative" effect of the
antifouling paints based on rosin or rosin metal salts could be largely
overcome by using silylesters of rosin (alternatively called silylated
resinates or silyl abietates).</p><p num="0014">Thus the present invention provides the use in self-polishing antifouling
paints of silylesters of rosin as binder component of the binder system.</p><p num="0015">For the purpose of this specification, the term "binder system" means a
composition consisting essentially of silylesters of rosin and optionally other
binder components well known by the man of the art. </p><p num="0016">The present invention provides also a process for preparing self-polishing
antifouling paints characterised in that one step of the process is the
addition of silylesters of rosin as binder component of the binder system.</p><p num="0017">The invention is based on the recognition that the self-polishing properties
of antifouling paints containing rosin were insufficient due to the presence
of free carboxylic groups on the rosin; said properties being unexpectedly
found to be greatly improved after reaction of the free carboxylic group of
rosin with a silyl group.</p><p num="0018">Rosin is a loosely used term, denoting the result of a harvesting of the gum
exudations from surface cuts made in certain species of trees. Rosin is
sometimes defined restrictively as the product obtained from pines; similar
products comprised in the generic term "rosin" as used herein include
Congo copal, Kauri copal, Damar and Manilla gums. Other processes for
obtaining rosin include dissolving wood rosin from pine stumps after forests
have been felled, or refining a by-product of the kraft paper manufacturing
process to produce tall oil rosin.

Pine-originating rosin is preferably chosen. The main component (about 80
%) of rosin is abietic acid, also called sylvic acid (CAS RN. = 514-10-03),
which could be used instead of rosin.</p><p num="0019">The silylester of rosin in this invention can also be a silylester of a rosin
derivative.

In the present context the term "rosin derivative" is intended to mean all
types of rosin (as defined above) modified or derivatised according to
various chemical reactions or processes which leave at least one carboxylic
acid group per molecule available for silylation. A number of processes are
expected to lead to rosin derivatives which have superior paint constituent
properties with respect to improvement of the mechanical properties and/or
control of the self-polishing properties. </p><p num="0020">As examples, one can cite:
<sl><li>A. the adducts of unsaturated acids (such as acrylic acid, maleic acid
or fumaric acid)-and the mono-esters of di-acids with rosin.</li><li>B. adducts of rosin itself (dimerised rosin, oligomerised or polymerised
rosin)</li><li>C. hydrogenated or partially hydrogenated rosin</li><li>D. dismutated or disproportionated rosins</li></sl></p><p num="0021">A more extensive description of rosin and rosin derivatives can be found in
WO 9744401 (Hempel's).</p><p num="0022">Commercially available examples of some rosin and rosin derivatives are
given in Table 1. Most of these examples have high softening points and
have therefore no adhesive properties.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Commercially available examples of rosin derivatives.</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Description</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Trade name</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Company</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Acid number</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Softening (°C)<!--footnotes removed--></b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Portuguese gum rosin</entry><entry align="left">(rosin)</entry><entry align="left">Demonchi</entry><entry align="left">170</entry><entry align="left">70</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hydrogenated rosin</entry><entry align="left">Foral AX-E</entry><entry align="left">Hercules</entry><entry align="left">170</entry><entry align="left">80</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dimerized rosin</entry><entry align="left">Dymerex</entry><entry align="left">Hercules</entry><entry align="left">145</entry><entry align="left">150</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Partially polymerized rosin</entry><entry align="left">Poly-Pale</entry><entry align="left">Hercules</entry><entry align="left">140</entry><entry align="left">102</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Acid modified ester</entry><entry align="left">B106</entry><entry align="left">Hercules</entry><entry align="left">200</entry><entry align="left">183</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Maleic anhydride ester</entry><entry align="left">K1614</entry><entry align="left">Lawter</entry><entry align="left">200</entry><entry align="left">160</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fumarated rosin</entry><entry align="left">Ennesin FM6</entry><entry align="left">Lawter</entry><entry align="left">305</entry><entry align="left">140<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0023">The reaction of carboxylic acid groups with substituted silyl groups is well
known in the art; see e.g. <ul list-style="bullet"><li>J.D. Nicholson in The Analyst. vol. 103, n°1224, pp 193-222 (March
1978)</li><li>M. Lalonde, T.H. Chan in Synthesis pp 817-845 (September 1985)</li></ul></p><p num="0024">The preparation and gas chromatography of the trimethylsilyl ester of rosin
(CAS RN=21414-50-6) was reported (J. Gas Chromatogr. 1968, 6 (3) 158 -
160).

Examples of silylating agents are triorganosilyl chlorides and hydrides, and
hexaorgano disiloxanes and disilazanes :
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">R<st32:sub pos="post">1</st32:sub>R<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub>R<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub>Si-X with X = H or Cl</st32:df><st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">R<st32:sub pos="post">1</st32:sub> R<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub>R<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub>Si-X-Si R<st32:sub pos="post">4</st32:sub> R<st32:sub pos="post">5</st32:sub>R<st32:sub pos="post">6</st32:sub> with X = O or NH</st32:df></p><p num="0025">According to the invention, the silicon substituents are alkyl radicals, which
may be the same or different, including methyl, ethyl, n-propyl, isopropyl, n-butyl,
isobutyl, t-butyl and phenyl. An example of silylating agent with
different substituents is dimethyl t-butyl silyl chloride. The preferred
substituents are methyl and ethyl, more preferred substituents being
methyl.</p><p num="0026">According to another preferred embodiment, di-, tri- , tetrafunctional
silylating agents and mixtures thereof can also be used, for example
dimethylsilyl dichloride, ethylsilyl trichloride and tetrachlorosilane, to obtain
respectively dialkylsilyl diresinate, alkylsilyl triresinate, silyl tetraresinate
and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0027">An object of the present invention is the use in self-polishing antifouling
paints of silylesters of rosin as binder component of the binder system
wherein the silylesters of rosin are in an amount of from 5 to 100% by
weight, based on the total weight of the binder system composition. </p><p num="0028">According to an embodiment, the silylesters of rosin are used in an amount
of from 5 to 25% by weight, based on the total weight of the binder system
composition.</p><p num="0029">According to another embodiment, the silylesters of rosin are used in an
amount of from 35 to 65% by weight, based on the total weight of the
binder system composition.</p><p num="0030">According to yet another embodiment, the silylesters of rosin are used in an
amount of 100% by weight, based on the total weight of the binder system
composition.</p><p num="0031">The inventor has now surprisingly found that the complete conversion of the
acid functionality of rosin compounds into a silylester has many advantages
for paint formulation, manufacturing and stability by providing a silyl ester
that is :
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>Inert to reactive pigments such as zinc oxide and cuprous oxide. It
is well known that self-polishing antifouling paints containing rosin
compounds react through their free acid functionality with reactive
pigments, in practice always present in antifouling paints, such as zinc
oxide or cuprous oxide, to form the corresponding salts e.g. zinc resinate or
cuprous resinate. The metal salts of resinates have the disadvantage of
being hardly soluble in seawater and having poor adhesive and film forming
properties.</li><li>Inert to biocides. There is for example no more risk of gelation that
usually occurs when zinc/copper pyrithione is used in rosin-based
formulations. It is well known that zinc pyrithione is one of the modern
biocides used in antifouling paints but that it has the disadvantage of being
unstable in the presence of carboxylic acid groups and/or the metal salts of
carboxylic acid groups. This biocide can therefore e.g. not without special
precautions be used in rosin-based paints because they always do contain 
carboxylic acid groups to some extent which lead to an irreversible gelation
of the paint.</li><li>More sensitive to dissolving and erosion processes in water (fresh
water or seawater).</li><li>Less brittle; in other words having a lower glass transition
temperature (Tg) and softening point than corresponding metal salts of the
resinate species concerned.</li></ul></p><p num="0032">Indeed, whilst the reaction of rosin compounds with zinc oxide or cuprous
oxide has the effect of increasing the softening point and the Tg as well,
e.g. softening point from 70 °C for rosin to 160 °C for zinc resinate. In
contrast there is hardly an increase when the acid function of rosin
compounds has reacted with a silyl group according to the invention (e.g.
Tg values in example 1: from 52 °C for rosin to only 62 °C for trimethylsilyl
resinate).</p><p num="0033">The hydrolysable silylesters of rosin can be used as sole resin or preferably
in combination with other binders to form a binder system that are
commonly in use in antifouling formulations. When other binders are
present, those are in an amount of from more than 0 up to 95% by weight,
based on the total weight of the binder system composition.</p><heading><u style="single">Examples of other binders are:</u></heading><p num="0034"><ul list-style="bullet"><li>Resinates of Ca, Cu or Zn</li><li>Naphthenates of Ca, Cu, Zn</li><li>Vinyls like Laroflex MP (commercially available from BASF)</li><li>Acrylates like Neocryl B725 (commercially available from Avecia)</li><li>Cu/Zn/Ca acrylates, e.g. as described in EP 342276; EP 982324
(Kansai) or polyesters e.g. as described in EP 1033392 (Kansai). </li><li>Tri-organosilyl(meth)acrylates copolymers as described e.g. in EP
131626 (M&amp;T); US 4593055 (M&amp;T); EP 775773 (Chugoku); EP 646630
(NOF); US 5436284 (NOF); WO 0162811 and WO 0162858 (SIGMA
COATINGS).</li><li>Hydrophilic (meth) acrylates such as e.g. described in FR 2 557 585
(Jotun), EP 526441 and EP 289441 (SIGMA COATINGS). It has been
observed that blends of the hydrophilic acrylic resins such as described in
EP 526441 and EP 289441 with a silylester of rosin had improved
properties over blends with zinc resinate. The film was more flexible, had
better adhesive properties and showed a hydrolysis-driven erosion process
at pH 12 while not showing defects upon immersion in fresh and sea water
conditions (pH 7 and 8 respectively).</li> </ul></p><p num="0035">The following non-limiting examples illustrate the invention. The measuring
methods used in the examples are given further.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1 : synthesis of trimethylsilyl resinate</u></heading> <p num="0036">420 g Portugese gum rosin was put in a 2-L 4-necked flask and kept under
nitrogen. The four necks of the flask were equipped with stirring means, a
reflux cooler, a thermometer for temperature control of the reaction, and
means for addition of the reactants. The gum rosin was dissolved in a
solvent mixture of 218 g xylene and 850 g toluene. Here after 128 gram triethylamine
was carefully added in 5 minutes under vigorous stirring. As a
consequence the temperature of the contents of the flask rose by 10°C.
The addition of the tri-ethyl amine was followed by the slow addition of 138
g trimethylsilyl chloride under vigorous stirring.</p> <p num="0037">A white salt was instantaneously formed and the exothermic reaction made
the contents raise to a temperature of 50°C. The reaction mixture was kept
at a temperature of 50°C for 5 hours. Then the heating and the stirring was 
stopped. The next day the formed trimethylsilyl resinate was purified by
filtration and evaporation of the toluene solvent fraction. The yield was 530
g (circa 78 %) of a brown colored solution, that was 75 wt % in solids and
had a viscosity of 3 dPa.s. The binder was very flexible and had a good
adhesion on glass and epoxy primer and showed hydrolysis within minutes
upon immersion in an alkaline solution of pH 12. This all in contrast with
zinc resinate which had a hard and brittle film with moderate adhesion on
glass and without showing any hydrolysis behavior up to pH 13. The binder
had a Tg of 62 °C.</p> <heading><u style="single">Example 2 : synthesis of dimethylsilyldiresinate</u></heading><p num="0038">The same equipment and procedures were used as for the synthesis of
example 1 with the following differences:

335 g Portugese gum rosin had been dissolved in 121 g xylene and 500 g
toluene.

To this had been added consecutively 101 g tri-ethyl amine and 64,5 g
dimethyldichlorosilane.

The yield was 300 g of a brown colored solution that was 70 wt % in solids
and had a viscosity of 10 dPa.s.

The binder had a good adhesion on glass and epoxy primers.

The binder was very sensitive to alkaline hydrolysis. A binder film dissolved
in water of pH 12 completely within 15 minutes.

The binder had a Tg of 52 °C.</p><p num="0039">Some properties of trimethylsilyl resinate and dimethylsilyl resinate are
specified in table 2.</p><p num="0040">Examples 1 and 2 demonstrate that silylesters of resinates dissolve in
alkaline solutions more quickly than for example zinc resinate and that they
are less brittle than zinc resinate. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Parameter</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Trimethylsilyl-resinate (ex 1)</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Dimethylsilyl-diresinate (ex 2)</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Zinc Resinate</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Rosin</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tg (°C)</entry><entry align="left">62</entry><entry align="left">52</entry><entry align="left">160</entry><entry align="left">52</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dissolving (at pH)</entry><entry align="left">Yes (pH 12)</entry><entry align="left">Yes (pH 12)</entry><entry align="left">No (pH 13)</entry><entry align="left">Yes (pH 12)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Paint Formulas : Examples 3 to 6 and comparative example A.</u></heading><p num="0041">Several paints where prepared whose composition by weight is given in
Table 3.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1">Paint compositions</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>Example →</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>3</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>4</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>5</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>6</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>A</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Ingredients</b></entry><entry align="left">Description</entry><entry align="left">wt%</entry><entry align="left">wt%</entry><entry align="left">wt%</entry><entry align="left">Wt%</entry><entry align="left">wt%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">TrimethylSiresinate</entry><entry align="left">75 wt % in xylene (ex. 1)</entry><entry align="center">24.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">DimethylSidiresinate</entry><entry align="left">70 wt % in xylene (ex. 2)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">27.5</entry><entry align="center">12.5</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">50MA/25VP/25BA</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">17.4</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">17.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zinc resinate</entry><entry align="left">Erkacit 250</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">10.9</entry><entry align="center">8.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Laroflex MP 45</entry><entry align="left">Vinylchloride (BASF)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">4.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Thix. Agents</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cuprous oxide</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">40.2</entry><entry align="center">42.1</entry><entry align="center">38.4</entry><entry align="center">38.4</entry><entry align="center">38.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zinc oxide</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">15.0</entry><entry align="center">7.9</entry><entry align="center">14.3</entry><entry align="center">14.3</entry><entry align="center">14.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Iron oxide</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">6.7</entry><entry align="center">7.0</entry><entry align="center">6.4</entry><entry align="center">6.4</entry><entry align="center">6.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zinc pyrithione</entry><entry align="left">Zinc Omadine (Arch)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Xylene</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">12.6</entry><entry align="center">11.2</entry><entry align="center">9.7</entry><entry align="center">21.3</entry><entry align="center">13.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">100.0</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0042">In Example 5 and Comparative Example A, there was used a solution (50
wt % in xylene) of resin 50MA/25VP/25BA according to example 1 of EP-A-526
441, having the monomer weight composition 50 % methyl acrylate,
25 % vinyl pyrrolidone and 25 % butyl acrylate. In Comparative Example A, 
there was used zinc resinate.

The amount by weight of the silylesters of rosin, based on the total weight
of the binder system, used in the several paint formulas is given in table 4
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>3</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>4</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>5</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>6</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>A</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Ingredients</b></entry><entry align="center">wt%</entry><entry align="center">wt%</entry><entry align="center">wt%</entry><entry align="center">wt%</entry><entry align="center"><b>wt%</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">TrimethylSiresinate</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">DimethylSidiresinate</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">50.1</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">-</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0043">Properties of the paints are presented in Table 5.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1">Paint properties</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Properties</b></entry><entry align="left">Units (parameters)</entry><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="left">A</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity</entry><entry align="left">dPa.s</entry><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="left">13</entry><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="left">11</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Can Stability</entry><entry align="left">(3 months; 20 °C)</entry><entry align="left">ok</entry><entry align="left">ok</entry><entry align="left">ok</entry><entry align="left">Ok</entry><entry align="left">ok</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Erosion rate</entry><entry align="left">µm/month (average during 12 months)</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fouling (1 season)</entry><entry align="left">% (fouled area)</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">3%</entry><entry align="left">10 %</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0044">None of the paint formulas did show any significant raise in viscosity upon
3 months storage at 20°C.

The paints have been tested for antifouling activity and erosion rate.

Paints according to the invention present outstanding antifouling and self-polishing
properties.

No significant weed or animal fouling has been observed on the panels
coated with the paints according to the invention and the algal slime was
practically non-existent.</p><p num="0045">Measuring methods used in the examples are as follows : </p><heading><u style="single">Determination of the solids content</u></heading><p num="0046">The solids content was determined by weighing before and after heating a
sample for 1 hour at 120°C [standard test methods ISO 3233/ASTM
2697/DIN 53219].</p><heading><u style="single">Determination of the viscosity</u></heading><p num="0047">The viscosity of binder solutions and of paints was determined with a
Brookfield at 25°C [ASTM test method D2196-86].

The viscosity of paints had been adjusted between 10 and 20 dPa.s. with
xylene. The viscosity was measured using a Haake VT 181 (body E30 or
100) viscosimeter under standard conditions.</p><heading><u style="single">Evaluation of the hydrolysability of the binders</u></heading><p num="0048">The hydrolysability has been evaluated by dipping draw-downs in an
alkaline solution (NaOH, pH 12.0 - 13.4). Hydrolysablitiy is reported as "yes"
at a certain pH when hydrolysis or complete dissolving of a film (50-100 µm)
could be observed within one hour.</p><heading><u style="single">Determination of the softening point</u></heading><p num="0049">The ring and ball method according ASTM-E28 was used.</p><heading><u style="single">Determination of the Tg of the binders</u></heading><p num="0050">Samples for the actual determination were made by making draw downs of
the resins on glass and drying for 16 hours at 120 °C. Here after the
measurements had been carried out with a differential scanning apparatus 
of TA instruments, DSC10 according ASTM 3418.</p><heading><u style="single">Evaluation of the polishing of paints</u></heading><p num="0051">The erosion rate is the average decrease in film thickness (expressed in
µm/month) per month over the whole test.

Stainless steels discs, 20 cm in diameter, were protected with a standard
anti-corrosive system (300 µm in dry film thickness). Two layers of the self-polishing
paint to be tested were applied, to give a total dry film thickness
between 200 and 300 µm. The tests were carried out in constantly
refreshed natural seawater, at a constant temperature of 20 °C. The discs
were rotated at 1000 rpm, corresponding to about 34 km/h (18 knots) at 9
cm from the center.

The total dry film thickness was determined at 2 monthly intervals, after
allowing the paint to dry during one day. It was measured at a number of
fixed points, each located at 9 cm from the center of the discs.</p><heading><u style="single">The evaluation of the antifouling activity of the paints.</u></heading><p num="0052">The antifouling activity was tested by applying the prepared paints to a
plaque over a vinyl resins/tar anti-corrosive paint, mounting the plaque on a
panel and immersing the panel from a raft in a river estuary off the
Southern Netherlands during the active season (March → October). Each
test also included plaques coated with a non-toxic control (which became
heavily fouled with seaweed and some animal life within 4 weeks). The
fouling rate is reported by stating the area covered with fouling.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>Use in self-polishing antifouling paints of silylesters of rosin as
binder component of the binder system.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>Use according to claim 1 wherein the silylesters of rosin are in an
amount of from 5 to 100% by weight, based on the total weight of
the binder system.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>Use according to claim 1 wherein the silylesters of rosin are
selected from the group consisting of trialkylsilyl monoresinate,
dialkylsilyl diresinate, alkylsilyl triresinate, silyl tetraresinate and
mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>Use according to claim 3 wherein the silyl alkyl substituents are
selected from the group consisting of methyl, ethyl, n-propyl,
isopropyl, n-butyl, isobutyl, t-butyl and phenyl substituents and
mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>Use according to claim 4 wherein the silyl alkyl substituents are
selected from the group consisting of methyl and ethyl substituents
and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>Use according to claim 5 wherein the silyl alkyl substituents are
selected from the group consisting of methyl substituents.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>Use according to anyone of the preceding claims wherein
silylesters of rosin are used in combination with other binder
components.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A process for preparing self-polishing antifouling paints
characterised in that one step of the process is the addition of
silylesters of rosin as binder component of the binder system.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>