<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1138656-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1138656" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="27342923" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20011004"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1138656-A1" status="new" fvid="23234189"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1138656</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20011004</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01303041-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01303041</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010330</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000097741-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000097741</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000331</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2001013260-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2001013260</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010122</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2001063490-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2001063490</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010307</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23B  27/14        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23B  27/14        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23P  15/28        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B23P  15/28        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/584       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/584       20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  35/593       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  41/45        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  41/52        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  41/87        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  41/87        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  41/89        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  41/89        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  41/52</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  41/89</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Siliziumnitridbauteil, Verfahren zur Herstellung desselben, und Schneidwerkzeug</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Silicon nitride member, method for manufacturing the same, and cutting tool</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Corps en nitrure de silicium, procédé de sa  fabrication, et outil de coupage</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="JP-4136174-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>4136174</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-4202075-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>4202075</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI  Week 199612 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB;  AN 1996-112542 XP002169856 -&amp; JP 08 012471 A (SUMITOMO ELECTRIC IND. CO.), 16 January 1996 (1996-01-16)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 16, no. 411 (C-0979), 31 August 1992 (1992-08-31) &amp; JP 04 136174 A (MITSUBISHI MATERIALS CORP.), 11 May 1992 (1992-05-11)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 16, no. 533 (C-1002) &amp; JP 04 202075 A (SUMITOMO ELECTRIC IND. LTD.), 22 July 1992 (1992-07-22)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NGK SPARK PLUG CO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NGK SPARK PLUG CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NGK SPARK PLUG CO., LTD</last-name><address><street>14-18, Takatsuji-cho, Mizuho-ku</street><city>Nagoya-shi, Aichi 467-8525</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ABUKAWA KOHEI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ABUKAWA, KOHEI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Abukawa, Kohei, NGK Spark Plug Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>14-18, Takatsuji-cho, Mizuho-ku</street><city>Nagoya-shi, Aichi-ken 467-8525</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Nicholls, Michael John</last-name><address><street>J.A. KEMP &amp;amp; CO. 14, South Square Gray's Inn</street><city>LONDON WC1R 5JJ</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A silicon nitride member is disclosed which exhibits little impairment in
strength even when a substrate thereof is coated with a hard film, and exhibits
excellent resistance to chipping and wear resistance. A method for manufacturing
the silicon nitride member is disclosed and a cutting tool is disclosed.</p><p>A cutting tool 1 includes a substrate 3 formed through sintering of a silicon
nitride material, and a hard film 5 composed of a plurality of hard-component layers.
The cutting tool 1 is characterized in that: when the amount of a grain boundary
phase as measured at a central portion (for example, the barycenter) of the substrate 3
is taken as 100% by volume, the amount of the grain boundary phase at a depth of
300 µm from the surface of the substrate 3 is 50% to 70% by volume; when the
strength of the substrate 3 as measured before coating with the hard film 5 is taken as
100%, the strength as measured after coating with the hard film 5 is 70% to 95%; and
a change in weight of the substrate 3 associated with sintering is 1.5% to 3.5% by
weight.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="70" img-format="tif" img-content="ad"  file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="68"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a silicon nitride member including a substrate
formed through sintering of a silicon nitride material, and a hard film formed on the
surface of the substrate, as well as to a method for manufacturing the same and to a
cutting tool.</p><p num="0002">Conventionally, in order to enhance wear resistance of a sintered member,
such as a ceramic member, the surface of a substrate of, for example, a sintered
silicon nitride member is coated with a hard film composed of hard components,
such as TiCN.</p><p num="0003">Examples of the above-mentioned coating method include a CVD (chemical
vapor deposition) process and a PVD (physical vapor deposition) process, in which
hard components are deposited on the substrate surface to thereby form a hard film
on the same.</p><p num="0004">When a sintered member coated with a hard film was used as, for example, a
cutting tool, the cutting tool (a coated tool) exhibited significantly enhanced wear
resistance.</p><p num="0005">In recent years, applications of a coated tool have been shifting toward heavy
cutting, which involves a heavy cutting load. Under the circumstances, even a
coated tool has been required to exhibit a certain level of resistance to chipping, in
addition to high wear resistance.</p><p num="0006">According to the CVD process or the PVD process mentioned above, hard
components are deposited at high temperature, thus involving the following
problems: because of difference in coefficient of thermal expansion between the hard
film and the substrate, stress remains in the substrate surface; and high temperature
employed during deposition modifies the substrate surface. As a result, the strength
of the substrate coated with the hard film is impaired as compared with that of the
bare substrate.</p><p num="0007">The present invention has been achieved in view of the above problems, and
an object of the present invention is to provide a silicon nitride member exhibiting
little impairment in strength even when a substrate thereof is coated with a hard film, 
and exhibiting excellent resistance to chipping and wear resistance, as well as to
provide a method for manufacturing the same and to provide a cutting tool.</p><p num="0008">The present inventors have conducted extensive studies on a silicon nitride
member in an attempt to minimize impairment in the strength of a substrate thereof
coated with a hard film (a coating film) as compared with that of the bare substrate,
and have found the following.</p><p num="0009">A tensile stress remaining in the substrate surface is the primary cause for
impairment in the strength of the substrate of a silicon nitride member (a sintered
member) obtained through sintering. In cooling the substrate after coating at high
temperature with a hard film, the difference in coefficient of thermal expansion
between the hard film (high coefficient of thermal expansion) and the substrate (low
coefficient of thermal expansion) causes the residual stress.</p><p num="0010">In recent years, because of advancement of sintering technology and in order
to improve wear resistance, the sintering-aid content of a silicon nitride member
tends to be reduced. As a result, the coefficient of thermal expansion of the substrate
surface becomes low. When the substrate is coated with popular Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, TiCN, or the
like, which constitute a hard film, the difference in coefficient of thermal expansion
between the substrate and the hard film becomes more significant.</p><p num="0011">Specifically, as the difference in coefficient of thermal expansion between the
substrate and the hard film increases, a tensile stress remaining in the substrate
surface increases, with a resultant impairment in strength of the substrate coated with
the hard film. Thus, an important consideration is to minimize the difference in
coefficient of thermal expansion between the substrate and the hard film.</p><p num="0012">According to a conceivable measure to minimize the difference in coefficient
of thermal expansion between the substrate and the hard film, a silicon nitride
member is caused to assume a composition of high sintering-aid content, or a
composition of low sintering-aid content, as mentioned above, combined with
optimization of sintering conditions, to thereby suppress to the utmost extent
volatilization of a grain boundary phase (a glass phase of sintering aids formed on
the surface of a silicon nitride grain) formed on the substrate surface as schematically
shown in FIG. 1 of the accompanying drawings.</p><p num="0013">However, when the amount of a grain boundary phase is increased through
addition of a large amount of sintering aids or through suppression of volatilization 
of the grain boundary phase, the difference in coefficient of thermal expansion
decreases, but wear resistance of the substrate itself is impaired. As a result, even
when the substrate is coated with the hard film, sufficient wear resistance cannot be
obtained, so that the intended effect of coating cannot be yielded.</p><p num="0014">Thus, in order to maintain good wear resistance and a certain level of
resistance to chipping of a silicon nitride member coated with a hard film, an
important consideration is to control volatilization of a grain boundary phase, which
is formed on the surface of a substrate during sintering of the substrate, so as to
establish an appropriate amount of a grain boundary phase. On the basis of the
finding, the present invention has been achieved.</p><p num="0015">The present invention and its preferred features and aspects will next be
described.
<sl><li>(1) The present invention provides a silicon nitride member comprising a
substrate formed through sintering of a silicon nitride material, and a hard film
formed on a surface of the substrate. The silicon nitride member is characterized in
that, when the bending strength of the substrate as measured before the substrate is
coated with the hard film is taken as 100%, the bending strength of the silicon nitride
member as measured after the substrate is coated with the hard film is 70% to 95%.
According to the present invention, when the bending strength of the
substrate as measured before the substrate is coated with the hard film is taken as
100%, the bending strength of the silicon nitride member as measured after the
substrate is coated with the hard film is 70% to 95%. That is, the silicon nitride
member exhibits a high bending strength of not less than 800 MPa when measured
after the substrate is coated with the hard film, as will be described below in the
examples.Since the silicon nitride member of the present invention has higher strength
as compared with a conventional counterpart, resistance to chipping thereof is
excellent. Also, coating with the hard film imparts excellent wear resistance thereto.
Because of excellent wear resistance and resistance to chipping, the silicon nitride
member of the present invention favorably serves as a material for, for example, a
cutting tool.</li><li>(2) Preferably, a change in weight of the substrate associated with sintering
is 1.5% to 3.5% by weight. When the change in weight of the substrate associated with sintering is less
than 1.5% by weight, impairment in the strength is not very great, but, for example,
practically desirable wear resistance is not obtained. When the change in weight is in
excess of 3.5% by weight, the strength after coating is greatly impaired.According to a preferred aspect of the present invention, a change in weight
of the substrate associated with sintering is 1.5% to 3.5% by weight. Therefore, the
silicon nitride member has high strength (thus high resistance to chipping) and high
wear resistance, and is thus preferably applicable to, for example, a cutting tool.Notably, a change in weight of the substrate associated with sintering is a so-called
volatilization rate. Herein, the change in weight (volatilization rate) is
expressed as the difference between the weight of a debindered body before sintering
and the weight of a primary sintered body divided by the weight of the primary
sintered body.</li> <li>(3) A further aspect of the present invention provides a silicon nitride
member comprising a substrate formed through sintering of a silicon nitride material,
and a hard film formed on a surface of the substrate. The silicon nitride member is
characterized in that, when the amount of a grain boundary phase as measured at a
central portion of the substrate is taken as 100% by volume, at least one of the
following conditions (1) to (5) is satisfied.
<sl><li>(1) The amount of a grain boundary phase as measured in the vicinity of a
depth of 100 µm from the surface of the substrate is less than 30% by volume;</li><li>(2) The amount of a grain boundary phase as measured in the vicinity of a
depth of 200 µm from the surface of the substrate is 30% to 50% by volume;</li><li>(3) The amount of a grain boundary phase as measured in the vicinity of a
depth of 300 µm from the surface of the substrate is 50% to 70% by volume;</li><li>(4) The amount of a grain boundary phase as measured in the vicinity of a
depth of 400 µm from the surface of the substrate is 70% to 85% by volume; and</li><li>(5) The amount of a grain boundary phase as measured in the vicinity of a
depth of 500 µm from the surface of the substrate is 85% to 100% by volume.</li> </sl>According to the present invention, when the amount of a grain boundary
phase as measured at a central portion of the substrate is taken as 100% by volume,
the amount of a grain boundary phase in a region located in the vicinity of a
predetermined depth (i.e., a region located in a surface portion of the substrate) from 
the surface (so-called sintered skin) of the substrate assumes the above-mentioned
value in % by volume. That is, the amount of a grain boundary phase tends to vary
continuously when measured up to a depth of approximately 500 µm.Accordingly, the thus-configured silicon nitride member has higher strength
(thus higher resistance to chipping) and higher wear resistance as compared with a
conventional counterpart, and is thus favorably applicable to use as, for example, a
cutting tool.Notably, the amount of a grain boundary phase can be obtained through, for
example, image analysis of a scanning electron micrograph (a photograph taken by
means of an SEM), as, for example, the area ratio of a grain boundary phase to the
entire image.The central portion of the substrate can be, for example, a region extending
radially at a radius of 500 µm from the barycenter of the substrate (a region in the
vicinity of the barycenter), but is preferably the barycenter of the substrate. The
vicinity of a predetermined depth α (for example, 300 µm) from the substrate surface
can range from +50 µm to -50 µm in the thickness direction with respect to the depth
α (for example, 300 µm) from the substrate surface, but is preferably the depth α.</li> <li>(4) Preferably, as in the case of aspect (2) above, a change in weight of the
substrate associated with sintering is 1.5% to 3.5% by weight. Therefore, the silicon
nitride member of the present aspect has high strength (thus high resistance to
chipping) and high wear resistance, and is thus preferably applicable as, for example,
a cutting tool.</li> <li>(5) A further aspect of the invention provides a method for manufacturing a
silicon nitride member described above, which method is characterized in that a
condition employed in sintering the substrate is adjusted such that a change in weight
of the substrate associated with sintering is 1.5% to 3.5% by weight.
According to this aspect of the present invention, when the substrate made of
a silicon nitride material is to be sintered, a sintering condition is adjusted such that a
change in weight of the substrate associated with sintering is 1.5% to 3.5% by
weight. Thus, when, subsequent to sintering, the substrate surface is coated with a
hard film to thereby yield a silicon nitride member, the difference in coefficient of
thermal expansion between the substrate and the hard film is small. Therefore, the thus-obtained silicon nitride member has high strength (thus
high resistance to chipping) and high wear resistance, and is thus preferably
applicable as, for example, a cutting tool.Notably, sintering conditions include the maximum temperature during
sintering and gas pressure (nitrogen gas pressure) during sintering. For example,
through increase in the maximum temperature during sintering, the change in weight
can be increased. By contrast, through increase in gas pressure, the change in weight
can be decreased.</li><li>(6) Preferably, the method according to the present aspect of the invention
for manufacturing a silicon nitride member, comprises the steps of: heating the
substrate at a temperature of 1800°C to 1900°C for 60 to 180 minutes in a nitrogen
atmosphere pressurized at 2 to 6 atmospheres; subsequently lowering the temperature
to a range of 1550°C to 1650°C; and maintaining the substrate at the reduced
temperature for 60 to 180 minutes under a reduced pressure not higher than 13 kPa.
A change in weight of the substrate associated with sintering (for example, a
state of volatilization as represented by a volatilization rate) cannot be easily
controlled. However, through control of the volatilization by means of the method of
the present invention, a desired silicon nitride member can be obtained.According to the present aspect of the invention, the substrate is densified in
a pressurized nitrogen atmosphere, and then the temperature is lowered to a
temperature at which silicon nitride does not decompose, followed by heat treatment
under reduced pressure to thereby appropriately volatilize a grain boundary phase
without decomposition of silicon nitride.According to the present aspect of the invention, the temperature is lowered
to a temperature range of 1550°C to 1650°C for the following reason. At a
temperature lower than 1550°C, the grain boundary phase fails to be sufficiently
volatilized. At a temperature higher than 1650°C, silicon nitride decomposes. The
substrate is heat-treated at a pressure not higher than 13 kPa, since at a pressure
higher than 13 kPa, the grain boundary phase fails to be sufficiently volatilized
(regardless of temperature).Manufacture of the silicon nitride member involves a debindering process, a
primary sintering process, and an HIP (hot isostatic press) process. In the present 
invention, the step for heating the substrate at respective temperatures corresponds to
the primary sintering process.</li><li>(7) A further aspect of the invention provides a cutting tool formed of a
silicon nitride member described in any one of aspects (1) to (4) above.</li></sl></p><p num="0016">A cutting tool formed of a silicon nitride member having the above-mentioned
properties exhibits excellent wear resistance and resistance to chipping,
and is thus favorably applicable not only to normal cutting but also to heavy cutting,
which involves a heavy cutting load.</p><p num="0017">The aforementioned silicon nitride member having excellent wear resistance
and resistance to chipping is applicable not only to cutting tools but also, for
example, to wear resistant members of automobile engine components and rotary
tools, such as drills and end mills.</p><p num="0018">Examples of the aforementioned silicon nitride material include sialon and a
mixture of silicon nitride, such as α-Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>, and sintering aids, such as MgO, Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>,
Yb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, Y<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, ZrO<sub>2</sub>, Hf<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, and Er<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.</p><p num="0019">Hard components serving as material for the hard film include Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, TiCN,
TiN, and TiC.</p><p num="0020">The hard film may assume the form of a single layer of a single hard
component or a multilayer of the same hard component or different hard
components.</p><p num="0021">Embodiments of the invention will now be described, by way of example
only, with reference to the accompanying drawings in which:-
<sl><li>FIG. 1 is a schematic view showing the internal structure of a silicon nitride
member.</li><li>FIG. 2 is a perspective view showing a cutting tool according to an
embodiment of the present invention.</li><li>FIG. 3 is a schematic enlarged sectional view of the cutting tool according to
the embodiment.</li><li>FIG. 4 comprises photographs showing the cutting tool according to the
embodiment, wherein (a) is a photograph of a surface of the substrate taken by use of
a scanning electron microscope, and (b) is a photograph of a center portion of the
substrate taken by use of the scanning electron microscope.</li></sl></p><p num="0022">Embodiments of a silicon nitride member, a method for manufacturing the
same, and a cutting tool according to the present invention will next be described.
<sl><li>a) First, a cutting tool formed of a silicon nitride member according to the
present embodiment will be described.
As shown in FIG. 2, a cutting tool 1 of the present embodiment is a ceramic
insert assuming the SNGN120412 shape prescribed in ISO Standards 1832.2 (1984);
i.e., a substantially square plate-like shape.As shown in FIG. 3, the cutting tool 1 includes a substrate 3 formed through
sintering of a silicon nitride material, and a hard film (coating film) 5 composed of a
plurality of hard-component layers and having a thickness of 2.0 µm.The cutting tool 1 of the present embodiment is characterized in that, when
the amount of a grain boundary phase as measured at a central portion of the
substrate 3; for example, at the barycenter, is taken as 100% by volume, the amount
of the grain boundary phase (% by volume) gradually increases over the range from
the surface (sintered skin) of the substrate 3 to a depth of 500 µm. Specifically, the
amount of the grain boundary phase as measured at a depth of 100 µm from the
surface of the substrate 3 is less than 30% by volume; the amount of the grain
boundary phase at a depth of 200 µm is 30% to 50% by volume; the amount of the
grain boundary phase at a depth of 300 µm is 50% to 70% by volume; the amount of
the grain boundary phase at a depth of 400 µm is 70% to 85% by volume; and the
amount of the grain boundary phase at a depth of 500 µm is 85% to 100% by
volume.When the bending strength of the substrate 3 as measured before the substrate
3. is coated with a hard film 5 is taken as 100%, the bending strength of the cutting
tool 1 as measured after the substrate 3 is coated with the hard film 5 is 70% to 95%.
A change in weight of the substrate 3 associated with sintering is 1.5% to 3.5% by
weight.The above-mentioned features of the present embodiment impart high wear
resistance and high strength (thus high resistance to chipping) to the cutting tool 1.</li><li>b) Next, a method for manufacturing the cutting tool 1 according to the
present embodiment will be described.
First, the following materials are measured out: 97% by weight α-Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>,
which serves as a main component and has an average grain size not greater than 1.0 
µm; and 0.5% by weight MgO, 1.0% by weight Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, and 1.5% by weight Yb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>,
which serve as sintering aids and have an average grain size not greater than 1.0 µm.The thus-measured materials are placed in a pot lined with Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> and mixed
for 96 hours by use of Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> balls and an ethanol solvent to thereby yield a slurry.The thus-obtained slurry is sieved through a 325-mesh sieve. A micro-wax-type
organic binder dissolved in ethanol is added to the sieved slurry in an amount of
5.0% by weight, followed by spray drying.The thus-granulated powder is compacted into the SNGN120412 shape
prescribed in ISO Standards 1832.2 (1984). The resulting compact is placed in a
heating apparatus and debindered at 600°C for 60 minutes in a nitrogen atmosphere
of 1 atmosphere.The thus-debindered compact undergoes primary sintering under the
following conditions.The debindered compact is heated at a temperature of 1800°C to 1900°C for
60 to 180 minutes in a nitrogen atmosphere pressurized at 2 to 6 atmospheres;
subsequently, the temperature is lowered to a range of 1550°C to 1650°C; and the
debindered compact is maintained at the reduced temperature for 60 to 180 minutes
under a reduced pressure not higher than 13 kPa.In the present embodiment, conditions of the above-mentioned sintering.
process were adjusted such that the difference between the weight of the debindered
compact measured before sintering and the weight of the debindered compact
measured after primary sintering (the weight of a primary sintered body) divided by
the weight of the primary sintered body falls within a range of 1.5% to 3.5% by
weight.In this case, the weight of the debindered compact and the weight of the
primary sintered body were measured to thereby obtain a change in weight
associated with sintering.Next, secondary sintering is performed by means of HIP. Specifically, the
primary sintered body is heated at a temperature of 1600°C to 1800°C for 120
minutes in a nitrogen atmosphere pressurized at 1000 atmospheres, thereby yielding
a sintered silicon nitride body. The thus-obtained sintered silicon nitride body is machined into the
SNGN120412 cutting-tool shape (specifically, the shape of the substrate 3 of the
cutting tool 1).Next, the hard film (coating film ) 5 composed of hard components is formed
on the surface of the substrate 3 by a CVD process.Specifically, a TiCN layer (0.2 µm thick), an Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer (0.5 µm thick), a
TiCN layer (0.2 µm thick), an Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer (0.5 µm thick), a TiC layer (0.2 µm thick),
a TiCN layer (0.2 µm thick), and a TiN layer (0.2 µm thick) were formed in that
order on the substrate 3, thereby forming the hard film 5 having a thickness of 2.0
µm on the surface of the substrate 3.Thus, a silicon nitride member composed of the substrate 3 and the hard film
5, which is formed on the surface of the substrate 3; i.e., the cutting tool 1 of the
present embodiment was completed.Next will be described experiments conducted in order to confirm the effects
of the present invention.First, samples of Example Nos. 3, 4, 6, 9, and 12 to 14, which fall within the
scope of the present invention, were manufactured by the method described
previously in the Embodiments section.The samples assumed the form of a test piece for use in the 3-point bending
test prescribed in JIS R1601 (1981) and were manufactured under the heat treatment
conditions (conditions of primary sintering) shown below in Table 1. 20 samples
were manufactured for each of the Examples. Of the 20 samples, 10 samples were
not coated with a hard film, and 10 other samples were coated with a hard film.
Also, for use in a wear resistance test, 10 cutting tool samples were manufactured for
each of the Examples by the method described previously in the Embodiments
section.Samples of Comparative Example Nos. 1, 2, 5, 7, 8, 10, 11, and 15 to 17,
which fall outside the scope of the present invention, were manufactured.The samples assumed the form of a test piece for use in the bending test and
were manufactured under the heat treatment conditions (conditions of primary
sintering) shown below in Table 1. 20 samples were manufactured for each of the
Comparative Examples. Of the 20 samples, 10 samples were not coated with a hard
film, and 10 other samples were coated with a hard film. Also, for use in a wear 
resistance test, 10 cutting tool samples were manufactured for each of the
Comparative Examples.
<sl><li>(1) When the samples of the Examples and the Comparative Examples were
manufactured, the samples were measured for a change in weight (volatilization rate)
associated with primary sintering. The average of measured values was calculated
for each of the Examples and the Comparative Examples. The results are shown in
Table 2.</li><li>(2) 10 samples of each of the Examples and the Comparative Examples were
subjected to the 3-point bending test prescribed in JIS R1601. The average of
measured values of 10 samples was calculated for each of the Examples and the
Comparative Examples, with respect to a bending strength of before coating with the
hard film and a bending strength of after coating with the hard film. The results are
shown in Table 2.</li><li>(3) The strength of a sample after coating with the hard film was divided by
that before coating with the hard film. The resulting value was expressed in
percentage for use as the strength ratio. The results are shown in Table 2.</li><li>(4) The cutting tools of the Examples and the Comparative Examples were
chamfered (0.2 mm x 25°) at the nose thereof. Then, the cutting tools were subjected
to cutting under the following conditions:
<sl><li>Workpiece material: FC200 (plain cast iron) prescribed in JIS G5501 (1989)</li><li>Cutting speed: 100 m/min</li><li>Feed rate: 0.1 mm/rev</li><li>Depth of cut: 1.0 mm</li><li>Cutting time: 60 min</li></sl>The cutting tools were measured for the amount of flank wear and the amount
of notch wear. The results are shown in Table 2.</li><li>(5) The cutting tool samples before coating with the hard film were observed
for microstructure in the following manner. The surface of a substrate and the
central cut surface of the substrate were polished to mirror finish. The polished
surfaces were observed for microstructure by use of a scanning electron microscope
(SEM).</li></sl>Specifically, a surface of the substrate (a surface obtained through
polishing an un-polished sintered body to a depth of 300 µm) was observed by use of 
the scanning electron microscope to thereby obtain a (SEM) photograph
(magnification: 60000) of the microstructure of the surface (see FIG. 4(a)). Further,
a central cut surface (specifically, a cut surface passing through the barycenter) of the
substrate was observed by use of the scanning electron microscope to thereby obtain
a photograph (magnification: 60000) of the microstructure of the central cut surface
of the substrate (see FIG. 4(b)). Through analysis of the images of these
photographs, the amount of the grain boundary phase was measured.It is to be noted that the "surface of the substrate" refers to a surface of an
insert obtained by grinding a sintered body, and in general, refers to a surface
obtained by removing, through grinding, a surface portion of the sintered body by an
amount of 200 to 300 µm. Through analysis of the image of the SEM photograph of
the surface of the substrate, the ratio of a grain boundary phase in a region extending
radially at a radius of 1.5 µm from a point located at a depth of 300 µm from the
surface of the substrate was obtained for use as the amount of a grain boundary phase
of a surface portion of the substrate. Also, through analysis of the image of the SEM
photograph of the central cut surface of the substrate, the ratio of a grain boundary
phase in a region extending radially at a radius of 1.5 µm from the barycenter of the
substrate was obtained for use as the amount of a grain boundary phase of a central
portion of the substrate. The amount of a grain boundary phase of a surface portion
of the substrate was divided by that of a central portion of the substrate. The
resulting value was expressed in percentage for use as the amount of a grain
boundary phase of the substrate surface (the amount of a grain boundary phase at a
depth of 300 µm). The results are shown in Table 2. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"  namest="1"/><entry align="center"  namest="2">Sample No.</entry><entry nameend="5"  align="center" namest="3">Heat Treatment Conditions</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Temp. [°C]</entry><entry align="center">Time [min]</entry><entry align="center">Pressure [kPa]</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="1">Comparative Example</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1500</entry><entry align="center">180</entry><entry align="center">6.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">2</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">240</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="1">Example</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">3</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">1550</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">60</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comparative Example</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">5</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">26</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">6</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">180</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">6.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="1">Comparative Example</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">7</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">240</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">8</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">1600</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">9</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">120</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="1">Comparative Example</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">10</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">240</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">11</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">1650</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="2">Example</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">12</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">60</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">13</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">180</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">14</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">13</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="2">Comparative Example</entry><entry align="center" namest="2">15</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">26</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">16</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">1700</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">30</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">13</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">17</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">60</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="131" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="229"/></li><li>c) As seen from Tables 1 and 2, the samples of Example Nos. 3, 4, 6, 9, and
12 to 14, which fall within the scope of the present invention, exhibit a volatilization
of 1.5% to 3.5% by weight and an amount of grain boundary phase of 50% to 70%
by volume as measured at the substrate surface.</li></sl></p><p num="0023">As a result, the samples of the Examples exhibit a strength ratio not less than
70, indicating a low impairment in strength after coating with the hard film. The
samples also exhibit a small amount of flank wear not greater than 0.2 mm and a
small amount of notch wear not greater than 0.22 mm. Thus, the cutting tools of the
Examples have excellent resistance to chipping and wear resistance and are thus
favorably applicable not only to normal cutting but also, for example, to heavy
cutting.</p><p num="0024">By contrast, the samples of Comparative Example Nos. 1, 2, 5, 8, 11, and 15
respectively exhibit a volatilization rate of 1, 1.1, 1.3, 1.3, 1.3, and 1.3% by weight
and an amount of grain boundary phase of 90%, 89%, 80%, 80%, 81%, and 86% by
volume as measured at the substrate surface.</p><p num="0025">As a result, the samples of the Comparative Examples exhibit a high strength
ratio of 94.6, 92.2, 92.7, 95, 93.3, and 91.1. However, the samples exhibit a large
amount of flank wear of 0.35, 0.35, 0.34, 0.33, 0.32, and 0.33 mm and a large
amount of notch wear of 0.31, 0.39, 0.35, 0.35, 0.33, and 0.4 mm. Thus, the cutting
tools of the Comparative Examples fail to exhibit sufficiently high resistance to wear.</p><p num="0026">The samples of Comparative Example Nos. 7, 10, and 16 respectively exhibit
a volatilization rate of 3.7, 4, and 4% by weight and an amount of grain boundary
phase of 48%, 40%, and 42% by volume as measured at the substrate surface.</p><p num="0027">As a result, the samples of the Comparative Examples exhibit a low strength
ratio of 55.5, 54.9, and 51.3, although the samples exhibit a small amount of flank
wear of 0.12, 0.13, and 0.13 mm and a small amount of notch wear of 0.11, 0.13, and
0.18 mm. Thus, due to low bending strength, the cutting tools of the Comparative
Examples exhibit impaired resistance to chipping.</p><p num="0028">The samples of Comparative Example No. 17 could not be evaluated, since
silicon nitride was decomposed due to high heating temperature. </p><p num="0029">The present invention is not limited to the above-described embodiments, but
may be embodied in various forms without departing from the scope of the present
invention.</p><p num="0030">For example, the present invention is applicable not only to a square plate-like
cutting tool but also to a triangular plate-like cutting tool.</p><p num="0031">As described above, the silicon nitride member of the present invention
exhibits merely a slight impairment in strength as measured after coating with the
hard film, and thus has high wear resistance and high resistance to chipping.</p><p num="0032">According to the method for manufacturing a silicon nitride member of the
present invention, a silicon nitride member having high wear resistance and high
resistance to chipping can be readily manufactured.</p><p num="0033">A cutting tool formed of the thus-manufactured silicon nitride member can
exhibit long life under heavy-load working conditions.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A silicon nitride member comprising a substrate formed through
sintering of a silicon nitride material, and a hard film formed on a surface of said
substrate, said silicon nitride member characterized in that:
   when the strength of said substrate as measured before said substrate is
coated with said hard film is taken as 100%, the strength of said silicon nitride
member as measured after said substrate is coated with said hard film is 70% to 95%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A silicon nitride member according to Claim 1, wherein a change in
weight of said substrate associated with sintering is 1.5% to 3.5% by weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A silicon nitride member comprising a substrate formed through
sintering of a silicon nitride material, and a hard film formed on a surface of said
substrate, said silicon nitride member characterized in that:
   when the amount of a grain boundary phase as measured at a central portion
of said substrate is taken as 100% by volume, at least one of the following conditions
(1) to (5) is satisfied:
<claim-text><claim-text>(1) the amount of a grain boundary phase as measured in the vicinity of a
depth of 100 µm from the surface of said substrate is less than 30% by volume;</claim-text><claim-text>(2) the amount of a grain boundary phase as measured in the vicinity of a
depth of 200 µm from the surface of said substrate is 30% to 50% by volume;</claim-text><claim-text>(3) the amount of a grain boundary phase as measured in the vicinity of a
depth of 300 µm from the surface of said substrate is 50% to 70% by volume;</claim-text><claim-text>(4) the amount of a grain boundary phase as measured in the vicinity of a
depth of 400 µm from the surface of said substrate is 70% to 85% by volume; and</claim-text><claim-text>(5) the amount of a grain boundary phase as measured in the vicinity of a
depth of 500 µm from the surface of said substrate is 85% to 100% by volume.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A silicon nitride member according to Claim 3, wherein a change in
weight of said substrate associated with sintering is 1.5% to 3.5% by weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A method, for manufacturing a silicon nitride member defined in any
preceding claim, which comprises the step of:
   adjusting a condition employed in sintering said substrate such that a change
in weight of the substrate associated with sintering is 1.5% to 3.5% by weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method according to claim 5 for manufacturing a silicon nitride
member, comprising the steps of:
   heating the substrate at a temperature in the range of from 1800°C to 1900°C
for 60 to 180 minutes in a nitrogen atmosphere pressurized at from 2 to 6
atmospheres; subsequently lowering the temperature to the range of 1550°C to
1650°C; and maintaining the substrate at the reduced temperature for 60 to 180
minutes under a reduced pressure not higher than 13 kPa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A cutting tool formed of a silicon nitride member as defined in any
one of Claims 1 to 4.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>