<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1298191-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1298191" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25512236" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030402"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1298191-A1" status="new" fvid="23732213"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1298191</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030402</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02256540-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02256540</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020920</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-96704901-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>96704901</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010928</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 125/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 125/10        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 125/20        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 125/22        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 125/24        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 125/26        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 129/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 129/93        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 135/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 135/10        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 141/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 141/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 141/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 151/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 151/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 163/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 163/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 169/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 169/04        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  10/02        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  10/04        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  20/04        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  30/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  40/02        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  40/04        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 141/08</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 141/10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 163/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M201:062</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M201:08</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M201:082</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M201:084</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M201:085</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M201:087</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M201:102</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M207:129</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M207:34</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M219:044</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M219:046</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N210:01+2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N210:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N220:021</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N220:142</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N230:04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N230:26</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N240:04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N240:08</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Schmiermittelzusammensetzung mit verbesserter Wassertoleranz</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Lubricant composition with improved water tolerance</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition lubrifiante avec une tolerance à l'eau améliorée</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0976813-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0976813</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4263155-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4263155</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1988003943-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1988003943</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHEVRON ORONITE CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHEVRON ORONITE COMPANY LLC</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Chevron Oronite Company LLC</last-name><address><street>1301 McKinney Street</street><city>Houston, Texas 77010</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HARRISON JAMES J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NELSON KENNETH D</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HARRISON, JAMES J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NELSON, KENNETH D.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HARRISON, JAMES J.</last-name><address><street>12 Stonehaven Court</street><city>Novato, California 94947</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NELSON, KENNETH D.</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 5192</street><city>Clear Lake, California 95422</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Nash, David Allan</last-name><address><street>Haseltine Lake &amp;amp; Co., Imperial House, 15-19 Kingsway</street><city>London WC2B 6UD</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Disclosed are lubricant compositions comprising a dispersed hydrated alkali
metal borate, a polyalkylene succinic dispersant selected from a polyalkylene succinic
anhydride, a mixture of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides or derivatives thereof; and a
metal salt of a polyisobutenyl sulfonate. Also disclosed are methods for improving
the water tolerance of a lubricant composition and methods for preparing such
lubricants comprising a dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate and a dispersant
mixture.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Field of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0001">This invention is directed, in part, to novel lubricant compositions. These
compositions comprise an alkali metal borate; a polyalkylene succinic anhydride
including mixtures and/or derivatives thereof; and a metal salt of a polyisobutenyl
sulfonate. Surprisingly, these compositions have improved compatibility, extreme
pressure properties and/or water tolerance over compositions comprising other metal
sulfonates.</p><p num="0002">This invention is also directed, in part, to methods for improving the water
tolerance of a lubricant composition comprising an alkali metal borate. Such methods
employ compositions comprising an alkali metal borate; and a polyalkylene succinic
anhydride including mixtures and/or derivatives thereof; and a metal salt of a
polyisobutenyl sulfonate.</p><heading><u style="single">References</u></heading><p num="0003">The following references are cited in this application as superscript
numbers:
<sl><li><sup>1</sup> Peeler, U.S. Patent No. 3,313,727, <i>Alkali Metal Borale E.P. Lubricants</i>,
issued April 11, 1967</li><li><sup>2</sup> Adams, U.S. Patent No. 3,912,643, <i>Lubricant Containing Neutralized
Alkali Metal Borales</i>, issued October 14, 1975</li><li><sup>3</sup> Sims, U.S. Patent No. 3,819,521, <i>Lubricant Containing Dispersed Borate
and a Polyol</i>, issued June 25, 1974 </li><li><sup>4</sup> Adams, U.S. Patent No. 3,853,772, <i>Lubricant Containing Alkali Metal
Borate Dispersed with a Mixture of Dispersants,</i> issued December 10, 1974</li><li><sup>5</sup> Adams, U.S. Patent No. 3,997,454, <i>Lubricant Containing Potassium
Borate,</i> issued December 14, 1976</li><li><sup>6</sup> Adams, U.S. Patent No. 4,089,790, <i>Synergistic Combinations of Hydrated
Potassium Borate, Antiwear Agents, and Organic Sulfide Antioxidants,</i> issued
May 16, 1978</li><li><sup>7</sup> Adams, U.S. Patent No. 4,163,729, <i>Synergistic Combinations of Hydrated
Potassium Borate, Antiwear Agents, and Organic Sulfide Antioxidants,</i> issued
August 7, 1979</li><li><sup>8</sup> Frost, U.S. Patent No. 4,263,155, <i>Lubricant Composition Containing an
Alkali Metal Borate and a Sulfur-Containing Polyhydroxy Compound</i>, U.S. Patent
No. 5,461,184, issued October 24, 1995</li><li><sup>9</sup> Frost, U.S. Patent No. 4,401,580, <i>Lubricant Composition Containing an
Alkali Metal Borate and an Ester-Polyol Compound,</i> issued August 30, 1983</li><li><sup>10</sup> Frost, U.S. Patent No. 4,472,288, <i>Lubricant Composition Containing an
Alkali Metal Borate and an Oil-Soluble Amine Salt of a Phosphorus Compound,</i>
issued September 18, 1984</li><li><sup>11</sup> Clark, U.S. Patent No. 4,584,873, <i>Automotive Friction Reducing
Composition,</i> issued August 13, 1985</li><li><sup>12</sup> Brewster, U.S. Patent No. 3,489,619, <i>Heat Transfer and Quench Oil</i>,
issued January 13, 1970</li></sl></p><p num="0004">All of the above references are herein incorporated by reference in their
entirety to the same extent as if each individual publication or patent was specifically
and individually indicated to be incorporated by reference in its entirety.</p><heading><u style="single">State of the Art</u></heading><p num="0005">High load conditions often occur in gear sets such as those used in automobile
transmissions and differentials, pneumatic tools, gas compressors, centrifuges,
high-pressure hydraulic systems, metal workings and similar devices as well as in
many types of bearings. When employed in such environments, it is conventional to
add an extreme-pressure agent to the lubricant composition and, in this regard, alkali
metal borates are well known extreme-pressure agents for such compositions.<sup>1-12</sup></p><p num="0006">Because the alkali metal borate is insoluble in lubricant oil media, it is
conventional to include a dispersant/detergent in such compositions in order to
facilitate the formation of a homogenous dispersion. Examples of
dispersant/detergents include ionic surface-active agents such as metal salts of oil
soluble acidic organic compounds, e.g., sulfonates, carboxylates and phenolates, as
well as non-ionic surface-active agents such as alkenyl succinimides or other nitrogen
containing dispersants.<sup>1-4</sup> It is also conventional to employ the alkali metal borate at
particle sizes of less than 1 micron in order to facilitate the formation of the
homogenous dispersion.<sup>11</sup></p><p num="0007">The use of alkali metal borates in lubricant compositions is complicated by the
presence of water in the environment where the composition is employed.
Conventional preparation methods remove essentially all the water from the media<sup>12</sup>.
However, when the presence of water exceeds a threshold concentration in the
lubricant composition, the borate crystallizes out of the composition and forms hard
granules. These granules cause severe noise in the lubricated systems and can
severely damage the gears or bearings themselves as well as leading to seal leakage.<sup>10</sup>
Further, borate lost by crystallization decreases the extreme pressure properties of the
lubricant composition.</p><p num="0008">On the other hand, lubricant compositions employing alkali metal borates are
often employed in environments where water is invariably present.</p><p num="0009">In view of the above, enhanced water tolerance of lubricant compositions
comprising an alkali metal borate would be particularly beneficial.</p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0010">This invention is directed to the novel and unexpected discovery that enhanced
water tolerance and lubricant oil compatibility for alkali metal borates can be
achieved by employing a dispersant mixture comprising:
<sl><li>a) a polyalkylene succinic dispersant which is selected from the group
consisting of a polyalkylene succinic anhydride, a non-nitrogen containing derivative
of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride, mixtures of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides,
mixtures of non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic
anhydride and mixtures of one or more polyalkylene succinic anhydrides and one or
more non-nitrogen containing derivatives of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides; and</li><li>b) a metal salt of a polyisobutenyl sulfonate.</li></sl></p><p num="0011">Accordingly, in one of its composition aspects, this invention is directed to a
lubricant composition which comprises a base oil of lubricating viscosity, a dispersed
hydrated alkali metal borate, and a dispersant mixture comprising:
<sl><li>a) a polyalkylene succinic dispersant which is selected from the group
consisting of a polyalkylene succinic anhydride, a non-nitrogen containing derivative
of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride, mixtures of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides,
mixtures of non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic
anhydride, and mixtures of one or more polyalkylene succinic anhydrides and one or
more non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride; and</li><li>b) a metal salt of a polyisobutenyl sulfonate.</li></sl></p><p num="0012">Preferably, the dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate is present in a ratio of at
least 2:1 relative to the dispersant mixture of polyalkylene succinic dispersant and
polyisobutenyl sulfonate. More preferably, the ratio of dispersed hydrated alkali
metal borate to dispersant mixture is from 2:1 up to 10:1. Most preferably the ratio is
5:2.</p><p num="0013">Preferably, the dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate is a dispersed hydrated
sodium borate. Even more preferably the dispersed hydrated sodium borate and has a
sodium to boron ratio of from about 1:2.75 to about 1:3.25.</p><p num="0014">In a particularly preferred embodiment, the dispersed hydrated alkali metal
borate is a hydrated sodium metal borate having a hydroxyl:boron ratio (OH:B) of
from about 0.8:1 to1.6:1 (more preferably about 0.8:1 to 1:1) and a sodium to boron
ratio of from about 1:2.75 to 1:3.25 and the polyalkylene succinic anhydride is a
polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride.</p><p num="0015">Preferably, the hydrated alkali metal borate contains small amounts of a water
soluble oxo anion. Only from 0.001 moles to 0.11 moles of water
soluble oxo anion should be present per mole of boron. This water-soluble oxo anion
can include nitrate, sulfate, carbonate, phosphate, pyrophosphate, silicate, aluminate,
germanate, stannate, zincate, plumbate, titanate, molybdate, tungstate, vanadate,
niobate, tantalate, uranates, or can include the isopolymolybdates and
isopolytungstates, or the heteropolymolybdates and heteropolytungstates, or mixtures
thereof.</p><p num="0016">Preferably, the polyalkylene succinic dispersant, is a dispersant selected from a
polyalkylene succinic anhydride or a mixture of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides.
More preferably, the polyalkylene succinic anhydride is a polyisobutenyl succinic 
anhydride. In one preferred embodiment, the polyalkylene succinic anhydride is a
polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride having a number average molecular weight of at
least 500, more preferably at least 900 and still more preferably from at least about
900 to about 3000.</p><p num="0017">In another preferred embodiment, a mixture of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides
is employed. In this embodiment, the mixture preferably comprises a low molecular
weight polyalkylene succinic anhydride component and a high molecular weight
polyalkylene succinic anhydride component. More preferably, the low molecular
weight component has a number average molecular weight of from about 500 to
below 1000 and the high molecular weight component has a number average
molecular weight of from 1000 to about 3000. Still more preferably, both the low and
high molecular weight components are polyisobutenyl succinic anhydrides.</p><p num="0018">Preferably the metal salt of the polyisobutenyl sulfonate can be an alkali metal
or alkaline earth metal salt. More preferably, the metal salt of the polyisobutenyl
sulfonate is a calcium salt. Even more preferably, the calcium polyisobutenyl
sulfonate employed has a total base number (TBN) of from about 14-17 due to the
presence of some Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub> in the composition.</p><p num="0019">The polyisobutene employed is of sufficient molecular weight to provide
oil-solubility to the polyisobutenyl sulfonic acid or metal salt thereof. Suitably,
polyisobutenes having a number average molecular weight of from at least about
200 are employed. Preferably, the polyisobutene has a number average molecular
weight of from about 200 to about 3000; more preferably, from about 300 to 2000;
still more preferably, from about 400 to 1200; and even more preferably from about
500 to 1100.</p><p num="0020">This invention is also directed to methods for enhancing the water tolerance of
lubricant compositions comprising alkali metal borate. Accordingly, in one of its
method aspects, this invention is directed to a method for enhancing the water
tolerance of lubricant compositions comprising alkali metal borate which method
comprises adding an anti-wear effective amount of an alkali metal borate to a base oil
of lubricating viscosity in combination with a dispersant effective amount of a
dispersant mixture comprising:
<sl><li>a) a polyalkylene succinic dispersant which is selected from the group
consisting of a polyalkylene succinic anhydride, a non-nitrogen containing derivative
of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride, mixtures of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides, 
mixtures of non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic
anhydride, and mixtures of one or more polyalkylene succinic anhydrides and one or
more non-nitrogen containing derivatives of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides; and</li><li>b) a metal salt of a polyisobutenyl sulfonate.</li></sl></p><p num="0021">This invention is still further directed to methods for the preparation of such
lubricant compositions. Accordingly, in another of its method aspects, this invention
is directed to a method for preparing a lubricant composition comprising a base oil of
lubricating viscosity, a dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate, and a dispersant
mixture comprising:
<sl><li>a) a polyalkylene succinic dispersant which is selected from the group
consisting of a polyalkylene succinic anhydride, a non-nitrogen containing derivative
of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride, mixtures of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides,
mixtures of non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic
anhydride, and mixtures of one or more polyalkylene succinic anhydrides and one or
more non-nitrogen containing derivatives of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides; and</li><li>b) a metal salt of a polyisobutenyl sulfonate</li></sl>
   which method comprises:

   mixing, under agitation, (1) an aqueous solution of boric acid and alkali metal
hydroxide, and (2) a diluent oil containing the polyalkylene succinic dispersant and
the metal salt of a polyisobutenyl sulfonate; then heating the mixture to partially
dehydrate the mixture.</p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0022">This invention is directed, in part, to novel lubricant compositions comprising
a base oil of lubricating viscosity, dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate and a
dispersant mixture comprising:
<sl><li>a) a polyalkylene succinic dispersant which is selected from the group
consisting of a polyalkylene succinic anhydride, a non-nitrogen containing derivative
of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride, mixtures of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides,
mixtures of non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic
anhydride, and mixtures of one or more polyalkylene succinic anhydrides and one or
more non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride; and</li><li>b) a metal salt of a polyisobutenyl sulfonate.</li></sl></p><p num="0023">Each of these components in the claimed composition will be defined herein. </p><heading><b>THE DISPERSED HYDRATED ALKALI METAL BORATE</b></heading><p num="0024">Hydrated alkali metal borates are well known in the art. Representative patents
disclosing suitable borates and methods of manufacture include: U.S.
Patent Nos. 3,313,727; 3,819,521; 3,853,772; 3,912,643; 3,997,454; and 4,089,790.<sup>1-6</sup> </p><p num="0025">The hydrated alkali metal borates can be represented by the following formula:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">M<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub>O·<st32:italic>m</st32:italic>B<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub>O<st32:sub pos="post">3</st32:sub>·<st32:italic>n</st32:italic>H<st32:sub pos="post">2</st32:sub>O</st32:df>
   where M is sodium or potassium, <i>m</i> is a number preferably from 2.5 to 4.5 (both
whole and fractional), and <i>n</i> is a number preferably from 1.0 to 4.8. Preferred
hydrated alkali metal borates are hydrated potassium borates and more preferably the
hydrated sodium borates because of their improved water tolerance. Most preferred
are the hydrated sodium borates having a sodium-to-boron ratio of about 1:3. In
another of its preferred embodiment, the hydrated borate particles generally have a
mean particle size of less than 1 micron.</p><p num="0026">The hydrated alkali metal borates will generally comprise about 10 to
75 weight percent, preferably 25 to 50 weight percent, more preferably about 35 to
40 weight percent of the lubricant composition. (Unless otherwise stated, all
percentages are in weight percent based on the total weight of the composition.)</p><p num="0027">The hydrated alkali metal borate dispersions have been found to be reactive in
the presence of water. The presence of water has been found to alter the size, shape,
and composition of the dispersed, amorphous borate particles to ultimately produce a
number of crystalline borates which generally separate out from the oil phase to form
deposits in the oil, and can damage the elastomer seals in various engine parts and
cause leakage.</p><p num="0028">We have also found that sodium borates give better water tolerance and
compatibility than potassium borates.</p> <p num="0029">Preferably, the hydrated alkali metal borates contain small amounts of a water
soluble oxo anion. Only from 0.001 moles to 0.11 moles of water soluble oxo anion
should be present per mole of boron. This water-soluble oxo anion can include
nitrate, sulfate, carbonate, phosphate, pyrophosphate, silicate, aluminate, germanate,
stannate, zincate, plumbate, titanate, molybdate, tungstate, vanadate. niobate,
tantalate, uranates, or can include the isopolymolybdates and isopolytungstates, or the
heteropolymolybdates and heteropolytungstates, or mixtures thereof. </p> <p num="0030">The presence of small amounts of water soluble oxo anions in the alkali metal
borates is thought to improve the water tolerance of the alkali metal borates by
disrupting the crystal structure of the hydrolysis products. This results in a lower
tendency to form crystals or in a reduced rate of crystallization.</p> <p num="0031">Preferred hydrated alkali metal borates include hydrated sodium borates
particularly those characterized by a hydroxyl:boron ratio (OH:B) of from about
0.8:1 to1.6:1, preferably about 0.9:1 to 1.50:1, and by a sodium to boron ratio of from
about 1:2.75 to 1:3.25. Even more preferred hydrated sodium metal borates are those
having a hydroxyl:boron ratio of from about 1.00:1 to 1.40:1 and a sodium to boron
ratio of about 1:3.</p><p num="0032">In this regard, the term "hydroxyl:boron ratio" or "OH:B" refers to the number
of hydroxyl groups attached to boron (moles of hydroxyl groups per mole of boron) in
the dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate compositions as exemplified, for example,
by the structure below. For the purposes of this application, the OH:B ratio of a
hydrated sodium borate is calculated from the maximum infra-red, IR, absorbance
between 3800 and 3250 cm<sup>-1</sup> corrected by subtracting the baseline which is taken to
be the absorbance at 3900 cm<sup>-1</sup> of a 5.000% solution of the dispersed hydrated alkali
metal borate in an oil of lubricating viscosity wherein all interfering absorbances due
to other compounds or impurities have been subtracted. The remaining absorbance in
this range corresponds to the hydroxyl groups of the dispersed sodium borate which is
then converted to the OH:B ratio as follows:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">OH:B = 21.0A<st32:sub pos="post">max</st32:sub>/ %B</st32:df>
where A<sub>max</sub> is the IR absorbance (peak height in the region of 3800 to 3250 cm<sup>-1</sup>); and

   %B is the percent boron in the original (non-diluted) dispersed sodium borate
sample.</p><p num="0033">The absorbance in this range, 3800 to 3250 cm<sup>-1</sup>, corresponds to the hydroxyl
groups of the sodium borate oligomer complex. If other additives are added to mask
or interfere with the absorbance within this preferred range such groups will be
subtracted from the IR spectra in the initial calculation of the OH:B measurement.</p><p num="0034">This absorbance is measured with a Nicolet 5DXB FTIR Spectrometer fitted
with a DTGS detector and CsI beam splitter. The spectrometer has CaF<sub>2</sub> windows 
with 0.2 mm Teflon® spacer with small section cut out and a suitable cell holder. A
spectrum of the sample is obtained using a 4 cm<sup>-1</sup> resolution.</p><p num="0035">These sodium metal borates, having a 1:3 ratio of sodium to boron, can
generally be represented by the following theoretical formula:
<img id="img-00090001" orientation="unknown" wi="54" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00090001.tif" inline="no" he="45"/>
   where <i>n</i> is a number preferably from 1.0 to 10.</p><p num="0036">Dispersed alkali metal borate compositions are generally prepared by forming,
in deionized water, a solution of alkali metal hydroxide and boric acid optionally in
the presence of a small amount of alkali metal carbonate. The solution is then added
to a lubricant composition comprising an oil of lubricating viscosity, a dispersant
mixture of the polyalkylene succinic dispersant and polyisobutenyl sulfonate as
described above and any optional additives to be included therein (e.g., a detergent,
2,2'-thiodiethanol, and the like) to form an emulsion that is then dehydrated.
Dehydration proceeds in three steps including an initial step of water removal that is
initiated at a temperature of slightly over 100°C. This initial step is followed by a
slow increase in temperature whereupon the emulsion changes from turbid to clear.
In the final step, there is a rapid increase in temperature and the liquid once again
becomes turbid.</p><p num="0037">Formation of the hydrated alkali metal borates described herein is achieved by
stoichiometric selection of the appropriate amounts of alkali metal hydroxide and
boron trioxide and control of the extent of dehydration such that the resulting product
has the desired ratio of alkali metal to boron and the desired ratio of hydroxyl to
boron.</p><p num="0038">The dehydration of the reaction mixture is carefully controlled (i.e. using a
slower dehydration rate or employing a sweep gas, and the like) in order to avoid
condensation of water on the walls of the reaction chamber. Condensation can result 
in water droplets in the lubricant composition which, in turn, can lead to undesired
precipitate formation as described above. Such precipitate formation typically results
in large particles that fall from suspension and have deleterious properties as
previously noted. Accordingly, in a preferred embodiment of this invention,
dehydration occurs over a period of from about 3 to 8 hours.</p><p num="0039">In a particularly preferred embodiment, the hydrated alkali metal borate
particles generally have a mean particle size of less than 1 micron.</p><heading><b>THE POLYALKYLENE SUCCINIC DISPERSANT</b></heading><p num="0040">The polyalkylene succinic dispersant can be a polyalkylene succinic anhydride
or a non-nitrogen containing derivative of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride and is
preferably selected from the group consisting of a polyalkylene succinic anhydride, a
non-nitrogen containing derivative of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride, mixtures
of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides, mixtures of non-nitrogen containing derivatives
of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride, and mixtures of one or more polyalkylene
succinic anhydrides and one or more non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the
polyalkylene succinic anhydride. Non-nitrogen containing derivatives of
polyalkylene succinic anhydrides preferably include, succinic acids, Group I and/or
Group II mono- or di-metal salts of succinic acids, succinate esters formed by the
reaction of a polyalkylene succinic anhydride, acid chloride, or other derivatives with
an alcohol (e.g., HOR' where R' is alkyl of from 1 to 10) and the like.</p><p num="0041">The polyalkylene succinic anhydride is preferably a polyisobutenyl succinic
anhydride. In one preferred embodiment, the polyalkylene succinic anhydride is a
polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride having a number average molecular weight of at
least 500, more preferably at least 900-3000 and still more preferably from at least
about 900 to about 2300.</p><p num="0042">In another preferred embodiment, a mixture of polyalkylene succinic
anhydrides is employed. In this embodiment, the mixture preferably comprises a low
molecular weight polyalkylene succinic anhydride component and a high molecular
weight polyalkylene succinic anhydride component. More preferably, the low
molecular weight component has a number average molecular weight of from about
500 to below 1000 and the high molecular weight component has a number average 
molecular weight of from 1000 to about 3000. Still more preferably, both the low and
high molecular weight components are polyisobutenyl succinic anhydrides.</p><p num="0043">Preferably, the dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate is employed in a weight
ratio of at least 2:1 relative to the polyalkylene succinic anhydride dispersant while
being in the range of 2:1 to 10:1. In a preferred embodiment the weight ratio is at
least 4:1. In a preferred embodiment, mixtures as defined above of the polyalkylene
succinic anhydrides are employed.</p><p num="0044">The polyalkylene succinic anhydride is the reaction product of a polyalkylene
(preferably polyisobutene) with maleic anhydride. One can use conventional
polyisobutene, or high methylvinylidene polyisobutene in the preparation of such
polyalkylene succinic anhydrides. One can use thermal, chlorination, free radical,
acid catalyzed, or any other process in this preparation. Examples of suitable
polyalkylene succinic anhydrides are thermal PIBSA (polyisobutenyl succinic
anhydride) described in U.S. Patent No. 3,361,673; chlorination PIBSA described in
U.S. Patent No. 3,172,892; a mixture of thermal and chlorination PIBSA described in
U.S. Patent No. 3,912,764; high succinic ratio PIBSA described in U.S. Patent
No. 4,234,435; PolyPIBSA described in U.S. Patent Nos. 5,112,507 and 5,175,225;
high succinic ratio PolyPIBSA described in U.S. Patent Nos. 5,565,528 and
5,616,668; free radical PIBSA described in U.S. Patent Nos. 5,286,799, 5,319,030,
and 5,625,004; PIBSA made from high methylvinylidene polybutene described in
U.S. Patent Nos. 4,152,499, 5,137,978, and 5,137,980; high succinic ratio PIBSA
made from high methylvinylidene polybutene described in European Patent
Application Publication No. EP 355 895; terpolymer PIBSA described in U.S. Patent
No. 5,792,729; sulfonic acid PIBSA described in U.S. Patent No. 5,777,025 and
European Patent Application Publication No. EP 542 380; and purified PIBSA
described in U.S. Patent No. 5,523,417 and European Patent Application Publication
No. EP 602 863. The disclosures of each of these documents is incorporated herein
by reference in their entirety.</p><p num="0045">The number average molecular weight of the polyalkylene tail in the
polyalkylene succinic anhydride should be from about 300 to about 5000. This
should be compatible with the previous ranges given before with the particular
molecular weight depending on dispersant or mixture of dispersants to be employed.
Preferably, the polyalkylene succinic anhydride component comprises from 2 to 
40 weight percent, more preferably 10 to 15 weight percent of the weight of the
lubricant composition.</p><p num="0046">Most preferable is the case where the polyalkylene succinic anhydride
component is a polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride.</p><p num="0047">This invention is based, in part, on the discovery that the combination of a
polyalkylene succinic dispersant and a metal salt of a polyisobutenyl sulfonate
provides enhanced water tolerance and lubricating oil compatibility, when used in
lubricating compositions comprising an alkali metal borate. It has also been found
that a mixture of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides can be effectively employed. The
mixture preferably comprises a low molecular weight polyalkylene succinic
anhydride component and a high molecular weight polyalkylene succinic anhydride
component. Alternatively, various molecular weight polyalkylene succinic anhydride
components can be combined as a dispersant.</p><heading><b>THE POLYISOBUTENYL SULFONATE DISPERSANT</b></heading><p num="0048">The metal salts of polyisobutenyl sulfonates used in the compositions of this
invention can be highly overbased metal sulfonates or low overbased metal
sulfonates. In addition, the sulfonic acids themselves can also be used. Overbased
metal sulfonates are well known in the art. Highly overbased metal sulfonates
typically have a total base number (TBN) of from about 250 to about 500, whereas
low overbased metal sulfonates typically have a TBN of from about 0 to about 150.
Both highly overbased metal sulfonates and low overbased metal sulfonates are well
known in the art.</p><p num="0049">The term "metal sulfonate" is intended to encompass the salts of sulfonic acids
derived from polyisobutene. Such polyalkenyl sulfonic acids are the subject of
US Patent No. 6,410,491 (Application Serial No. 09/527166), and
incorporated herein by reference in its entirety. They can be obtained by treating
polyisobutene with sulfur trioxide or a similar sulfonating agent such as acetyl sulfate
and the like. The acids thus obtained are known as polyisobutene sulfonic acids and
the salts as metal sulfonates. Suitable metals include the alkali metals
(e.g., potassium, sodium, cesium), alkaline earth metals (e.g., magnesium, calcium,
barium). of which calcium and barium are preferred.</p><p num="0050">The polyisobutene employed is of sufficient molecular weight to provide
oil-solubility to the polyisobutenyl sulfonic acid or metal salt thereof. Suitably, 
polyisobutenes having a number average molecular weight of from at least about
200 are employed. Preferably, the polyisobutene has a numbered average molecular
weight of from about 200 to about 3000; more preferably, from about 300 to 2000;
still more preferably, from about 400 to 1200; and even more preferably from about
500 to 1100.</p><p num="0051">Suitable polyisobutenes are commercially available or can be prepared by art
recognized techniques such as those disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 4,605,808 to
Samson, issued August 12, 1986, which is incorporated by reference in its entirety.</p><p num="0052">Preferably, the polyisobutenyl sulfonates are derived from high
methyl-vinylidene isomers and/or 1,1-dialkyl isomer, preferably a 1,1-dimethyl
isomer. More preferably the polyisobutene sulfonates are high methylvinylidene
polyisobutenyl sulfonates or a mixture of such.</p><p num="0053">Preferably, the polyisobutenyl sulfonate is a low overbased calcium
polyisobutenyl sulfonate having a TBN of from about 14-17 and comprises from
0.5 to 20 weight percent, more preferably 2 to 10 weight percent of the lubricant
composition.</p><p num="0054">In one preferred embodiment, the ratio of polyisobutenyl sulfonate dispersant
to the hydrated alkali metal borate employed in the composition is from about
0.05:1 to 1:1 and more preferably about 0.11:1.</p><p num="0055">In another preferred embodiment, the ratio of the polyalkylene succinic
dispersant to the polyisobutenyl sulfonate used in the dispersant mixture is from about
4:1 and more preferably from about 2.6:1.</p><heading><b>THE OIL OF LUBRICATING VISCOSITY</b></heading><p num="0056">The lubricating oil to which the borates and the dispersant mixture are added
can be any hydrocarbon-based lubricating oil or a synthetic base oil stock. The
hydrocarbon-based lubricating oils may be derived from synthetic or natural sources
and may be paraffinic, naphthetic or asphaltenic base, or mixtures thereof. The
diluent oil can be natural or synthetic, and can be different viscosity grades.</p><p num="0057">The lubricating oil comprises from 30 to 70 weight percent, more preferably
from 45 to 55 weight percent of the lubricant composition. </p><heading><b>FORMULATIONS</b></heading><p num="0058">The dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate compositions of the present
invention (as described herein above) are generally blended to form additive packages
comprising such dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate compositions. These additive
packages typically comprise from about 10 to 75 weight percent of the dispersed
hydrated alkali metal borate composition described above and from about 90 to
15 weight percent of one or more of conventional additives selected from the group
consisting of ashless dispersants (0-5%), detergents (0-2%), sulfurized hydrocarbons
(0-30%), dialkyl hydrogen phosphates (0-10%), zinc dithiophosphates (0-20%),
dialkyl hydrogen phosphates (0-10%), pentaerythritol monooleate (0-10%),
2,5-dimercaptothiadiazole (0-5%), benzotriazole (0-5%), dispersed molybdenum
disulfide (0-5%), imidazolines (0-10%), and foam inhibitors (0-2%) and the like
wherein each weight percent is based on the total weight of the composition.</p><p num="0059">Fully formulated finished oil compositions of this invention can be formulated
from these additive packages upon further blending with an oil of lubricating
viscosity. Preferably, the additive package described above is added to an oil of
lubricating viscosity in an amount of from about 5 to 15 weight percent to provide for
the finished oil composition wherein the weight percent of the additive package is
based on the total weight of the composition. More preferably, added along with the
oil of lubricating viscosity is a polymethacrylate viscosity index improver which is
included at a level of 0-12% and/or a pour point depressant at a level of 0-1%, to form
a finished oil wherein the weight percent of each of the viscosity index improver and
pour point depressant is based on the total weight of the composition.</p><p num="0060">A variety of other additives can be present in lubricating oils of the present
invention. Those additives include antioxidants, rust inhibitors, corrosion inhibitors,
extreme pressure agents, antifoam agents, other viscosity index improvers, other
anti-wear agents, and a variety of other well-known additives in the art.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLES</b></heading><p num="0061">The invention will be further illustrated by the following examples, which set
forth particularly advantageous method embodiments. While the examples are
provided to illustrate the present invention, they are not intended to limit it. </p><p num="0062">As used herein, the following abbreviations have the following meanings. If
not defined, the abbreviation will have its art recognized meaning.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="10"><dt>cSt</dt><dd>=   centistokes</dd><dt>g</dt><dd>=   gram</dd><dt>IR</dt><dd>=   infra-red</dd><dt>LOB</dt><dd>=   low overbased</dd><dt>M</dt><dd>=   metal</dd><dt>mm</dt><dd>=   millimeters</dd><dt>mL</dt><dd>=   milliliter</dd><dt>Mn or M<sub>n</sub></dt><dd>=   number average molecular weight</dd><dt>NTU or ntu</dt><dd>=   nephelometric turbidity unit</dd><dt>PIB</dt><dd>=   polyisobutylene</dd><dt>PIBS</dt><dd>=   polyisobutenyl sulfonate</dd><dt>PIBSA</dt><dd>=   polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride</dd><dt>PSD</dt><dd>=   particle size distribution (microns)</dd><dt>TBN</dt><dd>=   total base number (mgKOH/g)</dd><dt>vis</dt><dd>=   viscosity</dd></dl></p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0063">A dispersed alkali metal borate composition is prepared by dehydrating a
water-in-oil emulsion of an aqueous solution of an alkali metal hydroxide and boric
acid. Preferably a solution is prepared having an alkali metal to boron ratio of 1 to 3.
This solution is then added to a combination of neutral oil, succinic dispersant, and a
polyisobutenyl (PIB) sulfonate and mixed to form an emulsion. The resulting
emulsion is heated to partially dehydrate it. Reduced pressures can also be used and
the temperature set accordingly. During dehydration of the emulsion there is an initial
period when water is removed from the emulsion at a rapid rate at a constant
temperature for example at about 102°C. After this period, nearly all process water
has been eliminated and water removed after this stage is due to the dehydration of
the hydrated borate oligomer. Then the temperature slowly increases and the
emulsion changes from turbid to clear. As the degree of dehydration and temperature
continue to increase, the resulting liquid will again become turbid.</p><heading><u style="single">Sodium borate dispersions:</u></heading><p num="0064">A hydrated sodium borate dispersion was prepared by dehydration of an
oil-in-water emulsion of an aqueous sodium borate and a succinic dispersant/PIB 
sulfonate oil solution by heating it to 270°F for about 3 hours. The aqueous solution
was prepared in 2 liter glass beaker by stirring and heating mixtures of: 136.4g of
deionized water, 109.8g of 99.5% Boric Acid (EMScience), 46.8g of 50% Sodium
Hydroxide in water (VWR), and 0.30g of 99.5% Sodium Carbonate (EMScience),
until the boric acid completely dissolved. Oil-in-water emulsions were made by
gradually adding the aqueous phase to an oil phase containing: 136.15g of
Exxon 150 Neutral oil, a group I base oil, 30.25g of a polyisobutenyl alkenyl succinic
anhydride having a molecular weight of about 1100 amu, and 13.25g of a low
overbased calcium polyisobutenyl sulfonate having a TBN of about 14-17 mgKOH/g
and wherein the polyisobutenyl moiety has an average molecular weight of about
550 amu, under a vigorous mixing action. A high shear mixer is preferred to form an
emulsion or a micro-emulsion.</p><p num="0065">The emulsion was then dehydrated in a 1-liter stainless steel kettle equipped
with a mechanical stirrer, heat mantle, temperature controller, and nitrogen sweep line
at a temperature of about 270°F for a period of about 3 hours to provide a hydrated
sodium borate composition having a hydroxyl:boron ratio of about 0.8:1 and a sodium
to boron ratio of 3:1.</p><p num="0066">This composition contains approximately:
<sl><li>45 weight percent of the hydrated sodium borate;</li><li>13 weight percent of polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride;</li><li>5 weight percent of the calcium polyisobutenyl sulfonate; and
the balance being the oil of lubricating viscosity.</li></sl></p><heading>EXAMPLES 2-4</heading><p num="0067">In addition, using the procedure as described above, three other hydrated
sodium borate compositions were prepared. Example 2 used a low overbased calcium
polyisobutenyl sulfonate having a TBN of about 14-17 mgKOH/g and wherein the
polyisobutenyl moiety has a number average molecular weight of about 1000 amu.
Example 3 employed a calcium alkylaromatic sulfonate having a number average
molecular weight of about 500 and a TBN of about 28 in place of the calcium
polyisobutenyl sulfonate; and Example 4 employed a calcium natural sulfonate with a
TBN of about 5, in place of the calcium polyisobutenyl sulfonate. All dispersants in 
the above examples were employed as a mixture with the same polyisobutenyl
succinic anhydride at approximately the same ratio of 2.6:1. The other components in
the hydrated sodium borate compositions were employed in approximately the same
ratio as Example 1. These results are summarized in Table 1.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1">Chemical and Physical Properties of Borate Dispersions</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ex</entry><entry align="left">Dispersant Mixture

PIBSA/Sulfonate</entry><entry align="center">TBN</entry><entry align="center">Turbidity Ntu</entry><entry align="center">OH:B</entry><entry align="center">PSD 90 %</entry><entry align="center">PSD 50 %</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">PIBSA/Calcium polyisobutenyl sulfonate PIBS 550</entry><entry align="center">121.5</entry><entry align="center">17.4</entry><entry align="center">0.81:1</entry><entry align="center">0.18</entry><entry align="center">0.14</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">PIBSA/Calcium polyisobutenyl sulfonate PIBS 1000</entry><entry align="center">122.9</entry><entry align="center">104</entry><entry align="center">0.87:1</entry><entry align="center">0.19</entry><entry align="center">0.14</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">PIBSA/Calcium alkyl-aromatic sulfonate</entry><entry align="center">123.3</entry><entry align="center">84</entry><entry align="center">0.72:1</entry><entry align="center">0.19</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">PIBSA/Natural sulfonate</entry><entry align="center">123.2</entry><entry align="center">104</entry><entry align="center">0.79:1</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0068">In Table 1, the column "PSD 90%" refers to particle size distribution and is a
measure of particle size wherein at least 90% of the particles are less than the
indicated value, in microns. Similarly, the column "PSD 50%" measures particle size
wherein at least 50% of the particles are less than the indicated value, in microns.</p><heading><u style="single">Water Tolerance Performance</u></heading><p num="0069">The water tolerance of a gear oil composition as a function of the dispersant
mixture used was evaluated. Hydrated sodium borate compositions prepared
similarly to that of Example 1 above were combined with additives to form fully
formulated gear oil compositions. These were prepared by taking the borate
lubricating compositions of Example 1, and blending at a dosage of about 46% into a
typical additive package comprising, ashless dispersant, calcium sulfonate, corrosion
inhibitor, EP agent, friction modifier, multifunctional additives, metal deactivator, etc.
This additive package was then added at the level of 6.5% to diluent oil to make an
80W90 finished oil formulation. This formulation was then run in the Coordinating
Research Counsel L-33 test, to test water tolerance; see U.S. Patent 4,089,790
incorporated herein by reference. </p><p num="0070">Each of these gear oil formulations were then subjected to water
contamination at elevated temperatures using the CRC L-33 test. This test evaluates
lubricant performance by exposure of the lubricant to a severe environment.
Performance is based upon deposit and rust conditions within the test equipment as
well as the condition of the lubricant upon completion of the test. In this test,
1.2 liters of test lubricant are placed in a bench-mounted automotive differential
assembly and water, approximately 30 milliliters, is added thus, simulating a type of
severe filed service in which corrosion promoting moisture in the form of condensed
water vapor has accumulated in the axle assembly. This test has been determined to
correlate to field service. The results of this test are found in Table 2 below:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">Water Tolerance Data</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex</entry><entry align="center">Dispersant Mixture</entry><entry align="center">L33 Deposits, Area %</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">Polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride/ calcium polyisobutenyl sulfonate PIBS 550</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">Polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride/ calcium polyisobutenyl sulfonate PIBS 1000</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">Polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride/ calcium alkyl-aromatic sulfonate</entry><entry align="center">6</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">Polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride/ natural sulfonate</entry><entry align="center">8.5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0071">L33 deposits, area %, are the percentage of the differential housing and parts
covered with deposits, as determined by the prescribed method. The results of this
test illustrate that water tolerance for the compositions of this invention are
significantly superior to those of conventional additive combinations.</p><p num="0072">From the foregoing description, various modifications and changes in the above
described invention will occur to those skilled in the art. All such modifications
coming within the scope of the appended claims are intended to be included therein.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A lubricant composition which comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>a base oil of lubricating viscosity;</claim-text><claim-text>a dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate; and</claim-text><claim-text>a dispersant mixture comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) a polyalkylene succinic dispersant which is selected from the group
consisting of a polyalkylene succinic anhydride, a non-nitrogen containing derivative
of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride, mixtures of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides,
mixtures of non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic
anhydride, and mixtures of one or more polyalkylene succinic anhydrides and one or
more non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride; and</claim-text><claim-text>b) a metal salt of a polyisobutenyl sulfonate.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 1, wherein the
dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate is a dispersed hydrated sodium borate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 2, wherein the
dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate is a dispersed hydrated sodium borate and has a
sodium to boron ratio of from about 1:2.75 to about 1:3.25.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 1, wherein the polyalkylene
succinic anhydride is a polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride having a number average
molecular weight of at least 500.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 4, wherein the
polyisobutenyl succinic anhydride has a number average molecular weight of from
about 900 to about 3000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 1, comprising a mixture of
polyalkylene succinic anhydrides, said mixture having a low number average
molecular weight component of from 500 to below 1000, and having a high number
average molecular weight component of from 1000 to about 3000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 1, wherein the dispersed
hydrated alkali metal borate has a ratio of at least 2:1 relative to the dispersant
mixture of polyalkylene succinic dispersant and polyisobutenyl sulfonate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 7, wherein the dispersed
hydrated alkali metal borate has a ratio of from 2:1 to 10:1 relative to the dispersant
mixture.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 8, wherein the dispersed
hydrated alkali metal borate has a ratio of about 5:2 relative to the dispersant mixture.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 1, wherein the metal salt of
a polyisobutenyl sulfonate is an alkali metal or alkaline earth metal salt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 10, wherein the metal salt of
a polyisobutenyl sulfonate is an alkaline earth metal salt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 11, wherein the alkaline
earth metal salt is calcium.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 1, wherein the metal salt of
a polyisobutenyl sulfonate has a polyisobutenyl moiety having a number average
molecular weight of from about 200 to about 3000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 13 wherein the metal salt of
a polyisobutenyl sulfonate has a polyisobutenyl moiety having a number average
molecular weight of from about 500 to about 1100.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 1, which further comprises
from about 0.001 moles to about 0.11 moles of a water soluble oxo anion per mole of
boron.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 15, wherein said oxo anion
is selected from the group consisting of nitrate, sulfate, carbonate, phosphate,
pyrophosphate, silicate, aluminate, germanate, stannate, zincate, plumbate, titanate,
molbydate, tungstate, vanadate, niobate, tantalate, uranate, isopolymolybdate,
isopolytungstate, heteropolymolybdate, heteropolytungstates, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A method for enhancing the water tolerance of lubricant compositions
comprising alkali metal borate which method comprises adding an anti-wear effective
amount of an alkali metal borate to a base oil of lubricating viscosity in combination
with a dispersant effective amount of a dispersant mixture comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) a polyalkylene succinic dispersant which is selected from the group
consisting of a polyalkylene succinic anhydride, a non-nitrogen containing derivative
of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride, mixtures of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides,
mixtures of non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic
anhydride, and mixtures of one or more polyalkylene succinic anhydrides and one or
more non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride; and</claim-text><claim-text>b) a metal salt of a polyisobutenyl sulfonate.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A method for preparing a lubricant composition comprising a base oil of
lubricating viscosity, a dispersed hydrated alkali metal borate, and a dispersant
mixture comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) a polyalkylene succinic dispersant which is selected from the group
consisting of a polyalkylene succinic anhydride, a non-nitrogen containing derivative
of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride, mixtures of polyalkylene succinic anhydrides,
mixtures of non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic
anhydride and mixtures of one or more polyalkylene succinic anhydrides and one or
more non-nitrogen containing derivatives of the polyalkylene succinic anhydride; and</claim-text><claim-text>b) a metal salt of a polyisobutenyl sulfonate;</claim-text></claim-text>
   which method comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>mixing, under agitation, (1) an aqueous solution of boric acid and alkali metal
hydroxide, and (2) a diluent oil containing the polyalkylene succinic dispersant and
the polyisobutenyl sulfonate; and</claim-text><claim-text>heating the mixture to remove the water.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The method according to Claim 18 wherein the dispersed hydrated alkali
metal borate is a dispersed hydrated sodium borate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The lubricant composition according to Claim 1, wherein the dispersed
hydrated alkali metal borate is a dispersed hydrated sodium borate having a hydroxyl
to boron ratio of from about 0.8:1 to 1.6:1.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>