<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1184387-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1184387" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="24628821" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020306"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1184387-A2" status="new" fvid="23374262"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1184387</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20020306</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01307020-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01307020</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010817</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-65542300-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>65542300</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000905</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07B  61/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07B  61/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07F   7/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07F   7/12        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07F   7/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07F   7/16</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Steigerung der Bildung von Dialkyldihalosilan während des Direkt-Verfahrens</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method for promoting dialkyldihalosilane formation during direct method alkylhalosilane production</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé d' augmentation de formation de silane dialkyl-dihalo pendant le "procédé direct"</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0320260-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0320260</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0604092-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0604092</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1055675-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1055675</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1156051-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1156051</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="E" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4602101-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4602101</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5312948-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5312948</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5596119-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5596119</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5874604-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5874604</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5880307-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5880307</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6005130-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6005130</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000063217-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000063217</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2001081354-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2001081354</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="E" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEN ELECTRIC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1 River Road</street><city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BABLIN JOHN MATTHEW</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DEMOULPIED DAVID CHENEY</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GARDNER MARTHA MAPLES</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LEWIS LARRY NEIL</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WARD WILLIAM JESSUP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BABLIN, JOHN MATTHEW</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DEMOULPIED, DAVID CHENEY</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GARDNER, MARTHA MAPLES</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LEWIS, LARRY NEIL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WARD, WILLIAM JESSUP</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BABLIN, JOHN MATTHEW</last-name><address><street>36 Ellsworth Street</street><city>Amsterdam, New York 12010</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DEMOULPIED, DAVID CHENEY</last-name><address><street>35 Commons Boulevard</street><city>Clifton Park, New York 12065</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GARDNER, MARTHA MAPLES</last-name><address><street>2004 Regent Street</street><city>Niskayuna, New York 12309</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>LEWIS, LARRY NEIL</last-name><address><street>7 Harvest Drive</street><city>Scotia, New York 12302</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WARD, WILLIAM JESSUP</last-name><address><street>4028 Windsor Drive</street><city>Niskayuna, New York 12309</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Szary, Anne Catherine, Dr.</last-name><address><street>GE London Patent Operation, Essex House, 12-13 Essex Street</street><city>London WC2R 3AA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Dialkyldihalosilane formation during direct method alkylhalosilane production
is promoted by effecting reaction between alkyl halide and powdered silicon in the
presence of a catalyst comprising copper, zinc, and aluminum and further comprising
an amount of phosphorus and tin wherein the amount of phosphorus and tin
substantially enhances the selectivity of dialkyldihalosilane formation in comparison
to the selectivity of dialkyldihalosilane formation in the presence of the catalyst
comprising copper, zinc, aluminum and tin without phosphorus.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention is directed to a method for enhancing the formation and
recovery of dialkyldihalosilane from alkylhalosilane crude. More particularly, the
present invention relates to a direct method for methylchlorosilane manufacture by
maintaining an optimum amount of tin and phosphorus in the catalyst.</p><p num="0002">Prior to the present invention, methylchlorosilanes, hereinafter sometimes
designated "methylchlorosilane" for brevity, were made by effecting a reaction
between powdered silicon and methyl chloride in the presence of a copper-zinc-tin
catalyst, as shown by U.S. Patent Number 4,500,724, Ward et al., assigned to the
same assignee as the present invention. Silicon (Si) is typically combined with copper
(Cu) in a range between about 0.5% and about 10% by weight copper relative to
silicon, zinc (Zn) in a range between about 0.01 part and about 0.5 part per part
copper, and tin (Sn) in a range between about 200 parts per million and about 3,000
parts per million per part of copper.</p><p num="0003">By the prior art method, there is produced a mixture of alkylhalosilanes and in
particular, methylchlorosilanes. As utilized hereinafter, the term
"methylchlorosilanes" includes dimethyldichlorosilane (Di), which is the preferred
methylchlorosilane, and a variety of other silanes such as tetramethylsilane,
trimethylchlorosilane (Mono), methyltrichlorosilane (Tri), silicon tetrachloride,
trichlorosilane, methyldichlorosilane (MH), and dimethylchlorosilane (M<sub>2</sub>H).</p><p num="0004">In addition to the above methylchlorosilanes, residue is also formed during the
production of methylchlorosilane crude. "Crude" as used herein refers to the
unpurified product mixture of methylchlorosilanes. "Residue" as used herein refers to
products in the methylchlorosilane crude that have a boiling point greater than about
70°C at atmospheric pressure. Residue typically consists of such materials as
disilanes, for example, symmetrical 1,1,2,2-tetrachlorodimethyldisilane, 1,1,2-trichlorotrimethyldisilane, 
disiloxanes, disilmethylenes, and other higher boiling
species, for example, trisilanes, trisiloxanes, and trisilmethylenes.</p><p num="0005">Generally, it is desirable to effect high rates of production in the
methylchlorosilane reaction as well as selectively produce dimethyldichlorosilane
over the other products. New techniques are constantly being sought to improve the
selectivity of the methylchlorosilane reaction as well as increase the yield of the
methylchlorosilane products.</p> <heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0006">The present invention provides a method for promoting the formation of
dialkyldihalosilane during direct method alkylhalosilane production, the method
comprising effecting reaction between alkyl halide and powdered silicon in the
presence of a catalyst comprising copper, zinc, and aluminum and further comprising
an amount of phosphorus and tin wherein the amount of phosphorus and tin
substantially enhances the selectivity of dialkyldihalosilane formation in comparison
to the selectivity of dialkyldihalosilane formation in the presence of the catalyst
comprising copper, zinc, aluminum and tin without phosphorus.</p><heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0007"><sl><li>Figure 1 shows weight percent of dimethyldichlorosilane produced at varying
levels of tin with and without phosphorus.</li><li>Figure 2 shows weight percent of residue produced at varying levels of tin
with and without phosphorus.</li> </sl> </p> <heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0008">The present invention relates to a process involving the reaction of methyl
chloride and silicon in the presence of a direct method catalyst containing optimal
amounts of tin and phosphorus. "Direct method" as used herein refers to the process
of passing an alkyl halide through a bed of copper and silicon to yield
alkylhalosilanes. "Direct method catalyst" as used herein refers to a combination of
constituents which increase the rate of reaction and selectivity to dialkyldihalosilanes. 
Constituents of the direct method catalyst typically include tin, zinc, copper,
phosphorus, aluminum, and combinations thereof. While tin is recognized as a
constituent of direct method catalyst, its effectiveness for dialkyldihalosilane
formation during direct method operation can be substantially enhanced by
introducing phosphorus into the reactor while maintaining a high tin content.
"Substantially enhanced" dialkyldihalosilane formation as used herein refers to an
increase in the amount of dialkyldihalosilanes produced in comparison to the amount
of dialkyldihalosilanes produced with a catalyst containing copper, zinc, aluminum
and tin without phosphorus. Typically, the dialkyldihalosilane formation is
substantially enhanced when the percentage of dialkyldihalosilanes produced is
greater than about 80% based on total alkylhalosilanes produced. The presence of
phosphorus and tin has a synergistic effect on the process for making
dialkyldihalosilanes. Phosphorus is present in a range between greater than about 100
parts per million (ppm) and less than about 1000 ppm based on the weight of the total
reaction mixture and preferably, in a range between greater than about 100 ppm and
about 500 ppm based on the weight of the total reaction mixture. Tin is present in a
range between about 10 ppm and about 150 ppm based on the weight of the total
reaction mixture and preferably, in a range between about 15 ppm and about 30 ppm
based on the weight of the total reaction mixture. "Total reaction mixture" as used
herein refers to the weight of the combination of silicon and catalyst. If the tin level is
too low or too high, it has been unexpectedly found that the addition of phosphorus
does not have an effect on the amount of the dialkyldihalosilane produced. In
addition, the small scale laboratory reactors typically require an amount of tin in a
range between about 2 and about 3 times greater than the level used for large scale
commercial reactors to achieve the effect on the amount of dialkyldihalosilane
produced in a reactor used for production purposes.</p><p num="0009">Copper and zinc are present in the direct method catalyst. Copper is typically
present in a range between about 1% by weight and about 10% by weight copper
relative to silicon, and preferably in a range between about 3% by weight and about
5% by weight. Zinc is typically present in a range between about 400 ppm and about
2000 ppm per part copper, preferably in a range between about 400 ppm and about
700 ppm per part copper. Aluminum is also present in a range between about 500 
ppm and about 5000 ppm per part copper, and preferably in a range between about
1000 ppm and about 2500 ppm per part copper.</p><p num="0010">The tin used in the present invention can come from a variety of sources.
"Source" as used herein refers to the chemical compound which provides the
necessary element or elements for the direct reaction catalyst. Sources of tin include,
but are not limited to, tin metal dust, tin halides, tin oxide, tetramethyl tin, alkyl tin
halides, brass, bronze, and combinations thereof.</p><p num="0011">The sources of phosphorus that may be used include, but are not limited to,
copper phosphide (Cu<sub>3</sub>P), zinc phosphide (Zn<sub>3</sub>P<sub>2</sub>), phosphorus trichloride (PCl<sub>3</sub>),
alkylphosphines (R<sub>3</sub>P) such as triethylphosphine [(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>3</sub>P] and trimethylphosphine
[(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>P], and combinations thereof.</p><p num="0012">Among the copper compounds that can be used as copper sources in the
practice of the present invention are carboxylate salts of copper, partially oxidized
copper, and combinations thereof. Additional copper sources include, but are not
limited to, particulated cupric chloride and cuprous chloride, copper flake, brass,
bronze, and combinations thereof.</p><p num="0013">Examples of effective sources of zinc include, but are not limited to, zinc
metal powder; halides of zinc, such as zinc chloride; zinc oxide; and combinations
thereof.</p><p num="0014">The aluminum used in the direct reaction catalyst is supplied from various
sources. The source of aluminum, for instance, may comprise aluminum powder,
various alloys including, but not limited to, copper-aluminum alloy, silver-aluminum
alloy, silicon-aluminum alloy, magnesium-aluminum alloy, and combinations thereof.</p><p num="0015">Although methyl chloride is the alkyl halide of choice for the alkylhalosilane
reaction, other alkyl halides such as C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl chlorides, for example, ethyl chloride,
propyl chloride, etc., also can be used. Correspondingly, the term "alkylhalosilane"
includes dialkyldihalosilanes such as dimethyldichlorosilane (Di), which is the
preferred alkylhalosilane, and a variety of other alkylhalosilanes such as
trimethylchlorosilane (Mono), methyltrichlorosilane (Tri), silicon tetrachloride, 
trichlorosilane, methyldichlorosilane (MH), and dimethylchlorosilane (M<sub>2</sub>H), and also
tetramethylsilane.</p><p num="0016">Among the processes which can be used in the practice of the present
invention, there are included those in which at least one reactor comprises a fixed bed,
a stirred bed, or a fluid bed. The present invention can be practiced in a continuous,
semi-continuous, or batch manner. More specifically, a fixed bed reactor may be a
column that contains silicon particles through which alkyl halide gas passes. A stirred
bed may be similar to a fixed bed in which there is mechanical agitation of some sort
in order to keep the bed in constant motion. Reaction typically occurs at a
temperature in a range between about 250°C and about 350°C, and preferably in a
range between about 280°C and about 320°C. It is also advisable to carry out the
reaction under a pressure in a range between about 1 atmosphere and about 10
atmospheres in instances where a fluid bed reactor is used since higher pressure
increases the rate of conversion of methyl chloride to methylchlorosilanes. Desirably,
the pressure is in a range between about 1.1 atmospheres and about 3.5 atmospheres
and preferably in a range between about 1.3 atmospheres and about 2.5 atmospheres.</p><p num="0017">The expression "semi-continuous conditions" with respect to the description of
processes means that reactants are added and the reactor is run until about 50% of the
silicon has been utilized. After about 50% silicon utilization, additional silicon and
catalysts may be added. With a batch mode reaction, all of the reactant components
are combined and reacted until most of the reactants are consumed. In order to
proceed, the reaction has to be stopped and additional reactants added. A fixed bed
and stirred bed may both be run under batch conditions. A fluidized reactor is
typically run under continuous conditions. With continuous conditions, the reaction
does not have to be stopped in order to add more reactants.</p><p num="0018">In instances where a fluid bed reactor is used, methyl chloride, an inert gas
such as argon, or mixture thereof can be used to fluidize the bed of silicon particles.
The silicon particles can have a mean diameter below about 700 microns, with an
average size of greater than about 20 microns and less than about 300 microns being
preferred. Preferably, the mean diameter of the silicon particles is in a range between
about 100 microns and about 150 microns. Silicon used in the alkylhalosilane 
reaction can have an iron (Fe) content in a range between about 0.1% and about 1%
by weight based on total silicon, calcium (Ca) content in a range between about
0.01% and about 0.2% by weight based on total silicon, and an aluminum (Al) content
in a range between about 0.02% and about 0.5% by weight based on total silicon.
Silicon is usually obtained at a purity of at least about 98% by weight of silicon and it
is then comminuted to particles of powdered silicon for preparation of the contact
mass. "Contact mass" as used herein refers to a source of copper which is pre-reacted
with a silicon powder. The contact mass is typically prepared by reacting silicon and
a copper source such as cuprous chloride at a temperature in a range between about
280°C and about 400°C in a furnace in an inert atmosphere like nitrogen or argon
until evolution of silicon tetrachloride (SiCl<sub>4</sub>) ceases. The contact mass may be added
to the reactor with other catalyst components. "Pre-contact mass" as used herein
refers to a mixture of cuprous chloride, silicon, and tin which is not reacted.</p><p num="0019">Analysis of the alkylhalosilane product may be conducted to determine crude
composition. Silicon utilization is determined by weighing crude samples of the
alkylhalosilane product at various times. Typically data is recorded at about 20% by
weight silicon utilization. Selectivity may be determined by gas chromatography,
"GC", with thermal conductivity detectors. Individual silane component analysis is
performed by comparision to reagent grade silanes. GC calibrations are performed by
analysis of silane mixtures of known composition. Percent dimethyldichlorosilane
produced is of particular interest in the present invention.</p><p num="0020">In addition to percent dimethyldichlorosilane produced, another measure of
performance of the methylchlorosilane reaction is the rate of crude methylchlorosilane
formation. The reaction rate constant for methylchlorosilane formation is based on
the rate of methylchlorosilane production and is measured as grams of crude silane
per grams of silicon per hour. The amount of tin and phosphorus in the present
invention enhances the rate of methylchlorosilane formation as well as decreases the
amount of residue formed.</p><p num="0021">Those skilled in the art are also interested in the T/D weight ratio of the
methylchlorosilane crude. The T/D ratio is the ratio of the methyltrichlorosilane (T or
Tri) to dimethyldichlorosilane (D or Di) in the crude methylchlorosilane reaction 
product. Accordingly, an increase in the T/D ratio indicates that there is a decrease in
the production of the preferred dimethyldichlorosilane. When tin and phosphorus are
added to the direct method reaction and the tin content exceeds about 150 parts per
million, the T/D ratio generally increases.</p><p num="0022">In order that those skilled in the art will be better able to practice the present
invention, the following examples are given by way of illustration, and not by way of
limitation. All parts are by weight unless otherwise indicated.</p><heading>GENERAL PROCEDURE</heading><p num="0023">The fluid bed reactor was a 3.8 centimeter (cm) inside diameter (ID) glass tube
with a glass frit at the center to support the silicon bed. The reactor was heated by a
second concentric 5.1 cm ID glass tube coated with tin oxide to which two pairs of
electrodes were attached to create two heated sections.</p><p num="0024">In order to fluidize the silicon it was necessary both to stir the reacting silicon
and to vibrate the reactor. Pulverized silicon was used. The silicon was produced by
Elkem Chemicals and was taken from a standard lot made for plant feed. A large
quantity of this silicon was ground and the resulting ground powder was used as feed
to the lab reactors. The surface area was 0.38 meters<sup>2</sup>/gram. The elemental
composition of the silicon was as follows (ppm):
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Al</entry><entry align="center">Ca</entry><entry align="center">Fe</entry><entry align="center">P</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1800</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">5000</entry><entry align="center">40</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0025">Vibration was accomplished by attaching one end of a clamp to the reactor,
and the other end to the base of a variable intensity test tube shaker. By adjusting the
intensity of the vibration and the firmness with which the clamp gripped the reactor,
the necessary agitation of the silicon bed was achieved. Typically vibration was used
intermittently during a run.</p><p num="0026">A typical contact mass was prepared as follows: silicon (40 grams, 0.38
micron mean diameter) was combined with hexane (5.43 grams) and a 25% solids 
hexane slurry (12.67 grams) composed of copper chloride and 48 ppm tin dust for a
copper to tin ratio of 1000:1. The mixture was taken to dryness first by evaporation
under a stream of nitrogen and then by heating in a vacuum oven at 100°C. At this
point the mixture could be used as a pre-contact mass of copper chloride, silicon, and
tin. A true contact mass was used for this example. To make a true contact mass the
dried solid of copper chloride, silicon, and tin was place in a crucible and then into a
furnace under a flow of argon and then heated to 350°C until silicon tetrachloride
evolution ceased (ammonium hydroxide indicator used to monitor composition of
effluent). In this example, 3.12 g of copper chloride should produce 7.9 mmol of
silicon tetrachloride or a theoretical weight loss of 1.34g. The actual weight loss in
this case was 1.41g.</p><p num="0027">The reaction of approximately 20 grams of contact mass was performed at
300°C or 310°C as measured by a thermocouple immersed in the contact mass. The
reactor was fed methyl chloride in a range between about 93 standard cubic
centimeters per minute (sccm) and about 97 sccm. Product silanes were collected
across a condenser system maintained at -20°C.</p><p num="0028">The reactor and downstream glassware heating and cooling systems were
brought to their set temperatures and the reactor was first purged with argon (30
minutes at 95 sccm) and then methyl chloride (1 hour at 95 sccm). After purging, the
contact mass was charged into the reactor through a funnel. Following the addition of
the contact mass, the reactor stirring and vibration was begun. Condensate samples of
1 to 2 grams were collected on an hourly basis.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0029">The following methylchlorosilane reaction was carried out in a fluid bed
reactor in accordance with the General Procedure. The fluid bed reactor was charged
with silicon composed of pre-reacted contact mass 5% by weight copper chloride
based on the original weight of copper chloride (contact mass) and 1000 ppm zinc
dust [20 milligrams (mg) per 20 gram (g)], all amounts based on the weight of the
total composition charged to the reactor. The amount of tin (as tin dust) was varied in
a range between about 50 ppm and about 150 ppm. The reactor was then heated to 
310°C under a methyl chloride flow. Crude product, methylchlorosilane crude, was
collected manually and weighed to determine reaction rate and then analyzed by Gas
Chromatography. Rate, % dimethyldichlorosilane (as a percent of total crude
product), % methyldichlorosilane and T/D ratio were compared at the 20% silicon
utilization point.</p><p num="0030">In the following cases, 500 ppm phosphorus was added to the reactor in the
form of copper phosphide and in one case it was added as zinc phosphide (316 ppm
phosphorus). It was not surprising that an increase of tin from 50 ppm to 150 ppm
gave an increase in residue. However, it was unexpectedly found that when tin was
increased from 50 ppm to 150 ppm and phosphorus was added, an increased
selectivity for dimethyldichlorosilane occurred at the expense of methyltrichlorosilane
and residue. These results are shown in Figure 1 for dimethyldichlorosilane and
Figure 2 for residue.</p><p num="0031">The graph in Figure 1 shows the impact phosphorus has, at a 500 ppm level,
on promoting dimethydichlorosilane formation during direct method
methylchlorosilane production. As shown by the graph, tin levels in a range between
about 50 ppm and about 150 ppm were particularly effective for increasing the
efficiency of the process of making dimethyldichlorosilanes in the presence of
phosphorus.</p><p num="0032">The graph in Figure 2 shows the impact phosphorus has, at a 500 ppm level,
on decreasing the amount of residue formed during direct method methylchlorosilane
production. As shown by the graph, tin levels in a range between about 50 ppm and
about 150 ppm were particularly effective for decreasing the amount of residue
formed in the process of making dimethyldichlorosilanes in the presence of
phosphorus.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 2.</heading><p num="0033">The following two methylchlorosilane reactions were carried out in a fluid bed
reactor in accordance with Example 1 at a temperature of 310°C. The fluid bed
reactor was charged with silicon composed of 5% copper chloride (pre-contact mass)
and either 5000 ppm zinc dust (100 mg per 20 g) or 1500 ppm zinc dust (30 mg per 
20 g), all amounts based on the weight of the total composition charged to the reactor.
Both experiments were initially reacted in the absence of tin. During the course of the
experiments, amounts of tin (as tin dust) were added, varying in a range between
about 25 ppm and about 50 ppm. Consistent with both experiments was the result of
the methylchlorosilane reaction without tin, as shown in Table 1. It was not
surprising that methylchlorosilane reactivity increased with the addition of tin from 0
ppm to 25 ppm. However, it was unexpectedly found that when additional tin was
added to the reaction, methylchlorosilane reactivity ceased to increase.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1">Effect of Bed [Sn] on Cumulative Crude Selectivity</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Run #</entry><entry align="center">Bed [Sn] ppm</entry><entry align="center">% Di</entry><entry align="center">T/D</entry><entry align="center">Residue (%)</entry><entry align="center">Normal Rate (g/g-silicon-hr)</entry><entry align="center">[Zn]</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">69.1</entry><entry align="center">.132</entry><entry align="center">6.70</entry><entry align="center">.02</entry><entry align="center">5000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">86.7</entry><entry align="center">.072</entry><entry align="center">2.86</entry><entry align="center">.08</entry><entry align="center">5000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">85.4</entry><entry align="center">.082</entry><entry align="center">2.74</entry><entry align="center">.23</entry><entry align="center">5000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">80.5</entry><entry align="center">.103</entry><entry align="center">7.33</entry><entry align="center">.23</entry><entry align="center">5000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">63.6</entry><entry align="center">.158</entry><entry align="center">7.30</entry><entry align="center">.03</entry><entry align="center">1500</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">86.5</entry><entry align="center">.077</entry><entry align="center">2.73</entry><entry align="center">.11</entry><entry align="center">1500</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">75</entry><entry align="center">85.4</entry><entry align="center">.086</entry><entry align="center">2.66</entry><entry align="center">.04</entry><entry align="center">1500</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>EXAMPLE 3.</heading><p num="0034">The following two methylchlorosilane reactions were carried out in a fluid bed
reactor in accordance with Example 1 at a temperature of 310°C. The fluid bed
reactor was charged with silicon composed of 5% copper chloride (pre-contact mass),
5000 ppm zinc dust, and 50 ppm tin dust. Both experiments were reacted to a similar
silicon utilization point prior to the addition of 5 mg of tin as tin dust (Sn) or tin
tetrachloride (SnCl<sub>4</sub>). Consistent with both experiments was the result of the
methylchlorosilane reaction after the tin addition. It was unexpectedly found that
when the additional tin was added to the reaction, 250 ppm by weight of the
combination of silicon and catalyst, the comparative methylchlorosilane reactivity
declined and the amount of residue increased.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1">Effect of Bed [Sn] on Cumulative Crude Selectivity and Rate</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Run #</entry><entry align="center">[Sn] ppm</entry><entry align="center">Amount of Silicon</entry><entry align="center">Di</entry><entry align="center">T/D</entry><entry align="center">Residue %</entry><entry align="center">Normal Rate (g/g-silicon-hr) </entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Utilized (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">28</entry><entry align="center">82.7</entry><entry align="center">.115</entry><entry align="center">4.1</entry><entry align="center">.39</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">300</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">72.3</entry><entry align="center">.183</entry><entry align="center">10.4</entry><entry align="center">.06</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">19</entry><entry align="center">80.0</entry><entry align="center">.131</entry><entry align="center">4.7</entry><entry align="center">.30</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">300</entry><entry align="center">21</entry><entry align="center">71.5</entry><entry align="center">.193</entry><entry align="center">10.5</entry><entry align="center">.09</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>EXAMPLE 4.</heading><p num="0035">The following methylchlorosilane reaction was carried out in a fluid bed
reactor in accordance with Example 1 at a temperature of 310°C. The fluid bed
reactor was charged with silicon composed of 5% weight based on the original weight
of copper chloride (contact mass), and 75 ppm tin dust. The equivalent of 3350 ppm
zinc was added as ZnCl<sub>2</sub> (Zinc chloride - 99.99% Aldrich) to the reaction followed by
an addition of 3100 ppm phosphorus as trimethylphosphine (1.0 molar P(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> in
toluene Aldrich). A significant improvement in selectivity followed the phosphorus
addition; however the reacting bed mass exhibited visual agglomeration. This
agglomeration or " bed stickiness" would preclude the use of high levels of
phosphorus as demonstrated here.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 5.</heading><p num="0036">The following methylchlorosilane reaction was carried out in a fixed bed
reactor. A fixed bed reactor was set up consisting of a 20 cm long by 1.3 cm diameter
outside diameter (OD) glass tube with a glass frit located 6 cm from the end to
support the bed. Since the silicon was not stirred and the methylchlorosilane reaction
is highly exothermic, the diameter of the bed was limited by heat transfer
considerations. The thermal conductivity of the silicon was assumed to be the same
as sand, namely 0.2 BTU/ft-hr-°F. The highest anticipated reaction rate was 1 gram
of crude silane/gram of silicon-hour. For this rate, a temperature rise of about 10°C
along the center line of the reactor was calculated. Over this temperature range, no
changes in crude composition were observed. The other reactor design consideration
was pressure drop. To be practical and safe, a pressure drop of no more than
approximately 5 pounds per square inch (psi) was considered acceptable, and this
limited the bed size to 6 grams. </p><p num="0037">The reactor was centered vertically in a 5 cm glass tube wrapped with
Nichrome® ribbon or coated with tin oxide. Two pairs of electrodes were fitted to the
tin oxide or Nichrome to create two heated sections. One section was for the inlet to
the system, and was used to preheat the methyl chloride feed. The other section was
for the reactor itself. The 5 cm heated glass tube was centered in a 6.4 cm glass tube
used for insulation of the reactor and for safety.</p><p num="0038">The reactor was charged with 6 g of solid (pre-contact mass) composed of
silicon with CuCl (2.5% by weight), elemental zinc (2.8 mg) and elemental tin (0.15
mg). The reaction was run under a flow of methyl chloride, 35 sccm at 315°C. At
20% silicon utilization, the crude product contained 89.7% dimethyldichlorosilane.
The experiment was repeated except that 100 ppm phosphorus in the form of
triethylphosphine was added. At 20% silicon utilization, the crude product was
composed of 88.5% dimethyldichlorosilane indicating that this low level of
phosphorus did not lead to improved selectivity. This example defines the lower
effective limit of phosphorus as being greater than about 100 ppm phosphorus.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 6.</heading><p num="0039">The methylchlorosilane reaction was carried out as described in Example 5
with a 500 ppm phosphorus level. At 20% silicon utilization, the crude product was
composed of 93.9% dimethyldichlorosilane indicating a strong promoting effect at
this level of phosphorus.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 7</heading><p num="0040">The methylchlorosilane reaction was carried out as described in Example 5
except that 1000 ppm phosphorus was used. At 20% silicon utilization, the crude was
composed of 91% dimethyldichlorosilane indicating that phosphorus was still a strong
promoter at this level. However, the reactor bed was sticky with 1000 ppm
phosphorus. Due to the problems with stickiness under these conditions, an effective
maximum useful amount of phosphorus is less than about 1000 ppm.</p><p num="0041">While typical embodiments have been set forth for the purpose of illustration,
the foregoing descriptions should not be deemed to be a limitation on the scope of the 
present invention. Accordingly, various modifications, adaptations, and alternatives
may occur to one skilled in the art without departing from the spirit and scope of the
present invention.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for promoting the formation of dialkyldihalosilane during direct
method alkylhalosilane production, the method comprising effecting reaction between
alkyl halide and powdered silicon in the presence of a catalyst comprising copper,
zinc, and aluminum and further comprising an amount of phosphorus and tin wherein
the amount of phosphorus and tin substantially enhances the selectivity of
dialkyldihalosilane formation in comparison to the selectivity of dialkyldihalosilane
formation in the presence of the catalyst comprising copper, zinc, aluminum and tin
without phosphorus.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method in accordance with claim 1, where the phosphorus is present in
a range between greater than about 100 parts per million and less than about 1000
parts per million based on the weight of the combination of silicon and catalyst and
tin is present in a range between about 10 parts per million and about 150 parts per
million based on the weight of the combination of silicon and catalyst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method in accordance with claim 1 or claim 2, where the phosphorus is
in a range between greater than about 100 parts per million and about 500 parts per
million based on the weight of the combination of silicon and catalyst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method in accordance with any preceding claim, where the tin is in a
range between about 15 parts per million and about 30 parts per million based on the
weight of the combination of silicon and catalyst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method in accordance with any preceding claim, where the reaction is
conducted in a fixed bed reactor, a stirred bed reactor or a fluid bed reactor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method in accordance with any preceding claim, where the reaction is
conducted in a continuous manner.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method in accordance with any preceding claim, where the zinc is
present in a range between about 400 parts per million and about 2000 part per
million per part copper.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method in accordance with claim 7, where the zinc is present in a
range between about 400 parts per million and about 700 parts per million copper.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method in accordance with any preceding claim, where the aluminum
is present in a range between about 500 parts per million and about 4000 parts per
million per part copper.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method in accordance with claim 9, where the aluminum is present in
a range between about 1000 parts per million and about 2500 parts per million copper.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The method in accordance with any preceding claim, where the copper is
present in a range between about 1% and about 10% by weight copper relative to
silicon.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The method in accordance with claim 11, where the copper is present in a
range between about 3% and about 5% by weight copper relative to silicon.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The method in accordance with any preceding claim, where the
phosphorus is introduced into the reactor as copper phosphide, an alkylphosphine,
phosphorus trichloride, or combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The method in accordance with claim 13, where the phosphorus is
introduced into the reactor as triethylphosphine or trimethylphosphine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The method in accordance with any preceding claim, where the alkyl
halide comprises methyl chloride.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The dialkyldihalosilane made by the method of any preceding claim.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A method for promoting the formation of dimethyldichlorosilane in a
continuous manner during direct method methylchlorosilane production, the method
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>effecting reaction in a fluid bed reactor between methyl chloride and
powdered silicon in the presence of a catalyst comprising copper, silicon, zinc, tin,
and phosphorus having an average proportion of copper in a range between about 3%
and about 5% based on the weight of silicon;</claim-text><claim-text>tin in a range between about 15 parts per million and about 30 parts per
million based on the weight of the combination of silicon and catalyst; and</claim-text><claim-text>phosphorus in a range between greater than about 100 parts per million and
about 500 parts per million, based on the weight of the combination of silicon and
catalyst.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The method in accordance with claim 17, where the phosphorus is
introduced as copper phosphide, phosphorus trichloride or triethylphosphine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The dimethyldichlorosilane made by the method of claim 17 or claim 18.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>