<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1374921-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1374921" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="29717981" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040102"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1374921-A1" status="new" fvid="23940753"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1374921</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040102</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03254122-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03254122</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030627</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-18505302-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>18505302</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020628</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L  17/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L  17/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L  27/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L  27/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L  31/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61L  31/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  63/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  63/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  63/64        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  63/664       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  63/78        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61L  17/12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61L  31/06+C08L67/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  63/08</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  63/64</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  63/664</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  63/78</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Kristallisierbare Polylacton-co-polymere herstellbar ausgehend von mono- und difunctionalisierten Polymerisationsinitiatoren</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Crystallizable polylactone copolymers prepared from mono- and di-functional polymerization initiators</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Copolymères de polylactone crystallisables preparés à partir d'initiateurs de polymérisation mono- et difunctionalisés</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0908142-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0908142</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0908482-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0908482</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5951997-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5951997</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2001040348-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2001040348</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ETHICON INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ETHICON, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ETHICON, INC.</last-name><address><street>U.S. Route 22</street><city>Somerville, NJ 08876</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ANDJELIC SASA</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BEZWADA RAO S</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>JAMIOLKOWSKI DENNIS D</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KELLY BRIAN M</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>NEWMAN HUGH D JR</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ANDJELIC, SASA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BEZWADA, RAO S.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>JAMIOLKOWSKI, DENNIS D.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KELLY, BRIAN M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NEWMAN, HUGH D. JR</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ANDJELIC, SASA</last-name><address><street>595 Main Street, Apt.901</street><city>New York, NY10044</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BEZWADA, RAO S.</last-name><address><street>1 Nevius Road</street><city>Whitehouse Station, NJ 08889</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>JAMIOLKOWSKI, DENNIS D.</last-name><address><street>20 Fawnridge Drive</street><city>Long Valley, NJ 07853</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KELLY, BRIAN M.</last-name><address><street>28 Kensington Road</street><city>Bedminster, NJ 07921</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NEWMAN, HUGH D. JR</last-name><address><street>4 Larch Drive</street><city>Chester, NJ 07930</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Mercer, Christopher Paul</last-name><address><street>CARPMAELS &amp;amp; RANSFORD 43, Bloomsbury Square</street><city>London WC1A 2RA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention is directed to absorbable polylactone copolymers prepared
in part from about 2 to about 80 mole percent glycolide, utilizing a combination of a
monofunctional polymerization initiator and a di-functional polymerization initiator, to achieve
rates of crystallization of the copolymer of at least about 2 times faster than the rate of
crystallization of a copolymer made by a similar process utilizing either the mono-functional or
the di-functional polymerization initiator alone. Medical devices containing such copolymers are
also disclosed.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b><u style="single">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</u></b></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to methods of making absorbable polylactone
copolymers suitable for use in implantable medical devices, which methods include the use of
both mono- and di-functional polymerization initiators, otherwise known as molecular weight
control agents, to polymers prepared by such methods and to medical devices prepared from
such polymers.</p><heading><b><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></b></heading><p num="0002">Homopolymers and copolymers of p-dioxanone (PDO) are known for use in the
medical device and pharmaceutical fields due to their low toxicity, softness and flexibility.
Poly(p-dioxanone) (PDS) homopolymer in particular has been suggested as an absorbable
polymer for use in synthetic surgical devices. By the early 1980's the PDS homopolymer was
used by surgeons in the form of a monofilament surgical suture. Since that time, many p-dioxanone
copolymers have been described for use in such devices. Surgical monofilament
sutures based on a copolymer prepared from trimethylene carbonate (TMC), glycolide (GLY)
and p-dioxanone (PDO) monomer currently are available for use. PDO based polymeric
materials also can be injection molded into a number of non-filamentous surgical devices such as
surgical clips and fasteners for use in, e.g. meniscal repair. These surgical articles take full
advantage of the general toughness exhibited by this family of homopolymers and copolymers
known heretofore.</p><p num="0003">Segmental block copolymers composed of p-dioxanone and glycolide (at a molar
ratio of PDO:GLY of approximately 90:10) were thought to be polymers potentially suitable for
use as a "soft" monofilament suture having a break strength retention (BSR) profile similar to 
Vicryl® sutures, available from Ethicon, Inc. However, these copolymers were found to
crystallize relatively slowly upon cooling from the melt, making the fiber manufacturing
processes more difficult and challenging, and thus hampering the conversion of such polymers to
"soft" monofilament sutures. It would be advantageous, then, to determine polymerization
process parameters necessary to produce such polymers having properties suitable for conversion
to "soft" monofilament sutures, as well as other implantable medical devices. The present
invention provides such processes, polymers made by such processes and having unique
properties, and medical devices made from such polymers.</p><heading><b><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></b></heading><p num="0004">The present invention is directed to a polymerization process for making
absorbable polylactone copolymers, wherein from about 2 to about 80 mole percent of a first
lactone monomer comprising glycolide and about 98 to about 20 mole percent of a second
lactone monomer other than glycolide are contacted with a monofunctional polymerization
initiator and a di-functional polymerization initiator, at a molar ratio of monofunctional to di-functional
initiator ranging from 10:90 to 90:10, and the glycolide and second lactone monomers
are in the presence of the monofunctional and di-functional polymerization initiators under
conditions effective to copolymerize the monomers, thereby providing the absorbable
polylactone copolymer. When medical devices are manufactured from certain polymers
prepared by such processes, the rate of crystallization during formation of the device is at least
about 2 times faster, and preferably greater than about 10 times faster, than the rate of
crystallization when a polylactone polymer made by a substantially similar or the same
polymerization process, but utilizing either the monofunctional or the di-functional
polymerization initiator alone, is used to form the device. Thus, the present invention provides
increased crystallization rates as compared to conventional processing, as taken under the same
or similar measurement conditions or techniques. The invention also is directed to absorbable
polylactone copolymers prepared by processes of the present invention and to medical devices
comprising such copolymers. </p><heading><b><u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE FIGURES</u></b></heading><p num="0005">Figure 1 is a series of plots at various crystallization temperatures of spherulite
diameter versus time for the isothermal crystallization of copolymer ID.</p><p num="0006">Figure 2 is a plot of experimentally-obtained spherulitic growth rates, dD/dt
(micron/min), obtained at various isothermal crystallization temperatures for copolymers 1A-1E
and PDS homopolymer and the expected relationship based on the Hoffinan-Lauritzen theory
(See Hoffinan, J.D, Davis, G.T, Lauritzen, J.I. 1976, Treatise on Solid State Chemistry, Hannay
NB, editor, Plenum Press: New York, Chapter 7.).</p><p num="0007">Figure 3 is a semi-logarithmic plot of nucleation rates (dN/dt) versus
crystallization temperature for copolymers 1A-1E.</p><p num="0008">Figure 4 shows Hot Stage Optical Microscopy images of copolymers 1A-1D,
captured after 60 minutes of isothermal crystallization at 40°C.</p><p num="0009">Figure 5 is a non-isothermal DSC trace, including a slope value, obtained during
crystallization from the melt at a constant cooling rate of 0.5°C/minute of copolymer 1C.</p><heading><b><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></b></heading><p num="0010">Properties of monofilament fibers produced from polylactone copolymers
comprising glycolide copolymerized with a second lactone monomer other than glycolide,
including fiber strengths, stiffness and break strength retention, were found to vary depending on
whether the polymerization reaction used to prepare the copolymers was initiated with
monofunctional initiators or di-functional initiators. It now has been discovered unexpectedly
that the use of a combination monofunctional and di-functional polymerization initiators in
polymerization processes, e.g. ring-opening polymerization, may provide certain polylactone
copolymers that, in turn, provide improved crystallization characteristics during manufacture of
certain medical devices manufactured at least in part from such polylactone copolymers. </p><p num="0011">In order to produce a high molecular weight polymer by a ring-opening
polymerization (ROP) in a timely, reproducible and economical fashion, a catalyst usually is
combined with a mono- or multi-functional initiator. These initiators are desirably hydroxyl-containing
compounds, usually primary alcohols, that can be used to generate linear or branched
polymers. If the initiator contains one or two hydroxyl groups, a linear material will result. It is
expected that both mono- and di-functional initiators normally will produce linear materials
because one chain, without branch points, is produced from each molecule of initiator. If the
initiator contains three or more hydroxyls, branched materials are generally formed. Various
catalysts for the ring ring-opening polymerization of lactones have been used. They are generally
metal based and include the organic titanates and zirconates (as sold by DuPont under the
tradename TYZOR) Organotin compounds have found great utility as catalysts for the ring-opening
polymerization of lactones for medical applications. Tin catalysts include Sn (IV)
compounds such as dibutyltin oxide and Sn (II) compounds such as stannous chloride.
Particularly advantageous for use as a catalyst is stannous octoate.</p><p num="0012">The polymerization is conveniently done in a bulk process, i.e. solventless,
although it also may be conducted in solution. The polymerization is usually conducted in the
melt, that is, above the melting points of the various monomers making up the feed, as well as
above the melting point of the forming polymer. In some special cases, the ring-opening
polymerization of certain lactones can be conducted in the solid state, that is, below the melting
point of the forming polymer. An example of the later is the homopolymerization of p-dioxanone.
Although the total-monomer-to-total-initiator molar ratio can range from about 100:1
to about 10,000:1, the preferred range of the total-monomer-to-total-initiator molar ratio for
polymer to be used in extrusion and injection molding processes ranges from about 400:1 to
about 2,000:1. This is because the amount of initiator greatly influences the molecular weight of
the formed resin. In the absence of side reactions, each initiator molecule ideally generates one
polymer chain. The more relative initiator available, the greater the number of chains formed
and consequently the lower the molecular weight of the resin formed. In the preferred range of
total-monomer-to-total-initiator molar ratio of about 400:1 to about 2,000:1, the molecular
weight of the resulting polymer is more suitable for extrusion and injection molding applications. </p><p num="0013">Cyclic esters, i.e. lactones, that function as suitable monomers can be selected
from the group comprising small rings, especially the 5-, 6-, and 7-member rings. Of particular
utility are the lactones containing a heteroatom, especially oxygen, adjacent to the α-carbon.
Preferred 6-member cyclic esters include glycolide, L(-)-lactide, D(+)-lactide, meso-lactide, and
p-dioxanone. A preferred 7-member lactone is ε-caprolactone (epsilon-caprolactone). The
characteristics of suitable monomer for the present invention include those that provide
reasonable reaction rates under suitable reaction conditions. The polymers that are formed are
advantageously biocompatible, making them suitable for the fabrication of medical devices.</p><p num="0014">One of the characteristic methods for preparation of branched and highly
functional aliphatic polyesters might involve hydroxyl functionalities as the pendant groups in a
polymer chain. See for instance the work of M. Trollsas, J. L. Hedrick, D. Mecerreyes, Ph.
Dubois, R. Jerome, H. Ihre, and A. Hult, in Macromolecules 1998, 31, 2756. These molecules
containing a plurality of pendant hydroxyl groups might serve as macroinitiators for the initiation
of ring-containing monomers in a subsequent copolymerization step to prepare dendri-graft
(comb) molecular structures. Similarly, hydroxyl groups of multifunctional initiators might be
fully substituted to produce star-shaped polymers with two, four, five and six arms. See for
instance the work of A. Schindler, Y.M. Hibionada, and C. G. Pitt in the Journal of Polymer
Science: Polymer Chemistry Edition 1982, 20, 319 as well as the work of C. A. P Joziasse, H.
Grablowitz, and A.J. Pennings in Macromol. Chem. Phys. 2000, 201, 107.</p><p num="0015">Due to their unique molecular architecture, branched compounds exhibit different
physiochemical properties compared to their linear counterparts. It is generally recognized that
long-branches can decrease viscosity, thus improving processability in some instances, and
increase elasticity, while short chain branches predominately affect crystallinity. For instance, F.
Tasaka, Y. Ohya, and T. Ouchi (Macromolecules 2001, 34, 5494) graft polymerized 1-lactid
(LA) in bulk using Sn(Oct)<sub>2</sub> in the presence of poly[(Glc-Ser)-LA] having pendant hydroxyl
groups as a macroinitiator. Such obtained comb-like polymers showed a substantial reduction in
crystallinity compared to the linear poly (L-lactide), PLLA (15-22% vs. 55%). An abrupt
decrease in both the glass transition temperature (40-43°C vs. 65°C) and the melting point (135-140°C
vs. 167°C) was also detected. Owing to the lower crystallinity, biological properties are 
affected as well. In vitro degradation rate of comb-type PLLA was found to be significantly
faster than that of linear PLLA.</p><p num="0016">The rheology of a polymer melt even within one structure or chemistry, as related
to processing and fabrication, is affected by many factors such as the molecular weight and
molecular weight distribution, the polymer architecture and blending. In particular, long chain
branching has a significant contribution. Although limiting the synthesis to linear materials helps
to simplify the processing and fabrication issues that would arise because of the contributions
that branching would bring to the melt rheology, crystallization concerns speak away from
branched materials. Although we do not wish to be limited by scientific theory, branched
polymers frequently are more difficult to crystallize when compared to unbranched (linear)
materials of the material.</p><p num="0017">Returning to linear materials, mono- or di-functional initiators, as already alluded
to, have found extensive use in producing polymers useful for producing absorbable surgical
devices. Diols have been used in ring opening "pre-polymerizations" to produce α,ω-dihydroxymacroinitiators
(alpha, omega-dihydroxymacroinitiators) that are then used in a subsequent
copolymerization to produce polymers with special sequence distributions. This sequential
addition ROP, in which a monomer feed portion is added in a subsequent step, is one method to
make so-called segmented block copolyesters. An example is a glycolide/epsilon-caprolactone
copolymer that has enjoyed considerable commercial success. See R. S. Bezwada, D. D.
Jamiolkowski, et. al., "MONOCRYL™ Suture, a New Ultra-Pliable Absorbable Monofilament
Suture" Biomaterials, 16 (15), 1141-1148 (1995).</p><p num="0018">Within the scope of the present invention is the use of mono- or di-functional
initiators in sequential addition ring opening polymerizations in which the monomer feed is
added in sequence. That is, portions of the total monomer are allowed to enter the reactor in
sequence or in mutiple steps, as opposed to having all the monomer added at once. It is also
within the scope of the present invention polymerization processes in which the monomer is
indeed added to the reactor in substantially in a single step at the start of the polymerization. In
all cases, it should be understood that the monomers employed can be added to the reactor as 
solids, in the case where the monomers are indeed a solid at room temperature, or as molten
liquids. If the reaction is to be conducted in the presence of a solvent, the monomers may be
added in solution. It is also within the scope of the present invention polymerization processes in
which the initiators are added in sequence or are added independently added as a function of
time.</p><p num="0019">In the absence of transesterification, the molecular weight distributions may be
slightly different. For instance, Mw/Mn values of 2 and 1.5 are expected for polymers made with
mono- and di-functional initiators, respectively. In the presence of substantial transesterification,
a value of two is approached for both types. Likewise, the monomer sequence distribution in
copolymerizations may differ slightly as well. In studying the effect of the functionality of the
initiator in the sequential addition ROP of lactones, the use of mono- and di-functional alcohols
was explored. One would expect the properties of polymers made using a mixture of mono-functional
and di-functional initiators to lie between the extremes exhibited by materials based
on only mono- or only di-functional initiators. Contrary to such expectation, it was discovered
that employing a mixture of mono- and di-functional initiators can produce structures that are
unexpectedly different and that have very advantageous properties. They include much more
rapid crystallization characteristics, with a resultant impact in processability, and mechanical and
biological performance enhancements.</p> <p num="0020">Initiators of lactone ring-opening polymerizations can, under the right conditions,
be aliphatic alcohols, phenols, thiols or mercaptans, thiophenols, or amines. Alcohols, of course,
possess hydroxyl groups, while thiols possess sulfhydryl groups. The alcohols and amines may
be primary, secondary or tertiary and they may be linear or branched. Of particular utility are
aliphatic alcohols, especially primary aliphatic alcohols. Of even greater utility are primary
aliphatic alcohols of low volatility. Once placed in the reactor, such initiators are not easily lost
during vacuum purging cycles, thus allowing much better process control of the resulting
polymer's molecular weight. For purposes of the present invention, in determining whether an
initiator is classified as a mono- or di-functional initiator, only those functional groups capable of
initiating lactone ring-opening polymerization will be considered as an "initiator" functional
group. Thus, initiators may have more than one functional group and still be considered to be a 
mono-functional initiator for purposes of the present invention. For instance, an initiator may
simultaneously contain a hydroxyl group and a halide. As the hydroxyl is capable of initiating
ring-opening polymerization and a halide is not, such an initiator would be considered mono-functional.
Thus for purposes of the present invention, 10-methoxyoctanol
(CH<sub>3</sub>OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OH) is considered mono-functional, even though it
possesses both a hydroxyl group and an ether group.</p><p num="0021">Preferred monofunctional initiators are C<sub>4</sub> or higher primary aliphatic alcohols,
especially C<sub>10</sub> or higher linear primary aliphatic alcohols such as 1-dodecanol. Primary aliphatic
monofunctional alcohols include: 1-hexanol, 1-heptanol, 1-octanol, 1-nonanol, 1-decanol, 1-hendecanol,
1-dodecanol (lauryl alcohol), 1-tridecanol, 1-tetradecanol (myristyl alcohol), 1-pentadecanol,
1-hexadecanol (cetyl alcohol), 1-heptadecanol, 1-octadecanol (stearyl alcohol),
and branched primary aliphatic monofunctional alcohols such as 10-methyl-1-hendecanol
(isolauryl alcohol), 9-methyl-1-hendecanol (anteisolauryl alcohol), 12-methyl-1-tridecanol
(isomyristyl alcohol), 11-methyl-1-tridecanol (anteisomyristyl alcohol), 14-methyl-1-pentadecanol
(isopalmityl alcohol), 13-methyl-1-pentadecanol (anteisopalmityl alcohol), 16-methyl-1-heptadecanol
(isostearyl alcohol), and 15-methyl-1-pentadecanol (anteisostearyl
alcohol). Primary aliphatic monofunctional alcohols can be mutibranched in nature such as
2,6,10,14-tetramethyl-1-pentadecaonol (C<sub>19</sub>H<sub>40</sub>O, pristanol).</p><p num="0022">Some fatty alcohols have one double bond (monounsaturated). Their general
formula is:CH<sub>3</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>x</sub>CH=CH(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>y</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>OH. The unique double bond may be found in
different positions: at the C-6: i.e. cis-6-octadecen-1-ol (petroselenyl alcohol), the C-9 i.e, cis-9-octadecen-1-ol
(oleyl alcohol) or the C-11 i.e., cis-11-octadecen-1-ol (vaccenyl alcohol).</p><p num="0023">Some alcohols have isoprenoid structures, such as Geraniol, Farnesol,
Geranylgeraniol, Solanesol, or Castaprenols-Ficaprenols. These isoprenoid alcohols are also
known as terpenols or polyprenols. They are important molecules in the synthesis of various
terpenes, the acylation of proteins and the synthesis of vitamins (Vitamins E and K). Geraniol
(from rose oil), is a monoterpene (2 isoprene units), farnesol (present in small amounts in
essential oils) is a sesquiterpene (3 isoprene units), geranylgeraniol is a diterpene. Mono- and 
sesquiterpenes can be obtained by steam distillation of the tissues of many plants. One type of
polyisoprenoid alcohols with one saturated isoprenoid unit (dolichol) is well known for its
important role as glycosyl carrier in the synthesis of polysaccharides in bacteria and animals
(similar compounds have the same function in plants).</p><p num="0024">Di-functional initiators contain two groups or moieties capable of initiating a
lactone ring-opening polymerization. Preferred di-functional initiators are C<sub>4</sub> or higher
compounds possessing two primary aliphatic alcohol groups, such as 1,4-butanediol, 1,5-pentanediol,
1,6-hexanediol, 1,7-heptanediol, 1,8-octanediol, 1,9-nonanediol, 1,10-decanediol,
1,12-dodecanol, 1,16-hexadecanediol, and especially diethylene glycol. The later is an example
of a diol containing an extra heteroatom.</p> <p num="0025">It may be necessary to determine the composition of the formed polymers. The
use of NMR (nuclear magnetic resonance) in elucidating structure is well known. Because the
amounts of initiator are relatively small, it may be difficult to identify what initiators were
employed in the polymerization. One convenient way to do so, however, is to completely
hydrolyze the polyester concurrently converting the initiator moiety back to the corresponding
original free initiator. For example, a p-dioxanone glycolide copolymer initiated with dodecanol
and diethylene glycol would have the alcohols converted to esters in the course of the
polymerization. Hydrolysis of the polyester would result in the generation of 2-hydroxyethoxyglycolic
acid (ring opened form of p-dioxanone), glycolic acid, dodecanol and
diethylene glycol. The composition could then be determined by analyzing the hydrolyzate by a
suitable means. These include LC (liquid chomatographic) methods.</p> <p num="0026">The polymers of the present invention either crystallize at a faster rate, or
crystallize to a higher extent, or both, than their counterparts made with either a monofunctional
initiator alone or a di-functional initiator alone. Crystallizing at a higher rate has advantages
when melt processing the polymers of the present invention. This is especially true when
fabricating, e.g. medical devices, using an injection molding process. Rapid crystallization is
particularly advantageous when injecting molding articles from resins with low glass transition
temperatures, because dimensional stability is usually achieved by crystallization. In the absence 
of crystallization, injection molded parts made from polymers possessing low glass transition
temperatures also frequently display distortion and deformation upon removal from the mold
because they are not able to withstand the forces exerted, however mild, during the removal
process. As articles crystallize faster, cycle times may be decreased. Not only is there potential
for an economic impact, i.e., decreased costs, faster cycle times reduce the time the polymer
resides in the machine at elevated temperatures. This reduces the amount of degradation that
may occur, further improving part quality. The amount of crystallinity needed in the part prior to
ejection from the mold depends on glass transition temperature of the resin as well as the
molecular weight of the resin. The lower the glass transition temperature, the higher the level of
crystallinity required. It is advantageous to have a crystallinity level of at least 10 % with some
synthetic absorbable polymers possessing low glass transition temperatures. In the case of
fibers, with higher molecular orientation, the level of crystallinity required is higher. In such
cases, at least about 15% and desirably greater than about 25% may be necessary to provide
dimensional stability.</p> <p num="0027">Achieving higher levels of crystallinity may also be advantageous, in that articles
manufactured from the polymers, e.g. medical devices, may exhibit better dimensional stability,
higher strength and stiffness. Increasing nucleation rates provide many more sites for the
initiation of crystal formation. This in turn increases the number of crystals. With more crystals
forming in a given volume, it is easy to see that each crystal must necessarily be smaller in size,
once crystallization is finished. Smaller crystal size can result in a much tougher material. It
has often been observed that the polymer morphologies of the polymers of the present invention
that are developed during crystallization from the melt are much finer-grained than polymers
made with either a monofunctional initiator alone, or a di-functional initiator alone. The smaller
crystal size has positive impact on certain physical characteristics. For instance, in the case of
injection molded suture clips, a tough absorbable resin with a glass transition below room
temperature would allow a one-piece, hinged, clip design. The high stress on the hinge that is
developed during closure when the clip is in place and activated, however, can limit the use of
the clip. Having a finer grain (smaller crystal size) allows the clip to withstand higher loads for
longer time. Such clips are exemplified in United States Patents 5,409,499 and 5,234,449, the
contents each of which are hereby incorporated by reference in their entirety. </p><p num="0028">In the case of undyed 92/8 (mole %) PDO/GLY segmented block copolymers,
crystal sizes commonly run in the 50 to 100 micron range. It is often advantageous to have finer
grained molded articles to provide, for instance, superior toughness. When employing the
polymerization processes of the subject invention, an average crystal size (diameter) of less than
10 microns was experimentally observed. Desirably, average crystal size of the inventive
copolymer is about 25 microns or less. Crystal sizes of the copolymer were measured in
accordance with teachings described herein. In cases where the inventive copolymers have been
subjected to various fabrication techniques, for example molding into a device or finished
product, it may be necessary to first isolate the polymer in order to analyze the crystal size.</p><p num="0029">In order to explore the effect of using combinations of monofunctional and di-functional
initiators on crystallization properties of undyed polylactone copolymers and medical
devices made therefrom, supramolecular crystalline morphology and crystallization kinetics of
polylactone copolymers prepared according to processes of the present invention were evaluated
utilizing Hot Stage Optical Microscopy (HSOM) and Differential Scanning Calorimetry (DSC),
using both isothermal and non-isothermal conditions. The development of spherulites, both in
terms of nucleation and growth, can be accurately described by optical measurements, whereas
calorimetric data more precisely reflect the overall rate of crystallization. One of the big
advantages of HSOM is that nucleation and spherulitic growth rates in, for example,
PDO/glycolide segmented block copolymers, can be determined separately; de-convoluting the
crystallization process into the two parts. With these two complementary techniques, the entire
scope of the crystallization process can be examined.</p><p num="0030">Calorimetric results were generated on a TA Instruments Differential Scanning
Calorimeter, Model 2910 MDSC, using dry N<sub>2</sub> as a purge gas. Both non-isothermal and
isothermal crystallization studies were conducted. In non-isothermal conditions, after melting of
the polylactone copolymer, the copolymer was cooled under a controlled rate; or, after melting,
the copolymer was quenched below its glass transition temperature, then heated under a
controlled rate. In the isothermal studies, after melting the copolymer, the melted copolymer
was cooled rapidly to a temperature of interest and the crystallization measured under those
isothermal conditions. </p><p num="0031">In a typical non-isothermal crystallization of polylactone copolymers utilizing a
constant cooling rate, a polymer sample weighing around 4 mg first was heated to approximately
35-40°C above its melting temperature and held in the molten state for five minutes to eliminate
any crystallinity in the polymer. A subsequent cooling step was performed at a constant rate, q,
and the crystallization exotherm recorded. In a non-isothermal crystallization run utilizing a
constant heating rate, the polymer sample first was heated to approximately 35-40°C above its
melting point and then quenched from its amorphous, melted state to below its glass transition
temperature, followed by a controlled heating step.</p><p num="0032">In an isothermal crystallization of polylactone copolymers, a polymer sample of
about 4 mg first was heated to a temperature about 35-40°C above its melting point and
maintained as a melt for five minutes in order to remove any vestiges of the nucleation sites
originally present in a sample. Subsequently, the melted polymer was cooled rapidly, e.g. at a
rate of 35°C/min, to the constant test (crystallization) temperature. The isothermal method
assumes that no crystallization occurs before the sample reaches the test temperature.
Crystallization behavior was characterized over a wide range of temperatures, e.g. between 20°C
and 80°C. The isothermal heat flow curve then was integrated to determine the crystallinity as a
function of time. The evolution of crystallinity with time can be assessed from the degree of
crystallization, α, which is expressed by the ratio:
<img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="29"/>
where dQ/dt is the respective heat flow, ΔH<sub>t</sub> is the partial area between the DSC curve and the
time axis at time t, while ΔH<sub>∞</sub> is the total area under the peak and corresponds to the overall heat
of crystallization. The degree of crystallization, α, is the crystalline volume fraction developed at
time t. </p><p num="0033">Dimensional stability of an article can be readily determined. In the case of
injection molded articles, dimensional comparison to the mold can be made to ascertain warpage.
Dimensional stability of parts is important during shipping and storage where the part may be
exposed to slightly elevated temperature, again causing warpage or shrinkage of certain key
dimensions. The driving force to warp, distort or shrink is related to the amount of molecular
orientation (stress) generated during the molding process. The greater the amount of orientation,
the greater the drive to distort as temperatures are raised. Assessment of dimensional stability
can be done by subjecting test samples to increasing temperature, followed by measuring and
recording dimensional changes. The resulting profile provides a useful characterization.</p><p num="0034">HSOM was conducted using a Mettler FP90 central processor with a Mettler
FP82HT hot stage to control sample conditions. The hot stage, with nitrogen flow, was mounted
on a Nikon SMZ-U microscope equipped with a 1X objective and a 1:10 zoom. Images from the
microscope were obtained using a Microimage i308 Low Light Integrating Video Camera. The
digital images were captured and analyzed using Image Pro Plus (Version 4.0) imaging software.</p><p num="0035">Growth rate measurements at each temperature were conducted on freshly
prepared polymer films to avoid possible degradation issues that might arise with these
hydrolytically unstable polylactone polymers. The polymer film samples were prepared in the
following manner. A small amount of ground polymer was placed on the microscope glass slide
and a thin cover glass positioned on top of it. The resulting sandwich then was inserted into a hot
stage block regulated at, or above, the equilibrium melting point, to render the sample molten. In
the case of the polymers of Example 1 (Polymers 1A to 1E), this temperature was 140°C. The
polymeric sample then was heated for two minutes under a nitrogen purge to melt. A thin film
was obtained by applying slight pressure on the top of the cover glass. Monitoring with a digital
micrometer, the polymer film thickness was adjusted to 0.135 mm for each sample run. The thin
film samples were then melted for an additional five minutes at, or above, the equilibrium
melting temperature (140°C in the case of the polymers of Example 1) in a separate hot stage
apparatus as described above. They were then quickly brought to a second pre-heated measuring
device to perform isothermal measurements. </p><p num="0036">Some supporting evidence was obtained by conventional Wide Angle X-Ray
Diffraction (WAXD) analysis. The WAXD measurements of the isothermally grown films were
carried out on a Siemens Hi-Stars™ unit using CuKα radiation at the wavelength of 1.542 Å. The
instrument was operated at 40 kV and 40 mA with the collimator size of ⊘ 0.5mm. The
convolution of the X-ray images and the calculation of crystallinity content were conducted
using the DIFFRAC PLUS™ software developed by Siemens.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 1</u></b></heading><p num="0037">A series of undyed 92/8 (mole %) PDO/GLY segmented block copolymers were
prepared by ring-opening polymerization in a metal reactor outfitted with a suitable agitator, as
described below, using stannous octoate as a monomer-to-catalyst mole ratio of 30,000:1,
utilizing various ratios of mono-functional initiator, e.g. dodecanol (DD), to di-functional
initiator, e.g. diethylene glycol (DEG), (See table 1).</p><p num="0038">The polymerization process used in preparation of the PDO/GLY block
copolymer 1C is a two stage block co-polymerization comprising a first stage
homopolymerization using 100% p-dioxanone and a second stage block co-polymerization with
an added monomer composition of 100 mole % glycolide. The overall final composition
provides a polymer comprising 92 mole % polymerized p-dioxanone and 8 mole % polymerized
glycolide. The catalyst and initiators are added with the first stage monomer. The overall
monomer to catalyst ratio is 30,000 moles of monomer per mole of catalyst. The monomer to
catalyst ratio based on first stage monomer and the quantity of catalyst added is 27,600 moles of
monomer per mole of catalyst. The monomer to initiators ratio for this example is 1,000 to 1.
Thus for this 50/50 mole % mixture of DD and DEG as the initiators, the monomer to DD ratio is
2,000 to 1 and the monomer to DEG ratio is 2,000 to 1.</p><p num="0039">In the first stage, 10.26 kilo-grams p-dioxanone, 10.18 grams DD, 5.8 grams DEG
and 11.0 ml of a 12.6 w/v% stannous octoate catalyst solution were charged under a nitrogen
purge to a clean, dry stainless steel, oil-heated, jacketed reactor equipped with a mechanical
agitator. The vessel was evacuated to less than 1,000 mTorr for about 20 minutes, after which 
nitrogen gas was introduced to raise the pressure slightly over atmospheric (approximately +5
psi). The evacuation/nitrogen purge process was repeated using a 25-minute vacuum-hold
period. The constituents were heated under constant agitation to 110°C and then maintained at
this temperature for about four and one-half hours. The temperature of the oil entering the outer
jacket of the reactor was increased to 135°C. The second-stage monomer (1,014 grams
glycolide) was then added under nitrogen purge. Glycolide can be added as a solid or in melted
form, although the later is frequently preferred. The stirrer speed was increased to 20 RPM for
the first 15 minutes of the second-stage to enhance blending of ingredients. The polymerization
was continued for three and one-half hours. The polymer was discharged into trays. When the
polymer was cool to the touch, the polymer was placed into tared storage bags, weighed and
transferred to freezer storage. The frozen polymer was subsequently ground and sieved - size
reduction and classification - and dried under vacuum at elevated temperature.</p><p num="0040">The dried polymer 1C had the following properties:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Inherent Viscosity</entry><entry align="left">1.61 dL/g, as determined at 25.0°C in hexafluroisopropanol (HFIP) at a concentration of 0.1 g/dL</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Melt Index</entry><entry align="left">0.120 g/10 minutes (150°C, 6,600 gram weight, 0.026" diameter die opening with a 0.315" die length) using a Tinius Olsen Extrusion Plastometer</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mw</entry><entry align="left">68,000 g/mole</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mn</entry><entry align="left">24,000 g/mole</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Composition:</entry><entry align="left">mole %, by NMR: Polymerized PDO 91.6, Residual PDO 0.3, Polymerized GLY 8.1, Residual GLY 0.0.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables>
The dried polymer was stored under vacuum until ready for use or evaluation.</p><p num="0041">Crystallization characteristics of polymers and films made therefrom were
evaluated. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Polymer ID</entry><entry align="center">DD/DEG molar ratio (%)</entry><entry align="center">Monomer to initiators ratio</entry><entry align="center">IV ((dL/g)</entry><entry align="center">M<sub>w</sub> (g/mol)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1A</entry><entry align="center">100/0</entry><entry align="center">∼1,200:1</entry><entry align="center">1.73</entry><entry align="center">80,000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1B</entry><entry align="center">75/25</entry><entry align="center">∼1,000:1</entry><entry align="center">1.77</entry><entry align="center">73,000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1C</entry><entry align="center">50/50</entry><entry align="center">∼1,000:1</entry><entry align="center">1.61</entry><entry align="center">68,000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1D</entry><entry align="center">25/75</entry><entry align="center">∼1,000:1</entry><entry align="center">1.55</entry><entry align="center">55,000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1E</entry><entry align="center">0/100</entry><entry align="center">∼800:1</entry><entry align="center">1.41</entry><entry align="center">49,000</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 2</u></b></heading><p num="0042">A series of five 150 gram undyed 95/5 (mole % L(-)lactide/glycolide) random
copolymers were prepared by ring-opening polymerization in a round bottom glass reactors
outfitted with a suitable agitator, using stannous octoate at a monomer-to-catalyst mole ratio of
160,000:1 and utilizing various ratios of mono-functional initiator, e.g. dodecanol (DD), to di-functional
initiator, e.g. diethylene glycol (DEG). See Table 2. Crystallization characteristics of
polymers and films made therefrom were evaluated.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><b>-95m% L(-)LAC -5 m% GLY Random Copolymers</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center">Polymer ID</entry><entry align="center">DD/DEG molar ratio (%)</entry><entry align="center">Monomer to initiators ratio</entry><entry align="center">IV (dL/g)</entry><entry align="center">M<sub>w</sub> (g/mol)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2A</entry><entry align="center">100/0</entry><entry align="center">∼570:1</entry><entry align="center">1.72</entry><entry align="center">110,000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2B</entry><entry align="center">75/25</entry><entry align="center">∼570:1</entry><entry align="center">1.72</entry><entry align="center">110,000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2C</entry><entry align="center">50/50</entry><entry align="center">∼570:1</entry><entry align="center">1.64</entry><entry align="center">102,000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2D</entry><entry align="center">25/75</entry><entry align="center">∼570:1</entry><entry align="center">1.60</entry><entry align="center">98,000</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2E</entry><entry align="center">0/100</entry><entry align="center">∼570:1</entry><entry align="center">1.52</entry><entry align="center">92,000</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0043">Crystallization kinetics during spherulite growth are usually expressed via radius
or diameter growth rates, dR/dt or dD/dt, where t is the time and R (D) the radius (diameter) of
the spherulite, measured by means of an optical micrometer. The general expression of crystal
growth is described by Lauritzen and Hoffinan as:
<img id="img-00170001" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00170001.tif" inline="no" he="19"/>
where G is the growth rate dR/dt, G<sub>0</sub> is the growth rate constant, U* represents the activation
energy for polymer diffusion, R<sub>0</sub> the gas constant and T<sub>C</sub> the crystallization temperature. T<sub>∞</sub> is
the temperature at which molecular motion is frozen and viscosity approaches an infinitive value.
Hoffinan et. al. suggest using a value for U* of 1500 cal/mol and that T<sub>∞</sub> can be approximated
by T<sub>g</sub>-30, where T<sub>g</sub> is the glass transition temperature of the polymer (T<sub>g</sub> = -7°C for the 92/8
PDO/GLY copolymers). The term ΔT in Equation 2 stands for the amount of undercooling (ΔT =
T<sub>m</sub>°-T<sub>C</sub>), where T<sub>m</sub>° is the equilibrium melting temperature (T<sub>m</sub>° = 140°C for the 92/8 PDO/GLY
copolymers and for PDS, as found by optical microscopy). Parameter f is a dimensionless term
expressed by f = 2T<sub>C</sub>/(T<sub>C</sub>+ T<sub>m</sub>°). K<sub>g</sub> is the nucleation rate constant.</p><p num="0044">As shown in Figure 1, the spherulite diameter was plotted against time for
polymer 1D crystallized at various constant temperatures. These data clearly show that the radius
of the supramolecular formations grew linearly with time over the entire range of investigated
crystallization temperatures. The average linear correlation coefficient found in these plots
suggests almost a perfect linearity, implying that the growth rates were independent of the size of
the spherulites. The slopes of the curves generated (see Figure 2) were a smooth function of the
crystallization temperature, in that dD/dt systematically increased to a maximum value, then
decreased as the melting point was approached. Radial growth ceased only when all surfaces
were bounded or impinged.</p><p num="0045">In order to correlate data that were obtained during various spherulitic growth
measurements with the Lauritzen-Hoffman theory, Equation 2 can be rewritten in the following
form: <st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">ln<st32:italic>G</st32:italic> + <st32:frac align="centre"><st32:italic>U</st32:italic>* <st32:over><st32:italic>R<st32:sub pos="post">0</st32:sub>(T<st32:sub pos="post">C</st32:sub>-T<st32:sub pos="post">∞</st32:sub>)</st32:italic></st32:over></st32:frac> = ln<st32:italic>G</st32:italic><st32:sub pos="post">0</st32:sub> - <st32:frac align="centre"><st32:italic>K</st32:italic><st32:sub pos="post"><st32:italic>g</st32:italic></st32:sub><st32:over>ƒ<st32:italic>T</st32:italic><st32:sub pos="post">C</st32:sub>Δ<st32:italic>T</st32:italic></st32:over></st32:frac></st32:df></p><p num="0046">A linear plot can be obtained by drawing the left-hand side of Equation 3 as a
function of 1/fT<sub>C</sub>ΔT. The intercept of this plot is In G<sub>0</sub> and its slope is the nucleation constant K<sub>g</sub>.
The growth rates G were determined earlier from the slopes of the lines displayed in Figure 1.</p><p num="0047">Experimentally determined growth rates, G = dD/dt, are plotted against
temperature in Figure 2 for the series of copolymers of Example 1 and a PDS homopolymer as a
comparison. Results showed a characteristic "bell-shaped" dependence between crystal growth
rate and crystallization temperature, with the maximum rate observed at intermediate
temperature zones. Data clearly indicates that for any given crystallization temperature, the
spherulitic growth rate of PDS homopolymer is significantly higher (∼8x) than those obtained
from the copolymer series of Example 1. The reason for this behavior can be attributed to the
disruptive role that glycolic acid comonomer plays in the overall ability of the copolymer's
macromolecular chains to align properly for the crystal formation. In the series of copolymers of
Example 1, there is practically no difference in the crystallization kinetics for the temperature
range used except for sample 1C, which crystal growth was found slightly slower than those of
the other copolymers in the series. Solid lines that connect data points of PDS and polymers of
Example 1 were calculated according to Equation 2, using the previously obtained values for K<sub>g</sub>
and In G<sub>0</sub> from Figure 3. The excellent fit of the model (note that no adjustable parameters are
involved) over a very broad range of temperatures is particularly noted.</p><p num="0048">The second part of an isothermal supramolecular crystallization analysis involves
the nucleation density evaluation. Nucleation density, the number of nuclei per unit volume,
generally increases with increasing molecular weight, but decreases with increasing
crystallization temperature. An estimation of the nucleation rate using HSOM usually requires a
manual counting of nucleation sites present in an arbitrary chosen field of the sample as a
function of time. In order to determine nucleation rates, the initial slopes of these curves were
calculated as a function of crystallization temperatures. Such obtained nucleation rates, dN/dt, 
are plotted in Figure 3 over a limited temperature range. These data suggest that, within the
experimentally accessible region, i.e. 60° to 80°C, polymer 1B exhibits the highest nucleation
rates.</p><p num="0049">Outstanding crystallization properties of polymer 1C were discovered when
studied under those conditions. First, the nucleation rates for copolymer 1 C, observed at higher
temperatures, were found slower than in polymer 1B, but increased rather abruptly when the
crystallization temperature is lowered (see Figure 3). When studied at a lower temperature range,
a visual inspection of the copolymer's crystalline morphology indicated that, due to the extensive
nucleation process, total crystal impingement occurred almost instantaneously (see Figure 4). It
was discovered that the nucleation density of polymer 1C was extremely high compared to the
balance of copolymers described in Table 1. While not intending to be bound by this theory, such
a high degree of nucleation apparently controlled the crystal growth via an impingement process,
even at very early stages of the process. Thus, the boundaries of developed structures
approached each other, causing the crystals to stop growing. This produced, in turn, a large
number of crystals with very small size. It was estimated that the average diameter of the
crystals at the studied conditions (40°C after 60 minutes) was about 8 microns. The balance of
the copolymers described in Table 1 had a value significantly higher at about 70 microns.</p><p num="0050">The overall crystallization rates depend heavily on two factors: the concentration
of growing spherulites with time (nucleation rate) and the rate of spherulite growth. It is
anticipated that these processes would have a measurable effect on calorimetric data. DSC has
several technical advantages including small sample size, an easy-to-handle apparatus, and more
importantly, the ability to achieve a rapid thermal equilibrium, especially at high undercooling.
Because of these characteristics, DSC has been one of the most convenient and popular methods
in studying crystallization behavior of polymers using both, non-isothermal and isothermal
methods.</p><p num="0051">DSC data generated on the copolymers of Example 1 during cooling from the
melt support earlier evidence from HSOM, indicating clearly superb crystallization behavior of
copolymer 1C. A thermogram captured during the constant cooling rate (0.5°C/min) experiment 
for this copolymer is shown in Figure 5. Several important parameters can be extracted from this
figure. The high temperature slope of the peak represents the crystallization rate under given
conditions. The area under the peak is proportional to overall crystallinity in the material. The
temperature at the maximum peak indicates the location of the crystallization processes at the
given cooling rate. A summary of thermal characteristics for all the copolymers of Example 1
and a PDS homopolymer obtained by the same method is listed in Table 3.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1"><b>Non-isothermal crystallization data obtained during the constant cooling rate of 0.5°C/min for a series of VLM copolymers and a PDS homopolymer.</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center">Polymer</entry><entry align="center">T<sub>C</sub> (°C)</entry><entry align="center">Peak area at T<sub>C</sub> (J/g)</entry><entry align="center">α (%)<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">Absolute Value of Slope<!--footnotes removed--> (Wg<sup>-1</sup>°C<sup>-1</sup>)</entry><entry align="center">Relative Rate<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row><row><entry align="center">Copolymer 1A</entry><entry align="center">52.5</entry><entry align="center">8.2</entry><entry align="center">6.7</entry><entry align="center">0.000265</entry><entry align="center">0.9 X</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Copolymer 1B</entry><entry align="center">52.1</entry><entry align="center">8.9</entry><entry align="center">7.2</entry><entry align="center">0.000219</entry><entry align="center">0.8 X</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Copolymer 1C</entry><entry align="center">46.8</entry><entry align="center">43.9</entry><entry align="center">35.3</entry><entry align="center">0.00694</entry><entry align="center">24.7 X</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Copolymer 1D</entry><entry align="center">48.5</entry><entry align="center">9.3</entry><entry align="center">7.5</entry><entry align="center">0.000154</entry><entry align="center">0.5 X</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Copolymer 1E</entry><entry align="center">48.7</entry><entry align="center">10.2</entry><entry align="center">8.2</entry><entry align="center">0.000298</entry><entry align="center">1.1 X</entry></row><row><entry align="center">PDS Homopolymer</entry><entry align="center">57.8</entry><entry align="center">39.3</entry><entry align="center">31.7</entry><entry align="center">0.00381</entry><entry align="center">13.5 X<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0052">For this set of conditions, copolymer 1C crystallized radically faster, e.g. 25x, and
to a much higher extent, e.g. 4-5x than the rest of the copolymers of Example 1. In addition,
about a 2-6°C lower crystallization temperature observed for polymer 1 C suggests that, in this
particular case, the extensive nucleation at lower temperatures is the most dominant
crystallization mechanism. It was unexpectedly discovered that both the crystallizability and
non-isothermal kinetics of this material are even greater than those calculated for the PDS
homopolymer alone. A comparison of DSC crystallization data between copolymer 1C and PDS
homopolymer obtained using a wide range of cooling rates revealed the same trend. Copolymer
1 C showed faster crystallization and a higher overall crystallinity than the PDS homopolymer
and the balance of the copolymers of Example 1.</p><p num="0053">The second part of the non-isothermal DSC crystallization study was conducted
on the copolymers of Example 1 utilizing controlled heating steps. Samples were initially
quenched from the molten state to obtain a fully amorphous morphology and subsequently
heated at rates of 2.5, 5.0, 7.5 and 10°C/min, respectively.</p><p num="0054">DSC thermograms suggested that the area under the crystallization peaks equals
roughly that for a fusion process, suggesting that the heating scan started from the fully
amorphous samples. For the copolymers of Example 1 tested, at the constant hearing rate of
10°C/min, the T<sub>g</sub>s of the copolymers in semi-crystalline and amorphous states were -3°C and-7°C,
respectively. At the same heating rate employed, the unannealed material melts at
approximately 90°C (about 8°C lower than PDS). For all Example 1 copolymers studied, the
melting point locations obtained after the first (annealed) and second (unannealed) heating runs,
as well as the heat of fusion generated on the annealed samples, were found almost constant for
the test conditions used. On the other hand, due to the significantly higher crystallization tare,
the melting peak area (corresponding to the crystallinity level) of copolymer 1 C was larger than
that of the balance of the copolymers of Example 1. In addition, at the given heating rate used,
the copolymer crystallized to considerably higher extent than the PDS homopolymer. This
unusual finding, obtained under non-isothermal heating conditions, is in line with the relative
crystallization rates observed earlier for the samples crystallized under non-isothermal controlled
cooling rate experiments. </p><p num="0055">The kinetic data for isothermal melt crystallization of copolymer 1C were
analyzed using a classical Avrami approach. According to the Avrami model, the time
dependence of α can be described by the following kinetic expression:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">-ln(1-α) = <st32:italic>K×t<st32:sup pos="post">n</st32:sup></st32:italic></st32:df>
where K is the composite rate constant and <i>n</i> is the Avrami exponent, typically ranging from 2 to
4 for semicrystalline polymers. These constants are related to the crystallization half-time, t<sub>1/2</sub>,
and to the type of nucleation and geometry of the crystal growth. Crystallization half-time, t<sub>1/2</sub>, is
the time needed for crystallinity to reach 50% conversion. The Avrami exponent, n, was
determined from the slope of the log[-1n(1-α)] vs. log t curve. Finally, the composite rate
constant, K, can be evaluated either from the intercept or calculated using the following
expression:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center"><st32:italic>K</st32:italic> = <st32:frac align="centre">ln 2<st32:over><st32:italic>t</st32:italic><st32:sub pos="post">1/2</st32:sub><st32:sup pos="post"><st32:italic>n</st32:italic></st32:sup></st32:over></st32:frac></st32:df></p><p num="0056">The value t<sub>1/2</sub> was determined by fitting each set of data to Equation 4 and then
graphically locating the crystallization time that corresponds to α=0.5. Using this approach, it
was found that an excellent agreement exists between the actual experimental data and theory. A
summary of important kinetic parameters is listed in Table 4 for the temperature range between
35 to 60 C. A data comparison with PDS homopolymer is given in the table as well. <img id="img-00230001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00230001.tif" inline="no" he="130"/></p><p num="0057">The analysis of the half-time values indicates that they are a strong function of T<sub>c</sub>.
The fastest isothermal crystallization rate (the lowest t<sub>1/2</sub> value) for copolymer 1C was detected
at 40°C. This temperature is lower than that that of the homopolymer (45°C), because of the
extensive nucleation mechanism observed for the copolymer at lower temperatures. Despite
significantly higher nucleation rates, overall crystallization rates for the copolymer were found
slower for all studied isothermal conditions. Overall crystallization rates do not exactly follow
the nucleation trends observed earlier by HSOM measurements, because the second part of the
crystallization process for PDS homopolymer, i.e. spherulitic growth, is more than eight (8)
times faster at any given temperature (see Figure 2). However, a copolymer's nucleation effect 
on overall isothermal crystallization is still very pronounced. The overall crystallization rate (t<sub>1/2</sub>
values in Table 4) is only about half that of the PDS homopolymer.</p><p num="0058">Geometry of the crystal habit during isothermal crystallization of copolymer 1C,
expressed via the Avrami exponent, <i>n,</i> is also listed in Table 4. The values of <i>n</i> were relatively
constant at 2.6 indicating that the crystal growth was three-dimensional. A nearly identical value
was found earlier for the PDS homopolymer (2.5).</p><p num="0059">Finally, data from Table 4 suggest that crystallization content of isothermally
treated copolymer 1 C was significantly higher than in the PDS homopolymer at any given
crystallization temperature. This is also in agreement with results obtained during non-isothermal
crystallization measurements utilizing controlled heating and cooling rates. The percent of
crystallinity determined from DSC heat of fusion were additionally confirmed by the WAXD
technique. A big advantage of the copolymers having higher crystal content is the boost in
mechanical properties, which in turn, can improve functioning of many current and future
products based on these absorbable materials.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An absorbable polylactone copolymer, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>from about 5 mole percent to about 10 mole percent of a first polymerized lactone
comprising polymerized glycolide and about 95 mole percent to about 90 mole percent of a
second polymerized lactone other than polymerized glycolide, wherein said copolymer has a
degree of crystallinity of at least about 15 %.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The copolymer of claim 1, wherein said second polylactone is prepared from lactone
monomers selected from the group consisting of p-dioxanone, lactide, ε-caprolactone and
trimethylene carbonate and combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The copolymer of claim 1, comprising about 8 mole percent polymerized glycolide and
about 92 mole percent polymerized p-dioxanone, said copolymer having a degree of crystallinity
of from about 20 to about 40 %.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A medical device, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an absorbable polylactone copolymer, said copolymer comprising from about 5 mole
percent to about 10 mole percent of a first polymerized lactone comprising polymerized
glycolide and about 95 mole percent to about 90 mole percent of a second polymerized lactone
other than polymerized glycolide, wherein said copolymer has a degree of crystallinity of at least
about 15 %.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The device of claim 4 wherein said second polylactone is prepared from lactone
mononers selected from the group consisting of p-dioxanone, lactide, ε-caprolactone and
trimethylene carbonate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The device of claim 4 wherein the copolymer comprises about 8 mole percent
polymerized glycolide and about 92 mole percent of polymerized p-dioxanone, said copolymer
having a degree of crystallinity of from about 20 to about 40 %.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The medical device of claim 4 selected from the group consisting of sutures, clips, staples
and fibers.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The medical device of claim 4 which is capable of being deformed.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The medical device of claim 4 which is repeatedly deformable.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The medical device of claim 4 which is resiliently deformable.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A composition for producing an absorbable polylactone copolymer comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a.) about 2 mole percent to about 80 mole percent a first lactone monomer
comprising glycolide;</claim-text><claim-text>b.) from about 98 to about 20 mole percent of a second lactone monomer other than
glycolide;</claim-text><claim-text>c.) a monofunctional initiator; and</claim-text><claim-text>d.) a di-functional initiator;</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein the molar ratio of mono-functional to di-functional initiator is from about
10:90 to about 90:10;</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The reaction product of the composition of claim 11.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The reaction product of claim 12 having a degree of crystallinity at least 15% using non-isothermal
crystallization under a substantially constant cooling rate of about 0.5°C/minute.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>An absorbable polylactone copolymer comprising from about 5 mole percent to about 10
mole percent of a first polylactone comprising polyglycolide and about 95 mole percent to about
90 mole percent of a second polylactone other than polyglycolide, wherein said copolymer has
an average crystal size of about 25 microns or less.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>