<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1069108-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1069108" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="16454188" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010117"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1069108-A1" status="new" fvid="23020092"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1069108</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010117</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00114727-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00114727</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000708</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-20223499-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>20223499</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990715</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07B  61/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07B  61/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 253/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 253/28        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 255/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 255/50        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 213/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 213/84        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 213/85        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C 253/28</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung von aromatischer und heterocyclischer Nitrile</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Process for producing aromatic and heterocyclic nitriles</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour la préparation de nitriles aromatiques et hétérocycliques</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-1643722-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>1643722</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="OPP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="DE-3114709-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>3114709</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="OPP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0222249-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0222249</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="OPP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0273317-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0273317</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="OPP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0699476-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0699476</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source name="OPP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3462476-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3462476</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="OPP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3637797-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3637797</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="OPP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3803204-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3803204</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4044042-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4044042</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4284781-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4284781</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4814479-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4814479</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5235088-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5235088</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199532 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class B05, AN 1995-242657 XP002150456 &amp; JP 07 145133 A (SUMITOMO CHEM CO LTD), 6 June 1995 (1995-06-06)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>Encyclopedia of Chem. Processing and Design, p. 156-162, vol. 31</text><sources><source name="OPP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>Hydrocarbon Processing, 1969, p. 252, Xylylenediamine</text><sources><source name="OPP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>Hydrocarbon Processing, 1976, p. 103-106, Make Aromatic Nitriles this way</text><sources><source name="OPP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI GAS CHEMICAL CO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI GAS CHEMICAL COMPANY, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MITSUBISHI GAS CHEMICAL COMPANY, INC.</last-name><address><street>No. 5-2, Marunouchi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>EBATA SHUJI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KANAMORI YOSHINORI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OGINO HIDEAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OKAWA TAKASHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>EBATA, SHUJI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KANAMORI, YOSHINORI</name> </addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OGINO, HIDEAKI</name></addressbook></inventor> <inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OKAWA, TAKASHI</name> </addressbook> </inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Ebata, Shuji, Mitsubishi Gas Chemical Co. Inc.</last-name><address><street>Niigata Res. Lab., 182, Aza-Shinwari, Tayuhama</street><city>Niigata-shi, Niigata-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KANAMORI, YOSHINORI MITSUBISHI GAS CHEMICAL CO.INC</last-name><address><street>Niigata Res. Lab., 182, Aza-Shinwari, Tayuhama</street><city>Niigata-shi, Niigata-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Ogino, Hideaki, Mitsubishi Gas Chemical Co. Inc.</last-name><address><street>Niigata Res. Lab., 182, Aza-Shinwari, Tayuhama</street><city>Niigata-shi, Niigata-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Okawa, Takashi, Mitsubishi Gas Chemical Co. Inc.</last-name><address><street>Niigata Res. Lab., 182, Aza-Shinwari, Tayuhama</street><city>Niigata-shi, Niigata-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Türk, Gille, Hrabal, Leifert</last-name><address><street>Patentanwälte Brucknerstrasse 20</street><city>40593 Düsseldorf</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>BE</country><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>IT</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A carbocyclic or heterocyclic compound, ammonia and an oxygen-containing
gas are subjected to fluid catalytic reaction in vapor phase in the
presence of a catalyst containing alkali metal to produce an aromatic or
heterocyclic nitrile. The use of the catalyst containing a specific amount of
alkali metal enables the stable production of the aromatic or heterocyclic
nitrile in high yields with little change with time even when water is present
in the reaction system. The use of the catalyst containing the alkali metal
also enables the recycle and reuse of unreacted ammonia which is usually
accompanied by water, thereby reducing production costs.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><heading>1. Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a process for producing nitrile
compounds by reacting carbocyclic or heterocyclic compounds with a mixed gas
of ammonia and oxygen.</p><heading>2. Description of the Prior Art</heading><p num="0002">Aromatic nitrites produced by ammoxidation of carbocyclic compounds
are useful as raw materials for manufacturing synthetic resins, agricultural
chemicals, etc., and as intermediate materials for producing amines,
isocyanates, etc. Heterocyclic nitrites produced by ammoxidation of
heterocyclic compounds are also useful as intermediates of medicines, animal
feed additives, food additives, etc.</p><p num="0003">Ammoxidation of carbocyclic or heterocyclic compounds to aromatic or
heterocyclic nitrite compounds generates a larger amount of heat as compared
to ammoxidation of olefins. Therefore, a vapor-phase fluid catalytic reaction
has been advantageously used for the ammoxidation of carbocyclic or
heterocyclic compounds because the heat of reaction can be easily removed and
side reactions due to local heating can be avoided. Various catalyst systems
comprising a metal oxide or comprising a metal oxide supported on a carrier
such as silica and alumina have been proposed for use in the vapor-phase fluid
catalytic reaction.</p><p num="0004">For instance, Japanese Patent Publication No. 49-45860 produces an
aromatic nitrite by ammoxidation of an alkyl-substituted aromatic compound
in the presence of a catalyst containing V, Cr and B. Japanese Patent
Application Laid-Open No. 49-13141 conducts the similar reaction in the
presence of a catalyst containing Fe, Bi and Mo. Japanese Patent Application
Laid-Open No. 63-190646 discloses ammoxidation of an alkyl-substituted 
aromatic compound or an alkyl-substituted alicyclic compound using an Fe-Sb
catalyst.</p><p num="0005">Japanese Patent Application Laid-Open No. 1-275551 discloses
ammoxidation of an alkyl-substituted aromatic compound or an alkyl-substituted
heterocyclic compound in the presence of a V-Cr-B-Mo catalyst.
Japanese Patent Application Laid-Open No. 5-170724 conducts the similar
reaction in the presence of an Mo-P catalyst. Japanese Patent Application
Laid-Open No. 9-71561 produces dicyanobenzene by ammoxidation of xylene
in the presence of an Fe-Sb-V catalyst.</p><p num="0006">These known processes are advantageous because aromatic or
heterocyclic nitriles are produced in high yields. However, the catalysts used
in the processes are decreased in their activity with time. Therefore, it has
been demanded to produce nitrile compounds in high yields over a long period
of time. To meet the demands, there have been proposed a method for
inhibiting the catalyst deterioration in fluidized reaction, a catalyst with little
activity change with time, etc. For instance, Japanese Patent Application
Laid-Open No. 10-120641 teaches to prevent the deterioration of a metal oxide
catalyst containing V and/or Mo by a controlled feeding of raw materials to a
fluid reactor.</p><p num="0007">As described above, in the process for producing nitrile compounds by
fluid catalytic ammoxidation of carbocyclic or heterocyclic compounds in vapor-phase,
various attempts have been made to improve catalysts and apparatuses
for preventing deterioration of the catalysts. However, it is still demanded to
produce the mtrile compounds stably in high yields over a prolonged period of
time.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0008">It is an object of the present invention to provide an economical process
for producing a nitrile compound by vapor-phase fluid catalytic reaction of a
carbocyclic or heterocyclic compound with ammonia and an oxygen-containing 
gas in high yields with little lowering with time over a long period of time.</p><p num="0009">As a result of extensive researches and studies on the production of
nitrile compounds in view of the above objects, the inventors have found that
one of the attributing causes of the deterioration of catalyst activity is water
accompanying unreacted ammonia during its recycle and reuse, and that the
use of catalysts containing a specific amount of alkali metal enables the
ammoxidation to be stably performed with little change with time in the yields
over a long period of time. The present invention has been accomplished
based on this finding.</p><p num="0010">Namely, in accordance with the present invention, there is provided a
process for producing an aromatic or heterocyclic nitrile, comprising a step of
subjecting a carbocyclic or heterocyclic compound, ammonia and an oxygen-containing
gas to fluid catalytic reaction in vapor phase in the presence of a
catalyst containing 0.10 to 0.40% by weight of alkali metal; and a step of
recycling unreacted ammonia recovered from a reaction product gas.</p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0011">The present invention will be described in detail below.</p><p num="0012">In the vapor-phase catalytic reaction of the present invention, a
carbocyclic compound or a heterocyclic compound is reacted with an oxygen-containing
gas and ammonia. To effectively remove heat of reaction and
avoid side reactions due to local heating, the catalytic reaction is carried out in
fluidized manner.</p><p num="0013">The carbocyclic compounds used as raw materials in the present
invention has a carbon ring selected from the group consisting of benzene,
naphthalene, anthracene, cyclohexene, cyclohexane, dihydronaphthalene,
tetralin and decaline. The carbon ring has at least one nitrile-forming group
selected from the group consisting of methyl, ethyl, propyl, formyl, acetyl,
hydroxymethyl and methoxycarbonyl. Further, the carbocycic compound
may have another substituent such as halogen atom, hydroxyl, alkoxyl, amino, 
nitro, etc. Examples of the carbocycic compounds include toluene, xylene,
trimethylbenzene, ethylbenzene, methylnaphthalene, dimethylnaphthalene,
methyltetralin, dimethyltetralin, chlorotoluene, dichlorotoluene, methylaniline,
cresol and methylanisole.</p><p num="0014">The heterocyclic compounds used in the present invention have at least
one hetero ring selected from the group consisting of furan, pyrrole, indole,
thiophene, pyrazole, imidazole, oxazole, pyran, pyridine, quinoline,
isoquinoline, pyrroline, pyrrolidine, imidazoline, imidazolidine, piperidine and
piperazine. The hetero ring has at least one nitrile-forming group selected
from the same group as described above for the carbocyclic compounds.
Examples of the heterocyclic compounds include furfural, 2-methylthiophene,
3-methylthiophene, 2-formylthiophene, 4-methylthiazole, methylpyridine,
dimethylpyridine, trimethylpyridine, methylquinoline, methylpyrazine,
dimethylpyrazine and methylpiperazine.</p><p num="0015">The ammonia used as a raw material in the present invention may be of
industrial grade. The amount of ammonia used is 1.5 to 10 moles, preferably
3 to 5 moles per one mole of the nitrile-forming group in the carbocyclic or
heterocyclic compound. When the amount of ammonia used is less than the
above range, the yield of the nitrile compound is lowered. When the amount
of ammonia used exceeds the above range, the space time yield of the nitrile
compound becomes small.</p><p num="0016">In the process of the present invention, the unreacted ammonia in
reaction product gas is recovered and recycled to the reaction system for reuse.
The method of recovering the unreacted ammonia from the reaction product
gas is not particularly restricted. From an industrial viewpoint, it is suitable
that the unreacted ammonia is absorbed in water, and then separated from
by-products by distillation.</p><p num="0017">The oxygen-containing gas used in the present invention may be usually
air. Alternatively, diluted air or oxygen with an inert gas such as nitrogen,
carbon dioxide or waste gases may also be used as the oxygen-containing gas. 
The oxygen concentration in the oxygen-containing gas is preferably 10 to
20 % by volume. The amount of oxygen used is 1.5 moles or larger, preferably
2 to 50 moles per one mole of the nitrile-forming group in the carbocyclic or
heterocyclic compound. When less than the above range, the yield of the
nitrite compound is lowered. When exceeding the above range, the space time
yield of the nitrite compound becomes small.</p><p num="0018">The catalyst used in the present invention contains an alkali metal in
an amount of 0.1 to 0.4% by weight, preferably 0.1 to 0.3% by weight based on
the weight of a supported catalyst (total weight of the catalyst and carrier).</p><p num="0019">When the content of the alkali metal is less than the above range, the
catalyst is poor in mechanical strength such as wear resistance (attrition
resistance). When the content exceeds the above range, the sintering of the
catalyst proceeds by interaction between water in the raw materials and the
alkali metal in the catalyst, resulting in the reduction with time of yields of
the nitrite compound.</p><p num="0020">The process of the present invention is preferably performed in the
presence of a catalyst comprising at least one oxide selected from the group
consisting of oxides of V, Mo and Fe.</p><p num="0021">In addition to the oxides of V, Mo and Fe, the catalyst may further
contain at least one oxide selected from the group consisting of oxides of Mg,
Ca, Ba, La, Ti, Zr, Cr, W, Co, Ni, B, Al, Ge, Sn, Pb, P, Sb and Bi. Such a
catalyst is represented by the formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">(V)<sub>a</sub>(Mo)<sub>b</sub>(Fe)<sub>c</sub>(X)<sub>d</sub>(Y)<sub>e</sub>(O)<sub>f</sub></st32:che>
wherein X is at least one element selected from the group consisting of Mg, Ca,
Ba, La, Ti, Zr, Cr, W, Co and Ni; Y is at least one element selected from the
group consisting of B, Al, Ge, Sn, Pb, P, Sb and Bi; and subscripts a, b, c, d and
e represent atomic proportions, a being 0.01 to 1, preferably 0.1 to 0.7; b being
0.01 to 1, preferably 0.05 to 0.7; c being 0 to 1, preferably 0.05 to 0.7; d being 0
to 1, preferably 0.05 to 0.7; e being 0 to 1, preferably 0.05 to 0.7 and f being the
number of oxide-forming oxygen atoms. </p><p num="0022">Of the metal oxide catalysts, preferred are V-Cr-B-Mo-P-(Na and/or K)
metal oxide catalysts. Examples of the vanadium sources may be inorganic
salts of vanadium such as ammonium salts and sulfates, and vanadium salts
of organic acids such as oxalic acid and tartaric acid. Examples of the
molybdenum sources may be ammonium molybdate, phosphomolybdic acid,
ammonium phosphomolybdate and molybdenum salts of organic acids such as
oxalic acid and tartaric acid. Examples of the chromium sources may be
chromic acid, nitrates of chromium, hydroxides of chromium, ammonium
chromate, ammonium dichromate, and chromium salts of organic acids such
as oxalic acid and tartaric acid. Examples of the boron sources may be boric
acid, ammonium borate, etc. The alkali metal may be Li, Na, K, Rb and Cs,
and Na and K are preferable. Examples of the alkali metal sources may be
alkali hydroxides, alkali carbonates, alkali nitrates and alkali salts of organic
acids such as oxalic acid, tartaric acid and acetic acid. The sources for other
metals may be metal salts of inorganic or organic acids, which are easily
converted into metal oxides by heating in air.</p><p num="0023">The metal oxide catalysts are preferably supported on known carrier
such as silica, alumina, etc., and preferably silica. Examples of silica used as
the carrier include silica gel, colloidal silica, anhydrous silica, etc. as described,
for example, in "Chemical Handbook, Applied Chemistry 1" published by
Maruzen (1986), pp. 256-258. The amount of alkali metal contained in the
silica carrier should be considered in preparing a supported catalyst so that
the alkali metal content falls within the range specified above. The amount
of the carrier used is 20 to 80% by weight, preferably 40 to 70% by weight
based on the weight of the supported catalyst.</p><p num="0024">The catalyst used in the present invention can be produced by known
methods. For instance, the preparation of a supported catalyst comprising a
silica carrier supporting V-Cr-B-Mo-P-Na oxide catalyst is described below.
An aqueous boric acid solution, sodium acetate and silica sol are successively
added to an oxalic acid solution dissolving vanadium oxide and chromium 
oxide, thereby obtaining a slurry. A dissolving assistant such as polyhydric
alcohols, α-monocarboxylic acids and dioxycarboxylic acids may be added, if
desired, to facilitate the dissolution of boric acid. The slurry is sprayed for
drying and then further dried, if necessary, at 110 to 150°C. The dried slurry
is calcined at 400 to 700°C, preferably 450 to 650°C for several hours or longer
in a stream of air. Prior to the calcination, the dried slurry is preferably pre-calcined
at 200 to 400°C.</p><p num="0025">The catalyzed ammoxidation of the carbocyclic or heterocyclic
compounds is carried out at 300 to 500°C, preferably 330 to 470°C. When the
reaction temperature is lower than the above range, the conversion is low.
When the reaction temperature is higher than the above range, the production
of carbon dioxide, hydrogen cyanide, etc., is promoted, so that the yields of the
aromatic or heterocyclic nitriles are reduced.</p><p num="0026">The reaction pressure is generally ordinary pressure. However, the
reaction may be performed under increased or reduced pressure, if desired.
The contact time between the reactant gas and the catalyst is usually in the
range of 0.5 to 30 seconds, although varies depending upon kinds of raw
materials, charged ratio between raw materials, air and ammonia, reaction
temperature, etc.</p><p num="0027">In the present invention, the aromatic or heterocyclic nitriles may be
collected by any known method, for example, by a method of cooling the
reaction product gas to a temperature enough to precipitate the aromatic or
heterocyclic nitriles, or a method of washing the reaction product gas with
water or other suitable solvents.</p><p num="0028">Known catalysts do not undergo the deterioration with time in catalytic
activity when water is not contained in the starting carbocyclic or heterocyclic
compounds, oxygen-containing gas such as air and ammonia. However, when
a non-negligible amount of water is contained, the sintering of the catalysts is
promoted so that the catalyst activity is considerably deteriorated with time,
thereby failing to stably produce the aromatic or heterocyclic nitriles. </p><p num="0029">Since the recovered ammonia contains a non-negligible amount of water,
the catalyst activity is adversely affected by water. Although the water can
be removed by distillation, adsorption, etc., these additional operations
increase the production cost.</p><p num="0030">In the present invention, this problem in the prior art has been solved
by the addition of alkali metal to the catalyst comprising oxides of V, Mo, Fe,
etc. The addition of alkali metal maintains the catalyst strength such as
wear resistance sufficiently high and prevents the deterioration of catalytic
activity even when water enters into the reaction system accompanying the
recycled ammonia, thereby stably producing the aromatic or heterocyclic
nitriles at high yields over a long period of time.</p><p num="0031">The present invention will be described in more detail by reference to
the following examples and comparative examples. However, it should be
noted that the following examples are not intended to limit the invention
thereto.</p><heading>Example 1</heading><heading>(Preparation of catalyst)</heading><p num="0032">A mixture of 229 g of vanadium pentoxide (V<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) and 500 ml of water
was heated to 80 to 90°C, and then, 477 g of oxalic acid were dissolved therein
under vigorous stirring. Separately, a mixture of 963 g of oxalic acid and 400
ml of water was heated to 50 to 60°C, and then, a solution of 252 g of chromic
anhydride (CrO<sub>3</sub>) in 200 ml of water was dissolved therein under vigorous
stirring. The vanadyl oxalate solution and the chromium oxalate solution
thus prepared were mixed with each other at 50 to 60°C to obtain a vanadium-chromium
solution, to which were successively added a solution of 41.1 g of
phosphomolybdic acid (H<sub>3</sub>[PMo<sub>12</sub>O<sub>40</sub>]·20H<sub>2</sub>O) in 100 ml of water and a
solution of 4.0 g of potassium acetate (CH<sub>3</sub>COOK) in 100 ml of water. To the
resultant solution, were added 2,500 g of 20wt.% aqueous silica sol (containing
0.02% by weight of Na<sub>2</sub>O) to obtain a slurry, to which 78 g of boric acid
(H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>) were added. The slurry was heated and concentrated until the 
weight was reduced to about 3,800 g. The catalyst slurry thus prepared was
spray-dried while maintaining the inlet temperature at 250°C and the outlet
temperature at 130°C. The spray-dried catalyst was further dried in a dryer
at 130°C for 12 hours, pre-calcined at 400°C for 0.5 hour, and then calcined
under air flow at 550°C for 8 hours. The supported catalyst thus prepared
had an alkali metal content of 0.21% by weight, an atomic ratio of V : Cr : B :
Mo : P : Na : K = 1: 1: 0.5 : 0.086 : 0.007 : 0.009 : 0.020 and a catalyst
concentration of 50% by weight.</p><heading>(Test of catalyst strength)</heading><p num="0033">Into a test tube (38 mm inner diameter) provided at an upper portion
thereof with a collecting thimble (No. 84, produced by Toyo Roshi Co., Ltd.), 50
g of the supported catalyst prepared above were charged. Air was then
introduced into the test tube at a feed rate of 312 m/sec at room temperature
to fluidize the supported catalyst for 20 hours. The amount of the worn-out
catalyst particles scattered into the collecting thimble during the fluidization
was 2.1% by weight based on the charged amount. This shows that the
supported catalyst had a mechanical strength sufficient for practical use.</p><heading>(Test of catalytic activity)</heading><p num="0034">Into a reactor (23 mm inner diameter) heated by a resistance heat
generator, 40 ml of the supported catalyst were charged. A water-free mixed
gas comprising 3.2% by volume of m-xylene, 25.3% by volume of ammonia and
71.5% by volume of air, or a mixed gas further containing, in addition to the
above components, water in an amount of 20.0% by volume based on ammonia
was introduced into the reactor and subjected to fluid catalytic ammoxidation
at 420°C at which the supported catalyst gave the maximum yield of
isophthalonitrile and at a hourly space velocity (SV) of 850 hr<sup>-1</sup>. The actual
yields of isophthalonitrile based on m-xylene were 86.5 mol% when using the
water-free mixed gas, and 86.1 mol% when using the water-containing mixed
gas. After the heat load of 450°C x 300 hours, the fluid catalytic
ammoxidation was repeated at 420°C. As a result, the yields of 
isophthalonitrile based on m-xylene were 86.1 mol% for the water-free mixed
gas, and 85.8 mol% for the water-containing mixed gas. As seen from the
results, isophthalonitrile was stably produced in high yields with little
lowering with time even when the mixed gas contained water.</p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0035">The same procedures of the activity test as in Example 1 were repeated
using the supported catalyst prepared in Example 1 except that 3-methylpyridine
was used instead of m-xylene. Specifically, a water-free
mixed gas comprising 2.6% by volume of 3-methylpyridine, 11.5% by volume of
ammonia and 85.9% by volume of air, or a mixed gas further containing, in
addition to the above components, water in an amount of 19.0% by volume
based on ammonia, was introduced into the reactor, and the fluid catalytic
ammoxidation was carried out at 390°C at which the maximum yield of 3-cyanopyridine
was attained and at a hourly space velocity (SV) of 810 hr<sup>-1</sup>.
The yield of 3-cyanopyridine based on 3-methylpyridine was 89.5 mol% when
using the water-free mixed gas, and 89.3 mol% when using the water-containing
mixed gas. After the heat load of 450°C x 300 hours, the
ammoxidation was repeated at 390°C. The yield of 3-cyanopyridine based on
3-methylpyridine was 89.3 mol% when using the water-free mixed gas, and
89.0 mol% when using the water-containing mixed gas. As seen from the
results, 3-cyanopyridine was stably produced in high yields with little lowering
with time even when the mixed gas contained water.</p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="0036">The same procedures of the activity test as in Example 1 were repeated
using the supported catalyst prepared in Example 1 except that the fluid
catalytic ammoxidation was conducted at 410°C and p-xylene was used
instead of m-xylene. The yield of terephthalonitrile based on p-xylene was
88.3 mol% when using the water-free mixed gas, and 88.0 mol% when using
the water-containing mixed gas. After the heat load of 450°C x 300 hours, the
reaction was repeated at 410°C. The yield of terephthalonitrile based on p-xylene 
was 87.8 mol% when using the water-free mixed gas, and 87.4 mol%
when using the water-containing mixed gas. As seen from the results,
terephthalonitrile was stably produced in high yields with little lowering with
time even when the mixed gas contained water.</p><heading>Example 4</heading><heading>(Preparation of catalyst)</heading><p num="0037">A mixture of 700 ml of concentrated nitric acid and 900 ml of water was
heated to 50 to 60°C, and then, 92 g of electrolytic iron was dissolved therein
little by little. The solution was further added with 1,460 g of 20wt.%
aqueous silica sol (containing 0.02% by weight of Na<sub>2</sub>O) to obtain a slurry, to
which 359 g of diantimony trioxide (Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>), 19 g of phosphoric acid (H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>)
and a solution of 2.53 g of potassium acetate (CH<sub>3</sub>COOK) in 100 ml of water
were dissolved under mixing. After adjusting the pH to 2 by 15% aqueous
ammonia, the resultant slurry mixture was aged at 100°C for 3 hours. The
slurry was further mixed with a chromium solution of 33 g of chromium
nitrate nonahydrate (Cr(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>·9H<sub>2</sub>O) in 400 ml of water. Separately, a
mixture of 60 g of vanadium pentoxide (V<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) and 130 ml of water was heated
to 80 to 90°C, and then, 125 g of oxalic acid were dissolved therein under
vigorous stirring, thereby preparing a vanadyl oxalate solution. The vanadyl
oxalate solution was mixed with the slurry under vigorous stirring to prepare
a catalyst slurry, which was then spray-dried while maintaining an inlet
temperature at 250°C and an outlet temperature at 130°C. The spray-dried
catalyst was further dried in a dryer at 130°C for 12 hours, pre-calcined at
400°C for 0.5 hour, and then calcined under air flow at 800°C for 8 hours.
The resultant supported catalyst had an alkali metal content of 0.21% by
weight, an atomic ratio of Fe : Sb :V :Cr :P :Na : K = 1:0.7 :0.4 :0.25 : 0.77 :
0.011: 0.031 and a catalyst concentration of 50% by weight.</p><heading>(Test of catalyst strength)</heading><p num="0038">The same procedures of the strength test as in Example 1 were repeated
on the supported catalyst prepared above. The supported catalyst was 
fluidized for 20 hours. As a result, the amount of the worn-out catalyst
particles scattered into the collecting thimble was 2.6% by weight based on the
charged amount. This shows that the supported catalyst had a mechanical
strength sufficient for practical use.</p><heading>(Test of catalytic activity)</heading><p num="0039">The same procedures of the activity test as in Example 1 were repeated
except that the fluid catalytic ammoxidation was performed at 440°C using the
above supported catalyst. The yield of isophthalonitrile based on m-xylene
was 78.5 mol% when using the water-free mixed gas, and 77.5 mol% when
using the water-containing mixed gas. After the heat load of 450°C x 300
hours, the reaction was repeated at 440°C. The yield of isophthalonitrile
based on m-xylene was 78.4 mol% when using the water-free mixed gas, and
77.5 mol% when using the water-containing mixed gas. As seen from the
results, isophthalonitrile was stably produced in high yields with little
lowering with time even when the mixed gas contained water.</p><heading>Comparative Example 1</heading><heading>(Preparation of catalyst)</heading><p num="0040">The same procedures for the preparation of catalyst as in Example 1
were repeated except that 3.0 g of potassium acetate (CH<sub>3</sub>COOK) were used.
The resultant supported catalyst had an alkali metal content of 0.48% by
weight, an atomic ratio of V : Cr : B : Mo: P : Na : K= 1 : 1: 0.5 : 0.086 :
0.007 : 0.064 : 0.012, and a catalyst concentration of 50% by weight.</p><heading>(Test of catalyst strength)</heading><p num="0041">The same procedures of the strength test as in Example 1 were repeated
on the above supported catalyst. The supported catalyst was fluidized for 20
hours. As a result, the amount of the worn-out catalyst particle <u style="single">scattered</u>
into the collecting thimble was 1.7% by weight based on the charged amount.
This shows that the supported catalyst had a mechanical strength sufficient
for practical use.</p><heading>(Test of catalytic activity)</heading><p num="0042">The same procedures of the activity test as in Example 1 were repeated
except that the fluid catalytic ammoxidation was performed at 420°C using the
above supported catalyst. The yield of isophthalonitrile based on m-xylene
was 86.9 mol% when using the water-free mixed gas, and 86.8 mol% when
using the water-containing mixed gas. After the heat load of 450°C x 300
hours, the reaction was repeated at 420°C. As a result, the yield of
isophthalonitrile based on m-xylene was 86.6 mol% when using the water-free
mixed gas, and 80.7 mol% when using the water-containing mixed gas. As
seen from the results, isophthalonitrile was stably produced in high yields
with little lowering with time even when the mixed gas contained water.</p><heading>Comparative Example 2</heading><heading>(Preparation of catalyst)</heading><p num="0043">The same procedures for the preparation of catalyst as in Example 1
were repeated except that no potassium acetate (CH<sub>3</sub>COOK) was used. The
resultant supported catalyst had an alkali metal content of 0.04% by weight,
an atomic ratio of V : Cr: B: Mo: P: Na = 1:1 :0.5 : 0.1: 0.086: 0.004, and a
catalyst concentration of 50% by weight.</p><heading>(Test of catalyst strength)</heading><p num="0044">The same procedures of the strength test as in Example 1 were repeated
on the above supported catalyst. The supported catalyst was fluidized for 20
hours. As a result, the amount of the worn-out catalyst particles scattered.
into the collecting thimble was 7.8% by weight based on the charged amount.
This indicates that the supported catalyst had a poor strength and not suitable
for practical use.</p><heading>Comparative Example 3</heading><p num="0045">In the same manner as in Example 2, the fluid catalytic ammoxidation
was repeated at 390°C except that 3-methylpyridine was used instead of m-xylene
using the supported catalyst prepared in Comparative Example 1.
The yield of 3-cyanopyridine based on 3-methylpyridine was 89.8 mol% when
using the water-free mixed gas, and 89.5 mol% when using the water-containing 
mixed gas. After the heat load of 450°C x 300 hours, the reaction
was repeated at 390°C. As a result, the yield of 3-cyanopyridine based on 3-methylpyridine
was 89.7 mol% when using the water-free mixed gas. The
yield when using the water-containing mixed gas drastically lowered to 80.2
mol%. As seen from the results, the comparative catalyst failed to stably
produce 3-methylpyridine due to significant lowering with time of the yield.</p><heading>Comparative Example 4</heading><heading>(Preparation of catalyst)</heading><p num="0046">The same procedures for the preparation of catalyst as in Example 4
were repeated except that 6.49 g of potassium acetate (CH<sub>3</sub>COOK) was used.
The resultant supported catalyst had an alkali metal content of 0.48% by
weight, an atomic ratio of Fe : Sb : V : Cr : B : Na : K = 1 : 1.5 : 0.4 : 0.5: 0.77 :
0.011 0.081, and a catalyst concentration of 50% by weight.</p><heading>(Test of catalyst strength)</heading><p num="0047">The same procedures of the strength test as in Example 1 were repeated
on the above supported catalyst. The supported catalyst was fluidized for 20
hours. As a result, the amount of the worn-out catalyst scattered into the
collecting thimble was 2.4% by weight based on the charged amount. This
indicates that the supported catalyst had a mechanical strength sufficient for
practical use.</p><heading>(Test of catalytic activity)</heading><p num="0048">The same procedures of the activity test as in Example 1 were repeated
except that the fluid catalytic ammoxidation was performed at 440°C using the
above supported catalyst. The yield of isophthalonitrile based on m-xylene
was 79.1 mol% when using the water-free mixed gas, and 78.0 mol% when
using the water-containing mixed gas. After the heat load of 450°C x 300
hours, the reaction was repeated at 440°C. As a result, the yield of
isophthalonitrile based on m-xylene was 78.5 mol% when using the water-free
mixed gas. The yield when using the water-containing mixed gas drastically
lowered to 72.4 mol%. As seen from the results, the comparative catalyst 
failed to stably produce isophthalonitrile due to significant lowering with time
of the yield.</p><heading>Comparative Example 5</heading><heading>(Preparation of catalyst)</heading><p num="0049">The same procedures for the preparation of catalyst as in Example 1
were repeated except that no potassium acetate (CH<sub>3</sub>COOK) was used. The
resultant supported catalyst had an alkali metal content of 0.04% by weight,
an atomic ratio of Fe : Sb : V : Cr : B : Na = 1 : 1.5: 0.4 : 0.5 : 0.77 : 0.011, and
a catalyst concentration of 50% by weight.</p><heading>(Test of catalyst strength)</heading><p num="0050">The same procedures of the strength test as in Example 4 were repeated
on the above supported catalyst. The supported catalyst was fluidized for 20
hours. As a result, the amount of the worn-out catalyst scattered into the
collecting thimble was as large as 9.2% by weight based on the charged
amount. This indicates that the mechanical strength of the supported
catalyst was so poor for practical use.</p><p num="0051">As is apparent from the above examples, the catalyst containing a
specific amount of alkali metal enables the stable production of aromatic
nitriles or heterocyclic nitriles in high yields with little change with time by
vapor-phase fluid catalytic ammoxidation of carbocyclic or heterocyclic
compounds, because the catalytic activity is not deteriorated by water in the
recycled unreacted ammonia recovered from the reaction product gas.</p><p num="0052">Accordingly, aromatic nitriles or heterocyclic nitriles are produced in
industrially advantageous manner. Thus, the present invention has a large
industrial value.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process for producing an aromatic or heterocyclic nitrile, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>subjecting a carbocycic or heterocyclic compound, ammonia and an
oxygen-containing gas to fluid catalytic reaction in vapor phase in the presence
of a catalyst containing 0.1 to 0.4% by weight of alkali metal to produce the
aromatic or heterocyclic nitrile; and</claim-text><claim-text>recycling unreacted ammonia recovered from a reaction product gas
from the fluid catalytic reaction in vapor phase.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The process according to claim 1, wherein the catalyst further contains
at least one oxide selected from the group consisting of oxides of V, Mo and Fe.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The process according to claim 2, wherein the catalyst further contains
at least one oxide selected from the group consisting of oxides of Mg, Ca, Ba,
La, Ti, Zr, Cr, W, Co, Ni, B, Al, Ge, Sn, Pb, P, Sb and Bi.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The process according to claim 3, wherein the catalyst is supported on
silica.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The process according to claim 1, wherein the fluid catalytic reaction in
vapor phase is carried out in the presence of a supported catalyst comprising
silica supporting a catalyst containing the alkali metal and oxides of V, Cr, B,
Mo and P.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The process according to claim 1, wherein the alkali metal is Na and/or
K.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The process according to claim 1, wherein the carbocyclic compound has
a carbon ring substituted by at least one nitrile-forming group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The process according to claim 7, wherein the nitrile-forming group is
selected from the group consisting of methyl, ethyl, propyl, formyl, acetyl,
hydroxymethyl and methoxycarbonyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The process according to claim 1, wherein the heterocyclic compound
has a hetero ring substituted by at least one nitrile-forming group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The process according to claim 9, wherein the nitrile-forming group is
selected from the group consisting of methyl, ethyl, propyl, formyl, acetyl,
hydroxymethyl and methoxycarbonyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The process according to claim 3, wherein the oxide component of the
catalyst is represented by the following formula:
(V)a(Mo)b(Fe)c(X)d(Y)e(O)f
wherein X is at least one element selected from the group consisting of Mg, Ca,
Ba, La, Ti, Zr, Cr, W, Co and Ni; Y is at least one element selected from the
group consisting of B, Al, Ge, Sn, Pb, P, Sb and Bi; and subscripts a, b, c, d, e
and f represent atomic proportions, a being 0.01 to 1; b being 0.01 to 1; c being
0 to 1; d being 0 to 1; e being 0 to 1 and f being the number of oxide-forming
oxygen atoms.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>