<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2005059300-A1" country="WO" doc-number="2005059300" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34678211" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20050630"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2005059300-A1" status="new" fvid="79075097"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2005059300</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050630</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="GB-2004004888-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2004004888</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20041119</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-74162503-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>74162503</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031219</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>E21B  33/13</main-classification><further-classification>C04B  28/02</further-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/42        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/467       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  28/02A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/467</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">FOAMED FLY ASH CEMENT COMPOSITIONS AND METHODS OF CEMENTING</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">COMPOSITIONS DE CIMENT DE CENDRES LEGERES EN MOUSSE ET PROCEDES DE CIMENTATION</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0611081-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0611081</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0779467-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0779467</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-20020050231-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20020050231</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4466833-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4466833</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6063738-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6063738</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6332921-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6332921</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BALCER BRENT P</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BRENNEIS DARRELL CHAD</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHATTERJI JITEN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CROMWELL ROGER S</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>EVERETT DON M</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERV INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KING BOBBY J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PEISER BARRY L</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WAIN CHRISTOPHER PAUL</name><address><country>GB</country></address> </addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BALCER, BRENT, P.</name></addressbook></applicant> <applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BRENNEIS, DARRELL, CHAD</name> </addressbook> </applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHATTERJI, JITEN</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CROMWELL, ROGER, S.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>EVERETT, DON, M.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERVICES, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KING, BOBBY, J.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PEISER, BARRY, L.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WAIN, CHRISTOPHER, PAUL</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>BALCER BRENT P</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>BRENNEIS DARRELL CHAD</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHATTERJI JITEN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CROMWELL ROGER S</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>EVERETT DON M</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KING BOBBY J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PEISER BARRY L</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BALCER, BRENT, P.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BRENNEIS, DARRELL, CHAD</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHATTERJI, JITEN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CROMWELL, ROGER, S.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>EVERETT, DON, M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KING, BOBBY, J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PEISER, BARRY, L.</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Methods of cementing and low density foamed cement compositions therefor are disclosed. A low density foamed cement composition of the invention comprises fly ash comprising calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foamed cement composition, and sufficient gas to foam the foamed cement composition.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>L'invention concerne des procédés de cimentation et des compositions de ciment en mousse basse densité. Cette composition contient des cendres légères composées d'oxyde de calcium ou d'hydroxyde de calcium, de l'eau en quantité suffisante pour créer une pâte liquide, un tensioactif de moussage et de stabilisation de mousse ou un mélange de tensioactifs en quantité suffisante pour faciliter la formation de mousse et stabiliser cette composition de ciment en mousse, et suffisamment de gaz pour faire mousser cette composition.</p></abstract><description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="2"/>--><p num="p0001"> FOAMED FLY ASH CEMENT COMPOSITIONS AND METHODS OF CEMENTING Background of the Invention</p><p num="p0002">1. Field of the Invention. The present invention relates generally to methods of cementing and low density foamed fly ash cement compositions.</p><p num="p0003">2. Description of the Prior Art. In general cementing operations wherein hard substantially impermeable cementitious masses are formed in desired locations, hydraulic cement compositions have heretofore been utilized which contain hydraulic cements such as Portland cements, gypsum cements, silica cements and the like along with water and other additives. In primary well cementing, i.e., the forming of a cement sheath in the annular space between pipe disposed in a well bore and the walls of the well bore, a pumpable hydraulic cement composition is introduced into the annular space and the cement composition is permitted to set therein. The resulting cement sheath provides physical support and positioning to the pipe in the well bore and prevents undesirable fluid migration between subterranean zones and formations penetrated by the well bore.</p><p num="p0004">In some locations, the subterranean zones or formations into or through which wells are drilled have high permeabilities and low compressive and tensile strengths. As a result, the resistances of the zones or formations to shear are low and they have low fracture gradients. When a well fluid such as a hydraulic cement composition is introduced into the well bore penetrating such a subterranean zone or formation, the hydrostatic pressure exerted on the walls of the well bore can exceed the fracture gradient of the zone or formation and cause fractures to be formed in the zone or formation into which the cement composition is lost.</p><p num="p0005">While lightweight cement compositions have been developed and used heretofore, subterranean zones or formations are still encountered which have fracture gradients too low for even the lightweight cement compositions to be utilized without fracturing the formation and the occurrence of loss circulation problems. Also, the lightweight cement compositions utilized heretofore have often not had sufficient compressive, tensile and bond strengths upon setting. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>-->
 Thus, there are continuing needs for improved low density cement compositions for use in general cementing as well as in cementing in subterranean zones or formations having very low fracture gradients. Summary of the Invention The present invention provides methods of cementing and low density cement compositions which meet the needs described above and overcome the deficiencies of the prior art. The methods of this invention for cementing in subterranean zones which readily fracture at low hydrostatic pressures are comprised of the following steps. A low density foamed cement composition is prepared or provided comprising fly ash comprising calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foamed cement composition, and sufficient gas to form the cement composition. Thereafter, the cement composition is placed in the zone and allowed to set therein. The methods of the present invention used in general cementing comprise the following steps. A low density foamed cement composition is placed into a zone to be cemented, the foam cement composition comprising fly ash comprising calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foam cement composition, and sufficient gas to foam the cement composition. Thereafter, the foam cement composition is allowed to set in the zone. The low density foamed cement compositions of this invention comprise fly ash comprising calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foamed cement composition, and sufficient gas to foam the cement composition. The objects, features and advantages of the present invention will be readily apparent to those skilled in the art upon a reading of the description of preferred embodiments which follows. Description of Preferred Embodiments Improved methods of cementing in subterranean zones which readily fracture at low hydrostatic pressures are provided by the present invention. The methods basically comprise 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
the following steps. A low density foamed cement composition is prepared or provided comprising fly ash mixed with calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foamed cement composition, and sufficient gas to foam the cement composition. Thereafter, the foamed cement composition is placed in the zone and the foamed cement composition is allowed to set therein. Because the foamed cement composition of this invention has a low density, i.e., a density such that the hydrostatic pressure of the cement composition exerted in the subterranean zone is less than the fracture gradient of the subterranean zone, fracturing of the zone does not take place. Fly ash is the finely divided residue that results from the combustion of ground or powdered coal and it is carried by the flue gases generated. Fly ash is a mixture of alumina, silica, unburned carbon and various metallic oxides. While various forms of fly ash can be utilized, mixed with calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide, ASTM Class C or ASTM Class F fly ashes are preferred with ASTM Class F being the most preferred. Class C fly ash generally contains a stoichiometric amount of calcium oxide (lime). Class F fly ash does not contain calcium oxide (lime) or calcium hydroxide (hydrated lime) and in order for the Class F fly ash to function as a cement, a stoichiometric amount of calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide is mixed with the Class F fly ash. That is, when Class F fly ash is mixed with calcium oxide, the mixture comprises 90% (74 lb/sk) Class F fly ash and 10% (8.32 lb/sk) calcium oxide by weight of the mixture. When the Class F fly ash is mixed with calcium hydroxide, the mixture comprises 87% (74 lb/sk) Class F fly ash and 13% (11 lb/sk) calcium hydroxide by weight of the mixture. The Class C fly ash containing calcium oxide or the Class F fly ash mixed with calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide are generally present in the low density foamed cement composition of this invention in an amount of about 87% by weight of the cement composition. The calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide can be naturally present or can be mixed with the fly ash and are generally present in an amount in the range of from about 10% to about 25% by weight of the cement composition. In an exemplary embodiment, the fly ash comprises calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide in an amount in the range of from about 12% to about 18% by weight of the cement composition. In another embodiment, the fly ash comprises calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide in an amount of 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
about 15% by weight of the cement composition. The water in the foamed cement composition can be fresh water or salt water and the water is mixed with the fly ash and calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, i.e., the water is present in an amount in the range of from about 39% to about 68% by weight of the fly ash present in the composition. While various foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants can be utilized in accordance with this invention, a particularly suitable such surfactant comprises a mixture of an ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate present in the mixture in an amount of about 63.3 parts by weight, cocoylamidopropylbetaine present in the mixture in an amount of about 31.7 parts by weight and cocoylamidopropyldimethylamine oxide present in the mixture in an amount of about 5 parts by weight. This surfactant mixture is described in detail in United States Patent No. 6,063,738 issued to Chatteπi et al. on May 16, 2000, which is incorporated herein by reference thereto. The surfactant mixture is commercially available from Halliburton Energy Services, Inc. of Duncan, Oklahoma, under the trade designation "ZONESEALANT 2000™." The foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant utilized is generally present in the cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 0.8% to about 5% by volume of water in the composition, preferably in an amount of about 2%. Other foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants are available and can be utilized in accordance with the present invention. Mixtures of other suitable surfactants are described in U.S. Pat. Nos. 6,210,476; 5,897,699; 5,875,845; 5,820,670; 5,711,801; and 5,588,489; the relevant disclosures of which are incorporated herein by reference. For example, suitable foaming surfactant are commercially available from Halliburton Energy Services of Duncan, Okla., under the trade designations CFA-S™, HALLIBURTON FOAM ADDITIVE™, AQF- 1™, AQF-2™, and HOWCO-SUDS™. Suitable foam stabilizing agents are commercially available from Halliburton Energy Services under the trade designations HALLIBURTON FOAM STABILIZER™ and HC-2™. The gas utilized to foam the cement composition can be air or nitrogen with nitrogen being preferred. The gas is generally present in the foamed cement composition in an amount sufficient to foam the cement composition, i.e., in an amount in the range of from about 20% to about 80% by volume of the fly ash, lime or hydrated lime and water slurry formed. A preferred method of general cementing utilizing a foamed cement composition of 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
this invention is as follows. A low density foamed cement composition is placed into a zone to be cemented. The foamed cement composition comprises fly ash mixed with calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foamed cement composition, and sufficient gas to foam the foamed cement composition. After being placed, the foamed cement composition is allowed to set in the zone. A preferred method of this invention for cementing in a subterranean zone which fractures at low hydrostatic pressures comprises the steps of: (a) preparing or providing a low density foamed cement composition comprising fly ash mixed with calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foamed cement composition, and sufficient gas to foam the cement composition; (b) placing the foamed cement composition in the zone; and (c) allowing the foamed cement composition to set therein. A preferred method of general cementing on the surface or otherwise comprises: (a) placing a low density foamed cement composition into a zone to be cemented, the foamed cement composition comprising fly ash mixed with calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foamed cement composition, and sufficient gas to foam the cement composition; and (b) allowing the foamed cement composition to set in the zone. A low density foamed cement composition of this invention comprises: fly ash mixed with calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide; water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry; a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foamed cement composition; and sufficient gas to foam the foamed cement composition. As it will be understood by those skilled in the art, the foamed cement compositions of this invention can include various additives to bring about desired results such as accelerators, set retarders, fluid loss additives, and the like. In order to further illustrate the methods and low density foamed cement compositions of this invention, the following examples are given. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
 EXAMPLE 1 A cement slurry having a density of 13.64 pounds per gallon was prepared by mixing 57.3% (74/lb/sk) Class F fly ash, 8.5% (11 lb/sk) hydrated lime and 34.2% (5.3 gal/sk) water by weight of the cement slurry. A portion of the slurry was cured at 140°F for 24 hours after which the cured cement was tested for compressive strength, tensile strength and shear bond- Anhydrous calcium chloride was added to two additional portions of the slurry in amounts of 2% by weight and 4% by weight, respectively. Those two slurries were also cured at 140°F for 24 hours and had thickening times of 2 hours and 30 minutes and 2 hours and 24 minutes respectively. The results of these tests are set forth in Table I below.</p><p num="p0006">TABLE I 74 lb/sk Class F Fly Ash +11 lb/sk Hydrated Lime @ 13.64 lb/gal (Cured at 140°F for 24 hours)</p><p num="p0007"><img id="imgf000007_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000007_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="31"/></p><p num="p0008">From Table I, it can be seen that the three cured slurries exhibited similar properties.</p><p num="p0009">EXAMPLE 2 An additional portion of the cement slurry of Example 1 having a density of 13.64 pounds er gallon was rni?.ed wi a foaming and foam, stabilizing sμrfgft nt mixture in an amount of 1.5% by volume of water (b.v.o.w.). Portions of the slurry were foamed with air at ambient temperature and pressure to foamed densities of 10, 11 and 12 pounds per gallon. The resulting foamed slurries were cured at 140°F for 24 hours and then tested for compressive strength, tensile strength and shear bond. The thickening time of one of the foamed cement slurries was also determined. The results of these tests are shown in Table II. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>-->
 TABLE II 74 lb/sk Class F Fly Ash 11 lb/sk Hydrated Lime + 1.5% "ZONESEALANT 2000™'<sup>:</sup> (b.v.o.w.) +5.3 gal/sk Water @13.64 lb/gal (Cured at 140°F for 24 hours)</p><p num="p0010"><img id="imgf000008_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000008_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="32"/></p><p num="p0011">From Table II, it can be seen that the cured foamed slurries had similar compressive strengths, tensile strengths and shear bond.</p><p num="p0012">EXAMPLE 3 The tests described above in Example 2 were repeated except that the slurries each included 2% calcium chloride. The results of these tests are shown in Table III below.</p><p num="p0013">TABLE III 74 lb/sk Class F Fly Ash + 11 lb/sk Hydrated Lime + 2.0% CaCl<sub>2</sub> by Wt. of Fly Ash + 1.5% "ZONESEALANT2000™" (b.v.o.w.) + 5.35 gal/sk Water @ 13.64 lb/gal (Cured at 140°F for 24 hours)</p><p num="p0014"><img id="imgf000008_0002" orientation="portrait" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000008_0002.tif" inline="yes" he="31"/></p><p num="p0015">From Table III, it can be seen that the presence of anhydrous calcium chloride brought about an increase in compressive strength, tensile strength and shear bond. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>-->
 EXAMPLE 4 The tests described in Example 3 were repeated except that 4.0% anhydrous calcium chloride by weight of fly ash and hydrated lime was included in each test cement slurry. The results of these tests are shown in Table IV below.</p><p num="p0016">TABLE IV 74 lb/sk Class F Fly Ash + 11 lb/sk Hydrated Lime + 4.0% CaCl<sub>2</sub> by Wt. of Fly Ash + 1.5% "ZONESEALANT2000™" (b.v.o.w.) + 5.35 gal/sk Water @ 13.64 lb/gal (Cured at 140°F for 24 hours)</p><p num="p0017"><img id="imgf000009_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000009_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="31"/></p><p num="p0018">From Table IV, it can be seen that the compressive strength, tensile strength and shear bond were less than those obtained in Example 3.</p><p num="p0019">EXAMPLE 5 A cement slurry containing the same components and amount as those prepared in Example 3 was foamed to 11 pounds per gallon at 175°F and 1,000 psi pressure. The foamed slurry was cured at 200°F for 48 hours and then was tested for compressive strength. The results of the tests set forth in Table V show the compressive strengths of the cured foamed slurry and that the variation in cured slurry density was no more than plus or minus one pound per gallon. The foam was generated under temperature and pressure using the multiple analysis cement slurry analyzer (MACS), a complete description of which is given in United States Patent No. 6,227,294 incorporated herein by reference thereto. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="10"/>-->
 TABLE V 74 lb/sk Class F Fly Ash + 11 lb/sk Hydrated Lime + 2.0% CaCl<sub>2</sub> by Wt. of Fly Ash + 1.5% "ZONESEALANT 2000™" (b.v.o.w.) + 5.35 gal/sk Water @13.64 lb/gal: Foamed to 11.0 lb/gal and Cured at 200°F</p><p num="p0020"><img id="imgf000010_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000010_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="36"/></p><p num="p0021">The results given in Tables I-V show that the foamed fly ash cement slurries have excellent properties for cementing subterranean zones penetrated by a well bores and for general surface cementing.</p><p num="p0022">Thus, the present invention is well adapted to attain the objects and advantages mentioned as well as those which are inherent therein. While numerous changes may be made by those skilled in the art, such changes are encompassed within the spirit of this invention as defined by the appended claims. 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="11"/>--><claim-text/><claim-text>What is claimed is:</claim-text><claim-text>1. A method of cementing in a subterranean zone comprising: preparing or providing a low density foamed cement composition comprising fly ash comprising calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate form and stabilize the foamed cement composition, and sufficient gas to foam the foamed cement composition; placing the foamed cement composition in the zone; and allowing the foamed cement composition to set therein. 2. The method of claim 1 wherein the fly ash is selected from the group consisting of Class C fly ash and Class F fly ash. 3. The method of claim 1 wherein the fly ash is Class C fly ash. 4. The method of claim 1 wherein the fly ash is Class C fly ash containing calcium oxide. 5. The method of claim 1 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash. 6. The method of claim 1 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash mixed with calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide. 7. The method of claim 1 wherein the fly ash comprises calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide and is present in the foamed composition in an amount of about 87% by weight of the composition. 8. The method of claim 1 wherein the calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide are generally present in an amount in the range of from about 10% to about 25% by weight of the cement composition. 9. The method of claim 1 wherein the calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide are generally present in an amount of about 15% by weight of the cement composition. 10. The method of claim 1 wherein the water in the foamed cement composition is selected from the group consisting of fresh water and salt water. 11. The method of claim 1 wherein the water is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 39% to about 68% by weight of the fly ash in the composition. 12. The method of claim 1 wherein the foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant comprises a mixture of an ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate present in the mixture in an 
<!-- EPO <DP n="12"/>-->
amount of about 63.3 parts by weight, cocoylamidepropylbetaine present in the mixture in an amount of about 31.7 parts by weight and cocoylamidopropyldimethylamine oxide present in the mixture in an amount of about 5 parts by weight. 13. The method of claim 1 wherein the foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 0 8% to about 5% by volume of water in the composition. 14. The method of claim 1 wherein the gas is selected from the group consisting of air and nitrogen and is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 20% to about 80% by volume of the slurry. 15. A method of cementing comprising: placing a low density foamed cement composition into a subterranean zone to be cemented, the foamed cement composition comprising fly ash comprising calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foamed cement composition, and sufficient gas to foam the foamed cement composition; and allowing the foamed cement composition to set in the zone. 16. The method of claim 15 wherein the fly ash is selected from the group consisting of Class C fly ash and Class F fly ash. 17. The method of claim 15 wherein the fly ash is Class C fly ash. 18. The method of claim 15 wherein the fly ash is Class C fly ash containing calcium oxide. 19. The method of claim 15 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash. 20. The method of claim 15 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash mixed with calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide. 21. The method of claim 15 wherein the fly ash comprises calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide and is present in the foamed composition in an amount of about 87% by weight of the composition. 22. The method of claim 15 wherein the calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide are generally present in an amount in the range of from about 10% to about 25% by weight of the cement composition. 23. The method of claim 15 wherein the calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide are 
<!-- EPO <DP n="13"/>-->
generally present in an amount of about 15% by weight of the cement composition. 24. The method of claim 15 wherein the water in the foamed cement composition is selected from the group consisting of fresh water and salt water. 25. The method of claim 15 wherein the water is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 39% to about 68% by weight of the fly ash in the composition. 26. The method of claim 15 wherein the foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant comprises a mixture of an ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate present in the mixture in an amount of about 63.3 parts by weight, cocoylamidepropylbetaine present in the mixture in an amount of about 31.7 parts by weight and cocoylamidopropyldimethylamine oxide present in the mixture an amount of about 5 parts by weight. 27. The method of claim 15 wherein the foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 0.8% to about 5% by volume of water in the composition. 28. The method of claim 15 wherein the gas is selected from the group consisting of air and nitrogen and is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 20% to about 80% by volume of the slurry. 29. A foamed cement composition comprising: fly ash comprising calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide; water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry; a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foamed cement composition; and sufficient gas to foam the foamed cement composition. 30. The composition of claim 29 wherein the fly ash is selected from the group consisting of Class C fly ash and Class F fly ash. 31. The composition of claim 29 wherein the fly ash is Class C fly ash. 32. The composition of claim 29 wherein the fly ash is Class C fly ash containing calcium oxide. 33. The composition of claim 29 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash. 34. The composition of claim 29 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash mixed with calcium oxide and the mixture comprises 90% by weight Class F fly ash and 10% calcium oxide by weight of the mixture. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="14"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>35. The composition of claim 29 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash mixed with calcium hydroxide and the mixture comprises 87% Class F fly ash and 13% calcium hydroxide by weight of the mixture. 36. The composition of claim 29 wherein the fly ash comprises calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide and is present in the foamed composition in an amount of about 87% by weight of the composition. 37. The composition of claim 29 wherein the calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide are generally present in an amount in the range of from about 10% to about 25% by weight of the cement composition. 38. The composition of claim 29 wherein the calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide are generally present in an amount of about 15% by weight of the cement composition. 39. The composition of claim 29 wherein the water in the foamed cement composition is selected from the group consisting of fresh water and salt water. 40. The composition of claim 29 wherein the water is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 39% to about 68% by weight of the fly ash in the composition. 41. The composition of claim 29 wherein the foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant comprises a mixture of an ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate present in the mixture in an amount of about 63.3 parts by weight, cocoylamidepropylbetaine present in the mixture in an amount of about 31.7 parts by weight and cocoylamidopropyldimethylamine oxide present in the mixture an amount of about 5 parts by weight. 42. The foamed cement composition of claim 29 wherein the foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 0.8% to about 5% by volume of water in the composition. 43. The foamed cement composition of claim 29 wherein the gas is selected from the group consisting of air and nitrogen and is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 20% to about 80% by volume of the slurry. 44. A method of cementing in a subterranean zone comprising: preparing or providing a foamed fly ash cement composition, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry, a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate form and stabilize the foamed cement composition, and sufficient gas to foam the foamed cement composition; 
<!-- EPO <DP n="15"/>-->
 placing the foamed cement composition in the zone; and allowing the foamed cement composition to set therein. 45. The method of claim 44 wherein the composition comprises fly ash selected from the group consisting of Class C fly ash and Class F fly ash. 46. The method of claim 45 wherein the fly ash is Class C fly ash. 47. The method of claim 46 wherein the fly ash is Class C fly ash containing calcium oxide. 48. The method of claim 45 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash. 49. The method of claim 48 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash mixed with calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide. 50. The method of claim 44 wherein the foamed fly ash cement composition comprises calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide and is present in an amount of about 87% by weight of the composition. 51. The method of claim 50 wherein the calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide are generally present in an amount in the range of from about 10% to about 25% by weight of the cement composition. 52. The method of claim 50 wherein the calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide are generally present in an amount of about 15% by weight of the cement composition. 53. The method of claim 44 wherein the water in the foamed cement composition is selected from the group consisting of fresh water and salt water. 54. The method of claim 44 wherein the water is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 39% to about 68% by weight of the fly ash in the composition. 55. The method of claim 44 wherein the foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant comprises a mixture of an ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate present in the mixture in an amount of about 63.3 parts by weight, cocoylamidepropylbetaine present in the mixture in an amount of about 31.7 parts by weight and cocoylamidopropyldimethylamine oxide present in the mixture in an amount of about 5 parts by weight. 56. The method of claim 44 wherein the foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 0.8% to about 5% by volume of water in the composition. 57. The method of claim 44 wherein the gas is selected from the group consisting 
<!-- EPO <DP n="16"/>-->
of air and nitrogen and is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 20% to about 80% by volume of the slurry. 58. A foamed fly ash cementing composition comprising: a settable fly ash; water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry; a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant or a mixture of surfactants present in an amount sufficient to facilitate foam and stabilize the foamed cement composition; and sufficient gas to foam the foamed cement composition. 59. The composition of claim 58 wherein the fly ash is selected from the group consisting of Class C fly ash and Class F fly ash. 60. The composition of claim 58 wherein the fly ash is Class C fly ash. 61. The composition of claim 58 wherein the fly ash is Class C fly ash containing calcium oxide. 62. The composition of claim 58 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash. 63. The composition of claim 58 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash mixed with calcium oxide and the mixture comprises 90% by weight Class F fly ash and 10% calcium oxide by weight of the mixture. 64. The composition of claim 58 wherein the fly ash is Class F fly ash mixed with calcium hydroxide and the mixture comprises 87% Class F fly ash and 13% calcium hydroxide by weight of the mixture. 65. The composition of claim 58 wherein the fly ash comprises calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide and is present in the composition in an amount of about 87% by weight of the composition. 66. The composition of claim 65 wherein the calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide are generally present in an amount in the range of from about 10% to about 25% by weight of the composition. 67. The composition of claim 65 wherein the calcium oxide or calcium hydroxide are generally present in an amount of about 15% by weight of the cement composition. 68. The composition of claim 58 wherein the water in the foamed cement composition is selected from the group consisting of fresh water and salt water. 69. The composition of claim 58 wherein the water is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 39% to about 68% by weight of 
<!-- EPO <DP n="17"/>-->
the fly ash in the composition. 70. The composition of claim 58 wherein the foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant comprises a mixture of an ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate present in the mixture in an amount of about 63.3 parts by weight, cocoylamidepropylbetaine present in the mixture in an amount of about 31.7 parts by weight and cocoylamidopropyldimethylamine oxide present in the mixture an amount of about 5 parts by weight. 71. The foamed cement composition of claim 58 wherein the foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 0.8% to about 5% by volume of water in the composition. 72. The foamed cement composition of claim 58 wherein the gas is selected from the group consisting of air and nitrogen and is present in the foamed cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 20% to about 80% by volume of the slurry. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>