<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1167426-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1167426" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="11457834" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020102"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1167426-A1" status="new" fvid="23330297"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1167426</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020102</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01114515-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01114515</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010615</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="IT-TO20000593-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>IT</country><doc-number>TO20000593</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000620</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B   7/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B   7/02        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B   7/10        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B   7/90        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29K  21/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29K 105/16        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C   1/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C   1/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/20        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/36        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/54        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/548       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  21/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  21/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08J   3/20+L21/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   3/36+L21/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/548+L21/00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung von silicahaltigen, vulkanisierbaren Kautschukzusammensetzungen zur Produktion von Laufflächen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method of preparing curable-rubber mixtures containing silica, for producing treads</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour la préparation d' une composition de caoutchouc durcissable contenant de la silice pour la fabrication de bandes de roulement</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0732362-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0732362</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0744438-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0744438</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0763558-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0763558</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0821029-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0821029</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BRIDGESTONE CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BRIDGESTONE CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BRIDGESTONE CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>10-1, Kyobashi 1-Chome, Chuo-Ku</street><city>Tokyo 104-0031</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PONTECORVO MAURO</name><address><country>IT</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PONTECORVO, MAURO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PONTECORVO, MAURO</last-name><address><street>Via Fosso Centocorvi, 16</street><city>00052 Cerveteri</city><country>IT</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Jorio, Paolo</last-name><address><street>STUDIO TORTA S.r.l., Via Viotti, 9</street><city>10121 Torino</city><country>IT</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A method of preparing curable-rubber mixtures
containing silica, for producing treads, wherein, in the
course of a first step, at least a cross-linkable
unsaturated-chain polymer base, a silica-based
reinforcing filler, and a silane bonding agent are loaded
simultaneously and mixed together inside a mixer, the
first step being stopped on reaching a temperature
ranging from 155°C to 175°C; wherein, in the course of a
second step, at least one noncuring ingredient is added
to and homogeneously dispersed in the mixture being
prepared, the second step being stopped on reaching a
temperature ranging from 145°C to 175°C; and wherein, in
the course of a third step, at least one curing agent is
added to and homogeneously dispersed in the mixture being
prepared; the third step being stopped at a temperature
below the curing temperature.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a method of
producing curable-rubber mixtures containing silica, for
producing treads.</p><p num="0002">Here and hereinafter:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>the term "silica" is intended to mean a silicon
dioxide-based reinforcing agent, silicates, and mixtures
thereof;</li><li>the term "cross-linkable unsaturated-chain polymer
base" is intended to mean any natural or synthetic
noncross-linked polymer capable of assuming all the
chemical, physical and mechanical characteristics typical
of elastomers following cross-linking (curing) with
sulfur-based systems;</li><li>the term "mixture containing silica" is intended to
mean a mixture containing reinforcing agents which
definitely comprise silica, but which may also comprise,
among other things, carbon black.</li></ul></p><p num="0003">In the tire manufacturing industry, to minimize tire
rolling resistance, carbon black, as a reinforcing 
filler, is replaced partly or fully by inorganic
reinforcing fillers, such as chalk, talc, kaolin,
bentonite, titanium dioxide, various types of silicate
and, above all, silica.</p><p num="0004">Silica poses various drawbacks by being difficult to
disperse in the polymer base, and, if dispersed poorly
within the mixture, results in a mixture with highly
variable, heterogeneous physical and mechanical
characteristics.</p><p num="0005">The reason for this lies in the presence, on silica,
of surface silanolic groups, which assist the formation
of hydrogen bonds and, hence, silica particle clusters,
and impart to the silica hydrophilic characteristics
incompatible with the hydrophobic characteristics of
rubber.</p><p num="0006">To solve the above dispersion problems, use has been
made for some time now (see, for example, EP-B-0447066)
of silane bonding agents, which prevent the formation of
hydrogen bonds by bonding with silanolic groups, and, at
the same time, chemically attach the silica to the
polymer base.</p><p num="0007">The silica-silane bonding agent reaction is a
critical passage in the preparation of mixtures
containing silica, by requiring conformance with given
temperature conditions. That is, the reaction must be
conducted at a temperature of over 140°C to permit the
reaction to take place rapidly, but below 175°C to
prevent premature curing of the mixture. Moreover, the 
silica-silane bonding agent reaction produces a byproduct
of ethyl alcohol, which, on evaporating, is
responsible, together with the water in the silica, for
the formation of porous zones seriously impairing the
dimensional stability of treads, so that a low tread
strip drawing speed must be maintained to ensure the
drawn product conforms with specifications.</p><p num="0008">In known methods of preparing mixtures containing
silica, the silica-silane bonding agent reaction is made
to occur after the polymer base has been mixed with other
normally used ingredients. That is, known methods
comprise a first mixing step, in which the polymer base
is mixed with other ingredients; and a second mixing
step, in which the mixture produced in the first step is
mixed with silica and the silane bonding agent to bring
about the silica-silane bonding agent reaction.</p><p num="0009">Alternatively, known methods provide for adding
silica to the polymer base in the first step, and the
silane bonding agent in the second step to bring about
the silica-silane bonding agent reaction.</p><p num="0010">The above methods of preparing mixtures containing
silica have several drawbacks, by failing to provide for
correct silica dispersion, and by involving severe
porosity initiating phenomena. That is, while
successfully removing part of the water in the silica,
they fail to remove the ethyl alcohol produced by the
silica-silane bonding agent reaction, and, at the same
time, have such low MOONEY scorch values as, at times, to 
impair the workability of the mixture.</p><p num="0011">Moreover, normally used methods can be extremely
time-consuming when viewed in terms of output
requirements and the number of production cycles
performed on each production unit.</p><p num="0012">It is an object of the present invention to provide
a method of preparing curable-rubber mixtures containing
silica, for producing treads - in particular, for
passenger road vehicles, and which provides for ensuring
correct silica dispersion in the polymer base and a
substantial reduction in porosity by removing ethyl
alcohol, as well as for higher MOONEY scorch values
together with greater output.</p><p num="0013">According to the present invention, there is
provided a method of preparing curable-rubber mixtures
containing silica, for producing treads, the method being
characterized by comprising at least a first step to
obtain a first mixture by simultaneously loading into a
mixer and mixing together at least a cross-linkable
unsaturated-chain polymer base, a silica-based
reinforcing filler, and a silane bonding agent; said
first step being arrested upon said first mixture
reaching a temperature ranging from 155°C to 175°C.</p><p num="0014">The method defined above preferably comprises a
second step to obtain a second mixture by adding to and
dispersing in the first mixture at least one noncuring
ingredient, said second step being arrested on reaching a
temperature ranging from 145°C to 175°C; and a third step 
to obtain a third mixture by adding to and dispersing in
the second mixture at least one curing agent, said third
step being arrested at a temperature below a curing
temperature of the third mixture.

Preferably, at least in said first step the ingredients
are mixed together in one uninterrupted mixing comprising
a first part, in which said mixer is operated at a
relatively high first mixing speed, said first part
terminating on reaching a temperature ranging from 120 to
145°C; and a second successive part, in which said mixer
is operated at a second mixing speed lower than the first
speed and such as to maintain the mixture at a
temperature ranging from 150 to 165°C.</p><p num="0015">Preferably, both said first step and said second
step comprise said first part at said first mixing speed,
and said second successive part at said second mixing
speed.</p><p num="0016">Preferably, said first mixing speed ranges from 50
to 80 rpm, whereas said second mixing speed ranges from
20 to 50 rpm; the difference between said two mixing
speeds being at least 10 rpm.</p><p num="0017">In the method defined above, part of the silica
is preferably also added in the second step.</p><p num="0018">The amount of silica added in the first step
preferably constitutes 50% to 75% by weight of the total
amount of silica used.</p><p num="0019">The method set forth above preferably comprises,
between the second and third step, a further remixing 
step, in which no ingredients are added, and which is
stopped on reaching a temperature ranging from 135°C to
175°C.</p><p num="0020">Preferably, said further remixing step comprises
said first part at said first mixing speed, and said
second successive part at said second mixing speed.</p><p num="0021">In the method defined above, a carbon black-based
reinforcing filler is preferably added in the first step.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLES</u></heading><p num="0022">The examples disclosed hereinbelow comprise three
silica-containing mixtures obtained both in accordance
with the method of the present invention and according to
the known state of the art. In particular two of the
mixtures are respectively obtained in two different ways
in accordance with the method of the present invention.</p><p num="0023">For each one of the mixtures, identical in parts and
weight, but obtained in different ways, the physical
characteristics are compared.</p><p num="0024">It should also be pointed out that, in preparing
each mixture in accordance with the known state of the
art, care was taken, at each processing step, to adopt
the same mixer fill factor as in the corresponding step
according to the teachings of the invention method, so as
to show how the advantages of the method according to the
invention derive solely from a different processing
method, as opposed to different processing conditions.</p><p num="0025">The silica-based reinforcing filler used ranges from
20 to 85 parts by weight per 100 parts of polymer base. </p><p num="0026">The amount of silane bonding agent used ranges from
1% to 20% by weight of the silica-based reinforcing
filler.</p><p num="0027">For the purposes of the invention, preferred cross-linkable
unsaturated-chain polymer bases are unsaturated-chain
polymers or copolymers obtained by polymerizing
conjugated dienes and/or aliphatic or aromatic vinyl
monomers.</p><p num="0028">More specifically, the polymer bases is selected
from the group consisting of: natural rubber, cis-1,4-polyisoprene,
cis-1,4-polyibutadiene, isobutene-isoprene
copolymers, possibly halogenated, acrylonitrile-,
butadiene-styrene and isoprene-butadiene-styrene
terpolymers, either in solution or emulsion, and
ethylene-propylene-diene terpolymers.</p><p num="0029">The above polymer bases are used singly or mixed,
depending on the characteristics to be imparted to the
finished product.</p><p num="0030">For the purposes of the invention, a silane bonding
agent has the following structural formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R3-Si-CnH2nX</st32:che>
   where:
<sl><li>R is an alkyl or alkoxy group comprising 1 to 4 carbon
atoms or one chlorine atom;</li><li>n is a whole number from 1 to 6;</li><li>x is a group selected from -Sm-Cn'H2n'-Si-R'3, where:
<sl><li>m and n' are whole numbers from 1 to 6,</li><li>R' is butadiene an alkyl or alkoxy group comprising 
1 to 4 carbon atoms or one chlorine atom.</li></sl></li></sl></p><p num="0031">In formula (I), particularly advantageous bonding
agents are bis(3-triethoxysilyl-propyl)tetrasulfide and
bis(3-triethoxysilyl-propyl)disulfide, marketed by
DEGUSSA as Si69 and Si75 respectively.</p><p num="0032">In all the examples, the term "mixer (1)" indicates
a POMINI 270-liter tangential-rotor mixer (Banbury), and
the term "mixer (2)" a HOMRICH 330-liter tangential-rotor
mixer (Banbury).</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 1 - Preparation of a curable-rubber mixture
A</u></b></heading><heading><b>(Step I)</b></heading><p num="0033">A "mixer (1)" was loaded simultaneously with 81.67
kg of S-SBR, 40.11 kg of E-SBR, 35.73 kg of carbon black,
25.28 kg of silica, 3.32 kg of silane bonding agent, and
smaller amounts of other commonly used ingredients.</p><p num="0034">The characteristics of the ingredients used were the
following:
<sl><li><b>S-SBR</b> = butadiene-styrene copolymer solution;</li><li><b>E-SBR</b> = butadiene-styrene copolymer emulsion;</li><li><b>Carbon black</b> = N115 (Cabot Corporation) type;</li><li><b>Silica</b> = ULTRASIL VN3 (Degussa) type;</li><li><b>Silane bonding agent</b> = Si75 (Degussa) type.</li></sl></p><p num="0035">"Mixer (1)" was operated at a speed of 50 rpm for
116 seconds, corresponding to attainment of a temperature
of 170°C, to obtain 190 kg of a silica-containing mixture
A'.</p><p num="0036">The above step was repeated to obtain a further 190 
kg of mixture A'.</p><heading><b>(Step II-a)</b></heading><p num="0037">Of the 380 kg of mixture A', 235.54 kg (this value
depends, as already stated, on the need to conform with a
given fill coefficient) were loaded into a "mixer (2)"
and added to 13.26 kg of silica of the above type, and to
smaller amounts of other commonly used ingredients.
"Mixer (2)" was operated at a speed of 50 rpm for 72
seconds, corresponding to attainment of a temperature of
170°C, to obtain 250 kg of a silica-containing mixture
A".</p><heading><b>(Step II-b)</b></heading><p num="0038">Mixture A'' was cooled and mixed further in a "mixer
(2)" operated at 50 rpm for 86 seconds, corresponding to
attainment of a temperature of 170°C.</p><heading><b>(Step III)</b></heading><p num="0039">After the above mixing operation, 198.73 kg of
mixture A'' were loaded into a "mixer (1)" and added to
6.27 kg of commonly used curing agents. "Mixer (1)" was
operated at 35 rpm for 98 seconds, corresponding to
attainment of a temperature of 110°C, to obtain 205 kg of
a final silica-containing mixture A, the composition of
which, expressed in parts by weight, is shown in Table I.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">SBR</entry><entry align="right">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbon black</entry><entry align="right">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silica</entry><entry align="right">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silane agent (Si75)</entry><entry align="right">3 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Wax</entry><entry align="right">1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Stearic acid</entry><entry align="right">1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Antioxidant</entry><entry align="right">1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zinc oxide</entry><entry align="right">2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Curing agents</entry><entry align="right">4</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 2 - Preparation of a curable-rubber mixture
B - (comparison: silica and bonding agent added in the
second step)</u></b></heading><heading><b>(Step I)</b></heading><p num="0040">A "mixer (1)" was loaded with 96.14 kg of S-SBR,
47.21 kg of E-SBR, 42.06 kg of carbon black, and smaller
amounts of other commonly used ingredients.</p><p num="0041">The characteristics of the ingredients used are as
indicated in Example 1.</p><p num="0042">"Mixer (1)" was operated at a speed of 50 rpm for
120 seconds, corresponding to attainment of a temperature
of 180°C, to obtain 190 kg of a nonsilica mixture B'.</p><p num="0043">The above step was repeated to obtain a further 190
kg of mixture B'.</p><heading><b>(Step II-a)</b></heading><p num="0044">Of the 380 kg of mixture B', 200.09 kg (this value
depends, as already stated, on the need to conform with a
given fill coefficient) were loaded into a "mixer (2)"
and added to 44.60 kg of silica, 4.11 kg of silane
bonding agent, and to smaller amounts of other commonly
used ingredients. The characteristics of the silica and
silane bonding agent are as indicated in Example 1. </p><p num="0045">"Mixer (2)" was operated at a speed of 50 rpm for
105 seconds, corresponding to attainment of a temperature
of 170°C, to obtain 250 kg of a silica-containing mixture
B".</p><heading><b>(Step II-b)</b></heading><p num="0046">Mixture B'' was cooled and mixed further in a "mixer
(2)" operated at 50 rpm for 73 seconds, corresponding to
attainment of a temperature of 170°C.</p><heading><b>(Step III)</b></heading><p num="0047">After the above mixing operation, 198.73 kg of
mixture B'' were loaded into a "mixer (1)" and added to
6.27 kg of commonly used curing agents, at any rate
identical to those used in Example 1.. "Mixer (1)" was
operated at 35 rpm for 87 seconds, corresponding to
attainment of a temperature of 110°C, to obtain 205 kg of
a final mixture B having the same composition as mixture
A in Table I.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 3 - Preparation of a curable-rubber mixture
C</u></b></heading><p num="0048">The method described in Example 1 was repeated, only
this time using as a polymer base a SBR/NR mixture (NR =
SMR20 type natural rubber), to obtain a silica-containing
mixture with the composition, expressed in parts by
weight, shown in Table III
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">SBR/NR</entry><entry align="right">80/20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbon black</entry><entry align="right">32</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silica</entry><entry align="right">32 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silane agent (Si75)</entry><entry align="right">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Wax</entry> <entry align="right">1.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Stearic acid</entry><entry align="right">2</entry></row> <row><entry align="left">Antioxidant</entry> <entry align="right">1</entry> </row><row><entry align="left">Zinc oxide</entry><entry align="right">2.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Curing agents</entry><entry align="right">4.1</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 4 - Preparation of a curable-rubber mixture
D</u></b></heading><p num="0049">In this example, the method used in Example 3 was
repeated with some differences: a mixer (1) for step I
and a mixer (2) for the step II-a were operated at a
variable speed, and step II-b is missing.</p><p num="0050">In particular:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>In <b>step I</b>, a mixer (1) was operated at a speed of
70 rpm up to a temperature of 130°C; at this
point, the mixer (1) was slowed down to 50 rpm up
to a temperature of 170°C. The total time of step
I was 107 seconds</li><li>In <b>step II-a</b> a mixer (2) was operated at a speed
of 50 rpm up to a temperature of 130°C; at this
point, the mixer (2) was slowed down to 30 rpm up
to a temperature of 160°C. The total time of step
II-a was 95 seconds.</li><li><b>Step II-b</b> is missing.
The amounts used were selected to obtain a mixture
having the same composition as mixture C in Example
3 and as shown in Table III.</li></ul></p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 5 - Preparation of a curable-rubber mixture</u></b><b><u style="single">E - (comparison: bonding agent added in the second step)</u></b></heading><p num="0051">The method described in Example 2 for preparing
mixture B was repeated, only this time adding silica in
the first step and the bonding agent in the second step.
The amounts used were selected to obtain a mixture having
the same composition as mixture C in Example 3 and as
shown in Table III.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 6 - Preparation of a curable-rubber mixture
F -</u></b></heading><p num="0052">The method described in Example 1 for preparing
mixture A was repeated, only this time using a SBR/NR
mixture (NR = SMR10 type natural rubber) as a polymer
base, and a Si69 (Degussa) type silane bonding agent,
which has a structural stability weaker than the silane
bonding agent referred to as Si75.

Because of this weakness of the Si69 in steps I, II-a and
II-b, the mixing temperatures reached were lower than
those described in Example 1.</p><p num="0053">In particular:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>in <b>step I</b>, a mixer (1) was operated for 90
seconds reaching a temperature of 155°C;</li><li>in <b>step II-a</b>, a mixer (2) was operated for 65
seconds reaching a temperature of 155°C; and</li><li>in <b>step II-b</b>, the mixer (2) was operated for 65
seconds reaching a temperature of 155°C.</li></ul></p><p num="0054">The other parameters (e.g. the mixing and the order
in which ingredients were added) were maintained the
same as those described in Example 1. </p><p num="0055">A silica-containing mixture was obtained with the
composition expressed in parts by weight, shown in Table
VI.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">SBR/NR</entry><entry align="right">80/20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbon black</entry><entry align="right">32</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silica</entry><entry align="right">32</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silane agent (Si69)</entry><entry align="right">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Wax</entry><entry align="right">1.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Stearic acid</entry><entry align="right">2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Antioxidant</entry><entry align="right">1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zinc oxide</entry><entry align="right">2.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Curing agents</entry><entry align="right">4.1</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 7 - Preparation of a curable-rubber mixture
G</u></b></heading><p num="0056">In this example the method used in Example 6 was
repeated with some differences: a mixer (1) for step I
and a mixer (2) for step II-b were operated at a variable
speed, all the silica amount was added in step I, and
step II-a is missing.</p><p num="0057">In particular:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>In <b>step I</b>, a mixer (1) was operated at a speed of
70 rpm up to a temperature of 130°C; at this
point, the mixer (1) was slowed down to 50 rpm up
to a temperature of 155°C. The total time of step
I was 83 seconds.</li><li><b>Step II-a</b> is missing.</li><li>In <b>step II-b</b>, a mixer (2) was operated at a speed 
of 50 rpm up to a temperature of 130°C; at this
point, the mixer (2) was slowed down to 30 rpm up
to a temperature of 155°C. The total time of step
II-a was 80 seconds.</li></ul></p><p num="0058">The mixture obtained had the same composition as
mixture C in Example 6 and as shown in Table VI.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 8 - Preparation of a curable-rubber mixture
H - (comparison: bonding agent added in the second step)</u></b></heading><p num="0059">The method described in Example 5 for preparing
mixture D was repeated, only this time using a Si69
(Degussa) type silane bonding agent. The amounts used
were selected to obtain a mixture having the same
composition as mixture F in Example 6 and as shown in
Table VI.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 9 - Laboratory test results of specimens
obtained from mixtures A, B, C, D, E, F, G and H</u></b></heading><p num="0060">Specimens were taken from each of the mixtures in
Examples 1 to 6 and tested to determine, for each
mixture, the values of a number of particularly
significant parameters.</p><p num="0061">The parameters considered were the following:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>viscosity (ML1'+4' at 130°C) and Mooney scorch at
130°C expressed in minutes, measured in accordance
with ASTM standard D1646;</li><li>physical property values (ultimate elongation,
fracture strength, M300% modulus values), measured in
accordance with ASTM standard D412C;</li><li>silica dispersion, assessed on the basis of the Payne 
effect coefficient as described in "RUBBER CHEM.
TECHNOL." (1971) by Payne and Whittaker; the Payne
effect is the difference between the elasticity
modulus (E') at 5% and the elasticity modulus (E') at
0.3%; though not shown, the elasticity moduli were
measured in accordance with ASTM standard D5992;</li><li>% porosity values measured on the drawn treads and
calculated according to the equation:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">[ (Dc - Dg) / Dc ] x 100</st32:df><sl><li>Dc = specific weight of cured specimen</li><li>Dg = specific weight of green specimen</li></sl></li></ul></p><p num="0062">The test results are shown in Table IX below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="9"><tbody><row><entry align="center">MIXTURE</entry><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">B (Comparison)</entry><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="center">D</entry><entry align="center">E (Comparison)</entry><entry align="center">F</entry><entry align="center">G</entry><entry align="center">H (Comparison)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">ML1'+4' at 130°C</entry><entry align="center">84</entry><entry align="center">82</entry><entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">56</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">51</entry></row><row><entry align="center">MOONEY SCORCH (min)</entry><entry align="center">15.9</entry><entry align="center">14.2</entry><entry align="center">13.86</entry><entry align="center">13.9</entry><entry align="center">11.59</entry><entry align="center">14.0</entry><entry align="center">14.2</entry><entry align="center">13.12</entry></row><row><entry align="center">FRACTURE STRENGTH* (MPa)</entry><entry align="center">20.5</entry><entry align="center">22.4</entry><entry align="center">21.1</entry><entry align="center">20.5</entry><entry align="center">19.7</entry><entry align="center">23.1</entry><entry align="center">23.0</entry><entry align="center">21.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">300% MODULUS<!--footnotes removed--> (MPa)</entry><entry align="center">13.73</entry><entry align="center">13.79</entry><entry align="center">12.8</entry><entry align="center">13.1</entry><entry align="center">11.8</entry><entry align="center">13.3</entry><entry align="center">13.2</entry><entry align="center">12.9</entry></row><row><entry align="center">ULTIMATE ELONGATION<!--footnotes removed--> (MPa)</entry><entry align="center">402</entry><entry align="center">433</entry><entry align="center">433</entry><entry align="center">430</entry><entry align="center">435</entry><entry align="center">469</entry><entry align="center">452</entry><entry align="center">441</entry></row><row><entry align="center">FRACTURE STRENGTH<!--footnotes removed--> (MPa)</entry><entry align="center">20.2</entry><entry align="center">20.8</entry><entry align="center">21.0</entry><entry align="center">21.0</entry><entry align="center">20.0</entry><entry align="center">20.0</entry><entry align="center">20.5</entry><entry align="center">20.6</entry></row><row><entry align="center">300% MODULUS<!--footnotes removed--> (MPa)</entry><entry align="center">15.95</entry><entry align="center">15.51</entry><entry align="center">14.30</entry><entry align="center">14.2</entry><entry align="center">13.83</entry><entry align="center">14.83</entry><entry align="center">14.6</entry><entry align="center">14.53</entry></row><row><entry align="center">ULTIMATE ELONGATION<!--footnotes removed--> (MPa)</entry><entry align="center">366</entry><entry align="center">381</entry><entry align="center">404</entry><entry align="center">406</entry><entry align="center">391</entry><entry align="center">393</entry><entry align="center">405</entry><entry align="center">388</entry></row><row><entry align="center">POROSITY (%)</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">BLISTERING</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">PAYNE COEFFICIENT</entry><entry align="center">1.07</entry><entry align="center">1.19</entry><entry align="center">1.08</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry><entry align="center">1.46</entry><entry align="center">1.76</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry><entry align="center">2.04<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0063">As shown in Table VII, with respect to the
comparison Examples, the mixtures produced using the
method according to the invention show better silica
dispersion, as deduced from the lower Payne coefficient
values, much lower porosity, and higher Mooney scorch 
times.</p><p num="0064">Another important point to note is the considerable
reduction in processing time, with respect to the
comparison mixtures, of the mixtures obtained using the
method according to the invention. In this connection, it
should be stressed that, whereas the method according to
the invention does not necessarily call for a further
remixing step (step II-b in the Examples), methods
according to the known state of the art, wherein the
silane bonding agent is added in the second step, call
for a compulsory remixing step to promote a correct
silica-silane bonding agent reaction. In particular, as
seen in examples 4 and 7, the method comprising a
variation of the mixing speed has fewer mixing steps, and
maintains the mixture viscosity at acceptable values.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method of preparing curable-rubber mixtures
containing silica, for producing treads, the method being
characterized by comprising at least a first step to
obtain a first mixture by simultaneously loading into a
mixer and mixing together at least a cross-linkable
unsaturated-chain polymer base, a silica-based
reinforcing filler, and a silane bonding agent; said
first step being stopped upon said first mixture reaching
a temperature ranging from 155°C to 175°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 1, and further
comprising a second step to obtain a second mixture by
adding to, and dispersing in, the first mixture at least
one non-curing ingredient, said second step being
arrested on reaching a temperature ranging from 145°C to
175°C; and a third step to obtain a third mixture by
adding to, and dispersing in, the second mixture at least
one curing agent; said third step being stopped at a
temperature below a curing temperature of the third
mixture.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 2, wherein at least
in said first step the ingredients are mixed together in
one uninterrupted mixing comprising a first part, in
which said mixer is operated at a relatively high first
mixing speed, said first part terminating on reaching a
temperature ranging from 120 to 145°C; and a second
successive part, in which said mixer is operated at a
second mixing speed lower than the first speed and such
as to maintain the mixture at a temperature ranging from
150 to 165°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 3, wherein both said
first step and said second step comprise said first part
at said first mixing speed, and said second successive
part at said second mixing speed.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 3 or 4, wherein said
first mixing speed ranges from 50 to 80 rpm, whereas said
second mixing speed ranges from 20 to 50 rpm; the
difference between said two mixing speeds being at least
10 rpm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method as claimed in anyone of the Claims 2 to
5, wherein part of the silica-based reinforcing filler is
also added in the second step.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 6, wherein the
amount of silica-based reinforcing filler added in the
first step constitutes 50% to 75% by weight of the total
amount of silica used.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A method as claimed in anyone of the foregoing
Claims, characterized by comprising a further remixing
step between the second and third step; said further
remixing step involving the addition of no ingredients,
and being arrested on reaching a temperature ranging from
135°C to 175°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 3 and 8, wherein
said further remixing step comprises said first part at
said first mixing speed, and said second successive part
at said second mixing speed.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the foregoing
Claims, wherein a carbon black-based reinforcing filler
is added in said first step.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the foregoing
Claims, wherein the amount of silica-based reinforcing
filler ranges from 20 to 85 parts by weight per 100 parts
of polymer base.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the foregoing
Claims, wherein the amount of silane bonding agent used
ranges from 5% to 15% by weight of the amount of silica-based
reinforcing filler.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the foregoing
Claims, wherein the cross-linkable unsaturated-chain
polymer base used is selected from the group consisting
of natural rubber, cis-1,4-polyisoprene, isobutene-isoprene
copolymers, possibly halogenated, acrylonitrile-butadiene,
butadiene-styrene and isoprene-butadiene-styrene
terpolymers, either in solution or emulsion, and
ethylene-propylene-diene terpolymers; said polymer bases
being used singly or mixed together.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A method as claimed in any one of the foregoing
Claims, wherein said silane bonding agent has the
following structural formula:
R3-Si-CnH2nX
   where:
<claim-text><claim-text>R is an alkyl or alkoxy group comprising 1 to 4 carbon
atoms or one chlorine atom;</claim-text><claim-text>n is a whole number from 1 to 6;</claim-text><claim-text>x is a group selected from -Sm-Cn'H2n'-Si-R'3, where m
and n' are whole numbers from 1 to 6, and R' is an alkyl
or alkoxy group comprising 1 to 4 carbon atoms or one
chlorine atom.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A method as claimed in Claim 14, wherein said
bonding agent is selected from the group consisting of
bis (3-triethoxysilyl-propyl)tetrasulfide and bis(3-triethoxysilyl-propyl)disulfide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A curable-rubber mixture containing silica, for
producing treads, characterized by being obtained using a
method as claimed in any one of the foregoing Claims.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A tread, characterized by being obtained from a
mixture as claimed in Claim 16.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A road vehicle tire, characterized by comprising
a tread as claimed in Claim 17.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A tire as claimed in Claim 18, wherein the tire
is a passenger road vehicle tire.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>