<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1201776-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1201776" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26603146" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020502"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1201776-A2" status="new" fvid="23454087"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1201776</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20020502</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01125422-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01125422</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011031</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000332675-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000332675</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001031</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2001126009-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2001126009</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010424</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C21D   6/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C21D   6/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C21D   9/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C21D   9/22        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  14/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  14/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  14/06        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  14/06        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C21D   6/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C21D   9/22</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  14/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  14/06F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  14/06G</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M23C14:06F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M23C14:06G</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Werkzeug zum Schneiden von Zahnrädern aus Schnellarbeitsstahl und Herstellungsverfahren</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">High speed tool steel gear cutting tool and manufacturing method thereof</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Outil à tailler les engrenages en acier à coupe rapide et procédé de sa fabrication</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-2517147-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>2517147</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0301168-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0301168</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1167551-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1167551</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="E" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6105374-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6105374</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>BARRON R F:  "CRYOGENIC TREATMENT OF TOOL STEELS" CONFERENCE MANUFACTURING STRATEGIES, XX, XX, vol. 6, 17 March 1996 (1996-03-17), pages 535-548, XP001021857</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MMC KOBELCO TOOL CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MMC KOBELCO TOOL CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MMC Kobelco Tool Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>179-1, Nishioike, Kanagasaki, Uozumicho</street><city>Akashi-shi, Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ICHIMIYA NATSUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MAEDA KOICHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>TANAKA KAZUAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TANAKA YUSUKE</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YAMADA YASUYUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ICHIMIYA, NATSUKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MAEDA, KOICHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TANAKA, KAZUAKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TANAKA, YUSUKE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YAMADA, YASUYUKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Ichimiya, Natsuki, MMC Kobelco Tool Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>179-1, Nishioke, Kanagasaki, Uozumicho</street><city>Akashi-shi, Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook> </inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Maeda, Koichi, MMC Kobelco Tool Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>179-1, Nishioke, Kanagasaki, Uozumicho</street><city>Akashi-shi, Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country> </address> </addressbook> </inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Tanaka, Kazuaki, MMC Kobelco Tool Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>179-1, Nishioke, Kanagasaki, Uozumicho</street><city>Akashi-shi, Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Tanaka, Yusuke, MMC Kobelco Tool Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>179-1, Nishioke, Kanagasaki, Uozumicho</street><city>Akashi-shi, Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Yamada, Yasuyuki, MMC Kobelco Tool Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>179-1, Nishioke, Kanagasaki, Uozumicho</street><city>Akashi-shi, Hyogo-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HOFFMANN - EITLE</last-name><address><street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Arabellastrasse 4</street><city>81925 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The invention provides a high-speed tool steel gear cutting tool in which fracture
or chipping does not occur at the cutting edge, and which realizes excellent cutting
performance over long periods. Moreover, a method of manufacturing a gear cutting tool
including: a step for quenching a tool material comprising high-speed tool steel and which
has been rough processed to a shape corresponding to a final shape of a gear cutting tool,
to transform a structure of the tool material into martensite, a step for temperling the tool
material after quenching to transform any residual austenite dispersingly distributed
throughout a matrix of the martensite structure formed by the quenching, into martensite,
and a step for finishing the tool material after tempering to a final shape, is characterized
in that the tool material after quenching is subjected to sub-zero treatment involving
cooling and holding at a temperature of less than -150 °C.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><heading>1. Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a high-speed tool steel gear cutting tool (hereunder
referred to simply as a gear cutting tool) in which fractures or chipping (minute fractures)
do not occur at the cutting edge even when performing gear cutting at high-speed, and
which realizes excellent cutting performance over long periods, and a manufacturing
method therefor.</p><heading>2. Description of the Related Art</heading><p num="0002">Heretofore, in the gear cutting of tooth profiles for various gears used as
constituent members for automobiles, aircraft, and various drive units, a gear cutting tool
such as for example the hob (solid hob) shown in FIG. 1, a pinion cutter, or a shaving
cutter are used.</p><p num="0003">Furthermore, manufacture of this gear cutting tool by the following steps as
illustrated hereunder in (a) to (e) it also well known.
<sl><li>(a) Hot forge an ingot of high-speed tool steel at a temperature of 1100 to 1150
°C to make a bar with an outer diameter of 50 to 150 mm.</li><li>(b) Fully anneal the bar stock and then cut to a predetermined length, mill, and
rough treatment into a tool material of a shape corresponding to the shape of the final gear
cutting tool.</li><li>(c) Heat and hold the tool material at a temperature of 1210 to 1270 °C in an
atmosphere of nitrogen, and then quench the tool material by blow cooling with
pressurized nitrogen gas, to transform the structure of the tool material into martensite. </li><li>(d) Heat and hold the post quenched tool material at a temperature of 500 to
550 °C in an atmosphere of nitrogen to temper the tool material and transform the residual
austenite dispersingly distributed in the matrix of the martensite structure formed in the
quenching into martensite.</li><li>(e) Finish the post quenched and tempered tool material into a final shape by
for example grinding or polishing.</li></sl></p><p num="0004">Furthermore, as the abovementioned gear cutting tool, there is also known a coated
gear cutting tool as disclosed for example in Japanese Patent Application, First
Publication No. Hei 7-310173, where the surface of the high-speed tool steel base metal is
physical vapor deposited to an average thickness of 2 to 15 µm with a hard coating layer
comprising either or both of; a composite nitride [hereunder denoted by (Ti, Al) N] layer
of Ti and Al and a composite carbonitride [hereunder denoted by (Ti, Al) CN] layer of Ti
and Al, for which in the case where these are expressed by composition formula: [Ti<sub>1-x</sub>Al<sub>x</sub>]
N and composition formula: [Ti<sub>1-x</sub>Al<sub>x</sub>] C<sub>1-m</sub>Nm, the atomic ratio measured using an Auger
spectroscopy analysis apparatus, of a central portion in the thickness direction satisfies x:
0.30 to 0.70, m: 0.6 to 0.99.</p><p num="0005">This coated gear cutting tool is shown for example in outline in FIG. 2, and is
manufactured using a cathodic arc ion plating apparatus being one type of physical vapor
deposition apparatus. In this case, for example the interior of the apparatus is made a
vacuum atmosphere of 20 m. torr, and in a condition heated with a heater to a temperature
of 500 °C, an arc discharge is generated under conditions of for example voltage: 35 V,
current: 90 A between an anode electrode and the cathode electrode on which is set a Ti ∼
Al alloy having a predetermined composition. At the same time, a nitrogen gas, or a
nitrogen and methane gas, is introduced to inside the apparatus as the reaction gas, and a 
bias voltage of for example 200 V is applied to the base metal comprising the high-speed
tool steel (hereunder simply base metal) so that the hard coating layer is physical vapor
deposited on the surface of the base metal.</p><p num="0006">However, in recent times FA (factory automation) of gear cutting apparatus has
become remarkable and there is a strong demand for labor saving and energy saving in the
gear cutting process and a reduction in cost. Together with this, there is a demand for
generality to enable a variety of gear cutting processes to be perforrned with only one type
of gear cutting tool, and there is also a trend towards speeding up the gear cutting process.</p><p num="0007">As a result, in the conventional gear cutting tool, in the case where this is used in
gear cutting under normal conditions there are no problems. However when used in high-speed
gear cutting, this is susceptible chipping, particularly at the ridge Line intersection of
the rake face and the relief face of the cutting edge, so that the useful life is reached in a
comparatively short time.</p><p num="0008">On the other hand, in the case of the conventional coated gear cutting tool, in the
case where this is used in gear cutting under normal conditions, with carbon steel or cast
iron or the like there are no problems. However when used in high-speed gear cutting of
gears such as low-alloy steel or mild steel with extremely high viscosity, since the affinity
between the chips produced by the cutting and the (Ti, Al) N layer or the (Ti, Al) CN layer
constituting the hard coating layer is high, the chips are susceptible to adhering to the
surface of the cutting edge of the gear cutting tool. This adhering phenomena becomes
remarkably apparent the higher the speed of the gear cutting process, and with this
adhering phenomena as the cause, fracture and chipping occurs at the cutting edge, so that
the useful life is reached in a comparatively short time.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0009">The present inventors, as a result of performing research from the abovementioned
view point, into the manufacture of gear cutting tools for which the ridge line of the
cutting edge demonstrates excellent anti-chipping even when used in high-speed gear
cutting processes, have obtained the following research results shown in (1) to (4).
<sl><li>(1) In the case of the abovementioned conventional manufacturing method for
a gear cutting tool, a 20 to 30 weight % (hereunder simply %) residual austenite exists in
the martensite matrix in the tool material after quenching. Consequently, even if the
residual austenite diffusingly distributed in the matrix of the martensite structure formed
by the quenching is transformed into martensite, the existence of around 1 to 5 % residual
austenite cannot be avoided. This 1 to 5 % residual austenite is comparatively coarse, and
the shape thereof is nonuniform. Therefore this becomes a starting point for the chipping
at the time of high-speed gear cutting.</li><li>(2) When the post quenched tool material is subjected to sub-zero treatment by
cooling and holding at a temperature of below -150 °C, the residual austenite dispersingly
distributed in a proportion of 20 to 30 % in the matrix which has been transformed into
martensite by the quenching is reduced to below 5 %, and the shape thereof becomes fine
and uniform.</li><li>(3) When tempering is performed on the post sub-zero treated tool material, a
condition results where residual austenite is substantially non existent in the matrix which
has been transformed into martensite, or exists but the proportion thereof is less than
0.5 %. Moreover, the form thereof is extremely fine grained.</li><li>(4) In the gear cutting tool having a structure where residual austenite is
substantially non existent in the matrix which has been transformed into martensite, or
having a structure where residual austenite exists, but the proportion thereof is less than
0.5 % and the form thereof is very fine grained, the starting point for chipping does not 
exist in the structure. Therefore, even if high-speed gear cutting is performed, there is no
occurrence of chipping in the ridge line of the cutting edge, and excellent cutting
performance can be demonstrated over a long period.</li></sl></p><p num="0010">The present invention is based on the abovementioned research results, and is one
where a method of manufacturing a gear cutting tool including: a step for quenching a tool
material comprising high-speed tool steel and which has been rough processed to a shape
corresponding to a final shape of a gear cutting tool, to transform a structure of the tool
material into martensite, a step for tempering the tool material after quenching to
transform any residual austenite dispersingly distributed throughout a matrix of the
martensite structure formed by the quenching, into martensite, and a step for finishing the
tool material after tempering to a final shape, is characterized in that the tool material after
quenching is subjected to sub-zero treatment involving cooling and holding at a
temperature of less than -150 °C, and transforming any residual austenite which is
dispersingly distributed throughout the matrix into martensite, to thereby transform the
structure of the tool material after tempering into a structure in which residual austenite
which is a starting point for chipping at the time of high-speed gear cutting does not exist
in the matrix of the martensite.</p><p num="0011">Furthermore, regarding the sub-zero treatment, preferably this is performed under
conditions where the tool material after quenching is cooled using liquid nitrogen, at a
predetermined cooling rate within a range of 1 to 10 °C/minute to a predetermined
temperature within a range of -150 to -200 °C, and held at this temperature for a
predetermined time within a range of 1 to 5 hours, and then raised in temperature at a
predetermined temperature raising rate within a range of 1 to 10 °C/min. </p><p num="0012">The cooling rate, the cooling temperature of less than -150 °C, the holding time at
the cooling temperature, and the temperature raising rate in the above mentioned sub-zero
treatment are all empirically determined. In particular, regarding the cooling temperature,
if the cooling temperature is higher than -150 °C, it is difficult to transform the residual
austenite into the desirable martensite.</p><p num="0013">On the other hand, as a result of performing research into developing a coated gear
cutting tool for which the adhesion of chips to the surface of the cutting edge is difficult,
even in the case where this is used in a high-speed gear cutting process particularly for
gears such as a low-alloy steel or a mild steel, the present inventors have obtained the
following research results shown in (5) and (6).
<sl><li>(5) When Ta is dissolved in the (Ti, Al) N layer and the (Ti, Al) CN layer constituting
the hard coating layer of the conventional coated gear cutting tool, so that the proportion
held for the gross weight of Ti and Al becomes a proportion of 0.01 to 0.35 for the atomic
ratio based on measurements using an Auger spectroscopy apparatus, of a thickness
direction central portion, and a hard coating layer is made with the composite nitride of Ti,
Al and Ta (hereunder shown as (Ti, Al, Ta) N) and the composite carbonitride (hereunder
(Ti, Al, Ta) CN) layer of Ti, Al and Ta obtained from the results, due to the action of the
Ta in this hard coating layer, the affinity to the work piece, in particular a highly viscous
difficult to machine material such as low-alloy steel or mild steel is considerably reduced.
Hence this has high chip lubrication properties. As a result, adhesion of the chips to the
cutting edge is markedly suppressed. However, the high toughness held by the (Ti, Al) N
layer and (Ti, Al) CN layer is lost.</li><li>(6) On the other hand, when the (Ti, Al) N layer and the (Ti, Al) CN layer
constituting the hard coating layer of the conventional coated gear cutting tool, and the (Ti,
Al, Ta) N layer and the (Ti, Al, Ta) CN layer shown in (5) above are alternately coated 
with the thickness of each extremely thin, that is an average thickness of 0.005 to 0.2 µm,
to form a hard coating layer, the problem points of the respective layers, that is the high
affinity to the chips in the (Ti, Al) N layer and the (Ti, Al) CN layer (hereunder referred to
as the first thin layer), and the low toughness in the (Ti, Al, Ta) N layer and the (Ti, Al,
Ta) CN layer (hereunder referred to as the second thin layer) is cancelled out between the
two, thereby furnishing the high toughness held by the first thin layer and the high chip
lubrication properties held by the second thin layer. As a result, even when a coated gear
cutting tool having this hard coating layer is used in high-speed gear cutting of a gear
comprising a difficult to machine material of high viscosity such as a low-alloy steel or
mild steel, chips are unlikely to adhere to the surface of the cutting edge, and excellent
cutting performance is demonstrated over a long period.</li></sl></p><p num="0014">The present invention is based on the abovementioned research results. The coated
gear cutting tool is characterized in that a hard coating which is physical vapor deposited
at an overall average thickness of 2 to 15 µm, is formed on a surface of a base metal of a
high-speed tool steel, by coating a first thin layer and a second thin layer with respective
average thicknesses of 0.005 to 0.2 µm,
<sl><li>the first thin layer comprising either or both of a (Ti, Al) N layer and a (Ti, Al) CN
layer for which in the case where these are represented by
<sl><li>composition formula : [Ti<sub>1-x</sub>Al<sub>x</sub>] N and</li><li>composition formula : [Ti<sub>1-x</sub>Al<sub>x</sub>] C<sub>1-m</sub>N<sub>m</sub>,</li></sl>
the atomic ratio based on measurements using an Auger spectroscopy apparatus, of a
thickness direction central portion satisfies X: 0.30 to 0.70, m: 0.6 to 0.99, and</li><li>the second thin layer comprising either or both of a (Ti, Al, Ta) N layer and a (Ti,
Al, Ta) CN layer for which in the case where these are represented by
<sl><li>composition formula : [Ti <sub>1-(X+Y)</sub>Al<sub>X</sub>Ta<sub>Y</sub>] N and </li><li>composition formula : [Ti <sub>1-(X+Y)</sub> Al<sub>X</sub>Ta<sub>Y</sub>] C<sub>1-m</sub>N<sub>m</sub>,</li></sl>
the atomic ratio based on measurements using an Auger spectroscopy apparatus, of a
thickness direction central portion satisfies X: 0.30 to 0.70, Y: 0.01 to 0.35 and m: 0.6 to
0.99.</li></sl></p><p num="0015">In this coated gear cutting tool, the reason for making the average layer thickness
of the first thin layer and the second thin layer constituting the hard coating layer
respectively 0.005 to 0.2 µm, is because if in either of these thin layers the average layer
thickness becomes less than 0.005 µm, the characteristics inherent in these thin layers, that
is the high toughness inherent in the first thin layer and the high chip lubrication
properties inherent in the second thin layer cannot be adequately imparted to the hard
coating layer. On the other hand, if the average layer thickness thereof respectively
exceeds 0.2 µm, the inherent problem points of the respective thin layers, that is the chip
adhering nature inherent in the first thin layer and the drop in toughness in the second thin
layer, become apparent in the hard coating layer. The average layer thickness of the first
thin layer and the second thin layer is more preferably 0.007 to 0.10 µm for each.</p><p num="0016">Furthermore, in the coated gear cutting tool of the present invention, the Al in the
(Ti, Al) N layer and the (Ti, Al) CN layer constituting the first thin layer of the hard
coated layer, and in the (Ti, Al, Ta) N layer and the (Ti, Al, Ta) CN layer constituting the
second thin layer, is added in order to improve the hardness with respect to TiCN, and
improve the wear resistance. However, with the X value in
<sl><li>composition formula : [Ti<sub>1-x</sub>Al<sub>x</sub>] N and</li><li>composition formula : [Ti<sub>1-x</sub>Al<sub>x</sub>] C<sub>1-m</sub>N<sub>m</sub>, and also in</li><li>composition formula : [Ti <sub>1-(X+Y)</sub>Al<sub>X</sub>Ta<sub>Y</sub>] N and</li><li>composition formula : [Ti <sub>1-(X+Y)</sub>Al<sub>X</sub>Ta<sub>Y</sub>] C<sub>1-m</sub>N<sub>m</sub>,</li></sl> 
is less than 0.30 for the atomic ratio (and similarly hereunder), the desired wear resistance
cannot be ensured. On the other hand, if the above value exceeds 0.70, then fracture or
chipping of the cutting edge is likely to occur. Therefore, in the present embodiment, the
X value is set at 0.30 to 0.70. This X value is more preferably 0.35 to 0.65.</p><p num="0017">Furthermore, since the C component in the abovementioned (Ti, Al) CN layer and
the (Ti, Al, Ta) CN layer provides an affect of improving the hardness, then the (Ti, Al)
CN layer and the (Ti, Al, Ta) CN layer each have a relatively high hardness compared to
the abovementioned (Ti, Al) N layer and the (Ti, Al, Ta) N layer. However, if the
proportion of the C component in the above mentioned composition formula is less than
0.01, that is the m value exceeds 0.99, the predetermined hardness improvement effect is
not obtained. On the other hand, if the proportion of the C component exceeds 0.4, that is
the m value is less than 0.6, the toughness decreases suddenly. Therefore, in the present
invention, the m value is set at 0.6 to 0.99. This m value is more preferably 0.8 to 0.9.</p><p num="0018">Furthermore, due to the effect of the (Ti, Al, Ta) N layer and the (Ti, Al, Ta) CN
layer constituting the second thin layer, this has excellent chip lubrication compared to the
(Ti, Al) N layer and the (Ti, Al) CN layer of the first thin layer. However, if the Y value
in the abovementioned composition formula is less than 0.01, the Ta content becomes
insufficient, so that the predetermined chip lubrication improvement effect cannot be
imparted to the hard coating layer. On the other hand, if the Y value exceeds 0.35, the
toughness decreases rapidly in the overall hard coating layer. Therefore, in the present
invention, the Y value is set at 0.01 to 0.35. This Y value is more preferably 0.07 to 0.30.</p><p num="0019">Furthermore, the reason for making the overall average thickness of the hard
coating layer 2 to 15 µm, is that at a layer thickness of 2 µm a desirable excellent wear
resistance cannot be ensured, while if the layer thickness exceeds 15 µm, fracture or 
chipping of the cutting edge is likely to occur. The layer thickness is more preferably 3 to
10 µm.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0020"><sl><li>FIG. 1 is an outline perspective view of a cutting tool (solid hob) to which the
present invention is applied.</li><li>FIG. 2 is an outline explanatory diagram of a cathodic arc ion plating apparatus.</li></sl></p><heading>PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading><heading>First Embodiment</heading><p num="0021">A cutting tool of the present invention will now be specifically described by means
of an embodiment.</p><p num="0022">Three types of high-speed tool steel ingots prescribed by Japan Industrial Standard
JIS SKH55, SKH56 and SKH57, all having an outside diameter of 300 mm were prepared,
and each of the ingots was subjected to hot forging in a condition heated to a temperature
of 1130 °C, to produce bar stock of 150 mm diameter. These bar stocks were then held
for 30 minutes at 880 °C and fully annealed after which they were each cut to a length of
100 mm, and then milled so that all were rough processed into tool materials of a shape
corresponding to a final shape shown in FIG. 1. These tool materials were then heated to
1250 °C in a nitrogen atmosphere and held for 20 minutes, and then cooled while
maintaining the cooling speed at 40 - 120 °C/minute by adjusting the blast proportion of
pressurized nitrogen gas to effect quenching, thereby transforming the structure of the tool
materials into martensite. Furthermore, the proportion of residual austenite dispersingly 
distributed throughout the martensite matrix in the post quenched tool materials was
measured using an X-ray diffractometer.</p><p num="0023">Then, liquid nitrogen was gasified and blown onto the quenched tool materials,
and the blast proportion adjusted so that the tool materials were cooled at a predetermined
cooling rate shown in Table 1 (annex) and cooled until a predetermined cooling
temperature similarly shown in Table 1, and then held for 1 hour at this cooling
temperature. Next, a heating condition was adjusted using a heater so that these tool
materials were subjected to a sub-zero treatment of a temperature rise at a predetermined
temperature rise rate similarly shown in Table 1, after which the proportion of the residual
austenite dispersingly distributed throughout the martensite matrix was measured using an
X-ray diffractometer.</p><p num="0024">Then, the post sub-zero treated tool materials were held for 1.5 hours at 550 °C to
temper the tool materials, after which the proportion of residual austenite dispersingly
distributed throughout the martensite matrix in the tool materials was measured using the
X-ray diffractometer. Finally, by grinding each of the tempered tool materials, gear
cutting tools of the shape shown in FIG. 1, having an overall dimension of 80 mm
diameter and 120 mm length, and having 3 right handed threads and 20 grooves in the
surface, were respectively manufactured in accordance with the manufacturing methods
corresponding to Table 1 "Present invention methods 1 to 9".</p><p num="0025">Furthermore, for the purpose of comparison, cutting tools of the shape shown in
FIG. 1 where respectively made by manufacturing methods corresponding to Table 1
"Conventional methods 1 to 3" (manufacturing methods the same as for the present
invention except that the abovementioned sub-zero treatment was not pcrformed).</p><p num="0026">Then using the gear cutting tools made by the present invention methods 1 to 9 and
the conventional methods 1 to 3, the processing for a gear with a material corresponding 
to a low-alloy steel of JIS SCr 420H, and having dimensions and shape of; module: 1.75,
pressure angle: 17.5 degrees, number of teeth: 33, twist angle 36 degrees left hand, gear
height: 5.86 mm, gear width: 15.5 mm, was performed under high-speed cutting
conditions of; cutting speed (rotational speed): 150 m/min, feed: 2 mm/rev, no climb, no
shift, dry (air blown), and the number of gears processed until the wear width of the relief
face reached 0.10 mm (useful life) was measured. The measurement results are shown in
Table 1.</p><p num="0027">Furthermore, Table 1 also shows the measurement results for the residual austenite
in the martensite matrix after the abovementioned quenching process, sub-zero treatment
and tempering process.</p><p num="0028">From the results shown in Table 1 it can be seen that with the gear cutting tool
made by the present invention methods 1 to 9, residual austenite does not exist in any of
the martensite matrices, or if this does exist the proportion thereof is minimal at less than
0.5 %. Furthermore, while not shown in Table 1, in the gear cutting tools made by the
present invention methods 1 to 9, the form of the residual austenite is extremely fine
grained, and the grain size is uniform. As a result, in the gear cutting tools made by the
present invention methods 1 to 9, there is no chipping, particularly at the ridge line portion
of the cutting edge, and these show excellent wera resistance over a long period.</p><p num="0029">On the other hand, in the gear cutting tools made by the conventional methods 1 to
3, the proportion of residual austenite in the martensite matrix is comparatively large and
the grain size thereof is coarse and nonuniform. Since this becomes a starting point for
chipping during high-speed gear cutting, the occurrence of chipping in the cutting edge
ridge line portion is unavoidable, and as a result the useful life is reached in a
comparatively short time. </p><p num="0030">As described above, according to the manufacturing method for a gear cutting tool
of the present invention, a gear cutting tool can be manufactured which shows excellent
resistance to chipping, and demonstrates wear resistance over a long period, not only in
the case of gear cutting under normal conditions of a gear comprising for example a low-alloy
steel, but also in the case of high-speed gear cutting of a gear comprising a high
hardness steel or the like. Consequently, the manufacturing method for a gear cutting tool
of the present invention contributes to speeding up of the gear cutting process, savings in
labor and energy, and a reduction in costs.</p><heading>Second Embodiment</heading><p num="0031">Next is a specific description by means of an embodiment, of a coated gear cutting
tool of the present invention.</p><p num="0032">As a base metal made of a high-speed tool steel, a single thread hob for a gear
made from a JIS SKH 55 material and having an outside diameter of 60 mm, and an
overall dimension of 60 mm (module: 2) prescribed in JIS B 4354, and a pinion cutter
made from the same material JIS SKH 55 and with 50 teeth and a pitch circle diameter of
100 mm (module: 2) prescribed by JIS B 4356 were prepared. These base metals were
then ultrasonic cleaned in acetone and respectively placed in a dry condition in a
conventional cathodic arc ion plating apparatus as shown for example in FIG. 2. On the
other hand, for the cathode electrode (vapor source), metal alloys of respective
predetermined component compositions were selected for predetermined combinations,
from the first thin layer forming Ti-Al alloy and the second thin layer forming Ti-Al-Ta
alloy each having component compositions shown in Table 2 (annex), and these were
installed at respective corresponding positions centered on the rotation axis. Next, the
interior of the apparatus was evacuated, and while being maintained at a vacuum of 0.5 pa, 
the interior of the apparatus was heated to 500 °C by a heater. Then Ar gas was
introduced to the interior of the apparatus to give an Ar atmosphere of 10 Pa. In this
condition, the rotation shaft was intermittently rotated for each predetermined time lapse
corresponding to the thickness of the layer to be formed. On the other hand, a bias voltage
of -800 V was applied to the base metal, and the base metal surface was bombarded and
cleaned by the Ar gas. Next, a nitrogen gas, or a nitrogen and methane gas as a reaction
gas was introduced to inside the apparatus to give a reaction atmosphere of 6 Pa, and also
the bias voltage applied to the base metal was reduced to -200V and an arc discharge
produced between the cathode electrode (the alloy on one side) and the anode electrode.
Then, based on this operation, a first thin layer and a second thin layer having an objective
composition and an objective thickness shown in Table 2, were alternately deposited and
laminated on the surface of the base metal in a combination as shown in Table 3 (annex)
and in a number of laminations as shown in the same Table 3, to thereby form a hard
coating layer. As a result, coated gear cutting tools corresponding to the present invention
coated gear cuttings tools 1 to 13 of Table 3 were respectively manufactured.</p><p num="0033">Furthermore, for comparison, in the above cathodic arc ion plating apparatus, a
hard coating layer comprising a (Ti, Al) N layer and/or a (Ti, Al) CN layer of an objective
composition and an objective layer thickness as shown in Table 4, was formed on the
surface of the base metals under the same conditions except that for the cathode electrode
(vapor source) a predetermined one type from Ti-Al alloys having various component
compositions was mounted. By so doing, gear cutting tools corresponding to Table 4
"Conventional coated gear cutting tools 1 to 12" were respectively manufactured.</p><p num="0034">For the hard coating layers respectively constituting the abovementioned coated
gear cutting tools 1 to 13 of the present invention and the conventional coated gear
cuttings tools 1 to 12, the composition of the thickness direction central portion for each of 
the constituent layers was measured using the Auger spectroscopic apparatus.
Furthermore, the layer thicknesses thereof were measured using a scanning electron
microscope. In all of the cases, the objective composition and the objective layer
thickness showed substantially the same composition and layer thickness.</p><p num="0035">Next, for hobs of the abovementioned present invention coated gear cutting tools 1
to 13 and the conventional coated gear cutting tools 1 to 12, under high-speed cutting
conditions of;
<sl><li>cutting speed (rotation speed): 200m/min (1062 rpm), and</li><li>feed: 2.0 mm/rev,</li></sl>
gear cutting was performed for gears having dimensions of; outside diameter 100 mm,
length 25 mm, and number of teeth 48, and a material comprising a low-alloy steel of JIS
SCr 420.</p><p num="0036">Furthermore, for pinion cutters, under high-speed cutting conditions of;
<sl><li>strokes per minute: 750 stroke/min</li><li>circumferential feed: 4 mm/stroke and</li><li>radial feed: 0.01 mm/stroke,</li></sl>
gear cutting was performed for gears having dimensions of; outside diameter 66 mm,
length 25 mm, number of teeth 31, and a material comprising low-alloy steel of JIS SCr
420.</p><p num="0037">Next, in each of the gear cutting processes, the number of gears cut until the
maximum relief face wear of the cutting edge reached 0.2 mm was measured (useful life).
These measurement results are respectively shown in Table 3 and Table 4. The <img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="3" img-format="tif" img-content="ff" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="3"/> mark
in the column for the number of gears processed in Table 3 and Table 4 shows the results
for a wet process (using cutting oil), while the non marked results show the results for a
dry process (air blow). </p><p num="0038">From the results shown in Table 3 and Table 4, in the present invention coated
gear cutting tools 1 to 13 where the hard coating layer comprises alternate multi-layers of
the first thin layer and the second thin layer, even if the gear cutting process for low-alloy
steel is performed at high-speed accompanied with high heat generation, due to the
considerable improvement in the chip lubrication by the second thin layer, the affinity of
the hard coating layer to chips with high temperature heating can be considerably reduced.
As a result, the adhering of chips to the hard coating layer is prevented and the surface
lubrication of the cutting edge is maintained. Consequently, the situation of the
occurrence of chipping of the cutting edge attributable to the adhering of the chips to the
cutting edge ceases to exist, and excellent wear resistance is demonstrated.</p><p num="0039">On the other hand, in the conventional coated gear cutting tools 1 to 12 where the
hard coating layer substantially comprises a single layer of the same composition as the
first thin layer, the chips are susceptible to adhering to the hard coating layer, and with this
as the cause, the hard coated layer is partially pealed off. As a result, chipping occurs at
the cutting edge, and the useful life is reached in a comparatively short time.</p><p num="0040">As described above, the coated gear cutting tool of the present invention
demonstrates excellent surface lubrication with respect to chips, and shows generality in
cutting performance, not only in the case of gear cutting of gears comprising carbon steel
or cast iron or the like under normal conditions, but also in this case of high-speed gear
cutting of gears comprising a low-alloy steel or mild steel or the like particularly with high
viscosity, and which are susceptible to chips adhering to the cutting edge surface.
Consequently, the coated gear cutting tool of the present invention contributes to speeding
up of the gear cutting process, savings in labor and energy, and a reduction in costs. </p><p num="0041">The scope of the present invention is not limited to the above mentioned disclosed
contents, and various modifications within a scope which does not depart from the gist of
the present invention are also included in the present invention. <img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="215"/><img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="195"/><img id="img-00200001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00200001.tif" inline="no" he="209"/><img id="img-00210001" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00210001.tif" inline="no" he="221"/></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A high-speed tool steel gear cutting tool which has been subjected to a process for
preventing the occurrence of fracture or chipping of the cutting edge.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method of manufacturing a high-speed tool steel gear cutting tool according to
claim 1 including:
<claim-text><claim-text>a step for quenching a tool material comprising high-speed tool steel and which
has been rough processed to a shape corresponding to a final shape of a gear cutting tool,
to transform a structure of said tool material into martensite,</claim-text><claim-text>a step for tempering said tool material after quenching to transform any residual
austenite dispersingly distributed throughout a matrix of said martensite structure formed
by the quenching, into martensite, and</claim-text><claim-text>a step for finishing said tool material after tempering to a final shape,</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein said tool material after quenching is subjected to sub-zero treatment involving
cooling and holding at a temperature of less than -150 °C, and transforming any residual
austenite which is dispersingly distributed throughout the matrix into martensite, to
thereby transform the structure of said tool material after tempering into a structure in
which residual austenite which is a starting point for chipping at the time of high-speed
gear cutting does not exist in the matrix of said martensite.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A high-speed tool steel gear cutting tool according to claim 1, wherein a hard
coating which is physical vapor deposited at an overall average thickness of 2 to 15 µm, is
formed on a surface of a base metal of a high-speed tool steel, by coating a first thin layer
and a second thin layer with respective average thicknesses of 0.005 to 0.2 µm,
   said first thin layer comprising either or both of a (Ti, Al) N layer and a (Ti, Al)
CN layer for which in the case where these are represented by
<claim-text><claim-text>composition formula : [Ti1-xAlx] N and</claim-text><claim-text>composition formula : [Ti1-xAlx] C1-mNm,</claim-text></claim-text>
the atomic ratio based on measurements using an Auger spectroscopy apparatus, of a
thickness direction central portion satisfies X: 0.30 to 0.70, m: 0.6 to 0.99, and
   said second thin layer comprising either or both of a (Ti, Al, Ta) N layer and a (Ti,
Al, Ta) CN layer for which in the case where these are represented by
<claim-text><claim-text>composition formula : [Ti 1-(X+Y)AlXTaY] N and</claim-text><claim-text>composition formula : [Ti 1-(X+Y)AlXTaY] C1-mNm,</claim-text></claim-text>
the atomic ratio based on measurements using an Auger spectroscopy apparatus, of a
thickness direction central portion satisfies X: 0.30 to 0.70, Y: 0.01 to 0.35 and m: 0.6 to
0.99.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>