<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1193308-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1193308" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="24710792" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020403"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1193308-A1" status="new" fvid="23395095"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1193308</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020403</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01308096-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01308096</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010924</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-67550400-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>67550400</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000929</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/10        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/16        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/18        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/188       20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/192       20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/195       20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/22        20060101AFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/222       20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L  10/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L  10/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L  10/04        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10L   1/14B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10L  10/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:14B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:16A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:16B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:16P1B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:18D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:18D1</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:18D1B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:18P10F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:22P10</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Ein Mannichkondensationsprodukt, ein Poly(oxyalkylen)monool, und eine Carbonsäure enthaltende Brennstoffzusatzszusammensetzungen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Fuel additive compositions containing a mannich condensation product, a poly(oxyalkylene)monool, and a carboxylic acid</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Compositions d'additifs pour combustible contenant un produit de condensation Mannich, un poly(oxyalkylène)monool, et un acide carboxylique</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0647700-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0647700</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0831141-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0831141</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1008642-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1008642</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3798247-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3798247</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4071327-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4071327</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4398921-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4398921</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4877416-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4877416</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHEVRON ORONITE CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHEVRON ORONITE TECHNOLOGY B V</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHEVRON ORONITE COMPANY LLC</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHEVRON ORONITE TECHNOLOGY B.V.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Chevron Oronite Company LLC</last-name><address><street>Third Floor, 2613 Camino Ramon</street><city>San Ramon, CA 94583-4289</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Chevron Oronite Technology B.V.</last-name><address><street>Petroleumweg 32</street><city>3196 KD Vondelingenplaat, Rotterdam</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>AHMADI MAJID R</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>GRAY JAMES A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SENGERS HENK P M</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AHMADI, MAJID R.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GRAY, JAMES A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SENGERS, HENK P.M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>AHMADI, MAJID R.</last-name><address><street>321 Del Monte Way</street><city>Pinole, California 94564</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GRAY, JAMES A.</last-name><address><street>730 Arlington Circle</street><city>Novato, California 94947</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SENGERS, HENK P.M.</last-name><address><street>Willem de Zwijgerlaan 40</street><city>3116 HZ Schiedam</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Nash, David Allan</last-name><address><street>Haseltine Lake &amp;amp; Co., Imperial House, 15-19 Kingsway</street><city>London WC2B 6UD</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A fuel additive composition comprising:
<sl><li>a) a Mannich condensation product of (1) a high molecular weight alkylsubstituted
hydroxyaromatic compound wherein the alkyl group has
a number average molecular weight of from about 300 to about
5,000 (2) an amine which contains an amino group having at least
one active hydrogen atom, and (3) an aldehyde, wherein the
respective molar ratio of reactants (1), (2), and (3) is 1:0.1-10:0.1-10;</li><li>b) a hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool having an
average molecular weight of about 500 to about 5,000, wherein the
oxyalkylene group is a C<sub>2</sub> to C<sub>5</sub> oxyalkylene group and the
hydrocarbyl group is a C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbyl group; and</li><li>c) a carboxylic acid as represented by the formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>1</sub>(COOH)<sub>x</sub></st32:che>
or anhydride thereof, wherein R<sub>1</sub> represents a hydrocarbyl group
having about 2 to about 50 carbon atoms, and x represents an
integer of 1 to about 4.</li></sl></p><p>The unique fuel additive composition provides excellent control of engine deposits,
particularly engine intake system deposits, such as intake valve deposits. The
improved performance may be attributable to the improved compatibility of the fuel
additive composition of the present invention. The improved compatibility
manifests itself in less insoluble material, haze, and floes. Improved anti-corrosion
properties are also provided by the fuel additive composition of the present
invention.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Field of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to fuel additive compositions containing a Mannich
condensation product, a hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool, and a
carboxylic acid. In one aspect the present invention relates to the use of these
additive compositions in fuel compositions to prevent and control engine deposits,
particularly engine intake system deposits, such as intake valve deposits. In a
further aspect the present invention relates to a method of improving the
compatibility of a fuel additive composition.</p><heading><u style="single">Description of the Related Art</u></heading><p num="0002">Numerous deposit-forming substances are inherent in hydrocarbon fuels. These
substances, when used in internal combustion engines, tend to form deposits on
and around constricted areas of the engine contacted by the fuel. Typical areas
commonly and sometimes seriously burdened by the formation of deposits include
carburetor ports, the throttle body and venturies, engine intake valves, etc.</p><p num="0003">Deposits adversely affect the operation of the vehicle. For example, deposits on
the carburetor throttle body and venturies increase the fuel to air ratio of the gas
mixture to the combustion chamber thereby increasing the amount of unburned
hydrocarbon and carbon monoxide discharged from the chamber. The high fuel-air
ratio also reduces the gas mileage obtainable from the vehicle. </p><p num="0004">Deposits on the engine intake valves when they get sufficiently heavy, on the other
hand, restrict the gas mixture flow into the combustion chamber. This restriction,
starves the engine of air and fuel and results in a loss of power. Deposits on the
valves also increase the probability of valve failure due to burning and improper
valve seating. In addition, these deposits may break off and enter the combustion
chamber possibly resulting in mechanical damage to the piston, piston rings,
engine head, etc.</p><p num="0005">The formation of these deposits can be inhibited as well as removed by
incorporating an active detergent into the fuel. These detergents function to
cleanse these deposit-prone areas of the harmful deposits, thereby enhancing
engine performance and longevity. There are numerous detergent-type gasoline
additives currently available which, to varying degrees, perform these functions.</p><p num="0006">Mannich condensation products are known in the art as fuel additives for the
prevention and control of engine deposits. For example, U.S. Patent No. 4,
231,759, issued November 4, 1980 to Udelhofen et al., discloses reaction products
obtained by the Mannich condensation of a high molecular weight alkyl-substituted
hydroxyaromatic compound, an amine containing an amino group having at least
one active hydrogen atom, and an aldehyde, such as formaldehyde. This patent
further teaches that such Mannich condensation products are useful detergent
additives in fuels for the control of deposits on carburetor surfaces and intake
valves.</p><p num="0007">U.S. Patent No. 5,876,468, issued March 2, 1999 to Moreton, discloses a
compound comprising a Mannich reaction product of a polyisobutylene-substituted
phenol wherein at least 70% of the terminal olefinic double bonds in the
polyisobutylene are of the vinylidene type, an aldehyde, and ethylenediamine
(EDA). This compound is shown to be a more effective detergent in hydrocarbon
fuels than Mannich compounds made from dimethylaminopropylamine (DMAPA),
diethylenetriamine (DETA), and triethylenetetramine (TETA). However, the other 
compounds are shown to have good detergency properties relative to base fuel.
Moreton also discloses an additive package consisting of the EDA Mannich,
alkoxylated alkylphenol, and an aromatic solvent.</p><p num="0008">Generally, Mannich condensation products are utilized in combination with other
fuel additive components. For example, polyolefins and polyether compounds are
also well known in the art as fuel additives. It is not uncommon for the literature to
refer to the enhanced benefits of the combination of two or more such fuel
additives for the prevention and control of engine deposits.</p><p num="0009">U.S. Patent No. 5,514,190, issued May 7, 1996 to Cunningham et al., discloses a
fuel additive composition for the control of intake valve deposits which comprises
(a) the Mannich reaction product of a high molecular weight alkyl-substituted
phenol, an amine, and an aldehyde, (b) a poly(oxyalkylene) carbamate, and (c) a
poly(oxyalkylene) alcohol, glycol or polyol, or a mono or diether thereof.</p><p num="0010">U.S. Patent No. 5,634,951, issued June 3, 1997 to Colucci et al., discloses
gasoline compositions containing Mannich condensation products as detergents.
This patent teaches that carrier fluids, including liquid polyalkylenes, may be
added to the compositions to enhance the effectiveness of the Mannich
condensation products in minimizing or reducing intake valve deposits and/or
intake valve sticking.</p><p num="0011">U.S. Patent No. 5,697,988, issued December 16, 1997 to Malfer et al., discloses a
fuel additive composition which provides reduced fuel injector, intake valve, and
combustion chamber deposits which comprises (a) the Mannich reaction product
of a high molecular weight alkyl-substituted phenol, an amine, and an aldehyde,
(b) a polyoxyalkylene compound, preferably a polyoxyalkylene glycol or monoether
derivative thereof, and (c) optionally a poly-alpha-olefin. </p><p num="0012">U.S. Patent No. 6,048,373, issued April 11, 2000 to Malfer et al., discloses a fuel
composition comprising (a) a spark-ignition internal combustion fuel, (b) a Mannich
detergent; and (c) a polybutene having a molecular weight distribution (Mw/Mn) of
1.4 or below.</p><p num="0013">U.S. Patent No. 4,357,148, issued November 2, 1982 to Graiff, discloses the
control or reversal of octane requirement increase together with improved fuel
economy in a spark ignition internal combustion engine is achieved by introducing
with the combustion charge a fuel composition containing an octane requirement
increase-inhibiting amount of certain oil-soluble aliphatic polyamines and certain
low molecular weight polymers and/or copolymers of mono-olefins having up to 6
carbon atoms, in a certain ratio.</p><p num="0014">U.S. Patent No. 4,877,416, issued October 31, 1989 to Campbell, discloses a fuel
composition which contains (a) from about 0.001 to 1.0 percent by weight of a
hydrocarbyl-substituted amine or polyamine having an average molecular weight
of about 750 to 10,000 and at least one basic nitrogen atom, and (b) a
hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool having an average molecular
weight of about 500 to 5,000, wherein the weight percent of the hydrocarbyl-terminated
poly(oxyalkylene) monool in the fuel composition ranges from about
0.01 to 100 times the amount of hydrocarbyl-substituted amine or polyamine.</p><p num="0015">U.S. Patent No. 5,006,130, issued April 9, 1991 to Aiello et al., discloses an
unleaded gasoline composition containing a mixture of (a) about 2.5 parts per
million by weight or higher of basic nitrogen in the form of an oil-soluble aliphatic
alkylene polyamine containing at least one olefinic polymer chain, said polyamine
having a molecular weight of about 600 to 10,000, and (b) from about 75 to about
125 parts per million by weight based on the fuel composition of certain oil-soluble
olefinic polymers, a poly(oxyalkylene) alcohol, glycol or polyol or a mono or diether
thereof, non-aromatic naphthenic or paraffinic oils or polyalphaolefins. This 
patent further teaches that, as a matter of practicality, the basic nitrogen content of
the aliphatic polyamine component is usually about 4.0 or below and that this
generally corresponds to a concentration of about 100 to 160 ppm when the
aliphatic polyamine is a 1,050 molecular weight aliphatic diamine, such as N-polyisobutenyl
N'-N'-dimethyl-1, 3-diaminopropane.</p><p num="0016">U.S. Patent No. 5,405,419, issued April 11, 1995 to Ansari et al., discloses a fuel
additive composition comprising (a) a fuel-soluble aliphatic hydrocarbyl-substituted
amine having at least one basic nitrogen atom wherein the hydrocarbyl group has
a number average molecular weight of about 700 to 3,000; (b) a polyolefin polymer
of a C<sub>2</sub> to C<sub>6</sub> monolefin, wherein the polymer has a number average molecular
weight of about 350 to 3,000; and (c) a hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene)
monool having an average molecular weight of about 500 to 5,000. This patent
further teaches that fuel compositions containing these additives will generally
contain about 50 to 500 ppm by weight of the aliphatic amine, about 50 to 1,000
ppm by weight of the polyolefin and about 50 to 1,000 ppm by weight of the
poly(oxyalkylene) monool. This patent also discloses that fuel compositions
containing 125 ppm each of aliphatic amine, polyolefin and poly(oxyalkylene)
monool provide better deposit control performance than compositions containing
125 ppm of aliphatic amine plus 125 ppm of poly(oxyalkylene) monool.</p><p num="0017">U.S. Patent No. 3,798,247, March 19, 1974 issued to Piasek and Karll, discloses
that the reaction under Mannich condensation conditions, like other chemical
reactions, does not go to theoretical completion and some portion of the reactants,
generally the amine, remains unreacted or only partially reacted as a coproduct.
Unpurified products of Mannich processes also commonly contain small amounts
of insoluble particle byproducts of the Mannich condensation reaction that appear
to be the high molecular weight condensation product of formaldehyde and
polyamines. The amine and amine byproducts lead to haze formation during
storage and, in diesel oil formulations, to rapid buildup of diesel engine piston ring 
groove carbonaceous deposits and skirt varnish. The insoluble or borderline
soluble byproducts are substantially incapable of removal by filtration and severely
restrict product filtration rate. These drawbacks were overcome by adding long-chain
carboxylic acids during the reaction to reduce the amount of solids formation
from the Mannich reaction. This was thought to render the particulate polyamineformaldehyde
condensation product soluble through formation of amide-type links.
In particular, oleic acid worked well at 0.1 to 0.3 mole/mole of alkylphenol. The
quantity of unconsumed or partially reacted amine was not mentioned in the
patent.</p><p num="0018">U.S. Patent No. 4,334,085, issued June 6, 1982 to Basalay and Udelhofen,
discloses that Mannich condensation products can undergo transamination, and
use this to solve the problem of byproduct amine-formaldehyde resin formation
encountered in U.S. Patent No. 3,748,247 eliminating the need for using a fatty
acid. U.S. Patent No. 4,334,085 defined transamination as the reaction of a
Mannich adduct based on a single-nitrogen amine with a polyamine to exchange
the polyamine for the single-nitrogen amine. The examples in this patent infer that
the unconsumed amine and partially reacted amine discussed in U.S. Patent
3,798,247 are not merely unconsumed, but must be in chemical equilibrium with
the product of the Mannich condensation reaction. In Example 1 of U.S. Patent
No. 4,334,085, a Mannich condensation product is made from 0.5 moles of
polyisobutylphenol, 1.0 mole of diethylamine and 1.1 moles of formaldehyde. To
0.05 moles of this product was added 0.05 moles of tetraethylenepentamine
(TEPA) and then the mixture was heated to 155°C while blowing with nitrogen.
The TEPA replaced 80 to 95% of the diethylamine in the Mannich as the nitrogen
stripped off the diethylamine made available by the equilibrium with the Mannich.</p><p num="0019">U.S. Patent No. 5,360,460, issued November 1, 1994 to Mozdzen et al., discloses
a fuel additive composition comprising (A) an alkylene oxide condensate or the
reaction product thereof and an alcohol, (B) a monocarboxylic fatty acid, and (C) a 
hydrocarbyl amine, or the reaction product thereof, and an alkylene oxide. The fuel
additive composition deals with cleaning of injection ports, lubricating a fuel line
system in a diesel vehicle, and with minimizing corrosion in the fuel line system.
However, the use of a Mannich condensation product is neither disclosed nor
suggested.</p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0020">It has now been discovered that a certain combination of a Mannich condensation
product, a hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool, and a carboxylic acid
affords a unique fuel additive composition which provides excellent control of
engine deposits, particularly engine intake system deposits, such as intake valve
deposits.</p><p num="0021">Accordingly, the present invention provides a novel fuel additive composition
comprising:
<sl><li>a) a Mannich condensation product of (1) a high molecular weight alkyl-substituted
hydroxyaromatic compound wherein the alkyl group has
a number average molecular weight of from about 300 to about
5,000 (2) an amine which contains an amino group having at least
one active hydrogen atom, and (3) an aldehyde, wherein the
respective molar ratio of reactants (1), (2), and (3) is 1:0.1-10:0.1-10;</li><li>b) a hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool having an
average molecular weight of about 500 to about 5,000, wherein the
oxyalkylene group is a C<sub>2</sub> to C<sub>5</sub> oxyalkylene group and the
hydrocarbyl group is a C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbyl group; and</li><li>c) a carboxylic acid as represented by the formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>1</sub>(COOH)<sub>x</sub></st32:che> 
or anhydride thereof, wherein R<sub>1</sub> represents a hydrocarbyl group
having about 2 to about 50 carbon atoms, and x represents an
integer of 1 to about 4.</li></sl></p><p num="0022">The present invention further provides a fuel composition comprising a major
amount of hydrocarbons boiling in the gasoline or diesel range and an effective
deposit-controlling amount of a fuel additive composition of the present invention.</p><p num="0023">The present invention still further provides a fuel concentrate comprising an inert
stable oleophilic organic solvent boiling in the range of from about 150°F to about
400°F and from about 10 to about 90 weight percent of a fuel additive composition
of the present invention.</p><p num="0024">The present invention yet provides for a method of improving the compatibility of a
fuel additive composition comprising blending together the components of the fuel
additive composition of the present invention.</p><p num="0025">The present invention provides further still for a method of controlling engine
deposits in an internal combustion engine by operating an internal combustion
engine with a fuel composition containing the fuel additive composition of the
present invention.</p><p num="0026">Among other factors, the present invention is based on the surprising discovery
that the unique combination of a Mannich condensation product, a hydrocarbyl-terminated
poly(oxyalkylene) monool, and a carboxylic acid provides excellent
control of engine deposits, particularly engine intake system deposits, such as
intake valve deposits. It is not unusual for small quantities of low molecular weight
amine and amine-formaldehyde intermediate (both measured as water-soluble
amine) in the Mannich to interact with organic acid mixtures that are typically used
in fuel additive formulations to provide anti-corrosion properties. The interaction 
can lead to formation of insoluble material, haze, and flocs. Therefore, it is quite
surprising that the formulation compatibility is greatly improved by the presence of
a selected carboxylic acid or anhydride that interacts with the residual amine. In
addition, the selected carboxylic acid or anhydride provides anti-corrosion
properties. Thus, the improved compatibility manifests itself in less insoluble
material, haze, and flocs.</p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0027">The fuel additive composition of the present invention comprises a Mannich
condensation product, a hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool, and a
carboxylic acid.</p><heading><u style="single">Definitions</u></heading><p num="0028">Prior to discussing the present invention in detail, the following terms will have the
following meanings unless expressly stated to the contrary.</p><p num="0029">The term "hydrocarbyl" refers to an organic radical primarily composed of carbon
and hydrogen which may be aliphatic, alicyclic, aromatic or combinations thereof,
e.g., aralkyl or alkaryl. Such hydrocarbyl groups may also contain aliphatic
unsaturation, i.e., olefinic or acetylenic unsaturation, and may contain minor
amounts of heteroatoms, such as oxygen or nitrogen, or halogens, such as
chlorine. When used in conjunction with carboxylic fatty acids, hydrocarbyl will
also include olefinic unsaturation.</p><p num="0030">The term "alkyl" refers to both straight- and branched-chain alkyl groups.</p><p num="0031">The term "alkylene" refers to straight- and branched-chain alkylene groups having
at least 2 carbon atoms. Typical alkylene groups include, for example, ethylene
(-CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-), propylene (-CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-), isopropylene (-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)CH<sub>2</sub>-), n-butylene 
(-CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-), sec-butylene (-CH(CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>)CH<sub>2</sub>-), n-pentylene
(-CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>-), and the like.</p><p num="0032">The term "polyoxyalkylene" refers to a polymer or oligomer having the general
formula:
<img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="47" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="23"/>
wherein R<sub>a</sub> and R<sub>b</sub> are each independently hydrogen or lower alkyl groups, and c
is an integer from about 5 to about 100. When referring herein to the number of
oxyalkylene units in a particular polyoxyalkylene compound, it is to be understood
that this number refers to the average number of oxyalkylene units in such
compounds unless expressly stated to the contrary.</p><p num="0033">The term "fuel" or "hydrocarbon fuel" refers to normally liquid hydrocarbons having
boiling points in the range of gasoline and diesel fuels.</p><heading><u style="single">The Mannich Condensation Product</u></heading><p num="0034">Mannich reaction products employed in this invention are obtained by condensing
an alkyl-substituted hydroxyaromatic compound whose alkyl-substituent has a
number average molecular weight of from about 300 to about 5,000, preferably
polyalkylphenol whose polyalkyl substituent is derived from 1-mono-olefin
polymers having a number average molecular weight of from about 300 to about
5,000, more preferably from about 400 to about 3,000; an amine containing at
least one &gt;NH group, preferably an alkylene polyamine of the formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">H<sub>2</sub>N-(A-NH-)<sub>y</sub>H</st32:che> 
wherein A is a divalent alkylene radical having 1 to about 10 carbon atoms and y is
an integer from 1 to about 10; and an aldehyde, preferably formaldehyde, in the
presence of a solvent.</p><p num="0035">High molecular weight Mannich reaction products useful as additives in the fuel
additive compositions of this invention are preferably prepared according to
conventional methods employed for the preparation of Mannich condensation
products, using the above-named reactants in the respective molar ratios of high
molecular weight alkyl-substituted hydroxyaromatic compound, amine, and
aldehyde of approximately 1.0:0.1-10:1-10. A suitable condensation procedure
involves adding at a temperature of from room temperature to about 95°C, the
formaldehyde reagent (e.g., formalin) to a mixture of amine and alkyl-substituted
hydroxyaromatic compounds alone or in an easily removed organic solvent, such
as benzene, xylene, or toluene or in solvent-refined neutral oil, and then heating
the reaction mixture at an elevated temperature (about 120°C to about 175°C)
while the water of reaction is distilled overhead and separated. The reaction
product so obtained is finished by filtration and dilution with solvent as desired.</p><p num="0036">Preferred Mannich reaction product additives employed in this invention are
derived from high molecular weight Mannich condensation products, formed by
reacting an alkylphenol, an ethylene polyamine, and a formaldehyde affording
reactants in the respective molar ratio of 1.0:0.5-2.0:1.0-3.0, wherein the alkyl
group of the alkylphenol has a number average weight of from about 300 to about
5,000.</p><p num="0037">Representative of the high molecular weight alkyl-substituted hydroxyaromatic
compounds are polypropylphenol, polybutylphenol, and other polyalkylphenols,
with polyisobutylphenol being the most preferred. Polyalkylphenols may be
obtained by the alkylation, in the presence of an alkylating catalyst such as BF<sub>3</sub>, of
phenol with high molecular weight polypropylene, polybutylene, and other 
polyalkylene compounds to give alkyl substituents on the benzene ring of phenol
having a number average molecular weight of from about 300 to about 5,000.</p><p num="0038">The alkyl substituents on the hydroxyaromatic compounds may be derived from
high molecular weight polypropylenes, polybutenes, and other polymers of
mono-olefins, principally 1-mono-olefins. Also useful are copolymers of
mono-olefins with monomers copolymerizable therewith, wherein the copolymer
molecule contains at least about 90% by weight of mono-olefin units. Specific
examples are copolymers of butenes (1-butene, 2-butene, and isobutylene) with
monomers copolymerizable therewith wherein the copolymer molecule contains at
least about 90% by weight of propylene and butene units, respectively. Said
monomers copolymerizable with propylene or said butenes include monomers
containing a small proportion of unreactive polar groups, such as chloro, bromo,
keto, ether, or aldehyde, which do not appreciably lower the oil-solubility of the
polymer. The comonomers polymerized with propylene or said butenes may be
aliphatic and can also contain non-aliphatic groups, e.g., styrene, methylstyrene,
p-dimethylstyrene, divinyl benzene, and the like. From the foregoing limitation
placed on the monomer copolymerized with propylene or said butenes, it is clear
that said polymers and copolymers of propylene and said butenes are
substantially aliphatic hydrocarbon polymers. Thus, the resulting alkylated
phenols contain substantially alkyl hydrocarbon substitutents having a number
average molecular weight of from about 300 to about 5,000.</p><p num="0039">In addition to the foregoing high molecular weight hydroxyaromatic compounds,
other phenolic compounds which may be used include, high molecular weight
alkyl-substituted derivatives of resorcinol, hydroquinone, cresol, cathechol, xylenol,
hydroxy-di-phenyl, benzylphenol, phenethylphenol, naphthol, tolylnaphthol, among
others. Preferred for the preparation of such preferred Mannich condensation
products are the polyalkylphenol reactants, e.g., polypropylphenol and
polybutylphenol, particularly polyisobutylphenol, whose alkyl group has a number 
average molecular weight of about 300 to about 5,000, preferably about 400 to
about 3,000, more preferably about 500 to about 2,000, and most preferably about
700 to about 1,500.</p><p num="0040">As noted above, the polyalkyl substituent on the polyalkyl hydroxyaromatic
compounds employed in the invention may be generally derived from polyolefins
which are polymers or copolymers of mono-olefins, particularly 1-mono-olefins,
such as ethylene, propylene, butylene, and the like. Preferably, the mono-olefin
employed will have about 2 to about 24 carbon atoms, and more preferably, about
3 to about 12 carbon atoms. More preferred mono-olefins include propylene,
butylene, particularly isobutylene, 1-octene and 1-decene. Polyolefins prepared
from such mono-olefins include polypropylene, polybutene, especially
polyisobutene, and the polyalphaolefins produced from 1-octene and 1-decene.</p><p num="0041">The preferred polyisobutenes used to prepare the presently employed polyalkyl
hydroxyaromatic compounds are polyisobutenes which comprise at least about
20% of the more reactive methylvinylidene isomer, preferably at least about 50%
and more preferably at least about 70% methylvinylidene isomer. Suitable
polyisobutenes include those prepared using BF<sub>3</sub> catalysts. The preparation of
such polyisobutenes in which the methylvinylidene isomer comprises a high
percentage of the total composition is described in U.S. Patent
Nos. 4,152,499 and 4,605,808.</p><p num="0042">Examples of suitable polyisobutenes having a high alkylvinylidene content include
Ultravis 10, a polyisobutene having a molecular weight of about 950 and a
methylvinylidine content of about 76%, and Ultravis 30, a polyisobutene having a
molecular weight of about 1,300 and a methylvinylidene content of about
74%, both available from British Petroleum, and Glissopal 1000, 1300, and
2200, available from BASF. </p><p num="0043">The preferred configuration of the alkyl-substituted hydroxyaromatic compound is
that of a para-substituted mono-alkylphenol. However, any alkylphenol readily
reactive in the Mannich condensation reaction may be employed. Accordingly,
ortho mono-alkylphenols and dialkylphenols are suitable for use in this invention.</p><p num="0044">Representative amine reactants are alkylene polyamines, principally polyethylene
polyamines. Other representative organic compounds containing at least one
&gt;NH group suitable for use in the preparation of the Mannich reaction products are
well known and include the mono- and di-amino alkanes and their substituted
analogs, e.g., ethylamine, dimethylamine, dimethylaminopropyl amine, and
diethanol amine; aromatic diamines, e.g., phenylene diamine, diamino
naphthalenes; heterocyclic amines, e.g., morpholine, pyrrole, pyrrolidine,
imidazole, imidazolinidine, and piperidine; melamine and their substituted analogs.</p><p num="0045">The alkylene polyamine reactants which are useful with this invention include
polyamines which are linear, branched, or cyclic; or a mixture of linear, branched
and/or cyclic polyamines wherein each alkylene group contains from 1 to about 10
carbon atoms. A preferred polyamine is a polyamine containing from about
2 to about 10 nitrogen atoms per molecule or a mixture of polyamines containing
an average of from about 2 to about 10 nitrogen atoms per molecule such as
ethylenediamine, diethylene triamine, triethylene tetramine, tetraethylene
pentamine, pentaethylene hexamine, hexaethylene heptamine, heptaethylene
octamine, octaethylene nonamine, monoethylene decamine, and mixtures of such
amines. Corresponding propylene polyamines such as propylene diamine,
dipropylene triamine, tripropylene tetramine, tetrapropylene pentamine, and
pentapropylene hexamine are also suitable reactants. A particularly preferred
polyamine is a polyamine or mixture of polyamines having from about 3 to about 7
nitrogen atoms, with diethylene triamine or a combination or mixture of ethylene
polyamines whose physical and chemical properties approximate that of
diethylene triamine being the most preferred. In selecting an appropriate 
polyamine, consideration should be given to the compatibility of the resulting
detergent/dispersant with the gasoline fuel mixture with which it is mixed.</p><p num="0046">Ordinarily the most highly preferred polyamine, diethylene triamine, will comprise a
commercially available mixture having the general overall physical and/or chemical
composition approximating that of diethylene triamine but which can contain minor
amounts of branched-chain and cyclic species as well as some linear polyethylene
polyamines such as triethylene tetramine and tetraethylene pentamine. For best
results, such mixtures should contain at least about 50% and preferably at least
about 70% by weight of the linear polyethylene polyamines enriched in diethylene
triamine.</p><p num="0047">The alkylene polyamines are usually obtained by the reaction of ammonia and
dihalo alkanes, such as dichloro alkanes. Thus, the alkylene polyamines are
obtained from the reaction of about 2 to about 11 moles of ammonia with 1 to
about 10 moles of dichloro alkanes having about 2 to about 6 carbon atoms and
the chlorines on different carbons.</p><p num="0048">Representative aldehydes for use in the preparation of the high molecular weight
Mannich reaction products employed in this invention include the aliphatic
aldehydes such as formaldehyde, acetaldehyde, propionaldehyde, butyraldehyde,
valeraldehyde, caproaldehyde, heptaldehyde, and stearaldehyde. Aromatic
aldehydes which may be used include benzaldehyde and salicylaldehyde.
Illustrative heterocyclic aldehydes for use herein are furfural and thiophene
aldehyde, etc. Also useful are formaldehyde-producing reagents such as
paraformaldehyde, or aqueous formaldehyde solutions such as formalin. Most
preferred is formaldehyde or formalin. </p><heading><u style="single">The Hydrocarbyl-Terminated Poly(oxyalkylene) Monool</u></heading><p num="0049">The hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) polymers employed in the present
invention are monohydroxy compounds, i.e., alcohols, often termed monohydroxy
polyethers, or polyalkylene glycol monohydrocarbylethers, or "capped"
poly(oxyalkylene) glycols and are to be distinguished from the poly(oxyalkylene)
glycols (diols), or polyols, which are not hydrocarbyl-terminated, i.e., not capped.
The hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) alcohols are produced by the
addition of lower alkylene oxides, such as ethylene oxide, propylene oxide, the
butylene oxides, or the pentylene oxides to the hydroxy compound R<sub>2</sub>OH under
polymerization conditions, wherein R<sub>2</sub> is the hydrocarbyl group which caps the
poly(oxyalkylene) chain. Methods of production and properties of these polymers
are disclosed in U.S. Pat. Nos. 2,841,479 and 2,782,240 and Kirk-Othmer's
"Encyclopedia of Chemical Technology", 2<sup>nd</sup> Ed Volume 19, p. 507. In the
polymerization reaction, a single type of alkylene oxide may be employed, e.g.,
propylene oxide, in which case the product is a homopolymer, e.g., a
poly(oxyalkylene) propanol. However, copolymers are equally satisfactory and
random copolymers are readily prepared by contacting the hydroxyl-containing
compound with a mixture of alkylene oxides, such as a mixture of propylene and
butylene oxides. Block copolymers of oxyalkylene units also provide satisfactory
poly(oxyalkylene) polymers for the practice of the present invention. Random
polymers are more easily prepared when the reactivities of the oxides are
relatively equal. In certain cases, when ethylene oxide is copolymerized with other
oxides, the higher reaction rate of ethylene oxide makes the preparation of random
copolymers difficult. In either case, block copolymers can be prepared. Block
copolymers are prepared by contacting the hydroxyl-containing compound with
first one alkylene oxide, then the others in any order, or repetitively, under
polymerization conditions. A particular block copolymer is represented by a
polymer prepared by polymerizing propylene oxide on a suitable monohydroxy 
compound to form a poly(oxypropylene) alcohol and then polymerizing butylene
oxide on the poly(oxyalkylene) alcohol.</p><p num="0050">In general, the poly(oxyalkylene) polymers are mixtures of compounds that differ in
polymer chain length. However, their properties closely approximate those of the
polymer represented by the average composition and molecular weight.</p><p num="0051">The polyethers employed in this invention can be represented by the formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>2</sub>O-(R<sub>3</sub>O)<sub>z</sub>-H</st32:che>
wherein R<sub>2</sub> is a hydrocarbyl group of from 1 to about 30 carbon atoms; R<sub>3</sub> is a C<sub>2</sub>
to C<sub>5</sub> alkylene group; and z is an integer such that the molecular weight of the
polyether is from about 500 to about 5,000.</p><p num="0052">Preferably, R<sub>2</sub> is a C<sub>7</sub> to C<sub>30</sub> alkylphenyl group. Most preferably, R<sub>2</sub> is
dodecylphenyl.</p><p num="0053">Preferably, R<sub>3</sub> is a C<sub>3</sub> or C<sub>4</sub> alkylene group. Most preferably, R<sub>3</sub> is a C<sub>3</sub> alkylene
group.</p><p num="0054">Preferably, the polyether has a molecular weight of from about 750 to about 3,000;
and more preferably from about 900 to about 1,500.</p><heading><u style="single">The Carboxylic Acid</u></heading><p num="0055">The fuel additive composition of the present invention may further contain a
carboxylic acid compound. The carboxylic acid to be employed in the invention
preferably is a compound which is represented by the formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>1</sub>(COOH)<sub>x</sub></st32:che> 
or anhydride thereof, wherein R<sub>1</sub> represents a hydrocarbyl group having about 2 to
about 50 carbon atoms, and x represents an integer of 1 to about 4.</p><p num="0056">The preferred hydrocarbyl groups are aliphatic groups, such as an alkyl group or
an alkenyl group, which may have a straight chain or a branched chain. Examples
of preferred carboxylic acids are aliphatic acids having about 8 to about 30 carbon
atoms and include caprylic acid, pelargonic acid, capric acid, lauric acid, myristic
acid, palmitic acid, margaric acid, stearic acid, isostearic acid, arachidic acid,
behenic acid, lignoceric acid, cerotic acid, montanic acid, melissic acid, caproleic
acid, palmitoleic acid, oleic acid, eraidic acid, linolic acid, linoleic acid, fatty acid or
coconut oil, fatty acid of hardened fish oil, fatty acid of hardened rapeseed oil, fatty
acid of hardened tallow oil, and fatty acid of hardened palm oil. The examples
further include dodecenyl succinic acid and its anhydride. Preferably, the
carboxylic acid is oleic acid.</p><heading><u style="single">Improved Compatibility</u></heading><p num="0057">One aspect of the present invention is a method of improving the compatibility of a
fuel additive composition which comprises blending together:
<sl><li>a) a Mannich condensation product of (1) a high molecular weight alkyl-substituted
hydroxyaromatic compound wherein the alkyl group has
a number average molecular weight of from 300 to about 5,000 (2)
an amine which contains an amino group having at least one active
hydrogen atom, and (3) an aldehyde, wherein the respective molar
ratio of reactants (1), (2), and (3) is 1:0.1-10:0.1-10;</li><li>b) a hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool having an
average molecular weight of about 500 to about 5,000, wherein the 
oxyalkylene group is a C<sub>2</sub> to C<sub>5</sub> oxyalkylene group and the
hydrocarbyl group is a C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbyl group; and</li><li>c) a carboxylic acid as represented by the formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>1</sub>(COOH)<sub>x</sub></st32:che>
or anhydride thereof, wherein R<sub>1</sub> represents a hydrocarbyl group
having about 2 to about 50 carbon atoms, and x represents an
integer of 1 to about 4; wherein the Mannich condensation product
and the carboxylic acid are blended together at a temperature
ranging from about room temperature (about 20°C) to about 100°C.</li></sl></p><p num="0058">In general, the amount of carboxylic acid is about 1 to about 10% of the weight of
the Mannich condensation product, or there is typically about 0.2 to about 1.5
equivalent of carboxylic acid per equivalent of water-soluble amine in the Mannich
condensation product.</p><p num="0059">In fuel additive applications, the presence of small amounts of low molecular
weight amine in dispersant components such as the Mannich condensation
product can lead to formulation incompatibilities (for example, with certain
corrosion inhibitors or demulsifiers) and air sensitivity (for example, reaction with
carbon dioxide in the air). For example, corrosion inhibitors are typically complex
mixtures of organic acids of wide molecular weight range. These can react with
trace amounts of low molecular weight amines in the Mannich component at room
temperature to form insoluble salts and at higher temperatures to form insoluble
amides. Formulation incompatibility and air sensitivity are manifested by formation
of haze, floc, solids, and/or gelatinous material in the formulation over time. The
incompatibility may occur in the absence of air. Consequently, the manufacturing
process for amine dispersant type fuel additives may include a step to remove low
molecular weight amines to low levels, or the compatibility issue may be
addressed during formulation. However, the unique chemistry of Mannich 
condensation products must be considered with either approach. In particular, the
chemical equilibrium can generate additional low molecular weight amines if the
product is heated too much during the purification step or after a formulation has
been prepared. Therefore, there is a need for either an economical process to
reduce the unconsumed amine and the amine-formaldehyde intermediate to a low
level after the Mannich reaction or a chemical scavenger that renders the water-soluble
amine harmless to formulation compatibility. The carboxylic acid treatment
of the Mannich condensation product of the present invention provides improved
compatibility with other additives in the desired finished fuel additive composition.
Compatibility in this instance generally means that the components in the present
invention as well as being fuel soluble in the applicable treat rate also do not
cause other additives to precipitate under normal conditions. The improved
compatibility manifests itself in less insoluble material, haze, and flocs.</p><heading><u style="single">Fuel Compositions</u></heading><p num="0060">The fuel additive composition of the present invention will generally be employed
in hydrocarbon fuels to prevent and control engine deposits, particularly intake
valve deposits. Typically, the desired control of engine deposits will be achieved
by operating an internal combustion engine with a fuel composition containing the
additive composition of the present invention. The proper concentration of additive
necessary to achieve the desired control of engine deposits varies depending
upon the type of fuel employed, the type of engine, engine oil, operating conditions
and the presence of other fuel additives.</p><p num="0061">Generally, the present fuel additive composition will be employed in a hydrocarbon
fuel in a concentration ranging from about 31 to about 4,000 parts per million
(ppm) by weight, preferably from about 51 to about 2,500 ppm. </p><p num="0062">In terms of individual components, hydrocarbon fuel containing the fuel additive
composition of this invention will generally contain about 20 to about 1,000 ppm,
preferably about 30 to about 400 ppm, of the Mannich condensation product
component, about 10 to about 4,000 ppm, preferably about 20 to about 800 ppm,
of the hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool component, and 1 to
about 100, preferably 1 to about 20 ppm of the carboxylic acid. The weight ratio of
the Mannich condensation product to hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene)
monool to carboxylic acid will generally range from about 100:50:1 to about
100:400:10, and will preferably be about 100:50:1 to about 100:300:5.</p><p num="0063">Preferably, the Mannich condensation product and carboxylic acid will be blended
together at a temperature ranging from about room temperature (about 20°C) to
about 100°C, more preferably from about room temperature to about 75°C, and
most preferably, from about room temperature to about 60°C.</p><p num="0064">The fuel additive composition of the present invention may be formulated as a
concentrate using an inert stable oleophilic (i.e., dissolves in gasoline) organic
solvent boiling in the range of about 150°F to about 400°F (about 65°C to about
205°C). Preferably, an aliphatic or an aromatic hydrocarbon solvent is used, such
as benzene, toluene, xylene, or higher-boiling aromatics or aromatic thinners.
Aliphatic alcohols containing about 3 to about 8 carbon atoms, such as
isopropanol, isobutylcarbinol, n-butanol, and the like, in combination with
hydrocarbon solvents are also suitable for use with the present additives. In the
concentrate, the amount of the additive will generally range from about 10 to about
70 weight percent, preferably about 10 to about 50 weight percent, more
preferably from about 20 to about 40 weight percent.</p><p num="0065">In gasoline fuels, other fuel additives may be employed with the additive
composition of the present invention, including, for example, oxygenates, such as
t-butyl methyl ether, antiknock agents, such as methylcyclopentadienyl 
manganese tricarbonyl, and other dispersants/detergents, such as hydrocarbyl
amines, or succinimides. Additionally, antioxidants, corrosion inhibitors, metal
deactivators, demulsifiers, other inhibitors, and carburetor or fuel injector
detergents may be present.</p><p num="0066">In diesel fuels, other well-known additives can be employed, such as pour point
depressants, flow improvers, lubricity improvers, cetane improvers, and the like.</p><p num="0067">The gasoline and diesel fuels employed with the fuel additive composition of the
present invention include clean burning gasoline where levels of sulfur, aromatics
and olefins range from typical amounts to only trace amounts and clean burning
diesel fuel where levels of sulfur and aromatics range from typical amounts to only
trace amounts.</p><p num="0068">A fuel-soluble, nonvolatile carrier fluid or oil may also be used with the fuel additive
composition of this invention. The carrier fluid is a chemically inert hydrocarbon-soluble
liquid vehicle which substantially increases the nonvolatile residue (NVR),
or solvent-free liquid fraction of the fuel additive composition while not
overwhelmingly contributing to octane requirement increase. The carrier fluid may
be a natural or synthetic fluid, such as mineral oil, refined petroleum oils, synthetic
polyalkanes and alkenes, including hydrogenated and unhydrogenated
polyalphaolefins, and synthetic polyoxyalkylene-derived fluids, such as those
described, for example, in U.S. Patent No. 4,191,537 to Lewis, and polyesters,
such as those described, for example, in U.S. Patent Nos. 3,756,793 to Robinson
and 5,004,478 to Vogel et al., and in European Patent Application Nos. 356,726,
published March 7, 1990, and 382,159, published August 16, 1990.</p><p num="0069">These carrier fluids are believed to act as a carrier for the fuel additive composition
of the present invention and to assist in the control of engine deposits, particularly
engine intake system deposits, such as the intake valves. The carrier fluid may 
also exhibit synergistic engine deposit control properties when used in
combination with the fuel additive composition of this invention.</p><p num="0070">The carrier fluids are typically employed in amounts ranging from about 25 to
about 5,000 ppm by weight of the hydrocarbon fuel, preferably from about 100 to
about 3,000 ppm of the fuel. Preferably, the ratio of carrier fluid to fuel additive will
range from about 0.2:1 to about 10:1, more preferably from about 0.5:1 to about
3:1.</p><p num="0071">When employed in a fuel concentrate, carrier fluids will generally be present in
amounts ranging from about 20 to about 60 weight percent, preferably from about
30 to about 50 weight percent.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLES</b></heading><p num="0072">The invention will be further illustrated by the following examples, which set forth
particularly advantageous specific embodiments of the present invention. While
the examples are provided to illustrate the present invention, it is not intended to
limit it.</p><p num="0073">In the following examples and tables, the components of the fuel additive
composition are defined as follows:
<sl><li>A. The term "Mannich" refers to a Mannich condensation product made
from the reaction of polyisobutylphenol, formaldehyde, and
diethylenetriamine in a ratio of 1:2:1, prepared in the manner as
described in Example 1. The polyisobutylphenol was produced from
polyisobutylene containing at least 70% methylvinylidene isomer as
described in U.S. Patent No. 5,300,701. </li><li>B. The Oleic Acid was available as TI 05 from Cognis Corporation as
well as from J. T. Baker Company and other suppliers.</li><li>C. The term "POPA" refers to a dodecylphenyl-terminated
poly(oxypropylene) monool having an average molecular weight of
about 1,000.</li></sl></p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 1 - MANNICH CONDENSATION PRODUCT</b></heading><p num="0074">A Mannich condensation product was produced in a reactor equipped with a
distillation column and an overhead Dean-Stark trap system by the following
general procedure. A solution of polyisobutylphenol in Solvesso Aromatic 100
solvent was charged to the reactor at about 40° to 45°C. Solvesso Aromatic 100
solvent is manufactured by Exxon-Mobil Chemical Company. The
polyisobutylphenol was produced from polyisobutylene containing at least 70%
methylvinylidene isomer as described in U.S. Patent No. 5,300,701. The
polyisobutylphenol had a nonvolatile residue of 62.1% and a hydroxyl number of
39.1 mg KOH/g. Diethylenetriamine (DETA) having an assay of 99.2% was
charged to the reactor in the ratio one mole of DETA per mole of
polyisobutylphenol and thoroughly mixed with the polyisobutylphenol. Heating of
the reactor was started after charging of the DETA. When the reactor temperature
was about 55° to 60°C, paraformaldehyde, having a purity of 91.9%, was charged
to the reactor. The charge ratio was two moles of formaldehyde per mole of
polyisobutylphenol. The temperature was increased over three hours to about
175° to 177°C and the pressure gradually lowered to about 520 to 540 mm Hg. As
byproduct water formed, water and solvent vapor distilled from the reactor and
passed up through the distillation column. The byproduct water and solvent were
separated and the solvent returned to the column as reflux so that no net solvent
was taken overhead. The final temperature and pressure were held for 6 hours to
make sure the Mannich condensation reaction went to completion. The Mannich
condensation product was cooled to 40°C, transferred to a filter-feed tank, and 
polished filtered using a filter precoat of HyFlo Super Cel filter aid. Crude product
was used as the precoat liquor, and then the Mannich condensation product was
passed through the filter without any filter aid as body feed. HyFlo Super Cel filter
aid is a diatomaceous earth manufactured by World Minerals Incorporated.

The Mannich condensation product was clear (0% haze using Nippon Denshoku
Model 300A haze meter), light gold in color (2.5 by ASTM D1500), and contained
2.8% nitrogen and 70% nonvolatile residue. A 3-gram sample of the Mannich
condensation product was diluted with 100 mL of hexane and 0.1 mL of
demulsifier and then extracted twice with 40 mL of warm water. The water extract
was titrated with 0.1 N hydrochloric acid. The water-soluble amine content was
measured as 0.176 mEq/g.</p><p num="0075">In another analytical method, 2 g of the Mannich condensation product was diluted
with 0.5 g of n-butanol and 1 g of deionized water in a vial and thoroughly mixed.
After phase separation, the aqueous layer was recovered and analyzed by gas
chromatography (GC). Reference standards and mass spectroscopy were used to
identify the major peaks. Based on this analysis, the Mannich condensation
product contained 0.61% DETA and 0.16% of 1-(2-aminoethyl), 3-isodiazolidine
(DETA with one formaldehyde-derived methylene group bridging two adjacent
nitrogens). There were other DETA-formaldehyde compounds present, but the
major constituent was 1-(2-aminoethyl), 3-isodiazolidine. The GC method does not
account for all of the water-soluble amine measured by the titration method
because not all GC peaks are quantified and because of differences in the
extraction procedures.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 2 - MANNICH CONDENSATION PRODUCT</b></heading><p num="0076">Following the same procedure and charge mole ratios as in Example 1, a second
batch of Mannich condensation product was produced. The starting
polyisobutylphenol had a nonvolatile residue of 67.5% and a hydroxyl number of 
40.0 mg KOH/g. The DETA had an assay of 99.2% and the paraformaldehyde an
assay of 91.6%. The Mannich condensation product was cooled to 60°C and
transferred to storage without the need for filtering.</p><p num="0077">The Mannich condensation product was clear (1% haze using Nippon Denshoku
Model 300A haze meter), light gold in color (2.5 by ASTM D1500), and contained
2.7% nitrogen and 72% nonvolatile residue. The water-soluble amine content was
measured as 0.176 mEq/g, giving the same result as in Example 1.

The gas chromatography analysis indicated that the Mannich condensation
product contained 0.65% DETA and 0.15% of 1-(2-aminoethyl), 3-isodiazolidine.
Again, there were other DETA-formaldehyde compounds present, but the major
constituent was 1-(2-aminoethyl), 3-isodiazolidine.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 3 - COMPARATIVE COMPATIBILITY AND AIR SENSITIVITY OF
FORMULATION WITH MANNICH CONDENSATION PRODUCT</b></heading><p num="0078">A typical formulation was blended at room temperature with treated Mannich
condensation product and was used to test the effect of water-soluble amine
concentration in the Mannich product on the compatibility and air sensitivity of the
formulation with other components. The formulation is shown in Table 1. Light
alkylate solvent is an aromatic solvent manufactured by Chevron Oronite S.A.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Typical Compatibility and Air Sensitivity Test Formulation</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Component</entry><entry align="center">Weight Percent</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mannich condensation product</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Light alkylate solvent</entry><entry align="center">38.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Synthetic carrier fluid</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Demulsifier</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Corrosion inhibitor</entry><entry align="center">0.8</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0079">Mannich condensation product formulation compatibility is measured at room
temperature in a 100-mL cylindrical oil sample bottle made of clear glass and filled
with the formulation. A cork is inserted into the mouth of the bottle to keep out air.
The sample is stored in a rack open to the light in the room. Two qualitative visual
rating scales are used; one for fluid appearance with ratings in the range of 0 to 6,
and one for the amount of sedimentation with ratings in the range 0 to 4. A low
rating number indicates good compatibility and a high rating number indicates poor
compatibility. For example, an appearance rating of 6 means the formulation
contained heavy cloud (close to opaque). A rating of 4 for sedimentation indicates
the presence of a large amount of sediment in the bottom of the bottle. The typical
requirement for a pass in this test is a fluid appearance rating in the range of 0 to 2
(absolutely bright to slight cloud) and a sedimentation rating 0 to 1 (no sediment to
very slight sediment).</p><p num="0080">The air sensitivity of the test formulation containing treated Mannich condensation
product is measured at room temperature using about 100 g of sample in a 250-mL
beaker that is open to the air. A 500-mL beaker is inverted over the 250-mL
beaker to keep out air drafts that would quickly cause solvent evaporation, while
still allowing equilibration with the surrounding air. The beaker is weighed at the
end to make sure the weight loss due to solvent evaporation is less than about
5%. If enough solvent is lost, phase separation can occur. The air sensitivity test
uses the same rating scales as the compatibility test. Both tests are supplemented
when possible with haze measurements using a Nippon Denshoku Model 300A
haze meter.</p><p num="0081">Diluted crude Mannich condensation product from Examples 1 and 2, each
containing 0.176 mEq/g of water-soluble amine, were evaluated in the
compatibility test for up to 30 days as shown in Table 2. Both diluted crude
Mannich condensation product samples caused failures in the formulation
compatibility test. </p><p num="0082">The formulation that contained diluted crude Mannich condensation product from
Example 1 failed immediately after blending due to cloud formation and had a
haze of 55.1% after 30 days.</p><p num="0083">The formulation that contained diluted crude Mannich condensation product from
Example 2 failed the test immediately after blending due to haze, floc, and
sediment. The percent haze after 30 days for three different samples was in the
range about 36.6 to 58.8%. Percent haze over about 15 to 20% is considered
unacceptable.</p><p num="0084">Since both samples did poorly in the compatibility test, no air sensitivity tests were
conducted. Analysis of the sediment by infrared spectroscopy (IR) and nuclear
magnetic spectroscopy (NMR) indicated the haze was caused by a reaction of the
carboxylic acid corrosion inhibitor with the residual amine in the Mannich
condensation product.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">Comparative Formulation Compatibility with Untreated Mannich Condensation Product</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry align="center" namest="2"/><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">Fluid/Sediment Rating in Compatibility Test</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Example</entry><entry align="center">Blend Number</entry><entry align="center">Initial</entry><entry align="center">7-days</entry><entry align="center">30-days</entry><entry align="center">%Haze (30-days)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">6/2</entry><entry align="center">55.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">6/0</entry><entry align="center">6/2</entry><entry align="center">58.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">11</entry><entry align="center">4/2</entry><entry align="center">3/2</entry><entry align="center">3/3</entry><entry align="center">36.6</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">13</entry><entry align="center">4/1</entry><entry align="center">3/2</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">41.8</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 4 - IMPROVEMENT OF COMPATIBILITY WITH OLEIC ACID</b></heading><p num="0085">After charging 200 g of Mannich condensation product from Example 2 to a 500-mL
reaction flask, 9.94 g of oleic acid from J. T. Baker Company (1 equivalent per
equivalent of water-soluble amine or 5.0% oleic acid on untreated Mannich
product) was added and the mixture was stirred and held at 100°C. The oleic acid
had an acid number of 202 mg KOH/g. The measured water-soluble amine
content of the treated Mannich was 0.171 mEg/g indicating that a salt was
probably formed between the oleic acid and residual amine as opposed to an
amide. This procedure was repeated at 60°C using 0.5 and 0.25 equivalents of
oleic acid per equivalent of water-soluble amine (2.5% and 1.24% oleic acid on
Mannich condensation product from Example 2). The water soluble amine
contents of the treated Mannich were 0.153 mEg/g and 0.169 mEg/g, respectively,
again indicating little change in the original water-soluble amine content of the
Mannich product and the presence of an oleic acid salt. The closed-bottle
compatibility test was performed using these three samples and gave the results in
Table 3.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">Formulation Compatibility of Oleic Acid Treated Mannich Condensation Product</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry align="center" namest="2"/><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="3">Fluid/Sediment Rating in Compatibility Test</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Blend Number</entry><entry align="center">Oleic Acid, % of Example 2 Mannich</entry><entry align="center">Initial</entry><entry align="center">7-days</entry><entry align="center">30-days</entry><entry align="center">% Haze (30-days)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">24</entry><entry align="center">5.0</entry><entry align="center">1/0</entry><entry align="center">1/0</entry><entry align="center">1/0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">1/0</entry><entry align="center">1/0</entry><entry align="center">1/0</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">26 Comparative</entry><entry align="center">1.24</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">18.7</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0086">At 2.5% and 5% treat levels of the Mannich condensation product with oleic acid,
the formulation compatibility was changed from an immediate failure to a strong
pass. A treat level of 1.24% was not adequate to pass the compatibility test.
These results are very surprising because the oleic acid seems to prefer to react
with the residual amine rather than the amine that is part of the Mannich base
structure. In addition, the offending corrosion inhibitor has carboxylic acid
functionality like the oleic acid.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 5 - EFFECT OF OLEIC ACID TREATMENT TEMPERATURE ON
FORMULATION COMPATIBILITY</b></heading><p num="0087">Mannich condensation product from Example 2 was treated with 3% oleic acid
(percent on untreated product) at 20°C (room temperature) and 60°C following the
procedure in Example 4. Two other samples were prepared at 150°C following a
slightly different procedure.</p><p num="0088">A 150°C temperature treatment was done as follows. 2,000 g of untreated
Mannich condensation product from Example 2 were charged to a 5-L cylindrical
reactor equipped with an agitator, heating mantle with temperature control, and
Dean-Stark trap for collecting water. 60 g of the oleic acid described in Example 4
were added to the reactor and mixed with the Mannich condensation product. The
mixture was heated to 150°C with nitrogen purge of about 50 cm<sup>3</sup>/minute and held
at this temperature for 2 hours. There was negligible refluxing. After cooling to
room temperature, the final mixture weight was 2,055.3 g indicating a weight loss
of 4.7 g. Theoretical water yield was estimated as 7.8 g if all oxygen is eliminated
as water (imidazo linkage) or half as much if a simple amide linkage is formed.
The Dean-Stark trap recovery was only 0.4 mL of water. It was unclear whether
the water of reaction was removed. The water-soluble amine content after the
treatment was 0.178 mEg/g. This gave a clear product that was light golden 
brown in color with a total nitrogen of 2.60%, nonvolatile residue of 72.8%, haze of
3.7%. This treatment corresponds to Blend Number 60.</p><p num="0089">The 150°C temperature procedure was repeated with 2,000 g of untreated
Mannich condensation product from Example 2 and 60 g of oleic acid except the
pressure was lowered during the hold period to 264 mm Hg in order to force reflux
to the Dean-Stark trap. This gave a final treated product weight of 2,015.9 g. 39.8
g of Exxon Aromatic 100 solvent was added back to make up for the solvent loss
to the Dean-Stark trap and dry ice trap. 4.1 g of water phase was collected in the
Dean-Stark trap and 4.3 g in the dry ice trap giving a total of 8.4 g of water phase.
The theoretical water yield, if an amide is formed, is about 7.8 g. The Dean-Stark
trap contained 16.7 g of solvent phase while the dry ice trap contained 2.3 g of
solvent phase. This gave a clear product that was light golden brown in color with
a water-soluble amine content of 0.116 mEg/g, total nitrogen of 2.56%, nonvolatile
residue of 70.5%, haze of 3.9%. This treatment corresponds to Blend Number 63.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1">Formulation Compatibility of Mannich Condensation Product Treated with Oleic Acid at Various Temperatures</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry align="center" namest="2"/><entry align="center" namest="3"/><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="4">Fluid/Sediment Rating in Compatibility Test</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Blend Number</entry><entry align="center">Oleic Acid % of Example 2 Mannich Product</entry><entry align="center">Treatment Temp., °C</entry><entry align="center">Initial</entry><entry align="center">7-days</entry><entry align="center">30-days</entry><entry align="center">% Haze (30-days)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">72</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">RT<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">1/0</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">86</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">RT</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">59</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="center">1/0</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">150</entry><entry align="center">2/0</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">32.2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative</entry></row><row><entry align="center">63</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">150</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">3/1</entry><entry align="center">20.6</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Comparative<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0090">Table 4 shows that both high temperature treatments gave poor results while
treatments at room temperature (RT), 60°C, and 100°C (Example 4) gave good
compatibility results. Blend Number 24 in Table 4 gives a direct comparison with
Blend 86 in Table 3 using 5% oleic acid at 100°C. The 150°C temperature
treatment results are not surprising considering that the Mannich condensation
product is in equilibrium with the DETA and DETA-formaldehyde intermediates.
Thus, while the oleic acid is reacting with some residual amine, more is being
generated.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 6 - EFFECT OF OLEIC ACID TREATMENT ON FORMULATION AIR
SENSITIVITY</b></heading><p num="0091">Several formulation samples using oleic acid treated Mannich product were
evaluated for air sensitivity using the test described in Example 3. This is a very
severe test since the formulation would incur minimal air exposure during storage
and handling. If solvent loss during the test is excessive, phase separation of
components can occur. Table 5 shows the air sensitivity ratings. These ratings
are much more difficult to perform with a 250-mL beaker compared to a 100-mL
cylindrical bottle. The variability that can be encountered in the rating during this
test is exemplified by the initial readings for Blends 82 and 92 in Table 5.
Sometimes a maximum sediment rating of 4 was given regardless of the quantity
of sediment simply because the material was gelatinous indicating a component
separation.</p><p num="0092">Using a maximum fluid/sediment rating of 2/1 as a pass in the test, the formulation
air sensitivity was acceptable up to about 3 to 8 days, depending upon the sample,
as shown in Table 5. This is an improvement over an immediate failure on
blending when no oleic acid treatment is done as shown in Example 3. None of
these samples exhibit typical sediment, but rather the formation of very small
gelatinous droplets that accumulate on the bottom and the side of the beaker at 
the air interface. It appears the material forms at the air interface and some of it
settles to the bottom of the beaker. A sample of the gelatinous material was
recovered and analyzed by IR, proton-NMR, and carbon-NMR. It was determined
to be a DETA-carbamate salt formed by the reaction of CO<sub>2</sub> in the air with DETA.
This effect was not seen with the formulations made from untreated Mannich
product because the formulations failed the compatibility test immediately due to
haze and floc.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Air Sensitivity Test of Formulations with Mannich Condensation Product Treated with Oleic Acid at Various Temperatures</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Blend Number</entry><entry align="center">82</entry><entry align="center">92</entry><entry align="center">86</entry> </row><row><entry align="left">Oleic Acid on Example 2 Mannich, %</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">5</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">Treatment Temperature, °C</entry> <entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="center">RT<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">RT</entry></row><row><entry nameend="4" align="left" namest="1">Fluid/Sediment Rating in Air Sensitivity Test</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Initial</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">2/0</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1-day</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2/0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3-days</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2/4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4-days</entry><entry align="center">1/1</entry><entry align="center">2/4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">6-days</entry><entry align="center">2/1</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2/4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">7-days</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2/4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">8-days</entry><entry align="center">2/2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">9-days</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2/4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">11-days</entry><entry align="center">2/4</entry><entry align="center">2/4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">%Haze at 30-days</entry><entry align="center">2.1</entry><entry align="center">7.7</entry><entry align="center">2.8<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 7 - IMPROVING FORMULATION AIR SENSITIVITY WITH
DODECENYLSUCCINIC ANHYDRIDE</b></heading><p num="0093">200 g of Mannich condensation Example 2 were mixed with 9.73 g of
dodecenylsuccinic anhydride (DDSA) in a 500 mL reaction flask for 30 minutes at
60°C. DDSA was supplied by Milliken Chemicals and had a neutralization number
of 406 mg KOH/g. Milliken uses C<sub>12</sub> branched-olefin derived from propylene
tetramer to make DDSA. The appearance of the Mannich was unchanged by the
treatment. A second treatment was done at room temperature. Table 6 shows the
formulation compatibility was greatly improved after treatment of the Mannich
condensation product with one equivalent of DDSA per equivalent of water-soluble
amine compared to the untreated Mannich condensation product results in
Example 3, Table 2. Formulation air sensitivity was also improved considerably
over the oleic acid treatment method as shown in Table 7 compared to the results
in Table 5.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1">Formulation Compatibility of Mannich Condensation Product Treated with DDSA</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry align="center" namest="2"/><entry align="center" namest="3"/><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="4">Fluid/Sediment Rating in Compatibility Test</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Blend Number</entry><entry align="center">DDSA, % of Example 2 Mannich</entry><entry align="center">Treatment Temp., °C</entry><entry align="center">Initial</entry><entry align="center">7-days</entry><entry align="center">30-days</entry><entry align="center">% Haze (30-days)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">49</entry><entry align="center">4.9</entry><entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center">85</entry><entry align="center">4.9</entry><entry align="center">RT<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">0.2<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1">Air Sensitivity Test of Formulation with Mannich Condensation Product Treated with DDSA</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry align="center" namest="2"/><entry align="center" namest="3"/><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="4">Fluid/Sediment Rating (Open-Beaker)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Blend Number</entry><entry align="center">Oleic Acid % On Batch #2</entry><entry align="center">Treatment Temp., °C</entry><entry align="center">Initial</entry><entry align="center">7-days</entry><entry align="center">30-days</entry><entry align="center">% Haze (30-days)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">85</entry><entry align="center">4.9</entry><entry align="center">RT<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0/0</entry><entry align="center">1/0</entry><entry align="center">3/0</entry><entry align="center">7.5<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 8 - FORD 2.3L ENGINE DYNAMOMETER TESTING</b></heading><p num="0094">The fuel additive composition of the present invention was tested in a four-cylinder
Ford 2.3L engine dynamometer test stand to evaluate intake system deposit
control performance. The four-cylinder Ford 2.3L engine is port fuel injected and
has twin spark plugs. The engine is prepared for tests in accordance with
accepted engine testing practices. The engine test is 60 hours in length and
consists of 277 repetitions of a 13-minute cycle.</p><p num="0095">The details of the test cycle for the Ford 2.3L engine are set forth in Table 8.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">Ford 2.3L Engine Dynamometer Test Cycle</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Cycle Step Duration (Seconds)</entry><entry align="center">Engine Speed (RPM)</entry><entry align="center">Engine Manifold Absolute Pressure (Millimeters of Mercury)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   270</entry><entry align="center">2000</entry><entry align="center">230</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   510</entry><entry align="center">2800</entry><entry align="center">539</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total 780</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0096">The test results from the Ford 2.3L Engine Dynamometer Test are set forth in
Table 9. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">Ford 2.3L Engine Dynamometer Test Results</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Sample</entry><entry align="center">Mannich (ppma)</entry><entry align="center">Oleic Acid (ppm)</entry><entry align="center">POPA (ppm)</entry><entry align="center">Ratio (POPA/Mannich)</entry><entry align="center">AVG IVD (mg./vlv.)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Base</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">849.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">466.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="center">2.24<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">239.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="center">2.24<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">310.4</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="right">75</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="right">75</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">108</entry></row><row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="right">75</entry><entry align="center">3.4<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="right">75</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">101.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="right">75</entry><entry align="center">3.4<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="right">75</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">153.1<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0097">As can be seen in Samples 2, 3, and 5 in Table 9, addition of oleic acid provides
an unexpected reduction in IVD mass relative to comparative Samples 1 and 4.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 9 - GM 2.4L ENGINE DYNAMOMETER TESTING</b></heading><p num="0098">The fuel additive composition of the present invention was tested in a four-cylinder
GM 2.4L engine dynamometer test stand to evaluate intake system deposit control
performance. The four-cylinder GM 2.4L engine is port fuel injected and is of a
four valve per cylinder configuration. The engine is prepared for tests in
accordance with accepted engine testing practices. The engine test is
approximately 124 hours in length and consists of 74 repetitions of a 100-minute
cycle.</p><p num="0099">The details of the test cycle for the GM 2.4L engine are set forth in Table 10. <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">GM 2.4L Engine Dynamometer Test Cycle</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Cycle Step Duration (Seconds)</entry><entry align="center">Engine Speed (RPM)</entry><entry align="center">Engine Manifold Absolute Pressure (Millimeters of Mercury)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   15</entry><entry align="center">800</entry><entry align="center">No Spec</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   705</entry><entry align="center">2000</entry><entry align="center">365</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   1005</entry><entry align="center">2400</entry><entry align="center">398</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   690</entry><entry align="center">2000</entry><entry align="center">365</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   1485</entry><entry align="center">2400</entry><entry align="center">398</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   1095</entry><entry align="center">1500</entry><entry align="center">353</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   1005</entry><entry align="center">2400</entry><entry align="center">398</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total 6000</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0100">The test results from the GM 2.4L Engine Dynamometer Test are set forth in
Table 11.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">GM 2.4L Engine Dynamometer Test Results</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Sample</entry><entry align="center">Mannich (ppma)</entry><entry align="center">Oleic Acid (ppm)</entry><entry align="center">POPA (ppm)</entry><entry align="center">Ratio (POPA/Mannich)</entry><entry align="center">AVG IVD (mg./vlv.)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Base</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">303.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">105.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">2.24<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">94.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">2.24<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">26.9<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0101">As can be seen in Samples 2 and 3 in Table 11, the addition of oleic acid provides
an unexpected improvement in Avg. IVD relative to comparative Sample 1. </p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 10 - DAIMLER-BENZ M102E 2.3L ENGINE DYNAMOMETER
TESTING</b></heading><p num="0102">The fuel additive composition of the present invention was tested in a four-cylinder
Daimler Benz 2.3L engine dynamometer test stand to evaluate intake system
deposit control performance. The four-cylinder Daimler Benz 2.3L engine has KE-Jetronic
fuel metering. The engine is prepared for tests in accordance with
accepted engine testing practices. The engine test is 60 hours in length and
consists of 800 repetitions of a 270-second cycle.</p><p num="0103">The details of the test cycle for the M102E engine are set forth in Table 12.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Daimler-Benz M102E 2.3L Engine Dynamometer Test Cycle</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Cycle Step Duration (Seconds)</entry><entry align="center">Engine Spee (RPM)</entry><entry align="center">Engine Torque (Nm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right">30</entry><entry align="right">800</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right">60</entry><entry align="right">1300</entry><entry align="center">29.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right">120</entry><entry align="right">1850</entry><entry align="center">32.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right">60</entry><entry align="right">3000</entry><entry align="center">35.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total:</entry><entry align="right">270</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0104">The test results from the Daimler-Benz M102E Engine Dynamometer Test are set
forth in Tables 13. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">Daimler-Benz M102E Engine Dynamometer Test Results</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Sample</entry><entry align="center">Mannich (ppma)</entry><entry align="center">Oleic Acid (ppm)</entry><entry align="center">POPA (ppm)</entry><entry align="center">Ratio (POPA/Mannich)</entry><entry align="center">AVG IVD (mg./vlv.)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">200</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">200</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">51</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">200<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">8.96</entry><entry align="center">200</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">23</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">125</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">125</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">120</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">125<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">5.60</entry><entry align="center">125</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">7<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0105">As can be seen in Table 13 addition of oleic acid in Samples 2 and 4 provide an
unexpected reduction in IVD mass relative to comparative Samples 1 and 3.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 11 - EFFECT OF OLEIC ACID TREATMENT ON ANTI-CORROSION
PROPERTIES</b></heading><p num="0106">Corrosion tests according to ASTM D665A were carried out to demonstrate the
effect of oleic acid treatment on the anti-corrosion properties of a formulation
based on Mannich. The D665A test is the most common corrosion test for
evaluating anti-corrosion performance of gasoline in dynamic conditions, such as
in vehicles or pipelines. In this test a polished cylindrical steel specimen was
immersed in a mixture of 300-mL gasoline and 30-mL water. The mixture was
stirred for 24 hours at room temperature (about 20 °C). At the end of this period
the steel specimen was rated for the degree of corrosion which had occurred. In
this example an Eurosuper-based gasoline was evaluated with and without
Mannich formulations. The results are shown below in Table 14. The reference
Mannich formulation was a mixture of Mannich with a synthetic carrier (300 and
200 mg/kg, respectively). Adding the Mannich formulation (Formulation "A") to
the base gasoline slightly improved the corrosion performance, which is not
unusual for a detergent package. Adding a corrosion inhibitor at 3 ppm - a 
commonly applied treat rate (Formulation "B") - improved the corrosion
performance significantly. However, this effect was exceeded by adding 6 ppm
oleic acid to the Mannich (Formulation "C")
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Anti-corrosion Properties</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="1">Base gasoline</entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="2">Eurosuper 95 RON</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Additive package</entry><entry align="center">no</entry><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">B</entry><entry align="center">C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Components, mg/kg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mannich condensation product</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">300</entry><entry align="center">300</entry><entry align="center">300</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oleic acid</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Synthetic carrier fluid (POPA)</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">200</entry><entry align="center">200</entry><entry align="center">200</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Corrosion inhibitor</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   Total mg/kg</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">500</entry><entry align="center">503</entry><entry align="center">506</entry></row><row><entry nameend="5" align="right" namest="1">ASTM D665A Results (in triplicate)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Corrosion rating</entry><entry align="center">E/E/C</entry><entry align="center">C/C/B+</entry><entry align="center">B/B/B</entry><entry align="center">A/A/B+</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Rating</entry><entry align="center">Test Surface Rusted, %</entry></row><row><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="center">B++</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.1%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">B+</entry><entry align="center">&lt;5%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">B</entry><entry align="center">5 - 25%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="center">26 - 50%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">D</entry><entry align="center">51 - 75%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">E</entry><entry align="center">76 - 100%</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0107">While the present invention has been described with reference to specific
embodiments, this application is intended to cover those various changes and
substitutions that may be made by those skilled in the art without departing from
the spirit and scope of the appended claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A fuel additive composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) a Mannich condensation product of (1) a high molecular weight alkyl-substituted
hydroxyaromatic compound wherein the alkyl group has
a number average molecular weight of from about 300 to about
5,000 (2) an amine which contains an amino group having at least
one active hydrogen atom, and (3) an aldehyde, wherein the
respective molar ratio of reactants (1), (2), and (3) is 1:0.1-10:0.1-10;</claim-text><claim-text>b) a hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool having an
average molecular weight of about 500 to about 5,000, wherein the
oxyalkylene group is a C2 to C5 oxyalkylene group and the
hydrocarbyl group is a C1 to C30 hydrocarbyl group; and</claim-text><claim-text>c) a carboxylic acid as represented by the formula:
R1(COOH)x
or anhydride thereof, wherein R1 represents a hydrocarbyl group
having about 2 to about 50 carbon atoms, and x represents an
integer of 1 to about 4.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 1, wherein the alkyl group
on said alkyl-substituted hydroxyaromatic compound has a number average
molecular weight of about 400 to about 3,000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 2, wherein the alkyl group
on said alkyl-substituted hydroxyaromatic compound has a number average
molecular weight of about 500 to about 2,000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 3, wherein the alkyl group
on said alkyl-substituted hydroxyaromatic compound has a number average
molecular weight of about 700 to about 1,500.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 1, wherein said alkyl-substituted
hydroxyaromatic compound is a polyalkylphenol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 5, wherein the
polyalkylphenol is polypropylphenol or polyisobutylphenol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 6, wherein the
polyalkylphenol is polyisobutylphenol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 7, wherein the
polyisobutylphenol is derived from polyisobutene containing at least about
70% methylvinylidine isomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 1, wherein the amine
component of said Mannich condensation product is an alkylene polyamine
having the formula:
H2N-(A-NH)y-H
wherein A is a divalent alkylene radical having 1 to about 10 carbon atoms
and y is an integer from 1 to about 10.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 9, wherein the alkylene
polyamine is polyethylene polyamine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 10, wherein the
polyethylene polyamine is diethylene triamine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 1, wherein the respective
molar ratio of reactants (1), (2), and (3) is 1.0:0.5-2.0:1.0-3.0.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 1, wherein the aldehyde
component of said Mannich condensation product is formaldehyde,
paraformaldehyde, or formalin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 1, wherein said
hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool has an average molecular
weight of about 900 to about 1,500.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 1, wherein the oxyalkylene
group of the hydrocarbyl-terminated polyoxyalkylene group of said
hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool is a C3 to C4 oxyalkylene
group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 15, wherein the
oxyalkylene group of said hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool
is a C3 oxypropylene group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 15, wherein the
oxyalkylene group of said hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool
is a C4 oxybutylene group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The fuel additive composition according to Claim 1, wherein the hydrocarbyl
group of said hydrocarbyl-terminated poly(oxyalkylene) monool is a C7 to
C30 alkylphenyl group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A fuel additive composition according to Claim 1, wherein said carboxylic
acid is a monocarboxylic acid having about 8 to about 30 carbon atoms.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>A fuel additive composition according to Claim 19, wherein said
monocarboxylic acid is oleic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>A fuel composition comprising a major amount of
hydrocarbon fuel boiling in the gasoline or diesel
range and an effective deposit controlling amount
of a fuel additive composition according to any
proceeding claim.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>A fuel composition according to claim 21, wherein
said composition comprises about 20 to about 1,000
ppm of the Mannich Condensation product, about 10
to about 4,000 ppm of the hydrocarbyl-terminated
poly(oxyalkylene) monool, and about 1 to about 100
ppm of the carboxylic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>A fuel composition according to claim 22, wherein
said composition comprises about 30 to about 400
ppm of the Mannich Condensation product, about 20
to about 800 ppm of the hydrocarbyl-terminated
poly(oxyalkylene) monool, and about 1 to about 20
ppm of the carboxylic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>A fuel concentrate comprising an inert stable
oleophilic organic solvent boiling in the range of
from about 150°F to about 400°F and from about 10
to about 90 weight percent of an additive
composition as claimed in any one of claims 1 to
20.</claim-text></claim><claim num="25"><claim-text>A method of improving the compatibility of a fuel
additive composition, said method comprising
blending together the fuel additive composition of
any of claims 1 to 20, wherein the Mannich
Condensation product and the carboxylic acid are
blended together at a temperature in the range of
about room temperature to about 100°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="26"><claim-text>A method of controlling engine deposits in an
internal combustion engine, said method comprising
operating an internal combustion engine with a
fuel composition according to claim 21, 22 or 23.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>