<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1535986-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1535986" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34463755" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050601"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1535986-A1" status="new" fvid="24366471"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1535986</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050601</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04257118-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04257118</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20041117</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2003387033-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2003387033</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031117</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 231/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 231/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 233/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 233/36        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 233/91        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 273/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 273/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 101/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 101/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 129/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 129/40        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 133/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 133/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 133/20        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 137/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 137/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 139/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 139/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 159/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 159/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 163/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 163/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 169/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 169/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 177/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 177/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  30/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  40/04        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  60/14        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07D 273/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 159/12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 163/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 177/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M207:026</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M207:126</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M209:084</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M215:064</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M215:08</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M215:102</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M215:22</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M215:223</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M215:28+2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M219:089</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M223:049</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M229:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N210:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N230:06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N240:042</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N260:14</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Schmiermittelzusammensetzung für Automatikgetriebe</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">A lubricating oil composition for automatic transmissions</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition d'huile lubrifiante pour transmissions automatiques</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="GB-878519-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>878519</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-20020072478-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20020072478</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3718663-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3718663</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5395539-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5395539</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000070001-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000070001</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>CHEVRONTEXACO JAPAN LTD</last-name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>CHEVRONTEXACO JAPAN LTD</last-name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ChevronTexaco Japan Ltd</last-name><address><street>Mitsui Asahi Building, 10th Floor 1-1, Kanda, Suda-cho</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 101-0041</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>SHIGA MICHIO</last-name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><last-name>SHIROI TOMOTSUGU</last-name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>SHIGA, MICHIO</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><last-name>SHIROI, TOMOTSUGU</last-name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SHIGA, MICHIO</last-name><address><street>507-9 Manda</street><city>Hiratsuka City Kanagawa Prefecture</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SHIROI, TOMOTSUGU</last-name><address><street>605-26 Hazu Sagara-Cho Haibara-Gun</street><city>Shizuoka Prefecture</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Nash, David Allan</last-name><address><street>HASELTINE LAKE, Redcliff Quay 120 Redcliff Street</street><city>Bristol BS1 6HU</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An additive compound comprising a non-borated and/or borated reaction
product, in which the reaction product is obtained by reacting a linear or
branched, saturated or unsaturated monovalent aliphatic acid having 8 to 22
carbon atoms, urea, and polyalkylenepolyamine, when employed in a
lubricating oil composition is favorably employable as an automatic
transmission fluid of internal combustion engines.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0001">Automatic transmissions in automobiles comprise a torque converter, a wet
multi-plate clutch, a gear mechanism, and a mechanism controlling these
elements. The torque transmission capacity is automatically set according to
the speed of automobile and the degree of load. Modern automatic
transmissions further comprise a lockup clutch mounted to the torque
converter, so as to improve fuel economy. The use of the lockup clutch
enables engine torque to be transmitted to the automatic transmission
according to driving conditions in addition to the driving force transmitted
through a lubricating oil. However, since the torque variation produced by the
operation of the lockup clutch sometimes disturbs passengers due to shudder,
the lockup clutch is generally set to operate only under high speed driving
conditions giving less torque variation.</p><p num="0002">Under low speed driving conditions as when an automobile starts, loss of
driving force transmission is caused between the engine output revolution and
the transmission input revolution. Therefore, enough improvement of fuel
economy is not attained. Accordingly, automatic transmissions adopt a slip
control system by which the lockup mechanism can operate under the low
speed driving conditions and the transmission loss can be reduced. However,
when the clutch is subjected to control by the slip control system, abnormal
vibration of the body of automobile (i.e., shudder) takes place on the friction 
surface of the lockup clutch. At low road speeds vehicle operation is rough and
engine vibration is transmitted through the drive train. Rough operation and
engine vibration are not acceptable to drivers.</p><p num="0003">Shudder occurs when the sliding rate (V) in the lockup clutch increases and the
coefficient of friction (µ) decreases. Thus, it is desirable to employ a lubricating
oil (automatic transmission fluid) which shows a favorable µ-V character, i.e.,
the friction coefficient increases when the sliding rate increases, and keeps the
favorable µ-V character for a prolonged period of time, i.e., prolonged shudder
inhibition performance.</p><p num="0004">JASO (Japanese Automobile Standard Organization) M349:2001 describes a
standard oil T-III which shows standard shudder inhibition performance and
transmissive torque capacity. However, there is given no information with
respect to formulation of the T-III standard oil.</p><p num="0005">Prolonged shudder inhibition can be attained by incorporating a friction modifier
(generally, friction decreasing agent). However, if too much friction modifier is
incorporated into a lubricating oil, the friction coefficient of the wet clutch
extremely decreases and hence enough transmissive torque capacity cannot
be obtained.</p><p num="0006">U.S. Patent No. 4,948,523 discloses a lubricating composition, preferably
essentially free of zinc dihydrocarbyldithiophosphate compounds, and
optionally free of chlorine containing silver lubricity agents, comprising a major
proportion of an oil of lubricating viscosity and a minor amount of a silver
protective agent comprising the reaction product of a C<sub>5</sub> to C<sub>60</sub> carboxylic acid
and at least one amine selected from the group consisting of (1) guanidine,
urea, and thiourea compounds; (2) C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>20</sub> hydrocarbyl or hydroxy-substituted
hydrocarbyl mono-amines, alkylene diamines, and (3) polyalkylene polyamines;
and N-alkyl glycine. </p><p num="0007">U.S. Patent No. 5,395,539 discloses certain hydrocarbon soluble or dispersible
amide reaction products (Component-1), and mixtures, and/or acid amine salts
of Component-1 and certain acid/esters (Component-2), which are useful as
friction modifying additives for oleaginous compositions such as lubricating oils,
including power transmitting fluids, particularly automatic transmission fluids
(ATF), and to the oleaginous compositions in which they are contained.</p><p num="0008">U.S. Patent No. 5,916,852 discloses lubricating fluids which include an additive
combination comprising a compound having the general formula R―NH<sub>2</sub> with
oil-soluble phosphorus compounds, an ashless dispersant, and, optionally,
other amine containing friction modifiers provide lubricating fluids which exhibit
excellent break-in characteristics that are capable of preventing green shudder
in automatic transmissions.</p><p num="0009">U.S. Patent No. 6,303,547 discloses lubricant formulations containing the
reaction product of at least one C<sub>5</sub> to C<sub>60</sub> carboxylic acid and at least one
amine selected from the group consisting of guanidine, aminoguanidine, urea,
thiourea and salts thereof is useful as a gear oil additive. The lubricant
formulations exhibit excellent low and high temperature rheology and are
particularly suited for use in automotive and industrial gear applications.
Lubricants of the present invention exhibit improved performance properties,
such as increased axle efficiencies and lower axle temperatures, improved
limited slip performance, reduced chatter, improved frictional durability and/or
improved power divider performance compared to lubricant formulations that
do not contain said reaction products.</p><p num="0010">Japanese Patent Publication No. 2001-247532 discloses fatty acid amide
compounds used for surface lubricant, vehicle component and thermal
recording materials, has three or more amide groups in a molecule having the
formula R<sub>1</sub>CONH(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>m</sub>((NCOR<sub>2</sub>)(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub>)<sub>t</sub>NHCOR<sub>3</sub>, where R<sub>1</sub>-R<sub>3</sub> is a C<sub>12</sub> to C<sub>50</sub>
alkyl or alkenyl group, m and n = 1-3, and l = 1-4. </p><p num="0011">U.S. Patent Application Publication No. 2002/0072478A1 discloses a
lubricating oil and one or more succinimide-modified compounds having long-lasting
anti-shudder property, enhanced transmission torque capacity for a wet
clutches and/or wet brakes, and an excellent shifting property for automatic
transmissions and continuously variable transmissions.</p><p num="0012">Japanese Patent No. 3330245 discloses lubricating oil compositions for slide
guide surfaces containing nitrogen-containing compounds of polyamines and
amides in mineral and/or synthetic oil.</p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0013">The present invention provides an additive compound employable in a
lubricating oil composition for automatic transmissions in internal combustion
engines. The lubricating oil composition employing the additive compound of
the present invention has a high transmissive torque capacity and prolonged
shudder inhibition when used as an automatic transmission fluid (ATF) in
automatic transmissions of internal combustion engines.</p><p num="0014">It is desirable that an automatic transmission fluid not only should show a high
shudder inhibiting ability when the transmission fluid is first used, but also
should keep the high shudder inhibiting ability for a prolonged period of time
without substantial decrease of the inhibiting ability and further should show a
high transmissive torque capacity.</p><p num="0015">Accordingly, the present invention relates to an additive compound employable
in a lubricating oil composition having the beneficial performances mentioned
above.</p><p num="0016">The additive compound of the present invention employable in the lubricating
oil composition comprises the reaction product of a linear or branched,
saturated or unsaturated monovalent aliphatic acid having 8 to 22 carbon 
atoms, urea, and polyalkylenepolyamine, wherein the reaction product is non-borated,
borated or a mixture thereof.</p><p num="0017">The present invention furthermore relates to a lubricating oil composition
comprising a major amount of base oil of lubricating viscosity and a minor
amount of the reaction product of a linear or branched, saturated or
unsaturated monovalent aliphatic acid having 8 to 22 carbon atoms, urea, and
polyalkylenepolyamine, wherein the reaction product is non-borated, borated or
a mixture thereof.</p><p num="0018">The present invention further relates to a method of reducing shudder in an
automatic transmission of an internal combustion engine by adding the
lubricating oil composition of the present invention to an automatic
transmission and operating the engine.</p><p num="0019">Among other factors, the present invention is based on the surprising discovery
that an additive compound comprising a non-borated and/or borated reaction
product, in which the reaction product is obtained by reacting a linear or
branched, saturated or unsaturated monovalent aliphatic acid having 8 to 22
carbon atoms, urea, and polyalkylenepolyamine, provides high transmissive
torque capacity and prolonged shudder inhibition when employed as a
lubricating oil in an automatic transmission of an internal combustion engine.
The lubricating oil composition employing the additive compound is useful as a
method for reducing shudder when used as an automatic transmission fluid.
Accordingly the present invention is also directed to the use of the present
additive compound in an automatic transmission fluid to reduce shudder in an
automatic transmission of an internal combustion engine.</p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0020">The preferred embodiments of the additive compound and lubricating oil
composition according to the present invention will be described in further
detail below. </p><heading><u style="single">The Additive Compound</u></heading><p num="0021">The additive compound of the present invention employable in the lubricating
oil composition of the present invention may be a non-borated (A) and/or
borated (B) reaction product in which the reaction product is obtained by
reacting a linear or branched, saturated or unsaturated monovalent aliphatic
acid having 8 to 22 carbon atoms, urea, and polyalkylenepolyamine. The
additive compounds A and B can be employed singly or in combination.</p><p num="0022">Additive compound A comprises the reaction product of a linear or branched,
saturated or unsaturated monovalent aliphatic acid having 8 to 22 carbon
atoms, urea, and polyalkyienepolyamine.</p><p num="0023">Additive compound B comprises the borated reaction product in which the
reaction product is obtained by reacting a linear or branched, saturated or
unsaturated monovalent aliphatic acid having 8 to 22 carbon atoms, urea, and
polyalkylenepolyamine.</p><heading><u style="single">Monovalent Aliphatic Acid</u></heading><p num="0024">The monovalent aliphatic acid is a compound which is represented by the
formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>4</sub> (COOH)<sub>y</sub></st32:che>
or anhydride thereof, wherein R<sub>4</sub> represents a hydrocarbyl group having about
2 to 50 carbon atoms, and y represents an integer of 1-4.</p><p num="0025">The monovalent aliphatic acid employed for the preparation of the additive
compound of the present invention is a linear or branched, saturated or
unsaturated monovalent aliphatic acid containing 8 to 22 carbon atoms.
Examples of the aliphatic acids include octanoic acid, lauric acid, myristic acid,
palmitic acid, stearic acid, isostearic acid, oleic acid, and behenic acid.
Particularly preferred is isostearic acid. </p><heading><u style="single">Urea</u></heading><p num="0026">Any ordinarily employable urea such as urea of industrial purity grade can be
employed.</p><heading><u style="single">Polyalkylenepolyamine</u></heading><p num="0027">Preferred is a polyalkylenepolyamine containing 2 to 30 carbon atoms and 2 to
15 nitrogen atoms, each of at least two nitrogen atoms constituting primary
amine. Preferably, the alkylene groups of such polyalkylenepolyamines will
contain form 2 to 6 carbon atoms, more preferably form 2 to 4 carbon atoms.
The nitrogen atom other than the nitrogen atoms constituting primary amine
generally constitutes secondary amine.</p><p num="0028">Examples of suitable polyalkylene polyamines include ethylenediamine,
propylenediamine, isopropylenediamine, butylenediamine, pentylenediamine,
hexylenediamine, diethylenetriamine, dipropylenetriamine,
dimethylaminopropylamine, diisopropylenetriamine, dibutylenetriamine, di-sec-butylenetriamine,
triethylenetetraamine, tripropylenetetraamine,
triisobutylenetetraamine, tetraethylenepentamine, pentaethylenehexamine,
hexaethyleneheptamine, dimethylaminopropylamine, and mixtures thereof.</p><heading>Particularly suitable polyalkylene polyamines are those having the formula:</heading><p num="0029"><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">H<sub>2</sub>N― (R<sub>5</sub>NH)<sub>z</sub>―H</st32:che>
wherein R<sub>5</sub> is a straight- or branched-chain alkylene group having 2 to 6 carbon
atoms, preferably 2 to 4 carbon atoms, most preferably about 2 carbon atoms,
i.e., ethylene (―CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub> ―); and z is an integer from 1-4, preferably 1-2.
Particularly preferred polyalkylene polyamines are ethylenediamine,
diethylenetriamine, triethylenetetraamine, tetraethylenepentamine,
pentaethylenehexamine, and hexaethyleneheptamine. Particularly preferred is
hexaethyleneheptamine. </p><p num="0030">Many of the polyamines suitable for use in the present invention are
commercially available and others may be prepared by methods that are well
known in the art. For example, methods for preparing amines and their
reactions are detailed in Sidgewick's "The Organic Chemistry of Nitrogen",
Clarendon Press, Oxford, 1966; Noller's "Chemistry of Organic Compounds",
Saunders, Philadelphia, 2nd Ed., 1957; and Kirk-Othmer's "Encydopedia of
Chemical Technology", 2nd Ed., especially Volume 2, pp. 99-116.</p><p num="0031">The additive compound of the present invention can be obtained by reacting
the acid compound (i.e., monovalent aliphatic acid), urea, the amine compound
(i.e., polyalkylenepolyamine) in such conditions (i.e., ratio and nature) that the
resulting reaction compound shows an oil-soluble property. The additive
compound of the present invention is preferably obtained by reacting one mole
of the monovalent aliphatic acid, 0.01 to 2 moles (preferably 0.03 to 0.5 moles)
of urea, and 0.1 to 1 mole (preferably 0.125 to 0.5 moles) of
polyalkylenepolyamine. The reaction can be performed generally at 100-250°C,
preferably at 150-200°C, generally for 1-30 hours, preferably for 2-6 hours.
Since the reaction is a condensation reaction, it is preferred that the produced
water is removed continuously. The progress of the reaction can be checked
by measuring the production of water.</p><p num="0032">The above-mentioned reaction product can be preferably borated by the
reaction using a boric acid compound to yield the borated additive compound
(B). The reaction can be carried out by adding to the above-mentioned reaction
product a solid boric acid compound in such amount that the amount of boron
in the boric acid compound is 0.001 to 0.25 weight part based one weight part
of nitrogen in the above-mentioned reaction product, and heating the mixture to
100-160°C at an atmospheric pressure or a reduced pressure (reduced to 6.7
kPa) for 5-12 hours. The reaction is preferably continued until the solid boric
acid compound diminishes in the reaction mixture. </p><heading><u style="single">Lubricating Oil Composition</u></heading><p num="0033">The present invention also relates to a lubricating oil composition containing
the additive compound of the present invention. Such a lubricating oil
composition will comprise a major amount of base oil of lubricating viscosity
and a minor amount of the additive compound of the present invention (A
and/or B) as described above.</p><p num="0034">Base oil as used herein is defined as a base stock or blend of base stocks
which is a lubricant component that is produced by a single manufacturer to the
same specifications (independent of feed source or manufacturer's location);
that meets the same manufacturer's specification; and that is identified by a
unique formula, product identification number, or both. Base stocks may be
manufactured using a variety of different processes including but not limited to
distillation, solvent refining, hydrogen processing, oligomerization,
esterification, and rerefining. Rerefined stock shall be substantially free from
materials introduced through manufacturing, contamination, or previous use.
The base oil of this invention may be any natural or synthetic lubricating base
oil fraction particularly those having a kinematic viscosity at 100° Centigrade
(C) and about 4 centistokes (cSt) to about 20 cSt. Hydrocarbon synthetic oils
may include, for example, oils prepared from the polymerization of ethylene,
polyalphaolefin or PAO, or from hydrocarbon synthesis procedures using
carbon monoxide and hydrogen gases such as in a Fisher-Tropsch process. A
preferred base oil is one that comprises little, if any, heavy fraction; e.g., little, if
any, lube oil fraction of viscosity about 20 cSt or higher at about 100 C. Oils
used as the base oil will be selected or blended depending on the desired end
use and the additives in the finished oil to give the desired grade of engine oil,
e.g. a lubricating oil composition having an SAE Viscosity Grade of 0W, 0W-20,
0W-30, 0W-40, 0W-50, 0W-60, 5W, 5W-20, 5W-30, 5W-40, 5W-50, 5W-60,
10W, 10W-20. 10W-30, 10W-40, 10W-50, 15W, 15W-20, 15W-30, or
15W-40. </p><p num="0035">There are no specific conditions with respect to the base oil, provided that the
base oil is selected from the base stocks generally employed for preparing
lubricating oil compositions. The base oil may be derived from natural
lubricating oils, synthetic lubricating oils or mixtures thereof. Suitable base oil
includes base stocks obtained by isomerization of synthetic wax and slack wax,
as well as hydrocrackate base stocks produced by hydrocracking (rather than
solvent extracting) the aromatic and polar components of the crude. Suitable
base oils include those in all API categories I, II, III, IV and V as defined in API
Publication 1509, 14th Edition, Addendum I, December 1998. Saturates levels
and viscosity indices for Group I, II and III base oils are listed in Table 1. Group
IV base oils are polyalphaolefins (PAO). Group V base oils include all other
base oils not included in Group I, II, III, or IV. Group III base oils are preferred.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><u style="single">Saturates, Sulfur and Viscosity Index of Group I, II, III, IV and V Base Stocks</u></entry></row><row><entry align="center">Group</entry><entry align="left">Saturates (As determined by ASTM D2007)</entry><entry align="left">Viscosity Index</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">Sulfur (As determined by ASTM D2270)</entry><entry align="left">(As determined by ASTM D4294, ASTM D4297 or ASTM D3120)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I</entry><entry align="left">Less than 90 % saturates and/or Greater than to 0.03 % sulfur</entry><entry align="left">Greater than or equal to 80 and less than 120</entry></row><row><entry align="center">II</entry><entry align="left">Greater than or equal to 90 % saturates and less than or equal to 0.03 % sulfur</entry><entry align="left">Greater than or equal to 80 and less than 120</entry></row><row><entry align="center">III</entry><entry align="left">Greater than or equal to 90 % saturates and less than or equal to 0.03% sulfur</entry><entry align="left">Greater than or equal to 120</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">IV</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">All Polyalphaolefins (PAOs)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1">V</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">All others not included in Groups I, II, III, or IV</entry></row></tbody> </tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0036">Natural lubricating oils may include animal oils, vegetable oils (e.g., rapeseed
oils, castor oils and lard oil), petroleum oils, mineral oils, and oils derived from
coal or shale.</p> <p num="0037">Synthetic oils may include hydrocarbon oils and halo-substituted hydrocarbon
oils such as polymerized and inter-polymerized olefins, alkylbenzenes,
polyphenyls, alkylated diphenyl ethers, alkylated diphenyl sulfides, as well as
their derivatives, analogues and homologues thereof, and the like. Synthetic
lubricating oils also include alkylene oxide polymers, interpolymers, copolymers
and derivatives thereof wherein the terminal hydroxyl groups have been
modified by esterification, etherification, etc. Another suitable class of synthetic
lubricating oils comprises the esters of dicarboxylic acids with a variety of
alcohols. Esters useful as synthetic oils also include those made from C<sub>5</sub> to C<sub>12</sub>
monocarboxylic acids and polyols and polyol ethers. Tri-alkyl phosphate ester
oils such as those exemplified by tri-n-butyl phosphate and tri-iso-butyl
phosphate are also suitable for use as base oils.</p> <p num="0038">Silicon-based oils (such as the polyalkyl-, polyaryl-, polyalkoxy-, or polyaryloxy-siloxane
oils and silicate oils) comprise another useful class of synthetic
lubricating oils. Other synthetic lubricating oils include liquid esters of
phosphorus-containing acids, polymeric tetrahydrofurans, polyalphaolefins, and
the like.</p> <p num="0039">The base oil may be derived from unrefined, refined, rerefined oils, or mixtures
thereof. Unrefined oils are obtained directly from a natural source or synthetic
source (e.g., coal, shale, or tar sand bitumen) without further purification or
treatment. Examples of unrefined oils include a shale oil obtained directly from
a retorting operation, a petroleum oil obtained directly from distillation, or an
ester oil obtained directly from an esterification process, each of which may
then be used without further treatment. Refined oils are similar to the unrefined
oils except that refined oils have been treated in one or more purification steps
to improve one or more properties. Suitable purification techniques include 
distillation, hydrocracking, hydrotreating, dewaxing, solvent extraction, acid or
base extraction, filtration, and percolation, all of which are known to those
skilled in the art. Rerefined oils are obtained by treating used oils in processes
similar to those used to obtain the refined oils. These rerefined oils are also
known as reclaimed or reprocessed oils and often are additionally processed
by techniques for removal of spent additives and oil breakdown products.</p><p num="0040">Base oil derived from the hydroisomerization of wax may also be used, either
alone or in combination with the aforesaid natural and/or synthetic base oil.</p><p num="0041">Such wax isomerate oil is produced by the hydroisomerization of natural or
synthetic waxes or mixtures thereof over a hydroisomerization catalyst.</p><p num="0042">It is preferred to use a major amount of base oil in the lubricating oil of the
present invention. A major amount of base oil as defined herein comprises 40
wt % or more. Preferred amounts of base oil comprise 40 to 99.9 wt %,
preferably greater than 50 to 97 wt %, more preferably 60 to 97 wt % of the
lubricating oil composition. (When weight percent is used herein, it is based on
the total weight percent of the lubricating oil composition unless otherwise
specified.)</p><p num="0043">The additive composition of the present invention in the lubricating oil
composition will be in a minor amount compared to the base oil of lubricating
viscosity. Generally, it will be in an amount from 0.1 to 10 wt %, preferably from
0.3 to 5 wt % and more preferably from 0.3 to 2.0 wt % based on the total
weight of the lubricating oil composition.</p><p num="0044">The lubricating oil composition of the present invention can further contain
various lubricating oil additives available in the art. Examples of the optionally
incorporable additives include viscosity index improvers, ashless dispersants,
metal-containing detergents, anti-wear agents, friction modifiers, oxidation
inhibitors, corrosion inhibitors, seal swelling agents, dyes, and pour point 
depressants. Particularly preferred additive is diphenyl hydrogen phosphite
which is known as an anti-wear agent.</p><p num="0045">A number of the above-mentioned optionally incorporable additives are well
known. Details of such additives are described below.</p><heading><u style="single">Viscosity Index Improver</u></heading><p num="0046">Examples of the viscosity index improvers include non-dispersant type viscosity
index improvers such as copolymers of various methacrylic acid esters and one
or more other monomers and their hydrogenated products and dispersant type
viscosity index improvers such as copolymers of various methacrylic acid
esters and nitrogen-containing monomers. Other non-dispersant type or
dispersant type viscosity index improvers such as copolymers of ethylene and
α-olefins (e.g., propylene, 1-butene, and 1-pentene) and their hydrogenated
products, and polyacrylic acid esters are also useful in the present invention.</p><p num="0047">The lubricating oil composition of the present invention generally contains a
viscosity index improver in an amount of 1 to 20 wt. %, preferably 1 to 8 wt. %.</p><heading><u style="single">Ashless Dispersant</u></heading><p num="0048">Alkenyl- or alkyl-succinimide or its derivative is the preferred ashless
dispersant. The alkenyl- or alkyl-group can be derived from polyolefin. The
nitrogen-atom containing compound is preferably contained in the lubricating
oil composition in an amount of 0.01 to 0.3 wt. % in terms of the nitrogen
content. A representative succinimide can be prepared by the reaction between
succinic anhydride having a high molecular weight alkenyl or alkyl substituent
group with polyalkylenepolyamine containing 4 to 10 nitrogen atoms (average,
preferably 5 to 7 nitrogen atoms) in one molecule. The high molecular weight
alkenyl or alkyl substituent group is preferably derived from polyolefin having a
number average molecular weight of approx. 900 to 5,000. A particularly
preferred polyolefin is polybutene. </p><p num="0049">The process for preparing the polybutenylsuccinic anhydride by the reaction
between polybutene and maleic anhydride is generally performed by a
chlorination method utilizing chlorine. While this reaction is advantageous in
giving a high reaction yield, it has disadvantageous feature in that a large
amount (for instance, approx. 2,000 ppm) of chlorine remains in the finally
obtained succinimide product. In contrast, a thermal reaction process utilizing
no chlorine gives a final reaction product having extremely low chlorine content
(such as 40 ppm or less). It is known that an improved thermal reaction
process employing a highly reactive polybutene (containing at least approx.
50% of methylvinylidene structure) in place of the conventional polybutene
(containing mainly β-olefin structure) gives a high reaction yield. The improved
thermal reaction process is further advantageous because a reaction ratio of
the polybutene increases and the resulting dispersant contains the effective
product (succinimide) in a high concentration. Accordingly, it is preferred that
the polybutenylsuccinic anhydride is produced from the highly reactive
polybutene converted by a thermal process and the resulting
polybutenylsuccinic anhydride is converted into succinimide by the reaction
with polyalkylenepolyamine containing 4 to 10 nitrogen atoms (average per one
molecule). The resulting succinimide can be further converted to a modified
succinimide by a further reaction with boric acid, alcohol, aldehyde, ketone,
alkylphenol, cyclic carbonate, organic acids, or inorganic acids such as
phosphoric acid. From the thermal stability and oxidation stability, particularly
preferred is a boron-containing alkenyl- or alkyl-succinimide which is produced
by the reaction with boric acid or a boron-containing compound.</p><p num="0050">Other ashless additives such as alkenylbenzylamine compounds and
alkenylsuccinic acid esters can be employed independently or in combination
with the above-mentioned alkenyl- or alkyl-succinimide or its derivative.</p><heading><u style="single">Metal-Containing Detergent</u></heading><p num="0051">Generally, a metal-containing detergent, i.e., metal atom-containing detergent,
having a total base number of 10 to 500 mg·KOH/g is employed in an amount 
of 0.01 to 2.0 wt. %. Examples of the metal-containing detergents include
alkaline earth metal salts of petroleum sulfonic acids, alkylbenzenesulfonic
acids, and alkyloxybenzenesulfonic acids or their over-based products. The
alkaline earth metal salts preferably are Mg salts or Ca salts. The metal-containing
detergents can be employed singly or in combination. Otherwise,
phenate sulfide or salicylate can be employed singly or in combination.</p><heading><u style="single">Anti-Wear Agent and Friction Modifier</u></heading><p num="0052">It is preferred that the lubricating oil composition of the present invention
further contains diphenyl hydrogen phosphite which serves as an anti-wear
agent and a friction modifier. The static friction coefficient retention of the
lubricating oil composition of the present invention is further improved by the
incorporation of diphenyl hydrogen phosphite. The diphenyl hydrogen
phosphite is generally contained in the lubricating oil composition of the
present invention in an amount of 0.01 to 2 wt. %, preferably 0.05 to 0.5 wt. %.</p><p num="0053">Other phosphoric acid esters, phosphoric acid amine salts, phosphorous acid
esters, and phosphorous acid amine salts can be incorporated into the
lubricating oil composition of the present invention independently or in addition
to diphenyl hydrogen phosphite. Examples of these compounds include
aromatic tertiary phosphites such as triphenyl phosphite and tris(nonylphenyl)
phosphite; aliphatic tertiary phosphites such as triethyl phosphite, trioctyl
phosphite, tridecyl phosphite, trilauryl phosphite, tris(tridecyl) phosphite,
tristearyl phosphite, and trioleyl phosphite; aliphatic secondary phosphites such
as dibutyl hydrogen phosphite, dioctyl hydrogen phosphite, didecyl hydrogen
phosphite, dilauryl hydrogen phosphite, and dioleyl hydrogen phosphite;
aromatic or aliphatic phosphoric triesters such as triphenyl phosphate, tricresyl
phosphate, tributyl phosphate, trioctyl phosphate, trilauryl phosphate, tristearyl
phosphate, and trioleyl phosphate; and aliphatic acidic phosphoric acid esters
such as methyl acid phosphate, ethyl acid phosphate, butyl acid phosphate,
octyl acid phosphate, decyl acid phosphate, dodecyl acid phosphate, tridecyl
acid phosphate, stearyl acid phosphate, and oleyl acid phosphate. Examples of 
the amine salts include linear or branched aliphatic amine compounds having 8
to 18 carbon atoms such as octylamine, decylamine, laurylamine, caprylamine,
coconut amine, tallow oil amine, and oleylamine.</p><p num="0054">If desired, zinc dialkyldithiophosphate, which is a known additive serving as an
anti-wear agent, an oxidation inhibitor, and an extreme-pressure agent, can be
incorporated into the lubricating oil composition of the present invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Oxidation Inhibitor</u></heading><p num="0055">It is preferred that the lubricating oil composition of the present invention
further contains an oxidation inhibitor such as a hindered phenol compound, a
diarylamine compound, or a molybdenum compound in an amount of 0.01 to 5
wt. % based on the amount of the lubricating oil composition.</p><p num="0056">Examples of the hindered phenol compounds include 2,6-di-t-butyl-p-cresol,
4,4'-methylenebis(2,6-di-t-butylphenol), 4,4'-methylenebis(6-t-butyl-o-cresol),
4,4'-isopropylidenebis(2,6-di-t-butylphenol), 4,4'-bis(2,6-di-t-butylphenol), 2,2'-methylenebis(4-methyl-6-t-butylphenol),
4,4'-thiobis(2-methyl-6-t-butylphenol),
2,2-thiodiethylenebis[3-(3,5-di-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propionate], octyl 3-(3,5-di-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propianate,
octadecyl 3-(3,5-di-t-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propionate
and octyl 3-(5-t-butyl-4-hydroxy-3-methylphenyl)propionate.</p><p num="0057">Examples of the diarylamine compounds include an alkyldiphenylamine
containing a mixture of alkyl groups having 4 to 9 carbon atoms, p,p'-dioctyldiphenylamine,
phenyl-α-naphthylamine, phenyl-β-naphthylamine,
alkylated α-naphthylamine, and alkylated phenyl-α-naphthylamine. Each of the
hindered phenol compounds and diarylamine compounds can be used singly
or in combination. Other oil soluble oxidation inhibitors can be employed in
combination. </p><p num="0058">The oxidation inhibitor can be a molybdenum-containing compound which is a
multi-functional additive. The molybdenum-containing compound is preferably
contained in the lubricating oil composition in an amount of 30 to 1,000 ppm in
terms of the molybdenum content.</p><p num="0059">Examples of the molybdenum-containing compounds are molybdenum-containing
imide, amide or amine compounds. Sulfur-containing
oxymolybdenum-succinimide complex compound can improve high
temperature detergency and oxidation inhibition, and hence is favorably
employed. Sulfated oxymolybdenum dithiocarbamate and sulfated
oxymolybdenum dithiophosphate can improve oxidation inhibition, wear
inhibition, and reduction of friction coefficient, and hence are favorably
employed.</p><heading><u style="single">Dye</u></heading><p num="0060">When the lubricating oil composition of the present invention is employed as an
ATF, the oil composition is preferably colored by a dye such as red dye.</p><heading><u style="single">Corrosion Inhibitor</u></heading><p num="0061">The corrosion inhibitor preferably is a copper corrosion inhibitor. The copper
corrosion inhibitor can be a thiazole compound, a triazole compound or a
thiadiazole compound. Examples of these compounds include benzotriazole,
tolyltriazole, octyltriazole, decyltriazole, dodecyltriazole, 2-mercaptobenzothiazole,
2,5-dimercapto-1,3,4-thiadiazole, 2-mercapto-4-hydrocarbyldithio-1,3,4-thiadiazole,
and 2,5-bis(hydrocarbyldithio)-1,3,4-thiadiazole.</p><p num="0062">Other employable corrosion inhibitors include alkenylsuccinic acid and its
anhydride. Examples of these compounds include tetrapropenylsuccinic acid,
tetrapropenylsuccinic anhydride, tetradocenylsuccinic acid,
tetradocenylsuccinic anhydride, octadecenylsuccinic acid, and
octadecenylsuccinic anhydride. Otherwise, an alkenylsuccinic acid having an 
alkenyl group of 8 to 24 carbon atoms, and a half ester of this alkenylsuccinic
acid and an alcohol such as polyglycol can be employed as corrosion inhibitor.</p><p num="0063">In addition, an amine compound, an acidic phosphoric acid ester, an
ethoxylated amine compound, an imidazoline compound, an aminosuccinic
acid, or their derivatives can be employed as corrosion inhibitor.</p><heading><u style="single">Pour Point Depressant</u></heading><p num="0064">Examples of the pour point depressants include polymethacrylic acid esters,
polyacrylic acid esters, polyacrylamides, condensation products of paraffin wax
and aromatic compounds.</p><heading><u style="single">Seal Swelling Agent</u></heading><p num="0065">When the lubricating oil composition of the present invention is used as an
ATF, a seal swelling agent which swells elastomer sealing material placed in
the automatic transmission system may be used. Examples of the seal swelling
agents include oil-soluble dialkylesters of dibasic acids such as adipic acid,
azelaic acid, sebacic acid, or phthalic acid. Examples of preferred seal swelling
agents include an adipic acid ester, an azelaic acid ester or a sebacic acid
ester of an alkanol having 8 to 13 carbon atoms, and a phthalic acid ester of an
alkanol having 4 to 13 carbon atoms.</p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0066">The invention will be further illustrated by the following examples, which set
forth particularly advantageous method embodiments. While the Examples are
provided to illustrate the present invention, they are not intended to limit it. This
application is intended to cover those various changes and substitutions that
may be made by those skilled in the art without departing from the spirit and
scope of the appended claims. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><heading>Preparation of Additive Compound A1 (Non-Borated)</heading><p num="0067">In a four-necked flask equipped with a stirrer, a thermometer, and a
dehydrating device were placed 1,034 g (3.5 moles) of isostearic acid and 15 g
(0.25 moles) of urea. The resulting mixture was heated to 100°C, and 137.5 g
(0.5 moles) of hexaethyleneheptamine was dropwise added to the heated
mixture under replacement of the reaction atmosphere with nitrogen gas. After
the addition was complete, the reaction mixture in the flask was gradually
heated to reach 160°C within 3 hours. Water produced by the reaction caused
in the course of heating was removed from the flask. Finally, the pressure of
inside of the flask was reduced to 6.7 kPa, so as to completely remove the
produced water. Finally obtained reaction product (Additive Compound A1)
was a brown liquid having 4.3 wt. % of nitrogen content.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><heading>Preparation of Additive Compound A2 (Non-Borated)</heading><p num="0068">In a four-necked flask equipped with a stirrer, a thermometer, and a
dehydrating device were placed 738 g (2.5 moles) of isostearic acid and 15 g
(0.25 moles) of urea. The resulting mixture was heated to 100°C, and 95 g (0.5
moles) of tetraethylenepentamine was dropwise added to the heated mixture
under replacement of the reaction atmosphere with nitrogen gas. After the
addition was complete, the reaction mixture in the flask was gradually heated
to reach 160°C within 3 hours. Water produced by the reaction caused in the
course of heating was removed from the flask. Finally, the pressure of inside of
the flask was reduced to 6.7 kPa, so as to completely remove the produced
water. Finally obtained reaction product (Additive Compound A2) was a brown
liquid having 4.2 wt. % of nitrogen content. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><heading>Preparation of Additive Compound B (Borated)</heading><p num="0069">In a four-necked flask equipped with a stirrer, a thermometer, and a
dehydrating device were placed 1,034 g (3.5 moles) of isostearic acid and 15 g
(0.25 moles) of urea. The resulting mixture was heated to 100°C, and 137.5 g
(0.5 moles) of hexaethyleneheptamine was dropwise added to the heated
mixture under replacement of the reaction atmosphere with nitrogen gas. After
the addition was complete, the reaction mixture in the flask was gradually
heated to reach 160°C within 3 hours. Water produced by the reaction caused
in the course of heating was removed from the flask. Finally, the pressure of
inside of the flask was reduced to 6.7 kPa, so as to completely remove the
produced water. Then, the pressure of inside of the flask was returned to
atmospheric pressure. The reaction product was cooled to 100°C, and 9.3 g
(0.15 moles) of boric acid was added to the cooled product. The reaction
mixture in the flask was heated to reach 155°C within 3 hours. The reaction
mixture was continuously heated to the same temperature for one hour.
Subsequently, the pressure of inside of the flask was reduced to 50 mmHg,
and the heating was continued for 2 hours. Finally obtained reaction product
(Additive Compound B) was a brown liquid having 4.2 wt. % of nitrogen content
and 0.2 wt. % of boron content (boron/nitrogen=0.05).</p><heading><u style="single">Example 4</u></heading><p num="0070">The below-mentioned additives and base oil were mixed to give a lubricating oil
composition of the present invention. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><u style="single">Weight %</u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Succinimide</entry><entry align="center">3.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Borated succinimide</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Overbased calcium sulfonate</entry><entry align="center">0.08</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Reaction product A1</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oleic acid</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dioctyldiphenylamine</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2,6-Di-t-butylphenol</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diphenyl hydrogen phosphite</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tolyltriazole</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silicone oil (anti-foaming agent)</entry><entry align="center">0.002</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Nitrogen-containing polymethacrylate</entry><entry align="center">5.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Base oil (purified mineral oil)</entry><entry align="center">87.068</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 5</u></heading><p num="0071">The procedures of Example 4 were repeated except for replacing Additive
Compound A1 with Additive Compound A2, to give a lubricating oil composition
of the present invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 6</u></heading><p num="0072">The procedures of Example 4 were repeated except for replacing Additive
Compound A1 with Borated Additive Compound B, to give a lubricating oil
composition of the present invention. </p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Example A</u></heading><p num="0073">The procedures of Example 4 were repeated except no Additive Compound A1
was used and changing the amount of the base oil to 88.568 wt %, to give a
lubricating oil composition for comparison.</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Example B</u></heading><p num="0074">The procedures of Example 4 were repeated except for replacing Additive
Compound A1 with the same amount of an amide compound (imidazoline-amide
mixture produced by the reaction of 3 moles of isostearic acid and 1
mole of tetraethylenepentamine), to give a lubricating oil composition for
comparison.</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Example C</u></heading><p num="0075">The procedures of Example 4 were repeated except for replacing Additive
Compound A1 with the same amount of an imide compound (succinimide
produced by the reaction of 2 moles of isooctadecenylsuccinic anhydride and 1
mole of diethylenetriamine), to give a lubricating oil composition for
comparison.</p><p num="0076">Each of the lubricating oil compositions of Examples 4 to 6 and Comparative
Examples A to C was examined for its shudder inhibition performance retention
and transmissive torque capacity according to the following measuring
procedures. The results are set forth in Table 2.</p><heading>(1) Shudder inhibition performance retention</heading><p num="0077">The shudder inhibition was measured according to Shudder Inhibition
Performance Test Method for Automobiles and Automobile Automatic
Transmission Fluid (defined in JASO M349.2001). In the measurements, an 
LVFA (Low Velocity Friction Apparatus) tester was employed, and dµ/dV (0.3)
and dµ/dV (0.9) were determined under the following test conditions:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>Test conditions
<sl><li>Friction material: ZDR 522. OK, Steel plate (FZ132-8Y2)</li><li>Oil volume: 150 mL</li></sl></li><li>Break-in operation
<sl><li>Oil temperature: 80°C, Surface pressure: 1 MPa,</li><li>Sliding rate: 0.6 m/s, Period: 30 min.</li></sl>After the break-in operation was complete, the friction character was measured
according to the below-stated µ-V character-measuring conditions.</li><li>µ-V Character-measuring conditions
<sl><li>Oil temperature: 40°C, 80°C, 120°C,</li><li>Surface pressure: 1 MPa, Sliding rate: 0 to 1.5 m/s</li></sl>After the first measurement of µ-V character was complete, the retention ability
was evaluated by measuring µ-V character at the lapse of the predetermined
period of time by repeating the same measuring procedure.</li><li>Retention ability conditions
<sl><li>Oil temperature: 120°C, Surface pressure: 1 MPa,</li><li>Sliding rate: 0.9 m/s, Sliding period: 30 min. </li><li>Rest: one min., Measurement: Every 24 hours</li></sl></li><li>Measurements
<sl><li>dµ/dV (0.3): dµ/dV (m/s) at sliding rate of 0.3 m/s</li><li>dµ/dV (0.9): dµ/dV (m/s) at sliding rate of 0.9 m/s</li></sl></li></ul></p><p num="0078">Shudder life: period of time until one of dµ/dV (0.3) and d<sub>µ</sub>/dV (0.9) became a
minus value. A shorter period was adopted as the shudder life.</p><heading>(2) Transmissive torque capacity</heading><p num="0079">Dynamic friction test and static friction test were carried out by means of SAE
No.2 Tester according to Friction Test Method for Automobiles and Automobile
Automatic Transmission Fluid (defined in JASO M348.2002).
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>Friction material
<sl><li>Friction material: FZ127-24-Y12, Steel plate (FZ132-8Y2)</li></sl></li><li>Dynamic friction measurement
<sl><li>Inertial moment of inertia disc: 0.343 kg·m<sup>2</sup></li><li>Oil temperature: 100°C</li><li>Rotation: 3,600 rpm</li><li>Surface pressure of friction plate: 785 MPa</li><li>Test cycle: 30 sec./cycle, Test number: 5,000 cycles</li></sl></li><li>Static friction measurement <sl><li>Rotation: 0.7 rpm</li><li>Oil temperature: 100°C</li><li>Surface pressure of friction plate: 785 MPa</li><li>Test period: 3 min. after initiation of rotation</li><li>Test cycle: after 1, 5, 10, 20, 50, 100, 200, 500, 1000, 2000, 3000,
4000, and 5000 cycles</li></sl></li><li>Measurement
Static friction coefficient (µs) at the maximum torque caused when the rotation
at 0.7 rpm starts and static coefficient (µt) at the lapse of 2 seconds.Transmission torque capacity was evaluated by the value of µt. The µt value
larger than 0.100 means that the transmission torque capacity is high, and a
further larger µt value means a higher transmission torque capacity.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Shudder Inhibition Performance</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Shudder Inhibition Life (hr.)</entry><entry align="center">µt after 20 cycles</entry><entry align="center">µt after 500 cycles</entry><entry align="center">µt after 1000 cycles</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 4</entry><entry align="left">552</entry><entry align="center">0.136</entry><entry align="center">0.135</entry><entry align="center">0.131</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 5</entry><entry align="left">504</entry><entry align="center">0.132</entry><entry align="center">0.133</entry><entry align="center">0.130</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 6</entry><entry align="left">528</entry><entry align="center">0.135</entry><entry align="center">0.138</entry><entry align="center">0.133</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comp.Ex.A</entry><entry align="left">24</entry><entry align="center">0.142</entry><entry align="center">0.140</entry><entry align="center">0.139</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comp. Ex. B</entry><entry align="left">216</entry><entry align="center">0.094</entry><entry align="center">0.089</entry><entry align="center">0.086</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comp. Ex. C</entry><entry align="left">168</entry><entry align="center">0.126</entry><entry align="center">0.119</entry><entry align="center">0.123</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></li></ul></p><p num="0080">The results set forth in Table 2 indicate that the lubricating oil compositions of
the present invention (Examples 4 to 6) show a long shudder inhibition life
(which means a long shudder inhibition capacity retention) and a high µl value
such as a value exceeding 0.130 (which means a high transmissive torque
capacity). In contrast, the comparative lubricating oil composition containing
neither the amide compound nor the imide compound (Comparative Example
A) shows a short shudder inhibition life while the µt value is high. The
comparative lubricating oil compositions containing a conventional amide
compound or imide compound (Comparative Examples B and C) show a low µl
value and only a slightly longer shudder inhibition life (longer than the life of the
lubricating oil composition of Comparative Example A) but shorter than the
lubricating oil compositions of the present invention (Examples 4 to 6).</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An additive compound comprising the reaction product of a linear or
branched, saturated or unsaturated monovalent aliphatic acid having 8
to 22 carbon atoms, urea, and polyalkylenepolyamine, wherein the
reaction product is non-borated, borated or a mixture thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The additive compound of claim 1, wherein the reaction product is
borated.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The additive compound of claim 1, wherein the reaction product is
produced by reacting one mole of a linear or branched, saturated or
unsaturated monovalent aliphatic acid having 8 to 22 carbon atoms,
0.01 to 2 moles of urea, and 0.1 to 1 mole of polyalkylenepolyamine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The additive compound of claim 1, wherein the polyalkylenepolyamine
contains 2 to 30 carbon atoms and 2 to 15 nitrogen atoms, wherein at
least two nitrogen atoms are in the form of primary amines.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The additive compound of claim 4, wherein the polyalkylenepolyamine is
selected from the group consisting of ethylenediamine,
diethylenetriamine, triethylenetetramine, tetraethylenepentamine,
pentaethylenehexamine, and hexaethyleneheptamine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The additive compound of claim 5, wherein the polyalkylenepolyamine is
hexaethyleneheptamine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The additive compound of claim 1, wherein the aliphatic acid is
isostearic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A lubricating oil composition comprising a major amount of base oil of
lubricating viscosity and a minor amount of the reaction product of a
linear or branched, saturated or unsaturated monovalent aliphatic acid
having 8 to 22 carbon atoms, urea, and polyalkylenepolyamine, wherein
the reaction product is non-borated, borated or a mixture thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The lubricating oil composition of claim 8, wherein the reaction product
is borated.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The lubricating oil composition of claim 8, wherein the reaction product
is produced by reacting one mole of a linear or branched, saturated or
unsaturated monovalent aliphatic acid having 8 to 22 carbon atoms,
0.01 to 2 moles of urea, and 0.1 to 1 mole of polyalkylenepolyamine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The lubricating oil composition of claim 8, wherein the
polyalkylenepolyamine contains 2 to 30 carbon atoms and 2 to 15
nitrogen atoms, wherein at least two nitrogen atoms are in the form of
primary amines.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The lubricating oil composition of claim 11, wherein the
polyalkylenepolyamine is selected from the group consisting of
ethylenediamine, diethylenetriamine, triethylenetetramine,
tetraethylenepentamine, pentaethylenehexamine, and
hexaethyleneheptamine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The lubricating oil composition of claim 12, wherein the
polyalkylenepolyamine is hexaethyleneheptamine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The lubricating oil composition of claim 8, wherein the aliphatic acid is
isostearic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The lubricating oil composition of claim 8, which further contains 0.01 to
2 wt. % of diphenyl hydrogen phosphite.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The lubricating oil composition of claim 8, which further contains a
metal-containing detergent, an ashiess dispersant, and an oxidation
inhibitor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>An automatic transmission apparatus containing the lubricating oil
composition of claim 8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A method for reducing shudder in an automatic transmission of an
internal combustion engine, said method comprising adding the
lubricating oil composition of claim 8 to the automatic transmission and
operating the engine.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>