<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1239014-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1239014" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="25178421" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020911"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1239014-A1" status="new" fvid="23536982"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1239014</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020911</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02251455-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02251455</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020301</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-80045001-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>80045001</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010305</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Die Anwendung organischer Säuren zur Regelung der Eigenschaften von Tintenstrahltinten</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Use of mixtures of organic acids to adjust properties of ink-jet inks</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Utilisation des mélanges d'acides organiques pour l'ajustement de propriétés des encres à jet d'encre</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0997506-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0997506</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-2332438-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2332438</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5679143-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5679143</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998044057-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998044057</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HEWLETT PACKARD CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HEWLETT-PACKARD COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hewlett-Packard Company</last-name><address><street>3000 Hanover Street</street><city>Palo Alto, CA 94304</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ADAMIC RAYMOND J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PARAZAK DENNIS P</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>REHMAN ZIA</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ADAMIC, RAYMOND J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PARAZAK, DENNIS P.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>REHMAN, ZIA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Adamic, Raymond J.,</last-name><address><street>810 NW Antelope Place</street><city>Corvallis, OR 97330</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PARAZAK, DENNIS P.</last-name><address><street>4769 Via Escala</street><city>Oceanside, CA 92056</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>REHMAN, ZIA</last-name><address><street>3010 NE Glacier Way</street><city>Corvallis, OR 97330</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Jackson, Richard Eric</last-name><address><street>Carpmaels &amp;amp; Ransford, 43 Bloomsbury Square</street><city>London WC1A 2RA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Ink-jet ink compositions are described comprising a mixture of succinic acid
and at least one second organic acid. The ink-jet ink compositions alleviate color
bleed, and lead to reliable pen performance when incorporated in a pen architecture.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="137" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="119"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to color ink compositions for ink-jet printing,
and more particularly, to color ink compositions that enhance pen performance while
minimizing color bleed.</p><heading>Background of the Invention</heading><p num="0002">The combination of low cost and high quality output have recently made ink-jet
printers a popular alternative to other types of non-impact printers such as laser
printers.</p><p num="0003">The ink-jet printing process involves the ejection of fine droplets of ink onto a
print medium such as paper in response to electrical signals generated by a
microprocessor. Typically, an ink-jet printer utilizes a pen set mounted on a carriage
that is moved relative to the surface of a print medium. In commercially available ink-jet
color printers, such as the DESKJET™ printer available from Hewlett-Packard
Company, a four-pen set including cyan, yellow, magenta and black inks is generally
employed to achieve the necessary color combinations.</p><p num="0004">A typical pen includes print heads with orifice plates that have very small
nozzles (typically 10-50 µm diameter) through which the ink droplets are ejected.
Adjacent to these nozzles are ink chambers where ink is stored prior to ejection. Ink
drop ejection is currently achieved either thermally or piezoelectrically. In thermal
ink-jet printing, each nozzle is associated with a resistor element. Each resistor
element is in turn connected to a microprocessor, whose signals direct one or more
resistor elements to heat up rapidly. This causes a rapid expansion of ink vapor that 
forces a drop of ink through the associated nozzle onto the print medium. In
piezoelectric ink-jet printing, ink droplets are ejected due to the vibrations of
piezoelectric crystals stimulated by electrical signals generated by the microprocessor.</p><p num="0005">Interactions between the ink and pen architecture (<i>e.g.</i> the resistor element,
nozzle, etc.) strongly influence the reliability of pen performance. In addition,
interactions between the ink and both the surface and bulk of the print medium play a
key role in determining print quality. A significant amount of research has recently
been conducted to produce improved ink compositions for ink-jet printers that exhibit
favorable interactions with both the pen architecture and the print medium.</p><p num="0006">A variety of complex interactions between the ink and pen architecture can
affect both the short and long term reliability of pen performance. For example,
kogation, defined as the build up of residue on the surface of resistor elements as a
result of repeated firings, can cause individual thermal heaters to fail, leading to a
gradual degradation in pen performance.</p><p num="0007">Puddling and crusting relate respectively to the formation of ink puddles and
insoluble crusts on the orifice plates of the printhead. Such obstructions lead to poor
drop ejection characteristics <i>(e.g.</i> drop volume, velocity and direction), and hence to a
degradation in print quality. Again, ink composition plays an important role in
determining the extent of these two phenomena; the low surface tension of surfactant
containing inks may cause puddling, while the evaporation of a volatile ink
composition could lead to crusting.</p><p num="0008">In addition to the aforementioned properties affecting the reliability of the
pens of a given pen set, a particular concern for <i>color</i> ink-jet printing, has been the
mixing or "bleeding" that occurs both on the surface and within the print medium
when inks of two different colors are printed side by side. Bleeding may cause
undesired color formation at the interface <i>(e.g.</i> when cyan and yellow mix to give
green) and a concurrent loss of color separation, resolution, and edge acuity. The
more contrasting the two adjacent liquids are in color <i>(e.g.</i> black and yellow), the
more visual the bleed. Several methods, including reducing dry times and increasing
penetration rates, have been proposed to reduce bleed of adjacent printing liquids. In
addition, pH-sensitive dyes may also be employed to control bleed. </p><p num="0009">US Patent No. 5,181,045 (incorporated by reference herein) discloses a
method of ink-jet printing wherein one ink (a pH sensitive ink, usually a black ink)
contains a colorant that becomes insoluble under defined pH conditions, and a second
ink (the target ink, usually a color ink) has a pH that renders the colorant contained in
the first ink insoluble. To completely control bleed, this method typically requires a
pH differential of 4-5 units between the two inks. Accordingly, an ink with a pH not
exceeding 4 would be preferred to effectively eliminate bleed from a pH-sensitive ink
having a pH of 8.</p><p num="0010">US Patent No. 5,785,743 (incorporated by reference herein) discloses that the
addition of an organic acid component to the so-called target ink composition reduces
the pH differential required to control bleed to as little as 1-3 units. As a result, the pH
of the target ink could be as high as 7 and still eliminate bleed from an encroaching
pH-sensitive ink having a pH of 8, thereby reducing some of the corrosion risks
associated with low pH inks.</p><heading>Summary of the Invention</heading><p num="0011">The invention is an ink-jet ink composition. The composition comprises at
least one colorant and a vehicle. The vehicle includes a mixture of succinic acid and at
least one second organic acid. The second organic acid may be a monofunctional,
difunctional or polyfunctional organic acid. The second organic acid may be glutaric
acid, oxalic acid, maleic acid, methylsuccinic acid, malonic acid, adipic acid, fumaric
acid, dihydroxyfumaric acid, malic acid, mesaconic acid, itaconic acid, phthalic acid,
isophthalic acid, terephthalic acid, aspartic acid, glutamic acid, 1,2-, 1,3- and 1,4-cyclohexane
dicarboxylic acids, 1,2,3-cyclohexane tricarboxylic acid, 1,2,4-cyclohexane
tricarboxylic acid, 1,3,5-cyclohexane tricarboxylic acid, 1,2- and 1,3-cyclopentane
dicarboxylic acids, citric acid, tartaric acid, dihydroxyterephthalic acid,
1,2,3-, 1,2,4- and 1,2,5-benzene tricarboxylic acids, tricarballylic acid, 1,2,4,5-benzene
tetracarboxylic acid, norbornene tetracarboxylic acid, 3,3',4,4'-benzophenone
tetracarboxylic acid, 1,2,3,4,5,6-benzene hexacarboxylic acid, acetic acid, polyacrylic
acid, glycolic acid, and derivatives thereof. Preferably the second organic acid is
glutaric acid.</p><p num="0012">The concentration of succinic acid may be from about 2 to about 8 wt %, for 
example from about 3 to about 6 wt %. The concentration of glutaric acid may be
from about 0.1 to about 4 wt %, for example from about 0.5 to about 1.5 wt %.</p><p num="0013">The vehicle may further include from about 0.1 to about 7 wt % surfactants
and from about 5 to about 25 wt % organic cosolvents.</p><heading>Brief Description of the Drawing</heading><p num="0014">The invention is described with reference to the sole figure of the drawing, in
which Figure 1 is a series of photographs of cross-hatchings in which a pigment black
ink was printed adjacently to a series of magenta color inks.</p><heading>Detailed Description</heading><p num="0015">The invention will now be described in detail with particular reference to
aqueous ink-jet ink compositions and the materials therein.</p><heading>A. Ink Compositions</heading><p num="0016">Exemplary embodiments of the ink compositions comprise, by weight (all
percents are by weight unless otherwise indicated) from 0.01 to 50%, preferably from
5 to 25% organic cosolvents; from 0 to 40%, preferably from 0.1 to 7% surfactants;
from 3 to 12% mixed organic acids; and from 0.5 to 10% dye. The remainder of the
ink compositions are mostly water; however, other components such as biocides that
inhibit growth of microorganisms; chelating agents such as EDTA that eliminate
deleterious effects of heavy metal impurities; buffers; and viscosity modifiers or other
acrylic and non-acrylic polymers, may be added to improve various properties of the
ink composition.</p><p num="0017">In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the ink compositions comprise, by
weight, about 18% organic cosolvents, about 6% surfactants, about 6% mixed organic
acid, and about 4% dye.</p><heading>B. Ink Composition Materials</heading><heading>1. Organic Cosolvents</heading><p num="0018">One or more organic cosolvents may be used to prepare the ink
compositions of the present invention. In a preferred embodiment, the organic 
cosolvents are water-soluble. Exemplary water-soluble organic cosolvents suitable for
this purpose include, but are not limited to, aliphatic alcohols, aromatic alcohols,
diols, triols, amides, ketones, polyketones or ketoalcohols, nitrogen-containing
heterocyclic ketones, ethers, glycol ethers, poly(glycol) ethers, alkylene glycols,
polyalkylene glycols, thioglycols containing alkylene groups, lower alkyl ethers of
polyhydric alcohols and lactams. The concentration of the organic cosolvents may
range from 0.01 to 50 wt %, preferably from 5 to 25 wt %.</p><heading>2. Surfactants</heading><p num="0019">One or more water soluble surfactants may be employed in the
formulation of a vehicle for the ink. For convenience, examples of surfactants are
divided into two categories: (1) non-ionic and amphoteric and (2) ionic. The former
class includes the alkyl polyethylene oxides (POEs); alkyl phenyl POEs; ethylene
oxide/propylene oxide block copolymers; acetylenic POEs; POE esters; POE diesters;
POE amines; POE amides; and dimethicone copolyols. U.S. Patent No. 5,106,416
(incorporated by reference herein) discusses many of the surfactants listed above in
greater detail. Amphoteric surfactants such as substituted amine oxides or members of
the Octyl dimethyl glycine family of octylamine choloroacetic adducts are also useful
in the practice of this invention. Cationic surfactants such as protonated POE amines,
and anionic surfactants such as diphenyl sulfonate derivatives like, but not limited to,
sodium hexadecyl diphenyloxide disulfonate, and ethoxylated oleoalcohol phosphate
esters may also be used.</p><p num="0020">Non-ionic/amphoteric surfactants are preferred over the ionic surfactants.
Specific examples of surfactants that are preferably employed in the practice of this
invention include Secondary alcohol ethoxylate, SURFYNOL™ CT-111, Octyl
dimethyl glycine, Sodium hexadecyl diphenyloxide disulfonate, Oleyl triethoxy mono
diphosphate, iso-hexadecyl ethylene oxide 20 (available from the ICI Group as
ARLASOLVE™ 200), and amine oxides such as N,N-dimethyl-N-dodecyl amine
oxide, N,N-dimethyl-N-tetradecyi amine oxide, N,N-dimethyl-N-hexadecyl amine
oxide, N,N-dimethyl-N-octadecyl amine oxide, N,N-dimethyl-N-(Z-9-octadecenyl)-N-amine
oxide. The ink composition of the present invention comprises by weight
from 0 to 40%, preferably from 0.1 to 7%, surfactants. </p><heading>3. Organic Acids</heading><p num="0021">Two or more organic acids may be included in the ink compositions of
the present invention. As mentioned earlier, the organic acids effectively reduce the
pH differential between adjacent inks that is preferentially required to control color
bleed. Preferably succinic acid is one of the organic acids. Exemplary organic acids
suitable for use as additional organic acids include monofunctional organic acids,
difunctional organic acids, and polyfunctional organic acids. These include, but are
not limited to, glutaric acid, oxalic acid, maleic acid, methylsuccinic acid, malonic
acid, adipic acid, fumaric acid, dihydroxyfumaric acid, malic acid, mesaconic acid,
itaconic acid, phthalic acid, isophthalic acid, terephthalic acid, aspartic acid, glutamic
acid, 1,2-, 1,3- and 1,4-cyclohexane dicarboxylic acids, 1,2,3-cyclohexane
tricarboxylic acid, 1,2,4-cyclohexane tricarboxylic acid, 1,3,5-cyclohexane
tricarboxylic acid, 1,2- and 1,3-cyclopentane dicarboxylic acids, citric acid, tartaric
acid, dihydroxyterephthalic acid, 1,2,3-, 1,2,4- and 1,2,5-benzene tricarboxylic acids,
tricarballylic acid, 1,2,4,5-benzene tetracarboxylic acid, norbornene tetracarboxylic
acid, 3,3',4,4'-benzophenone tetracarboxylic acid, 1,2,3,4,5,6-benzene hexacarboxylic
acid, acetic acid, polyacrylic acid, glycolic acid, and derivatives thereof. Preferably
glutaric acid is a second organic acid of the invention. The ink composition of the
present invention preferably comprises by weight from 3 to 12% mixed organic acid.</p><heading>4. Dyes</heading><p num="0022">Suitable dyes for the present invention include but are not limited to
aqueous dyes such as Direct Blue 86, Direct Blue 199, Direct Yellow 132, Acid
Yellow 132, Direct Red 9, Direct Red 32, Acid Yellow 23, Acid Blue 185, Acid Blue
9, Acid Red 17, Acid Red 52, Acid Red 249, and Reactive Red 180. The ink
composition of the present invention preferably comprises by weight from 0.5 to 10%
aqueous dye. </p> <heading>Examples</heading><p num="0023">In order to further illustrate the invention, some exemplary compositions are
set forth below.</p><heading>Example 1 ― Bleed</heading><p num="0024">Ink-jet ink compositions were prepared as shown in Table 1 (all values
are weight percentages unless otherwise indicated): <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Component</b></entry> <entry align="center"><b>Ink comprising Glutaric acid <i>only</i> </b> </entry><entry align="center"><b>Inks comprising Glutaric <i>and</i> Succinic acids</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ink comprising Succinic acid <i>only</i></b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Alkyl diol</b></entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Polyethylene glycol</b></entry><entry align="center">3.3</entry><entry align="center">3.3</entry><entry align="center">3.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Octyl dimethyl glycine</b></entry><entry align="center">4.4</entry><entry align="center">4.4</entry><entry align="center">4.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Secondary alcohol ethyloxylate</b></entry><entry align="center">0.7</entry><entry align="center">0.7</entry><entry align="center">0.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Sodium hexadecyl diphenyloxide disulfonate</b></entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Oleyl triethoxy mono diphosphate</b></entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Succinic acid<!--footnotes removed--></b></entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry><entry align="center">0.9-4.5</entry><entry align="center">5.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Glutaric acid<!--footnotes removed--></b></entry><entry align="center">6.0</entry><entry align="center">5.0-1.0</entry><entry align="center">0.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Chelating agent</b></entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Magenta dye</b></entry><entry align="center">4.2</entry><entry align="center">4.2</entry><entry align="center">4.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Water</b></entry><entry align="center">balance</entry><entry align="center">balance</entry><entry align="center">balance</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>pH<!--footnotes removed--></b></entry><entry align="center">4.0</entry><entry align="center">4.0</entry><entry align="center">4.0<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0025">A black to magenta color bleed test was performed on Union Camp
JAMESTOWN™ paper using the ink-jet ink compositions of Table 1. The color bleed
results obtained are depicted in Figure 1. The color bleed test involved printing a
pigment black ink (used in the HP DESKJET 970 PROFESSIONAL SERIES™
printer) adjacently to a series of magenta color inks. As can be seen from Table 1, the
magenta color inks comprised organic cosolvents, surfactants and a magenta dye. In
addition the magenta color inks each included 450 mmol organic acid per kg wherein,
the molar fraction of glutaric acid was (a) 1.000, (b) 0.833, (c) 0.667, (d) 0.500, (e)
0.333, (f) 0.167 and (g) 0.000 and the remaining fraction consisted of succinic acid. 
The results shown in Figure 1, indicate that color bleed is acceptable for all of the
inks, and hence that inks containing a mixture of succinic and glutaric acid perform as
well as inks that contain succinic or glutaric acid only. Similar results were obtained
when the color bleed test was performed on Hewlett-Packard BRIGHT WHITE
INKJET™ paper or Champion DATACOPY™ paper.</p><heading>Example 2 - Reliability</heading><p num="0026">The short term and long term decap performance of the ink formulation shown
in Table 2 were measured.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Component</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ink comprising Glutaric <i>and</i> Succinic acids</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Alkyl diol</b></entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>polyethylene glycol</b></entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Octyl dimethyl glycine</b></entry><entry align="center">3.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Secondary alcohol ethoxylate</b></entry><entry align="center">0.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Sodium hexadecyl diphenyloxide</b></entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>disulfonate</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Oleyl triethoxy mono diphosphate</b></entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>succinic acid</b></entry><entry align="center">4.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>glutaric acid</b></entry><entry align="center">0.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>chelating agent</b></entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>magenta dye</b></entry><entry align="center">4.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>water</b></entry><entry align="center">balance</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>pH<!--footnotes removed--></b></entry><entry align="center">4.0<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0027">Short term decap performance describes the period in between successive
firings a nozzle can tolerate without a defect. The ink-filled pens were placed in the
printer and used to print a so-called "print file" with a predetermined print pattern. 
The print file was set to cause the nozzles to pause between successive ink drop
ejections for predetermined periods of time. The printed nozzle pattern was examined
for defects such as weak (i.e. producing low drop volume and/or velocity),
misdirected, or non-functional nozzles. The longest inoperative time that a nozzle
could withstand between resistor firings without a defect is reported as short term
decap. It is desirable that the nozzles tolerate long periods of inactivity between
resistor firings, typically short term decap times are required to be longer than 3
seconds. Here, a score of "marginal" was given for decap times in the range 1-3
seconds, of "good" in the range 3-5 seconds, and of "very good" for any decap time
longer than 5 seconds. The ink composition of Table 2 exhibited <i>good</i> short term
decap performance.</p><p num="0028">Long term decap performance describes the level of nozzle recovery after the
nozzles have been idle for an extended period of time. To test this, the nozzles were
left untaped (<i>i.e.</i> exposed to air) at ambient temperature for a period of three days.
Following this storage period, the ink-filled pens were placed in the printer and used
to print a predetermined "print file." Pen performance was evaluated by measuring the
percentage of nozzles that recovered after printing the print file four times without
interruption. A nozzle was considered to have recovered if it fired drops of the proper
volume and velocity and in the proper location. It is preferred that 100% of the
nozzles recover; however, acceptable recovery levels for such a storage period are in
the range of 93-100%. Here, a score of "marginal" was given for recovery levels
lower than 93%, of "good" in the range 93-97%, and of "very good" in the range 97-100%.
The ink composition of Table 2 exhibited <i>very good</i> long term decap
performance.</p><heading>Conclusion</heading><p num="0029">The benefits of the present invention are highlighted when the color bleed data
and pen reliability data are combined. In Example 1 it was shown that succinic and
glutaric acids can be used interchangeably and as a mixed acid system in an ink
composition without any loss of bleed control. In Example 2 it was shown that the
mixed acid system exhibits good short term decap times and very good long term
decap recovery. </p><p num="0030">In addition, the use of mixtures of organic acids instead of individual organic
acids is even more beneficial when the combined organic acids complement each
other in some way. For example, while succinic acid is an irritant at high
concentrations, glutaric acid is not. On the other hand, glutaric acid is about an order
of magnitude more expensive than succinic acid. A suitable mixture of the two not
only exhibits improved pen performance but minimizes toxicity and cost in
comparison to an ink composition that comprises only succinic acid or only glutaric
acid.</p><p num="0031">Other embodiments of the invention will be apparent to those skilled in the art
from a consideration of the specification or practice of the invention disclosed herein.
It is intended that the specification and examples be considered as exemplary only,
with the true scope of the invention being indicated by the following claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An ink-jet ink composition, comprising at least one colorant and a vehicle,
said vehicle including a mixture of succinic acid and at least one second
organic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink composition of claim 1, wherein said second organic acid is
selected from the group consisting of monofunctional organic acids,
difunctional organic acids, and polyfunctional organic acids.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink composition of claim 2, wherein said second organic acid is
selected from the group consisting of glutaric acid, oxalic acid, maleic acid,
methylsuccinic acid, malonic acid, adipic acid, fumaric acid,
dihydroxyfumaric acid, malic acid, mesaconic acid, itaconic acid, phthalic
acid, isophthalic acid, terephthalic acid, aspartic acid, glutamic acid, 1,2-, 1,3-and
1,4-cyclohexane dicarboxylic acids, 1,2,3-cyclohexane tricarboxylic acid,
1,2,4-cyclohexane tricarboxylic acid, 1,3,5-cyclohexane tricarboxylic acid,
1,2- and 1,3-cyclopentane dicarboxylic acids; citric acid, tartaric acid,
dihydroxyterephthalic acid, 1,2,3-, 1,2,4- and 1,2,5-benzene tricarboxylic
acids, tricarballylic acid, 1,2,4,5-benzene tetracarboxylic acid, norbornene
tetracarboxylic acid, 3,3',4,4'-benzophenone tetracarboxylic acid, 1,2,3,4,5,6-benzene
hexacarboxylic acid, acetic acid, polyacrylic acid, glycolic acid, and
derivatives thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink composition of claim 3, wherein said second organic acid is
glutaric acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink composition of claim 4, wherein the concentration of succinic
acid is from about 2 wt % to about 8 wt %, and the concentration of glutaric
acid is from about 0.1 wt % to about 4 wt %.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink composition of claim 5, wherein the concentration of succinic
acid is from about 3 wt % to about 6 wt %, and the concentration of glutaric
acid is from about 0.5 wt % to about 1.5 wt %.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink composition of claim 1, wherein the vehicle further comprises
surfactants and organic cosolvents.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink composition of claim 7, wherein the vehicle comprises from
about 0.1 to about 7 wt % surfactants and from about 5 to about 25 wt %
organic cosolvents.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>