<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1369401-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1369401" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="27612844" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20031210"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1369401-A2" status="new" fvid="23912041"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1369401</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20031210</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03253519-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03253519</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030604</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-16250602-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>16250602</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020604</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/42        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/46        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  28/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/46</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Dichtungsmasse</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Sealing composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition d'étanchéité</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-5335726-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5335726</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5358051-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5358051</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5836392-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5836392</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6192986-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6192986</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6196317-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6196317</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERV INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERVICES, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Halliburton Energy Services, Inc.</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 1431</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73536</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VAN DER WERFF NIELS</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VERLAAN MARCO L</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VAN DER WERFF, NIELS</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VERLAAN, MARCO L.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VAN DER WERFF, NIELS</last-name><address><street>Juliana van Stolberglaan 274</street><city>The Hague 2595 CP</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VERLAAN, MARCO L.</last-name><address><street>Zwethkade 8</street><city>Rotterdam 3046 NV</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Wain, Christopher Paul</last-name><address><street>A.A. Thornton &amp;amp; Co. 235 High Holborn</street><city>London WC1V 7LE</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A subterranean zone penetrated by a well bore is sealed using a sealing composition
comprising a cementitious material, cross-linkable material, and sufficient water to form a slurry,
the cross-linkable material preferably being a 2-hydroxyethyl acrylate or a copolymer of
acrylamide and t-butyl acrylate.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates generally to a sealing composition for sealing a
subterranean zone penetrated by a well bore.</p><p num="0002">In the drilling and completion of an oil or gas well, a cementing composition is often
introduced in the well bore for cementing pipe string or casing. In this process, known as
"primary cementing," the cementing composition is pumped into the annular space between the
walls of the well bore and the casing. The cementing composition sets in the annular space,
supporting and positioning the casing, and forming a substantially impermeable barrier, or
cement sheath, which isolates the well bore into subterranean zones. Thus, the undesirable
migration of fluids between zones is prevented after primary cementing.</p><p num="0003">Changes in pressure or temperature in the well bore over the life of the well can result in
compromised zonal isolation. Also, activities undertaken in the well bore, such as pressure
testing, well completion operations, hydraulic fracturing, and hydrocarbon production can affect
zonal isolation. Such compromised zonal isolation is often evident as cracking or plastic
deformation in the cementing composition, or de-bonding between the cementing composition
and either the well bore or the casing. Compromised zonal isolation requires remedial
operations to reestablish isolation between the zones.</p><p num="0004">One such remedial operation is known as a squeeze, where pressure is used to force a
sealing composition into cracks or other leak paths and restore zonal isolation. Accordingly, a
sealing composition comprising cement can be used in a squeeze operation to plug a perforated
interval of casing and sheath, and is particularly useful because cement allows subsequent re-perforation
if desired. Therefore, a sealing composition incorporating cement, but having
superior sealing properties, is desirable for squeeze operations.</p><p num="0005">We have now devised such a sealing composition.</p><p num="0006">In one aspect, the invention provides a sealing composition for sealing a subterranean
zone penetrated by a well bore, which composition comprises cement, cross-linkable material,
and water.</p><p num="0007">The invention also provides a method of sealing a subterranean zone penetrated by a well
bore, which method comprises placing a sealing composition into the subterranean zone; and
allowing the sealing composition to set therein, the sealing composition being of the invention. </p><p num="0008">A variety of cements can be used in the present invention, including cements comprised
of calcium, aluminum, silicon, oxygen, and/or sulfur, which set and harden by reaction with
water ("hydraulic cements"). Such hydraulic cements include Portland cements, pozzolan
cements, gypsum cements, aluminous cements, silica cements, and alkaline cements. Portland
cements of the type defined and described in API Specification 10, 5<sup>th</sup> Edition, July 1, 1990, of
the American Petroleum Institute (to which reference should be made) are preferred. API
Portland cements include Classes A, B, C, G, and H, of which API Class G is particularly
preferred for the present embodiment. As will be understood, the desired amount of cement is
dependent on the volume required for the sealing operation. Alternatively, the cement can be
microfine cement, such as is available from Dyckerhoff GmBH, Lengerich, Germany, under the
trademark "MICRODUR RU."</p><p num="0009">In one embodiment, the cross-linkable material is a 2-hydroxy ethyl acrylate monomer,
such as is available from Halliburton Energy Services of Duncan, Oklahoma, USA, under the
trademark "PERMSEAL™ ." Such cross-linkable material is described in U.S. patent nos.
5,358,051 and 5,335,726, to which reference should be made. Suitable crosslinkable material
comprises water soluble, vinyl monomers preferably selected from compounds represented
by the general formula
<img id="img-00020001" orientation="unknown" wi="96" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00020001.tif" inline="no" he="23"/>
   wherein:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R<sub>1</sub> = ―CH<sub>3</sub> or ―H.</st32:che><img id="img-00020002" orientation="unknown" wi="71" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00020002.tif" inline="no" he="12"/><img id="img-00030001" orientation="unknown" wi="85" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030001.tif" inline="no"  he="25"/><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">E= ―N(C<i><sub>n</sub></i>H<sub>2</sub><i><sub>n</sub></i>+1)<sub><i>a</i></sub>, ―C(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>H or ―H.</st32:che>
      n=1 or 2, a=2 or 3,

      m=0, 1, 2 or 3 and b=0 or 1;

   when
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">D=―SO<sub>3</sub>H,―PO<sub>3</sub>H,</st32:che><img id="img-00030002" orientation="unknown" wi="34" img-format="tif" img-content="cf"  file="00030002.tif"  inline="no"  he="20"/>
or
<img id="img-00030003" orientation="unknown" wi="31" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030003.tif" inline="no" he="26"/>
then b = 0;

   when
<img id="img-00030004" orientation="unknown" wi="63" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030004.tif" inline="no" he="14"/>
      then b= 1; and

   when

      a=3, then a suitable counter ion is present.

      In preferred embodiments
<img id="img-00030005" orientation="unknown" wi="59" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00030005.tif" inline="no" he="16"/><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">E is ―C(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>H or ―H,</st32:che>
      b is 1 and m is 0 or 1.</p><p num="0010">Suitable crosslinking agents, in broad terms, are multifunctional, vinyl monomers preferably
selected from compounds represented by the general formulas selected from the group
consisting of <st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">G(B-F-A)<sub>x</sub></st32:che><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">B(F-A)<sub>2</sub></st32:che>
and
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">AG(F-A);</st32:che>
   wherein
<img id="img-00040001" orientation="unknown" wi="35" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif" inline="no" he="16"/><img id="img-00040002" orientation="unknown" wi="35" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040002.tif" inline="no" he="9"/><img id="img-00040003" orientation="unknown" wi="60" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040003.tif" inline="no" he="24"/><img id="img-00040004" orientation="unknown" wi="65" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040004.tif" inline="no" he="32"/><img id="img-00040005" orientation="unknown" wi="69" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040005.tif" inline="no" he="29"/><img id="img-00040006" orientation="unknown" wi="68" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040006.tif" inline="no" he="14"/>
      F can be the same or different,
<img id="img-00040007" orientation="unknown" wi="52" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040007.tif" inline="no" he="7"/>
   d=2 or 3,

   e=0-20,

   f=1 or 2 and

   x=2, 3 or 4.</p><p num="0011">The controllable initiator of this invention, in broad terms, is for example a water soluble
azo compound.</p><p num="0012">Preferably, the cross-linkable material is present in an amount of 0.3 mass percent to 10 
mass percent of the sealing composition.</p><p num="0013">In a second embodiment, the cross-linkable material is a copolymer of acrylamide and
t-butyl acrylate, such as is available from Halliburton Energy Services of Duncan, Oklahoma,
USA, under the trademark "H<sub>2</sub>ZERO<sup>TM</sup>." Such cross-linkable material is described in U.S.
patent nos. 5,836,392, 6,192,986, and 6,196,317, to which reference should be made.</p><p num="0014">Suitable cross-linkable materials include a water soluble copolymer of:
<sl><li>(i) at least one non acidic ethylenically unsaturated polar monomer and</li><li>(ii) at least one copolymerisable ethylenically unsaturated ester.</li></sl></p><p num="0015">The invention also comprises compositions comprising the water soluble copolymer and
a polyvalent metal ion gelling agent.</p><p num="0016">The present invention also provides a process for delaying the rate of gelling of an acrylic
polymer with a gelling agent, in which the acrylic polymer is said copolymer comprising (i) and
(ii).</p><p num="0017">The invention also provides a method for conformance control of a reservoir, especially
one with high formation temperatures, which method comprises:
<sl><li>(a) injecting into the formation an aqueous solution of said composition,</li><li>(b) allowing the solution to flow through at least one zone of high permeability in
said formation under increasing temperature conditions,</li><li>(c) allowing the composition to gel under said conditions. The copolymer is formed
from at least one, e.g. 1-3 polar monomer(s) and at least one, e.g. 1-3 ester(s), and
comprises structural units derived from said monomer(s) and ester(s); preferably
the copolymer consists essentially of said structural units. The ester is
substantially neutral as it is a fully esterified derivative of an acid, i.e. complete
ester, rather than a partial ester with free acid group(s).</li></sl></p><p num="0018">The ester is usually formed from a hydroxyl compound and an ethylenically unsaturated
carboxylic acid. The ethylenically unsaturated group may be in the alpha-beta or beta gamma
position relative to the carboxyl group or may be further distant; preferred acids have 3-20
carbons, such as 3-12, e.g. alkenoic and aralkenoic acids with 3-6 or 9-12 carbons respectively.
Examples of the acids are acrylic, methacrylic, crotonic and cinnamic acids. The hydroxyl
compound is usually an alcohol and may be of formula ROH, where R is a hydrocarbyl group,
preferably an alkyl group, e.g. of 1-30 or 2-30 such as 1-6, 2-6, 7-30 or 7-24 carbons, alkenyl 
groups, e.g. of 2-20 carbons such as 2-6 carbons, cycloalkyl group, e.g. of 5-8 carbons, aryl
group, e.g. aromatic hydrocarbyl group such as 6-20 carbons or aralkyl group, e.g. of 7-24
carbons. Examples of such R groups are methyl, ethyl, n- and iso propyl, n, sec, iso and tert
butyl, n, sec, iso and tert amyl and hexyl, octyl and 2-ethylhexyl, decyl, allyl, cyclohexyl,
palmityl, steryl, phenyl and benzyl. The R group may also be a hydrocarbyl group, substituted by
at least one substituent e.g. 1-3 substituents, especially from hydroxyl, ether, and thio ether
groups; electron donating groups are preferred. Ether substituents are preferred, especially
alkoxy, aryloxy and aralkoxy, in which the alkyl, aryl and aralkyl groups may be as described
above. Preferably the substituent is on the same carbon atom of the R group as is bonded to the
hydroxyl group in the hydroxyl compound; alkoxymethyl and aralkoxy methyl groups are
preferred. The hydroxyl compound may be a primary, secondary, iso or tertiary compound,
especially with a tertiary carbon atom bonded to the hydroxyl group, e.g. tert butyl and trityl. The
group R may also comprise a heterocyclic group either for bonding directly to the hydroxyl group
of ROH or separated there from by an alkylene group, e.g. of 1-4 carbons such as methylene.
Thus group R may be a saturated or unsaturated heterocyclic or heterocyclic alkylene group, e.g.
of 3-8 carbons and at least one, e.g. one or two ring heteroatoms selected from 0, N and S,
especially 0 and/or N, examples of such groups are furyl, tetrahydrofuryl, furfuryl and
tetrahydrofurfuryl, pyranyl and tetra hydropyranyl. Most preferred R groups are tert-butyl, trityl,
methoxymethyl, benzyloxymethyl and tetrahydropyranyl; stearyl, iso propyl, ethyl and methyl
may also be preferred.</p><p num="0019">The ester (i) may also be derived from a hydroxyl compound, e.g. of formula ROH and an
ethylenically unsaturated sulphonic or phosphoric acid, which may contain 2-20 carbons,
especially 2-6 carbons, such as alkenyl acids, e.g. vinyl sulphonic acid and vinyl phosphonic
acid. Thus the ester may be methyl or ethyl vinyl sulphonate or phosphonate. The ester may be
derived from an acid containing an ethylenically unsaturated carboxamide (e.g. acrylamido)
group, as well as the sulphonic or phosphonic acid group; an example of such an acid is 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane
sulphonic acid.</p><p num="0020">The ester is copolymerised with an ethylenically unsaturated polar monomer, in which
the unsaturated group is usually vinyl or alpha methyl vinyl and may be derived from an
unsaturated carboxylic acid (the acid being as further described above) e.g. primary, secondary or
tertiary amide thereof, in which the amide is derived from ammonia, or a primary or secondary 
alkylamine, e.g. of 1-10 carbons, which may optionally be substituted by at least one hydroxyl
group as in alkylol amides such as ethanolamides; examples of such carboxylic derived polar
monomers are acrylamide, methacrylamide and acrylic ethanol amide. The polar monomer may
also be a vinyl heterocyclic compound e.g. with at least one O, S or N atom in a ring with 3-8
carbons such as one with at least one carbonyl group in the ring, e.g. N-vinyl-pyrrolidone or-caprolactam,
or a vinyl pyridine.</p><p num="0021">The copolymer may contain 0.01-50% e.g. 0.1-40% or 1-30%, especially 5-15% mol of
structural units from said ester(s) and 99.99-50% e.g. 99.9-60% or 99-70 or 95-85% mol of
structural units from said polar monomer(s). The copolymer may be a block or non block
copolymer, e.g. a regular or random copolymer or a graft copolymer, especially with ester units
grafted onto polymeric polar, monomer, e.g. ester grafted on polyacrylamide.</p><p num="0022">The copolymer is usually soluble in water to an extent of at least 1 g/l e.g. 1-200 g/l such
as at least 10 g/l in distilled water at 15° C., especially in aqueous sodium chloride solution
containing 32 g/l NaCI at 25° C. If desired, the copolymer may be mixed with a surfactant (e.g.
in amount of 0.01-5% by wt of the solution) to help solubilise it in the water or sodium chloride
solution.</p><p num="0023">The copolymer may have a weight average molecular weight of at least 50,000 e.g.
50,000-20 million, such as 100,000 to 10 million, especially 100,000-500,000 or 1-10 million;
the molecular weight may be determined by conventional methods, e.g. gel permeation
chromatography or intrinsic viscosity. The low mole wt copolymer may have a viscosity in
aqueous 3.6% wt solution at 19° C. of 10-500 cps (measured at 60 rpm with a Haake
viscometer). Preferably the copolymer is sheer thinnable, e.g. with the viscosity reducing by at
least 10% on increasing the sheer rate by 10%. Preferably, the cross-linkable material is present
in a range of 0.3 mass percent to 10 mass percent of the sealing composition.</p><p num="0024">The water used to form the slurry is present in an amount sufficient to make the slurry
pumpable for introduction down hole. The water used to form a slurry in the present
embodiment can be fresh water, unsaturated salt solution, including brines and seawater, and
saturated salt solution. Generally, any type of water can be used, provided that it does not
contain an excess of compounds well known to those skilled in the art, that adversely affect
properties of the sealing composition. The water is preferably present in an amount of about
25-98 mass percent of the sealing composition, and more preferably in an amount of about 38 
mass percent of the sealing composition.</p><p num="0025">The sealing composition may further comprise a latex comprising a styrene/butadiene
copolymer having a styrene to butadiene weight ratio of about 25:75, with the styrene/butadiene
copolymer suspended in a 50% by weight aqueous emulsion, discussed in Patent No. 5,688,844,
and available from Halliburton Energy Services of Duncan, Oklahoma, USA, under the
trademark "LATEX 2000™.''</p><p num="0026">In another embodiment, the sealing composition may further comprise a stabilizer, such
as a C<sub>15</sub> alcohol ethoxylated with 40 moles of ethylene oxide, available from Halliburton Energy
Services of Duncan, Oklahoma, USA, under the trademark "434C™ ."</p><p num="0027">A variety of additives may be added to the sealing composition to alter its physical
properties. Such additives may include slurry density modifying materials (e.g., silica flour,
silica fume, sodium silicate, microfine sand, iron oxides and manganese oxides), dispersing
agents, set retarding agents, set accelerating agents, fluid loss control agents, strength
retrogression control agents, and viscosifying agents well known to those skilled in the art.</p><p num="0028">The following Examples illustrate the invention.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0029">Components in the amounts listed in TABLE 1 were added to form five slurries for
squeeze operations. Slurries 1 and 2 contained no cross-linkable material, while Slurries 3-5
contained cross-linkable material dispersed in fresh water in a ratio of 5% by weight of the
resulting composition.</p><p num="0030">Slurries 1-5 variously include one or more of the following additives: fine silica flour
available from Halliburton Energy Services of Duncan, Okla., under the trademark "SSA-1™ ";
a bond improving/expanding additive comprising dead burned magnesium oxide for providing
crystalline growth, available from Halliburton Energy Services of Duncan, Okla., under the
trademark "MICROBOND HT™ "; a fluid loss additive comprising a copolymer of AMPS and
N,N dimethylacrylamide, available from Halliburton Energy Services of Duncan, Okla., under
the trademark "HALAD®-344"; and a friction reducer comprising the condensation reaction
product of formaldehyde, acetone and sodium bisulfite, available from Halliburton Energy
Services of Duncan, Okla., under the trademark "CFR-3L™.''</p><p num="0031">Various properties determined for each slurry are listed in TABLE 1. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Component</entry><entry align="left">Slurry 1</entry><entry align="left">Slurry 2</entry><entry align="left">Slurry 3</entry><entry align="left">Slurry 4</entry><entry align="left">Slurry 5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">H<sub>2</sub>ZERO cross-linkable material[% by weight of cement ("bwoc")]</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">45.9</entry> <entry align="left">45.7</entry><entry align="left">61.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fresh water [% bwoc]</entry><entry align="left">45.9</entry> <entry align="left">61.6</entry> <entry align="left">- -</entry> <entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">--</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Portland Class 'G' cement [%bwoc]</entry><entry align="left">100</entry><entry align="left">100</entry><entry align="left">100</entry><entry align="left">100</entry><entry align="left">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SSA-1 silica flour [%bwoc]</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">35</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MICROBOND HT additive[%bwoc]</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">0.75</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">0.75</entry></row><row><entry align="left">HALAD®-344 fluid loss additive [%bwoc]</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry><entry align="left">0.3</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">0.3</entry><entry align="left">0.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">CFR-3L friction reducer[1/100kg]</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">0.25</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">0.25</entry><entry align="left">0.25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Density [SG]</entry><entry align="left">1.85</entry><entry align="left">1.85</entry><entry align="left">1.85</entry><entry align="left">1.85</entry><entry align="left">1.85</entry></row><row><entry align="left">BHST[°F]</entry><entry align="left">212</entry><entry align="left">257</entry><entry align="left">212</entry><entry align="left">212</entry><entry align="left">257</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rheology at mix</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">262-187-</entry><entry align="left">300+-</entry><entry align="left">300+-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">300-200-100-6-3</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">105</entry><entry align="left">300+-289-</entry><entry align="left">300+-224-</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">21-17</entry><entry align="left">22-14</entry><entry align="left">25-18</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rheology @ 195°F</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">197-140-</entry><entry align="left">300+-</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry></row><row><entry align="left">300-200-100-6-3</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">87</entry><entry align="left">300+-185-</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">20-17</entry><entry align="left">12-7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Squeeze pressure [psi]</entry><entry align="left">300</entry><entry align="left">250</entry><entry align="left">250</entry><entry align="left">250</entry><entry align="left">250</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Captured filtrate [cc/min]</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">100/3</entry><entry align="left">15/30</entry><entry align="left">5/5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelled</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">Yes</entry><entry align="left">Yes</entry><entry align="left">Yes</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Max. flowback pres [psi]</entry><entry align="left">300</entry><entry align="left">600</entry><entry align="left">750</entry><entry align="left">2100</entry><entry align="left">2250</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0032">As shown in Table 1, Slurry 1 was a standard cement slurry which had a flowback
pressure of 300 psi. Slurry 2 was a standard cement slurry tested at a higher bottom hole static
temperature (BHST), and had a backflow pressure of 600 psi.</p><p num="0033">In contrast, Slurry 3, a composition according to the present invention, had a backflow
pressure of 750 psi, more than twice that of the standard (Slurry 1). Slurry 4, also a composition
according to the present invention, was treated with fluid loss additive and had a much higher
backflow pressure of 2100 psi. Slurry 5, also a composition according to the present invention,
was tested at a higher bottom hole static temperature, and had a backflow pressure of 2250 psi,
more than three times that of the applicable standard (Slurry 2). Thus, TABLE 1 shows the
increased effectiveness of the sealing compositions of the present invention. </p><heading>EXAMPLE 2</heading><p num="0034">Components in the amounts listed in TABLE 2 were added to form two slurries, Slurries
6-7, which contained cross-linkable material gelled in fresh water in a ratio of 5% by weight of
the resulting composition.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Component</entry><entry align="left">Slurry 6</entry><entry align="left">Slurry 7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">H<sub>2</sub>ZERO cross-linkable material [%bwoc]</entry><entry align="left">49.42</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PERMSEAL cross-linkable material [%bwoc]</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">49.63</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fresh water [%bwoc]</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry><entry align="left">- -</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dyckerhoff 'G' cement [%bwoc]</entry><entry align="left">100</entry><entry align="left">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Density [SG]</entry><entry align="left">1.85</entry><entry align="left">1.85</entry></row><row><entry align="left">BHST [°F]</entry><entry align="left">195</entry><entry align="left">195</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rheology at mix 300-200-100-6-3</entry><entry align="left">300+-220-136-39-35</entry><entry align="left">57-48-35-16-15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rheology @ 195°F 300-200-100-6-3</entry><entry align="left">218-173-77-6-3</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Squeeze pressure [psi]</entry><entry align="left">250</entry><entry align="left">250</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Captured filtrate [cc/min]</entry><entry align="left">60/5</entry><entry align="left">62/0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Gelled</entry><entry align="left">Yes</entry><entry align="left">Yes</entry></row><row><entry align="left">UCA</entry></row><row><entry align="left">50 psi [hrs:min]</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">64:49</entry></row><row><entry align="left">500 psi [hrs:min]</entry><entry align="left">23:27</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Final CS [psi/hrs]</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry><entry align="left">ND</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0035">Table 2 shows that the filtrate of both Slurries 6 and 7 gelled, while providing a curable
sealine composition</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A sealing composition for sealing a subterranean zone penetrated by a well bore, which
composition comprises cement, cross-linkable material, and water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 1, wherein the cement is Portland cement, pozzolan
cement, gypsum cement, aluminous cement, silica cement or alkaline cement.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 1, wherein the cement is class G cement.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 1, 2 or 3, wherein the cross-linkable material is a
2-hydroxyethyl acrylate monomer, or a copolymer of acrylamide and t-butyl acrylate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A composition according to any of claims 1 to 4, wherein the cross-linkable material is
present in an amount of 0.3 mass percent to 10 mass percent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A composition according to any of claims 1 to 5, wherein the water is present in an
amount of 25-98 mass percent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A composition according to any of claims 1 to 6, further comprising a latex with a
styrene/butadiene weight ratio of substantially 25:75, with the styrene/butadiene copolymer
suspended in a substantially 50% by weight aqueous emulsion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A composition according to any of claims 1 to 7, which further comprises a stabilizer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method of sealing a subterranean zone penetrated by a well bore, which method
comprises placing a sealing composition into the subterranean zone; and allowing the sealing
composition to set therein, the sealing composition being as claimed in any of claims 1 to 8.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>