<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1008384-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1008384" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22781353" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000614"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1008384-A1" status="new" fvid="22868172"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1008384</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000614</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99124064-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99124064</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991210</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-21003998-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>21003998</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981211</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  31/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  31/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  37/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  37/03        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10G  50/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10G  50/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  31/02C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  31/02D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  37/03C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10G  50/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01J231:20</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung eines Perfluoroalkylsulfonsäure-Katalysatorsystems auf Silikaträger</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method of preparation of silica supported perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid catalyst system</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Méthode de préparation d'un sytème catalytique de l'acide perfluoroalcanesulphonique sur support de silice</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0663377-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0663377</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4861923-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4861923</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5276239-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5276239</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997011081-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997011081</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>HARMER M A ET AL: "TOWARDS THE SULFURIC ACID OF SOLIDS" ADVANCED MATERIALS,DE,VCH VERLAGSGESELLSCHAFT, WEINHEIM, vol. 10, no. 15, 20 October 1998 (1998-10-20), pages 1255-1257, XP000783193 ISSN: 0935-9648</text><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PHILLIPS PETROLEUM CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CONOCOPHILLIPS COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PHILLIPS PETROLEUM COMPANY</last-name><address><street>Fifth and Keeler</street><city>Bartlesville Oklahoma</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GREENWOOD GIL J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>RANDOLPH BRUCE B</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GREENWOOD, GIL J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>RANDOLPH, BRUCE B.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GREENWOOD, GIL J.</last-name><address><street>1429 S. Shawnee</street><city>Bartlesville, Oklahoma 74003</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>RANDOLPH, BRUCE B.</last-name><address><street>233 Turkey Creek Rd</street><city>Bartlesville, OK 74006</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Dost, Wolfgang, Dr.rer.nat., Dipl.-Chem.</last-name><address><street>Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Bardehle . Pagenberg . Dost . Altenburg . Geissler . Isenbruck Postfach 86 06 20</street><city>81633 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A method of preparing a catalyst system which comprises mixing
a first solid material comprising at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt
with a second solid material comprising at least one silanol comprising hydroxy
groups and silicon to form a gel comprising silica and the at least one
perfluororalkylsulfonic acid salt, and contacting the gel with an acidic solution
to convert at least a portion of the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt to
at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid is disclosed.</p><p>Alternatively, a method of preparing a catalyst system which
comprises mixing at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt with silica gel to
form a gel comprising silica and at least one perfluororalkylsulfonic acid salt,
and contacting the gel with an acidic solution to convert at least a portion of the
at least one perfluororalkylsulfonic acid salt to at least one
perfluororalkylsulfonic acid is disclosed.</p><p>The thus-obtained catalyst systems are employed as catalysts in
the oligomerization of a hydrocarbon feedstock comprising unsaturated
hydrocarbons.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><i><b>Background of the Invention</b></i></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to catalyst systems useful in
hydrocarbon upgrading processes and to methods for their production and use.</p><p num="0002">In another aspect, this invention relates to catalyst systems and
processes for oligomerizing hydrocarbons employing the novel catalyst systems
of this invention.</p><p num="0003">Perfluoroalkylsulfonic acids are useful for oligomerization of
olefins having in the range of from 3 to 8 carbon atoms per molecule to diesel
fuel range hydrocarbons having in the range of from 8 to 24 carbon atoms per
molecule. However, many of these compounds are waxy, low surface area
solids. The perfluoroalkyl groups of the perfluroalkylsulfonic acids tend to
inhibit the dissolution of hydrocarbons into the perfluoroalkylsulfonic acids,
and mass transfer limitations occur resulting in low catalyst activity. </p><p num="0004">Therefore, it is desirable to develop catalyst systems comprising
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid wherein the perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid is supported
on a high-surface-area support so as to significantly increase the activity of the
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid in oligomerizing at least one olefin to diesel fuel
range hydrocarbons.</p><heading><i><b>Summary of the Invention</b></i></heading><p num="0005">It is an object of this invention to provide a novel catalyst system
which is useful for at least partially oligomerizing at least one olefin to diesel
fuel range hydrocarbons.</p><p num="0006">A further object of this invention is to provide a method of
preparing a novel catalyst system effective for at least partially oligomerizing at
least one olefin to diesel fuel range hydrocarbons.</p><p num="0007">It is a further object of this invention to employ this novel catalyst
system as a catalyst in the at least partial oligomerization of at least one olefin
to diesel fuel range hydrocarbons.</p><p num="0008">It is still a further object of the present invention to increase the
efficiency of the oligomerization of at least one olefin to diesel fuel range
hydrocarbons.</p><p num="0009">Yet another object of the present invention is to provide an
improved oligomerization process of increased efficiency. </p><p num="0010">According to a first embodiment of the present invention, a
method which can be used for producing a catalyst system is provided. The
method comprises the steps of:
<sl><li>dissolving at least a portion of at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic
acid salt of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>X in a basic solution comprising a base to
thereby form a first liquid material, wherein n ranges from 2 to 20 and X is an
element selected from the group consisting of sodium and potassium;</li><li>dissolving at least a portion of at least one hydrolyzable silane
compound in a first acidic solution comprising a first acid to thereby form a
second liquid material comprising at least one silanol comprising hydroxy
groups and silicon;</li><li>mixing the first liquid material and the second liquid material to
thereby form a gel comprising silica and the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic
acid salt;</li><li>contacting the gel with a second acidic solution comprising a
second acid to thereby form an acid-treated gel and to thereby convert at least a
portion of the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt to at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>H and to thereby convert
at least a portion of the second acid to an acid salt; </li><li>removing at least a portion of the acid salt from the acid-treated
gel to thereby form a purified gel; and</li><li>drying the purified gel to thereby form the catalyst system.</li></sl></p><p num="0011">According to a second embodiment of the present invention, an
alternative method which can be used for producing a catalyst system is
provided. The method comprises the steps of:
<sl><li>mixing at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt of the formula
C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>X with silica gel and water to thereby form a gel comprising silica
and at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt, wherein n ranges from 2 to 20
and X is an element selected from the group consisting of sodium and
potassium;</li><li>contacting the gel with an acidic solution comprising an acid to
thereby form an acid-treated gel and to thereby convert at least a portion of the
at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt to at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>H and to thereby convert
at least a portion of the acid to an acid salt;</li><li>removing at least a portion of the acid salt from the acid-treated
gel to form a purified gel; and</li><li>drying the purified gel to thereby form the catalyst system.</li></sl></p><p num="0012">According to a third embodiment of the present invention, a
process is provided for oligomerizing at least a portion of a hydrocarbon
feedstock comprising at least one olefin having in the range of from 3 to 8
carbon atoms per molecule. The process comprises contacting the hydrocarbon
feedstock with a catalyst system prepared by the method of the first
embodiment or, alternatively, the method of the second embodiment.</p><p num="0013">Other objects and advantages will become apparent from the
detailed description and the appended claims.</p><heading><i><b>Detailed Description of the Invention</b></i></heading><p num="0014">According to the first embodiment of the present invention, the
catalyst system can be prepared by the following method.</p><p num="0015">At least a portion of at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid of the
formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>H, wherein n ranges from 2 to 20, can be converted to at
least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>X, wherein
X comprises an element selected from the group consisting of sodium and
potassium, by contacting the perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid with a first basic
solution comprising water and a compound of the formula XOH. The at least
one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid can be contacted in any suitable manner known
to effect the contact of the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid with the
compound. It is preferred for the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid to be 
dissolved in an aqueous solution comprising XOH to thereby form the at least
one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt.</p><p num="0016">Alternatively, at least a portion of at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonyl halide of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>2</sub>Y, wherein n ranges
from 2 to 20 and Y is a halide selected from the group consisting of chlorine,
fluorine, bromine, iodine, astatine and mixtures of any two or more thereof,
preferably fluorine and chlorine, can be converted to at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>X, wherein X
comprises an element selected from the group consisting of sodium and
potassium, by contacting the perfluoroalkylsulfonyl halide with a first basic
solution comprising water and a compound of the formula XOH. The at least
one perfluoroalkylsulfonyl halide can be contacted in any suitable manner
known to effect the contact of the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonyl halide
with the compound. It is preferred for the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonyl
halide to be dissolved in an aqueous solution comprising XOH to thereby form
the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt.</p><p num="0017">Perfluoroalkylsulfonic acids are not easily purified. Thus,
producing a sufficient quantity of purified perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid using
typical separation techniques, such as distillation, to produce an effective
oligomerization catalyst is extremely expensive and inefficient. However, the 
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt (as produced above) of the
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid can be easily separated from the aqueous solution,
by washing, settling and filtration techniques, resulting in a purified
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt.</p><p num="0018">The purified at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt can be
dissolved in a basic solution comprising a base comprising hydroxy groups to
form a first liquid material.</p><p num="0019">At least one hydrolyzable silane compound can be dissolved in a
first acidic solution comprising a first acid and water to thereby form a second
liquid material comprising at least one silanol comprising hydroxy groups and
silicon.</p><p num="0020">Suitable hydrolyzable silane compounds include, but are not
limited to, alkoxysilane compounds, preferably, tetramethoxysilane and
tetraethoxysilane.</p><p num="0021">Any suitable acid effective in hydrolyzing the hydrolyzable silane
compound can be used as the first acid. Preferably, the first acid is
hydrochloric acid.</p><p num="0022">The first liquid material and second liquid material can be mixed
in any suitable manner, including, but not limited to, stirring or blending, 
sufficient to effect a thorough mixing so as to form a gel comprising silica
(SiO<sub>2</sub>) and the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt.</p><p num="0023">The gel can then be contacted with a second acidic solution
comprising a second acid to thereby form an acid-treated gel and to thereby
convert at least a portion of the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt to at
least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>H.</p><p num="0024">Any suitable acid effective in converting at least a portion of the
at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt to at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid can be used as the second acid. Preferably, the
second acid is sulfuric acid.</p><p num="0025">More particularly, the contacting of the gel with the second acidic
solution results in the at least partial conversion of the at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>X to the at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>H and the at least partial
conversion of the acid to its acid salt. The preferred acid, sulfuric acid (H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>),
is at least partially converted to its acid salt (X<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>).</p><p num="0026">The acid-treated gel can then be washed with water in order to at
least partially remove the acid salt to thereby form a purified gel.</p><p num="0027">The purified gel can then be dried at a temperature of between
about 140°F (60°C) and about 180°F (82.2°C) to thereby form the catalyst 
system. Preferably, the drying is performed under vacuum conditions and for
greater than 2 hours.</p><p num="0028">Optionally, a platinum group metal compound can be
incorporated into the catalyst system, by any suitable manner, to provide active
sites to aid in catalyst regeneration. As used herein, platinum group metals
include, but are not limited to, iron, ruthenium, osmium, cobalt, rhodium,
iridium, nickel, palladium and platinum.</p><p num="0029">According to the second embodiment of the present invention, the
catalyst system can alternatively be prepared by the following method.</p><p num="0030">The at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt can be prepared
by the method described above in the first embodiment.</p><p num="0031">The at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt can be combined,
by mixing, stirring or blending, with a silica gel and water to thereby form a gel
comprising silica and the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt.</p><p num="0032">The gel can then be contacted with an acidic solution comprising
an acid to thereby form an acid-treated gel and to thereby convert at least a
portion of the at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt to at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>H.</p><p num="0033">Any suitable acid effective in converting at least a portion of the
at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt to at least one 
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid can be used as the acid. Preferably, the acid is
sulfuric acid.</p><p num="0034">More particularly, the contacting of the gel with the acidic
solution results in the at least partial conversion of the at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>X to the at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid of the formula C<sub>n</sub>F<sub>2n+1</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>H and the at least partial
conversion of the acid to its acid salt. The preferred acid, sulfuric acid (H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>),
is at least partially converted to its acid salt (X<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>).</p><p num="0035">The acid-treated gel can then be washed with water in order to at
least partially remove the acid salt to thereby form a purified gel.</p><p num="0036">The purified gel can then be dried at a temperature of between
about 140°F (60°C) and about 180°F (82.2°C) to thereby form the catalyst
system. Preferably, the drying is performed under vacuum conditions and for
greater than 2 hours.</p><p num="0037">Optionally, a platinum group metal compound can be
incorporated into the catalyst system, by any suitable manner, to provide active
sites to aid in catalyst regeneration.</p><p num="0038">According to the third embodiment of the present invention, a
process useful for oligomerizing at least a portion of a hydrocarbon feedstock
comprises, consists essentially of, or consists of contacting the hydrocarbon 
feedstock with a catalyst system under conditions sufficient to effect the
oligomerization of at least a portion of the hydrocarbon feedstock. The catalyst
system can be produced by the method of the first embodiment or, alternatively,
by the method of the second embodiment.</p><p num="0039">The term "hydrocarbon feedstock" is generally referred to, unless
otherwise indicated, as one or more hydrocarbons or substituted hydrocarbons
having in the range of from about 2 carbon atoms to about 30 carbon atoms,
preferably about 3 to about 20, and most preferably 3 to 16 carbon atoms per
molecule. Non-limiting examples of suitable hydrocarbon feedstocks include
gasolines from catalytic oil cracking (e.g., FCC and hydrocracking) processes,
pyrolysis gasolines from thermal hydrocarbon (e.g., ethane, propane, and
naphtha) cracking processes, coker naphtha, light coker naphtha, straight run
naphtha, light naphtha and the like. The most preferred hydrocarbon feedstock
comprises at least one olefin containing in the range of from 3 to 10 carbon
atoms per molecule.</p><p num="0040">Generally, the hydrocarbon feedstock is contacted with the
inventive catalyst system contained in an oligomerization zone. The
hydrocarbon feedstock can be contacted with the inventive catalyst system by
any suitable manner. The contacting step can be operated as a batch process
step or, preferably, as a continuous process step. In the latter operation, a solid 
catalyst bed or a moving catalyst bed or a fluidized catalyst bed can be
employed. Any of these operational modes has advantages and disadvantages,
and those skilled in the art can select the one most suitable for a particular feed
and catalyst system.</p><p num="0041">The contacting step is preferably carried out within an
oligomerization zone, wherein is contained the inventive catalyst system, and
under reaction conditions that suitably promote oligomerization of at least a
portion of the unsaturated hydrocarbons of the hydrocarbon feedstock. The
reaction temperature of the oligomerization zone is more particularly in the
range of from about 150°F (65.6 °C) to about 300°F (148.9°C), preferably in
the range of from about 190°F (87.8°C) to about 260°F (126.7°C), and most
preferably in the range of from 200°F (93.3 °C) to 240°F (115.6°C). The
oligomerization zone is operated at a pressure sufficient to maintain the
reactants in liquid form. The contacting pressure of the oligomerization zone is
generally within the range of from about 0 psig to about 1000 psig, preferably
in the range of from about 50 psig to about 500 psig, and most preferably from
100 psig to 250 psig.</p><p num="0042">The flow rate at which the hydrocarbon feedstock is charged to
the oligomerization zone is such as to provide a weight hourly space velocity
("WHSV") in the range of from exceeding 0 hour<sup>-1</sup> upwardly to about 1000 
hour<sup>-1</sup>. The term "weight hourly space velocity", as used herein, shall mean the
numerical ratio of the rate at which a hydrocarbon feedstock is charged to the
oligomerization zone in pounds per hour divided by the pounds of catalyst
contained in the oligomerization zone to which the hydrocarbon feedstock is
charged. The preferred WHSV of the hydrocarbon feedstock to the
oligomerization zone is preferably in the range of from about 0.25 hour<sup>-1</sup> to
about 250 hour<sup>-1</sup> and, most preferably, in the range of from 0.5 hour<sup>-1</sup> to 100
hour<sup>-1</sup>.</p><p num="0043">The following examples are presented to further illustrate the
invention and are not to be construed as unduly limiting its scope. </p><heading><i><b>Example I</b></i></heading><p num="0044">This example illustrates the preparation of catalysts which were
subsequently tested as catalysts in the oligomerization of a hydrocarbon feed
comprising olefins.</p><heading><i><b>Catalyst A</b></i></heading><p num="0045">A 302.4 gram quantity of tetraethoxysilane was hydrolyzed in
83.6 grams of distilled water containing 2 grams of concentrated HCl solution
to form a first liquid material. A clear homogenous solution was obtained in
approximately 10 minutes. A second liquid material consisting of 25.0 grams
of perfluorooctanesulfonic acid salt (C<sub>8</sub>F<sub>17</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>-K<sup>+</sup>) was dissolved in 180 mL of
0.333 N NaOH solution. The first and second liquid materials were combined
and gelation occurred within 20 seconds. Excess water was decanted and the
gel was dried under vacuum at 50°C for 16 hours.</p><p num="0046">After drying, 30.5 grams of the dried solid was washed with 100
mL of 3.5 N HCl solution followed by a 100 mL distilled water wash. A
second wash with 100 mL of 3.5 N HCl solution was performed, this solution
also contained 2.16 g of a 10% PtCl<sub>4</sub> solution in water. The solid was filtered
and washed with 50 mL of distilled water.</p><p num="0047">The filtered solid was placed into a 500 mL flask and 100 mL of
70% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> solution was prepared and added at a temperature above 70°C to 
the solid. The acidified mixture was stirred for 12 hours. Stirring was stopped
and 400 mL of distilled water was added and the solid was filtered off. The
solid was then dried at 50°C for 8 hours. The final catalyst contained 21.0
weight % perfluorooctanesulfonic acid based on the total weight of the catalyst.</p><heading><i><b>Catalyst B</b></i></heading><p num="0048">A 91.8 gram quantity of silica (Davison G57 grade) was
suspended in 500 mL of distilled water. A 31.7 gram quantity of
perfluorooctanesulfonic acid salt (C<sub>8</sub>F<sub>17</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>-K<sup>+</sup>) was dissolved in 100 mL of
distilled water and added to the silica/water suspension. The mixture was
mechanically stirred for 1 hour, then acidified by addition of 40 mL of 98%
H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. Stirring continued for 1 hour and then the solids were settled. The
water was decanted and the remaining solids were washed with 100 mL of
distilled water and filtered. After filtration, the solid was dried for 24 hours
under vacuum. The final catalyst contained 24.4 weight %
perfluorooctanesulfonic acid based on the total weight of the catalyst.</p><heading><i><b>Example II</b></i></heading><p num="0049">This example illustrates the use of the catalysts described in
Example I as catalysts in the oligomerization of a hydrocarbon feed comprising
olefins. </p><p num="0050">In Run 1, 20.89 grams of Catalyst A from Example I was placed
in an autoclave reactor including a stirring shaft and impeller. Air present in
the autoclave reactor was evacuated and the autoclave reactor was heated to
87.8°C for 1 hour. The reactor was then cooled to 74°C and N<sub>2</sub> was added to a
pressure of 50 psig. The autoclave reactor was heated to 94.3 °C and the
hydrocarbon feed was introduced to the autoclave reactor over a time period of
3.35 minutes with a stirring rate of 1000 rpm. The autoclave reactor
temperature, after 30.0 minutes of contact time, increased to 114.8 °C. The
product was collected for analysis after 30.0 minutes of contact time and
analysis was by means of a gas chromatograph. Test results are summarized in
Table 1.</p><p num="0051">In Run 2, 19.78 grams of Catalyst B from Example I was placed
in an autoclave reactor including a stirring shaft and impeller. Air present in
the autoclave reactor was evacuated and the autoclave reactor was heated to
87.8°C for 1 hour. The reactor was then cooled to 74°C and N<sub>2</sub> was added to a
pressure of 50 psig. At this time, the hydrocarbon feed was introduced to the
autoclave reactor over a time period of 5.50 minutes with a stirring rate of 500
rpm. The autoclave reactor temperature, after 30.0 minutes of contact time,
increased to 87.7°C. The product was collected for analysis after 30.0 minutes 
of contact time and analysis was by means of a gas chromatograph. Test results
are summarized in Table 1.</p><p num="0052">In Run 3, the 19.78 grams of Catalyst B from Run 2 remained in
the autoclave reactor which includes a stirring shaft and impeller. Air present
in the autoclave reactor was evacuated and the autoclave reactor was heated
under vacuum to 87.8°C for 1 hour. The reactor was then cooled to 74°C and
N<sub>2</sub> was added to a pressure of 50 psig. At this time, the hydrocarbon feed was
introduced to the autoclave reactor over a time period of 3.35 minutes with a
stirring rate of 1000 rpm. The autoclave reactor temperature, after 30.0 minutes
of contact time, increased to 115 °C. The product was collected for analysis
after 30.0 minutes of contact time and analysis was by means of a gas
chromatograph. Test results are summarized in Table 2.</p><p num="0053">In Run 4, the 19.78 grams of Catalyst B from Run 3 remained in
the autoclave reactor which includes a stirring shaft and impeller. N<sub>2</sub> was
added to a pressure of 50 psig. The autoclave reactor was heated to 95 °C and
the hydrocarbon feed was introduced to the autoclave reactor over a time period
of 3.35 minutes with a stirring rate of 1000 rpm. The autoclave reactor
temperature, after 30.0 minutes of contact time, increased to 115 °C. The
product was collected for analysis after 30.0 minutes of contact time and 
analysis was by means of a gas chromatograph. Test results are summarized in
Table 2. <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><i><b>Run 1 Catalyst A</b></i></entry><entry align="center"><i><b>Run 2 Catalyst B</b></i></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Grams of Catalyst</entry><entry align="center">20.89</entry><entry align="center">19.78</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Grams of Feed</entry><entry align="center">53.9</entry><entry align="center">99.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Temp. °C</entry><entry align="center">114.8</entry><entry align="center">87.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Contact time (min.)</entry><entry align="center">30.0</entry><entry align="center">30.0</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><i><b>Feed Composition (wt%)</b></i></entry></row><row><entry align="left">&lt;C<sub>4</sub></entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">0.26</entry></row><row><entry align="left">n-butane</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">2.42</entry></row><row><entry align="left">iso-butane</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">92.45</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-butene</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">4.86</entry></row><row><entry align="left">n-pentane</entry> <entry align="center">0.17</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">iso-pentane</entry><entry align="center">50.79</entry> <entry align="center">0.01</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">1-pentene</entry><entry align="center">23.98</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-methylbutene-1</entry><entry align="center">2.34</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-methylbutene-2</entry><entry align="center">22.51</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-pentene (trans)</entry><entry align="center">0.04</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-pentene (cis)</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2,3-dimethyl-2-butene</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Unknown C<sub>6</sub>+</entry><entry align="center">0.14</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><i><b>Product Composition (wt%)</b></i></entry></row><row><entry align="left">&lt;C<sub>4</sub></entry><entry align="center">1.57</entry><entry align="center">0.24</entry></row><row><entry align="left">n-butane</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">2.57</entry></row><row><entry align="left">iso-butane</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">93.49</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-butene</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">3.16 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">n-pentane</entry><entry align="center">0.14</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">iso-pentane</entry><entry align="center">57.00</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total pentenes</entry><entry align="center">24.81</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total hexenes</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>6</sub>+</entry><entry align="center">16.48</entry><entry align="center">0.55</entry></row><row><entry align="left">butene conversion (weight %)</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">35.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">pentene conversion (weight %)</entry><entry align="center">50.7</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">hexene conversion (weight %)</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>9</sub>+ selectivity</entry><entry align="center">80.6</entry><entry align="center">51.5</entry></row><row><entry>C<sub>9</sub>+ selectivity = % of C<sub>6</sub>+ material with 9 or more carbon atoms per molecule.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><i><b>Run 3 Catalyst B</b></i></entry><entry align="center"><i><b>Run 4 Catalyst B</b></i></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Grams of Catalyst</entry><entry align="center">19.78</entry><entry align="center">19.78</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Grams of Feed</entry><entry align="center">53.03</entry><entry align="center">45.39</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Temp. °C</entry><entry align="center">115</entry><entry align="center">115</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Contact Time (min.)</entry><entry align="center">30.0</entry><entry align="center">30.0</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><i><b>Feed Composition (wt%)</b></i></entry></row><row><entry align="left">propane</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">n-butane</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">iso-butane</entry><entry align="center">0.04</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-butene</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">n-pentane</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">0.10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">iso-pentane</entry><entry align="center">59.15</entry><entry align="center">51.03</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1-pentene</entry><entry align="center">20.20</entry><entry align="center">15.19</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-methylbutene-1</entry><entry align="center">1.64</entry><entry align="center">1.93</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-methylbutene-2</entry><entry align="center">18.60</entry><entry align="center">20.33</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-pentene (trans)</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-pentene (cis)</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2,3-dimethyl-2-butene</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">11.09</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Unknown C<sub>6</sub>+</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">0.27</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><i><b>Product Composition (wt%)</b></i></entry></row><row><entry align="left">&lt;C4</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">n-butane</entry><entry align="center">0.13</entry><entry align="center">0.09</entry></row><row><entry align="left">iso-butane</entry><entry align="center">4.14</entry><entry align="center">0.08</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2-butene</entry><entry align="center">0.16</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="left">n-pentane</entry><entry align="center">0.12</entry><entry align="center">0.08 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">iso-pentane</entry><entry align="center">58.84</entry><entry align="center">51.13</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total pentenes</entry><entry align="center">16.10</entry><entry align="center">14.47</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total hexenes</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">4.66</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>6</sub>+</entry><entry align="center">20.51</entry><entry align="center">29.48</entry></row><row><entry align="left">butene conversion (weight %)</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">---</entry></row><row><entry align="left">pentene conversion (weight %)</entry><entry align="center">60.2</entry><entry align="center">61.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">hexene conversion (weight %)</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">58.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>9</sub>+Selectivity</entry><entry align="center">91.3</entry><entry align="center">92.8</entry></row><row><entry>C<sub>9</sub>+ selectivity = % of C<sub>6</sub>+ material with 9 or more carbon atoms per molecule.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0054">The test data presented in Tables 1 and 2 show that inventive
Catalyst A used in Run 1 and inventive Catalyst B used in Runs 2, 3 and 4 were
active in oligomerizing olefins to diesel range material with olefin conversions
ranging from 35.1 weight % to 61.4 weight %.</p><p num="0055">Reasonable variations, modifications, and adaptations can be
made within the scope of the disclosure and the appended claims without
departing from the scope of this invention.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method of preparing a catalyst system which comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>dissolving at least a portion of at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt
of the formula CnF2n+1SO3X in a basic solution comprising a base to
thereby form a first liquid material, wherein n ranges from 2 to 20 and X is
an element selected from sodium and potassium;</claim-text><claim-text>dissolving at least a portion of at least one hydrolyzable silane compound
in a first acidic solution comprising a first acid to thereby form a second
liquid material comprising at least one silanol comprising hydroxy groups
and silicon;</claim-text><claim-text>mixing said first liquid material and said second liquid material to thereby
form a gel comprising silica and said at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic
acid salt;</claim-text><claim-text>contacting said gel with a second acidic solution comprising a second acid
to thereby form an acid-treated gel and to thereby convert at least a portion
of said at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt to at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid of the formula CnF2n+1SO3H and to thereby
convert at least a portion of said second acid to an acid salt;</claim-text><claim-text>removing at least a portion of said acid salt from said acid-treated gel to
thereby form a purified gel; and</claim-text><claim-text>drying said purified gel to thereby form said catalyst system.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method of preparing a catalyst system which comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>mixing at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt of the formula
CnF2n+1SO3X with silica gel and water to thereby form a gel comprising
silica and said at least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt, wherein n
ranges from 2 to 20 and X is an element selected from sodium and
potassium;</claim-text><claim-text>contacting said gel with an acid solution comprising an acid to thereby
form an acid-treated gel and to thereby convert at least a portion of said at
least one perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt to at least one
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid of the formula CnF2n+1SO3H and to thereby
convert at least a portion of said acid to an acid salt;</claim-text><claim-text>removing at least a portion of said acid salt from said acid-treated gel to
form a purified gel; and</claim-text><claim-text>drying said purified gel to thereby form said catalyst system</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 or 2, wherein said perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt
is prepared by contacting perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid with a compound of
the formula XOH to thereby form said perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 or 2, wherein said perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt
is prepared by contacting perfluoroalkylsulfonyl halide of the formula
CnF2n+1SO2Y with a compound of the formula XOH to thereby form said
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt, wherein Y is a halide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1, 3, and 4, wherein said first acid is
hydrochloric acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 1 and 3 to 5, wherein said second acid is
sulfuric acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 2 to 4, wherein said acid is sulfuric acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method of any of the preceding claims, wherein n is 8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method of any of the preceding claims, wherein said at least one
hydrolyzable silane compound is an alkoxysilane, in particular wherein
said alkoxysilane is selected from tetramethoxysilane and
tetraethoxysilane.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method of claim 1, wherein said perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt has
the formula C8F17SO3X and is prepared by contacting
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid of the formula C8F17SO3H with a compound of
the formula XOH to thereby form said perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt;
wherein said at least one hydrolyzable silane compound is an alkoxysilane
compound selected from tetramethoxysilane and tetraethoxysilane, and
wherein said first acid comprises hydrochloric acid, and said second acid
comprises sulfuric acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The method of claim 2, wherein said perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt has
the formula C8F17SO3X and is prepared by contacting
perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid of the formula C8F17SO3H with a compound of
the formula XOH to thereby form said perfluoroalkylsulfonic acid salt; and
wherein said acid comprises sulfuric acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A catalyst system obtainable by a method according to any of the
preceding claims.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A process for oligomerizing at least a portion of a hydrocarbon feedstock
comprising at least one olefin having in the range of from 3 to 10 carbon
atoms per molecule, said process comprising contacting said hydrocarbon
feedstock, at a temperature in the range of from 66 to 149°C (150 to 300
°F), with a catalyst system as defined in claim 12.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>Use of a catalyst system as defined in claim 12, for oligomerizing olefins.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="155" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="241" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="158" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="242" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>