<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-0970990-A1" country="EP" doc-number="0970990" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22337237" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000112"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-0970990-A1" status="new" fvid="22721018"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0970990</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000112</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99113148-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99113148</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990707</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-11121898-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>11121898</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19980707</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  45/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  45/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  47/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  47/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/20        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/20        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/10        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/13        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/1545      20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/19        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  71/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  71/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  71/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  69/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  69/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  69/10        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  67/02+B4Z2</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Gefärbte thermoplastische Polyestermaterialien, enthaltend Polyoxyalkylenverbindungen als Farbstoffe und spezielle oberflächenaktive Substanzen als Verdünner</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Colored polyester thermoplastic materials comprised of poly(oxyalkylenated) compounds as colorants and specific surfactants as diluents</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Matériaux de polyester colorés consistant des composés polyoxyalkyléniques comme colorants ainsi que des agents surfactifs spéciaux comme diluants</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0215322-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0215322</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0455370-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0455370</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4284729-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4284729</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5766268-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5766268</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MILLIKEN &amp; CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MILLIKEN &amp; COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Milliken &amp;amp; Company</last-name><address><street>920 Milliken Road</street><city>Spartanburg, SC 29304</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DANIELSON TODD DAVID</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>IRWIN ELIZABETH M</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>STEPHENSON EUGENE KYLE</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ZHAO XIAODONG EDWARD</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DANIELSON, TODD DAVID</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>IRWIN, ELIZABETH M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>STEPHENSON, EUGENE KYLE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ZHAO, XIAODONG EDWARD</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DANIELSON, TODD DAVID</last-name><address><street>129 Riveredge Drive</street><city>Moore,SC 29369</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>IRWIN, ELIZABETH M.</last-name><address><street>217 Pineville Road</street><city>Spartanburg,SC 29307</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>STEPHENSON, EUGENE KYLE</last-name><address><street>311 Golden Carriage Run</street><city>Spartanburg, SC 29316</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ZHAO, XIAODONG EDWARD</last-name><address><street>211 Windswept Court</street><city>Moore,SC 29369</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Behrens, Dieter, Dr.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>Wuesthoff &amp;amp; Wuesthoff Patent- und Rechtsanwälte Schweigerstrasse 2</street><city>81541 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>BE</country><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep"  status="new"  lang="EN"><p>This invention relates to colored polyester thermoplastics comprised of polymeric
colorants having poly(oxyalkylene) moieties and/or anionic dye/quaternary ammonium
substantially inorganic salt-free colorant complexes mixed with diluents selected from the
group consisting essentially of sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>) monoesters, ethoxylated sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>)
monoesters, mixtures thereof of sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>) monoesters and ethoxylated sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>)
monoesters, ethoxylated nonyl-phenol ethers, ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers,
mixtures thereof of said ethoxylated nonyl-phenol ethers and ethoxylated dodecylphenol
ethers, and mixtures of (i) sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>) monoesters or ethoxylated sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>)
monoesters and (ii) ethoxylated nonyl-phenol ethers or ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers.
Such diluents facilitate the introduction of the preferred polymeric colorants within
feedstock polyester during the extrusion or injection molding process and provide a
significant improvement over traditional polyester article colorants. The inventive colored
polyester thermoplastic may be molded into any shape or form; however, plastics are
commonly utilized as containers for liquids, such as soft drinks. A method of coloring
polyester during an extrusion or injection molding procedure utilizing the inventive
colorant/diluent formulations are also provided.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention relates to colored polyester plastics comprised of polymeric
colorants having poly(oxyalkylene) moieties mixed with a diluent selected from the group
consisting essentially of sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>) monoesters, ethoxylated sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>) monoesters,
and mixtures thereof, ethoxylated nonyl-phenol ethers, ethoxylated dodecylphenol
ethers, and mixtures thereof. Such diluents facilitate the introduction of the preferred
polymeric colorants within feedstock polyester during an extrusion or injection molding
process and provide a significant improvement over traditional polyester article colorants.
The inventive colored polyester plastics may be molded into any shape or form, however,
are commonly utilized as containers for liquids, such as soft drinks. A method of coloring
polyester during an extrusion procedure utilizing the inventive colorant/diluent
formulations are also provided.</p><p num="0002">Poly(oxyalkylene) polymeric colorants have been utilized to permanently color
myriad substrates, including thermoplastic resins, such as U.S. Patent 4,284,729, to Cross
et al., U.S. Patent 4,507,407, to Kluger et al., and U.S. Patent 4,751,254, to Kluger et al.;
polyurethane foams, such as U.S. Patent 4,846,846, to Rekers et al.; aqueous and non-aqueous
liquids, such as U.S. Patent 4,871,371, to Harris; and have been used as fugitive
tints for textiles and threads, such as U.S. Patent 4,167,510, to Brendle. Such colorants
provide effective and stable colorations to such materials, are easily handled, and exhibit
desirable migratory properties within certain substrates.</p><p num="0003">Colorants have been developed for utilization within polymer resins, including in
polyester (polyethylene terephthalate, for instance), such as U.S. Patents 4,332,587, to
Kresser et al., 4,640,690, to Baumgartner et al., 4,732,570, to Baumgartner et al.,
4,812,141, to Baumgartner et al., 5,157,067, to Burditt et al., 5,240,980, to Danielson et al.,
5,326,516, to Branon, 5,443,775, to Brannon, and 5,686,515, to Phillips et al. The primary
method of coloring such thermoplastics has been through the utilization of a color
concentrate. Such a concentrate is basically comprised of colored polymer chips which,
when introduced within a standard extrusion or injection molding process, melts with the
subject resin pellets and subsequently colors the molten plastic upon mixing. Although
this procedure is the primary manner of coloring thermoplastics, it also possesses certain
disadvantages which have created problems in the past. For instance, the colorants 
themselves must be able to sustain dispersing during at least two distinct stages, namely the
production of the concentrates polymer chips and then the coloring of the subject thermoplastic
resin. Because of the need to form an initial concentrate, the colorant must also
withstand high temperatures in the polymer chip formation and then, again, during the
creation of the molten resin. Such high temperatures may degrade the colorant and
subjecting such compounds to two distinct stages of melting increases the possibility of
colorant loss.</p><p num="0004">A secondary procedure has also been utilized to color such thermoplastic articles.
This procedure entails the introduction of a liquid colorant into an extrusion or injection
molding machine simultaneously with subject resin pellets or chips, and the like. This
method is preferable to the color concentrate because it is cost effective (there is no need to
produce initial colored polymer chips), subjects the colorant to only one period of high
temperature exposure, and allows for easy handling of the colorant in liquid form. Liquid
poly(oxyalkylenated) colorants provide excellent colorations within polyester thermoplastic
articles and withstand high temperatures processing reasonably well. It has proven
difficult, however, to incorporate such beneficially performing liquid poly(oxyalkylene)
colorants into polyester thermoplastic compositions by this secondary straight introduction
method and also produce suitable aesthetically pleasing colorations within such substrates.
The Baumgartner et al. references, for instance, each teach the utilization of such colorants
within polyester thermoplastics; however, undesirable streaks and specks are noticeable
within the final colored resin products. The problem appears to be that such colorants are
not thoroughly and uniformly incorporated within polyester when utilized on typical
commercial-scale molding equipment. Nowhere within the prior art is there a teaching or
fair suggestion as to how such problems can be remedied for liquid poly(oxyalkylene)
colorants. As a result, there still exists a need for providing the optimum coloring benefits
of polyoxyalkylenated polymeric colorants within polyester thermoplastic compositions
through the straight introduction of a liquid colorant during the extrusion or injection
molding process.</p><p num="0005">Therefore, an object of the invention is to provide a polyoxyalkylenated colorant
formulation which will effectively, thoroughly, and homogeneously color polyester
thermoplastics. Another object of the invention is to provide a relatively inexpensive but
greatly improved polymeric colorant formulation for the coloring of polyester thermoplastic
materials during an extrusion or injection molding procedure. Additionally, it is an
object of this invention to provide an poly(oxyalkylene) colorant/diluent surfactant
formulation which performs at the optimum coloring level within such polyester thermoplastic
media. Furthermore, it is a further object of the invention to provide a method for
effectively, thoroughly, and homogeneously coloring polyester thermoplastic materials. </p><p num="0006">These and other objects are met by the method, a thermoplastic material and a
colored polyester thermoplastic material of the present invention as defined by the
appended claims.</p><p num="0007">The method of the invention provides coloration to a polyester thermoplastic
material during an extrusion or injection molding procedure.</p><p num="0008">The poly(oxyalkylene) colorants are generally the same as those disclosed within
the prior patents listed above. The organic chromophore (R) is, more specifically, one or
more of the following types of compounds: azo, diazo, disazo, trisazo, diphenylmethane,
triphenylmethane, xanthane, nitro, nitroso, acridine, methine, indamine, thiazole, oxazine,
phthalocyanine, or anthraquinone. Preferably, R is one or more of nitro, triphenylmethane,
methine, or thiazole based compounds. Group A is present on group R and is utilized to
attach the polyoxyalkylene constituent to the organic chromophore. Nitrogen is the
preferred linking moiety. The polyoxyalkylene group is generally a combination of
ethylene oxide (EO) and propylene oxide (PO) monomers.</p><p num="0009">The preferred number of moles of polyoxyalkylene constituent per alcohol chain is
from 2 to 15 (n would therefore preferably be from 4 to 30), more preferably from 4 to 10
(n would most preferably be from 8 to 20). Also, preferably two such alcohol chains are
present on each polymeric colorant compound (x, above, is preferably 2). The colorants
utilized within the present invention are generally liquid at ambient conditions of
temperature and pressure. Examples of the particularly preferred colorants are presented in
tabulated form below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><i>Preferred Poly(oxyalkylenated) Colorants</i></entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. #</entry><entry align="left">Chromophore</entry><entry align="center">Moles EO</entry><entry align="center">Moles PO</entry><entry align="center">Group A</entry></row><row><entry align="right">1</entry><entry align="left">Methine</entry><entry align="right">7</entry><entry align="right">15</entry><entry align="left">N</entry></row><row><entry align="right">2</entry><entry align="left">Phthalocyanine</entry><entry align="right">13</entry><entry align="right">2</entry><entry align="left">N</entry></row><row><entry align="right">3</entry><entry align="left">Methine</entry><entry align="right">10</entry><entry align="right">14</entry><entry align="left">N</entry></row><row><entry align="right">4</entry><entry align="left">Methine</entry><entry align="right">16</entry><entry align="right">10</entry><entry align="left">N</entry></row><row><entry align="right">5</entry><entry align="left">Bisazo</entry><entry align="right">16</entry><entry align="right">20</entry><entry align="left">N</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0010">This list is, of course, merely intended to note the preferred colorants; any
poly(oxyalkylenated) polymeric dye is encompassed within the scope of the invention.</p><p num="0011">Other colorants may also be present within this composition, most notably a
substantially inorganic salt free complex comprised of an anionic dye and a quaternary
ammonium compound. Such quaternary ammonium compounds include trialkyl quats, 
such as methyl tri(hydrogenated tallow) ammonium chloride; dialkyl quats, such as dicoco
dimethyl ammonium chloride; dialkoxy alkyl quats, such as methyl bis(polyethoxyethanol)
coco ammonium chloride; monoalkoxy quats, such as methyl (polypropylene glycol)
diethyl ammonium chloride; and benzyl quats, such as dimethyl tallow benzyl ammonium
chloride. Preferred are methyl bis[polyethoxy (15) ethanol] coco ammonium chloride
(trade name Variquat® K1215, from Witco) and methyl (polypropylene glycol) diethyl
ammonium chloride (trade name Emcol™ CC-9, from Witco). The table below shows the
preferred anionic dyes which may be utilized also.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1"><i>Preferred Anionic Dye/Quaternary Ammonium Complex Colorants</i></entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. #</entry><entry align="left">Dyes</entry><entry align="center">Quaternary compounds</entry><entry align="center">Physical Form</entry></row><row><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="left">Acid red 52</entry><entry align="left">Variquat® K1215</entry><entry align="left">Liquid</entry></row><row><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="left">Acid yellow 17</entry><entry align="left">Variquat® K1215</entry><entry align="left">Liquid</entry></row><row><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="left">Quinoline yellow S</entry><entry align="left">Variquat® K1215</entry><entry align="left">Liquid</entry> </row><row><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="left">Quinoline yellow S</entry><entry align="left">Emcol™ CC-9</entry><entry align="left">Liquid</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">10</entry> <entry align="left">Acid yellow 23</entry><entry align="left">Variquat® K1215</entry><entry align="left">Liquid</entry></row><row><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="left">Direct violet 9</entry><entry align="left">Variquat® K1215</entry><entry align="left">Liquid</entry></row><row><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="left">Acid red 52</entry><entry align="left">Emcol™ CC-9</entry><entry align="left">Liquid</entry></row><row><entry align="left">13</entry><entry align="left">Direct blue 86</entry><entry align="left">Variquat® K1215</entry><entry align="left">Liquid</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0012">Other such complexes are intended to be within the scope of this invention as this list is not
intended to be exhaustive.</p><p num="0013">These complexes are produced first by determining the desired anionic dye to be
utilized for its shade, lightfastness, thermal stability, and the like, for the subject substrate
to be colored; second, select the appropriate quaternary ammonium compound for the
subject substrate based on the necessarily required physical properties such as migration,
uniform dispersion, solubility, washfastness, and the like; third, react the two compounds
together to form a liquid complex; and last, remove the unwanted salts formed from the
cation of the dye and the counter-ion of the quat. Various purification techniques may be
performed in order to remove substantially all of the residual inorganic salts (such as
chlorides and sulfates, as merely examples) from the complexes. Such techniques include,
but are not limited to, solvent extraction, phase separation, ultrafiltration, and other
filtration methods. Particularly preferred are ultrafiltration under high pressure, phase
separation through the utilization of an ammonium carbonate rinsing procedure (<i>i.e.</i>, three
consecutive washings with 25% aqueous ammonium carbonate in a 1:1 weight ratio to 
complex), and solvent extraction filtration though the utilization of methylene chloride,
chloroform, or the like. After the removal of excess inorganic salt, the resultant solution
should also be stripped of excess water in order to purify the colorant complex. The
inventive complexes will always form a liquid upon purification at a temperature below
about 100°C. The particular methods of producing these types of colorants, through
complexation and salt removal, are disclosed within U.S. Patent Application 09/065,597,
by Zhao et al., herein incorporated by reference.</p><p num="0014">The term polyester thermoplastic material (or composition or resin) is intended to
encompass any polyester, including co-polymers of different polyesters, thermoplastics
comprised of a majority of polyester constituents, and a single polymer of polyester (i.e.,
polyethylene terephthalate, which is the preferred species). Feedstock is intended to
encompass virgin or recycled polyester, whether in shredded, chipped, pelletized, or any
like form. The term thermoplastic is well known in the art to mean a polymeric material
which will melt upon exposure to sufficient heat but will retain its solidified state, but not
prior shape without use of a mold, upon sufficient cooling. The inventive colored polyester
thermoplastic is intended to be utilized ultimately as, for instance and not by limitation,
containers for soft drinks, beer, liquor, water, and the like, as well as containers for any
solid materials.</p><p num="0015">The specific surfactants required within this invention actually are utilized as
diluents, in addition to their use for their surface-active properties, for the particular
polymeric colorants. Such diluent surfactants have proven to provide the desired colorant
affinity for the particular polyester resin pellets in an extrusion or injection molding
process. Such a proper affinity allows for the production of the optimum colorations on
the solid polyester pellets as well as within the polyester when present in its molten state.
The compatibility of the poly(oxyethylenated) colorants with the particular polyester
thermoplastics is thus increased upon the addition of the particular diluent surfactants of
this invention in order to decrease the amount of color bubbles and streaks within the final
thermoplastic product. Additionally, such diluent surfactants produce an unexpected
benefit in reducing screw slippage during the extrusion procedure (within a screw extruder
machine). Such a discovery of the particular diluent surfactants which provide these
desired characteristics has thus required a great deal of testing in order to determine the
specific compounds, mixtures, and proportions of diluents which produce the required
effects, particularly in tandem with the preferred colorants utilized. The selection of such
colorants thus depended not only on the colorability provided by such compounds, but also
depended on the overall effects and characteristic produced in combination with the
specific diluent surfactants which were found to act synergistically with the preferred
colorants to generate the optimum color within polyester materials while also producing
the lowest degree screw slippage. </p><p num="0016">Further criteria which the particular colorant/diluent surfactant combination must
exhibit includes thermal stability while undergo high melting temperatures during the
extrusion process; no degradation of the polyester either during processing or once the final
product is made; cost effectiveness so as not to translate into higher prices for the
consumer; transparency of the polyester is uniform throughout the entire finished product;
low viscosity in order to permit better processing conditions; homogeneity of dissolution of
the diluent surfactant within the polymeric colorant; and substantially no migration of the
colorant from and within the finished polyester thermoplastic product. This non-migration
characteristic is particularly unexpected within the inventive method and article because
the utilization of a surfactant usually results in the removal of compounds from surfaces
and substrates, not the opposite as was discovered here. The inventive method and article
exhibits all of these necessary characteristics which thus shows the care and degree and
analysis required in order to select the proper diluent surfactant for combination with the
proper poly(oxyalkylene) colorant.</p><p num="0017">It was thus determined that the diluent surfactants which provide all of the
beneficial characteristics mentioned above in tandem with the preferred polymeric
colorants include sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>)monoesters, ethoxylated sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>) monoesters,
mixtures of sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>) monoesters and ethoxylated sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>) esters,
ethoxylated nonylphenol ethers, ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers, mixtures of ethoxylated
nonyl-phenol ethers and ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers, and mixtures of sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>)
monoesters or ethoxylated sorbitan (C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>22</sub>) monoesters and ethoxylated nonylphenol
ethers and ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers. Ethoxylated nonylphenol ethers include
ethoxylated dinonylphenol ethers as well. The sorbitan-based compounds not only provide
the optimum results of colorations in polyester thermoplastic resins but they are also
acceptable for use within materials compositions which may be utilized in association with
compositions which are to be used for human consumption and/or ingestion.</p><p num="0018">The preferred diluent surfactants for utilization within the inventive method
include, in tabulated form: <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><i>Preferred Diluent Surfactants (with Tradenames)</i></entry></row><row><entry align="center">Ex. #</entry><entry align="left">Surfactant</entry><entry align="left">Available as and From</entry></row><row><entry align="right">14</entry><entry align="left">sorbitan monooleate</entry><entry align="left">Span 80®; Imperial Chemical (ICI)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">15</entry><entry align="left">sorbitan monostearate</entry><entry align="left">Span 60®; ICI</entry></row><row><entry align="right">16</entry><entry align="left">sorbitan monopalmitate</entry><entry align="left">Span 40®; ICI</entry></row><row><entry align="right">17</entry><entry align="left">sorbitan monolaurate</entry><entry align="left">Span 20®; ICI</entry></row><row><entry align="right">18</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (20) sorbitan monooleate</entry><entry align="left">Tween 80®; ICI</entry></row><row><entry align="right">19</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (20) sorbitan monostearate</entry><entry align="left">Tween 60®; ICI</entry></row><row><entry align="right">20</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (20)sorbitan monopalmitate</entry><entry align="left">Tween 40®; ICI</entry></row><row><entry align="right">21</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (20) sorbitan monolaurate</entry><entry align="left">Tween 20®; ICI</entry></row><row><entry align="right">22</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (7) dinonylphenol ether</entry><entry align="left">Igepal® DM 430; Rhône-Poulenc (RP)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">23</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (6) nonylphenol ether</entry><entry align="left">gepal® CO 530; RP</entry></row><row><entry align="right">24</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (12) nonylphenol ether</entry><entry align="left">Igepal® CO 720; RP</entry></row><row><entry align="right">25</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (9) dinonylphenol ether</entry><entry align="left">Igepal® DM 530; RP</entry></row><row><entry align="right">26</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (9) nonylphenol ether</entry><entry align="left">gepal® CO 630; RP</entry></row><row><entry align="right">27</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (4) nonylphenol ether</entry><entry align="left">gepal® CO 430; RP</entry></row><row><entry align="right">28</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (1.5) nonylphenol ether</entry><entry align="left">Igepal® CO 210; RP</entry></row><row><entry align="right">29</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (4) nonylphenol ether.</entry><entry align="left">gepal® CO 430; RP</entry></row><row><entry align="right">30</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (9.5) nonylphenol ether</entry><entry align="left">Syn Fac® 905; Milliken &amp; Company</entry></row><row><entry align="right">31</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (5.5) dodecylphenol ether</entry><entry align="left">Igepal® RC 520; RP 430</entry></row><row><entry align="right">32</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (9.5) dodecylphenol ether</entry><entry align="left">Igepal® RC 620; RP</entry></row><row><entry align="right">33</entry><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene (11) dodecylphenol ether</entry><entry align="left">Igepal® Rd 630; RP</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0019">This list is not exhaustive as these are merely the preferred diluent surfactants
within the inventive method and polyester thermoplastic article. Certain mixtures of
ethoxylated and non-ethoxylated sorbitan esters may be utilized. Such specific
combinations are listed below within the Preferred Embodiment. The same is true for the
nonylphenol ethers and dodecylphenol ethers, as well as for the preferred colorants of this
invention.</p><p num="0020">The colorant composition comprises about 15 to about 85% by weight of colorant
and from about 15 to about 85% by weight of diluent surfactant. Preferably the amount of
diluent surfactant is from about 25 to about 75% and most preferably from about 50 to
about 57%. An amount of 5% of diluent surfactant has been utilized in the past with
unsatisfactory results. Thus, the amount of diluent must be above such a low amount in the
colorant/diluent formulation in order to provide the desired beneficial results. Optional 
additives may include plasticizers, such as PEG-400 and dibutyl phthalate, and the like,
antistatic agents, stabilizers, ultraviolet absorbers, and other similar standard polyester
thermoplastic additives.</p><p num="0021">Examples of particularly preferred methods of coloring polyester thermoplastics
and the preferred correlated colored articles within the scope of the present invention are
exemplified below.</p><p num="0022">The colorant/diluent composition was introduced within an injection molding
operation for a polyester thermoplastic, namely polyethylene terephthalate. A metering
system was utilized whereby the colorant/diluent is added by way of a positive displacement
or transfer pump, either continuously or, preferably, intermittently into the injection
molding machine (such as an Arburg Molder). At the same time, the polyester resin was
fed into the throat of the molding machine by way of a screw which works in concert with
the transfer pump metering the liquid colorant/diluent. The rotating screw drew the resin
pellets into the feed throat while the pump activated introduction of the liquid colorant/diluent
into the same area of the machine (in this manner a consistent ratio of pellets to
colorant were utilized in the coloring procedure). At that point, the mix of colorant/diluent
and pellets was either fed into a mixing chamber within the molding machine or gravity fed
directly into the feed section of the molder. Upon mixing or upon placement within the
feed section, the pellets were subsequently melted. In the feed section, melting was
accomplished through the utilization of a heated (heat transferred from the barrel of the
machine) screw extruder which rotated. The rotating screw also effectuated thorough
mixing of the colorant and the molten resin together producing a uniformly colored plastic
melt which was then injected into a mold in order to form the desired thermoplastic article.</p><p num="0023">Testing for coloring improvements and other important criteria was accomplished
through the formation of plaques of colored polyethylene terephthalate thermoplastic resin.
These plaques were formed through the process outlined above with the specific
compositions listed below in Table 4 for colorants and diluents.
<img id="img-00080001" orientation="unknown" wi="150" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00080001.tif" inline="no" he="69"/><img id="img-00090001" orientation="unknown" wi="132" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00090001.tif" inline="no" he="216"/></p><p num="0024">These plaque formulations are, of course, merely preferred embodiments of the inventive
article and method and are not intended to limit the scope of this invention. The resultant
plaques were then tested for Dispersion within each formed resin plaque. Such a test is
empirical and objective in nature utilizing an eye view analysis of resultant colored resins
with a sheet of white paper as the background. A ranking system was developed from 1 to
5 indicating the following:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="4"><dt>1 -</dt><dd>no coloring possible</dd><dt>2 -</dt><dd>colorations clearly not uniform (heavy swirls of color throughout)</dd><dt>3 -</dt><dd>slight swirls apparent through very close analysis</dd><dt>4 -</dt><dd>very slight swirls viewed through hard analysis</dd><dt>5 -</dt><dd>no swirls at all</dd></dl></p><p num="0025">Ten plaques produced through the same procedure and with the same colorant/diluent
formulation are prepared and ranked individually. An average ranking was then taken from
those ten which was the ranking given overall for the specific colorant/diluent formulation.
An overall ranking of 3 or higher is considered acceptable for coloring polyester
thermoplastic articles on a large scale. The following Table lists those for the plaques
prepared in Table 4.
<img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="110" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="126"/><img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="179"/></p><p num="0026">The resultant plaques thus exhibited excellent colorations upon production of the
molten polyethylene terephthalate resin in admixture with each of the specific colorant/diluent
formulations.</p><p num="0027">Two other tests were undertaken to determine the particularly preferred colorant/diluent
formulations of the invention. A 30 second Hobart Mixer test analyzed the mixing
of 250 g of polyester resin pellets with a colorant/diluent formulation loading of 1000 for
30 seconds at a low speed in a Hobart mixer at room temperature (<i>i.e</i>., approximately
25°C). Resultant samples showing clearly non-uniform large blots of random colorations
were considered "poor"; non-uniform small blots of random colorations were considered
"fair"; and uniform colorations throughout were considered "good" for this test. Plaques A 
and V, from Tables 4 and 5, exhibited the best results for this test. The final test was a
Screw Slippage Out-put analysis within an extrusion machine. A control of 1.00 was set
with no additives introduced into 1000 g samples of polyethylene terephthalate resin
pellets (at a 10,000 loading being extruded on the killion at a 32:1 rate). The time to
extrude 1000 g of resin was recorded. The out-put factor for each colorant/diluent
composition was measured as the ratio of time required to extrude 1000 g of colored
samples in relation to the pure control sample. An out-put factor at or near 1.00 (either
above or below) indicated very little screw slippage and thus a highly favorable result.
Again, the formulation utilized for Plaques A and V in Tables 4 and 5 exhibited the best
out-put factors of 0.93 and 1.04, respectively.</p><p num="0028">For comparative purposes, and in order to show the difficulty in determining the
proper diluents for introduction with the inventive polyester thermoplastic coloring
methods and articles, a number of similar compositions of colorants and diluents were
prepared and utilized within the same extrusion/coloring method outlined above. The
Dispersion (D), Hobart Mixer (HM), and Screw Slippage (SS) tests were performed for
each of these with the following results:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><i>Comparative Colorant/ Diluent Formulations</i></entry></row><row><entry align="center">Colorant (from Table 1 and/or 2) in wt %</entry><entry align="left">Diluent (wt %)</entry><entry align="left">D</entry><entry align="left">HM</entry><entry align="left">SS</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2, 3 and 5 (16.67% each)</entry><entry align="left">sorbitan trioleate (50%)</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="left"><!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center"><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row><row><entry align="left">3 and 13 (21.5% each)</entry><entry align="left">glycerol tristearate (57%)</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="left">poor</entry><entry align="center">0.95</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1 and 13 (21.5% each)</entry><entry align="left">N,N-bis-hydroxyethyl cocoamide</entry><entry align="center">2.3</entry><entry align="left">fair</entry><entry align="center">0.90</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1 and 2 (about 47.5% each)</entry><entry align="left">Tween® 80 (5%)</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="left">poor</entry><entry align="center">1.41<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0029">The characteristics provided by the particular diluent surfactants of this invention
are thus highly unexpected. The two most preferred colorant/diluent formulations provide
the best overall results for Dispersion, Hobart Mixer, and Screw Slippage which was
determined solely through a great deal of analysis of myriad different preparations. The
synergism displayed by the component colorants and surfactants was quite surprising. </p><p num="0030">Having described the invention in detail it is obvious that one skilled in the art will
be able to make variations and modifications thereto without departing from the scope of
the present invention. Accordingly, the scope of the present invention should be
determined only by the claims appended hereto.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for providing coloration to a polyester thermoplastic material during an
extrusion or injection molding procedure comprising the steps of
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) providing an amount of feedstock polyester thermoplastic;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) providing a composition comprising
a polyoxyalkylenated colorant defined by the Formula (I)
 R{A-[(alkyleneoxy constituent)n]m}x
wherein
<claim-text><claim-text>R is an organic chromophore;</claim-text><claim-text>A is a linking moiety in said chromophore selected from the group
consisting of N, O, S, and CO2;</claim-text><claim-text>Alkyleneoxy constituent contains from 2 to 4 carbon atoms;</claim-text><claim-text>n is an integer of from 2 to about 100;</claim-text><claim-text>m is 1 when A is O, S, or CO2, and m is 2 when A is N;</claim-text><claim-text>x is an integer of from 1 to about 5; and</claim-text><claim-text>a diluent selected from the group consisting of sorbitan (C8-C22)
monoesters, ethoxylated sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters, mixtures thereof of sorbitan (C8-C22)
monoesters and ethoxylated sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters, ethoxylated nonyl-phenol
ethers, ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers, mixtures thereof of said ethoxylated nonylphenol
ethers and ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers, and any mixtures thereof of
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters or ethoxylated sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters
and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) ethoxylated nonyl-phenol ethers or ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers;
and
optionally, a colorant substantially free from inorganic salts comprised of an
anionic dye and a quaternary ammonium compound;</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>(c) mixing said feedstock polyester and said colorant composition in a standard
plastic extrusion or injection molding machine thereby coloring said feedstock polyester
with said colorant composition;</claim-text><claim-text>(d) melting said colored feedstock polyester within said standard extrusion or
injection molding machine thereby producing a colored molten polyester;</claim-text><claim-text>(e) extruding or injection molding said colored molten polyester.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method of Claim 1 wherein
   said diluent is present in an amount of from about 25 to about 75%, especially in an
amount of from about 50 to about 57% by weight of the total composition (b).</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method of Claim 1 wherein
   said diluent is a mixture of a sorbitan (C8-C22) monoester and an ethoxylated nonyl-phenol
ether, especially a mixture of sorbitan monooleate and polyoxyethylene (7)
dinonylphenol ether.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method of Claim 1 wherein
   said diluent is an ethoxylated nonyl-phenol ether, especially polyoxyethylene (9.5)
nonyl-phenol ether.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A thermoplastic material comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>a composition comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>a poly(oxyalkylenated) colorant defined by the Formula (I)
R{A-[(alkyleneoxy constituent)n]m}x
wherein
<claim-text><claim-text>R is an organic chromophore;</claim-text><claim-text>A is a linking moiety in said chromophore selected from the group
consisting of N, O, S, and CO2;</claim-text><claim-text>Alkyleneoxy constituent contains from 2 to 4 carbon atoms;</claim-text><claim-text>n is an integer of from 2 to about 100;</claim-text><claim-text>m is 1 when A is O, S, or CO2, and m is 2 when A is N;</claim-text><claim-text>x is an integer of from 1 to about 5; and</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>a diluent selected from the group consisting of sorbitan (C8-C22)
monoesters,</claim-text><claim-text>ethoxylated sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters, mixtures thereof of sorbitan (C8-C22)</claim-text><claim-text>monoesters and ethoxylated sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters, ethoxylated
nonyl-phenol ethers, ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers, mixtures thereof of said
ethoxylated nonylphenol ethers and ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers, and any mixtures
thereof of
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters or ethoxylated sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters
and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) ethoxylated nonyl-phenol ethers or ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The thermoplastic material of Claim 5 wherein
   said diluent is a mixture of a sorbitan (C8-C22) monoester and an ethoxylated nonyl-phenol
ether, especially a mixture of sorbitan monooleate and polyoxyethylene (7) dinonylphenol
ether.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The thermoplastic material of Claim 5 wherein
   said diluent is an ethoxylated nonyl-phenol ether, especially polyoxyethylene (9.5)
nonyl-phenol ether.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A colored polyester thermoplastic material comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>a colorant complex substantially free from unwanted chloride and sulfate
salts comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>an anionic dye and</claim-text><claim-text>a quaternary ammonium compound;</claim-text></claim-text>
and</claim-text><claim-text>a diluent selected from the group consisting of sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters,
ethoxylated sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters, mixtures thereof of sorbitan (C8-C22)
monoesters and ethoxylated sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters, ethoxylated nonyl-phenol ethers,
ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers, mixtures thereof of said ethoxylated nonylphenol ethers
and ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers, and any mixtures thereof of
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters or ethoxylated sorbitan (C8-C22) monoesters
and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) ethoxylated nonyl-phenol ethers or ethoxylated dodecylphenol ethers.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The thermoplastic material of Claim 8 wherein
   said diluent is a mixture of a sorbitan (C8-C22) monoester and an ethoxylated nonyl-phenol
ether, especially a mixture of sorbitan monooleate and polyoxyethylene (7) dinonylphenol
ether.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The thermoplastic material of Claim 8 wherein
   said diluent is an ethoxylated nonyl-phenol ether, especially polyoxyethylene (9.5)
nonyl-phenol ether.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="155" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="238" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="236" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>