<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1489143-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1489143" kind="A1" lang="EN" date="20041222" family-id="33422178" date-produced="20090516" status="new"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference fvid="24245708" ucid="EP-1489143-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1489143</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20041222</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04253696-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04253696</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040621</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2003176272-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2003176272</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030620</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2003176273-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2003176273</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030620</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  67/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  67/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  67/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  67/50        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09B  67/00B5D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09B  67/00C2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09B  67/00M1B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title lang="DE" load-source="ep" status="new">Verfahren zur Herstellung von einem Phthalocyaninpigment des beta-Typs und dessen Verwendung</invention-title><invention-title lang="EN" load-source="ep" status="new">Process for the production of beta type copper phthalocyanine pigment and a use thereof</invention-title><invention-title lang="FR" load-source="ep" status="new">Procédé de production d'un pigment de phtalocyanine de cuivre sous forme béta et l'utilisation de ce pigment</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0392334-A2" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0392334</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA" category="A" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0803545-A2" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0803545</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA" category="Y" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0808878-A2" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0808878</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA" category="A" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="FR-2076889-A5" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>FR</country><doc-number>2076889</doc-number><kind>A5</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA" category="Y" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="FR-2265826-A1" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>FR</country><doc-number>2265826</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA" category="Y" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-7310024-A"  status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>JP</country><doc-number>7310024</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA" category="YD" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5492563-A" status="new"><document-id format="epo"  status="new"><country>US</country><doc-number>5492563</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA"  category="A"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2001066650-A2" status="new"><document-id format="epo" status="new"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2001066650</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source name="SEA" category="A" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 1996, no. 03, 29 March 1996 (1996-03-29) -&amp; JP 07 310024 A (DAINIPPON INK &amp; CHEM INC), 28 November 1995 (1995-11-28)</text><sources><source name="SEA" category="YD" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>TOYO INK MFG CO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>TOYO INK MFG. CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>TOYO INK MFG. CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>3-13, Kyobashi 2-chome, Chuo-ku</street><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>IDE YUSAKU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>KOTANI TAKUYA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>OSHIBA TOSHIO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="epo" status="new"><addressbook><name>SHIROMARU OSAMA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>IDE, YUSAKU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>KOTANI, TAKUYA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>OSHIBA, TOSHIO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="intermediate" status="new"><addressbook><name>SHIROMARU, OSAMA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Ide, Yusaku, c/o Toyo INK MFG. CO., LTD</last-name><address><street>3-13 Kyobashi 2-chome Chuo-ku</street><city>Tokyo 104-0031</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Kotani, Takuya, c/o Toyo INK MFG. CO., LTD</last-name><address><street>3-13 Kyobashi 2-chome Chuo-ku</street><city>Tokyo 104-0031</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Oshiba, Toshio, c/o Toyo INK MFG. CO., LTD</last-name><address><street>3-13 Kyobashi 2-chome Chuo-ku</street><city>Tokyo 104-0031</city><country>JP</country> </address></addressbook></inventor><inventor format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Shiromaru, Osama, c/o Toyo INK MFG. CO., LTD</last-name><address><street>3-13 Kyobashi 2-chome Chuo-ku</street> <city>Tokyo 104-0031</city> <country>JP</country> </address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent format="original" status="new"><addressbook><last-name>Srinivasan, Ravi Chandran</last-name><address><street>J.A. KEMP &amp;amp; CO. 14 South Square Gray's Inn</street><city>LONDON WC1R 5JJ</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract lang="EN" load-source="ep" status="new"><p>A process for the production of a β type copper phthalocyanine pigment,
comprising dry-milling a crude copper phthalocyanine having a purity of 97 to
100 % and a primary crystal diameter of 0.5 to 100 µm at a temperature of 180 to 50
°C, to prepare an α/β mixed crystal type copper phthalocyanine having an α ratio of
5 to 35 %, and treating the dry-milled product with a water-miscible organic solvent,

   wherein 0.1 to 20 % by weight of at least one compound selected from the
group consisting of a compound of the formula (1), a compound of the formula (2)
and a compound of the formula (3) is added to the dry-milled product before, during
or after the step (B).
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">MePc-{X-(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>k</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>}<sub>n</sub></st32:che><img file="80000001.tif" id="img-80000001" he="22" wi="73" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no"/><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">MePc-(SO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>N<sup>+</sup>R<sub>5</sub>R<sub>6</sub>R<sub>7</sub>R<sub>8</sub>)<sub>p</sub></st32:che></p></abstract><description lang="EN" load-source="ep" status="new"><heading>Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a process for the
production of a β type copper phthalocyanine pigment according
to a dry-milling method and a use thereof.</p><heading>Prior Arts of the Invention</heading><p num="0002">Generally, a copper phthalocyanine after synthesis
is called a crude copper phthalocyanine, and it is formed of
large particles having a primary crystal diameter of 0.5 to
100 µm. For this reason, it is impossible to directly use the
above crude copper phthalocyanine as a pigment for a printing
ink. The step of decreasing the size of primary crystals of
the above crude copper phthalocyanine to about 100 ± 50 nm,
which is a size usable as a printing ink, is called pigmentation.
There are a variety of methods for the pigmentation.</p><p num="0003">Most general is a method which is called a solvent
salt milling method. In this method, a milling assistant such
as a common salt and an organic solvent, which promotes the
conversion of crystals to β type, are added to the crude copper
phthalocyanine and the mixture is milled. A β type copper
phthalocyanine pigment obtained according to the above method
has an average primary crystal diameter of 80 ± 40 nm and a
primary crystal aspect ratio of 2.0 ± 0.5, that is, the size
and shape of primary crystals are uniform. The above
characteristics in physical properties advantageously reflect
on its aptitude, so that the β type copper phthalocyanine pigment
is suitable for a printing ink in terms of fluidity and tinting
strength and is thus widely used. However, the above method 
uses a milling assistant in an amount several times as large
as that of the pigment and it uses a high boiling solvent which
is a high environmental loading substance, so that numerous
amounts of time and energy are required for the step of recovering
the milling assistant or the organic solvent. In addition, the
above method has a significant problem in that inorganic salts
as a milling assistant corrode equipment, i.e., the load on
the equipment is high.</p><p num="0004">In contrast, there is known a method in which the crude
copper phthalocyanine is dry-milled and then the dry-milled
phthalocyanine is treated with an organic solvent or the like.
Since the steps of this method are simplified when compared
with those of the above-mentioned solvent salt milling method,
this method is very effective means for providing a low-price
β type copper phthalocyanine pigment.</p><p num="0005">Crystals of a β type copper phthalocyanine converts
into α type crystals, which is thermodynamically unstable, by
means of a mechanical impact force such as that in dry-milling.
It is known that, when a β type crude copper phthalocyanine
is dry-milled at a milling temperature of 80 to 90 °C, generally,
the α ratio in the dry-milled copper phthalocyanine becomes
60 % or more (JP-A-7-310024).</p><p num="0006">On the other hand, when the milling is carried out
by a small impact force, naturally, the ratio of α type crystals
can be controlled to be small. For example, JP-A-2-294365
discloses that, when the milling is carried out at a milling
temperature of 100 °C, the content of α type crystals in the
dry-milled product is 21 %. However, the milling by such a degree
of impact force cannot achieve the size distribution of pigment
particles obtained by the solvent salt milling method.</p><p num="0007">The solvent salt milling method is characterized by
applying a powerful frictional force to a dough composed of 
a crude copper phthalocyanine of huge primary crystals, an
organic solvent and a milling assistant.</p><p num="0008">On the other hand, the method in which the dry-milled
product is treated with an organic solvent or the like is
characterized in that α type crystals are converted into β type
crystals and, simultaneously, a strong aggregation of fine
primary crystals is deflocculated to obtain an intended
dispersed particle diameter. However, it is known that primary
crystals grow into a needle form in the step of converting the
α type crystals in the dry-milled product into β type crystals
and the aspect ratio becomes large when compared with that of
the solvent salt milling method.</p><p num="0009">The method, in which the crude copper phthalocyanine
is dry-milled and then treated with an organic solvent or the
like, is advantageous in that the step of recovering the milling
assistant required in the solvent salt milling method is
unnecessary, and it is also advantageous in view of a powder
treatment amount since the dry-milling is effectively carried
out. On the other hand, the above method has a defect in that
β type crystals are converted into α type crystals at the time
of applying a mechanical force. In addition, when α type crystals
are made to convert into β type crystals by the function of
the organic solvent, pigment primary crystals grow into a needle
form and the aspect ratio becomes larger as compared with that
of the solvent salt milling method. Therefore, there arise a
problem of reddening in hue based on the orientation of dispersed
particles and a problem of a decrease in fluidity based on the
structural viscosity. Further, there is a method in which the
crude copper phthalocyanine is dry-milled in the presence of
a small amount of an organic solvent for preventing the formation
of α type crystals. However, this method has a quality problem
of difficulty in controlling the α ratio based on an 
inhomogeneous treatment and a cost problem of investment in
equipment such as an explosion-proof apparatus suitable for
the solvent treatment.</p><p num="0010">The present inventors have focused attention on that
the α ratio in the above α/β mixed crystal type copper
phthalocyanine obtained by dry-milling exerts an influence upon
the aspect ratio of a pigment as an end product, and found that
the aspect ratio of pigment particles obtained by treatment
with an organic solvent or the like decreases with a decrease
in the α ratio in the milled product.</p><p num="0011">Further, the present inventors have found that the
deflocculation properties of the dry-milled product, which is
a strong aggregate, depend on the α ratio and that when the
α ratio is smaller than 5 %, the deflocculation properties
decrease extremely.</p><p num="0012">As the mechanical impact force or the milling time
increases, the α ratio in the dry-milled product obtained by
dry-milling increases. This phenomenon can be explained as
follows. The bonding of a copper atom, which is a β type
phthalocyanine center metal, to a nitrogen atom at a
meso-position in an adjacent phthalocyanine molecule oriented
in a longitudinal direction by the Jahn-Teller effect, is cut
by mechanical stress, so that the internal energy increases.
As a result thereof, the crystals convert into
thermodynamically-unstable α type crystals. It is thus supposed
that the crystals are again converted from α type into β type
by a function which aims at thermodynamical stabilization, such
as a function of heat or a nonacidic organic solvent, with
releasing an enthalpy of ΔH<sub>β ← α</sub> = -10.8 kJ/mol, i.e., releasing
10.8kJ/mol.</p><p num="0013">In the dry-milling step, it is sufficient, for
increasing the α ratio by decreasing the re-conversion of α 
type crystals into β type crystals, to jointly use a substance
which suppresses a lattice contraction in the c axis direction
of α type crystal. Conversely, it is inferred on the basis of
crystal structure analysis, that it is sufficient for obtaining
a dry-milled product having a low α ratio to use a crude copper
phthalocyanine having a less amount of the substance which
suppresses a lattice contraction in the c axis direction.</p><p num="0014">From the above inference, it is deduced that a
dry-milled product having a low α ratio can be more easily
obtained by dry-milling a high-purity crude copper
phthalocyanine. This point has been verified by an experiment.</p><p num="0015">From the above theoretical backgrounds, so long as
the crude copper phthalocyanine is high-purity, crystals are
not easily converted into α type crystals even when a mechanical
impact force is applied. Therefore, the degree of heating during
the dry-milling can be decreased.</p><p num="0016">The dry-milling conditions for obtaining an α/β mixed
crystal type copper phthalocyanine having an α ratio of 5 to
35 % are clarified as follows. The α/β mixed crystal type copper
phthalocyanine having an α ratio of 5 to 35 % is obtained by
dry-milling a crude copper phthalocyanine having a purity of
97 to 100 % at a dry-milling temperature of 180 to 50 °C, preferably
160 to 80 °C.</p><heading>Summary of the Invention</heading><p num="0017">It is an object of the present invention to maintain
a pigment quality equivalent to a pigment quality obtained by
a solvent salt milling method and, at the same time, overcome
problems that the solvent salt milling method has.</p><p num="0018">According to the present invention, there is provided
a process for the production of a β type copper phthalocyanine
pigment having an average primary crystal diameter of 80 ± 40 
nm and a primary crystal aspect ratio of 2.0 ± 1.0 and having
a crystallite diameter of 22 ± 5 nm in the direction perpendicular
to a monoclinic β (200) plane, a crystallite diameter of 27
± 5 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (001) plane and
a crystallite diameter of 15 ± 5 nm in the direction perpendicular
to a β (010) plane,

   which process comprises the step (A) of dry-milling
a crude copper phthalocyanine having a purity, based on a
sulfuric acid dissolution method, of 97 to 100 % and a primary
crystal diameter of 0.5 to 100 µm at a temperature of 180 to
50 °C, to prepare an α/β mixed crystal type copper phthalocyanine
having an α ratio of 5 to 35 %, and the step (B) of treating
the dry-milled product obtained in the step (A) in an organic
solvent or a mixed liquid of organic solvent and water, to convert
α type crystals into β type crystals, wherein 0.1 to 20 % by
weight of at least one compound selected from the group
consisting of a compound of the formula (1) , a compound of the
formula (2) and a compound of the formula (3) is added to the
dry-milled product before, during or after the step (B),
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">MePc-{X-(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>k</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>}<sub>n</sub></st32:che>
   in which Me represents H<sub>2</sub>, Cu, Fe, Co, Ni, Zn, AlOH
or FeOH, Pc represents a phthalocyanine residue, X represents
CH<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>2</sub>NHCOCH<sub>2</sub>, CO, SO<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>2</sub>NH, CH<sub>2</sub>NHCOCH<sub>2</sub>NH, CONH or SO<sub>2</sub>NH, k
is an integer of 0 to 6, R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> are each independently a hydrogen
atom or an substituted or non-substituted alkyl or alkenyl group
having 1 to 18 carbon atoms or R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> together form a
five-membered or six-membered ring which may further contain
a nitrogen atom, and n is an integer of 1 to 4, <img file="00070001.tif" id="img-00070001" he="32" wi="100" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" orientation="unknown" inline="no"/>
   in which Me and Pc have the same meanings as those
in the formula (1), Y is a halogen atom, an alkyl group, a nitro
group, an amino group, a sulfone group or a carboxylic group,
q is an integer of 1 to 3 and m is an integer of 0 to 4,
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">MePc- (SO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>N<sup>+</sup>R<sub>5</sub>R<sub>6</sub>R<sub>7</sub>R<sub>8</sub>)<sub>p</sub></st32:che>
   in which Me and Pc have the same meanings as those
in the formula (1), R<sub>5</sub>, R<sub>6</sub>, R<sub>7</sub> and R<sub>8</sub> are each independently
a hydrogen atom, a substituted or non-substituted alkyl or
alkenyl group having 1 to 30 carbon atoms or a polyoxy lower
alkyl or alkenyl group, provided that at least one of R<sub>5</sub>, R<sub>6</sub>,
R<sub>7</sub> and R<sub>8</sub> an alkyl or alkenyl group having at least 10 carbon
atoms or a polyoxy lower alkyl or alkenyl group, and p is an
integer of 1 to 8.</p><p num="0019">In the present invention, the compound represented
by the formula (1), the formula (2) or the formula (3) can be
added before, during or after the step (B) , while it is preferred
to add it before or during the step (B). The reason therefor
is because it is assumed that the compound of the formula (1) ,
the formula (2) or the formula (3) contributes to dispersion
stabilization of a copper phthalocyanine pigment dispersion
in an organic solvent and accelerates deflocculation of an
aggregate. A remarkable increase in the fluidity of the
dispersion substantiates the above assumption.</p><p num="0020">According to the present invention, further, there
are provided a printing ink, a coating composition and a colored
resin composition each of which uses the β type copper 
phthalocyanine pigment provided by the process of the present
invention.</p><heading>Detailed Description of the Invention</heading><p num="0021">The present invention will be explained in detail
hereinafter. The dry-milling of the present invention
pulverizes a crude copper phthalocyanine with a milling
apparatus containing milling media, such as beads,
substantially without a liquid substance. The milling is carried
out by utilizing a milling force or destructive force due to
a collision between the millingmedia. The dry-milling apparatus
can be selected from known milling apparatuses such as a dry-type
attritor, a ball mill, a vibrating mill, etc. Further, the
dry-milling may be carried out in a deoxidation atmosphere after
the atmosphere in the dry-milling apparatus is replaced with
the deoxidation atmosphere by supplying a nitrogen gas, etc.,
as required.</p><p num="0022">The dry-milling apparatus can be selected from known
dry-type milling apparatuses heatable with steam, oil or the
like, such as a dry-type attritor, a ball mill, a vibrating
mill, etc. The milling time can be freely set depending upon
the milling apparatus used or depending upon a desired
milled-particle diameter. In a general dry-milling, the inside
of the milling apparatus heats up, so that, in most cases, the
dry-milling is carried out with cooling the temperature down
to 80 to 100 °C. In the present invention, a milled product
having an intended α ratio is obtained by adjusting the inside
temperature to 180 to 50 °C, preferably 160 to 80 °C. When the
temperature exceeds 180 °C, undesirably, an influence is exerted
upon the quality of the pigment.</p><p num="0023">As the crude copper phthalocyanine, there is used a
crude copper phthalocyanine having a purity, based on a sulfuric 
acid dissolution method, of 97 to 100 %. When the above purity
is smaller than 97 %, a milled product having a high α ratio
is obtained.</p><p num="0024">In the present invention, the purity of the crude
copper phthalocyanine based on the sulfuric acid dissolution
method is measured as follows.</p><p num="0025">5 g of a sample is little by little added to 100 g
of 98 % sulfuric acid at room temperature with stirring. After
the completion of the addition, the mixture is stirred for 2
hours, and then it is poured into 500 ml of distilled water
with stirring. The resultant mixture is stirred under heat at
90 °C and, 0.5 hour later, it is dried at 100 °C to a constant
weight. Then, it is filtered under suction with a 17G4 glass
filter, which have been weighed, and washed with water until
the filtrate becomes free from acid. Then, the washed product
remaining on the glass filter is dried at 100 °C to a constant
weight, and then weighed. The purity can be obtained by the
following expression.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Purity/% = weight after treatment × 100 / weight before<st32:break type="required"/>
treatment</st32:df></p><p num="0026">The α ratio of the milled product is 5 to 35 %, preferably
10 to 30 %. A limitation is imposed upon the upper limit of
the α ratio by an increase in the aspect ratio of pigment primary
crystals. Further, a limitation is imposed upon the lower limit
by deflocculation properties of a strong aggregate.</p><p num="0027">The solvent treatment of the milled product obtained
is carried out with an organic solvent alone or a mixture of
the organic solvent with water.</p><p num="0028">The kind of the solvent is a water-miscible organic
solvent. Examples thereof include alcohol compounds such as
isopropanol, butanol, isobutanol, ethyl cellosolve, butyl
cellosolve and cyclohexanol and ketone compounds such as acetone 
or methyl ethyl ketone. These solvents may be used alone or
in combination.</p><p num="0029">In the solvent treatment step, there may be used a
bead mill such as an Eiger mill, a sand mill, a ball mill, a
pearl mill ("DCP mill" supplied by EIRICH, etc.), a cosmo mill,
a Z mill, a dispermat or a basket mill.</p><p num="0030">In the solvent treatment step, there may be used a
medialess disperser such as a wet type jet mill ("GENUS PY"
supplied by Genus, "Nanomizer" supplied by Nanomizer) or a
homomixer.</p><p num="0031">In the present invention, the pigment may be treated
with a resin for giving an aptitude suitable to an application
thereof. This treatment can be carried out during the step (A)
or the step (B). The resin may be added during the dry-milling
or during the solvent treatment. The resin can be freely selected
from resins suitable for a printing ink, a coating composition
or a colored resin, such as rosins typified by polymerized rosin,
hydrogenated rosin or disproportionated rosin, or a
rosin-modified phenol resin.</p><p num="0032">In the present invention, the pigment may be treated
with a surfactant for giving an aptitude suitable to an
application thereof. This treatment can be carried out during
the step (A) or during the step (B). The surfactant can be
freely selected from nonionic surfactants, anionic surfactants
and cationic surfactants so long as it is suitable for a printing
ink, a coating composition or a colored resin.</p><p num="0033">An offset ink, a coating composition and a colored
resin composition are provided by using the copper
phthalocyanine pigment produced by the process of the present
invention. The vehicle therefor is not specially limited and
it may contain an adjuvant or an extender pigment. For example,
the vehicle for the offset ink is composed of a resin, a plant 
oil and a solvent. Examples of the resin include a rosin-modified
phenol resin, a petroleum resin, an alkyd resin and a resin
obtained by modifying any one of these resins with a drying
oil. Examples of the plant oil include linseed oil, tung oil
and soybean oil. Examples of the solvent include n-paraffin,
I-paraffin, aromatic, naphthene, α-olefin and water.</p><p num="0034">For example, the vehicle for the coating composition
is composed of a resin and a solvent. Examples of the resin
include an acrylic resin, an alkyd resin, an epoxy resin,
chlorinated rubber, vinyl chloride, a synthetic resin emulsion,
a silicone resin, a polyurethane resin, a polyester resin, a
melamine resin, a urea resin, a mixture of at least two of these,
or a water-soluble resin or emulsion resin prepared by
solubilizing any one of the above resins in water. Examples
of the solvent include a hydrocarbon, an alcohol, a ketone,
an ether alcohol, an ether, an ester and water.</p><p num="0035">For example, the vehicle for a gravure printing ink
is composed of a resin and a solvent. Examples of the resin
include gum rosin, wood rosin, tall oil rosin, lime rosin, rosin
ester, a maleic resin, a polyamide resin, a vinyl resin,
cellulose nitrate, cellulose acetate, ethyl cellulose,
chlorinated rubber, cyclized rubber, an ethylene-vinylacetate
copolymer resin, a polyurethane resin, a polyester resin, an
alkydresin, anacrylicresin, gilsonite, dammar, shellac, etc.,
a mixture of at least two of these, and a water-soluble resin
or emulsion resin prepared by solubilizing any one of the above
resins or the mixture in water. Examples of the solvent include
a hydrocarbon, an alcohol, a ketone, an ether alcohol, an ether,
an ester and water.</p><p num="0036">A resin for a molding plastic, used for the colored
resin composition, includes polyethylene, polypropylene, an
ethylene/propylene copolymer, an ethylene/acrylic acid 
copolymer, an ethylene/maleic acid copolymer, an
α-olefin/acrylic acid copolymer, an α-olefin/maleic acid
copolymer, an ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer, polyvinyl
chloride, polyvinyl acetate, polyvinyl formal, polybutylal,
polyacrylonitrile, polymethacryl, polystyrene, an
acrylonitrile/butadiene/styrene copolymer, polyethylene
terephthalate, polyurethane, polycarbonate, 6-Nylon,
6,6-Nylon, unsaturated polyester, an epoxy resin, a urea resin,
a melamine resin, a cellulose resin, etc.</p><p num="0037">The printing ink, the coating composition or the
colored resin composition, provided by the present invention,
can be produced by mixing or dispersing the above copper
phthalocyanine pigment or a mixture of the copper phthalocyanine
pigment with a phthalocyanine derivative with/in the
corresponding vehicle with a dispersing apparatus. The
dispersing apparatus includes a dissolver, a high-speed mixer,
a homomixer, a kneader, a flusher, a roll mill, a sand mill,
an attritor and a single-spindle or multi-spindle rotary screw
extruder.</p><heading>Effect of the Invention</heading><p num="0038">The present invention can produce the β type copper
phthalocyanine pigment of which the primary crystal aspect ratio
is small. Further, the above β type copper phthalocyanine pigment
has quality, in terms of tinting strength, gloss, fluidity,
etc., equivalent to the quality of a pigment of the
generally-used solvent salt milling method, but gives less
loading to equipment and environment since salts as a milling
assistant and a high-boiling solvent having a high COD value
are not used.</p><heading>Examples</heading><p num="0039">The present invention will be explained concretely
with reference to Examples and Comparative Examples hereinafter.
Standard pigments used in the Examples were prepared as follows.</p><p num="0040">For a gravure ink or coating composition test
evaluation, a β type copper phthalocyanine pigment was prepared
from a crude copper phthalocyanine by a solvent salt milling
method (a common salt in five times amount), and the β type
copper phthalocyanine pigment and a compound of the formula
(1) were mixed in a weight ratio of 96:4.</p><p num="0041">For an offset printing ink or colored resin test
evaluation, a β type copper phthalocyanine pigment was prepared
from a crude copper phthalocyanine by a solvent salt milling
method (a common salt in five times amount), and the β type
copper phthalocyanine pigment and a compound of the formula
(2) were mixed in a weight ratio of 96:4. The aspect ratio of
pigment particles was about 2.0. The aspect ratio of primary
crystal was calculated from a photograph taken with a
transmission electron microscope.</p><p num="0042">Test methods were as follows. In the tests, a pigment
used was obtained by adding a predetermined pigment derivative
into each pigment of Examples and Comparative Examples as
required.</p><heading>Offset printing ink test</heading><p num="0043">100 parts by weight of a pigment was dispersed in 400
parts by weight of a vehicle for an offset ink comprising a
rosin-modified phenol resin and a solvent with a three roll
and then the vehicle for an offset ink and the solvent were
further added to prepare an offset ink. The offset ink was printed
with a simple printer, to obtain a color sample.</p><heading>Colored resin test</heading><p num="0044">0.8 part by weight of a pigment and 1.2 parts by weight
of a plasticizer were dispersed to obtain a color paste. 0.5 
part by weight of the color paste and 50 parts by weight of
a transparent vinyl chloride compound were mixed with a two
roll adjusted at 155 °C, to obtain a deep color sheet. Further,
0.1 part by weight of the color paste and 50 parts by weight
of an opaque vinyl chloride compound were mixed similarly to
obtain a light color sheet. The deep color sheet and the light
color sheet were pressed under heat to obtain color samples.</p><heading>Coating composition test</heading><p num="0045">6 parts by weight of a pigment and an amino alkyd resin
varnish for a baking coating composition containing 56 parts
by weight of an alkyd resin varnish having a solid content of
60 %, 28 parts by weight of a melamine resin varnish having
a solid content of 50 % and 10 parts by weight of xylene were
dispersed using glass beads as dispersing media, to prepare
a coating composition. As a coating composition for a tinting
strength comparison, 1 part by weight of a pigment and a white
coating composition containing 10 parts by titanium dioxide
were mixed to prepare a light color coating composition. Each
of the coating compositions was applied onto an art paper with
a six-mil applicator and baked at 130 °C for 30 minutes, to
obtain color samples.</p><heading>Gravure test</heading><p num="0046">20 parts by weight of a pigment and a flexo ink varnish
containing 14 parts by weight of cellulose nitrate, 10 parts
by weight of ethyl acetate, 53 parts by weight of ethanol and
3 parts by weight of a plasticizer were dispersed using glass
beads as dispersing media, to obtain a gravure ink. The gravure
ink was applied onto a triacetate film with a bar coater No.3,
to obtain a color sample.</p><p num="0047">The α ratio and the diameter of a crystallite were
obtained from an X-ray diffraction profile. </p><p num="0048">The α ratio was calculatedby the following expression.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">α ratio/% = { (integrated intensity at a diffraction<st32:break type="required"/>
angle of 14.3° - 16.0°) - (integrated intensity at a diffraction<st32:break type="required"/>
angle of 13.8°) } × 100 / {(total of integrated intensities at<st32:break type="required"/>
diffraction angles of 12.2°, 14.3° - 16.0°, and 18.0°) -<st32:break type="required"/>
(integrated intensity at a diffraction angle of 13.8°)}</st32:df></p><p num="0049">The diameter of a crystallite was calculated by the
Scherrer expression from an integral width value based on
diffraction planes of β(001), β(200) and β(010) at diffraction
angles of 7.0°, 10.5° and 18.5°.</p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0050">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 99 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 115 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 15 % of α type crystals. 48 parts
by weight of the milled product was added to 100 parts by weight
of isobutanol and 50 parts by weight of water, and the mixture
was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour. It
was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less by the
above pre-mixing procedure. The confirmation of the α ratio
was carried out using a sample obtained by adding the slurry
after the pre-mixing treatment to an equal amount of methanol,
filtering the resultant mixture with a filter paper No.5C
supplied by TOYO ROSHI KAISHA, LTD., further dashing 3 times
amount of isobutanol over a material remaining on the filter
paper to wash the material, and air-drying the washed material.</p><p num="0051">Then, 200 parts by weight of isobutanol, 100 parts
by weight of water and 2 parts by weight of a phthalimide
methylated copper phthalocyanine (the number of substitutes 
of a phthalimide methyl group was 1/mol) were further added,
and the resultant mixture was circulatively dispersed with an
Eiger mill having a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal
beads at 50 °C for 1 hour. Then, 200 parts by weight of water
was added, and the resultant mixture was distilled and then
spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles
of the pigment was 2.2, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The
crystallite diameter was 22 nm in the direction perpendicular
to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it was 30 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (001) plane and it was 16 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (010) plane. The pigment was compared with
a standard pigment using the above crude copper phthalocyanine
as a raw material. An offset printing ink of the pigment of
the present Example had a quality at least equivalent to the
quality of an offset printing ink of the standard pigment in
terms of tinting strength, fluidity, etc., and the hue thereof
was greenish. Further, a colored resin of the pigment of the
present Example had a quality at least equivalent to the quality
of a colored resin of the standard pigment in terms of color
development, tinting strength, etc.</p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0052">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 97 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 90 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a milled
product containing 27 % of α type crystals. 48 parts by weight
of the milled product was added to 150 parts by weight of
isobutanol, 50 parts by weight of water and 0.7 part by weight
of PELEX OT-P (anionic surfactant supplied by KAO Corporation)
and the mixture was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C 
for 1.5 hours. It was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to
1 % or less. Then, 225 parts by weight of isobutanol, 75 parts
by weight of water and 2 parts by weight of a phthalimide
methylated copper phthalocyanine (the number of substitutes
of a phthalimide methyl group was 1/mol) were further added,
and the resultant mixture was circulatively dispersed with an
Eiger mill having a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal
beads at 60 °C for 1 hour. Then, 260 parts by weight of water
was added, and the resultant mixture was distilled and then
spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles
of the pigment was 2.6, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The
crystallite diameter was 20 nm in the direction perpendicular
to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it was 25 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (001) plane and it was 18 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (010) plane. The pigment was compared with
a standard pigment using the above crude copper phthalocyanine
as a raw material. An offset printing ink of the pigment of
the present Example had a quality at least equivalent to the
quality of an offset printing ink of the standard pigment in
terms of tinting strength, fluidity, etc., and the hue thereof
was greenish. Further, a colored resin of the pigment of the
present Example had a quality at least equivalent to the quality
of a colored resin of the standard pigment in terms of color
development, tinting strength, etc.</p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="0053">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 98 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 140 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 8 % of α type crystals. 48 parts by 
weight of the milled product was added to 75 parts by weight
of isobutanol, 175 parts by weight of water and 0.5 part by
weight of ESTER GUMAT (rosin ester type resin supplied by Arakawa
Chemical Industries, Ltd.), and the mixture was stirred with
a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour. It was confirmed that
the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less. Then, 175 parts by weight
of isobutanol, 75 parts by weight of water and 2 parts by weight
of CuPc-CH<sub>2</sub>NHCOCH<sub>2</sub>NH(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub> were further added, and the
resultant mixture was circulatively dispersed with an Eiger
mill having a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal beads
at 60 °C for 1.5 hours. Then, 75 parts by weight of water was
added and the resultant mixture was distilled and then
spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles
of the pigment was 2.1, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The
crystallite diameter was 23 nm in the direction perpendicular
to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it was 24 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (001) plane and it was 16 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (010) plane. The pigment was compared with
a standard pigment using the above crude copper phthalocyanine
as a raw material. A coating composition of the pigment of the
present Example had a quality at least equivalent to the quality
of a coating composition of the standard pigment in terms of
tinting strength, fluidity, etc.</p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0054">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 99 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 115 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 15 % of α type crystals. 48 parts
by weight of the milled product was added to 75 parts by weight 
of ethyl cellosolve and 75 parts by weight of water, and the
mixture was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour.
It was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less.
Then, 150 parts by weight of ethyl cellosolve, 150 parts by
weight of water and 2 parts by weight of CuPc-SO<sub>2</sub>NH (CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub>
were further added, and the resultant mixture was circulatively
dispersed with an Eiger mill having a mill volume of 200 ml
using 0.8 mm  steal beads at 50 °C for 1 hour. Then, 70 parts
by weight of water was added and the resultant mixture was
distilled and then spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The aspect
ratio of particles of the pigment was 2.3, and the α ratio was
1 % or less. The crystallite diameter was 23 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it was 26 nm in
the direction perpendicular to a β (001) plane and it was 14
nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (010) plane. The pigment
was compared with a standard pigment using the above crude copper
phthalocyanine as a raw material. A gravure ink of the pigment
of the present Example had a quality at least equivalent to
the quality of a gravure ink of the standard pigment in terms
of tinting strength, gloss, fluidity, etc.</p><heading>Comparative Example 1</heading><p num="0055">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 93%, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 130 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 45 % of α type crystals. 48 parts
by weight of the milled product was added to 100 parts by weight
of isobutanol and 50 parts by weight of water, and the mixture
was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 2 hours. It
was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less. Then, 
200 parts by weight of isobutanol, 100 parts by weight of water
and 2 parts by weight of a phthalimide methylated copper
phthalocyanine (the number of substitutes of a phthalimide
methyl group was 1/mol) were further added, and the resultant
mixture was circulatively dispersed with an Eiger mill having
a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal beads at 50 °C
for 1 hour. Then, 200 parts by weight of water was added and
the resultant mixture was distilled and then spray-dried, to
obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles of the pigment
was 4.0, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The crystallite diameter
was 21 nm in the direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200)
plane, it was 26 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (001)
plane and it was 16 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β
(010) plane. The pigment was compared with the standard pigment
prepared in Example 1. An offset printing ink of the pigment
of the present Comparative Example was poor in terms of tinting
strength, fluidity, etc., when compared with an offset printing
ink of the standard pigment of the solvent salt milling method.</p><heading>Comparative Example 2</heading><p num="0056">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 98 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled in the presence of 15 parts by weight
of xylene at 120 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a milled product
containing 3 % of α type crystals. 48 parts by weight of the
milled product was added to 75 parts by weight of isobutanol
and 175 parts by weight of water, and the mixture was stirred
with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour. It was confirmed
that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less. Then, 175 parts by
weight of isobutanol, 75 parts by weight of water and 2 parts 
by weight of CuPc-SO<sub>2</sub>NH(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>3</sub>N(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub> were further added, and
the resultant mixture was circulatively dispersed with an Eiger
mill having a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal beads
at 60 °C for 1.5 hours. Then, 75 parts by weight of water was
added and the resultant mixture was distilled and then
spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles
of the pigment was 2.0, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The
crystallite diameter was 20 nm in the direction perpendicular
to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it was 27 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (001) plane and it was 14 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (010) plane. The pigment was compared with
the standard pigment prepared in Example 4. A gravure ink of
the pigment of the present Comparative Example was poor in terms
of tinting strength, fluidity, etc. , when comparedwith a gravure
ink of the standard pigment of the solvent salt milling method.</p><heading>Comparative Example 3</heading><p num="0057">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 99 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 115 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 15 % of α type crystals. 50 parts
by weight of the milled product was added to 100 parts by weight
of isobutanol and 50 parts by weight of water, and the mixture
was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour. It
was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less by the
above pre-mixing procedure. Then, 200 parts by weight of
isobutanol and 100 parts by weight of water were further added,
and the resultant mixture was circulatively dispersed with an
Eiger mill having a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal
beads at 50 °C for 1 hour. Then, 200 parts by weight of water 
was added, and the resultant mixture was distilled and then
spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles
of the pigment was 2.3, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The
crystallite diameter was 23 nm in the direction perpendicular
to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it was 26 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (001) plane and it was 15 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (010) plane. The pigment was compared with
a pigment (1) prepared by adding a phthalimide methylated copper
phthalocyanine into the above pigment in the same weight ratio
as that of a standard pigment. An offset printing ink of the
pigment of the present Comparative Example was poor in terms
of tinting strength, gloss, fluidity, etc., when compared with
an offset printing ink of the pigment (1).</p><p num="0058">Standard pigments used in Examples 5 to 8 were prepared
as follows. A β type copper phthalocyanine pigment was prepared
from a crude copper phthalocyanine by a solvent salt milling
method (a common salt in five times amount), and the β type
copper phthalocyanine pigment and a compound of the formula
(3) were mixed in a weight ratio of 92:8. The aspect ratio of
pigment particles was about 2.0. The aspect ratio of primary
crystal was calculated from a photograph taken with a
transmission electron microscope.</p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="0059">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 99 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 115 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 15 % of α type crystals. 46 parts
by weight of the milled product was added to 100 parts by weight 
of isobutanol and 50 parts by weight of water, and the mixture
was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour. It
was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less by the
above pre-mixing procedure. The confirmation of the α ratio
was carried out using a sample obtained by adding the slurry
after the pre-mixing treatment to an equal amount of methanol,
filtering the resultant mixture with a filter paper No.5C
supplied by TOYO ROSHI KAISHA, LTD., further dashing 3 times
amount of isobutanol over a material remaining on the filter
paper to wash the material, and air-drying the washed material.</p><p num="0060">Then, 200 parts by weight of isobutanol, 100 parts
by weight of water and 4 parts by weight of CuPc-SO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>N<sup>+</sup>H<sub>3</sub>(C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>25</sub>)
were further added, and the resultant mixture was circulatively
dispersed with an Eiger mill having a mill volume of 200 ml
using 0.8 mm  steal beads at 50 °C for 1 hour. Then, 200 parts
by weight of water was added, and the resultant mixture was
distilled and then spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The aspect
ratio of particles of the pigment was 2.3, and the α ratio was
1 % or less. The crystallite diameter was 22 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it was 29 nm in
the direction perpendicular to a β (001) plane and it was 16
nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (010) plane. The pigment
was compared with a standard pigment using the above crude copper
phthalocyanine as a raw material. A gravure ink of the pigment
of the present Example had a quality at least equivalent to
the quality of a gravure ink of the standard pigment in terms
of tinting strength, gloss, fluidity, etc., and the hue thereof
was greenish.</p><heading>Example 6</heading><p num="0061">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 97 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution 
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 90 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a milled
product containing 27 % of α type crystals. 46 parts by weight
of the milled product was added to 150 parts by weight of
isobutanol, 50 parts by weight of water and 0.7 part by weight
of PELEX OT-P (anionic surfactant supplied,by KAO Corporation)
and the mixture was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C
for 1.5 hours. It was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to
1 % or less. Then, 225 parts by weight of isobutanol, 75 parts
by weight of water and 4 parts by weight of
CuPc-SO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>N<sup>+</sup>(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>(C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>25</sub>) were further added, and the resultant
mixture was circulatively dispersed with an Eiger mill having
a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal beads at 60 °C
for 1 hour. Then, 260 parts by weight of water was added, and
the resultant mixture was distilled and then spray-dried, to
obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles of the pigment
was 2.7, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The crystallite diameter
was 21 nm in the direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200)
plane, it was 27 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (001)
plane and it was 14 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β
(010) plane. The pigment was compared with a standard pigment
using the above crude copper phthalocyanine as a raw material
and the above phthalocyanine derivative. A gravure ink of the
pigment of the present Example had a quality at least equivalent
to the quality of a gravure ink of the standard pigment in terms
of tinting strength, gloss, fluidity, etc., and the hue thereof
was greenish.</p><heading>Example 7</heading><p num="0062">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 98 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution 
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 140 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 8 % of α type crystals. 46 parts by
weight of the milled product was added to 75 parts by weight
of isobutanol, 175 parts by weight of water and 0.5 part by
weight of ESTERGUMAT (rosin ester type resin suppliedbyArakawa
Chemical Industries, Ltd.), and the mixture was stirred with
a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour. It was confirmed that
the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less. Then, 175 parts by weight
of isobutanol, 75 parts by weight of water and 4 parts by weight
of CuPc-SO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>N<sup>+</sup>H<sub>2</sub>(C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>37</sub>)<sub>2</sub> were further added, and the resultant
mixture was circulatively dispersed with an Eiger mill having
a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal beads at 60 °C
for 1.5 hours. Then, 75 parts by weight of water was added and
the resultant mixture was distilled and then spray-dried, to
obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles of the pigment
was 2.1, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The crystallite diameter
was 23 nm in the direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200)
plane, it was 26 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (001)
plane and it was 15 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β
(010) plane. The pigment was compared with a standard pigment
using the above crude copper phthalocyanine as a raw material
and the above phthalocyanine derivative. A gravure ink of the
pigment of the present Example had a quality at least equivalent
to the quality of a gravure ink of the standard pigment in terms
of tinting strength, gloss, fluidity, etc., and the hue thereof
was greenish.</p><heading>Example 8</heading><p num="0063">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 99 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution 
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 115 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 15 % of α type crystals. 46 parts
by weight of the milled product was added to 75 parts by weight
of ethyl cellosolve and 75 parts by weight of water, and the
mixture was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour.
It was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less.
Then, 150 parts by weight of ethyl cellosolve, 150 parts by
weight of water and 4 parts by weight of
CuPc-SO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>N<sup>+</sup>(CH<sub>3</sub>) (C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub>{[CH<sub>2</sub>CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)O]<sub>11</sub>H} were further added, and
the resultant mixture was circulatively dispersed with an Eiger
mill having a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal beads
at 50 °C for 1 hour. Then, 70 parts by weight of water was added
and the resultant mixture was distilled and then spray-dried,
to obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles of the pigment
was 2.3, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The crystallite diameter
was 22 nm in the direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200)
plane, it was 27 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (001)
plane and it was 18 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β
(010) plane. The pigment was compared with a standard pigment
using the above crude copper phthalocyanine as a raw material
and the above phthalocyanine derivative. A gravure ink of the
pigment of the present Example had a quality at least equivalent
to the quality of a gravure ink of the standard pigment in terms
of tinting strength, gloss, fluidity, etc., and the hue thereof
was greenish.</p><heading>Comparative Example 4</heading><p num="0064">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 93%, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged 
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 130 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 45 % of α type crystals. 46 parts
by weight of the milled product was added to 100 parts by weight
of isobutanol and 50 parts by weight of water, and the mixture
was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 2 hours. It
was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less. Then,
200 parts by weight of isobutanol, 100 parts by weight of water
and 4 parts by weight of CuPc-SO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>N<sup>+</sup>H<sub>3</sub>(C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>23</sub>) were further added,
and the resultant mixture was circulatively dispersed with an
Eiger mill having a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal
beads at 50 °C for 1 hour. Then, 200 parts by weight of water
was added and the resultant mixture was distilled and then
spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles
of the pigment was 4.0, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The
crystallite diameter was 23 nm in the direction perpendicular
to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it was 29 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (001) plane and it was 14 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (010) plane. The pigment was compared with
the standard pigment used in Example 5. A gravure ink of the
pigment of the present Comparative Example was poor in terms
of tinting strength, clarity, fluidity, etc., when compared
with a gravure ink of the standard pigment of the solvent salt
milling method.</p><heading>Comparative Example 5</heading><p num="0065">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 98 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled in the presence of 15 parts by weight
of xylene at 120 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a milled product 
containing 3 % of α type crystals. 46 parts by weight of the milled product was
added to 75 parts by weight of isobutanol and 175 parts by weight of water, and the
mixture was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour. It was confirmed
that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less. Then, 175 parts by weight of isobutanol, 75
parts by weight of water and 4 parts by weight of CuPc-SO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>N<sup>+</sup>H<sub>3</sub>(C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>37</sub>) were
further added, and the resultant mixture was circulatively dispersed with an Eiger
mill having a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal beads at 60 °C for 1.5
hours. Then, 75 parts by weight of water was added and the resultant mixture was
distilled and then spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles of the
pigment was 2.0, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The crystallite diameter was 20 nm
in the direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it was 25 nm in the
direction perpendicular to a β (001) plane and it was 16 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (010) plane. The pigment was compared with a standard
pigment using the above crude copper phthalocyanine as a raw material and the
above phthalocyanine derivative. A gravure ink of the pigment of the present
Comparative Example was poor in terms of tinting strength, clarity, gloss, etc., when
compared with a gravure ink of the standard pigment of the solvent salt milling
method.</p><p num="0066">Typically in the β-type pigment prepared by the process of the present
invention, substantially all of the primary pigment particles have the average primary
crystal diameter, primary crystal aspect ratio and crystallite diameters set out above.</p><p num="0067">Typically, said substituents on said substituted alkyl and alkenyl R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub>
groups in the formula (1) are selected from C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> alkyl and C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> alkenyl groups.</p><p num="0068">When R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub>, together with the N atom to which they are attached, form a
5 or 6 membered ring, said ring is aromatic or non-aromatic. Preferably, it is
non-aromatic. Said non-aromatic rings are saturated or unsaturated. Preferably, the
ring is saturated. In addition to the N atom to which R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> are attached, the 5-or
6- membered ring typically contains 0, 1 or 2 further heteroatoms selected from N,
O and S. Preferably, it contains 0 or 1 further heteroatoms which are N atoms.</p><p num="0069">Typically said substituents on the 5- or 6- membered ring are selected from
C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> alkyl and C<sub>2-4</sub> alkenyl groups.</p><p num="0070">Most preferably, said 5- or 6- membered ring is a piperidine, piperazine or</p></description><claims lang="EN" load-source="ep" status="new"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process for the production of a β type copper phthalocyanine pigment
having an average primary crystal diameter of 80 ± 40 nm and a primary crystal
aspect ratio of 2.0 ± 1.0 and having a crystallite diameter of 22 ± 5 nm in the
direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200) plane, a crystallite diameter of 27 ± 5
nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (001) plane and a crystallite diameter of 15 ±
5 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (010) plane,
   which process comprises,
<claim-text><claim-text>(A) dry-milling a crude copper phthalocyanine having a purity, based on a
sulfuric acid dissolution method, of 97 to 100 % and a primary crystal diameter of
0.5 to 100 µm at a temperature of 180 to 50 °C, to prepare an α/β mixed crystal type
copper phthalocyanine having an α ratio of 5 to 35 %, and</claim-text><claim-text>(B) treating the dry milled product with a water-miscible organic solvent,
wherein 0.1 to 20 % by weight of at least one compound of the formulae (1),
(2) or (3) is added to the dry-milled product before, during or after the step (B),
MePc-{X-(CH2)kNR1R2}n
   wherein Me represents H2, Cu, Fe, Co, Ni, Zn, AIOH or FeOH, Pc represents
a phthalocyanine residue, X represents CH2, CH2NHCOCH2, CO, SO2, CH2NH,
CH2NHCOCH2NH, CONH or SO2NH, k is an integer of 0 to 6, R1 and R2 are the
same or different and each represent a hydrogen atom or an substituted or
non-substituted alkyl or alkenyl group having 1 to 18 carbon atoms or R1 and R2,
together with the N atom to which they are attached, form a substituted or
unsubstituted five-membered or six-membered ring, and n is an integer of 1 to 4,
</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein Me and Pc are as defined in the formula (1), Y is a halogen atom, an
alkyl group, a nitro group, an amino group, a sulfone group or a carboxylic group, n
is an integer of 1 to 4 and m is an integer of 0 to 4,
MePc-(SO3-N+R5R6R7R8)p
   wherein Me and Pc are as defined in the formula (1), R5, R6, R7 and R8 are the
same or different and each represent a hydrogen atom, a substituted or
non-substituted alkyl or alkenyl group having 1 to 30 carbon atoms or a polyoxy
C1-C12 alkyl or C2-C12 alkenyl group, provided that at least one of R5, R6, R7 and R8
is an alkyl or alkenyl group having at least 10 carbon atoms or a polyoxy C1-C12
alkyl or C2-C12 alkenyl group, and p is an integer of 1 to 8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A process according to claim 1, wherein the water-miscible organic solvent is
a liquid mixed with water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A process according to claim 1 or 2, wherein step (B) is carried out by using a
bead mill.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A process according to any one of the preceding claims, wherein, in the
formula (I), k is from 1 to 6 when X is -CH2-NH-, -CH2NHCOCH2-NH-, -CO-NH-
or -SO2-NH-.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A process according to any one of the preceding claims, wherein, when Y in
the formula (2) is an alkyl group it is a C1-C4 alkyl group.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A printing ink comprising a β type copper phthalocyanine pigment produced
by a process according to any one of claims 1 to 5 and a vehicle for the printing ink.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A coating composition comprising a β type copper phthalocyanine pigment
produced by a process according to any one of claims 1 to 5, and a vehicle for the
coating composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A process for preparing a printing ink or a coating composition, which process
comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) preparing a phthalocyanine pigment by a process according to any one
of claims 1 to 5; and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) dispersing the thus obtained pigment in a vehicle.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A colored resin composition comprising a β type copper phthalocyanine
pigment produced by a process according to any one of claims 1 to 5, and a resin for
a molding plastic.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A process for preparing a colored resin composition, which process
comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) preparing a phthalocyanine pigment by a process according to any one
of claims 1 to 5; and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) dispersing the thus obtained pigment in a resin.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>