<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1013606-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1013606" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22815263" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000628"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1013606-A1" status="new" fvid="22858222"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1013606</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000628</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99125502-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99125502</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991221</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-21847498-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>21847498</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981222</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  29/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  29/86        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B  39/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B  39/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  29/86</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C01B  39/02P</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verbesserung von boroaluminosilikatverwandten Zeolitstrukturen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Enhancing boro-aluminosilicate zeolite structures</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Amélioration des structures zéolithiques de type boro-aluminosilicate</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0169026-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0169026</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0494535-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0494535</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="FR-2755958-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>FR</country><doc-number>2755958</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4767886-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4767886</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>EXXON RESEARCH ENGINEERING CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>EXXONMOBIL RESEARCH AND ENGINEERING COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>EXXON RESEARCH AND ENGINEERING COMPANY</last-name><address><street>P.O.Box 390, 180 Park Avenue</street><city>Florham Park, New Jersey 07932-0390</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>STROHMAIER KARL GOTTLIEB</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>VAUGHAN DAVID EVAN WILLIAM</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>STROHMAIER, KARL GOTTLIEB</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VAUGHAN, DAVID EVAN WILLIAM</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>STROHMAIER, KARL GOTTLIEB</last-name><address><street>47 Rockport Road</street><city>Port Murray, New Jersey 07865</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VAUGHAN, DAVID EVAN WILLIAM</last-name><address><street>1109 Croton Road</street><city>Flemington, New Jersey 08822</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Somers, Harold Arnold</last-name><address><street>ESSO Engineering (Europe) Ltd., Patents &amp;amp; Licences, Mailpoint 70, Esso House, Ermyn Way</street><city>Leatherhead, Surrey KT22 8XE</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent> </agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country> <country>CY</country> <country>DE</country> <country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A process for selectively removing detrital material from boro-aluminosilicates
selected from EUO, NES, and intergrown mixtures of EUO and
NES, boro-aluminosilicate topology zeolites having a Si/M ratio of greater than
about 40; the process comprising treating said boro-aluminosilicate with a base
for a time and at a temperature sufficient to remove detrital material, the
concentration of the base preferably being less than 0.5 normal.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to enhancing properties of boro-aluminosilicate
zeolite structures having EUO and NES topology; and further
relates to use thereof in wax isomerization.</p><p num="0002">It is known that EU-1 is a high activity aluminosilicate zeolite
catalyst (U.S. Patent 4,537,754) having 10-ring pores and high internal volume.
It is useful as a catalyst and sorbent and shows interesting shape selectivity (U.S.
Patent 4,537,754; Sovererijns et al, Microporous Materials, 4, page 123 (1995)).
Its compositional variations include the replacement of Al by Ga, Fe or B. As
the acidity of these different metal (M) forms decreases in the order Al, Ga, Fe,
B, reactions requiring the lowest acidity, such as paraffin isomerization, are
probably best carried out with the borosilicate form or those materials having
high Si/M ratios (i.e., lower number of acid sites). Unfortunately, when made at
the higher silica ratios (those greater than about 40) some EU-1 materials have
poor sorption capacity after removal of the templates normally used in its
synthesis) resulting in poor accessibility of reactants and low catalytic reactivity.
This may be caused by partial framework collapse (reflected in deteriorating
X-ray diffraction evidence) or trapped detrital material blocking the pores
(indicated by stable X-ray diffraction profiles but inferior n-hexane sorption
capacities). Evidence seems to point to the latter cause in these subject materials
and may be inherent to the high silica synthesis process, which requires excess
silica in the mother liquor, resulting in entrainment, primarily, of siliceous
species within the zeolite structure. In constrained pore systems such as EU-1, a 
small amount of detritus may readily block major parts of the accessible
structure. Whilst it is well known that post acid treatments or chemical
treatments with complexing agents may restore structural accessibility in some
zeolites, including EU-1, in this case, such treatments would tend to remove the
framework boron, or other M entities, responsible for the desired selective
catalytic activity.</p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0003">The instant invention is directed to a process for selectively
removing detrital material from boro-aluminosilicate selected from EUO, NES
and intergrown mixtures of EUO and NES boro-aluminosilicate topology
zeolites having a Si/M ratio of greater than about 40, comprising treating said
boro-aluminosilicate with a base for a time and at a temperature sufficient to
remove said detrital material from said boro-aluminosilicate wherein the
concentration of said base is less than about 0.5 normal. Base concentrations in
excess of this level may cause the removal of framework components leading to
subsequent structural degradation.</p><p num="0004">The invention is likewise especially directed to a boro-aluminosilicate
EU-1 having improved wax isomerization properties, said boro-aluminosilicate
prepared by treating a boro-aluminosilicate EU-1 containing
detrital material with a base for a time and at a temperature sufficient to remove
said detrital material from said boro-aluminosilicate EU-1. </p><heading><u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE FIGURES</u></heading><p num="0005"><sl><li>Figure 1 shows the conversion or selectivity of examples 1 and 3.
Example 1 is labeled A and Example 3 is labeled B. In the Figure, C, D, and E
represent conversion, constraint, and cracking, respectively.</li><li>Figure 2 depicts the n-hexane adsorption isotherm measured at room
temperature. The % weight uptake is plotted against pressure (torr) for boro-aluminosilicate
EU-1 (triangles), .1 N NaOH treated boro-aluminosilicate EU-1
(circles), and 0.2 N NaOH treated boro-aluminosilicate EU-1 (squares).</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0006">Applicants have discovered that mild base treatment of a boro-aluminosilicate
EU-1, frees the pores of detrital material blockages, enhances the
properties, and does not destroy the structure. The so treated boro-aluminosilicate
EU-1 has enhanced wax isomerization activity. Such activity is
improved by a factor of at least two, and preferably at least 4. Selectivity is
concomitantly improved, producing a desirable wax isomerization catalyst when
compared to other framework substituted EU-1 materials.</p><p num="0007">Although boro-aluminosilicate EU-1 has a desirable selective acidity
for wax isomerization, the activity is such that its use in wax isomerization
processes is not practical in the as synthesized form, in the required Si/M range
of greater than about 40, to yield desirable catalysts for the subject process. The
instant treatment method affords boro-aluminosilicate EU-1 having a Si/M of
greater than about 40 with an activity and selectivity suitable for wax isomerization
processes. </p><p num="0008">Applicants believe that the mild base treatment of the instant
invention removes detrital material, such as silica, from the boro-aluminosilicate
EU-1 channels without destroying the structure of the boro-aluminosilicate
EU-1.</p><p num="0009">The bases utilizable in the instant invention are any bases of
Groups I and IIA of the Periodic Table. For example, NaOH, KOH, Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>,
Sr(OH)<sub>2</sub>, LiOH, RbOH, CsOH, etc. Other bases are also utilizable and are
easily selected by the skilled artisan. The base utilized will have a concentration
of less than about 0.5 normal, preferably from about 0.1 to about 0.5 normal, and
most preferably from about 0.1 to about 0.4 N.</p><p num="0010">The time and temperature for the base treatment are those under
which the detrital material is removed. Typically, temperatures of about room
temperature for several hours (e.g., overnight) up to reflux (∼ 100°C) for less
than one hour are utilized. Whilst it is recognized that lower temperatures and
longer times, or higher temperatures (and therefore pressures over one
atmosphere) and shorter times, are also functional, the increased cost of such
temperature reactions make them economically undesirable. Similarly, although
solvents other than water for the bases (particularly polar organic solvents) are
acceptable (e.g., alcohols, ketones, ethers, etc.), their cost, safety, pollution and
process concerns render them less desirable. Higher temperature treatments also
require more control to prevent structural destruction in the zeolite.</p><p num="0011">Though the instant invention is primarily directed to EU-1 boro-aluminosilicates,
since NU-85, NU-86, and NU-87 are related structures
topologically or by intergrowths (i.e., structure types EUO, NES and
intergrowths and mixtures of the two, as described in 4th Edn. of the "Atlas of
zeolite structure types", Ed. Meier, Olson and Baerlocher, Elsevier (1996)), the 
instant process should be equally applicable to them. Such structures are well
documented in the literature. See for example, NU-85 (Euro. Patent Application
0462 745), NU-86 (U.S. Patent 5,108,579), NU-87 (U.S. Patent 5,102,641;
Shanon et al, Nature, v. 353, p. 417 (1991)), and ZSM-50 (U.S. Patent
4,640,829; Moini et at Zeolites, v. 14, p. 504 (1994) herein incorporated by
reference). Boro-gallosilicate analogs are similarly acceptable. Preferably, the
NU-87 zeolite will be used.</p><p num="0012">Typical preferred treatment times range from about 5 minutes to
about 4 hours.</p><p num="0013">The zeolites treated in accordance with the instant invention can be
utilized in a catalytic isomerization process conducted under catalytic
isomerization conditions. Typical conditions include those well known to the
skilled artisan. For example, the process is carried out in the presence of
hydrogen at temperatures of about 200 to 450°C and pressures ranging from
atmospheric to about 3000 pounds.</p><p num="0014">The following examples are illustrative and are not meant to be
limiting in any way.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0015">A sample of B-EU-1 obtained from the IFP company was evaluated.
The chemical analysis of this is shown in Table 1. 7B-MASNMR of this
material showed a single peak at 4.7 ppm indicative of tetrahedra framework
boron. This sample was measured for n-hexane sorption capacity and catalytic
activity (Figure 1) using methylcyclohexane as a model compound. Samples
were made into catalysts by impregnating with 0.5 wt% Pt from Pt(NH<sub>3</sub>)4Cl<sub>2</sub> 
solutions, calcined, pilled then crushed to 10/20 mesh granules before testing in
a standard acidity test using methylcyclohexane (MCH) as a model feed
(H<sub>2</sub>/feed=5/ MCH=20 ml/hr/200 psig H<sub>2</sub>). This test has proved to be useful in
selecting desirable zeolite wax isomerization catalysts. A desirable catalyst has
a high isomerization selectivity to ethylcyclopentane (ECP) with low cracking
activity. The data shown in Figure 1 (obtained at 320°C) shows good selectivity
but very poor activity. Surprisingly, the sorption capacity was negligible
compared to similar, but less desirable from a catalytic viewpoint, gallo- and
ferri-aluminosilicate analogs of the original base aluminosilicate EU-1. The
good crystallinity but poor sorption capacity indicated structural blockage.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0016">A 1 gram sample of the EU-1 described in Example 1 was reacted
with 20 ml of a 0.1N NaOH solution at 60°C for one hour. After filtering,
washing and drying the sample was evaluated by X-ray diffraction, activated
under vacuum on a Cahn sorption balance, then cooled to room temperature and
an n-hexane sorption isotherm measured. The X-ray structure is unchanged by
the base treatment, but shows improved sorption capacity compared to the base
material (Figure 2).</p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><p num="0017">The process of Example 2 was repeated except that the base
concentration was increased to 0.2 N NaOH. The X-ray structure was
unchanged by the treatment and a major improvement in sorption capacity
(Figure 2) was observed. A larger sample was given a repeated treatment then
exchanged with 10% wt. ammonium chloride solution (4 gm/40 ml/50°C/1 hr)
and was analyzed for constituent elements by ICPAES (Table 1), showing that 
silica was removed. This material was converted to a catalyst by impregnation
with 0.5% wt. Pt (as Pt(NH)<sub>4</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>) and reacted under the conditions described in
Example 1, the activity of B-EU-1 improves by a factor of four and selectivity is
improved. Chemical analysis of this sample (Table 1) showed silica depletion,
indicative of detrital silica removal.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 4</u></heading><p num="0018">The process of Example 2 was repeated except that the base
concentration was increased to 0.5N NaOH. The X-ray diffraction indicated that
the structure suffered major degradation by the treatment confirmed by a
decrease in sorption capacity compared to Example 3.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 5</u></heading><p num="0019">A sample of aluminosilicate EU-1, having an Si/Al ratio of 194, was
evaluated on a Cahn sorption balance with n-hexane, giving a sorption capacity
of 0.63 wt% (22°C/51 torr). After the base treatment described in Example 3,
the n-hexane sorption capacity increased to 4.2 wt%, again indicative of detrital
material removal from the pore space.</p><p num="0020">The Examples show that a mild base treatment is sufficient to clean
up the blocked EU-1 structure to improve catalytic activity by the removal of
detrital material, primarily silica, from the channels of the zeolite without
significant removal of B (or Al) from the framework so retaining catalytic
activity and selectivity. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">CHEMICAL ANALYSIS OF B-EU-1 SAMPLES</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sample</entry><entry align="center">% B</entry><entry align="center">% Al</entry><entry align="center">% Si</entry><entry align="center">% Na</entry><entry align="center">B:Al:Si Atomic Ratio</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 1</entry><entry align="center">0.12</entry><entry align="center">0.12</entry><entry align="center">44.0</entry><entry align="center">0.06</entry><entry align="center">1:0.40:141</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 3</entry><entry align="center">0.11</entry><entry align="center">0.19</entry><entry align="center">43.0</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">1:0.68:150</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process for selectively removing detrital material from a boro-aluminosilicate
selected from EUO and NES topology boro-aluminosilicate
zeolites and intergrown mixtures of the two, having a Si/M ratio greater than
about 40; the process comprising treating the boro-aluminosilicate with a base
for a time and at a temperature sufficient to remove detrital material from said
boro-aluminosilicate, the base having a concentration up to 0.5 normal.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, wherein the concentration of the
base is below 0.5N.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The process of claim 2, wherein the concentration of the base is
from 0.1N to 0.4N.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The process of any preceding claim, wherein the base is selected
from LiOH, NaOH, KOH, RbOH, CsOH, Ca(OH)2, Sr(OH)2, BA(OH)2 and
mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A process according to any preceding claim, wherein the EUO
topology boro-aluminosilicate is a boro-aluminosilicate EU-1 zeolite.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The process of any one of claims 1 to 4, wherein the boro-aluminosilicate
is an intergrowth of EU-1 and NES topology zeolites.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The process of any one of claims 1 to 4 and 6, wherein said NES
topology boro-aluminosilicate zeolite is selected from NU-85, NU-86, and NU-87
zeolites and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A boro-aluminosilicate EU-1 having improved wax
isomerization properties, said boro-aluminosilicate prepared by treating a boro-aluminosilicate
EU-1 containing detrital material with a base for a time and at a
temperature sufficient to remove detrital material.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A catalytic isomerization process, comprising contacting a
feedstock comprising a C16 to C46 carbon containing feedstock, under catalytic
isomerization conditions, with an isomerization catalyst comprising a boro-aluminosilicate
product of the process of any one of claims 1 to 7, or of claim 8.</claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure num="1"><img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="137" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="176"/></figure><figure num="2"><img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="142"/></figure></drawings><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="155" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="242" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="158" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="242" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>