<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1013744-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1013744" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18494396" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000628"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1013744-A1" status="new" fvid="22857842"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1013744</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000628</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99125504-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99125504</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991221</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-36942898-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>36942898</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981225</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/10        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/10        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/18        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/188       20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/19        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L  10/08        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L  10/08        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10L   1/08</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Grundöl für Dieselbrennstoff und dieses enthaltende Zusammensetzungen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Base fuel oil for diesel fuel oil and diesel fuel oil composition comprising the same</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Huile de base pour combustible de Diesel et composition la contenant</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0807676-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0807676</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997014768-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997014768</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998005740-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998005740</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TONEN CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TONEN CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TONEN CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>Palaceside Building, 1-1 Hitotsubashi, 1-Chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MURAKAMI KAZUYUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>NAMIYAMA KAZUYOSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>OHMORI NORIAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MURAKAMI, KAZUYUKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NAMIYAMA, KAZUYOSHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OHMORI, NORIAKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Murakami, Kazuyuki, Corp. Res. and Dev. Laboratory</last-name><address><street>Tonen Corporation, 1-3-1, Nishi-tsurugaoka</street><city>Ohi-Machi, Iruma-Gun, Saitama</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Namiyama, Kazuyoshi, Corp. Res. and Dev. Laborat.</last-name><address><street>Tonen Corporation, 1-3-1, Nishi-tsurugaoka</street><city>Ohi-Machi, Iruma-Gun, Saitama</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Ohmori, Noriaki, Corp. Res. and Dev. Laboratory</last-name><address><street>Tonen Corporation, 1-3-1, Nishi-tsurugaoka</street><city>Ohi-Machi, Iruma-Gun, Saitama</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Fletcher Watts, Susan Jane</last-name><address><street>ESSO Engineering (Europe) Ltd, Patents and Licences, Mailpoint 72, Esso House, Ermyn Way</street><city>Leatherhead, Surrey KT22 8XE</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>There is disclosed a base fuel oil, having improved response to
lubricity additives, for diesel fuel oil characterized by (1) sulfur content of
0.03 wt% or less, (2) nitrogen content of 35 wt. ppm or less, (3) density of
0.835 g/cm<sup>3</sup> or less and (4) solubility parameter of 7.00 to 8.10, and also
provides a diesel fuel oil composition comprising the above base fuel oil
incorporated with a lubricity additive.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to a novel diesel fuel oil composition, more
particularly a base fuel oil for diesel fuel oil to exhibit excellent lubricity
improving effect, which is incorporated with a lubricity improver.</p><heading><u style="single">DESCRIPTION OF THE RELATED ART</u></heading><p num="0002">Diesel engines are widely used for various purposes, e.g., for driving
automobiles, ships and construction machines, and are still spreading further. As
a result, fuel oil for diesel engines is increasingly in demand, and becoming
heavier to satisfy the increased demands, because straight-run diesel fuel oil is
distilled deeper and/or blended with heavier fractions. It is anticipated that the
above trends are accompanied by increased NOx and particulate matter
emissions in exhaust gases to further aggravate air pollution.</p><p num="0003">A variety of techniques have been proposed from wide angles to
abate air pollutants, e.g., NOx and particulate matter, present in exhaust gases
from diesel engines, such as improved combustion chamber shapes, installation
of various devices (e.g., exhaust gas recycle (EGR) system, exhaust gas
cleaning-up catalytic converter system and particulate matter trapping system),
and improvement of diesel fuel and lubricant oils. An EGR system, which is
considered to be one of the effective means to abate the pollutant emissions,
recycles part of exhaust gases from the diesel engine back to the combustion
chamber as part of the combustion air. However, it may cause several problems
when sulfate ions and particulate matter are present in the exhaust gases, such as
deteriorated durability and reliability of the engine, deteriorated lubricant oil,
increased emissions of particulate matter and decreased power output. These
problems will be further aggravated when it is installed in a direct-injection 
engine, which is required to operate at a high load. The sulfate ions are derived
from sulfur compounds present in diesel fuel oil, and "low-sulfur diesel fuel oil"
containing sulfur at 0.05 wt% or less has become a social need.</p><p num="0004">Sulfur in a diesel fuel oil can be reduced by refining, in particular
catalytic hydrotreating, of the base stocks. This, however, is accompanied by
decreased lubricity of diesel fuel oil itself, and will damage the injection device
of the engine. It is known that wear of the injection pump notably increases as
sulfur content decreases from 0.2 wt%.</p><p num="0005">Attempts have been made to improve diesel fuel oil lubricity by the
aid of lubricity improver to solve the above problems, but failed to produce
satisfactory results.</p><heading><u style="single">DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0006">The present invention relates to a base fuel oil for diesel fuel oil
having properties necessary for a lubricity improver to exhibit its lubricity-improving
effect, and a diesel fuel oil comprising the above base fuel oil
incorporated with a lubricity improver.</p><p num="0007">The present invention is based on the discovery that the lubricity
improver, that lubricity of diesel fuel oil is improved as a lubricity improver in
the base fuel oil is quickly adsorbed on the metal surface and that the base fuel
oil must have low affinity for the lubricity improver not to hinder adsorption of
the improver on the metal surface.</p><p num="0008">The present invention provides a base fuel oil for diesel fuel oil of
improved response to lubricity additives characterized by (1) sulfur content of 
0.03 wt% or less, (2) nitrogen content of 35 wt. ppm or less, (3) density of
0.835 g/cm<sup>3</sup> or less and (4) solubility parameter of 7.00 to 8.10.</p><p num="0009">The present invention also provides a diesel fuel oil composition
comprising the above base fuel oil which is incorporated with a lubricity
improver.</p><p num="0010">The present invention, relating to the above base fuel oil for diesel
fuel oil and diesel fuel oil composition, includes the following preferred
embodiments:
<sl><li>(1) the above mentioned base fuel oil for diesel fuel oil composition having a
density of 0.830 g/cm<sup>3</sup> or less,</li><li>(2) the base fuel oil for diesel fuel oil composition of the above (1) having a
solubility parameter of 7.50 to 8.05, and</li><li>(3) the above mentioned diesel fuel oil composition comprising the base fuel
oil of one of the above (1) and (2) which is incorporated with a lubricity
improver.</li></sl></p><p num="0011">The present invention is described below in further detail. The base
fuel oil of the present invention for diesel fuel oil has a sulfur content, nitrogen
content, density and solubility parameter in specific ranges. The diesel fuel oil
composition of the present invention comprises the above base fuel oil which is
incorporated with a lubricity improver. </p><heading><u style="single">BASE FUEL OIL FOR DIESEL FUEL OIL</u></heading><p num="0012">The base fuel oil of the present invention for diesel fuel oil has a
sulfur content of 0.03 wt% or less, preferably 0.025 wt% or less, and nitrogen
content of 35 wt. ppm or less, preferably 25 wt. ppm or less. When its sulfur
content exceeds 0.03 wt% or nitrogen content exceeds 35 wt. ppm, the base fuel
oil will have sufficient affinity for the lubricity improver with a polar group to
prevent it from being adsorbed on the metal surface. As a result, the lubricity
improver incorporated in the base fuel oil will no longer fully exhibit its
intended lubricity improving effect.</p><p num="0013">The base fuel oil of the present invention for diesel fuel oil also has a
density of 0.835 g/cm<sup>3</sup> or less, preferably 0.830 g/cm<sup>3</sup> or less. When its density
exceeds 0.835 g/cm<sup>3</sup>, difference in density between the base fuel oil and lubricity
improver will be sufficiently small to prevent the latter from being adsorbed on
the metal surface. As a result, the lubricity improver incorporated in the base
fuel oil will no longer fully exhibit its intended lubricity improving effect.</p><p num="0014">The base fuel oil of the present invention for diesel fuel oil also has a
solubility parameter of 7.00 to 8.10, preferably 7.50 to 8.05. When its solubility
parameter is below 7.00, the base fuel oil will be insufficiently compatible with
the lubricity improver, possibly causing phase separation. When its solubility
parameter exceeds 8.10, difference in solubility parameter between the base fuel
oil and lubricity improver will be sufficiently small to excessively increase
compatibility between them, possibly preventing the lubricity improver
incorporated in the base fuel oil from fully exhibiting its intended lubricity
improving effect. </p><p num="0015">Solubility parameter is a measure of solubility in a nonelectrolytic
solvent, and a solute will be more compatible with a solvent when difference
between them in solubility parameter decreases. It is given by surface tensions
of solvent and solute:
<st32:dfg xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center"><st32:df align="centre">δ = 4.19P<st32:sup pos="post">0.43</st32:sup></st32:df><st32:df align="centre">P = σV<st32:sup pos="post">-1/3</st32:sup></st32:df></st32:dfg>
wherein, δ stands for solubility parameter, P for internal pressure (dyn/cm<sup>2</sup>),
σ for surface tension (dyn/cm) and V for molar volume (cm<sup>3</sup>).</p><p num="0016">A lubricity improver can fully exhibit its intended effect when the
base fuel oil in which it is incorporated has the following properties: (1) sulfur
content of 0.03 wt% or less, (2) nitrogen content of 35 wt. ppm or less, (3)
density of 0.835 g/cm<sup>3</sup> or less and (4) solubility parameter of 7.00 to 8.10.</p><p num="0017">The above properties can be adjusted by various methods, e.g.,
blending of petroleum fractions from different crude sources, solvent extraction,
hydrotreatment and adequate combination thereof. These fractions are used
individually or in combination for the base fuel oil of the present invention.</p><heading><u style="single">DIESEL FUEL OIL COMPOSITION</u></heading><p num="0018">The diesel fuel oil composition of the present invention comprises
the above base fuel oil which is incorporated with a lubricity improver and other
types of additives.</p><p num="0019">The lubricity improver useful for the present invention is not limited,
and can be selected from the known ones. These include fatty acids, e.g., stearic, 
linolic and oleic acid, and esters, e.g., those of the above fatty acids and polyalcohols,
represented by the ester of linolic acid and glycerin. The preferable
one is an ester. A lubricity improver dosage below 0.002 wt% may not
satisfactorily improve lubricity, and above 0.1 wt% is not economical, because
lubricity will not be improved as much as increased dosage. The preferable
lubricity improver dosage is 0.005 to 0.05 wt%. The above lubricity improvers
may be used individually or in combination.</p><p num="0020">The diesel fuel oil composition of the present invention may be
incorporated, as required, with other known additives for fuel oil, so long as its
performance is not damaged. These additives include flow improver, pour point
depressant, cetane improver, antioxidant, metal deactivator, detergent, corrosion
inhibitor, de-icer, bactericide, combustion promoter, antistatic agent, and coloring
agent A general dosage of the additive is 0.1 to 0.5wt% in the case of pour
point depressant, although not limited to this level. One or more of these
additives may be used for the present invention, as required.</p><p num="0021">The flow improvers useful for the present invention include
polyethylene glycol ester-based compounds, ethylene-vinyl acetate-based
copolymers, ethylene-alkylacrylate-based copolymers, chlorinated polyethylene,
polyalkyl acrylate, alkenyl succinamide-based compounds and so on.</p><p num="0022">The diesel fuel oil composition of the present invention may be also
incorporated, as required, with one or more types of oxygenated compounds so
long as its performance is not damaged. These compounds include aliphatic
alcohols, e.g., methanol, ethanol, isopropanol, n-butanol, isobutanol, tert-butanol,
amyl alcohol, isoamyl alcohol, n-octanol, 2-ethyl hexanol, n-heptyl
alcohol, tridecyl alcohol, cyclohexanol and methyl cyclohexanol; ethers, e.g.,
methyl tert-butyl ether and ethyl tert-butyl ether; dialkyl phthalates, e.g., diethyl 
phthalate, dipropyl phthalate and dibutyl phthalate; glycol-ether compounds,
e.g., ethylene glycol monoisobutyl ether, diethylene glycol mono-n-butyl ether,
diethylene glycol monoisobutyl ether, diethylene glycol dimethyl ether, triethylene
glycol mono-n-butyl ether, triethylene glycol dimethyl ether, propylene
glycol monomethyl ether acetate and dipropylene glycol mono-n-butyl ether;
hydroxyl amine compounds; and diketones, e.g., acetyl acetone. A general
dosage of the oxygenated compound, if used, is 1 to 15 wt%, although not
limited to this level.</p><p num="0023">The present invention is described in more detail by Examples,
which by no means limit the present invention. The following base stocks and
lubricity improvers were used for Examples and Comparative Examples. The
method to determine solubility parameter was also described.</p><heading>(1) <u style="single">BASE STOCK</u></heading><p num="0024">The base stocks used for Examples and Comparative Examples are
described in Table 1.</p><p num="0025">Base stock A is a straight-run diesel fuel fraction from low-sulfur
Minas crude, hydrodesulfurized to adjust its properties.</p><p num="0026">Base stock B is a 50-50 mixture of straight-run diesel fuel fractions
from low-sulfur Minas crude and a Middle Eastern crude, also hydro-desulfurized.</p><p num="0027">Base stock C is a 50-50 mixture of Base stock B and a straight-run
kerosene fraction from a Middle Eastern crude. </p><p num="0028">Base stock D is a straight-run diesel fuel fraction from a Middle
Eastern crude.</p><p num="0029">Base stock E is a straight-run diesel fuel fraction from a low-sulfur
Minas crude.</p><p num="0030">Base stock F is an 80-20 mixture of Base stock D and a cracked
diesel fuel fraction.</p><p num="0031">Base stock G is an 80-20 mixture of Base stock E and a cracked
diesel fuel fraction. <tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="8" align="center" namest="2">Base Stocks</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">B</entry><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="center">D</entry><entry align="center">E</entry><entry align="center">F</entry><entry align="center">G</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Distillation (°C)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Initial boiling point</entry><entry align="center">158</entry><entry align="center">158</entry><entry align="center">161</entry><entry align="center">194</entry><entry align="center">194</entry><entry align="center">193</entry><entry align="center">193</entry></row><row><entry align="left">10%</entry><entry align="center">186</entry><entry align="center">187</entry><entry align="center">184</entry> <entry align="center">231</entry><entry align="center">237</entry><entry align="center">224</entry><entry align="center">226</entry></row> <row><entry align="left">50%</entry> <entry align="center">249</entry> <entry align="center">250</entry><entry align="center">217</entry><entry align="center">277</entry><entry align="center">278</entry><entry align="center">275</entry><entry align="center">276</entry></row><row><entry align="left">90%</entry><entry align="center">315</entry><entry align="center">316</entry><entry align="center">277</entry><entry align="center">324</entry><entry align="center">328</entry><entry align="center">321</entry><entry align="center">322</entry></row><row><entry align="left">End point</entry><entry align="center">343</entry><entry align="center">344</entry><entry align="center">326</entry><entry align="center">351</entry><entry align="center">350</entry><entry align="center">343</entry><entry align="center">346</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sulfur content, wt%</entry><entry align="center">0.022</entry><entry align="center">0.014</entry><entry align="center">0.024</entry><entry align="center">0.045</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry><entry align="center">0.04</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Nitrogen content, wt. ppm</entry><entry align="center">23</entry><entry align="center">11</entry><entry align="center">17</entry><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Density, g/cm3</entry><entry align="center">0.829</entry><entry align="center">0.826</entry><entry align="center">0.813</entry><entry align="center">0.836</entry><entry align="center">0.831</entry><entry align="center">0.840</entry><entry align="center">0.839</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Solubility parameter</entry><entry align="center">8.04</entry><entry align="center">8.02</entry><entry align="center">7.82</entry><entry align="center">8.11</entry><entry align="center">8.07</entry><entry align="center">8.09</entry><entry align="center">8.06</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>(2) <u style="single">LUBRICITY IMPROVER</u></heading><p num="0032">A lubricity improver with an ester-based compound as the active
component (PDN655, produced by Exxon Chemical) was used.</p><heading>(3) <u style="single">DETERMINATION OF SOLUBILITY PARAMETER</u></heading><p num="0033">Solubility parameter was determined by the following equations, as
described earlier:
<st32:dfg xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center"><st32:df align="centre">δ = 4.19P<st32:sup pos="post">0.43</st32:sup></st32:df><st32:df align="centre">P = σV<st32:sup pos="post">-1/3</st32:sup></st32:df></st32:dfg>
wherein, δ stands for solubility parameter, P for internal pressure (dyn/cm<sup>2</sup>),
σ for surface tension (dyn/cm) and V for molar volume (cm<sup>3</sup>).</p><p num="0034">Surface tension σ of the base stock was determined by a surface
tension meter (Kyowa Kaimen Kagaku, FACE automatic surface tension meter
PD-Z). Molar volume V of the base stock was determined from its molecular
weight M and density ρ (g/cm<sup>3</sup>) by the relationship <st32:f xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">V = M/ρ</st32:f>.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLES AND COMPARATIVE EXAMPLES</u></heading><p num="0035">Each diesel fuel oil was prepared by incorporating the base fuel oil
with 100 wt. ppm of the lubricity improver (PDN655), and lubricity-tested to
measure wear scar diameter. The results are given in Table 2. The method to
determine lubricity is also described. <tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="4" align="center" namest="2">EXAMPLES</entry><entry nameend="8" align="center" namest="5">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLES</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fuel oil</entry></row><row><entry align="left">• Composition (wt%)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Base Stock A</entry><entry align="center">99.99</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Base Stock B</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">99.99</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Base Stock C</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">99.99</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Base Stock D</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">99.99</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Base Stock E</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">99.99</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Base Stock F</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">99.99</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Base Stock G</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">99.99</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lubricity improver</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry></row><row><entry align="left">• Properties</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sulfur content, wt%</entry><entry align="center">0.022</entry><entry align="center">0.014</entry><entry align="center">0.024</entry><entry align="center">0.045</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry><entry align="center">0.04</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Nitrogen content, wt. ppm</entry><entry align="center">23</entry><entry align="center">11</entry><entry align="center">17</entry><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Density, g/cm<sup>3</sup></entry><entry align="center">0.829</entry><entry align="center">0.826</entry><entry align="center">0.813</entry><entry align="center">0.836</entry><entry align="center">0.831</entry><entry align="center">0.840</entry><entry align="center">0.839</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Solubility parameter</entry><entry align="center">8.04</entry><entry align="center">8.02</entry><entry align="center">7.82</entry><entry align="center">8.11</entry><entry align="center">8.07</entry><entry align="center">8.09</entry><entry align="center">8.06</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lubricity of diesel fuel oil</entry></row><row><entry align="left">• Improvement of wear scar diameter,<!--footnotes removed--> µm</entry><entry align="center">200</entry><entry align="center">210</entry><entry align="center">260</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">120</entry><entry align="center">70</entry><entry align="center">80<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">MEASUREMENT OF LUBRICITY</u></heading><p num="0036">Lubricity was assessed by resistance of diesel fuel oil to wear.
Resistance to wear was measured as per JPI-5S-50-98 (gas oil/lubricant oil
testing method). Wear scar diameter (µm) was determined using a high
frequency reciprocating rig (HFRR, produced by PCS) under the conditions
shown in Table 3. Wear scar diameter increases as lubricity of diesel fuel oil
decreases. Wear scar diameter is an avenge of major scar diameter and minor
scar diameter, (major scar diameter + minor scar diameter)/2. Lubricity is
represented by improvement of wear scar diameter, wear scar diameter with the
base fuel oil minus that with the diesel fuel oil.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Liquid quantity</entry><entry align="left">2 ± 0.20 ml</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Stroke</entry><entry align="left">1 ± 0.03 mm</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Frequency</entry><entry align="left">50 ± 1 Hz</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Liquid temperature</entry><entry align="left">40 ± 2°C, or 60 ± 2°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Load</entry><entry align="left">200 ± 1 gf</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Testing time</entry><entry align="left">75 ± 0.1 minute</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Liquid surface area</entry><entry align="left">6 ± 1 cm<sup>2</sup></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0037">As shown in Table 2, the diesel fuel oils prepared by Examples 1 to
3 are excellent in lubricity, showing larger improvements of wear scar diameter
than those prepared by Comparative Examples, which show very poor improvements,
because at least one of their sulfur content, nitrogen content, density and
solubility parameter is not in the specified range. </p><p num="0038">As described above in detail, the diesel fuel oil composition of the
present invention shows excellent lubricity because its base fuel oil has
properties of (1) sulfur content of 0.03 wt% or less, (2) nitrogen content of 35
wt. ppm or less, (3) density of 0.835 g/cm<sup>3</sup> or less and (4) solubility parameter of
7.00 to 8.10, and is incorporated with a lubricity improver.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A base fuel oil for diesel fuel oil characterized by (1) sulfur
content of 0.03 wt% or less, (2) nitrogen content of 35 wt. ppm or less, (3)
density of 0.835 g/cm3 or less and (4) solubility parameter in a range of 7.00 to
8.10, said fuel having an improved response to lubricity additives.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The base fuel oil of claim 1 further incorporated with one or
more additives comprising at least one lubricity improver to produce a diesel
fuel oil.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The base fuel oil of claim 1 or claim 2 wherein the sulfur content
is 0.025 wt% or less.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The base fuel oil of any one of claims 1 to 3 wherein the nitrogen
content is 25 wt. ppm or less.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The base fuel oil of any one of claims 1 to 4 wherein the density
is 0.830 g/cm3 or less.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The base fuel oil of any one of claims 1 to 5 wherein the
solubility parameter is in a range of from 7.50 to 8.05.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="154" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="241" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="158" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="240" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>