<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1333046-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1333046" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="19191421" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030806"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1333046-A2" status="new" fvid="23822215"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1333046</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20030806</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03000968-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03000968</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030116</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002008439-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002008439</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020117</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/16        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  59/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  59/32        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/16B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/16C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/16G</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/16M3</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/16M4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/16M7S</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/16M8S</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  59/32F</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Epoxidharzzusammensetzung, Verfahren zur Oberflächenbehandlung, Flüssigkeitsstrahlaufzeichnungskopf und ein Flüssigkeitsstrahlaufzeichnungsgerät</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Epoxy resin composition, surface treatment method, liquid-jet recording head and liquid-jet recording apparatus</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition de résine époxyde, procédé de traitement d'une surface, tête d'enregistrement par jet de liquide et appareil d'enregistrement à jet de liquide</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0319472-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0319472</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0368320-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0368320</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0942024-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0942024</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1085031-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1085031</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE CHEMABS CHEMICAL ABSTRACTS SERVICE, COLUMBUS, OHIO, US; 1996, VAN DE GRAMPEL, J.C. ET AL.: "New polysiloxanes for chemically amplified resist applications" XP002288046 &amp;  ACS SYMPOSIUM SERIES, vol. 614, 1995, pages 333-354,</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CANON KK</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CANON KABUSHIKI KAISHA</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CANON KABUSHIKI KAISHA</last-name><address><street>30-2, 3-chome, Shimomaruko, Ohta-ku</street><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>IMAMURA ISAO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NOGUCHI HIROMICHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SHIMOMURA AKIHIKO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>IMAMURA, ISAO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NOGUCHI, HIROMICHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SHIMOMURA, AKIHIKO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>IMAMURA, ISAO</last-name><address><street>Canon Kabushiki Kaisha, 30-2, Shimomaruko 3-chome</street><city>Ohta-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NOGUCHI, HIROMICHI</last-name><address><street>Canon Kabushiki Kaisha, 30-2, Shimomaruko 3-chome</street><city>Ohta-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SHIMOMURA, AKIHIKO</last-name><address><street>Canon Kabushiki Kaisha, 30-2, Shimomaruko 3-chome</street><city>Ohta-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Böckelen, Rainer</last-name><address><street>Tiedtke-Bühling-Kinne &amp;amp; Partner (GbR), TBK-Patent Bavariaring 4</street><city>80336 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An epoxy resin composition can be used for forming a
film having excellent water-repellency on a substrate
surface. The epoxy resin composition contains (a) an epoxy
resin having at least two alicyclic epoxy groups, at least
one perfluoroalkyl group having 6 to 12 carbon atoms, and at
least one alkylsiloxane group and (b) a cationic
polymerization catalyst. The alicyclic epoxy groups and the
perfluoroalkyl group are present in branched chains of the
epoxy resin, and the alkylsiloxane group is present in the
main chain of the epoxy resin.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><heading>Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a curing epoxy
resin composition which permits water-repellent and ink-repellent
surface treatment. Particularly, the present
invention relates to an epoxy resin composition capable of
forming a film pattern by ultraviolet irradiation, a surface
treatment method using the resin composition, a liquid-jet
recording head subjected to ink-repellent treatment with the
epoxy resin composition, and a liquid-jet recording
apparatus using the liquid-jet recording head.</p><heading>Description of the Related Art</heading><p num="0002">In various fields, a method of applying a water-repellent
coating to a member required to have water
resistance and ink repellency to obtain these properties is
generally known, and resin materials and coating materials
used for the method have been developed. For example, films
of fluoropolyolefin and a fluororesin coating material
having perfluoro groups are thermally and chemically stable, 
excellent in weather resistance, water resistance, chemical
resistance, solvent resistance, etc., and further excellent
in release property, abrasion resistance and water
repellency; such films are widely used for various
applications.</p><p num="0003">Meanwhile, a liquid-jet recording head adapted to
discharge liquid droplets such as ink droplets through
discharge nozzles and cause them to adhere to a recording
medium such as a sheet of paper so as to record or form an
image thereon has only recently been required to be able to
discharge smaller liquid droplets, be driven with a higher
driving frequency, and have a larger number of nozzles in
order to improve recording properties. Therefore, a
treatment for maintaining the nozzle surface in a clear
state becomes more important. However, it is difficult to
selectively treat the surface of a nozzle or precisely treat
the surface in the form of a pattern using any existing
material which avoids ink adhesion. This is because first,
a material mainly comprising a compound having a
photosensitive functional group must be used as a surface
treatment material for treating the surface in the form of a
pattern so that the material has characteristics like
photoresist suitable for pattern treatment; however, it is
very difficult to design the molecule of such a compound so
that the compound has water repellency and ink repellency at 
the same time.</p><p num="0004">Second, if the nozzle surface can be treated with
an existing fluorocarbon material, a film structure must be
designed so as to maintain the properties of the surface for
a long period of time. A material permitting such a pattern
surface treatment having the above-described properties is
extremely valuable for surface treatment of an ink-jet print
head, as described below.</p><p num="0005">Namely, in an ink-jet recording system in which an
ink is ejected as droplets, the discharge orifice (nozzle)
is preferably designed to have the following
characteristics:</p><p num="0006">(1) The residual ink of ink columns having turned
into droplets is immediately held back into the nozzle.</p><p num="0007">(2) The ink droplets adhering to the nozzle
surface can be readily wiped off by a cleaning operation.</p><p num="0008">(3) The nozzle surface has excellent scratch
resistance against the cleaning operation and paper transfer.</p><p num="0009">(4) In repeated formation of droplets and ink
refilling, a meniscus is formed on the nozzle surface (refer
to reference numeral 23 in Fig. 1).</p><p num="0010">(5) The discharge direction is normal to the
meniscus.</p><p num="0011">(6) Even with an ink having low surface tension or
under low-negative pressure, the interfacial tension, i.e., 
the contact angle, is sufficient to form the meniscus.</p><p num="0012">The above-noted characteristics are required for
the discharge orifice because if a recording liquid such as
an ink adheres to the periphery of the orifice, the
discharge (flying) direction of the ink droplets discharged
from the orifice deviates, making it impossible to print
highly accurately and directly degrade the printing
performance. In order to prevent adhesion of the ink to the
vicinity of the discharge orifice, which causes a deviation
in the discharge direction, a method is known in which the
surface of the discharge orifice is subjected to water-repellent
treatment.</p><p num="0013">For example, a method of ink-repellent treatment
with a polymer having fluoroacetyl groups and silazane
groups is known as prior art relating to the above-described
surface treatment (for example, Japanese Patent Laid-Open No.
2-39944). On the other hand, as a result of the increasing
demand for sophisticated printers utilizing liquid-jet
recording systems for recording images, the recording liquid
to be used for such recording systems is also required to
show sophisticated characteristics. More often, the
recording liquid to be used for such recording systems is
chemically regulated to be basic with a pH value of 7 to 11
in order to further improve dissolution stability and
dispersion stability of contents, and thus a structural 
material highly resistant against alkali and hydrolysis must
be used for a printer member.</p><p num="0014">However, when a recording liquid containing a
polar organic solvent or a recording liquid showing such a
high pH value is used, a water-repellent agent applied for
treating the surface of the discharge orifice in order to
satisfy the above requirements can damage the film forming
property of the agent and the tight adhesion of the agent to
the surface of the discharge orifice as it comes into
contact with the solvent of the recording liquid,
particularly the polar organic solvent of the recording
liquid. Then, the coat of the water-repellent agent can be
peeled off to decrease the water repellency of the surface.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0015">Therefore, it is an object of the present
invention to provide an epoxy resin composition that can be
suitably used for a water-repellent agent or water-repellent
coating to be applied to a surface that can be brought into
contact with a solution or material containing a component
such as a polar organic solvent that can damage the film
forming ability and the adhesion of the water-repellent
agent.</p><p num="0016">It is another object of the present invention to 
provide an epoxy resin composition adapted to surface
modifying treatment for maintaining the treated surface
constantly in a clear state.</p><p num="0017">Still another object of the present invention is
to provide a surface treatment method capable of precisely
imparting water-repellency to a surface of a member by using
the epoxy resin composition in a position-selective manner.</p><p num="0018">A further object of the present invention is to
provide a liquid-jet recording head and liquid-jet recording
apparatus in which the surface of a substrate is treated
with the epoxy resin composition so that the surface of a
nozzle can be constantly maintained in a clear state, and an
ink does not adhere to the surface of a printing head even
when the head is brought into contact with a recording
medium for a long period of time, thereby exhibiting high
dot landing precision, and permitting long-term maintenance
of printing quality.</p><p num="0019">These objects are achieved by the present
invention as described below.</p><p num="0020">In an embodiment of the present invention, an
epoxy resin composition comprises (a) an epoxy resin having
at least two alicyclic epoxy groups, at least one
perfluoroalkyl group having 6 to 12 carbon atoms, and at
least one alkylsiloxane group; and (b) a cationic
polymerization catalyst. In the epoxy resin composition, 
the alicyclic epoxy groups and the perfluoroalkyl group are
present in branch chains of the epoxy resin, and the
alkylsiloxane group is present in the main chain of the
epoxy resin.</p><p num="0021">In another embodiment of the present invention, a
surface treatment method comprises (i) coating the epoxy
resin composition on the surface of a substrate to form a
film; (ii) irradiating at least a portion of the film with
an active energy ray (position-selective manner); and (iii)
dissolving at least a portion of the film which was not
irradiated with the active energy ray in a liquid capable of
dissolving the film.</p><p num="0022">In still another embodiment of the present
invention, a surface treatment method comprises (i) coating
the epoxy resin composition on the surface of a substrate to
form a film; (ii) curing at least a portion of the film by
polymerization; and (iii) selectively removing an uncured
portion of the film.</p><p num="0023">In a further embodiment of the present invention,
a liquid-jet recording head comprises a discharge orifice
for discharging a liquid, wherein at least the periphery of
the discharge orifice is coated with a cured film of the
epoxy resin composition.</p><p num="0024">In a still further embodiment of the present
invention, a liquid-jet recording apparatus comprises the 
above-described liquid-jet recording head.</p><p num="0025">The epoxy resin composition of the present
invention is an epoxy resin system, and thus a film
comprising the resin composition has excellent adhesion to
various members and can be cured at a relatively low
temperature to provide a cured product having excellent
physical properties as a structural material. Furthermore,
since the epoxy resin composition contains an epoxy compound
having an alkylsiloxane group and perfluoroalkyl group, the
film is significantly improved in resistance to water-soluble
organic solvents, particularly polar organic
solvents. The film also has improved resistance to pigment
dispersion stabilizer and the like contained in a pigment-based
ink. Furthermore, when the resin composition contains
a compatibilizer, the compatibilizer provides compatibility
between the components of the resin composition, thereby
widening the range of component materials of the resin
composition of the present invention.</p><p num="0026">When the film formed by coating the resin
composition of the present invention and then drying the
coating contains, as a catalyst, an onium salt of a Lewis
acid which is activated with an active energy ray, the film
can be cured in the form of a pattern. Therefore, uncured
portions of the film are then removed to permit surface
treatment of a member in the form of a pattern. </p><p num="0027">The surface of a member can be treated in the form
of a pattern by a method comprising coating the resin
composition on the substrate and then drying the coating to
form a film, irradiating the film with an active energy ray
through a mask having a desired pattern, and then removing
uncured portions of the film by development with a developer.
Although the basic steps of this pattern treatment are the
same as a photolithography method, a solvent or solvent
composition suitable for the film comprising the resin
composition is selected as the developer. As the developer,
an aromatic hydrocarbon, a ketone, an ester, glycol ester,
or a mixture thereof can be used.</p><p num="0028">In the surface treatment in the form of a pattern
using the resin composition of the present invention, so-called
post-curing is preferably further performed by
heating the film or irradiating the film with an active
energy ray after development to completely cure the film of
the resin composition.</p><p num="0029">Therefore, the resin composition of the present
invention can be suitably used as a water-repellent agent or
water-repellent coating material applied to an area having
opportunity for contact with a solution or material
containing a component such as a polar organic solvent,
which can damage adhesion of the water-repellent agent. The
resin composition of the present invention is further 
suitably used for water-repellent and ink-repellent
treatment of the discharge orifice surface of the liquid-jet
recording head.</p><p num="0030">Namely, when the resin composition of the present
invention is applied to an ink-jet recording apparatus, the
precision of selective surface modifying treatment using
optical polymerizability, the solid strength of the cured
film, the durability as a device due to frictional strength,
and the high degree of water repellency and ink repellency
result in improvements in properties such as meniscus
retention of an aqueous ink, cleaning property, droplet
discharge direction precision, persistency of continuous
discharge, suitability for print start after a pause, etc.
The meniscus retention represents the property by which an
ink maintains the ink surface at the nozzle tip by surface
tension and recovers and holds a meniscus at a predetermined
position during repeated droplet discharges. With low
meniscus retention, the ink leaks from the nozzle tip, the
meniscus retreats to decrease the volume of the droplet
discharged, or in an extreme case, a defect occurs in the
discharge of ink droplets.</p><p num="0031">Further objects, features and advantages of the
present invention will become apparent from the following
description of the preferred embodiments with reference to
the attached drawings. </p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0032">Fig. 1 is a sectional view showing a principal
portion of an example of a liquid-jet recording head.</p><p num="0033">Fig. 2 is a perspective view of the principal
portion of the head shown in Fig. 1.</p><p num="0034">Fig. 3 is a drawing showing an example of a
liquid-jet recording apparatus including a multi-head.</p><p num="0035">Figs. 4A to 4C are drawings respectively showing
steps of a method of manufacturing a liquid-jet recording
head of the present invention.</p><p num="0036">Figs. 5A to 5C are drawings respectively showing
steps performed after the steps shown in Fig. 4C.</p><p num="0037">Fig. 6A and 6B are drawings respectively showing
steps performed after the steps shown in Fig. 5C.</p><heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading><p num="0038">The present invention will be described in detail
below with reference to a preferred embodiment.</p><p num="0039">An epoxy resin composition of the present
invention comprises (a) an epoxy resin having at least two
alicyclic epoxy groups, at least one perfluoroalkyl group
having 6 to 12 carbon atoms, and at least one alkylsiloxane 
group; and (b) a cationic polymerization catalyst. In the
epoxy resin composition, the alicyclic epoxy groups and the
perfluoroalkyl group are present in branch chains of the
epoxy resin, and the alkylsiloxane group is present in the
main chain of the epoxy resin.</p> <p num="0040">The epoxy resin of the epoxy resin composition is
not limited as long as the above conditions are satisfied.
Examples of the epoxy resin of the present invention include
epoxy resins represented by formula (1):
<img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="104"/></p><p num="0041">In formula (1), a is an integer from 1 to 50, b is
an integer from 1 to 50, and c is an integer from 2 to 100.
Furthermore, each of n<sub>1</sub>, n<sub>2</sub>, n<sub>3</sub>, n<sub>5</sub>, n<sub>6</sub>, and n<sub>7</sub> is an integer
from 1 to 5, and n<sub>4</sub> is an integer from 2 to 200.</p><p num="0042">In formula (1), each of R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>4</sub>, R<sub>5</sub>, R<sub>6</sub>, R<sub>7</sub>, and R<sub>10</sub>
is independently a hydrogen atom or a straight or branched
chain alkyl group having 1 to 3 carbon atoms, each of R<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>3</sub>,
R<sub>8</sub> and R<sub>9</sub> is independently a hydrogen atom, a straight or
branched chain alkyl group having 1 to 3 carbon atoms, or a
nitrile group, and R<sub>f</sub> is a straight or branched chain
perfluoroalkyl group having 6 to 12 carbon atoms,
particularly a perfluoroalkyl group having 8 to 10 carbon
atoms.</p><p num="0043">The epoxy resin represented by formula (1) can be
obtained by copolymerization of perfluoroalkyl methacrylate,
3,4-oxycyclohexylmethyl methacrylate, and an azo group-containing
polysiloxaneamide at an appropriate monomer ratio
according to an ordinary method. The epoxy resin may also
be commercially obtained.</p><p num="0044">More specifically, the epoxy resin can be
synthesized by heating, light irradiation or heating and
light irradiation of a compound represented by structural
formula (1)-i below in coexistence with vinyl monomers
represented by structural formulae (1)-ii and (1)-iii so as
to produce radical species. <img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="31"/>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> to R<sub>13</sub> are the same as R<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>3</sub>, R<sub>8</sub> and R<sub>9</sub> above, n<sub>8</sub>
and n<sub>9</sub> each represent 0 or an integer from 1 to 6, and X
represents a halogen atom.
<img id="img-00140002" orientation="unknown" wi="73" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140002.tif" inline="no" he="20"/><img id="img-00140003" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140003.tif" inline="no" he="28"/>
wherein R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>10</sub>, n<sub>1</sub>, and n<sub>7</sub> are the same as defined above.</p> <p num="0045">A compound represented by formula (1)-i can be
synthesized by the method disclosed in, for example,
Japanese Patent Publication No. 2-33053. Namely, the
compound can be obtained by reaction of a diamine
represented by formula (1)-iv below and dihalides
represented by formulae (1)-v and (1)-vi below.
<img id="img-00140004" orientation="unknown"  wi="81" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00140004.tif" inline="no"  he="31"/><img id="img-00150001"  orientation="unknown"  wi="84" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/><img id="img-00150002" orientation="unknown" wi="85" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150002.tif" inline="no" he="24"/></p> <p num="0046">The epoxy resin composition represented by formula
(1) preferably has a number average molecular weight of
8,000 to 22,000, and more preferably has a number average
molecular weight of 8,500 to 20,000 in light of the
durability of the water-repellent coating.</p> <p num="0047">An example of the epoxy resin represented by
formula (1) is an epoxy resin represented by formula (2)
below. In formula (2). R<sub>f</sub>, n<sub>4</sub>, and a, b and c are defined as
above.
<img id="img-00150003" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150003.tif" inline="no" he="104"/></p><p num="0048">Preferably, in the resin represented by structural
formula (2), a is 20 to 50, b is 5 to 40, c is 20 to 70, n
is 20 to 150, and the number average molecular weight is
8,000 to 20,000.</p><p num="0049">A more preferred example of the epoxy resin is an
acrylic epoxy resin (A-1) having a number average molecular
weight of about 20,000 and represented by the following
structural formula in which the monomer unit a is 40 mol%,
the monomer unit b is 20 mol%, and the monomer unit c is 40
mol%:
<img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="107"/></p><p num="0050">In the structure represented by formula (1) or (2),
a 3,4-epoxycyclohexyl group is shown as an alicyclic epoxy
group. However, the alicyclic group is not limited to this,
and a cyclopropyl group or cyclohexyl group may be
introduced.</p><p num="0051">The epoxy resin may be used independently. Since
the resin has a high molecular weight, the resin is
preferably mixed with an oligomer having a lower molecular
weight of the resin and a solvent to improve coating
performance for a substance to be treated with the resin
composition and to improve the drying property of a film
after the solvent is evaporated, thereby improving the
workability of treatment. Namely, the resin represented by
formula (1) or another high molecular weight resin is
preferably used to function as a binder. The resin
represented by formula (1) or other high molecular weight
resin is preferably used as the binder for exposure work in
the form of a pattern on a resin film. The oligomer is
preferably a resin having a lower molecular weight than the
resin represented by formula (1), but another low molecular
weight oligomer may be used.</p><p num="0052">Although the resin composition of the present
invention mainly comprises the epoxy resin represented by
formula (1) and the catalyst, the resin composition
preferably further contains at least one compatibilizer 
according to demand. Preferred examples of the
compatibilizer include compounds represented by the
following formula (3) and (4):
<img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="35"/>
   wherein p is an integer from 0 to 2.</p><p num="0053">A preferred example of this compound is a compound
where p is 0, i.e., 2,2-bis(4-glycidyloxyphenyl)hexafluoropropane.
<img id="img-00180002" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00180002.tif" inline="no" he="36"/>
   wherein q is an integer from 0 to 2, and
<img id="img-00180003" orientation="unknown" wi="88" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00180003.tif" inline="no" he="18"/></p><p num="0054">A preferred example of this compound is a compound
where q is 0, i.e., m-bis-[1-(2,3-epoxypropoxy)-2,2,2-trifluoro-1-(trifluoromethyl)ethyl]benzene.</p><p num="0055">The compound represented by formula (3) or (4) has
a fluoroalkyl group, and thus the film formed by using such 
a compound only minimally decreases the surface energy and
has low water repellency and ink repellency because of its
short chain length. The compound represented by formula (3)
or (4) can be synthesized by reaction of a divalent alcohol
and epichlorohydrin corresponding to a compound in which
groups containing the epoxy groups at both ends are removed
from the compound represented by general formula (3) or (4)
by an ordinary method.</p><p num="0056">The resin composition of the present invention
contains a polymerization initiator as a catalyst for curing
the resin composition. In the present invention,
particularly, the resin composition is designed so as to
have high reactivity to an onium salt of a Lewis acid which
is activated by an active energy ray permitting curing at
low temperature. Therefore, the surface of a substrate can
be selectively treated by a photolithography method using
the resin composition, and the resin composition is suitable
for surface modification of a substrate which cannot be
easily maintained at high temperature. Examples of the
catalyst include bis(4-tert-butylphenyl)iodonium salt,
Optomer SP-150 and Optomer SP-170 (trade name, produced by
Asahidenka Kogyo Co., Ltd.), and the like.</p><p num="0057">The chemical structure of Optomer SP-150 is
represented by the following formula: <img id="img-00200001" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00200001.tif" inline="no" he="34"/></p><p num="0058">The chemical structure of Optomer SP-170 is
represented by the following formula:
<img id="img-00200002" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00200002.tif" inline="no" he="38"/></p><p num="0059">In addition, Irgacure 261 (trade name, produced by
Chiba Specialty Co., Ltd.) represented by the following
structural formula, and the like can also be used as the
polymerization initiator:
<img id="img-00200003" orientation="unknown" wi="65" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00200003.tif" inline="no" he="35"/></p><p num="0060">The resin composition of the present invention is 
preferably combined with an epoxy polymer which can
participate in a cross-linking reaction by itself, as a
binder polymer other than the resin represented by formula
(1). Examples of such a polymer include an acrylic resin
obtained by copolymerization of an acryl monomer having a
side chain epoxy group, a vinyl polymer obtained by
polymerization of a vinyl monomer having an alicyclic epoxy
group in its side chain, a polyester polymer having an
alicyclic epoxy group in its side chain (for example,
EHPE3150, produced by Daicel Chemical Industries, Ltd.), and
the like. If a polymer without such an epoxy group is used,
physical properties are intentionally controlled according
to the application thereof. Examples of such a polymer
include general purpose polymer compounds for coating, such
as polymers of bisphenol epoxy resins (trade names PKHC and
PKHJ, produced by Union Carbide Co., Ltd.),
poly(ethylene/vinyl acetate), phenol resins, polycarbonate
resins, polyester resins, polyamide resins, soluble
polyimide resins, and the like.</p><p num="0061">As described above, the epoxy resin composition of
the present invention basically contains the components
below in a nonpolar solvent.
<sl><li>(a) epoxy resin;</li><li>(b) cationic polymerization catalyst; and</li><li>(c) compatibilizer if required.</li></sl> 
The preferred mixing ratio of these components (a), (b) and
(c) in the resin composition is as follows.</p><p num="0062">When the component (a) is used together with an
oligomer, the mixing ratio depends upon the softening point
and glass transition temperature of both components, and
thus the ratio is not generally limited. However, the ratio
of oligomer : component (a) is 10:90 to 90:10 (ratio by
mass). The ratio of the catalyst (b) is in the range of 0.5
part by mass to 7 parts by mass relative to 100 part by mass
of the total amount of the epoxy resin components. In some
cases, the oligomer has low compatibility with the polymer,
and thus the compatibilizer (c) is preferably used.</p><p num="0063">The epoxy resin composition of the present
invention is used for treating the surface of a substrate by
heating or irradiation with an active energy ray.
Specifically, the resin composition of the present invention
is dissolved in an aromatic solvent, an aliphatic
hydrocarbon solvent, an ester solvent, an ether solvent, a
fluorocarbon solvent, or the like, and the resultant
solution can be coated on the surface of the substrate by
any one of various coating/printing methods such as roll
coating, spin coating, spray coating, screen printing,
gravure printing, etc. After the solution is coated on the
surface of the substrate, the formed film is cured by
heating or irradiation with an active energy ray. As a 
source of an active energy ray for curing, a mercury lamp, a
laser beam, an electron beam, or the like, which contains
large amounts of bright line spectra in the range of
wavelengths from 200 to 480 nm, is preferred.</p><p num="0064">The epoxy resin composition of the present
invention preferably contains the binder component and is
prepared so as to form a dry solid film. Also, the epoxy
resin composition can facilitate selective surface treatment
of the substrate by patterning similar to a photoresist
process. In this case, a coating solution containing the
resin composition of the present invention is coated on the
substrate, and then the solvent is removed to form a dry
film. Then, the film is irradiated with an active energy
ray through a mask having an appropriate pattern or
irradiated with an active energy ray in the form of a
pattern, and then the uncured portion of the film is removed
by development with a solvent system which can dissolve the
film. When energy beam irradiation in the form of a pattern
is insufficient for curing, post-curing is preferably
performed after development. As an energy source for post-curing,
heating with a microwave or the like or an active
energy ray irradiation by an electron beam, ultraviolet rays,
or the like is used.</p><p num="0065">The above-described surface modifying method of
the present invention enables water-repellent and oil-repellent 
treatment with excellent film adhesion to the
substrate and surface hardness of the film, and thus has the
great advantage that the substrate can be modified to have
excellent durability.</p><p num="0066">In an example of application of the epoxy resin
composition of the present invention to a liquid-jet
recording head, for example, an ink-jet recording head, the
nozzle surface of the liquid-jet recording head is treated
with the resin composition of the present invention to form
a surface which exhibits no strong adhesion of an ink and
which has good release property, facilitating wiping of the
ink adhering to the nozzle surface by a cleaning operation.</p><p num="0067">A cleaning mechanism may be mounted on the liquid-jet
recording head, for example, the ink-jet recording head,
or a cleaning method may be performed. In this regard, for
example, the ink adhering to the orifice surface of the ink-jet
recording head may be wiped with a rubber blade, the ink
in a nozzle may be sucked by a pump, or the ink may be
discharged at a position other than on a recording sheet.
Any one of these methods cannot eliminate the phenomenon
that small droplets of excessive ink adhere to the periphery
of the nozzle because not all of the ink is turned into ink
droplets when an ink column withdrawn by discharge pressure
forms into a droplet. Therefore, if the small droplets
spontaneously drop, are sucked back to the inside of the 
nozzle, or are readily removed, the droplets have no
influence on ink discharge.</p><p num="0068">The epoxy resin composition of the present
invention can be cured at relatively low temperature to
provide a cured film having excellent water repellency, oil
repellency, adhesion to the substrate, chemical resistance,
and friction resistance.</p><p num="0069">Figs. 1 and 2 show the principal portion of an
example of the construction of a liquid-jet recording head
to which the resin composition of the present invention can
be applied. Fig. 1 is a sectional view taken along a flow
path of an ink, and Fig. 2 is a perspective view of the
liquid-jet recording head shown in Fig. 1.</p><p num="0070">The recording head 13 shown in Fig. 1 comprises a
substrate 15 on which a discharge energy generator (17, 18,
19) is disposed, and a member 14 laminated on the substrate
15 by forming a predetermined pattern of a cured product of
a thermosetting resin composition and/or an active energy
ray curing resin composition to form at least a flow path.</p><p num="0071">The substrate 15 comprises a base 20 made of a
material with a high heat release effect, such as alumina or
the like, and a heat storage layer 19, an exothermic
resistor layer 18 made of a metal, electrodes 17-1 and 17-2
made of aluminum or the like, and a protective layer 16,
which are laminated, in that order, on the surface of the 
base 20. By supplying electricity to the electrodes 17-1
and 17-2, the discharge energy generating element formed in
a portion (in the region shown by character n in Fig. 1) of
the exothermic resistor layer 18, in which the electrodes
are not formed, generates heat to exert thermal energy on an
ink positioned above the element.</p><p num="0072">In recording, in the state in which an ink 21 is
caused to fill in a discharge orifice (orifice) 22 as a
micro opening at the tip of the member 14, when a current is
passed through the electrodes 17-1 and 17-2 corresponding to
a recording signal, heat is rapidly generated from the
region n, and bubbles occur in the ink 21 in contact with
the region n due to film boiling to discharge the ink 21 as
droplets 24 from the orifice 22 by the pressure of the
bubbles. Therefore, the droplets 24 fly toward a recording
medium 25.</p><p num="0073">In the liquid-jet recording head according to the
present invention, a cured film 30 comprising the resin
composition of the present invention is used as a water-repellent
and ink-repellent agent in the peripheries of at
least the orifice openings 22 of the orifice surface 29 (Fig.
2), thereby preventing the droplets from adhering to the
surface to prevent a deviation in the discharge direction of
the droplets. In addition, the cured film comprising the
resin composition of the present invention not only exhibits 
excellent adhesion to the substrate, but also causes no
deterioration in water repellency and adhesion even when the
ink contains an organic solvent, particularly, a polar
organic solvent.</p><p num="0074">Fig. 3 shows an example of a liquid-jet recording
apparatus including such a multi-head as shown in Fig. 2.
In Fig. 3, reference numeral 61 denotes a blade serving as a
wiping member, one end of which is a fixed end held by a
blade holding member to establish a cantilever state. The
blade 61 is disposed at a position adjacent to a recording
region of the recording head. In this example, the blade 61
is held to project into the movement path of the recording
head. Reference numeral 62 denotes a cap disposed at a home
position adjacent to the blade 61 and is moved
perpendicularly to the movement direction of the recording
head to cap the orifices in contact therewith.</p><p num="0075">Furthermore, reference numeral 63 denotes an ink
absorber provided adjacent to the blade 61 and held to
project into the movement path of the recording head in the
same manner as the blade 61. The blade 61, the cap 62 and
the ink absorber 63 constitute a discharge recovery section
64 for removing moisture, dust particles, and the like from
the ink discharge orifice surface by the blade 61 and the
ink absorber 63.</p><p num="0076">Reference numeral 65 denotes a recording head for 
recording in a liquid-jet system, for example, having a
construction in which an ink is discharged by thermal energy,
as shown in Figs. 1 and 2. Reference numeral 66 denotes a
carriage for moving the recording head 65 mounted thereon.
The carriage 66 is slidably engaged with a guide shaft 67
and partially connected (not shown in the drawing) to a belt
69 driven by a motor 68. Therefore, the carriage 66 can be
moved along the guide shaft 67, i.e., can be moved to the
recording region of the recording head 65 and the adjacent
region thereof.</p><p num="0077">Reference numeral 51 denotes a paper feed section
into which a recording medium is inserted, and reference
numeral 52 denotes a paper feed roller driven by a motor not
shown in the drawing. This construction permits the
recording medium to be fed to a position opposite to the
discharge orifice surface of the recording head and expelled
through a paper-expelling roller 53 as recording proceeds.</p><p num="0078">In the above-described construction, when the
recording head 65 is returned to the home position at the
end of recording, the cap 65 of the head recovery section 64
retreats from the movement path of the recording head 65,
while the blade 61 projects into the movement path. As a
result, the orifice surface of the recording head 65 is
wiped. When the recording head 65 is capped with the cap 62
in contact with the orifice surface, the cap 62 is moved to 
project into the movement path of the recording head 65.</p><p num="0079">When the recording head 65 is moved from the home
position to the start position of recording, the cap 62 and
the blade 61 are at the same positions as at the time of
wiping. As a result, in this movement, the orifice surface
of the recording head 65 is wiped. The recording head 65 is
moved to the home position at the times of recording end and
recovery, but the recording head 65 is also moved to the
home position adjacent to the recording region of the
recording head at predetermined intervals when the recording
head 65 is moved in the recording region for recording.
During this movement, the discharge surface is also wiped.</p><p num="0080">In color recording, the ink jet recording
apparatus can use a recording head in which discharge
orifices for cyan, magenta, yellow and black inks are
arranged in parallel. Alternatively, recording heads for
the respective colors may be arranged in parallel. In this
case, each of the color inks may be discharged from one
discharge orifice or simultaneously discharged from a
plurality of discharge orifices to adhere at least two
droplets of the same color to the recording medium.</p><p num="0081">The liquid-jet recording head of the present
invention is subjected to surface treatment with an ink
repellent treatment material comprising the above-described
epoxy resin composition of the present invention and has the 
chemical properties described in the examples below.
Therefore, an ink adheres less, or adhered ink can be easily
removed by a cleaning wiper blade, thereby significantly
improving substantial retention of a print.</p><p num="0082">An example of the method of using the epoxy resin
composition of the present invention will be described. In
curing a film comprising the resin composition of the
present invention with an active energy ray, as described
above, a photo cation catalyst which releases a Lewis acid
by light is used as a catalyst.</p><heading>Film Forming Method</heading><p num="0083">The epoxy resin composition of the present
invention used in this method is dissolved in an organic
solvent and used in the form of a coating solution. With a
coating thickness of as small as several µm, an ordinary
fine coating device such as a roll coater, a spin coater, a
spray coater, or the like can be used. Alternatively, the
coating solution may be coated on a release sheet to form a
dry film, and the dry film may be bonded to the surface of a
substrate using a laminator or the like to form a film on
the surface of the substrate.</p><p num="0084">A first method of treating the surface of the
substrate in the form of a pattern can be achieved by
selectively irradiating the film with an active energy ray
through a mask having a predetermined pattern and then 
performing development with a developer to remove uncured
portions of the film. Although these basic steps are the
same as the photolithography process, a solvent or a solvent
composition suitable for the film comprising the resin
composition of the present invention must be selected as the
developer. As the developer, any one of aromatic
hydrocarbons, ketones, esters, glycol ethers, and the like,
and mixtures thereof can be used. In order to achieve the
completion of the curing reaction of the film, heating or
active energy ray irradiation is preferably performed as
post-curing after development.</p><p num="0085">A second method of treating the surface of the
substrate in the form of a pattern comprises the first step
(1) of coating the coating solution on the substrate and
drying the coating to form a film, the second step (2) of
irradiating the whole surface with an active energy ray
which accelerates polymerization to cure the film, and the
third step (3) of irradiating the film with a decay active
energy ray to selectively remove a desired portion of the
cured-portion of the film. As the active energy ray for
accelerating polymerization, ultraviolet rays rich in light
at wavelengths from 250 to 480 µm can be used. As the decay
active energy ray, light at wavelengths of 210 µm or less,
an excimer laser, or the like can be used. In the second
method, in order to complete curing of the film, the film is 
preferably heat-treated or irradiated with a polymerizing
active energy ray in any one of the steps.</p><p num="0086">As described above, the epoxy resin composition of
the present invention is useful as a water repellent agent
or water repellent coating material applied to a surface
which may come into contact with a solution or a material
containing a component such as a polar organic solvent,
which deteriorates the adhesion of the water repellent agent.
The epoxy resin composition can also be used for water
repellent and ink repellent treatment of the discharge
orifice surface of the liquid-jet recording head.</p><heading>Examples</heading><p num="0087">The present invention is described in further
detail below with reference to examples and comparative
examples. In the description below, "%" represents a
percent by mass unless otherwise specified. Examples of the
construction of the resin composition of the present
invention are described below. In the description below, a
ratio-represents a ratio by mass of a solid content, and
resin A-1 represents the above-described resin example.</p><heading>Composition Example 1</heading><p num="0088">Resin A-1:Optomer AP-170 = 96:4 (used in Example 1
below)</p><heading>Composition example 2</heading><p num="0089">Resin A-1:Optomer AP-170 = 94:6 (used in Example 2
below)</p><heading>Composition Example 3</heading><p num="0090">Resin A-1:0ptomer AP-170:1,4-bis(2-hydroxyhexafluoroisopropyl)benzene
= 95:5:25 (used in
Example 3 below)</p><heading>Composition Example 4</heading><p num="0091">Resin A-1:Optomer AP-170:1,4-bis(2-hydroxyhexafluoroisopropyl)benzene:2,2-bis(4-glycidyloxyphenyl)hexafluoropropane
= 80:5:25:25 (used in
Example 4 below)</p><heading>Examples 1 to 4</heading><p num="0092">Each of Composition Examples 1 to 4 was added to
diethylene glycol dimethyl ether as a solvent and dissolved
therein to form a 30% to 40% solution. Then, each of the
prepared solutions was applied to a silicon wafer substrate
having a 5-µm thick thermally oxidized film by means of a
spinner to have a thickness of 1 to 3 µm in a wet state.
Then, the substrate was dried on a hot plate at 110°C for 5
minutes to remove the solvent. Then, the substrate was
irradiated with ultraviolet rays to an accumulated dose of 2
J/cm<sup>2</sup> by means of an ultraviolet ray irradiation apparatus
using a high-pressure mercury lamp. Thereafter, the
substrate was heated in a furnace at 150°C for 15 minutes to 
complete the curing reaction. The thus-formed four
substrates were measured as described below.</p><heading>T1: Measurement of contact angle</heading><p num="0093">The static contact angle of the cured film of each
of the substrates was measured using pure water, a 10%
aqueous solution of oleic acid, a 20% aqueous solution of
glycerin, and a 1% aqueous solution of a surfactant
(polyoxyethylene nonyl phenyl ether; HLB = 10) at room
temperature.</p><heading>T2: Measurement of contact angle after immersion in a water
dispersion of dye</heading><p num="0094">Each of the substrates having the cured films was
immersed in an aqueous solution (pH = 10.3) containing 5%
carbon black and 1% styrene/acrylic acid copolymer at 60°C
for 7 days. Then, each of the substrates was cleaned with
pure water and then dried, and the contact angle of an ink
was measured again by the same method as the above-described
measurement T1.</p><heading>T3: Long-term printing durability</heading><p num="0095">As shown in Figs. 4A to 4C, positive type
photoresist (trade name ODUR-1010, produced by Tokyo Ohka
Kogyo Co., Ltd.) was coated to a thickness of 13 µm on a
substrate 401 to be treated; the substrate had been
previously provided with discharge energy generating
elements 402, by spin coating to form a resist layer 403, as 
shown in Fig. 4C. Then, an epoxy resin composition having
the composition shown in Table 1 was deposited to a
thickness of 25 µm as a flow path forming material 501 on
the resist layer 403, as shown in Fig. 5A.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Construction of Epoxy Resin Composition</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Composition</entry><entry align="center">Parts by mass</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cyclic epoxy resin (EHPE3150, Daicel Chemical Co., Ltd.)</entry><entry align="center">95</entry></row><row><entry align="left">NUC silane coupling agent A-187 (produced by Nippon Uniker Co., Ltd.)</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Optomer SP-170 (produced by Asahi Denka Kogyo Co., Ltd.)</entry><entry align="center">2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diethylene glycol dimethyl ether</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0096">After the flow path forming material layer 501 was
deposited, it was dried at 80°C on a hot plate for 3 minutes.
Then, a solution of each of Examples 1 to 4, respectively
containing Composition Examples 1 to 4, was coated on the
deposited layer by spin coating to form a film 502, as shown
in Fig. 5B. The thus-formed first (501) and second (502)
photosensitive resin layers were exposed to ultraviolet rays
of 1.0 J/cm<sup>2</sup> through a mask having the pattern of a discharge 
orifice portion using Canon mask analyzer MPA600, heat-treated
at 90°C for 4 minutes, and then immersed in a
developer containing MIBK and xylene at a ratio of 2:3 to
form discharge orifices 503 (Fig. 5C). Then, as shown in
Fig. 6A, an ink supply port 601 was formed at the back of
the Si substrate 401 by anisotropic etching, and, as shown
in Fig. 6B, the resist layer 403 was finally removed.
Furthermore, the first (501) and second (502) photosensitive
resin layers were heat-treated at 200°C for 1 hour for the
purpose of completely curing the layers to-complete nozzles.</p><p num="0097">The thus-obtained nozzles were incorporated into
an ink-jet recording head and electrically wired in a
predetermined manner. The ink-jet recording head was
mounted in a printer, and a long-term printing durability
test was conducted using an ink-jet ink comprising pure
water, glycerin, food black 2 (water-soluble black dye), and
N-methylpyrrolidone at a ratio of 70:15:3:12 (parts by mass).</p><p num="0098">The printing durability test was conducted by
printing a document and a pattern for evaluation of ink
landing precision on 100 sheets of paper. Finally, the
distortion of the printed dots was observed by referring to
a sample print. The results are shown in column T3-1 in
Table 2.
<sl><li>Rank A: Dot positions were not replaced, and printed
characters were clear. </li><li>Rank B: Dot positions were slightly replaced, and printed
characters were only slightly affected by the displacement.</li><li>Rank C: Dot positions were considerably replaced, and
clarity of printed characters was poor.</li><li>Rank D: A considerable number of dots were missing, and
printed characters were of a poor quality.</li></sl></p><p num="0099">In addition, the surface of each of the recording
heads used was observed after the test to evaluate ink
adhesion. The results are shown in column T3-2 in Table 2.
Rank A: Ink droplets were scarcely observed on the nozzle
surface.
<sl><li>Rank B: Small ink droplets were observed on the nozzle
surface.</li><li>Rank C: Large ink droplets were observed near the discharge
port of the nozzle.</li></sl></p><heading>Comparative Example 1</heading><p num="0100">Each of the measurements T1 to T3 was performed by
the same method as in Example 1, except that bisphenol AF
(the structure below), which is a fluorine-containing epoxy
resin, was used in place of the epoxy resin of Example 1.
<img id="img-00370001" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00370001.tif" inline="no" he="34"/></p><heading>Comparative Example 2</heading><p num="0101">Instead of the epoxy resin composition used in the
present invention, Flurorad TM FC-722 (fluoro-coating agent,
produced by Sumitomo 3M) was coated on a molded plate of
polyether sulfone using a spinner so that the thickness
after evaporation of the solvent was about 2 µm. Then, the
surface of the resultant coating was treated by drying at
100°C for 30 minutes. Then, this plate was irradiated with
an exicmer laser at a wavelength of 195 µm, which was
converged to a beam diameter of 5 µm, from above to form a
nozzle opening. However, the opening could not be
satisfactorily formed, and a large amount of decomposition
residue was produced at the edge, thereby causing a
nonuniform surface state. Under this condition, a substrate
was formed by the same method as Example 1, and the same
evaluations as T1 to T3 were performed by the same methods
as Example 1. The results are shown in Table 2. <tables><table><tgroup cols="9"><tbody><row><entry nameend="9" namest="1">Results of Evaluation</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="2">T1: Contact angle (°)</entry><entry nameend="7" align="center" namest="6">T2:Immersion Test Contact Angle (°)</entry><entry nameend="9" align="center" namest="8">T3: Long-Term Printing Durability Test</entry></row><row><entry align="left">composition</entry><entry align="center">pure water</entry><entry align="center">oleic acid</entry><entry align="center">glycerin</entry><entry align="center">surfactant</entry><entry align="center">before</entry><entry align="center">after</entry><entry align="center">T3-1</entry><entry align="center">T3-2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 1</entry><entry align="center">97</entry><entry align="center">86</entry><entry align="center">96</entry><entry align="center">91</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">80</entry><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">B</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 2</entry><entry align="center">104</entry><entry align="center">91</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">86</entry><entry align="center">93</entry><entry align="center">81</entry><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">A</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 3</entry><entry align="center">105</entry><entry align="center">95</entry><entry align="center">105</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">95</entry><entry align="center">85</entry><entry align="center">B</entry><entry align="center">A</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example 4</entry><entry align="center">106</entry><entry align="center">98</entry><entry align="center">106</entry><entry align="center">93</entry><entry align="center">98</entry><entry align="center">88</entry><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">A</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comp. Example 1</entry><entry align="center">88</entry><entry align="center">72</entry><entry align="center">87</entry><entry align="center">80</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">74</entry><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="center">C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Comp. Example 2</entry><entry align="center">105</entry><entry align="center">97</entry><entry align="center">108</entry><entry align="center">92</entry><entry align="center">106</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="center">C</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0102">As described above, a film comprising the resin
composition of the present invention exhibits a large
contact angle and excellent durability. Therefore, an ink
would not adhere to the surface of the printing head even if
the surface is held in contact with an ink for a long period
of time so that ink droplets have excellent landing
precision, and a high printing quality could be maintained
for a long period of time.</p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="0103">Each of Composition Examples 1 and 3, respectively
used in Examples 1 and 3, was coated on a molded plate of
polyether sulfone using a spinner so that the thickness 
after evaporation of the solvent was about 2 µm and then
dried. Then, this plate was irradiated with light with a
total of 10 J/cm<sup>2</sup> from a high-pressure mercury lamp to
perform polymerization curing of the film. Then, the plate
was irradiated with an excimer laser at a wavelength of 195
µm, which was converged to a beam diameter of 5 µm, from
above to form a nozzle opening. The opening was
satisfactorily formed, and no decomposition residue was
produced at the edge. As a result, it was found that the
composition of the present invention has excellent
suitability to processing with an ultraviolet laser,</p><p num="0104">As described above, according to the present
invention, there is provided a resin composition suitable as
a water-repellent agent or water-repellent coating material
which can be applied to a surface which is apt to be brought
into contact with a solution or substance containing a
component that can damage the film forming property and
adhesion of the water-repellent agent. Also, according to
the present invention, there is provided a resin composition
permitting surface modifying treatment, thereby making it
possible to maintain in clear state.</p><p num="0105">Furthermore, according to the present invention,
there is provided an ink-jet recording head and liquid-jet
recording apparatus in which the surface of a nozzle can be
maintained in a clear state by treating the substrate with 
the resin composition of the present invention so that ink
would not adhere to the surface of a printing head even if
it is in contact with the ink for a long period of time,
thereby improving the landing precision of dots, and
maintaining a print quality for a long time.</p><p num="0106">While the present invention has been described
with reference to what are presently considered to be the
preferred embodiments, it is to be understood that the
invention is not limited to the disclosed embodiments. On
the contrary, the invention is intended to cover various
modifications and equivalent arrangements included within
the spirit and scope of the appended claims. The scope of
the following claims is to be accorded the broadest
interpretation so as to encompass all such modifications and
equivalent structures and functions.</p><p num="0107">An epoxy resin composition can be used for forming a
film having excellent water-repellency on a substrate
surface. The epoxy resin composition contains (a) an epoxy
resin having at least two alicyclic epoxy groups, at least
one perfluoroalkyl group having 6 to 12 carbon atoms, and at
least one alkylsiloxane group and (b) a cationic
polymerization catalyst. The alicyclic epoxy groups and the
perfluoroalkyl group are present in branched chains of the
epoxy resin, and the alkylsiloxane group is present in the
main chain of the epoxy resin.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An epoxy resin composition comprising an epoxy
resin and a cationic polymerization catalyst, wherein the
epoxy resin has at least two alicyclic epoxy groups, at
least one perfluoroalkyl group having 6 to 12 carbon atoms,
and at least one alkylsiloxane group in its moledule; and
wherein the alicyclic epoxy groups, the perfluoroalkyl group
and the cyclic group are present in branched chains of the
epoxy resin, and the alkylsiloxane group is present in the
main chain of the epoxy resin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The epoxy resin composition according to claim 1,
wherein the epoxy resin is represented by formula (1):

wherein a is an integer from 1 to 50, b is an integer from 1
to 50, c is an integer from 2 to 100, each of n1, n2, n3, n5,
n6 and n7 is an integer from 1 to 5, n4 is an integer from 2
to 200, each of R1, R4, R5, R6, R7, and R10 is independently a
hydrogen atom or a straight or branched alkyl group having 1
to 3 carbon atoms, each of R2, R3, R8 and R9 is independently
a hydrogen atom, a straight or branched alkyl group having 1
to 3 carbon atoms, or a nitrile group, and Rf is a
perfluoroalkyl group having 6 to 12 carbon atoms.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The epoxy resin composition according to claim 1 or
2, wherein the epoxy resin is represented by formula (2):

wherein Rf, n4, a, b, and c are defined according to the
formula (1).</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The epoxy resin composition according to any one of
claims 1 to 3, wherein the cationic polymerization catalyst
comprises an onium salt of a Lewis acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The epoxy resin composition according to any one of
claims 1 to 4, further comprising at least one compound
represented by (3) or (4):

   wherein p is an integer from 0 to 2

   wherein q is an integer from 0 to 2, and
</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A surface treatment method for selectively treating
a surface of a substrate, the method comprising the steps
of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) coating an epoxy resin composition according to any
one of claims 1 to 5 on the surface of the substrate to form
a film;</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) irradiating at least a portion of the film with an
active energy ray; and</claim-text><claim-text>(iii) dissolving at least a portion of the film which
was not irradiated in a liquid capable of dissolving the
film to remove the at least a portion of the film which was
not irradiated.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A surface treatment method for selectively treating
a surface of a substrate, the method comprising the steps
of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) coating an epoxy resin composition according to any
one of claims 1 to 5 on the surface of the substrate to form
a film;</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) curing at least a portion of the film by
polymerizaiton; and</claim-text><claim-text>(iii) removing an uncured portion of the film.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A liquid-jet recording head comprising a discharge
orifice for discharging a liquid, wherein at least the
periphery of the discharge orifice is coated with a cured
film of an epoxy resin composition according to any one of
claims 1 to 5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A liquid-jet recording apparatus comprising a
liquid-jet recording head according to claim 8.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>