<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1528056-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1528056" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34400526" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050504"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1528056-A1" status="new" fvid="24339010"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1528056</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050504</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03078395-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03078395</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031029</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-03078395-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03078395</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031029</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 211/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 211/46        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07D 211/46</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07D211:46</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Deoxynojirimycin Derivate und ihre Verwendung als Glukosesylceramidase-Inhibitoren</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Deoxynojirimycin analogues and their uses as glucosylceramidase inhibitors</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Dérives de desoxynojirimycine et leurs utilisations en tant qu'inhibiteurs de glucosylceramidase</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="WO-1998002161-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998002161</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2002055498-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2002055498</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2004007453-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2004007453</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="E" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2004007454-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2004007454</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="E" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>OVERKLEEFT H S ET AL: "GENERATION OF SPECIFIC DEOXYNOJIRIMYCIN-TYPE INHIBITORS OF THE NON-LYSOSOMAL GLUCOSYLCERAMIDASE" JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY, AMERICAN SOCIETY OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTS, BALTIMORE, MD, US, vol. 273, no. 41, 9 October 1998 (1998-10-09), pages 26522-26527, XP000934220 ISSN: 0021-9258</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>AZ UNIV AMSTERDAM</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ACADEMISCH ZIEKENHUIS BIJ DE UNIVERSITEIT VAN</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Academisch Ziekenhuis bij de Universiteit van Amsterdam</last-name><address><street>Meibergdreef 15</street><city>1105 AZ AMSTERDAM</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>AERTS JOHANNES MARIA FRANCISCU</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AERTS, JOHANNES MARIA FRANCISCUS GERARDUS</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>AERTS, JOHANNES MARIA FRANCISCUS GERARDUS</last-name><address><street>Sandbergstraat 3</street><city>EJ Abcoude</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>van Westenbrugge, Andries</last-name><address><street>Nederlandsch Octrooibureau Postbus 29720</street><city>2502 LS Den Haag</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The invention provides a new class of deoxynojirimycin analogues,
or pharmaceutically acceptable salts thereof which can suitably be used for
the treatment of a disease selected from the group consisting of insulin
resistance, Gauger disease, inflammatory diseases, hyperpigmentation and/or
inflammatory skin conditions, overweight and obesity, lysosomal storage
disorders, fungal diseases, melanoma and other tumors, and microbacterial
infections. The invention further provides a pharmaceutical composition
comprising said deoxynojirimycon analogue, or pharmaceutically acceptable
salt thereof, and a pharmaceutically acceptable carrier.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to deoxynojirimycyin analogues, or
pharmaceutically acceptable salts thereof, that can suitably be used for the
treatment of various diseases in which the synthesis of glucosylceramide and/or
other glucosphingolipids play a role. Such diseases include insulin
resistance (diabetes mellitus type II), obesity and overweight,
glucosphingolipid storage disorders, inflammation, hyperpigmentation and
skin inflammatory conditions, melanoma and other tumors, fungal infections,
viral infections, microbial infections and endotoxins.</p><heading>GLYCOSPHINGOLIPIDS</heading><p num="0002">Glycosphingolipids are denominated as those lipid molecules that comprise a
ceramide moiety linked to a chain of sugars. The ceramide moiety is composed
of one characteristic long chain amino alcohol, mostly D-<i>erythro</i>-C16-sphingosine,
coupled via an amide bond to a fatty acid that may vary in length
and degree of saturation. Several hundreds of specific glycosphingolipids exist
due to variability in their oligosaccharide moiety that differs in number and
nature of sugar units and their glycosidic bonds. Glycosphingolipids are
classified into series such as for example gangliosides and globosides (see
ref.1).</p><p num="0003">For several decades glycosphingolipids have been considered as rather exotic
structures and received little attention in mainstream biochemistry. Their
complex composition and low abundance have limited research efforts to few
pioneering expert groups. Their physiological relevance has largely remained
mysterious since no clear function could be attributed to specific
glycosphingolipids, with exception of those that act as blood group antigen. </p><p num="0004">In the human body glycosphingolipids and their sphingolipid precursor
ceramide occur inside and outside cells. In the epidermis, ceramide and
glucosylceramide molecules are abundantly present as free entities as well as
protein-bound structures and they contribute to the water permeability and
integrity of the skin (see ref.2). Exchange of glycosphingolipids between the
liver, a prominent site of their synthesis, and peripheral tissues is mediated by
lipoproteins which contain significant amount of these lipids. In cells,
glycosphingolipids are more or less exclusively located in the outer leaflet of
the plasma membrane, their oligosaccharide chains being exposed to the
environment. The ceramide lipid backbone provides sphingolipids with special
physical properties (see ref.3). In the presence of cholesterol they can segregate
from the bulk of the membrane phospholipids, aggregating into a more
ordered, but still fluid 'liquid-ordered', domain. Membrane proteins involved in
signalling concentrate in these glycosphingolipid-cholesterol enriched
microdomains (or 'rafts') (see ref.4).</p><p num="0005">The composition of glycosphingolipids at the cell surface may vary with cell
growth, differentiation, viral transformation, ontogenesis and oncogenesis (see
ref.5). It has become clear that gangliosides are particularly abundant in
neuronal cells. As structural components they are essential for the function of
the nervous system. Glycosphingolipids are as components of microdomains
involved in the transduction of a multitude of extracellular signals into the
interior of the cells (see ref.6). Moreover, sphingolipids such as ceramide and
its metabolites sphingosine(-1-phosphate) are thought to play a direct role as
signalling molecules in a variety of cellular processes (see ref.7, 8 and 9).</p><heading>GLYCOSPHINGOLIPID SYNTHESIS AND DEGRADATION</heading><p num="0006">The synthesis and degradation of glycosphingolipids is a complex, multi-step
process taking place in various intracellular compartments (see ref.10 and 11).
The enzymes involved in ceramide biosynthesis are localized on the cytosolic 
leaflet of the endoplasmic reticulum. The biosynthesis starts with the
condensation of the amino acid serine with a palmitoyl coenzyme A by serine
palmitoyl transferase to yield 3-ketosphinganine. Next, this is reduced to D-erythro-sphinganine
by 3-ketosphinganine reductase and subsequently
acylated to dihydroceramide by a N-acyltransferase. Dihydroceramide is
largely desaturated to ceramide by the action of dihydroceramide desaturase.
Further metabolism of ceramide to three distinct categories of sphingolipids
occurs: sphingomyelin, galactosylceramide and derivatives or glucosylceramide
and derivatives. Ceramide is converted to sphingomyelin by the transfer of
phosphorylcholine from the phospholipid phosphatidylcholine on the 1-hydroxyl
group of ceramide. Diacylglycerol is liberated in this reaction.
Sphingomyelin biosynthesis occurs on the luminal part of Golgi membranes
but also other sites have been considered. The synthesis of galactosylceramide
occurs in the lumen of the endoplasmatic reticulum and is catalyzed by a
specific β-galactosyltransferase of which UDP-galactose is the co-substrate.
Galactosylceramide, and its sulphated derivative sulphatide, are only
synthesized in specific cell types. They play for example a crucial role in the
formation and stability of myelin in the central nervous system.
Glucosylceramide is formed by glucosylceramide synthase that is located on
the cytosolic leaflet of the Golgi apparatus. The enzyme uses UDP-glucose as
co-substrate and catalyzes the β-glycosidic linkage of glucose to the 1-position
of ceramide. Glucosylceramide subsequently translocates through the Golgi
membrane to reach the inner leaflet. From here, it can reach the plasma
membrane or can be modified by further glycosylation in the Golgi apparatus.
Lactosylceramide, the common precursor of glycosphingolipids in vertebrates,
is formed by the addition of a galactose moiety from UDP-Gal catalysed by
galactosyltransferase I. Next a variety of glycosphingolipids can be formed by
stepwise glycosylation that is performed by only a few glycosyltransferases of
limited specificity. Like on an assembly line, they transfer carbohydrate- and
sialic acid residues to glycosyl acceptors. A prominent series of 
glycosphingolipids is the ganglio-series. Biosynthesis of complex gangliosides
requires the activity of sialyltransferases I, II and III, GalNac transferase,
galactosyltransferase II and sialyltransferases IV and V.

Degradation of glycosphingolipids occurs in specialised acidic compartments of
cells, the lysosomes. Lysosomal glycosidases, assisted by activator proteins,
sequentially cleave off the sugar residues from the non-reducing end of their
glycolipid substrates and the remaining ceramide is finally hydrolysed by
lysosomal ceramidase to yield free fatty acid and sphingosine. The released
monosaccharides, sialic acids, fatty acids and sphingoid bases can leave the
lysosome and may be used again for biosynthetic purposes. More recently it
has been realized that degradation of glycosphingolipids may also occur
outside lysosomes. For example a non-lysosomal glucosylceramidase has been
discovered that is able to hydrolyse glucosylceramide to ceramide (see ref.12).
The latter enzyme is clearly distinct from the lysosomal glucosylceramidase
(glucocerebrosidase) that is deficient in Gaucher disease patients. The
physiological importance of extra-lysosomal degradation is still poorly
understood, although it seems likely that the associated formation of ceramide
may act as a signal and regulate cell behaviour (see ref.13).</p><heading>GLYCOSPINGOLIPID STORAGE DISORDERS</heading><p num="0007">Glycosphingolipids are continuously synthesized and degraded in cells. A
number of inherited diseases in man are characterized by intralysosomal
glycosphingolipid accumulation. These so called glycosphingolipid storage
disorders are caused by defects in lysosomal degradation (see ref.13).
Examples are GM1 gangliosidosis, Sandhoff disease (GM2 gangliosidosis, type
II or variant O), Tay-Sachs disease (GM2 gangliosidosis, type I or variant B),
Fabry disease (a-galactosyl-lactosylceramidosis), lactosylceramidosis, Gaucher
disease (glucocerebrosidosis). Other sphingolipidoses are multiple sulphatase
deficiency syndrome (mucosulphatidosis), Krabbe disease (global cell 
leukodystrophy, galactocerebrosidosis), Niemann-Pick disease
(sphingomyelinosis, Farber disease (ceramidosis).</p><heading>GAUCHER DISEASE</heading><p num="0008">Gaucher disease is the most frequently encountered lysosomal storage disorder
in man (see ref.14 and 15). In 1882 the clinical features of the disease were
firstly described in detail by the French medical student Philippe C.E.
Gaucher, reporting the presence of large unusual cells in a 32-year old female
with an enlarged spleen. Already at the beginning of the last century it was
suggested that the disease was a familial disorder. In 1934 the primary
storage material in Gaucher disease was finally identified as glucocerebroside
(glucosylceramide). The glycosphingolipid glucocerebroside is the common
intermediate in the synthesis and degradation of gangliosides and globosides.
It has been shown that the primary defect in Gaucher disease is a marked
deficiency in activity of the lysosomal enzyme glucocerebrosidase
(EC. 3.2.1.45) (see ref.16 and 17). Inherited deficiencies in glucocerebrosidase
result in accumulation of its lipid substrate in the lysosomal compartment of
macrophages throughout the body. Three different phenotypes are recognized,
which are differentiated on the basis of the presence or absence of neurological
symptoms. More recently additional phenotypes of Gaucher disease have been
identified. For example, complete deficiency in glucocerebrosidase activity
results in major skin permeability abnormalities with lethal consequences
either prenatally or shortly after birth. The most prevalent variant of the
disease is the non-neuronopathic form, named type 1 Gaucher disease. The age
of onset and clinical manifestations of type 1 Gaucher disease are highly
variable. The most common symptoms include splenomegaly with anaemia and
thrombocytopenia, mostly due to hypersplenism, hepatomegaly and bone
disease. Anaemia may contribute to chronic fatigue. Thrombocytopenia and
prolonged clotting times may lead to an increase in bleeding tendency. Atypical
bone pain, pathological fractures, avascular necrosis and extremely painful 
bone crises may also have a great impact on the quality of life. Type 1 Gaucher
disease is relatively common in all ethnic groups. It is prevalent among
Ashkenazim with a carrier frequency as high as about 1 in 10 and an incidence
of about 1 in 5000. The most common mutation in the glucocerebrosidase gene
of Caucasians, including Ashkenazim, encodes the amino acid substitution
N370S. The heteroallelic presence of the N370S mutation is always associated
with a non-neuronopathic course. It has been demonstrated that the N370S
glucocerebrosidase is normally produced and present in lysosomes. Its catalytic
activity is only severely impaired at pH values above 5.0, illustrating the
subtle nature of the mutation (see ref.18). Most, but not all homozygotes for
the N370S mutation do not develop significant clinical symptoms. Twin studies
and the poor predictive power of phenotype-genotype investigations in
Gaucher disease have clearly pointed out that epigenetic factors also play a
key role in Gaucher disease manifestation (see ref.19 and 20). Although
glucocerebrosidase is present in lysosomes of all cell types, type 1 Gaucher
disease patients solely develop storage of glucocerebroside in cells of the
mononuclear phagocyte system. Macrophages participate in the degradation of
invading microbes, the natural turnover of blood cells and in tissue modelling.
In view of this it is not surprising that in a considerable number of the
lysosomal storage disorders accumulation of storage material also takes
prominently place in tissue macrophages. The type 1 variant of Gaucher
disease is unique with respect to the fact that lysosomal storage occurs
exclusively in macrophages. It is believed that the storage material stems from
the breakdown of exogenous lipids derived from the turnover of blood cells. The
glucocerebroside-loaded cells show a characteristic morphology with a
'wrinkled paper'-like appearance of their cytoplasm which contains lysosomal
inclusion bodies; these cells are referred to as Gaucher cells. In the last
decades it has become apparent that Gaucher cells are not inert containers of
storage material but viable, chronically activated macrophages that contribute
to the diverse clinical manifestations of Gaucher disease. Increased circulating 
levels of several pro-inflammatory cytokines (TNF-alfa, IL-1 beta, IL-6 and IL-8),
the anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10, and M-CSF have been reported (see
ref.21 and 22). It has been hypothesized that cytokine abnormalities may play
a crucial role in the development of common clinical abnormalities in Gaucher
patients such as osteopenia, activation of coagulation, hypermetabolism,
gammopathies and multiple myeloma and hypolipoproteinaemias. More
recently, examination of gene expression profiles by suppressive subtraction
hybridisation analysis of Gaucher and control spleens has led to the
identification of over-expression by Gaucher cells of transcripts for cathepsins
B, K and S (see ref.23). It is of interest to note that osteoclast derived
cathepsin K is prominently involved in osseous type I collagen destruction.
Local release of this cathepsin may contribute to the osteolysis in Gaucher
disease.</p><heading>THERAPY OF GAUCHER DISEASE</heading><p num="0009">Type 1 Gaucher disease has generally been considered to be the most
attractive candidate among the inherited lysosomal storage disorders for
developing effective therapeutic interventions. Firstly, the molecular basis of
the underlying genetic defect had been already established in detail at gene
and protein level. Secondly, just a single cell type, the tissue macrophage, is
primarily implicated in the pathophysiology of the disorder. The rationale for
therapeutic intervention of type 1 Gaucher disease is therefore relatively
simple: correction (or prevention of ongoing formation) of Gaucher cells. This
could either be accomplished by supplementation of macrophages with the
enzyme glucocerebrosidase (enzyme replacement therapy), by reduction of
glycolipid synthesis with specific inhibitors (substrate deprivation or substrate
balancing therapy) or by introduction of glucocerebrosidase cDNA in
haematopoietic progenitors of macrophages (gene therapy). The pioneering
work of Brady, Barranger and co-workers at the National Institutes of Health
(Bethesda, USA) as well as valuable contributions by many others, has led to a 
highly effective treatment of type 1 Gaucher disease based on chronic
intravenous administration of human glucocerebrosidase (see ref.24-26). Three
independent studies of gene transfer to the haematopoietic cells of Gaucher
patients have been conducted but none produced encouraging results (see
ref.27). Low transduction efficiencies of CD34 cells and no sustained
expression of glucocerebrosidase in white blood cells have contributed to this.
The development of gene therapy strategies to correct haematological and
genetic disorders has been hampered by the low levels of gene transfer into
human stem cells using vectors derived from oncoretroviruses.</p><heading>SUBSTRATE REDUCTION THERAPY</heading><p num="0010">An alternative approach for therapeutic intervention of type 1 Gaucher and
other glycosphingolipidoses is substrate deprivation (also termed substrate
reduction) therapy. Radin and coworkers firstly formulated the challenging
concept (see ref.28). The approach aims to reduce the rate of glycosphingolipid
biosynthesis to levels which match the impaired catabolism. It is conceived
that patients who have a significant residual lysosomal enzyme activity could
gradually clear lysosomal storage material and therefore should profit most
from reduction of substrate biosynthesis (see ref.29).</p><p num="0011">Two main classes of inhibitors of glycosphingolipid biosynthesis have presently
been described, both of which inhibit the ceramide-specific glucosyltransferase,
(also termed glucosylceramide synthase; GIcT-1; UDP-glucose: N-acylsphingosine
D-glucosyl-transferase, EC 2.4.1.80). The enzyme catalyses
the transfer of glucose to ceramide, the first step of the biosynthesis of
glucosphingolipids. The first class of inhibitors is formed by analogues of
ceramide. The prototype inhibitor is PDMP (D, L-threo-1-phenyl-2-decanoylamino-3-morpholino-1-propanol).
More specific and potent analogues
have been subsequently developed based on substituting the morpholino group
for a pyrrolodino function and by substitutions at the phenyl group: 4-hydroxy-1-phenyl-2-palmitoylamino-3-pyrrolidono-1-propanol 
(p-OH-P4) and
ethylenedioxy-1-phenyl-palmitoylamino-3-pyrrolidino-1-propanol (EtDo-P4)
(see ref.30). Studies in a knock out mouse model for Fabry disease have shown
that oral administration of the compounds can result in a marked reduction of
the accumulating glycosphingolipid globotriaosylceramide (see ref.31).</p><heading>IMINOSUGARS</heading><p num="0012">The second class of inhibitors of glucosylceramide synthase is formed by N-alkylated
iminosugars. Such type of compounds were already in common use
as inhibitors of N-glycan processing enzymes and the potential application of
N-butyldeoxynojirimycin as HIV inhibitor had been studied in AIDS patients.
Platt and Butters at the Glycobiology Institute in Oxford were the first to
recognize the ability of N-butyldeoxynojirimycin to inhibit glycosylceramide
synthesis at low micromolar concentrations (see ref.32). The same researchers
demonstrated in knock out mouse models of Tay-Sachs disease and Sandhoff
disease significant reductions in glycosphingolipid storage in the brain (see
ref.33). Preclinical studies in animals and the previous clinical trial in AIDS
patients have indicated (transient) adverse effects in the gastrointestinal tract,
probably related to the ability of NB-DNJ to inhibit disaccharidases on the
intestinal brush border. Animal studies have shown that the galactose
analogue N-butyldeoxygalactonojirimycin (NB-DGJ) may have the same
therapeutic efficacy as N-butyldeoxygalactonojirimycin (NB-DNJ) but does not
cause gastrointestinal side effects (see ref.34). Overkleeft and coworkers in
their search for inhibitors of glucosidases have serendipitously developed a
more potent inhibitor of glucosylceramide synthase. N-Adamantane-1yl-methoxypentyl-deoxynojirimycin
(AMP-DNM) was found to inhibit
glycosphingolipid biosynthesis at nanomolar concentrations (see ref.35) and
able to prevent globotriaosylceramide accumulation in a Fabry knock out
mouse model without overt side effects. </p><p num="0013">The first clinical study of the use of N-butyldeoxynojirimycin (NB-DNJ) to
treat a glycosphingolipid storage disorder has been reported recently (Cox et
al. 2000). In an open-label phase I/II trial 28 adult type 1 Gaucher patients
received three times daily 100 mg NB-DNJ (OGT918; Oxford GlycoSciences).
Improvements in visceromegaly and haematological abnormalities as well as
corrections in plasma levels of glucosylceramide and biomarkers of Gaucher
disease activity have been described, although the extent of the response is
less spectacular than generally observed with high dose enzyme replacement
therapy. As expected, a dose-response relationship is demonstrable for NB-DNJ
in type 1 Gaucher patients. It was recently reported that administration
of three times daily 50 mg NB-DNJ is far less effective (see ref.37). Very
recently the EMEA (the European pendant of the FDA) has registered NB-DNJ
(Zavesca, Oxford GlycoSciences) for treatment of type 1 Gaucher patients
that are unsuitable to receive enzyme replacement therapy.</p><heading>IMINOSUGARS AND OTHER THERAPEUTIC APPLICATIONS</heading><p num="0014">Iminosugars are polyhydroxylated alkaloids that are structural mimics of
monosaccharides, where a nitrogen atom replaces the ring oxygen. Examples
of iminosugars have been described, for instance, in WO 98102161. As
transition charge-state analogues iminosugars may act as inhibitors of
enzymes catalyzing the removal or addition of sugars ('glycoconjugate-processing
enzymes'). Deoxynojirimycins which are close structural mimics of
glucose have been found to be inhibitors of glycoprotein processing alfa-glucosidases
I and II. Some N-alkylated deoxynojirimycins, like N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin,
have been evaluated as anti-viral (HIV) therapeutics with
limited clinical success, despite proven efficacy using in vitro models for viral
infectivity (see ref.38). Presently nonyl-deoxy-galactonojirimycin and N-7-oxanonyl-6-Me-deoxygalactonojirimycin
is investigated with regard to
therapeutic value for hepatitis virus infections. Other N-alkylated
deoxynojirimycins, like N-hydroxyethyl-deoxynojirimycin (Miglitol, Glyset) 
have been developed for inhibition of intestinal glycosidases. It is assumed
that reduction of activity of intestinal glycosidases is beneficial for individuals
suffering from insulin resistance (diabetes mellitus type II) since it would
buffer the uptake of monosaccharide from food complex carbohydrates.
Another use of iminosugars in drug development for metabolic control is in the
modification of N-linked oligosaccharides on cell-surface proteins to reduce
tumour-cell metastasis (see ref.39).</p><p num="0015">It has now been found that abnormal metabolism and abnormal concentrations
of glycosphingolipids are associated with a variety of pathological conditions
ranging from insulin resistance (diabetes mellitus type II), overweight and
obesity, lysosomal storage disorders, inflammation, to hyperpigmentation and
skin inflammatory conditions. Moreover, it has been found that
glycosphingolipids play an important role in viral, microbial and fungal
infections and sensitivity to some endotoxins. We believe that correction of
glycosphingolipid metabolism and reduction of excessive glycosphingolipids by
administration of carefully selected alkylated iminosugars may result in
beneficial responses in such pathological conditions. A prerequisite for the
success of such approach is however that the administered compound is
effective and well tolerated. It has also been found that iminosugars are able to
interfere not only with activity of glucosyltransferases such as
glucosylceramide synthase but also with that of various other enzymes
(intestinal and other cell surface glycosidases, lysosomal and endosomal
glycosidases, glycogen debranching enzyme, and glycoprotein modification
glycosidases). Successful therapeutic application of iminosugars therefore
requires specificity of biological activities. Essential is insight in the precise
nature of glycoconjugate-processing enzyme targets that should be inhibited by
a therapeutic iminosugar as well those that should not be inhibited. It forms
the basis for developing tailor-made therapeutic iminosugars for different
pathological conditions. The presently available iminosugars, however, are far 
from optimal. Firstly, they are not well bioavailable and relatively poor
inhibitors of glucosylceramide synthase. Secondly, they are relatively strong
inhibitors of beneficial enzyme activities and consequently cause unacceptable
side effects when administered at higher dose. Improvement is therefore
required at two different levels: 1, the design and synthesis of novel alkylated
iminosugars; and 2, selection of optimal alkylated iminosugars using
appropriate criteria of inhibitory activity for each pathological condition.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0016">The present invention relates to a particular class of novel alkylated
iminosugar derivates that can suitably be used for the treatment of various
diseases in which the synthesis of glucosylceramide and/or other
glycosphingolipids play a role.</p><p num="0017">Accordingly the present invention relates to a deoxynojirimycin
analogue, or a pharmaceutically acceptable salt thereof, having the general
structure (1)
<img id="img-00120001"  orientation="unknown"  wi="70"  img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="52"/>
wherein

R<sub>1</sub>-R<sub>5</sub> each independently comprise H or (CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub>CH<sub>3</sub> or X;

R<sub>6</sub> comprises H, CH<sub>2</sub>OH or CH<sub>2</sub>OX;

M is 0 or 1;

N is 0-9;

a, b, c, d, e are chiral centra having an R or S configuration;
 
and X comprises a large hydrophobic moiety and a spacer, whereby the
hydrophobic moiety is linked through the spacer to the nitrogen atom or
carbon atom concerned, and wherein the large hydrophobic moiety is derived
from a polycyclic alcohol containing three or more rings each sharing two or
more carbon atoms with another ring and is capable of inserting in lipid
bilayers.</p><p num="0018">With respect to pyrrolidines (m = 0) three (R<sub>6</sub> = H) or four (R<sub>6</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub>OH,
CH<sub>2</sub>OX, see Figure 2) chiral centra can be discerned. With respect to
piperidines (m = 1) four (R<sub>6</sub> = H) or five (R<sub>6</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub>OH, CH<sub>2</sub>OX) chiral centra
can be discerned. Depending on the nature and stereochemistry of the
individual chiral centra b, c, d and e the pyrrolidines and piperidines mimic
natural pentoses (in case R<sub>6</sub> = H) and hexoses (R<sub>6</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub>OH, CH<sub>2</sub>OX). The
nature of the chiral centrum a (in case R<sub>2</sub> is not H) defines whether the
iminosugar mimics an alpha (a = R) - or a beta (a = S) glycosidic linkage.
Specific examples of the deoxynojirimycin analogues according to the present
invention are listed below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1"><u style="single">Pyrrolidines</u> (R<sub>6</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub>OH or CH<sub>2</sub>OX, m = 0)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = R, b = S, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-ribofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = S, b = S, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-ribofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = R, b = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-arabinofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = S, b = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-arabinofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = R, b = S, d = S, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-xylofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = S, b = S, d = S, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-xylofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = R, b = S, d = R, e = S</entry><entry align="left">alpha-L-lyxofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = S, b = S, d = R, e = S</entry><entry align="left">beta-L-lyxofuranoside mimic</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1"><u style="single">Pyrrolidines</u> (R<sub>2</sub> = H, R<sub>6</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub>OH or CH<sub>2</sub>OX, m = 0) </entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-1-deoxyribofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-1-deoxyribofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-1-deoxyarabinofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-1-deoxyarabinofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, d = S, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-1-deoxyxylofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, d = S, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-1-deoxyxylofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, d = R, e = S</entry><entry align="left">alpha-L-1-deoxylyxofuranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, d = R, e = S</entry><entry align="left">beta-L-1-deoxylyxofuranoside mimic</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1"><u style="single">Piperidines</u> (R<sub>6</sub>= H, m = 1)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = S, b = S, c = S, d = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-xylopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = R, b = S, c = S, d = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-xylopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = S, b = R, c = S, d = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-lyxopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = R, b = R, c = S, d = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-lyxopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = S, b = S, c = S, d = S</entry><entry align="left">beta-L-arabinopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = R, b = S, c = S, d = S</entry><entry align="left">alpha-L-arabinopyranoside mimic</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1"><u style="single">Piperidines</u> (R<sub>2</sub> = H, R<sub>6</sub> = H, m = 1)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, c = S, d = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-1-deoxyxylopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, c = S, d = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-1-deoxyxylopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = R, c = S, d = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-1-deoxylyxopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = R, c = S, d = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-1-deoxylyxopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, c = S, d = S</entry><entry align="left">beta-L-1-deoxyarabinopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, c = S, d = S</entry><entry align="left">alpha-L-1-deoxyarabinopyranoside mimic</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1"><u style="single">Piperidines</u> (R<sub>6</sub> = CH<sub>2</sub>OH or CH<sub>2</sub>OX, m = 1)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = S, b = S, c = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-glucopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = R, b = S, c = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-glucopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = S, b = R, c = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-mannopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = R, b = R, c = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-mannopyranoside mimic </entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = S, b = S, c = R, d = S, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-galactopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = R, b = S, c = R, d = S, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-galacopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = S, b = S, c = R, d = R, e = S</entry><entry align="left">beta-L-idopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">a = R, b = S, c = R, d = R, e = S</entry><entry align="left">alpha-L-idopyranoside mimic</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1"><u style="single">Piperidines</u> (R<sub>2</sub> = H, R<sub>6</sub>= CH<sub>2</sub>OH or CH<sub>2</sub>OX, m = 1)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, c = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-1-deoxyglucopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, c = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-1-deoxyglucopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = R, c = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-1-deoxymannopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = R, c = R, d = R, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-1-deoxymannopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, c = R, d = S, e = R</entry><entry align="left">beta-D-1-deoxygalactopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, c = R, d = S, e = R</entry><entry align="left">alpha-D-1-deoxygalacopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, c = R, d = R, e = S</entry><entry align="left">beta-L-1-deoxyidopyranoside mimic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">b = S, c = R, d = R, e = S</entry><entry align="left">alpha-L-1-deoxyidopyranoside mimic</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0019">The deoxynojirimycin analogues according to the present invention
comprise at least one entity X that comprises a hydrophobic moiety and a
spacer. The entity X can be located at any of the positions Ri, R<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>3</sub>, R<sub>4</sub>, R<sub>5</sub>, R<sub>6</sub>.</p><p num="0020">The spacer and the hydrophobic moiety can suitably be represented by
Z and Y as shown in Figure 1.</p><p num="0021">Preferably, the large hydrophobic moiety is linked to said nitrogen
atom of the deoxynojirimycin by means of a spacer comprising an alkoxy
polyalkylene or polyalkylene chain of from 3 to 8 carbon atoms. More
preferably, the large hydrophobic moiety is derived from a compound selected
from the group consisting of adamantanemethanol, cholesterol, ß-cholestanol,
adamantanol and 9-hydroxyphenanthrene.</p><p num="0022">The word 'spacer' refers to any bivalent moiety or group capable of
linking a hydrophobic group to the N atom of deoxynojirimycine. </p><p num="0023">Preferably the deoxynojirimycin analogues according to the present
invention have the ido-configuration. In particular ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
is a preferred compound.</p><p num="0024">The preparation of the deoxynojirimycin analogues according to the present
invention is exemplified by the following examples.</p><heading><i><u style="single">N</u></i><u style="single">-(adamantane-1-yl-methoxypentyl)-L-</u><i><u style="single">ido</u></i><u style="single">-deoxynojirimycin 4.</u></heading><p num="0025">2,3,4,6-tetra-<i>O</i>-benzyl-L-<i>ido</i>-deoxynojirimycin 1 (Tetrahedron Lett. 44, 3085-3088,
2003) was debenzylated <i>via</i> hydrogenation (H<sub>2</sub>, Pd/C, HCl (aq.), EtOH) to
3, which was condensed with adamantane-1-yl-methoxypentanal 2 (J. Biol.
Chem. 273, 26522, 1998, WO 98102161) under reductive amination conditions
(H<sub>2</sub>, Pd/C, HCl (aq.), EtOH) to afford <i>N</i>-(adamantane-1-yl-methoxypentyl)-L-<i>ido</i>-deoxynojirimycin
4. Purification provided homogeneous target compound 4
in 93% yield as a light yellow syrup (see <b>Figure 2</b>).</p><heading><i><u style="single">N</u></i><u style="single">-(adamantane-1-yl-methoxypentyl)-D-</u><i><u style="single">galacto</u> </i><u style="single">-deoxynojirimycin</u><b><u style="single">7</u></b>.</heading><p num="0026">The synthesis of 7 was accomplished (see Figure 3) following the synthetic
route as outlined above for the ido-congener <b>4</b>, starting form 2,3,4,6-tetra-<i>O</i>-benzyl-D-<i>galacto</i>-nojirimycin
<b>7</b> (Tetrahedron 56, 32, 5819-5834, 2000).</p> <heading><u style="single"><i>C</i>1-beta-(adamantane-1-yl-methoxypentyl-deoxynojirimycin <b>17</b>, <i>N</i>-methyl-<i>C</i>1-beta-(adamantane-1-yl-methoxypentyl)-deoxynojirimycin
<b>18</b> and <i>N</i>-butyl-<i>C</i>1-beta-(adamantane-1-yl-methoxypentyl-deoxynojirimycin
<b>19</b>.</u> </heading> <p num="0027">The synthesis of beta-Cl-alkyldeoxynojirimycin derivatives <b>17, 18</b> and <b>19</b>
commences with the preparation of 5-<i>O</i>-(adamantane-1-methyl)-1-pentynol <b>13</b>
(see <b>Figure 4).</b> Pentyn-1-ol <b>8</b> was fully silylated (nBuLi, TMSCI) followed by
selective deprotection of the silyl-ether (1N HCI) to provide protected acetylene
<b>9</b>. The free alcohol of <b>9</b> was transformed into trifluoromethanesulfonyl ester <b>10</b> 
(trifluoromethanesulfonylchloride, triethylamine). Alkylation of adamantanemethanol
<b>11</b> with <b>10</b> (K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, refluxing CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>) and subsequent removal of the
TMS protective group (sodiummethanolate, MeOH/THF) afforded acetylene <b>13</b>
in 64% overall yield based on <b>8.</b> Nucleophillic addition of the lithiate of <b>13</b>
(prepared by reacting it with butyllithium in THF at -50 °C) to 2,3,4,6-tetra-<i>O</i>-benzyl-D-gluconic-delta-lactone
<b>14</b> (J. Org. Chem., 2531, 1967) afforded
ketoglucoside 15 as an anomeric mixture. Compound 15 was readily, and with
high stereoselectivity, transformed into the fully protected iminosugar 16
using the following three step procedure (Eur. J. Org. Chem. 5, 1185-1189,
1999): 1) reduction to the corresponding diol (NaBH<sub>4</sub>, CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>/MeOH), 2)
oxidation to the diketo compound (Swern oxidation) and 3) double reductive
amination employing ammonium formate and sodium cyanoborohydride
(overall yield based on <b>14</b> was 45%). Palladium-catalysed hydrogenation
afforded iminosugar <b>17</b> (79%), from which the methyl- and butyl homologues
<b>18</b> and <b>19</b> were readily prepared by reductive amination with formaldehyde
<b>(18,</b> 20% yield) and butanal <b>(19,</b> 73% yield), respectively.</p><heading><u style="single">2-<i>O</i>-(adamantane-1-yl-methoxypentyl)-deoxynojirimycin <b>28,</b><i>N</i>-methyl-2-<i>O</i>-(adamantane-1-yl-methoxypentyl)-deoxynojirimycin
<b>29</b> and <i>N</i>-butyl-2-<i>O</i>-(adamantane-1-yl-methoxypentyl)-deoxynojirimycin
<b>30.</b></u></heading><p num="0028">The preparation of 2-O-alkylated deoxynojirimycin derivatives <b>28, 29</b> and <b>30</b>
(see <b>Figure 5</b>) starts with the p-methoxybenzyl-protection of the free alcohol
function in allyl-3,4,6-tri-<i>O</i>-benzyl-ß-D-glucopyranoside <b>20</b> (Tetrahedron:
Asymmetry, 8, 765-774, 1997) and subsequent isomerization/hydrolysis of the
anomeric allyl-group to provide <b>22</b> in 80% over two steps. The hemi-acetal <b>22</b>
was transformed into the orthogonally protected deoxynojirimycin derivative
23 using the following four step procedure: 1) reduction to the corresponding
diol (LiAlH<sub>4</sub>, THF), 2) oxidation to the aldehydoketone (Swern oxidation), 3)
double reductive amination employing ammonium formate and sodium
cyanoborohydride and 4) protection of the resulting secondary amine with the 
benzyloxycarbonyl group (ZCl, K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, 71% over the four steps). Treatment of
<b>23</b> with 2% TFA afforded compound <b>24</b> (99% yield), with the C-2-OH
selectively deprotected for ensuing alkylation. The corresponding alkylating
agent 1-bromo-5-(adamantane-1-yl)methoxypentane <b>26</b> was prepared from
aldehyde 2 through reduction of the aldehyde function to the corresponding
primary alcohol (NaBH<sub>4</sub>, MeOH) followed by bromination under the agency of
PBr<sub>3</sub> (88%, two steps). Alkylation of <b>24</b> was effected by addition of excess <b>26</b>
and treatment with sodium hydride in DMF to furnish <b>27</b> in 83%. Reductive
removal of the Z- and benzyl protective groups in <b>27</b> afforded iminosugar <b>28</b>
(80% yield), from which the methyl- and butyl homologues <b>29</b> and <b>30</b> were
readily prepared by reductive amination with formaldehyde (<b>29</b>, 49% yield)
and butanal (<b>30</b>, 79% yield), respectively.</p><heading><b><i>Spectroscopic data:</i></b></heading><p num="0029"><img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="43" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="29"/><b><i>N</i>-(adamantane-1 -yl-methoxypentyl)-L-<i>ido</i>-deoxynojirimycin</b>
(4): <sup>1</sup>H-NMR (MeOD, 400 MHz): δ 4.01-3.97
(dd, 1H, H6), 3.89 (m, 1H, H2), 3.85-3.70 (m, 3H, H2, H3,
H4), 3.55-3.52 (m, 2H, CH2 spacer), 3.40-3.08 (m, 5H, 2*H1, H5, CH<sub>2</sub> spacer),
2.96 (s, 2H, O-CH<sub>2</sub> methoxy), 1.94 (broad s, 3H, CH adamantyl), 1.77-1.66
(broad dd, 6H, 3*CH<sub>2</sub> adamantyl), 1.63-1.54 (d, 4H, 2*CH<sub>2</sub> spacer), 1.55 (d, 6H,
3*CH<sub>2</sub> adamantyl), 1.45-1.37 (m, 2H, middle CH<sub>2</sub> spacer). MS (ESI): obs. m/z
= 398.2 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>; Calculated MW for C<sub>22</sub>H<sub>39</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>: 397.3.
<img id="img-00180002" orientation="unknown" wi="56" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00180002.tif" inline="no" he="29"/><b>2-<i>O</i>-(adamantane-</b> 1 -yl-methoxypentyl)-<b>deoxy-nojirimycin</b>
(28): <sup>1</sup>H-NMR (MeOD, 400
MHz): δ 3.92-3.84 (2*dd, 2H, 2*H6), 3.72-3.62 (m,
2H, O-CH<sub>2</sub> spacer), 3.57-3.43 (m, 3H, H2, H3,
H4), 3.38-3.36 (m, 2H, O-CH<sub>2</sub> spacer), 3.07 (m, 1H, H5), 2.95 (s, 2H, O-CH<sub>2</sub>
methoxy), 2.89-2.79 (m, 2H, 2*H1), 1.93 (broad s, 3H, CH adamantyl), 1.76-1.65 
(broad dd, 6H, 3*CH<sub>2</sub> adamantyl), 1.62-1.56 (d, 4H, 2*CH<sub>2</sub> spacer), 1.54
(d, 6H, 3*CH<sub>2</sub> adamantyl), 1.45-1.39 (m, 2H, middle CH<sub>2</sub> spacer). MS (ESI):
obs. <i>m</i>/<i>z</i> = 398.2 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>; Calculated MW for C<sub>22</sub>H<sub>39</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>: 397.3.
<img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="58" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="29"/><b><i>N</i>-Methyl-2-<i>O</i>-(adamantane- 1 -yl-methoxypentyl)-deoxy-nojirimycin
(29): <sup>1</sup>H</b>-NMR
(MeOD, 400 MHz): δ 4.13-4.10 (2*broad d,
2H, 2*H6), 3.72-3.64 (m, 2H, O-CH<sub>2</sub> spacer), 3.62-3.48
(m, 3H, H2, H3, H4), 3.42-3.38 (m, 2H, O-CH<sub>2</sub> spacer), 3.09-2.89 (m, 3H,
H5 and 2*H1), 3.01 (s, 3H, N-CH<sub>3</sub>), 2.95 (s, 2H, O-CH<sub>2</sub> methoxy), 1.96 (broad s,
3H, CH adamantyl), 1.78-1.65 (broad dd, 6H, 3*CH<sub>2</sub> adamantyl), 1.62-1.56 (d,
4H, 2*CH<sub>2</sub> spacer), 1.57 (d, 6H, 3*CH<sub>2</sub> adamantyl), 1.48-1.42 (m, 2H, middle
CH<sub>2</sub> spacer). MS (ESI): obs. m/z = 412.2 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>; Calculated MW for
C<sub>23</sub>H<sub>41</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>: 411.3.</p><heading><b><i>N</i>-Butyl-2-<i>O</i>-(adamantane- 1 -yl-methoxypentyl)-deoxy-nojirimycin
(30):</b></heading><p num="0030">MS (ESI): obs. m/z = 454.2 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>; Calculated MW for C<sub>26</sub>H<sub>47</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>: 453.3.
<img id="img-00190002" orientation="unknown" wi="58" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00190002.tif" inline="no" he="30"/><b><i>N</i>-benzyloxycarbonyl-2-<i>O</i>-(adamantane- 1-yl-methoxypentyl)-
3,4,6 -tri- <i>O</i> -benzyldeoxy-nojirimycin
(27):</b><sup>1</sup>H-NMR (CDCl<sub>3</sub>, 400
MHz): δ 7.31- 7.25 (m, 20H, CH Bn), 5.16-5.06
(2H, CH<sub>2</sub> Bn), 4.75-4.49 (2*CH<sub>2</sub> Bn), 4.43-4.31 (2H, CH<sub>2</sub> Bn), 4.14-4.12 (m, 1H,
H5), 4.00-3.97 (dd, 1H, H1 ax or eq), 3.93-3.89 (dd, 1H, H4), 3.67-3.54 (m, 4H,
H2, H3, 2*H6), 3.38-3.31 (m, 5H, H1 ax or eq, 2*O-CH<sub>2</sub> spacer), 2.93 (s, 2H,
CH<sub>2</sub> methoxy), 1.94 (broad s, 3H, CH adamantyl), 1.71-1.62 (broad dd, 6H,
3*CH<sub>2</sub> adamantyl), 1.58-1.52 (m, 10H, 3*CH<sub>2</sub> adamantyl, 2*CH<sub>2</sub> spacer), 1.38-1.33
(m, 2H, middle CH<sub>2</sub> spacer). <sup>13</sup>C-NMR (CDCl<sub>3</sub>, 100 MHz): δ 155.7 (C=O, Z-group), 
138.3, 136.6 (Cq Bn and Z), 128.4-127.4 (CH arom. Bn), 82.4, 79.5, 74.3
(3*CH, C2, C3 and C4), 73.1, 72.9, 72.8, 71.5, 69.0, 68.5, 67.1 (7*CH<sub>2</sub>, 3*CH<sub>2</sub>
Bn, CH<sub>2</sub> Z-group, 2*O-CH<sub>2</sub> spacer, C6), 55.8 (C5), 41.6 (C1), 39.7, 37,2 (2* CH<sub>2</sub>
adamantyl), 34.0 (Cq adamantyl), 29.7, 29.4 (2* CH2 spacer), 28.2 (CH
adamantyl), 22.7 (middle CH<sub>2</sub> spacer). MS (ESI): obs. <i>m</i>/<i>z</i> = 802.4 [M+H]<sup>+</sup>;
824.6 [M+Na]<sup>+</sup>; Calculated MW for C<sub>51</sub>H<sub>63</sub>NO<sub>7</sub>: 801.5.</p><heading>FIELDS OF APPLICATION</heading><heading>1. DIABETES MELLTUS TYPE II (insulin resistance)</heading><p num="0031">The incidence of diabetes mellitus type II is dramatically increasing in the
Western World. The primary underlying defect is an impaired uptake of
glucose from the bloodstream by muscle and adipose tissue as the result of a
reduced sensitivity to mobilize GLUT4 transporters to their cell surface in
response to insulin. It is already known for many years that increased
concentrations of fatty acids in muscle are associated with aberrant glucose
homeostasis. Conversely, the improvements of glucose homeostasis induced by
PPAR gamma agonists and rexinoids are associated with altered partitioning
of fatty acids, i.e. redistribution of fatty acids to adipose tissue and relative
depletion of muscle fatty acid uptake and metabolism. Poorly understood,
however, is the molecular mechanism by which lipotoxicity in the muscle
causes onset and progression of diabetes. Further insight in this matter will
therefore assist in improving/developing medicaments for treating insulin
resistance.</p><heading>MOLECULAR MECHANISM OF LIPOPATHOGENESIS</heading><p num="0032">Research activities on glycosphingolipids and diabetes type II in the
Department of Biochemistry at the Academic Medical Center/University of
Amsterdam has recently led to an unexpected new insight in the
lipopathogenesis of diabetes mellitus type II. The underlying mechanism is
described in detail below. </p><heading>ROLE FOR GLYCOSPHINGOLIPIDS IN ACQUIRED INSULIN
RESISTANCE</heading><p num="0033">A role was hypothesized for (glyco)sphingolipids in the pathogenesis of
diabetes. This thought stems from the ignored fact that palmitate is the
essential building block of the ceramide moiety in sphingolipids: the first step
of their biosynthesis involves the transfer of palmitate to serine, catalyzed by
serine palmitoyltransferase, see Figure 1. The rate of synthesis of
sphingolipids in the liver is highly dependent on the concentration of
palmitate. Importantly, this could be experimentally confirmed for cultured
muscle cells (smooth muscle cells, myoblasts): addition of 0.1, 0.5, 1.0 mM
palmitate in the culture medium led to proportional increases in the synthesis
of glycosphingolipids, as revealed by increased incorporation of radio-labelled
serine in these structures.

This finding prompted a more detailed examination of the possibility that
actually (glyco)sphingolipids mediate the lipotoxicity in muscles that underlies
diabetes. It has recently been evidenced that GM3 (the most simple
ganglioside at the cell surface, see Figure 2) may impair insulin signalling. In
this respect it is observed that the concentration of GM3 at the cell surface
appears to regulate the uptake of glucose in response to insulin by negatively
interfering with multi-clustering of insulin receptors. Moreover, high
concentrations of GM3 are associated with reduced mobilization of GLUT4 to
the cell surface. Conversely, reduction of GM3 is associated with enhanced
insulin sensitivity (see Yamishita et al. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA (2003) 100,
3445-9 Enhanced insulin sensitivity in mice lacking ganglioside GM3; Tagami
et al. (2002) J Biol Chem 277,3085-92 Ganglioside GM3 participates in the
pathological conditions of insulin resistance). We postulate that at obese
conditions, palmitate levels are chronically high and that therefore the
formation of glucosphingolipids in adipocytes as well as muscle cells will occur
at increased rates, favouring insulin resistance. The connection between 
increased concentration of palmitate in muscle as driving force for the
increased local glycosphingolipid synthesis (including GM3) and insulin
resistance (see Figure 3) has not yet been recognised by others.</p><heading>CRUCIAL ROLE OF GLUCOSYLCERAMIDE SYNTHASE</heading><p num="0034">Further it was realised that the concentration of GM3 and other ganglioside
at the cell surface is highly dependent on the activity of glucosylceramide
synthase (the synthesis of glucosylceramide), the rate limiting step in
ganglioside synthesis (see Figure 3). This enzyme catalyzes the formation of
glucosylceramide from ceramide and UDP-glucose. The Km values of both its
substrates (ceramide and UDP-glucose) are in the physiological range. We
show that glucosylceramide synthase is a key regulatory enzyme with respect
to insulin sensitivity. Increases in its activity have been observed and repor
previously in response to inflammatory cytokines (TNF-alfa), steroid
hormones, saturated fatty acid, and viral infection. It has now surprisingly
been found that the changes in glycosphingolipid synthesis have an impact
the promotion of diabetes mellitus type II (see Figure 4). This finding that
lipopathogenesis impacts diabetes type II shows that inhibition of
glucosylceramide synthase activity exerts a beneficial, anti-hyperglycaemic
effect.</p><heading>NOVEL USE OF IMINOSUGAR-BASED INHIBITORS</heading><p num="0035">It has become clear that deoxynojirimycins, a particular category of
iminosugars, are suitable agents to reduce glycosphingolipid synthesis by the
inhibition of the synthesis of glucosylceramide. Further, considerable hands
expertise has been obtained with the safety of iminosugar administration in
man.

N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin has been recently registered as drug for the
treatment of type 1 Gaucher disease. A clinical study, largely undertaken at
the Academic Medical Center in collaboration with the University of 
Cambridge, revealed that the drug is tolerated in the majority of patients, at
least up to 5 years. Despite the fact that glycosphingolipid synthesis is only
very moderately (20-30%) inhibited by 100 mg TID N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin,
some Gaucher patients however develop serious intestinal complaints and
occasionally alarming peripheral neuropathy. At higher doses of N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin
these adverse events occur even more frequently. We
postulate that the poor specificity of N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin with respect to
inhibition of glucosidases and glucosyltransferases contributes to these
undesired side-effects. As shown in Table 1, N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin is also a
very potent inhibitor of intestinal glycosidases. We postulate that this
inhibiting effect results in at least part of the intestinal complaints of patients.
It is an inhibitor of lysosomal alfa-glucosidase and glucocerebrosidase. We
postulate that this effect results in the associated risk for pathological
intralysosomal accumulation of glycogen and glucocerebroside in lysosomes. At
concentrations required to significantly lower GM3 in (pre)diabetic persons,
adverse events will undoubtedly occur when use is made of N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin.</p><heading>DESIGN OF SPECIFIC INHIBITORS AS THERAPEUTIC AGENTS FOR
INSULIN RESISTANCE (DIABETES MELLITUS TYPE II)</heading><p num="0036">N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin (formerly also known
as AMP-DNM) shows a number of attractive features for its use as therapeutic
agent for diabetes mellitus type II: the compound is highly bioavailable when
orally administered; the compound is a potent inhibitor of glucosylceramide
synthase; the compound is metabolically inert and shows no intrinsic cellular
toxicity at doses envisioned during therapy.

However, based on observations made with in vitro enzyme activity assays and
with cultured cells, it appears possible that chronic administration of N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
could also affect other
metabolic pathways. For example, potential inhibition of lysosomal glycosidase 
alfa-glucosidase and of lysosomal glucocerebrosidase following long term
administration of N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin can
not be entirely excluded. This might lead to intralysosomal accumulation
glycogen or glucosylceramide, respectively. Excessive lysosomal storage of
glycogen or glucosylceramide might result in pathology that resembles Pompe
and Gaucher disease, respectively. Furthermore, N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
is also an inhibitor of intestinal sucrase and
as such might cause gastrointestinal complications. A potent inhibition of
intestinal glycosidase would lead to accumulation of osmotic active sugars in
the gastrointestinal lumen and favour enterobacterial growth, both
contributing to spasms and diarrhoea. Such complications would affect
compliance and would reduce application of N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
in practice.

All these considerations led us to search for an iminosugar structure that still
harbours the desired properties of N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
but lacks its unfavourable features with regard to
chronic treatment of insulin-resistant individuals.</p><heading>THE FOLLOWING TWO SELECTION CRITERIA WERE APPLIED:</heading><heading>1. Reduced inhibition of lysosomal glycosidases: β-glucosidase and
glucocerebrosidase.</heading><p num="0037">In this respect it is observed that inhibition of lysosomal glycosidases by an
iminosugar is not desired since it may only increase the risk for pathological
intralysosomal storage of metabolites, mimicking lysosomal storage disorders.</p><heading>2. Lack of inhibition of intestinal glycosidases.</heading><p num="0038">Another approach to intervene in diabetes mellitus type II is based on
buffering the uptake of food-derived saccharide in the gastrointestinal tract by
inhibition of intestinal glycosidases. Synthetic inhibitors of sucrase (Acarbose, 
N-hydroxyethyl-deoxynojirimycin) are based on this concept and are registered
antidiabetic drugs.

N-hydroxyethyl-deoxynojirimycin is the most potent antidiabetic agent of the
sucrase inhibitors (Campbell L, Baker DE &amp; Campbell RK, Ann Pharmacother
2000;34:1291-1301). The big disadvantage of potent synthetic inhibitors of
intestinal glycosidase like N-hydroxyethyl-deoxynojirimycin and Acarbose is,
however, that they can cause inevitably severe intestinal complaints. The
potent intestinal glycosidase inhibitors

N-hydroxyethyl-deoxynojirimycin and Acarbose are therefore not very well
tolerated by many individuals, resulting in a poor compliance and limited
application.

Although N-hydroxyethyl-deoxynojirimycin and Acarbose exert beneficial
effects, we have realised that it is actually questionable whether this is related
to their ability to inhibit intestinal glycosidases. Interestingly, administration
of N-hydroxyethyl-deoxynojirimycin or Acarbose results even in the absence of
carbohydrate-rich food in reduction of blood glucose levels. This is inconsistent
with the presumed mode of therapeutic action of the compounds. It seems
more likely that after uptake in the body N-hydroxyethyl-deoxynojirimycin
and (metabolites of) Acarbose rather act beneficially by inhibiting
glucosylceramide synthase. This implies that inhibition of intestinal
glycosidases is not a prerequisite for their therapeutic effects but only leads to
undesired side effects.</p><p num="0039">Based on the selection criteria described above, ido-configuration of N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
was identified as an
attractive iminosugar for the treatment of insulin-resistance (diabetes mellitus
type II). Table 1 shows that <i>ido</i>- N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin,
as compared to N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin,
is not inhibiting lysosomal glucocerebrosidase and
only poorly inhibits β-glucosidase activity. Furthermore, <i>ido</i>-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin 
is a poor inhibitor of intestinal
glycosidases. Importantly, <i>ido-</i>N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
is still a potent inhibitor of glucosylceramide synthase
when tested on cultured cells (see Table 2).
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1"><b>In vitro IC50 value (uM) for inhibition of:</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Iminosugar</entry><entry align="left">GCsynthase</entry><entry align="left">GIcCer-ase</entry><entry align="left">Alfa-Glu-ase</entry><entry align="left">Sucras e</entry><entry align="left">Maltas e</entry><entry align="left">Lactase</entry></row><row><entry align="left">N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxyno jirimycin</entry><entry align="left">15</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry><entry align="left">0.1</entry><entry align="left">4.5</entry><entry align="left">&gt;25</entry><entry align="left">18</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxyno jirimycin</entry><entry align="left">150</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><b>In vivo IC50 value (uM) for inhibition of:</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Iminosugar</entry><entry align="left">GCsynthase</entry><entry align="left">GlcCer-ase</entry></row><row><entry align="left">N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry><entry align="left">0.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0040">The value of <i>ido</i>-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin as
anti-hyperglycaemic agent was subsequently analysed in animal models
exactly according to the procedures described above for N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin.
For this purpose animals were daily fed 
with <i>ido-</i>N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin at different
concentrations. At a dose of 250 mg <i>ido</i>-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
/kg similar beneficial effects to 25 mg N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
/kg were noted.</p><heading>ROLE OF GLYCOSPHINGOLIPIDS IN OBESITY</heading><p num="0041">We have found that the increasing consumption of animal fat (rich in
palmitate) and simple sugars (mono- and disaccharides) favours
overproduction of glycosphingolipids. High levels of glycosphingolipids inhibit
hormones involved in energy homeostasis, for example insulin. High
glycosphingolipid levels reinforce the misbalance between energy intake and
expenditure and favours ongoing gain of weight and associated co-morbidities.
This novel insight opens a new avenue for therapeutic intervention: the use of
iminosugars that can reduce overproduction of glycosphingolipids in
individuals with overweight and obesity. Accordingly, the deoxynojirimycin
analogues, or pharmaceutically acceptable salts thereof, according to the
present invention can suitably be used for the treatment of overweight and
obesity.</p><heading>SELECTION OF ALKYLATED IMINOSUGARS TO TREAT OVERWEIGHT
AND OBESITY</heading><p num="0042">In particular ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin was
found to be ideally suited compound for this purpose. It is well bioavailable,
show no cellular toxicity at envisioned dosages and are relatively specific
inhibitors of glucosylceramide synthase. The advantage of ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
is that it does not cause
gastrointestinal complaints, a complication caused by most iminosugars. The
absence of such side effects will improve compliance. </p><heading>2. OVERWEIGHT AND OBESITY</heading><p num="0043">Throughout the world, the prevalence of overweight and obesity has taken on
epidemic proportions. In the Netherlands, as elsewhere, there is a steady rise
in the number of individuals suffering from overweight and obesity. While it is
comparable to the situation in other European countries, this increase is less
pronounced than in the United Kingdom and Germany, for example. Most
staggering is the increased prevalence in the United States. On average, 40%
of Dutch adults are overweight, while 10% of the adult population is obese. It
is estimated that 1 to 1.5% of adults suffer from morbid obesity. In 2000 in the
United States 56% of adults were overweight, 20 % obese and 2.3 % morbidly
obese. According to the WHO definition, adults are defined as obese (severely
overweight) if they have a BMI of 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup> or more. Those with a BMI value of
between 25 and 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup> are said to be overweight. The BMI (Body Mass
Index) is defined as an individual's body weight (in kg) divided by the square of
their height (in metres).</p><p num="0044">One of the first consequences of weight gain is insulin resistance, which
disrupts the normal action of insulin. Insulin resistance plays a key role in the
development of metabolic syndrome. This syndrome is characterised by a
number of associated metabolic anomalies such as insulin resistance,
dyslipidaemia (low HDL serum cholesterol, high serum triglycerides, high LDL
serum cholesterol), hypertension, and abdominal obesity. These anomalies in
turn form the basis for the development of disorders such as type II diabetes
mellitus (age-related diabetes) and its complications. Other health risks that
are associated with overweight and obesity are: cardiovascular diseases,
various types of cancer, gall-bladder diseases, arthrosis, respiratory problems,
gout, infertility, menstrual disorders and foetal defects. The greater the
overweight the greater the risk of such comorbidity. Of all these health risks,
the increased prevalence of glucose intolerance and type II diabetes mellitus, is
particularly worrying. In the United States this is even occurring in children. </p><p num="0045">Recent studies revealed that about 60% of obese children (5-17 years) showed
additional risk factors for cardiovascular disease. Glucose intolerance was
observed in 25% of 55 obese children (4-10 years) and 21% of 112 teenagers
(11-18 year). In addition, obesity is often accompanied by psychological and
social problems, as well as a reduced quality of life. The morbidity associated
with obesity (and, to a lesser extent, with overweight) leads to numerous
(medicinal) treatments and additional work disability, as well as increased
costs for the health care. It is estimated that in the United States the cost of
health care directly related to overweight and obesity are 6-7% of total, the
indirect costs are estimated to be four-fold higher.</p><heading>3. LYSOSOMAL STORAGE DISORDERS</heading><p num="0046">Inherited disorders characterised by intralysosomal accumulation of
glucosphingolipids (GM1 gangliosidosis, Sandhoff disease (GM2 gangliosidosis,
type II or variant O), Tay-Sachs disease (GM2 gangliosidosis, type I or variant
B), Fabry disease (a-galactosyl-lactosylceramidosis), lactosylceramidosis,
Gaucher disease (glucocerebrosidosis) form a large fraction of all diagnosed
inborn of metabolism in the Western World. It has been previously envisioned
that patients suffering from these diseases should benefit from a reduction of
synthesis of the accumulating glucosphingolipids. Recently
N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin has been registered for the treatment of type 1
Gaucher disease by means of so called substrate reduction therapy (SRT).</p><p num="0047">The clinical experience with N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin has learned that the
application of the compound is limited by the poor features of this iminosugar.
N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin is poorly effective since it is only poorly bioavailable
and it is a relatively poor inhibitor of glucosylceramide synthase. On the other
hand, N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin causes serious side effects at higher doses due
to its ability to markedly inhibit lysosomal and intestinal glycosidases. </p><heading>A SPECIFIC DEOXYNOJIRIMYCIN DERIVATIVE FOR SRT OF
GLUCOSPHINGOLIPIDOSES: IDO-N-(5-ADAMANTANE-1-YL-METHOXY-PENTYL)DEOXYNOJIRIMYCIN</heading><p num="0048">We have found that more optimal iminosugars for SRT of glucosphingolipid
storage disorders can be designed. Compounds were selected on the basis of
their potency of inhibiting glucosylceramide synthase and inability to inhibit
activities of lysosomal and intestinal glycosidases. Tables 3 and 4 reveal that
ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin is an ideal
substance that shows superior features compared to N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1"><b>Apparent in vitro IC50 values (uM) for lysosomal glycosidases</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Iminosugar</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Hexosaminidase</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>A-Galactosidase</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>A b-Galactosidase</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Glucocerebrosidase</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>a-Glucosidase</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="left">500</entry><entry align="left">0.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="left">11</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0049">Enzyme activities were measured with appropriate 4-MU substrates using
purified enzymes from spleen. IC50 values for determined by assessment of
the amount of iminosugar required for 50% inhibition of enzyme activity.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1"><b>In vivo IC50 value for glucosylceramide synthase</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Iminosugar</entry><entry align="left">IC50 (uM)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin</entry><entry align="left">35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin</entry><entry align="left">2.5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0050"><i>In</i> vivo glucosylceramide synthase activity was determined according to the
procedure described in J.Biol.Chem, 273,26522-27 (1998). Briefly, 
glucosylceramide synthase activity was measured by exposing cells to
fluorescent C6-NBD-ceramide complexed to albumin. The conversion of C6-NBD-ceramide
to C6-NBD-glucosylceramide was analysed following
harvesting of cells, lipid extraction and quantitative thin layer
chromatography.</p><heading>4. INFLAMMATORY DISEASES</heading><p num="0051">Inflammation is accompanied by local tissue destruction and associated
clinical symptoms. Chronic inflammation is a particular harmful process. Such
type of inflammation is often driven by chronically activated macrophages.
Various pharmacological agents are used to treat inflammation and chronic
inflammation. However, these agents are either not optimally effective or exert
serious side effects. There is a need for improved anti-inflammatory agents
based on a distinct mode of action.</p><heading>ROLE OF GLYCOSPHINGOLIPIDS IN INFLAMMATION</heading><p num="0052">It has now been found that inflammation, especially chronic inflammation, is
associated with overproduction of glycosphingolipids and that this
overproduction enforces the inflammatory state of macrophages and thus
promotes the cascade of tissue inflammation. Increased glycosphingolipid
levels activate macrophages in two manners. Firstly, excessive degradation of
glucosylceramide by the non-lysosomal glucosylceramidase results in
formation of ceramide that acts as signalling molecule. Moreover, part of the
ceramide is metabolised to diacylglycerol that stimulates PKC. The production
of ceramide and diacylglycerol both favour ongoing activation of macrophages.
Secondly, increased synthesis of glycosphingolipids during inflammation
changes the glycosphingolipid composition of rafts at the cell surface. This
affects normal cell behaviour and promotes inflammatory processes. </p><heading>A NEW CLASS OF ANTI-INFLAMMATORY AGENTS</heading><p num="0053">The above findings allowed us to envision that iminosugars should be useful
anti-inflammatory agents that act via a novel mode of action. Based on the
desired features ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
was selected as ideally suited anti-inflammatory agent. This compound is well
bioavailable, shows no cellular toxicity at envisioned dosages and is well
tolerated. The compound is a potent inhibitors of the non-lysosomal
glucosylceramidase and glucosylceramide synthase, both enzyme activities
that contribute to the severity and chronic nature of inflammation.
Accordingly, the deoxynojirimycin analogues, or pharmaceutically acceptable
salts thereof, can suitable be used for the treatment of inflammatory diseases.</p><heading>5. HYPERPIGMENTATION AND INFLAMMATORY SKIN CONDITIONS
PIGMENTATION</heading><p num="0054">Humans produce two types of the pigment melanin: the brown/black type, or
eumelanin; and the amber/red type, or pheomelanin. Eumelanin is primarily
responsible for the colour seen in skin, hair and eyes. Synthesis of melanin
occurs in specific compartments of specialized cells, the melanosomes of
melanocytes. The pigment is subsequently transferred to the keratinocytes in
the skin.</p><p num="0055">Pigmentation usually increases with age and may be altered by genetic defects
or by acquired diseases. In some cases, this means an increase in
pigmentation (hyperpigmentation); in some cases, it means less colour
(hypopigmentation). Several types of hyperpigmentation occur: 1, freckles; 2,
pregnancy-related hyperpigmentation; 3, hyperpigmentation due to enzymatic
deficiencies; 4, disease-related (post-inflammatory) hyperpigmentation.
Freckles are areas where the melanocytes (pigment-making cells) are more
active and responsive to UV radiation than in neighbouring skin. The
increased pigmentation seen in pregnancy is due to the influence of estrogen, 
progesterone, and melanocyte-stimulating hormone. Hormonally related
hyperpigmentation, such as that occurring in pregnancy, can also show up as a
condition called the mask of pregnancy, or melasma. This is a condition in
which blotches of pigmentation appear on the face or in sun-exposed areas.
Melasma is harmless. The pigment seen in melasma mostly goes away within
several months of delivery. Individuals with a deficiency in the liver enzyme
that metabolizes carotenes may develop a yellow/orange skin colour upon
consumption of large quantities of carrots, peppers, or other yellow/orange
vegetables. Post-inflammatory hyperpigmentation (PIH) is a frequently
encountered problem and represents the sequelae of various cutaneous
disorders as well as therapeutic interventions. This acquired excess of pigment
can be attributed to various preceding disease processes that affect the skin;
these processes include infections, allergic reactions, mechanical injuries,
reactions to medications, phototoxic eruptions, trauma (e.g., burns), and
inflammatory diseases (e.g., lichen planus, lupus erythematosus, atopic
dermatitis, psoriasis and sarcoidosis).</p><heading>POSTINFLAMMATORY HYPERPIGMENTATION</heading><p num="0056">PIH is caused by 1 of 2 mechanisms that result in either epidermal melanosis
or dermal melanosis. The epidermal inflammatory response (i.e., dermatitis)
results in the release and subsequent oxidation of arachidonic acid to
prostaglandins, leukotrienes, and other products. These products of
inflammation alter the activity of both immune cells and melanocytes.
Specifically, these inflammatory products stimulate epidermal melanocytes,
causing them to increase the synthesis of melanin and subsequently to
increase the transfer of pigment to surrounding keratinocytes. Such increased
stimulation and transfer of melanin granules results in epidermal
hypermelanosis. On the contrary, dermal melanosis occurs when inflammation
disrupts the basal cell layer, causing melanin pigment to be released and 
subsequently trapped by macrophages in the papillary dermis, also known as
pigmentary incontinence.

PIH is a universal response of the skin, but it is more common in pigmented,
darker skin. The distribution of the hypermelanotic lesions depends on the
location of the original inflammatory dermatosis. The colour of the lesions
ranges from light brown to black, with a lighter brown appearance if the
pigment is within the epidermis (i.e., epidermal melanosis) and a darker grey
appearance if lesions contain dermal melanin (i.e., dermal melanosis). PIH can
occur with various disease processes that affect the skin. These processes
include allergic reactions, infections, trauma, and phototoxic eruptions.
Common inflammatory diseases that result in PIH include acne, lichen planus,
systemic lupus erythematosus, chronic dermatitis, and cutaneous T-cell
lymphoma, especially erythrodermic variants, psoriasis and sarcoidosis.</p><heading>TREATMENT OF HYPERPIGMENTATION AND INFLAMMATORY SKIN
CONDITIONS WITH DEOXYNOJIRIMYCIN ANALOGUES.</heading><p num="0057">The role of glycosphingolipids in inflammation has been extensively discussed
in the previous section. Importantly, an absolute requirement for melanin
production in melanocytes is the presence of glycosphingolipids like
glucosylceramide. Glycolipid negative melanoma cell lines lacking
glucosylceramide synthase activity differ from their parental cells with normal
glycosphingolipid synthesis by the lack in melanin. Addition of
glycosphingolipid or transfection with glucosylceramide synthase cDNA
restores melanin production, indicating that synthesis of glucosylceramide
(and/or other glycosphingolipids) is essential for melanin production in the
melanosome. The production of glycosphingolipids such as glucosylceramide
seems required for proper sorting of tyrosinase to the melanosomes. </p><p num="0058">It has now been found that overproduction of glycosphingolipids is a key
factor in inflammatory processes in the skin and thus may intrinsically cause
overproduction of melanin (hyperpigmentation). We postulate that
overproduction of glycosphingolipids (as the result of local inflammatory
conditions) causes increased local melanin synthesis (see scheme below).
Inhibitors of glycosphingolipid synthesis, such as the deoxynojirimycin
analogues, according to the present invention, can reduce the excessive
melanin production and associated hyperpigmentation.

Hence, the deoxynojirimycin analogues, or pharmaceutically acceptable salts
thereof, according to the present invention can suitably be used for the
treatment of hyperpigmentation and inflammatory skin conditions.

So far approaches to interfere in melanin production have aimed at other
targets in the process of melanogenesis than glycosphingolipid synthesis.
Many depigmentating agents act as alternative substrates of tyrosinase thus
inhibiting the first enzymatic step in melanin synthesis the conversion of
tyrosine to dopaquinone, leading to the melanin polymer. Although usually
reduces or removes hyperpigmentations quite effectively, it may cause also
cause <i>ochronosis</i> (black speckling in the dermis) in patients with darker skins.
Moreover, hydroquinones have been banned in parts of Europe and all
throughout Asia due to the belief that higher concentrations are carcinogenic.</p><heading>SPECIFIC DEOXYNOJIRIMYCIN ANALOGUES FOR THE TREATMENT
OF HYPERPIGMENTATION AND SKIN INFLAMMATORY PROCESSES</heading><p num="0059">Iminosugars were designed that harbour optimal features for use in skin.
Ceramide and glucosylceramide are important structural components of the
stratum corneum and regulate water permeability of the skin. It is known that
glucosylceramides together with other polar lipids are secreted into the
extracellular space of the stratum corneum by lamellar bodies and are
subsequently processed to ceramides. The lysosomal glucocerebrosidase plays
a role in this process as suggested by the fact that a complete deficiency in this 
enzyme is accompanied by markedly impaired epidermal barrier function.
Iminosugars should therefore not interfere with the crucial generation of
ceramide from glucosylceramide catalysed by lysosomal glucocerebrosidase.
Given this prerequisite, the iminosugar ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
was found to be an ideal compound (Table 5). Ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
is able to inhibit
glucosylceramide synthase activity and reduce melanin production in human
melanocytes.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1"><b>IC50 values (uM) in melanoma cells</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Iminosugar</entry><entry align="left">GC synthase</entry><entry align="left">Non-lysosomal GCase</entry><entry align="left">Lysosomal GCase</entry></row><row><entry align="left">N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin</entry><entry align="left">35</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Nonyl-DNM</entry><entry align="left">0.8</entry><entry align="center">0.003</entry><entry align="left">2.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin</entry><entry align="left">2.5</entry><entry align="center">0.003</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0060">Various iminosugars were analysed with respect to ability to inhibit
glucosylceramide synthase, non-lysosomal glucosylceramidase and lysosomal
glucocerebrosidase in cultured melanoma cells. Inhibition of the two first
enzyme activities is desired whilst inhibition of the latter activity is not.

In vivo glucocerebrosidase activity, non-lysosomal glucosylceramidase activity
and glucosylceramide synthase activity was determined according to the
procedure described in J.Biol.Chem, 273,26522-27 (1998). Briefly, in vivo
glucocerebrosidase and non-lysosomal glucosylceramidase activity was
measured by exposing cells to fluorescent C6-NBD-glucosylceramide
complexed to albumin. The conduritol-B-epoxide sensitive and insensitive
degradation of C6-NBD-glucosylceramide to C6-NBD-ceramide was analysed 
following harvesting of cells, lipid extraction and quantitative thin layer
chromatography. The activity that is inhibited by Conduritol-B-epoxide can be
attributed to glucocerebrosidase and the remainder to the non-lysosomal
glucosylceramidase. In vivo glucosylceramide synthase activity was measured
by exposing cells to fluorescent C6-NBD-ceramide complexed to albumin. The
conversion of C6-NBD-ceramide to C6-NBD-glucosylceramide was analysed
following harvesting of cells, lipid extraction and quantitative thin layer
chromatography.</p><p num="0061">Inhibition of glycosphingolipid synthesis with ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
in the MEB4 culture results in loss of
pigmentation. Two melanoma cultures, one dark pigmented (An) and the other
very lightly pigmented (M14) show a clearly higher content of
glucosylceramide (GlcCer) in the darkly pigmented culture both in the total
cell extract and in a melanosomal fraction.</p><p num="0062">In the melanocyte even within a single culture passage a significant decrease
in pigmentation is found with cells of the lighter and darker skin type upon
exposure to ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin. The
pharmaceutical application of the deoxynojirimycin analogues according to the
invention and will be in post-inflammatory hyperpigmentation and skin
inflammatory conditions. There is strong evidence that when administered
systemically these deoxynojirimycin analogues have strong anti-inflammatory
activity in vivo. They shows attractive pharmacological features (good
bioavailability, lack of metabolism, no adverse toxicological effects upon 2
weeks dosing in animals). Ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
is particularly suited for skin application since it does
not/hardly inhibit lysosomal glucocerebrosidase, a key enzyme activity for skin
integrity. </p><heading>6. MELANOMA AND OTHER TUMORS</heading><p num="0063">Tumor cells contain gangliosides on their surface and actively shed them
whereafter they are taken up by other cells. It has been reported that tumor
gangliosides have immunosuppressive activity, proangiogenic properties and
stimulate growth-factor mediated fibroblast and vascular endothelial cell
proliferation. Increased expression of gangliosides has been associated with
enhanced tumor formation and accelerated progression. Inhibition of
ganglioside biosynthesis may impede tumor progression and/or decrease
metastasis. An iminosugar inhibitor of glucosylceramide synthase (OGT2378)
was shown to exert a marked inhibition of melanoma tumor growth in a mouse
model.</p><heading>DEOXYNOJIRIMYCIN ANALOGUES FOR TREATMENT OF MELANOMA
AND OTHER TUMORS</heading><p num="0064">It has now been found that iminosugars that are potent and specific inhibitors
of glucosylceramide synthase as well as non-lysosomal glucosylceramidase can
reduce tumor growth and/or metastasis. Concomitant inhibition of both
enzyme activities is required for an optimal efficacy.

The deoxynojirimycin analogues according to the present invention harbour all
desired features including a good bioavailability, lack of metabolism and
toxicity. Therefore, the deoxynojirimycin analogues, or pharmaceutically
acceptable salts thereof, according to the present invention can suitable be
used for the treatment of melanoma and other tumors.</p><heading>EXPERIMENTAL DATA</heading><p num="0065">Various iminosugars were analysed with respect to ability to inhibit
glucosylceramide synthase, non-lysosomal glucosylceramidase and lysosomal
glucocerebrosidase in cultured melanoma cells. Inhibition of the two first
enzyme activities is desired whilst inhibition of the latter activity is not. <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1"><b>IC50 values (uM) in melanoma cells</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Iminosugar</entry><entry align="left">GC synthase</entry><entry align="left">Non-lysosomal GCase</entry><entry align="left">Lysosomal GCase</entry></row><row><entry align="left">N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin</entry><entry align="left">35</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Nonyl-DNM</entry><entry align="left">0.8</entry><entry align="center">0.003</entry><entry align="left">2.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin</entry><entry align="left">2.5</entry><entry align="center">0.003</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0066">In vivo glucocerebrosidase activity, non-lysosomal glucosylceramidase activity
and glucosylceramide synthase activity was determined according to the
procedure described in J.Biol.Chem, 273, 26522-27 (1998). Briefly, <i>in vivo</i>
glucocerebrosidase and non-lysosomal glucosylceramidase activity was
measured by exposing cells to fluorescent C6-NBD-glucosylceramide
complexed to albumin. The conduritol-B-epoxide sensitive and insensitive
degradation of C6-NBD-glucosylceramide to C6-NBD-ceramide was analysed
following harvesting of cells, lipid extraction and quantitative thin layer
chromatography. The activity that is inhibited by Conduritol-B-epoxide can be
attributed to glucocerebrosidase and the remainder to the non-lysosomal
glucosylceramidase. In vivo glucosylceramide synthase activity was measured
by exposing cells to fluorescent C6-NBD-ceramide complexed to albumin. The
conversion of C6-NBD-ceramide to C6-NBD-glucosylceramide was analysed
following harvesting of cells, lipid extraction and quantitative thin layer
chromatography.</p><heading>ANIMAL MODEL TO MONITOR EFFICACY OF SELECTED
DEOXYNOJIRIMYCIN ANALOGUES.</heading><p num="0067">Ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin can be
administered orally in the powdered chow. Use can be made of C57BL/6 mice 
injected intradermally with MEB4 cells, asubline of B16 murine melanoma
cells (Riken Cell Bank, Saitama, Japan). Mice can be examined for tumor
formation and size three times weekly. Tumor size can be measured in three
dimensions using callipers and tumor volume can be estimated using the
formula a x b x c/2 (Weiss et al. 2003. Cancer Research 63, 3654-8).</p><heading>7. FUNGAL DISEASES</heading><p num="0068">It has been recently become apparent that pathogenic fungi possess an enzyme
homologous to the human glucosylceramide synthase. Glucosylceramides are
produced selectively during hyphal growth and are concentrated in the cell
membrane adjacent to the growth tip. Inhibition of hyphal growth has been
observed following exposure of fungi to an analogue of ceramide that is known
to inhibit glucosylceramide synthase activity.</p><p num="0069">It has now been found that carefully selected hydrophobic iminosugars are
more potent and well tolerated inhibitors of glucosylceramide synthase.
Selection of an iminosugar that specifically interferes with fungal
glucosylceramide synthase activity and only poorly affects the endogenous
human glucosylceramide synthase can be employed to combat life-threatening
fungal infections. Such infections constitute a growing problem in the clinic.
Selected iminosugars could be used in combination with recombinant human
chitotriosidase, a chitinase that attacks the cell wall at the growth tip of fungal
hyphae. Accordingly, the deoxynojirimycin analogues, or pharmaceutically
acceptable salts thereof, according to the present invention can suitably be
used for the treatment of fungal diseases.</p><heading>8. VIRAL INFECTIONS</heading><p num="0070">Iminosugars have been investigated as agents for the treatment of viral
infections. Studies with N-butyldeoxynojirimycin to treat infection with HIV,
the causative agent of AIDS, have been conducted. AIDS affects several 
hundred million individuals worldwide. Viral infectivity and syncytium
formation was noted in vitro. Phase II clinical trials with N-butyldeoxynojirimycin
as anti-HIV agent did not render encouraging result. At
required serum concentrations major side effects occurred. Hepatitis B virus
(HBC) infects over 350 million people worldwide and can cause liver disease
and hepatocellular carcinoma. In woodchucks chronically infected with
woodchuck hepatitis virus, a closely related animal model of HBV infection,
treatment with nonyldeoxynojirimycin was found to prevent the secretion of
infectious enveloped virus. Worldwide, more than 100 million people are
chronically infected with the hepatitis C virus (HCV). In the absence of a
vaccine this represents one of the most serious threats to the public health of
developed nations. With an estimated 3.9 million North Americans chronically
infected, hepatitis C is now the leading reason for liver transplantation in the
United States. It causes about 8,000 U.S. deaths annually, a number that is
expected to triple in the next 20 years in the absence of effective intervention.
The iminosugar <i>N</i>-nonyldeoxynojirimycin has shown antiviral activity in
bovine viral diarrhoea virus, an in vitro surrogate model of hepatitis C.</p><p num="0071">It is believed that ER □-glucosidases are responsible for the stepwise removal
of terminal glucose residues from <i>N</i>-glycan chains attached to nascent
glycoproteins. This enables the glycoproteins to interact with the ER
chaperones calnexin and calreticulin, which bind exclusively to
monoglucosylated glycoproteins. Interaction with calnexin is crucial for the
correct folding of some but not all glycoproteins, and inhibitors of the
glucosidases can be used to specifically target proteins that depend on it. The
antiviral activity of deoxynojirimycins is thought to be based on inhibition of
ER □-glucosidases would lead to disruption of the proper folding and transport
of viral envelope glycoproteins and prevent the secretion of infectious
enveloped virus. </p><p num="0072">We postulate, however, that the observed antiviral activity of iminosugars is
not based on inhibition of ER a-glucosidases but rather on inhibition of
synthesis of glucosylceramide and its glycosphingolipid metabolites.
Glycosphingolipid-rich rafts on the surface of the host cell are likely to be of
key importance in fusion and budding of viruses. Manipulation of surface
glycosphingolipid composition will affect these processes.</p><p num="0073">This novel insight renders a new rationale for selection of iminosugars for the
treatment of viral infections. Compounds have to be selected primarily on the
criterion that they are potent inhibitors of glucosylceramide synthase activity.
Furthermore, the compounds should be well bioavailable and well tolerated.
The deoxynojirimycin analogues according to the present invention, in
particular ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin. Hence,
the deoxynojirimycin analogues, or pharmaceutically acceptable salts thereof,
according to the present invention can suitably be used for the treatment of
viral fulfil these criteria. </p><heading>9. MICROBIAL INFECTIONS AND ENDOTOXINS</heading><heading>MUCOSAL INFECTIONS</heading><p num="0074">Mucosal pathogens target sites of infection through specific adherence to host
glycoconjugate receptors. As a consequence, depletion of such receptors from
the cell surface may be expected to inhibit attachment, impair bacterial
colonization and reduce the activation of mucosal inflammation. Inhibitors of
glycosphingolipid synthesis can be used to deplete receptors.
<i>N</i>-butyl-deoxynojirimycin treated mice indeed reduced susceptibility to
experimental urinary tract infection with P-fimbriated <i>E. coli</i> (Svensson et al.
Mol.Microbiol.2003; 47:453-61). The mucosal inflammatory response was
impaired, as shown by reduced chemokine secretion and lower neutrophil
recruitment, and the bacteria colonized the urinary tract less efficiently than
in normal mice. E. coli species which cause urinary tract infections (UTI)
typically have fimbriae with a terminal receptor for the "P" antigen. The P
antigen is a blood group marker which is also found on the surface of cells
lining the perineum and urinary tract. Approximately 75% of the population
expresses the P antigen, and these individuals are particularly susceptible to
UTI's. The P antigen is also found in vaginal and prostatic secretions: these
secreted P antigens are protective in that they bind to the bacterial receptor,
preventing binding of the organism to the surface epithelium. The individuals
most susceptible to UTI are those who express P antigen on their cells and lack
P antigen in their secretions.

Another example forms Helicobacter pylori that causes complex disseminated
gastric inflammation. It has therefore now been found that glycosphingolipids
are also crucial for its firm adhesion to the mucosa. Depletion of gastric
glycosphingolipids by appropriate iminosugars could have great therapeutic
use. </p><heading>ENDOTOXINS</heading><p num="0075">It has further been found that Glycolipid receptors can not only act as the
primary interface between bacteria and their host, but also serve as target for
bacterial virulence factors such as endotoxins. The ganglioside GM1 can act as
a receptor for the B subunits of various AB5 toxins like Cholera toxin (CTX) or
the heat-stable toxin II from <i>Escherichia coli</i> whereas the globotriaoside Gb3
is a receptor for the AB5-toxin Shiga toxin (ST) and some related toxins like
Verotoxin. Prevention of endotoxin binding is of great clinical relevance. For
example, verotoxins are involved in endothelial targeting in the
microangiopathies of hemorrhagic colitis and hemolytic uremic syndrome
(HUS). Inhibitors of glycosphingolipid synthesis could be employed to
intervene in endotoxin-mediated pathology.</p><heading>DEOXYNOJIRIMYCIN ANALOGUES FOR THE TREATMENT OF
MUCOSAL BACTERIAL INFECTIONS AND PREVENTION OF
ENDOTOXIN-MEDIATED PATHOLOGY</heading><p num="0076">The above novel insights renders a rationale for selection of iminosugars for
the treatment of viral infections. Compounds have to be selected primarily on
the criterion that they are potent inhibitors of glucosylceramide synthase
activity. Furthermore, the compounds should be well bioavailable and well
tolerated. The present deoxynojirimycin analogues, in particular Ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin
fulfil these criteria. Hence,
the deoxynojirimycin analogues, or pharmaceutically acceptable salts thereof,
according to the present invention can suitably be used for the treatment of
mucosal bacterial infections ans prevention of endotoxin-mediated pathology. </p><heading>LEGENDS TO THE FIGURES</heading><p num="0077"><dl tsize="9"><dt><b>Figure 1.</b></dt><dd>Design of suitable hydrophobic entities</dd><dt><b>Figure 2.</b></dt><dd>Synthesis of deoxynojirimycin analogue <b>4</b>.</dd><dt><b>Figure 3.</b></dt><dd>Synthesis of deoxynojirimycin <b>7</b>.</dd><dt><b>Figure 4.</b></dt><dd>Synthesis of deoxynojirimycin analogues <b>17, 18</b> and <b>19.</b></dd><dt><b>Figure 5.</b></dt><dd>Synthesis of deoxynojirimycin analogues <b>28, 29</b> and <b>30.</b></dd></dl></p><heading>REFERENCES</heading><p num="0078"><sl><li>1. Kolter T, Proia RL and Sandhoff K. 2002. J. Biol.Chem. 277, 25859-62.
Combinatorial ganglioside biosynthesis.</li><li>2. Wertz PW &amp; van den Bergh B. 1998. Chem. Phys. Lipids 91, 85-96. The
physical, chemical and functional properties of lipids in the skin and other
biological barriers.</li><li>3. Simons K &amp; van Meer G. 1988. Biochemistry 27, 6197-6202. Lipid sorting
in epithelial cells.</li><li>4. Brown DA &amp; London E. 1998. J. Membr. Biol. 164, 103-114. Structure and
origin of ordered lipid domains in biological membranes.</li><li>5. Hakomori S. 1981. A.Rev.Biochem . 50, 733-764. Glycosphingolipids in
cellular interaction.</li><li>6. Huwiler A, Kolter T, Pfeilschifter J &amp; Sandhoff K 2000.
Biochim.Biophys.Acta 1485, 63-99. Physiology and pathophysiology of
sphingolipid metabolism and signaling.</li><li>7. Hannun YA &amp; Obeid LM. 1995. Trends Biochem.Sci.20, 73-77. Ceramide:
an intracellular signal for apoptosis.</li><li>8. Kolesnick R &amp; Kronke M. 1988. Annu.Rev.Physiol.60, 643-665. Regulation
of ceramide production and apoptosis. </li><li>9. van Blitterswijk WJ, van der Luit AH, Veldman RJ, Verheij M, &amp; Borst J.
2003.Biochem J. 2003 Jan 15;369(Pt 2):199-211. Ceramide: second
messenger or modulator of membrane structure and dynamics?</li><li>10. Merrill AH. 2002. J.Biol.Chem. 277, 25843-25846. De novo sphingolipid
biosynthesis: a necessary, but dangerous, pathway.</li><li>11. Sandhoff K &amp; Kolter T. 2003. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci.
358(1433):847-61. Biosynthesis and degradation of mammalian
glycosphingolipids.</li><li>12. Van Weely S, Brandsma M, Strijland A, Tager JM &amp; Aerts JMFG. 1993.
Biochim.Biophys.Acta 1181,55-62. The existence of a non-lysosomal
glucocerebrosidase that is not deficient in Gaucher disease.</li><li>13. Aerts JM, Hollak C, Boot R, &amp; Groener A. 2003. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B
Biol Sci. 358(1433):905-14. Biochemistry of glycosphingolipid storage
disorders: implications for therapeutic intervention.</li><li>14. Barranger JA &amp; Ginns EI. 1989. Glycosylceramide lipidosis: Gaucher
disease. In: Scriver CR, Beaudet AL, Sly WS, Vall D (eds) The metabolic
basis of inherited disease. McGraw-Hill, New York, p 1677-1698</li><li>15. Beutler E &amp; Grabowski GA. 1995. Gaucher's disease. In: Scriver CR,
Beaudet AL, Sly WS, Valle D (eds) The metabolic and molecular bases of
inherited disease. McGraw-Hill, New York, p 2641-2670</li><li>16. Brady RO, Kanfer JN, Bradley RM &amp; Shapiro D. 1966. Demonstration of a
deficiency of glucocerebroside-cleaving enzyme in Gaucher's disease. J Clin
Invest 45, 1112-1115 </li><li>17. Patrick AD. 1965. A deficiency of glucocerebrosidase in Gaucher's disease.
Biochem J 97, 17c-18c</li><li>18. Van Weely S, van den Berg M, Barranger JA, Sa Miranda MC, Tager JM &amp;
Aerts JMFG. 1993. Role of pH in determining the cell-type specific residual
activity of glucocerebrosidase in type 1 Gaucher disease. J Clin Invest 91,
1167-1175</li><li>19.Aerts JM, van Weely S, Boot R, Hollak CE &amp; Tager JM. 1993. Pathogenesis
of lysosomal storage disorders as illustrated by Gaucher disease. J Inherit
Met Dis 16, 288-291</li><li>20. Cox TM, &amp; Schofield JP. 1997. Gaucher's disease: clinical features and
natural history Baillieres Clin.Hematol. 10, 657-689</li><li>21.Aerts JMFG &amp; Hollak CEM. 1997. Plasma and metabolic abnormalities in
Gaucher's disease. Baillieres Clin Haematol 10, 691-709</li><li>22. Cox TM .2001. Gaucher disease: understanding the molecular pathogenesis
of sphingolipidoses. J Inherit Met Dis 24 (suppl 2), 106-121</li><li>23. Moran MT, Schofield JP, Hayman AR, Shi G-P, Young E &amp; Cox TM. 2000.
Pathologic gene expression in Gaucher disease: upregulation of cysteine
proteinases including osteoclastic cathepsin K. Blood 96, 1969-1978</li><li>24. Brady RO.1997. Gaucher's disease: past, present and future. Baillieres Clin
Haematol 10, 621-634 </li><li>25. Barranger JA, &amp; O'Rourke E. 2001. Lessons learned from the development
of enzyme therapy for Gaucher disease J Inherit Met Dis 24 (suppl 2), 89-96</li><li>26. Hollak CEM, Aerts JMFG, Goudsmit ER, Phoa SS, Ek M. van Weely S, von
dem Borne AE &amp; van Oers MH.1995. Individualised low-dose alglucerase
therapy for type 1 Gaucher's disease. Lancet 345, 1474-1478</li><li>27. Richter J &amp; Karlsson S. 2001. Clinical gene therapy in hematology: past
and future. Int. J Hematol 73, 162-169</li><li>28. Radin NS. 1996. Treatment of Gaucher disease with an enzyme inhibitor.
Glycoconj J 13, 153-157</li><li>29. Platt FM, Jeyakumar M, Andersson U, Priestman DA, Dwek RA,
ButtersTD, Cox TM, Lachmann RH, Hollak CEM, Aerts JMFG, Hrebicek
M, Moyses C, Gow I, Elstein D &amp; Zimran A. 2001. J. Inher. Met. Dis. 24,
275-290. Inhibition of substrate synthesis as a strategy for glycolipid
lysosomal storage disease therapy.</li><li>30. Lee L, Abe A &amp; Shayman JA. 1999. J Biol Chem 274, 146662-14665
Improved inhibitors of glucosylceramide synthase.</li><li>31 .Abe A, Gregory S, Lee L, Killen PD, Brady RO, Kulkarni A &amp; Shayman JA.
2000. Reduction of globotriaosylceramide in Fabry disease mice by
substrate deprivation. J Clin Invest 105, 1563-1567</li><li>32. Platt FM, Neises GR, Dwek RA &amp; Butters TD. 1994. N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin
is a novel inhibitor of glycolipid biosynthesis. J Biol Chem
269, 8362-8365 </li><li>33.Jeyakumar M, Butters TD, Cortina-Borja M, Hunnam V, Proia RL, Perry
VH, Dwek RA &amp; Platt FM. 1999. Delayed symptom onset and increased life
expectancy in Sandhoff mice treated with N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin. Proc
Natl Acad Sci USA 96, 6388-6393</li><li>34. Andersson U, Butters TD, Dwek RA &amp; Platt FM. 2000. N-butyldeoxygalactonojirimycin:
a more selective inhibitor of
glycosphingolipid biosynthesis than N-butyldeoxynojirimycin, in vitro and
in vivo. Biochem Pharmacol 49, 821-829</li><li>35. Overkleeft HS, Renkema GH, Neele J, Vianello P, Hung IO, Strijland A,
van den Burg A, Koomen, GJ, Pandit UK &amp; Aerts J. 1998. Generation of
specific deoxynijirimycin-type inhibitors of the non-lysosomal
glucosylceramidase. J Biol Chem 273, 26522-26527</li><li>36. Cox T, Lachmann R, Hollak C, Aerts J, van Weely S, Hrebicek M, Platt F,
Butters T, Dwek R, Moyses C, Gow I, Elstein D &amp; Zimran A. 2000. Lancet.
355(9214):1481-5. Novel oral treatment of Gaucher's disease with N-butyldeoxynojirimycin
(OGT 918) to decrease substrate biosynthesis.</li><li>37. Heitner R, Elstein D, Aerts J, Weely S &amp;Zimran A. 2002. Low-Dose N-Butyldeoxynojirimycin
(OGT 918) for Type I Gaucher Disease. Blood Cells
Mol Dis 28, 127-33</li><li>38. Fischl MA, Resnick L, Coombs R, Kremer AB, Pottage JC Jr, Fass RJ, Fife
KH, Powderly WG, Collier AC, Aspinall RL, et al. The safety and efficacy of
combination N-butyl-deoxynojirimycin (SC-48334) and zidovudine in
patients with HIV-1 infection and 200-500 CD4 cells/mm3. J Acquir
Immune Defic Syndr. 1994 Feb;7(2):139-47. </li><li>39. Goss PE, Reid CL, Bailey D &amp; Dennis JW. 1997. Phase 1B clinical trial of
the oligosaccharide processing inhibitor swainsonine in patients with
advanced malignancies.</li></sl></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>Deoxynojirimycin analogue, or a pharmaceutically acceptable salt
thereof, having the general structure (I)

wherein
R1-R5 each independently comprise H or (CH2)nCH3 or X;
R6 comprises H, CH2OH or CH2OX;
M is 0 or 1;
N is 0-9;
a, b, c, d, e are chiral centra having an R or S configuration;
and X comprises a large hydrophobic moiety and a spacer, whereby the
hydrophobic moiety is linked through the spacer to the nitrogen atom or
carbon atom concerned, and wherein the large hydrophobic moiety is derived
from a polycyclic alcohol containing three or more rings each sharing two or
more carbon atoms with another ring and is capable of inserting in lipid
bilayers.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>Deoxynojirimycin analogue, or a pharmaceutically acceptable salt thereof,
according to claim 1, wherein the large hydrophobic moiety is linked to said
nitrogen atom of the deoxynojirimycin by means of a spacer comprising an
alkoxy polyalkylene or polyalkylene chain of from 3 to 8 carbon atoms.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>Deoxynojirimycin analogue, or a pharmaceutically acceptable salt thereof,
according to claim 1 or 2, wherein the large hydrophobic moiety is derived from
a compound selected from the group consisting of adamantanemethanol,
cholesterol, ß-cholestanol, adamantanol and 9-hydroxyphenanthrene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>Deoxynojirimycin analogue, or a pharmaceutically acceptable salt thereof,
according to any one of claims 1-3, having the ido-configuration.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>Deoxynojirimycin analogue comprising ido-N-(5-adamantane-1-yl-methoxy-pentyl)deoxynojirimycin,
or a pharmaceutically acceptable salt thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>Deoxynojirimycin analogue according to any one of claims 1-5 for use in
the treatment of a disease involving increased levels of glucosylceramide and
glucosphingolipids.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>Deoxynojirimycin analogue according to any one of claims 1-5 for use in
the treatment of a disease involving increased levels of glucosylceramide,
glucosphingolipids and glucosidases.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>Dexynojirimycin analogue according to claim 6 for use in the treatment of
Gaucher disease.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>Dexynojirimycin analogue according to claim 6 for use in the treatment
of an inflammatory disease.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>Dexynojirimycin analogue according to claim 6 for use in the treatment of
hyperpigmentation and/or inflammatory skin conditions.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>Dexynojirimycin analogue according to claim 6 for use in the treatment
of a fungal disease.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>Dexynojirimycin analogue according to claim 6 for use in the treatment
of overweight and obesity.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>Dexynojirimycin analogue according to claim 6 for use in the treatment of
lysosomal storage disorders.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>Dexynojirimycin analogue according to claim 6 for use in the treatment of
melanoma and other tumors.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>Dexynojirimycin analogue according to claim 6 for use in the treatment of
a microbacterial infection.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>Dexynojirimycin analogue according to claim 7 for use in the treatment
of insulin resistance.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>Pharmaceutical composition comprising a deoxynojirimycon analogue,
or pharmaceutically acceptable salt thereof, according to any one of claims 1-5
and a pharmaceutically acceptable carrier.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>Method of treatment of an individual suffering from a disease selected
from the group consisting of insulin resistance, Gauger disease, inflammatory
diseases, hyperpigmentation and/or inflammatory skin conditions, overweight
and obesity, lysosomal storage disorders, fungal diseases, melanoma and other
tumors, and microbacterial infections, comprising administrating to said
individual an effective amount of the pharmaceutical composition according to
claim 17.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>