<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1493597-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1493597" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="33435391" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050105"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1493597-A1" status="new" fvid="24238590"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1493597</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050105</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04102693-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04102693</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040614</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-61022403-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>61022403</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030630</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C   1/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B60C   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 297/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 297/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/04        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/36        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L   9/00        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L   9/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L   9/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  53/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  53/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60C   1/00H</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B60C   1/00J</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F 297/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  53/02+B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  53/02+B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L   9/06+B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08K3:04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08K3:36</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L9:00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L9:06</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Luftreifenkomponente enthaltend eine Gummidreikomponentenzusammensetzung und Kieselsäure</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Pneumatic tire having a component containing a rubber triblend and silica</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Pneu avec un composant contenant un composition ternaire a base de caoutchouc et de la silice</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0738613-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0738613</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0747426-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0747426</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1035164-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1035164</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-20030114577-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20030114577</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5087668-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5087668</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5872179-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5872179</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>JOURNAL OF THE AMERICAN CHEMICAL SOCIETY vol. 60, 1930, page 304</text><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GOODYEAR TIRE &amp; RUBBER</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>THE GOODYEAR TIRE &amp; RUBBER COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>THE GOODYEAR TIRE &amp;amp; RUBBER COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1144 East Market Street</street><city>Akron, Ohio 44316-0001</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KAES CHRISTIAN</name><address><country>LU</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>THIELEN GEORGES MARCEL VICTOR</name><address><country>LU</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WEYDERT MARC</name><address><country>LU</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KAES, CHRISTIAN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>THIELEN, GEORGES MARCEL VICTOR</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WEYDERT, MARC</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KAES, CHRISTIAN</last-name><address><street>10A, rue Geischleid</street><city>9184 Schrondweiler</city><country>LU</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>THIELEN, GEORGES MARCEL VICTOR</last-name><address><street>49 Rue GD Charlotte</street><city>4995 Schouweiler</city><country>LU</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WEYDERT, MARC</last-name><address><street>17, Rue Mathias Goergen</street><city>8028 Strassen</city><country>LU</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kutsch, Bernd</last-name><address><street>Goodyear S.A., Patent Department, Avenue Gordon Smith</street><city>7750 Colmar-Berg</city><country>LU</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The invention is directed to a pneumatic tire having a component comprising a
vulcanizable rubber composition comprising, based on 100 parts by weight of
elastomer (phr),
<sl><li>(A) from 35 to 65 phr of a solution polymerized styrene-butadiene
rubber with a styrene content of from 38 to 50 percent by weight and a Tg of
from -22°C to -10°C;</li><li>(B) from 10 to 35 phr of an emulsion or solution polymerized styrene-butadiene
rubber with a styrene content of from 20 to 40 percent by weight and
a Tg of from -55°C to -28°C;</li><li>(C) from 10 to 35 phr of polybutadiene; and</li><li>(D) from 10 to 100 phr of silica.</li></sl></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">Background of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0001">It is highly desirable for tires to have good wet skid resistance, low rolling
resistance, and good wear characteristics. It has traditionally been very difficult
to improve a tire's wear characteristics without sacrificing its wet skid resistance
and traction characteristics. These properties depend, to a great extent, on the
dynamic viscoelastic properties of the rubbers utilized in making the tire.</p><p num="0002">In order to reduce the rolling resistance and to improve the treadwear
characteristics of tires, rubbers having a high rebound have traditionally been
utilized in making tire tread rubber compounds. On the other hand, in order to
increase the wet skid resistance of a tire, rubbers which undergo a large energy
loss have generally been utilized in the tire's tread. In order to balance these
two viscoelastically inconsistent properties, mixtures of various types of
synthetic and natural rubber are normally utilized in tire treads. For instance,
various mixtures of styrene-butadiene rubber and polybutadiene rubber are
commonly used as a rubbery material for automobile tire treads.</p><p num="0003">ESBR/silica systems give rise to tread compounds with excellent
tear/tensile properties, good wet performance, but tend to be deficient in rolling
resistance and wear properties. Mid-styrene SSBR silica systems give rise to
tread compounds with excellent wet/rolling resistance/wear balance, but they
tend to be somewhat deficient in tear/tensile properties.</p><heading><u style="single">Summary and Detailed Description of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0004">The present invention is directed to a pneumatic tire having a component
comprising a vulcanizable rubber composition according to claim 1.</p><p num="0005">One component of the rubber composition is from 35 to 65 phr of a
solution polymerized styrene-butadiene rubber with a styrene content of from 38
to 50 percent by weight and a Tg of from -22°C to -10°C, expressed as the Tg
midpoint for the non-oil extended polymer. Suitable solution polymerized
styrene-butadiene rubbers may be made, for example, by organo lithium
catalyzation in the presence of an organic hydrocarbon solvent. Suitable
solution polymerized styrene-butadiene rubbers are available commercially,
such as Enichem R74509; Dow SLR 6610; Nippon Zeon NS 412; Sumitomo
SE8529; and the like.</p><p num="0006">Another component of the rubber composition is from 10 to 30 phr of an
emulsion or solution polymerized styrene-butadiene rubber with a styrene 
content of from 20 to 40 percent by weight and a Tg of from -55°C to -28°C. By
emulsion polymerization prepared E-SBR, it is meant that styrene and 1,3-butadiene
are copolymerized as an aqueous emulsion. Such are well known to
those skilled in such art. Suitable emulsion or solution polymerized styrene-butadiene
rubbers are available commercially, such as (ESBR:) SBR1712;
SBR1502; 31% Styrene ESBR; (SSBR:) JSR HPR240E; Asahi Tufdene3330,
Goodyear SLF1216, Goodyear SLF31X22, Dow SLR 6410, and the like.</p><p num="0007">Another component of the rubber composition is from 10 to 35 phr of
polybutadiene. Suitable polybutadiene rubbers may be prepared, for example,
by organic solution polymerization of 1,3-butadiene. The BR may be
conveniently characterized, for example, by having at least a 90 percent cis 1,4-content.
Suitable polybutadiene rubbers are available commercially, such as
Budene® 1207 from Goodyear and the like.</p><p num="0008">The rubber composition may optionally include from 0 to 20 phr of 3,4-polyisoprene
rubber. The 3,4-polyisoprene rubber (3,4-PI) is considered
beneficial for the purpose of enhancing the tire's traction when it is used in a tire
tread composition. The 3,4-PI is more fully described in US-A- 5,087,668.</p><p num="0009">The phrase "rubber or elastomer containing olefinic unsaturation" is
intended to include both natural rubber and its various raw and reclaim forms as
well as various synthetic rubbers. In the description of this invention, the terms
"rubber" and "elastomer" may be used interchangeably, unless otherwise
prescribed. The terms "rubber composition", "compounded rubber" and "rubber
compound" are used interchangeably to refer to rubber which has been blended
or mixed with various ingredients and materials.</p><p num="0010">The vulcanizable rubber composition may include from 10 to 100 phr of
silica.</p><p num="0011">The commonly employed siliceous pigments which may be used in the
rubber compound include conventional pyrogenic and precipitated siliceous
pigments (silica), although precipitated silicas are preferred. The conventional
siliceous pigments preferably employed in this invention are precipitated silicas
such as, for example, those obtained by the acidification of a soluble silicate,
e.g., sodium silicate.</p><p num="0012">Such conventional silicas might be characterized, for example, by having
a BET surface area, as measured using nitrogen gas, preferably in the range of
40 to 600, and more usually in a range of 50 to 300 square meters per gram.
The BET method of measuring surface area is described in the <u style="single">Journal of the
American Chemical Society,</u> Volume 60, Page 304 (1930). </p><p num="0013">The conventional silica may also be typically characterized by having a
dibutylphthalate (DBP) absorption value in a range of 100 to 400, and more
usually 150 to 300.</p><p num="0014">The conventional silica might be expected to have an average ultimate
particle size, for example, in the range of 0.01 to 0.05 micron as determined by
the electron microscope, although the silica particles may be even smaller, or
possibly larger, in size.</p><p num="0015">Various commercially available silicas may be used, such as, only for
example herein, and without limitation, silicas commercially available from PPG
Industries under the Hi-Sil trademark with designations 210, 243, etc; silicas
available from Rhodia, with, for example, designations of Z1165MP and
Z165GR and silicas available from Degussa AG with, for example, designations
VN2 and VN3, etc.</p><p num="0016">The vulcanizable rubber composition may include from 5 to 50 phr of
carbon black</p><p num="0017">Commonly employed carbon blacks can be used as a conventional filler.
Representative examples of such carbon blacks include N110, N121, N134,
N220, N231, N234, N242, N293, N299, S315, N326, N330, M332, N339, N343,
N347, N351, N358, N375, N539, N550, N582, N630, N642, N650, N683, N754,
N762, N765, N774, N787, N907, N908, N990 and N991. These carbon blacks
have iodine absorptions ranging from 9 to 145 g/kg and DBP number ranging
from 34 to 150 cm<sup>3</sup>/100 g.</p><p num="0018">The vulcanizable rubber composition may include both silica and carbon
black in a combined concentration of from 20 to 100 phr, in any weight ratio of
silica to carbon black. In one embodiment, the vulcanizable rubber composition
includes both silica and carbon black in approximately the same weight
amounts, i.e., a weight ratio of 1.</p><p num="0019">Other fillers may be used in the rubber composition including, but not
limited to, particulate fillers including ultra high molecular weight polyethylene
(UHMWPE), particulate polymer gels such as those disclosed in US-A-6,242,534;
6,207,757; 6,133,364; 6,372,857; 5,395,891; or 6,127,488, and
plasticized starch composite filler such as that disclosed in US-A- 5,672,639.</p><p num="0020">It may be preferred to have the rubber composition for use in the tire
component to additionally contain a conventional sulfur containing organosilicon
compound. Examples of suitable sulfur containing organosilicon compounds
are of the formula: <st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Z―Alk―S<sub>n</sub>―Alk―Z</st32:che>
in which Z is selected from the group consisting of
<img id="img-00040001" orientation="unknown" wi="142" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif" inline="no" he="29"/>
where R<sup>6</sup> is an alkyl group of 1 to 4 carbon atoms, cyclohexyl or phenyl; R<sup>7</sup> is
alkoxy of 1 to 8 carbon atoms, or cycloalkoxy of 5 to 8 carbon atoms; Alk is a
divalent hydrocarbon of 1 to 18 carbon atoms and n is an integer of 2 to 8.</p><p num="0021">Specific examples of sulfur containing organosilicon compounds which
may be used in accordance with the present invention include: 3,3'-bis(trimethoxysilylpropyl)
disulfide, 3,3'-bis (triethoxysilylpropyl) disulfide, 3,3'-bis(triethoxysilylpropyl)
tetrasulfide, 3,3'-bis(triethoxysilylpropyl) octasulfide, 3,3'-bis(tri-t-butoxysilylpropyl)
disulfide, 2,2'-bis(methoxy diethoxy silyl ethyl)
tetrasulfide, 2,2'-bis(tripropoxysilylethyl) pentasulfide,
3,3'-bis(tricyclonexoxysilylpropyl) tetrasulfide, 3,3'-bis(diphenyl
isopropoxysilylpropyl) tetrasulfide, 18,18'-bis(trimethoxysilyloctadecyl)
tetrasulfide, 18,18'-bis(tripropoxysilyloctadecenyl) tetrasulfide, 4,4'-bis(trimethoxysilyl-buten-2-yl)
tetrasulfide,
3,3'-bis(dimethoxyphenylsilyl-2-methylpropyl) disulfide.</p> <p num="0022">The preferred sulfur containing organosilicon compounds are
3,3'-bis(trimethoxy or triethoxy silylpropyl) sulfides. The most preferred
compounds are 3,3'-bis(triethoxysilylpropyl) disulfide and 3,3'-bis(triethoxysilylpropyl)
tetrasulfide. Therefore, as to formula I, preferably Z is
<img id="img-00040002" orientation="unknown" wi="33" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040002.tif" inline="no" he="32"/>
where R<sup>7</sup> is an alkoxy of 2 to 4 carbon atoms, with 2 carbon atoms being
particularly preferred; alk is a divalent hydrocarbon of 2 to 4 carbon atoms with
3 carbon atoms being particularly preferred; and n is an integer of from 2 to 5
with 2 and 4 being particularly preferred.</p><p num="0023">The amount of the sulfur containing organosilicon compound of formula I 
in a rubber composition will vary depending on the level of other additives that
are used. Generally speaking, the amount of the compound of formula I will
range from 0.5 to 20 phr. Preferably, the amount will range from 1 to 10 phr.</p><p num="0024">It is readily understood by those having skill in the art that the rubber
composition would be compounded by methods generally known in the rubber
compounding art, such as mixing the various sulfur-vulcanizable constituent
rubbers with various commonly used additive materials such as, for example,
sulfur donors, curing aids, such as activators and retarders and processing
additives, such as oils, resins including tackifying resins and plasticizers, fillers,
pigments, fatty acid, zinc oxide, waxes, antioxidants and antiozonants and
peptizing agents. Representative examples of sulfur donors include elemental
sulfur (free sulfur), an amine disulfide, polymeric polysulfide and sulfur olefin
adducts. Preferably, the sulfur-vulcanizing agent is elemental sulfur. The
sulfur-vulcanizing agent may be used in an amount ranging from 0.5 to 8 phr,
with a range of from 1.5 to 6 phr being preferred. Typical amounts of tackifier
resins, if used, comprise 0.5 to 10 phr, usually 1 to 5 phr. Typical amounts of
processing aids comprise 1 to 50 phr. Such processing aids can include, for
example, aromatic, naphthenic, and/or paraffinic processing oils. Typical
amounts of antioxidants comprise 1 to 5 phr. Representative antioxidants may
be, for example, diphenyl-p-phenylenediamine and others, such as, for
example, those disclosed in <u style="single">The Vanderbilt Rubber Handbook</u> (1978), pages
344 through 346. Typical amounts of antiozonants comprise 1 to 5 phr. Typical
amounts of fatty acids, if used, which can include stearic acid comprise 0.5 to 3
phr. Typical amounts of zinc oxide comprise 2 to 5 phr. Typical amounts of
waxes comprise 1 to 5 phr. Typical amounts of peptizers comprise 0.1 to 1 phr.
Typical peptizers may be, for example, pentachlorothiophenol and
dibenzamidodiphenyl disulfide.</p><p num="0025">Accelerators are used to control the time and/or temperature required for
vulcanization and to improve the properties of the vulcanizate. In one
embodiment, a single accelerator system may be used, i.e., primary
accelerator. The primary accelerator(s) may be used in total amounts ranging
from 0.5 to 4, preferably 0.8 to 1.5, phr. In another embodiment, combinations
of a primary and a secondary accelerator might be used with the secondary
accelerator being used in smaller amounts, such as from 0.05 to 3 phr. In
addition, delayed action accelerators may be used which are not affected by
normal processing temperatures but produce a satisfactory cure at ordinary
vulcanization temperatures. Vulcanization retarders might also be used. 
Preferably, the primary accelerator is a sulfenamide. If a second accelerator is
used, the secondary accelerator is preferably a guanidine, dithiocarbamate or
thiuram compound.</p><p num="0026">The mixing of the rubber composition can be accomplished by methods
known to those having skill in the rubber mixing art. For example, the
ingredients are typically mixed in at least two stages, namely, at least one non-productive
stage followed by a productive mix stage. The final curatives
including sulfur-vulcanizing agents are typically mixed in the final stage which is
conventionally called the "productive" mix stage in which the mixing typically
occurs at a temperature, or ultimate temperature, lower than the mix
temperature(s) than the preceding non-productive mix stage(s). The rubber
composition may be subjected to a thermomechanical mixing step. The
thermomechanical mixing step generally comprises a mechanical working in a
mixer or extruder for a period of time suitable in order to produce a rubber
temperature between 140°C and 190°C. The appropriate duration of the
thermomechanical working varies as a function of the operating conditions, and
the volume and nature of the components. For example, the thermomechanical
working may be from 1 to 20 minutes.</p> <p num="0027">The rubber composition may be incorporated in a variety of rubber
components of the tire. For example, the rubber component may be a tread
(including tread cap and tread base), sidewall, apex, chafer, sidewall insert,
wirecoat or innerliner. Preferably, the compound is a tread.</p> <p num="0028">Preferably, the tire is a passenger or truck tire. The tire may also be a
radial or bias, with a radial being preferred.</p> <p num="0029">Vulcanization of the pneumatic tire of the present invention is generally
carried out at conventional temperatures ranging from 110°C to 180°C. Any of
the usual vulcanization processes may be used such as heating in a press or
mold, heating with superheated steam or hot air.</p><p num="0030">The following examples are presented for the purposes of. All parts are
parts by weight unless specifically identified otherwise.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE I</u></heading><p num="0031">In this example, three rubber compounds are compared. Samples 1 and
2 represent control samples typical of the prior art. Sample 3 is representative
of the present invention.</p><p num="0032">The elastomers were compounded with standard amounts of
conventional curatives and processing aids as indicated in Table 1, and cured 
with a standard cure cycle. Cured samples were evaluated for various physical
properties following standard tests protocols as indicated in Table 2.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Compound Recipe</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><u style="single">Sample</u></entry><entry align="center"><u style="single">1</u></entry><entry align="center"><u style="single">2</u></entry><entry align="center"><u style="single">3</u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polybutadiene<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">ESBR, 40% styrene<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">70</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SSBR, 25% styrene<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">70</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SSBR, 46% styrene <!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">55</entry></row><row><entry align="left">ESBR, 25% styrene<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zinc Oxide</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Process Oil</entry><entry align="center">26.5</entry><entry align="center">26.5</entry><entry align="center">26.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Stearic Acid</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Wax</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Silica</entry><entry align="center">86</entry><entry align="center">86</entry><entry align="center">85</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sulfur</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Antidegradants<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Accelerators<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupling Agent<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">13.8</entry><entry align="center">13.8</entry><entry align="center">13.6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Coupling Agent<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alpha-methylstyrene</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><u style="single">Sample</u></entry><entry align="center"><u style="single">Control</u><u style="single">1</u></entry><entry align="center"><u style="single">Control</u><u style="single">2</u></entry><entry align="center"><u style="single">3</u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity</entry><entry align="center">49</entry><entry align="center">56</entry><entry align="center">43</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Shore A</entry><entry align="center">68.5</entry><entry align="center">66.5</entry><entry align="center">63.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rebound 0°C</entry><entry align="center">12.3</entry><entry align="center">7.7</entry><entry align="center">6.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rebound 100°C</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">62</entry><entry align="center">60.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elongation, %</entry><entry align="center">600</entry><entry align="center">376</entry><entry align="center">560</entry></row><row><entry align="left">True Tensile, MPa</entry><entry align="center">123</entry><entry align="center">84</entry><entry align="center">125</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Modulus @ 300%</entry><entry align="center">8.3</entry><entry align="center">14.3</entry><entry align="center">8.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile Strength, MPa</entry><entry align="center">17.6</entry><entry align="center">17.6</entry><entry align="center">18.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tear Strength, N/mm</entry><entry align="center">31.1</entry><entry align="center">15.4</entry><entry align="center">29.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">RPA G' (1 % sw1)</entry><entry align="center">2.821</entry><entry align="center">2.273</entry><entry align="center">2.581</entry></row><row><entry align="left">RPA TD (10% sw2)</entry><entry align="center">0.167</entry><entry align="center">0.119</entry><entry align="center">0.121</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Drum Abrasion (Vol. Loss)</entry><entry align="center">136.6</entry><entry align="center">88.7</entry><entry align="center">113</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0033">As can be seen from Table 2, ESBR/silica systems give rise to tread
compounds with excellent tear/tensile properties, good wet performance, but
tend to be deficient in rolling resistance and wear properties. One such
example of a compound is Sample 1. Mid-styrene SSBR silica systems give
rise to tread compounds with excellent Wet/RR/Wear balance, but they tend to
be somewhat deficient in tear/tensile properties. One example of such a
compound is Sample 2. This disadvantage can be overcome by the use of high
styrene SSBR of Tg -22°C to -10°C. The addition of an additional mid-Tg SBR
(Tg -55°C to -28°C) may be required in order to maintain the G' onset at an
acceptably low temperature. The mid-styrene SBR may also act as a
compatibilizer between the BR phase and the high styrene SSBR.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A pneumatic tire having a component comprising a vulcanizable rubber
composition comprising, based on 100 parts by weight of elastomer (phr),
<claim-text><claim-text>(A) from 35 to 65 phr of a solution polymerized styrene-butadiene
rubber with a styrene content of from 38 to 50 percent by weight and a Tg of
from -22°C to -10°C;</claim-text><claim-text>(B) from 10 to 35 phr of an emulsion or solution polymerized styrene-butadiene
rubber with a styrene content of from 20 to 40 percent by weight and
a Tg of from -55°C to -28°C;</claim-text><claim-text>(C) from 10 to 35 phr of polybutadiene; and</claim-text><claim-text>(D) from 10 to 100 phr of silica.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The pneumatic tire of claim 1, wherein said vulcanizable rubber
composition comprises 50 to 100 phr of silica.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The pneumatic tire of claim 1 or 2, wherein said component is selected
from the group consisting of tread cap, tread base, sidewall, apex, chafer,
sidewall insert, wirecoat and innerliner.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The pneumatic tire of at least one of the previous claims, wherein said
vulcanizable rubber composition further comprises from 5 to 50 phr of carbon
black.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The pneumatic tire of at least one of the previous claims, wherein said
vulcanizable rubber composition comprises silica and carbon black in a
combined concentration of from 20 to 100 phr.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The pneumatic tire of at least one of the previous claims, wherein said
vulcanizable rubber composition comprises silica and carbon black in a
combined concentration of from 20 to 100 phr and a weight ratio of from 0.9 to
1.1, preferably 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The pneumatic tire of claim 1, wherein said vulcanizable rubber
composition further comprises from 0 to 20 phr, preferably 5 to 15 phr, of 3,4-polyisoprene.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>