<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1266930-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1266930" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="19011272" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021218"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1266930-A1" status="new" fvid="23637134"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1266930</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20021218</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02012501-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02012501</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020604</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2001169159-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2001169159</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010605</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  69/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  69/26        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  77/00        20060101CFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  77/10        20060101AFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  69/26</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   3/16+L77/00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Polyamid-Zusammensetzung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Polyamide composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition polyamide</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0285692-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0285692</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0659799-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0659799</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4172194-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4172194</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000078869-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000078869</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KURARAY CO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KURARAY CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kuraray Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>1621 Sakazu</street><city>Kurashiki-shi, Okayama-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HARA TETSUYA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>OKA HIDEAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>SASAKI SHIGERU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HARA, TETSUYA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OKA, HIDEAKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SASAKI, SHIGERU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HARA, TETSUYA</last-name><address><street>628-268, Kami-Tomii</street><city>Kurashiki-city, Okayama, 710-0846</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OKA, HIDEAKI</last-name><address><street>8-6, 3-chome, Kasuga</street><city>Tsukuba-city, Ibaraki, 305-0821</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SASAKI, SHIGERU</last-name><address><street>917-25, Oouchi</street><city>Kurashiki-city Okayama, 710-0817</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VOSSIUS &amp;amp; PARTNER</last-name><address><street>Siebertstrasse 4</street><city>81675 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Provided is a polyamide composition comprising 100 parts by weight
of (A) a semiaromatic polyamide having dicarboxylic acid units mainly
composed of aromatic dicarboxylic acid units and diamine units mainly
composed of aliphatic diamine units having 4 to 14 carbon atoms and
containing not more than 15 µeq/g of terminal amino groups; and 0.01
to 5 parts by weight of (B) a copper compound. The polyamide compositions
of the present invention have excellent heat aging characteristics, as
well as excellent mechanical characteristics, low-water-absorption
property and dimensional stability. The polyamide compositions of the
present invention can be used as molding materials for industrial
materials or household goods and are, especially, suited for a various
article, which is used at a high temperature, such as engine room parts
of an automobile.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a polyamide composition. The
polyamide compositions of the present invention have excellent heat aging
characteristics, as well as excellent mechanical characteristics,
low-water-absorption property and dimensional stability. The polyamide
compositions of the present invention can be used as molding materials.
for industrial materials or household goods. The polyamide compositions
of the present invention are, especially, suited for various articles,
which are used at a high temperature, such as engine room parts of an
automobile.</p><p num="0002">Crystalline polyamides represented by nylon 6 and nylon 66 have been
used widely in fibers for clothing or industrial materials, and as
general-purpose engineering plastics, because they have excellent
thermal properties, physical properties and rigidity with good balance.
Such general-purpose aliphatic polyamides are, however, pointed out to
have problems such as insufficient heat resistance and poor dimensional
stability due to water absorption. Particularly in recent years,
polyamides to be used in the fields of electrical and electronic parts,
automobile parts, and fibers have been requested to have excellent heat
aging characteristics.</p><p num="0003">To meet the above requirements, it has been tried to provide polyamide 
compositions comprising aliphatic polyamides and various stabilizers
such as (i) a copper salt derived from the reaction of a copper halide
and xylenediamine [See US-A-3,639,335], (ii) copper phthalate and an
alkali metal iodide [See US-A-3,457,325] and (iii) a mixture of copper-,
halogen- and phosphorus-containing compounds [See US-A-4,937,276].</p><p num="0004">On the other hand, polyamide compositions comprising a semiaromatic
polyamide, the heat resistance of which is generally better than that
of an aliphatic polyamide, and a copper compound as a stabilizer are
proposed. US-A-5,003,009 discloses impact resistant nylon molding
materials containing (A) a linear, thermoplastic nylon composed of
radicals derived from terephthalic acid, isophthalic acid and
alkanediamines of 4 to 10 carbon atoms, and (B) one or more copolymers
of (i) ethylene, an ester of (meth)acrylic acid and a monomer having
an acidic functional group or a latent acidic functional group, or (ii)
an ester of (meth)acrylic acid , a monomer having an acidic functional
group or a latent acidic functional group and a monomer having 2 or more
olefinic double bonds, and, if required, (c) effective amount of additives
such as antioxidant and stabilizers, e.g. copper (I) halides.
JP-A-228768/95 discloses a polyamide composition comprising (a) a
semiaromatic polyamide having (i) terephthalic acid units and
1,9-nonanediamine units or (ii) terephthalic acid units,
1,9-nonanediamine units and 2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine units, and
having an intrinsic viscosity [η] measured in concentrated sulfric acid
at 30 °C of 0.4 to 3.0 dl/g, (b) a copper compound, (c) an alkali metal
halide and (d) an organic stabilizer. JP-A-228773/95 discloses a
polyamide composition comprising (a) a semiaromatic polyamide having
(i) terephthalic acid units and 1,9-nonanediamine units or (ii) 
terephthalic acid units, 1,9-nonanediamine units and
2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine units, and having an intrinsic viscosity [η]
measured in concentrated sulfric acid at 30 °C of 0.4 to 3.0 dl/g, (b)
a copper compound and (c) a nucleating agent. US-A-5,763,561 discloses
an injection moldable composition comprising (a) a semiaromatic
polyamide containing about 0 to about 40 µeq/g of carboxylic acid
endgroups, said polyamide containing aliphatic diamine units of 4 to
14 carbon atoms and terephthalic acid units; and (b) a copper-containing
thermal stabilizer formulation comprising an alkali metal halide and
a copper (I) halide in a weight ratio of from about 2.5:1 to about 20:1.</p> <p num="0005">It is an object of the present invention to improve the heat aging
characteristics of the known polyamide compositions such as described
above in order to meet the requirement of excellent heat aging
characteristics which are needed for, e.g., engine room parts of an
automobile.</p><p num="0006">This object could be achieved on the basis of studies on the relation
between the number of terminal amino groups of a semiaromatic polyamide
and the heat aging characteristics of the polyamide compositions
comprising said semiaromatic polyamide where it was found that polyamide
compostions having excellent heat aging characteristics can be obtained
from a semiaromatic polyamide containing not more than 15 µeq/g of terminal
amino groups and a copper compound.</p><p num="0007">The present invention provides a polyamide composition, which
comprises 100 parts by weight of (A) a semiaromatic polyamide having
dicarboxylic acid units mainly composed of aromatic dicarboxylic acid
units and diamine units mainly composed of aliphatic diamine units having 
4 to 14 carbon atoms and containing not more than 15 µeq/g of terminal
amino groups; and 0.01 to 5 parts by weight of (B) a copper compound.</p><p num="0008">US-A-5,763,561, described above, shows the number of terminal amino
groups of the polyamide together with the number of terminal carboxyl
groups. However, this patent does not have an intent to improve the
heat aging characteristics of the polyamide compositions by adjusting
the number of terminal amino groups of the semiaromatic polyamide.
US-A-5,003,009, JP-A-228768/95 and JP-A-228773/95, described above, are
all silent with regard to the number of terminal amino groups of the
semiaromatic polyamide. The number of terminal amino groups of the
semiaromatic polyamide described in these 4 documents are, to the
knowledge of the present inventors, about 20 µeq/g [See the polyamide
obtained in the Referential Example 1 and Example 2 of JP-A-228768/95
and the polyamide obtained in the Examples 1 to 3 of JP-A-228773/95]
or more.</p><p num="0009">In addition, a semiaromatic polyamide having (i) terephthalic acid
units and 1,9-nonanediamine units or (ii) terephthalic acid units,
1,9-nonanediamine units and 2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine units are
recited in a lot of patent specification other than JP-A-228768/95 and
JP-A-228773/95. For example, JP-A-316731/95 discloses a conjugated
fiber obtained by (A) a semiaromatic polyamide composed of terephthalic
acid units and alkylenediamine units having 6 to 12 carbon atoms and
(B) thermoplastic polymer incompatible with the semiaromatic polyamide.
However, the number of terminal amino groups of the semiaromatic polyamide
described in these other patent applications are, to the knowledge of
the present inventors, 20 µeq/g or more. For example, the number of
terminal amino groups of the semiaromatic polyamide described in the 
Referential Examples 6 and 7 of JP-A-316731/95 is about 30-40 µeq/g.</p> <p num="0010">The semiaromatic polyamides (A) are ones having dicarboxylic acid
units mainly composed of aromatic dicarboxylic acid units and diamine
units mainly composed of aliphatic diamine units having 4 to 14 carbon
atoms. The dicarboxylic acid units of the semiaromatic polyamides (A)
contain aromatic dicarboxylic acid units in an amount of preferably from
60 to 100 mol %, more preferably from 70 to 100 mol %, and more preferably
from 80 to 100 mol %. On the other hand, the diamine units of the
semiaromatic polyamides (A) contain aliphatic diamine units having 4
to 14 carbon atoms in an amount of preferably from 60 to 100 mol %, more
preferably from 70 to 100 mol %, and more preferably from 80 to 100 mol %.</p> <p num="0011">The aromatic dicarboxylic acid units can include, for example, units
derived from aromatic dicarboxylic acid such as terephthalic acid,
isophthalic acid, 2,6-naphthalenedicarboxylic acid,
2,7-naphthalenedicarboxylic acid, 1,4-naphthalenedicarboxylic acid,
4-phenylenedioxv-diacetic acid, 1,3-phenylenedioxy-diacetic acid,
diphenic acid, 4,4'-oxydibenzoic acid, diphenyl-methane-4,4'-dicarboxylic
acid, diphenylsulfone-4,4'-dicarboxylic
acid and 4,4'-biphenyldicarboxylic acid. The semiaromatic polyamides
(A) may contain one or more types of those aromatic dicarboxylic acid
units. Among them, in view of the production cost and various properties
of the semiaromatic polyamides (A), preferred are terephthalic acid unit,
isophthalic acid unit or 2, 6-naphthalenedicarboxylic acid unit; andmost
preferred is terephthalic acid unit.</p> <p num="0012">The semiaromatic polyamides (A) may contain additional dicarboxylic
acid units other than aromatic dicarboxylic acid units. The additional 
dicarboxylic acid unit can include, for example, units derived from
aliphatic dicarboxylic acids such as malonic acid, dimethylmalonic acid,
succinic acid, glutaric acid, adipic acid, 2-methyladipic acid,
trimethyladipic acid, pimelic acid, 2,2-dimethylglutaric acid,
3,3-diethylsuccinic acid, azelaic acid, sebacic acid and suberic acid;
alicyclic dicarboxylic acids such as 1,3-cyclopentanedicarboxylic acid
and 1,4-cyclohexanedicarboxylic acid. The semiaromatic polyamides (A)
may contain one or more types of those additional dicarboxylic acid units.
The dicarboxylic acid units of the semiaromatic polyamides (A) can contain
such additional dicarboxylic acid unit in an amount of preferably not
more than 40 mol %, more preferably not more than 30 mol %, still more
preferably not more than 20 mol %. The semiaromatic polyamides (A) may
further contain units derived from polyfunctional carboxylic acids such
as trimellitic acid, trimesic acid and pyromellitic acid so long as the
semiaromatic polyamide is melt-moldable.</p><p num="0013">The aliphatic diamine units having 4 to 14 carbon atoms can include,
for example, units derived from linear aliphatic alkylenediamines such
as 1,4-tetramethylenediamine, 1,6-hexanediamine, 1,7-heptanediamine,
1,8-octanediamine, 1,9-nonanediamine, 1,10-decanediamine, 1,11-undecanediamine
and 1,12-dodecanediamine; or branched aliphatic
alkylenediamines such as 2-methyl-1,5-pentanediamine, 3-methyl--1,5-pentanediamine,
2,2,4-trimethyl-1, 6-hexanediamine, 2,4,4-trimethyl-1,6-hexanediamine,
2,4-dimethyl-1,6-hexanediamine, 2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine
and 5-methyl-1,9-nonanediamine. The
semiaromatic polyamides (A) may contain one or more types of those
aliphatic diamine units. Among them, in view of the production cost
and various properties of the semiaromatic polyamides (A), preferred 
are 1,4-tetramethylenediamine unit, 1,6-hexanediamine unit,
1,9-nonanediamine unit, 1,10-decanediamine unit, 1, 12-dodecanediamine
unit, 2-methyl-1,5-pentanediamine unit, 3-methyl-1,5-pentanediamine
unit or 2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine unit; and more preferred are
1,9-nonanediamine unit and/or 2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine unit.</p><p num="0014">The semiaromatic polyamides (A) may contain additional diamine units
other than aliphatic diamine unit having 4 to 14 carbon atoms. The
additional diamine unit can include, for example, units derived from
alicyclicdiamines such as cyclohexanediamine, methylcyclohexanediamine,
bis(4-aminocyclohexyl)methane, bis(aminomethyl)norbornane, bis(aminomethyl)tricylodecane
and bis(aminomethyl)cyclohexane; or
aromatic diamines such as p-phenylenediamine, m-phenylenediamine,
xylylenedlamine, 4,4'-diaminodiphenylsulfone and 4,4'-diaminodiphenylether.
The semiaromatic polyamides (A) may contain one or more
types of those additional diamine units. The diamine units of the
semiaromatic polyamides (A) can contain such additional diamine unit
in an amount of preferably not more than 40 mol %, more preferably not
more than 30 mol %, still more preferably not more than 20 mol %.</p><p num="0015">The semiaromatic polyamides (A) contain terminal amino groups in
an amount of not more than 15 µeq/g, preferably not more than 12 µeq/g,
more preferably not more than 10 µeq/g. A semiaromatic polyamide
containing more than 15 µeq/g of terminal amino groups does not have
satisfactory heat aging characteristics for the purpose of the present
invention and requires a lot of heat stabilizer. Such a lot of heat
stabilizer reduces the mechanical properties of the resulting polyamide
compositions and molded articles obtained therefrom.</p><p num="0016">The semiaromatic polyamides (A) are preferably ones in which at least 
10% of the terminal groups in the molecular chains are blocked with a
terminal-blocking agent such as a monocarboxylic acid and a monoamine,
that is a monofunctional compound having a reactivity with terminal amino
group or terminal carboxyl group of the polyamide. More preferably,
in the molecular chains of the semiaromatic polyamide (A), the ratio
of the terminal groups blocked with a terminal-blocking agent, that is
the percentage of terminal-blocking, is at least 40%, still more
preferably at least 70%. The semiaromatic polyamide (A) , in which the
terminal groups thereof are blocked, gives a polyamide composition having
improved properties such as melt stability and resistance to hot water
or steam. The amount of the terminal-blocking agent is properly set
depending on the various factors such as the molecular weight of the
polyamide, the reactivity of the terminal-blocking agent, boiling point
of the terminal-blocking agent, kind of reaction vessel and reaction
conditions. The amount of the terminal-blocking agent preferably falls
between 0.1 and 15 % by mole relative to the total amount of the dicarboxylic
acid component and the diamine component.</p><p num="0017">The monocarboxylic acids can include, for example, aliphatic
monocarboxylic acids such as acetic acid, propionic acid, butyric acid,
valeric acid, caproic acid, caprylic acid, lauric acid, tridecanoic acid,
myristic acid, palmitic acid, stearic acid, pivalic acid and isobutyric
acid; alicyclic monocarboxylic acids such as cyclohexanecarboxylic acid;
aromatic monocarboxylic acids such as benzoic acid, toluic acid, α
-naphthalenecarboxylic acid, β -naphthalenecarboxylic acid,
methylnaphthalenecarboxylic acid and phenylacetic acid; and mixtures
of any of them. Among them, preferred are acetic acid, propionic acid,
butyric acid, valeric acid, caproic acid, caprylic acid, lauric acid, 
tridecanoic acid, myristic acid, palmitic acid, stearic acid and benzoic
acid, in view of their reactivity and costs and of the stability of the
blocked terminals.</p><p num="0018">The monoamines can include, for example, aliphatic monoamines such
as methylamine, ethylamine, propylamine, butylamine, hexylamine,
octylamine, decylamine, stearylamine, dimethylamine, diethylamine,
dipropylamine and dibutylamine; alicyclic monoamines such as
cyclohexylamine and dicyclohexylamine; aromatic monoamines such as
aniline, toluidine, diphenylamine and naphthylamine; and mixtures of
any of them. Among them, preferred are butylamine, hexylamine,
octylamine, decylumine, stearylamine, cyclohexylamine and aniline, in
view of their reactivity, boiling point and costs and of the stability
of the blocked terminals.</p><p num="0019">Semiaromatic polyamides having reduced number of terminal amino
groups and desired molecular weight can be prepared by (i) using a
terminal-blocking agent in an appropriate molar amount and (ii) setting
the molar ratio, that is the balance of moles, of dicarboxylic acid
component based on the diamine component. It is also important to make
complete a reaction between each functional groups of a terminal-blocking
agent, a dicarboxylic acid component and a diamine component for reducing
the number of terminal amino groups.</p><p num="0020">For example, semiaromatic polyamides (A) can be produced by a method
comprising following steps of (i) forming a nylon salt by mixing a diamine
component and a dicarboxylic acid component, if necessary, together with
a catalyst and/or a terminal-blocking agent; (ii) converting the formed
nylon salt, at the temperature of 200 to 250 °C, into a prepolymer having
intrinsic viscosity [η] of 0.1 to 0.6 dl/g as determined in concentrated 
sulfuric acid at 30 °C and (iii) subjecting the prepolymer to a solid
phase polymerization or polymerization with melt extruder.</p><p num="0021">In the mixing step (i), it is important to use an appropriate molar
amount of a terminal-blocking agent and to use a dicarboxylic acid and
diamine component in an appropriate molar ratio. It is preferred to
adjust the amount of the above-described components to meet the following
equation (1):
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">0.1 ≦ [(X-X)/X] × 100 ≦ 2.0</st32:df>
wherein X means the total amount, expressed in moles, of carboxyl groups
contained in the dicarboxylic acid component, the catalyst and the
terminal-blocking agent, and Y means the total amount, expressed in moles,
of amino groups contained in the diamine component, the catalyst and
the terminal-blocking agent.</p><p num="0022">In step (ii) and (iii), when the intrinsic viscosity [η] of the
prepolymer falls within the range of 0.1 to 0.6 dl/g, polymerization
of the prepolymer proceeds with good retention of a balance between
carboxyl groups and amino groups and with little decrease in the
polymerization rate to give a polyamide having a small molecular weight
distribution, excellent properties and excellent moldability. When the
polymerization of the prepolymer is effected by a solid phase
polymerization, it is preferably carried out under reduced pressure or
under a stream of an inert gas. In addition, at a temperature of 200
to 280 °C, the polymerization proceeds with a high polymerization rate,
good productivity and reduced coloring or gelation. On the other hand,
when the polymerization of the prepolymer is effected with amelt extruder,
it is desirable to employ a polymerization temperature of not more than
370 °C, in view of producing a polyamide with minimum degradation. </p><p num="0023">In step (iii), it is important to make complete a reaction between
all functional groups of a terminal-blocking agent, a dicarboxylic acid
component and a diamine component.</p><p num="0024">In the preparation of the semiaromatic polyamides (A), a
phosphorus-based compound can be used as a catalyst. The
phosphorus-based compound includes, for example, phosphoric acid,
phosphorous acid, hypophosphorous acid, and salts or ester derivatives
thereof such as a salt of (a) phosphoric acid, phosphorous acid or
hypophosphorous acid and (b) a metal of sodium, potassium, magnesium,
vanadium, calcium, zinc, cobalt, manganese, tin, tungsten, germanium,
titanium or antimony; ammonium phosphate, ammonium phosphite, ammonium
hypophosphate; and ethyl esters, isopropyl esters, butyl esters, hexyl
esters, isodecyl esters, octadecyl esters, decyl esters, stearyl esters
or phenyl esters of (a) phosphoric acid, phosphorous acid or
hypophosphorous acid. Of those, preferred are sodium hypophosphite or
phosphorous acid, in view of the reaction rate of polymerization, its
own heat stability and cost.</p><p num="0025">The amount of the phosphorus-based compound preferably falls between
0.01 and 5% by weight, more preferably between 0.05 and 2% by weight,
still more preferably between 0.07 and 1% by weight, relative to the
total amount of the dicarboxylic acid component and the diamine component.</p><p num="0026">The intrinsic viscosity [η] of the semiaromatic polyamide (A) , as
measured in concentrated sulfuric acid at 30 °C, falls preferably between
0.4 and 3.0 dl/g, more preferably between 0.5 and 2.0 dl/g, still more
preferably between 0.6 and 1.8 dl/g, in view of a balance of melt flowability
and moldability. </p><p num="0027">The melting point of the semiaromatic polyamide (A) falls preferably
not less than 250 °C, more preferably between 270 and 330 °C, in view
of mechanical properties of the polyamide due to excellent crystallinity.</p><p num="0028">The polyamide composition of the present invention contains (B) a
copper compound. Copper compounds include, for example, copper halides
such as copper (I) chloride, copper (I) bromide, copper (I) iodide, copper
(II) chloride, copper (II) bromide and copper (II) iodide; inorganic
acid salts of copper such as copper (I) phosphate, copper (II)
pyrophosphate, copper (II) sulfate and copper (II) nitrate; carboxylic
acid salts of copper such as copper (II) acetate; copper complexes such
as copper (II) acetylacetonate. Among them, preferred is a copper (I)
compound, more preferred is a copper (I) halide, and most preferred is
copper (I) iodide. The polyamide composition may contain one or more
types of these copper compound.</p><p num="0029">The amount of copper compound (B) falls between 0.01 and 5 part by
weight, preferably between 0.02 and 0.5 part by weight, based on the
100 part by weight of the semiaromatic polyamide (A).</p><p num="0030">The polyamide composition of the present invention can preferably
contain (C) an alkali metal halide in an amount of 1 to 20 times by weight
of the copper compound (B). Alkali metal halides include, for example,
lithium chloride, lithium bromide, lithium iodide, sodium fluoride,
sodium chloride, sodium bromide, sodium iodide, potassium fluoride,
potassium chloride, potassium bromide and potassium iodide. Among them,
potassium iodide is preferable. The polyamide composition may contain
one or more types of those alkali metal halides. The amount of alkali
metal halide (C) is more preferably between 1 to 15 times by weight of
the copper compound (B). </p><p num="0031">In addition, the alkali metal halide (C) is used in an amount of
preferably from 0.01 to 5 part by weight, more preferably from 0.02 to
5 part by weight, based on 100 part by weight of the semiaromatic polyamide
(A).</p><p num="0032">A copper compound (B) and/or a alkali metal halide (C) can be used
as a solid form or as a solution dissolved in an appropriate solvent
such as water, methanol, ethanol, 2-propanol, 1,4-dioxane,
dimethoxyethane, N,N-dimethylformamide [DMF] and dimethylsulfoxide
[DMSO].</p><p num="0033">The polyamide composition of the present invention can contain (D).
a filler in an amount of not more than 60 % by weight based on the total
weight of the polyamide composition. The fillers include, for example,
fibrous ones such as glass fibers, carbon fibers, boron fibers, aramide
fibers and liquid crystalline polyester fibers; needle-like ones such
as a whisker of potassium titanate, a whisker of calcium carbonate, a
whisker of aluminum borate, a whisker of zinc oxide; or powdery ones
such as talc, mica, kaoline, clay, calcium carbonate, silica,
silica-alumina, alumina, titanium oxide, graphite, molybdenium
disuifide, montmorillonite, polytetrafluoroethylene and high molecular
weight polyethylene. The polyamide composition may contain one or more
types of those fillers. Among them, from the viewpoint of mechanical
properties of the molded article obtained from the resulting polyamide
composition, preferred are glass fibers, carbon fibers, a whisker of
potassium titanate or a whisker of aluminum borate. While, preferred
are carbon fibers, aramide fibers, a whisker of potassium titanate, a
whisker of calcium carbonate, a whisker of zinc oxide, talc, mica, graphite,
molybdenium disulfide, polytetrafluoroethylene or high molecular weight 
polyethylene, from the viewpoint of the slideness of the molded article
obtained from the resulting polyamide composition. In addition,
preferred are silica, alumina, talc, mica or a whisker of aluminum borate,
from the viewpoint of the dimensional stability of the molded article
obtained from the resulting polyamide composition.</p><p num="0034">Those fillers may be treated with silane couplers or titanium
couplers.</p><p num="0035">The polyamide composition of the present invention can include, if
required, an organic stabilizer. The organic stabilizers include, for
example, phenol-based, amine-based, phosphorus-basedorthioether-based
stabilizers. The polyamide composition may contain one or more types
of those organic stabilizers. Among them, preferred are phenol-based,
amine-based or phosphorus-based stabilizers, and more preferred are ones
which do not make a coordination on a copper compound (B) . The amount
of the organic stabilizer falls preferably between 0.01 and 5 part by
weight based on 100 part by weight of the semiaromatic polyamide (A).</p><p num="0036">The polyamide composition of the present invention can further contain
other additives in an amount, in total, of not more than 50 % by weight
based on the total weight of the polyamide composition. Such additives
include, for example, flame retardants such as brominated polymers,
antimony oxide, metal oxides, metal hydroxides, phosphorous compound,
polymers containing phosphorus, silicone-based compounds and compounds
containing nitrogen; UV absorbents such as benzophenone-based compounds,
benzotriazole-based compounds, benzoic acid-based compounds; antistatic
agents; plasticizers; lubricants; nucleating agents; processing aids;
colorants, e.g., of pigments or dyes; anti-dripping agents; impact
modifiers; various thermoplastic polymers other than the semiaromatic 
polyamides (A).</p><p num="0037">The polyamide compositions of the present invention can be prepared
by blending (A) a semiaromatic polyamide and (B) a copper compound, and
if necessary, together with other components described above, by a
conventional method. The semiaromatic polyamide (A), the filler (D)
and the stabilizers are preferably used in a form of powder or pellet.
A uniform polyamide composition can be preferably prepared, for example,
by kneading through an equipment for melt mixing such as a twin screw
extruder, at a temperature under which the semiaromatic polyamide (A)
is molten. In such a case, it is desired that the semiaromatic polyamide.
(A), the copper compound (B) and other components are dry blended, before
kneading, as in a solid form such as powder and pellet.</p><p num="0038">The polyamide compositions of the present invention can also be
prepared by blending 100 parts by weight of (A') a semiaromatic polyamide
having dicarboxylic acid units mainly composed of aromatic dicarboxylic
acid units and diamine units mainly composed of aliphatic diamine units
having 4 to 14 carbon atoms, 0.01 to 5 parts by weight of (B) a copper
compound and (E) an organic compound which is reactive with terminal
amino groups of said semiarcmatic polyamide (A') in an amount of 0.1
to 10 equivalent of the number of terminal amino groups of said semiaromatic
polyamide (A'), by kneading in melt. The semiaromatic polyamides (A' )
may contain more than 15 µeq/g of terminal amino groups. For example,
the polyamide compositions of the present invention can be prepared by
(i) blending (A') a semiaromatic polyamide, (B) a copper compound and
(E) an organic compound which is reactive with terminal amino groups
of said semiaromatic polyamide (A'), and if necessary, together with
other components described above, by a tumbler or a henshel mixer and 
(ii) subjecting the resulting blend to melt kneading with a twin screw
extruder at a temperature higher than the melting point of the semiaromatic
polyamide (A'). When a fibrous filler or a needle-like filler is used
as one of other components, it is desirable to feed such a filler to
the extruder through a side feeder. The obtained polyamide composition
is preferably extruded as a strand and cut in pieces to give a pellet.</p><p num="0039">The organic compound (E) reactive with amino group is preferably
a compound having a molecular weight of not less than 100, in view of
preventing evaporation at kneading. The organic compounds (E) include,
for example, monocarboxylic acids such as stearic acid,
cyclohexanecarboxylic acid, benzoic acid, anisic acid; dicarboxylic
acids such as adipic acid, azelaic acid, sebacic acid, terephthalic acid
and 4,4'-oxydibenzoic acid; acid anhydrides such as trimellitic
anhydride, 1,8-naphthalic anhydride, phthalic anhydride and maleic
anhydride; dianhydrides of tetracarboxiric acid such as pyromellitic
anhydride; isocyanates such as phenyl isocyanate; diisocyanates such
as 4,4'-diphenylmethane diisocyanate, tolylene diisocyanate, xylylene
diisocyanate, hexamethylene diisocyanate and isophorone diisocyanate;
and epoxy compounds such as bisphenol A type epoxy resins. Among them,
acid anhydrides are preferred from the viewpoint of reactivity with amino
group. The amount of the organic compound (E) is set between 0.1 and
10 equivalents based on the moles of the terminal amino groups contained
in the semiaromatic polyamide (A'), in order to produce a polyamide
composition having excellent heat aging characteristics. The amount
of the organic compound (E) falls preferablybetween 0.5 and 5 equivalents,
more preferably between 1 and 3 equivalents, based on the moles of the
terminal amino groups contained in the semiaromatic polyamide (A'). </p><p num="0040">The polyamide compositions of the present invention can be converted
into various molded articles by injection molding, extrusion and so on.
The polyamide compositions of the present invention are preferably used
for producing automobile engine room parts.</p><p num="0041">In addition, the polyamide compositions of the present invention
can be widely used as molding materials for electrical and electronic
parts, automobile parts, industrialmaterials or household goods, because
they have excellent heat aging characteristics, as well as excellent
heat resistance, impact resistance, low-water-absorption property, hot
water and steam resistance and chemical resistance.</p><p num="0042">The semiarcmatlcpolyamides (A) having dicarboxylic acid units mainly
composed of aromatic dicarboxylic acid units and diamine units mainly
composed of aliphatic diamine units having 4 to 14 carbon atoms and
containing not more than 15 µeq/g of terminal amino groups are novel.
The semiaromatic polyamides (A) are not only an important component of
the polyamide composition of the present invention but also can be used
for various applications as it is or as formulated into polyamide
compositions blended with other component such as polymeric compounds,
various additives and inorganic fillers.</p><heading><u style="single">Examples</u></heading><p num="0043">Now, the invention is described in more detail hereinbelow with
reference to the following Examples and Comparative Examples, which are
provided for the purposes of illustration only, however, and are not
intended to restrict the scope of the invention.</p><p num="0044">In the following Examples and Comparative Examples, -intrinsic
viscosity, number of terminal carboxyl groups, number of terminal amino 
groups, deflection temperature under load, water absorption, dimensional
stability, hot water resistance, chemical resistance and heat aging
characteristics are evaluated according to the following procedures.</p><heading><u style="single">Intrinsic Viscosity [η]</u></heading><p num="0045">A sample of the polyamide or the polyamide composition to be measured
is dissolved in concentrated sulfuric acid to give solutions having a
concentration of 0.05, 0.1, 0.2 or 0.4 g/dl, and the inherent viscosity
ηinh of each sample solution is measured at 30 °C as follows:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">ηinh = [ln (t<st32:sub pos="post">1</st32:sub>/t<st32:sub pos="post">0</st32:sub>)]/C (dl/g)</st32:df>
wherein t<sub>0</sub> means flow down time (seconds) of the solvent, t<sub>1</sub> means flow
down time (seconds) of the sample solution and C means concentration
of the sample in the sample solution.</p><p num="0046">Extrapolating the data of η inh with the control having a concentration
of 0 gives the intrinsic viscosity [η] of the sample.</p><p num="0047">When the sample solution contains a undissolved solid matter, such
solid matter is discharged by filtration using a 0.5µm aperture-membrane
filter and the obtained filtrate is tested for the inherent viscosity.</p><heading><u style="single">Number of terminal carboxyl groups</u></heading><p num="0048">1g of a polyamide or a polyamide composition is dissolved in 35 ml
of o-cresol with heating. After cooled to room temperature, 20 ml of
benzyl alcohol and 250 µl of formaldehyde are added to the resulting
solution to give a sample solution. The obtained sample solution is
subjected to potentiometric titration with a 0.1 N solution of potassium
hydroxide in methanol to determine the number of terminal carboxyl groups.</p><p num="0049">Test result for a polyamide composition is converted into a number
of terminal carboxyl groups of the polyamide contained therein based
on the weight ratio of the component of the polyamide composition. </p><heading><u style="single">Number of terminal amino groups</u></heading><p num="0050">1g of a polyamide or a polyamide composition is dissolved in 35 ml
of phenol. 2 ml of methanol is added to the resulting solution to give
a sample solution. The obtained sample solution is subjected to titration
with a 0.01 N of aqueous hydrochloric acid using Thymol Blue as an indicator
to determine the number of terminal amino groups.</p><p num="0051">Test result for a polyamide composition is converted into a number
of terminal amino groups of the polyamide contained therein based on
the weight ratio of the component of the polyamide composition.</p><heading><u style="single">Deflection temperature under load</u></heading><p num="0052">Deflection temperature under load is determined according to the
method of JIS K 7207, under the load of 1.82 MPa, using a thoroughly
dried test piece having a length of 127 mm, a width of 14 mm and a thickness
of 6.4 mm, prepared by injection molding at a temperature which is higher
than the melting point of the polyamide by about 20 °C.</p><heading><u style="single">Water absorption and dimensional stability</u></heading><p num="0053">A test piece having a length of 80 mm, a width of 80 mm and a thickness
of 3 mm is prepared by injection molding at a temperature which is higher
than the melting point of the polyamide by about 20 °C. The test piece
is thoroughly dried to determine the weight [W<sub>0</sub>] and the length [L<sub>0</sub>].
The test piece is immersed in water at 23 °C for 24 hours to determine
the weight [W<sub>1</sub>] and the length [L<sub>1</sub>]. Water absorption and dimensional
stability are calculated as follows:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Water absorption (%) = [(w<st32:sub pos="post">1</st32:sub>-w<st32:sub pos="post">0</st32:sub>)/W<st32:sub pos="post">0</st32:sub>] × 100</st32:df><st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Dimensional stability (%) = [(L<st32:sub pos="post">1</st32:sub>-L<st32:sub pos="post">0</st32:sub>)/L<st32:sub pos="post">0</st32:sub>] × 100</st32:df></p><heading><u style="single">Hot Water resistance</u></heading><p num="0054">A test piece having a shape of JIS No. 1 dumbbell-type and a thickness
of 3 mm, prepared by injection molding at a temperature which is higher
than the melting point of the polyamide by about 20 °C, is treated with
steam in an autoclave under 2 atmospheric pressures, at 120 °C for 120
hours. The test piece thus treated with steam is tested for its tensile
strength according to JIS K 7113. The retention of tensile strength
(%) against the values before the steam treatment is calculated.</p><heading><u style="single">Chemical Resistance</u></heading><p num="0055">A film having a thickness of 200 µm prepared by heat pressing at
a temperature higher than the melting point of polyamide by about 20 °C
is punched with JIS No. 3 Dumbbell to give a test piece. The test piece
is immersed in methanol at 23 °C for 7 days and then tested for tensile
strength according to the method of JIS K 7113. The retention of tensile
strength (%) against the tensile strength before immersion in methanol
is calculated.</p><heading><u style="single">Heat aging characteristics</u></heading><p num="0056">A test piece having a shape of JIS No. 1 dumbbell-type and a thickness
of 3 mm, prepared by injection molding at a temperature which is higher
than the melting point of the polyamide by about 20 °C, is thoroughly
dried and left in a gear-oven at 180 °C for 14 days. The test piece thus
treated is tested for its tensile strength according to JIS K 7113. The
retention of tensile strength (%) against the values before the heat
treatment is calculated. </p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><heading>(1) Preparation of semiaromatic polyamide</heading><p num="0057">An autoclave having an inner volume of 20 liters was charged with
4634.2 g (27.8 moles) of terephthalic acid, 4432.1 g (28.0 moles) of
a mixture of 80 % of 1,9-nonanediamine and 20 % of
2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine, 85.5 g (0.70 mole) of benzoic acid, 9.12
g (0.1% by weight based on the total weight of raw materials) of sodium
hypophosphite monohydrate and 2.5 liters of distilled water under nitrogen.
The resulting mixture was agitated at 100 °C for 30 minutes, then the
temperature of the mixture was elevated to 220 °C over 2 hours under
agitation. At this time, the inner pressure of the autoclave was 2 MPa.
The reaction mixture was agitated at 220°C for 2 hours, then the temperature
of the mixture was elevated to 230 °C under agitation. The reaction was
further conducted for 2 hours under constant temperature of 230 °C and
pressure of 2 MPa which was kept constant by discharging the formed water.
After that, the inner pressure of the autoclave was reduced to 1 MPa
over 30 minutes and the reaction mixture was further agitated for 1 hour
at 230 °C under the pressure of 1 MPa to give a prepolymer having an
intrinsic viscosity [η] of 0.18 dl/g. The prepolymer was dried at 100 °C
under reduce pressure for 12 hours and then pulverized to a particle
size of not more than 2 mm. The particles were subjected to solid phase
polymerization at 230 °C under 13 Pa [0.1 mmHg] of pressure for 10 hours
to give a white polyamide having a melting point of 306 °C, an intrinsic
viscosity [η] of 1.51 dl/g, a number of terminal amino groups of 12
µeq/g and a number of terminal carboxyl groups of 42 µeq/g. This
polyamide was abbreviated as "PA9T-1". </p><heading>(2) Preparation of polyamide composition</heading><p num="0058">PA9T-1 obtained above was dried at 120 °C under reduced pressure
for 14 hours. 100 part by weight of PA9T-1, thus dried, was mixed with
a solution of 0.4 part by weight of potassium iodide [KI] and 0.05 part
by weight of copper (I) iodide [CuI] in 0.4 part by weight of water.
The resulting mixture was left at room temperature for 12 hours and then
dried at 120 °C in a vacuum oven for 12 hours. The resulting blend was
kneaded and extruded by a twin-screw extruder [Laboplastmill 2D25W; made
by Toyo Seiki Seisakusho Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder
temperature of 330 °C and a rotating speed of 40 r.p.m. to give pellets
of polyamide composition. The obtained pellets were dried at 120°C under
vacuum for 12 hours. The intrinsic viscosity of the polyamide composition
[η], the number of terminal amino groups of the polyamide and the number
of terminal carboxyl groups of the polyamide were determined. Results
are shown in Table 1. The obtained pellest were subjected to injection
molding by an injection molder [NS15; made by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.]
under the condition of a cylinder temperature of 330 °C and a mold
temperature of 150 °C to give a molded article. The obtained molded
article was tested for deflection temperature under load, water absorption,
dimensional stability, hot water resistance, chemical resistance and
heat aging characteristics. Results are also shown in Table 1.</p><heading>Example 2</heading><heading>(1) Preparation of semiaromatic polyamide</heading><p num="0059">An autoclave having an inner volume of 20 liters was charged with
4601.0 g (27.7 moles) of terephthalic acid, 4432.1 g (28.0 moles) of
1,9-nonanediamine, 116.0 g (0.95 mole) of benzoic acid, 9.12 g (0.1% 
by weight based on the total weight of raw materials) of sodium
hypophosphite monohydrate and2.5 liters of distilled water under nitrogen.
The resulting mixture was agitated at 100 °C for 30 minutes, then the
temperature of the mixture was elevated to 220 °C over 2 hours under
agitation. At this time, the inner pressure of the autoclave was 2 MPa.
The reaction mixture was agitated at 220°C for 2 hours, then the temperature
of the mixture was elevated to 230 °C under agitation. The reaction was
further conducted for 2 hours under constant temperature of 230 °C and
pressure of 2 MPa which was kept constant by discharging the formed water.
After that, the inner pressure of the autoclave was reduced to 1 MPa
over 30 minutes and the reaction mixture was further agitated for 1 hour
at 230 °C under the pressure of 1 MPa to give a prepolymer having an
intrinsic viscosity [η] of 0.15 dl/g. The prepolymer was dried at 100 °C
under reduce pressure for 12 hours and then pulverized to a particle
size of not more than 2 mm. The particles were subjected to solid phase
polymerization at 230 °C under 13Pa [0.1 mmHg] of pressure for 10 hours
to give a white polyamide having a melting point of 317 °C, an intrinsic
viscosity [η] of 1.30 dl/g, a number of terminal amino groups of 9 µeq/g
and a number of terminal carboxyl groups of 41 µeq/g. This polyamide
was abbreviated as "PA9T-2".</p><heading>(2) Preparation of polyamide composition</heading><p num="0060">Procedures of Example 1 (2) were repeated except that 100 part by
weight of PA9T-2 was used instead of 100 part by weight of PA9T-1 to
give pellets of polyamide composition. The obtained pellets were dried
at 120 °C under vacuum for 12 hours. The intrinsic viscosity of the
polyamide composition [η], the number of terminal amino groups of the
polyamide and the number of terminal carboxyl groups of the polyamide 
were determined. Results are shown in Table 1. The obtained pellets
were subjected to injection molding by an injection molder [NS15; made
by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.] ] under the condition of a cylinder temperature
of 330 °C and a mold temperature of 150 °C to give a molded article. The
obtained molded article was tested for deflection temperature under load,
water absorption, dimensional stability, hot water resistance, chemical
resistance and heat aging characteristics. Results are also shown in
Table 1.</p><heading>Example 3</heading><heading>(1) Preparation of semiaromatic polyamide</heading><p num="0061">An autoclave having an inner volume of 20 liters was charged with
4667.4 g (28.1 moles) of terephthalic acid, 4432.1 g (28.0 moles) of
a mixture of 80 % of 1,9-nonanediamine and 20 % of
2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine, 102.6 g (0.84 mole) of benzoic acid, 9.20
g (0.1% by weight based on the total weight of raw materials) of sodium
hypophosphite monohydrate and 2.5 liters of distilled water under nitrogen.
The resulting mixture was agitated at 100 °C for 30 minutes, then the
temperature of the mixture was elevated to 220 °C over 2 hours under
agitation. At this time, the inner pressure of the autoclave was 2 MPa.
The reaction mixture was agitated at 220°C for 2 hours, then the temperature
of the mixture was elevated to 230 °C under agitation. The reaction was
further conducted for 2 hours under constant temperature of 230 °C and
pressure of 2 MPa which was kept constant by discharging the formed water.
After that, the inner pressure of the autoclave was reduced to 1 MPa
over 30 minutes and the reaction mixture was further agitated for 1 hour
at 230 °C under the pressure of 1 MPa to give a prepolymer having an 
intrinsic viscosity [η] of 0.16 dl/g. The prepolymer was dried at 100°C
under reduce pressure for 12 hours and then pulverized to a particle
size of not more than 2 mm. The particles were subjected to solid phase
polymerization at 230°C under 13 Pa [0.1 mmHg] of pressure for 10 hours
to give a white polyamide having a melting point of 306 °C, an intrinsic
viscosity [η] of 0.90 dl/g, a number of terminal amino groups of 12
µeq/g and a number of terminal carboxyl groups of 76 µeq/g. This
polyamide was abbreviated as "PA9T-3".</p><heading>(2) Preparation of polyamide composition</heading><p num="0062">PA9T-3 obtained above was dried at 120 °C under reduced pressure.
for 14 hours. 100 part by weight of PA9T-3, thus dried, was mixed with
a solution of 0.4 part by weight of potassium iodide [KI] and 0.05 part
by weight of copper (I) iodide [CuI] in 0.4 part by weight of water.
The resulting mixture was stood still at room temperature for 12 hours
and then dried at 120 °C in a vacuum oven for 12 hours. 30 part by weight
of glass fiber [3540; made by PPG Inc.] was blended with the dried mixture
of PA9T-3, KI and Cut. The resulting blend was kneaded and extruded
by a twin-screw extruder [Laboplastmill 2D25W; made by Toyo Seiki
Seisakusho Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder temperature of 330 °C
and a rotating speed of 40 r.p.m. to give pellets of polyamide composition.
The obtained pellets were dried at 120 °C under vacuum for 12 hours.
The intrinsic viscosity of the polyamide composition [η], the number
of terminal amino groups of the polyamide and the number of terminal
carboxyl groups of the polyamide were determined. Results are shown
in Table 1. The obtained pellets were subjected to injection molding
by an injection molder [NS15; made by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.] under
the condition of a cylinder temperature of 330 °C and a mold temperature 
of 150°C to give a molded article. The obtained molded article was tested
for deflection temperature under load, water absorption, dimensional
stability, hot water resistance, chemical resistance and heat aging
characteristics. Results are also shown in Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 1</heading><heading>(1) Preparation of semiaromatic polyamide</heading><p num="0063">An autoclave having an inner volume of 20 liters was charged with
4584.4 g (27.6 moles) of terephthalic acid, 4527.1 g (28.6 moles) of
a mixture of 80 % of 1,9-nonanediamine and 20 % of
2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine, 102.6 g (0.84 mole) of benzoic acid, 9.21
g (0.1% by weight based on the total weight of raw materials) of sodium
hypophosphite monohydrate and 2.5 liters of distilled water under nitrogen.
The resulting mixture was agitated at 100 °C for 30 minutes, then the
temperature of the mixture was elevated to 220 °C over 2 hours under
agitation. At this time, the inner pressure of the autoclave was 2 MPa.
The reaction mixture was agitated at 220 °C for 2 hours, then the temperature
of the mixture was elevated to 230 °C under agitation. The reaction was
further conducted for 2 hours under constant temperature of 230 °C and
pressure of 2 MPa which was kept constant by discharging the formed water.
After that, the inner pressure of the autoclave was reduced to 1 MPa
over 30 minutes and the reaction mixture was further agitated for 1 hour
at 230 °C under the pressure of 1 MPa to give a prepolymer having an
intrinsic viscosity [η] of 0.16 dl/g. The prepolymer was dried at 100 °C
under reduce pressure for 12 hours and then pulverized to a particle
size of not more than 2 mm. The particles were subjected to solid phase
polymerization at 230 °C under 13 Pa [0.1 mmHg] of pressure for 10 hours 
to give a white polyamide having a melting point of 306 °C, an intrinsic
viscosity [η] of 1.40 dl/g, a number of terminal amino groups of 30
µeq/g and a number of terminal carboxyl groups of 16 µeq/g. This
polyamide was abbreviated as "PA9T-4".</p><heading>(2) Preparation of polyamide composition</heading><p num="0064">Procedures of Example 1 (2) were repeated except that 100 part by
weight of PA9T-4 was used instead of 100 part by weight of PA9T-1 to
give pellets of polyamide composition. The obtained pellets were dried
at 120 °C under vacuum for 12 hours. The intrinsic viscosity of the
polyamide composition [η], the number of terminal amino groups of the
polyamide and the number of terminal carboxyl groups of the polyamide
were determined. Results are shown in Table 1. The obtained pellets
were subjected to injection molding by an injection molder [NS15; made
by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder temperature
of 330 °C and a mold temperature of 150 °C to give a molded article. The
obtained molded article was tested for deflection temperature under load,
water absorption, dimensional stability, hot water resistance, chemical
resistance and heat aging characteristics. Results are also shown in
Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 2</heading><heading>(1) Preparation of semiaromatic polyamide</heading><p num="0065">An autoclave having an inner volume of 20 liters was charged with
3438.3 g (20.7 moles) of terephthalic acid, 1007.4 g (6.9 moles) of adipic
acid, 2561.1 g (22.0 moles) of 1,6-hexanediamine, 765.0 g (6.6 moles)
of 2-methyl-1,5-pentanediamine, 50.4 g (0.84 mole) of acetic acid, 7.77
g of sodium hypophosphite monohydrate and 2.5 liters of distilled water 
under nitrogen. The resulting mixture was agitated at 100 °C for 30
minutes, then the temperature of the mixture was elevated to 220 °C over
2 hours under agitation. At this time, the inner pressure of the autoclave
was 2 MPa. The reaction mixture was agitated at 220 °C for 2 hours, then
the temperature of the mixture was elevated to 230 °C under agitation.
The reaction was further conducted for 2 hours under constant temperature
of 230 °C and pressure of 2 MPa which was kept constant by discharging
the formed water. After that, the inner pressure of the autoclave was
reduced to 1 MPa over 30 minutes and the reaction mixture was further
agitated for 1 hour at 230 °C under the pressure of 1NPa to give a prepolymer
having an intrinsic viscosity [η] of 0.19 dl/g. The prepolymer was
dried at 100 °C under reduce pressure for 12 hours and then pulverized
to a particle size of not more than 2 mm. The particles were subjected
to solid phase polymerization at 230 °C under 13 Pa [0.1 mmHg] of pressure
for 10 hours to give a white polyamide having dicarboxylic acid unit
of 75 mole % of terephthalic acid unit and 25 mole % of adipic acid unit
and diamine unit of 77 mole % of 1,6-hexanediamine unit and 23 mole %
of 2-methyl-1,5-pentanediamine unit and having an intrinsic viscosity
[η] of 1.04 dl/g, a number of terminal amino groups of 91 µeq/g and
a number of terminal carboxyl groups of 14 µeq/g. This polyamide was
abbreviated as "PA6M-6T".</p><heading>(2) Preparation of polyamide composition</heading><p num="0066">Procedures of Example 1 (2) were repeated except that 100 part by
weight of PA6M-6T was used instead of 100 part by weight of PA9T-1 to
give pellets of polyamide composition. The obtained pellets were dried
at 120 °C under vacuum for 12 hours. The intrinsic viscosity of the
polyamide composition [η], the number of terminal amino groups of the 
polyamide and the number of terminal carboxyl groups of the polyamide
were determined. Results are shown in Table 1. The obtained pellets
were subjected to injection molding by an injection molder [NS15; made
by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder temperature
of 330 °C and a mold temperature of 150 °C to give a molded article. The
obtained molded article was tested for deflection temperature under load,
water absorption, dimensional stability, hot water resistance, chemical
resistance and heat aging characteristics. Results are also shown in
Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 3</heading><heading>(1) Preparation of semiaromatic polyamide</heading><p num="0067">An autoclave having an inner volume of 20 liters was charged with
3322 g (20.0 moles) of terephthalic acid, 3166 g (20.0 moles) of
1,9-nonanediamine, 48.8 g (0.4 mole) of benzoic acid, 5.28g (0.06 mole)
of sodium hypophosphite monohydrate and 2.2 liters of distilled water
under nitrogen. The resulting mixture was agitated at 100 °C for 30
minutes, then the temperature of the mixture was elevated to 210 °C over
2 hours under agitation. At this time, the inner pressure of the autoclave
was 2.2 MPa. The reaction mixture was agitated at 210 °C for 1 hours,
then the temperature of the mixture was elevated to 230 °C under agitation.
The reaction was further conducted for 2 hours under constant temperature
of 230 °C and pressure of 2.2 MPa which was kept constant by discharging
the formed water. After that, the inner pressure of the autoclave was
reduced to 1 MPa over 30 minutes and the reaction mixture was further
agitated for 1 hour at 230 °C under the pressure of 1 MPa to give a prepolymer
having an intrinsic viscosity [η] of 0.17 dl/g. The prepolymer was 
dried at 100 °C under reduce pressure for 12 hours and then pulverized
to a particle size of not more than 2 mm. The particles were subjected
to solid phase polymerization at 230 °C under 13Pa [0.1 mmHg] of pressure
for 10 hours to give a white polyamide having a melting point of 312 °C,
an intrinsic viscosity [η] of 1.11 dl/g, a number of terminal amino
groups of 32 µeq/g and a number of terminal carboxyl groups of 10 µeq/g.
This polyamide was abbreviated as "PA9T-5".</p><p num="0068">PA9T-5 is identical with the polyamide obtained in the Referential
Example 6 of JP-A-316731/97.</p><heading>(2) Preparation of polyamide composition</heading><p num="0069">Procedures of Example 1 (2) were repeated except that 100 part by
weight of PA9T-5 was used instead of 100 part by weight of PA9T-1 to
give pellets of polyamide composition. The obtained pellets were dried
at 120 °C under vacuum for 12 hours. The intrinsic viscosity of the
polyamide composition [η], the number of terminal amino groups of the
polyamide and the number of terminal carboxyl groups of the polyamide
were determined. Results are shown in Table 1. The obtained pellets
were subjected to injection molding by an injection molder [NS15; made
by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder temperature
of 330 °C and a mold temperature of 150 °C to give a molded article. The
obtained molded article was tested for deflection temperature under load,
water absorption, dimensional stability, hot water resistance, chemical
resistance and heat aging characteristics. Results are also shown in
Table 1. </p><heading>Comparative Example 4</heading><heading>(1) Preparation of semiaromatic polyamide</heading><p num="0070">An autoclave having an inner volume of 20 liters was charged with
3355 g (20.2 moles) of terephthalic acid, 2691 g (17.0 moles) of
1,9-nonanediamine, 475 g (3.0 moles) of 2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine, 36.6
g (0.3 mole) of benzoic acid, 5.28 g (0.06 mole) of sodium hypophosphite
monohydrate and 2.2 liters of distilled water under nitrogen. The
resulting mixture was agitated at 100 °C for 30 minutes, then the
temperature of the mixture was elevated to 210 °C over 2 hours under
agitation. At this time, the inner pressure of the autoclave was 2.2
MPa. The reaction mixture was agitated at 210 °C for 1 hour, then the
temperature of the mixture was elevated to 230 °C under agitation. The
reaction was further conducted for 2 hours under constant temperature
of 230 °C and pressure of 2.2 MPa which was kept constant by discharging
the formed water. After that, the inner pressure of the autoclave was
reduced to 1 MPa over 30 minutes and the reaction mixture was further
agitated for 1 hour at 230°C under the pressure of 1 MPa to give a prepolymer
having an intrinsic viscosity [η] of 0.20 dl/g. The prepolymer was
dried at 100 °C under reduce pressure for 12 hours and then pulverized
to a particle size of not more than 2 mm. The particles were subjected
to solid phase polymerization at 230 °C under 13 Pa [0.1 mmHg] of pressure
for 10 hours to give a white polyamide having a melting point of 299 °C,
an intrinsic viscosity [η] of 1.02 dl/g, a number of terminal amino
groups of 44 µeq/g and a number of terminal carboxyl groups of 9 µeq/g.
This polyamide was abbreviated as "PA9T-6".</p><p num="0071">PA9T-6 is identical with the polyamide obtained in the Referential
Example 7 of JP-A-316731/97. </p><heading>(2) Preparation of polyamide composition</heading><p num="0072">Procedures of Example 1 (2) were repeated except that 100 part by
weight of PA9T-6 was used instead of 100 part by weight of PA9T-1 to
give pellets of polyamide composition. The obtained pellets were dried
at 120 °C under vacuum for 12 hours. The intrinsic viscosity of the
polyamide composition [η], the number of terminal amino groups of the
polyamide and the number of terminal carboxyl groups of the polyamide
were determined. Results are shown in Table 1. The obtained pellets
were subjected to injection molding by an injection molder [NS15; made
by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder temperature
of 330 °C and a mold temperature of 15C °C to give a molded article. The
obtained molded article was tested for deflection temperature under load,
water absorption, dimensional stability, hot water resistance, chemical
resistance and heat aging characteristics. Results are also shown in
Table 1.</p><heading>Comparative Example 5</heading><heading>(1) Preparation of semiaromatic polyamide</heading><p num="0073">An autoclave having an inner volume of 20 liters was charged with
3272.9 g (19.7 moles) of terephthalic acid, 2849.2 g (18.0 moles) of
1,9-nonanediamine, 316.58 g (2.0 moles) of 2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine,
73.27 g (0.6 mole) of benzoic acid, 6.5 g of sodium hypophosphite
monohydrate and 2.2 liters of distilled water under nitrogen. The
resulting mixture was agitated at 100 °C for 30 minutes, then the
temperature of the mixture was elevated to 210 °C over 2 hours under
agitation. At this time, the inner pressure of the autoclave was 2.2
MPa. The reaction mixture was agitated at 210 °C for 1 hours, then the 
temperature of the mixture was elevated to 230 °C under agitation. The
reaction was further conducted for 2 hours under constant temperature
of 230 °C and pressure of 2.2 MPa which was kept constant by discharging
the formed water. After that, the inner pressure of the autoclave was
reduced to 1 MPa over 30 minutes and the reaction mixture was further
agitated for 1 hour at 230 °C under the pressure of 1NPa to give a prepolymer
having an intrinsic viscosity [η] of 0.20 dl/g. The prepolymer was
dried at 100 °C under reduce pressure for 12 hours and then pulverized
to a particle size of not more than 2 mm. The particles were subjected
to solid phase polymerization at 230 °C under 13 Pa [0.1 mmHg] of pressure
for 10 hours to give a white polyamide having a melting point of 305 °C,
an intrinsic viscosity [η] of 1.23 dl/g, a number of terminal amino
groups of 23 µeq/g and a number of terminal carboxyl groups of 28 µ
eq/g. This polyamide was abbreviated as "PA9T-7".</p><p num="0074">PA9T-7 is identical with the polyamide obtained in the Example 2
of JP-A-228768/95.</p><heading>(2) Preparation of polyamide composition</heading><p num="0075">Procedures of Example 1 (2) were repeated except that 100 part by
weight of PA9T-7 was used instead of 100 part by weight of PAST-1 to
give pellets of polyamide composition. The obtained pellets were dried
at 120 °C under vacuum for 12 hours. The intrinsic viscosity of the
polyamide composition [η], the number of terminal amino groups of the
polyamide and the number of terminal carboxyl groups of the polyamide
were determined. Results are shown in Table 1. The obtained pellets
were subjected to injection molding by an injection molder [NS15; made
by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder temperature
of 330 °C and a mold temperature of 150 °C to give a molded article. The 
obtained molded article was tested for deflection temperature under load,
water absorption, dimensional stability, hot water resistance, chemical
resistance and heat aging characteristics. Results are also shown in
Table 1.</p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0076">Procedures of Example 1 (2) were repeated except that 0.05 part by
weight of copper (I) chloride [CuCl] was used instead of 0.05 part by
weight of copper (I) iodide to give pellets of polyamide composition.
The obtained pellet was dried at 120 °C under vacuum for 12 hours. The
intrinsic viscosity of the polyamide composition [η], the number of
terminal amino groups of the polyamide and the number of terminal carboxyl
groups of the polyamide were determined. Results are shown in Table
1. The obtained pellets were subjected to injection molding by an
injection molder [NS15; made by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.] under the
condition of a cylinder temperature of 330 °C and a mold temperature
of 150 °C to give amolded article. The obtained molded article was tested
for deflection temperature under load, water absorption, dimensional
stability, hot water resistance, chemical resistance and heat aging
characteristics. Results are also shown in Table 1. <img id="img-00350001" orientation="unknown" wi="135" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00350001.tif" inline="no" he="233"/></p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="0077">PA9T-4 obtained in Comparative Example 1 (1) was dried at 120 °C
under reduced pressure for 14 hours. 100 part by weight of PA9T-4, thus
dried, was blended in dry with 0.8 part by weight of potassium iodide
[KI], 0.1 part by weight of copper (I) iodide [CuI] and 0.5 part by weight
of phthalic anhydride. The resulting blend was kneaded and extruded
by a twin-screw extruder [BT-30; D = 30 mm ; L/D = 32; made by Research
Laboratory of Plastics Technology Co., Ltd.] under the condition of a
cylinder temperature of 320 °C and a rotating speed of 40 r.p.m. to give
pellets of polyamide composition. The intrinsic viscosity of the
polyamide composition [η] and the number of terminal amino groups of
the polyamide were determined. Results are shown in Table 2. The
obtained pellets were dried at 120 °C under vacuum for 12 hours. The
dried pellet was subjected to injection molding by an injection molder
[NS15; made by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder
temperature of 330 °C and a mold temperature of 150 °C to give a molded
article. The obtained molded article was tested for deflection
temperature under load, water absorption, dimensional stability, hot
water resistance, chemical resistance and heat aging characteristics.
Results are also shown in Table 2.</p><heading>Examples 6 and 7</heading><p num="0078">Procedures of Example 5 were repeated except that 0.4 part by weight
of pyromellitic dianhydride [Example 6] or 0.5 part by weight of anisic
acid [Example 7 ] was used instead of 0.5 part by weight of phthalic anhydride
to give pellets of polyamide composition. The intrinsic viscosity of
the polyamide composition [η] and the number of terminal amino groups 
of the polyamide were determined. Results are shown in Table 2. The
obtained pellets were dried at 120 °C under vacuum for 12 hours. The
dried pellets were subjected to injection molding by an injection molder
[NS15; made by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder
temperature of 330 °C and a mold temperature of 150 °C to give a molded
article. The obtained molded article was tested for deflection
temperature under load, water absorption, dimensional stability, hot
water resistance, chemical resistance and heat aging characteristics.
Results are also shown in Table 2.</p><heading>Example 8</heading><p num="0079">PA9T-4 obtained in Comparative Example 1 (1) was dried at 120 °C
under reduced pressure for 14 hours. 100 part by weight of PA9T-4, thus
dried, was blended in dry with 0.8 part by weight of potassium iodide
[KI], 0.1 part by weight of copper (I) iodide [CuI] and 0.5 part by weight
of phthalic anhydride. The resulting blend was kneaded and extruded
by a twin-screw extruder [BT-30; D = 30 mm ; L/D = 32; made by Research
Laboratory of Plastics Technology Co., Ltd.] under the condition of a
cylinder temperature of 320 °C and a rotating speed of 40 r.p.m., while
being fed with glass fiber [3540; made by PPG Inc.] in an amount of 30 %
by weight based on the weight of the PAST-4, to give pellets of polyamide
composition. The intrinsic viscosity of the polyamide composition [η]
and the number of terminal amino groups of the polyamide were determined.
Results are shown in Table 2. The obtained pellets were dried at 120 °C
under vacuum for 12 hours. The dried pellets were subjected to injection
molding by an injection molder [NS15; made by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.]
under the condition of a cylinder temperature of 330 °C and a mold 
temperature of 150 °C to give a mold article. The obtained molded article
was tested for deflection temperature under load, water absorption,
dimensional stability, hot water resistance, chemical resistance and
heat aging characteristics. Results are also shown in Table 2.</p><heading>Example 9</heading><p num="0080">PA6M-6T obtained in Comparative Example 2 (1) was dried at 120 °C
under reduced pressure for 14 hours. 100 part by weight of PA6M-6T,
thus dried, was blended in dry with 0.8 part by weight of potassium iodide
[KI], 0.1 part by weight of copper (I) iodide [CuI] and 1 part by weight
of phthalic anhydride. The resulting blend was kneaded and extruded
by a twin-screw extruder [BT-30; D = 30 mm ; L/D = 32; made by Research
Laboratory of Plastics Technology Co., Ltd.] under the condition of a
cylinder temperature of 320 °C and a rotating speed of 40 r.p.m. to give
pellets of polyamide composition. The intrinsic viscosity of the
polyamide composition [η] and the number of terminal amino groups of
the polyamide were determined. Results are shown in Table 2. The
obtained pellets were dried at 120 °C under vacuum for 12 hours. The
dried pellets were subjected to injection molding by an injection molder
[NS15; made by Nissei Jushi Kogyo Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder
temperature of 330 °C and a mold temperature of 150 °C to give a molded
article. The obtained molded article was tested for deflection
temperature under load, water absorption, dimensional stability, hot
water resistance, chemical resistance and heat aging characteristics.
Results are also shown in Table 2.</p><heading>Comparative Example 6</heading><p num="0081">Procedures of Example 5 were repeated except that no phthalic
anhydride was used. The intrinsic viscosity of the polyamide composition
[η] and the number of terminal amino groups of the polyamide were
determined. Results are shown in Table 2. The obtained pellets were
dried at 120°C under vacuum for 12 hours. The dried pellets were subjected
to injection molding by an injection molder [NS15; made by Nissei Jushi
Kogyo Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder temperature of 330 °C and
a mold temperature of 150 °C to give a molded article. The obtained molded
article was tested for deflection temperature under load, water absorption,
dimensional stability, hot water resistance, chemical resistance and
heat aging characteristics. Results are also shown in Table 2.</p><heading>Comparative Example 7</heading><p num="0082">Procedures of Example 9 were repeated except that no phthalic
anhydride was used. The intrinsic viscosity of the polyamide composition
[η] and the number of terminal amino groups of the polyamide were
determined. Results are shown in Table 2. The obtained pellets were
dried at 120°C under vacuum for 12 hours. The dried pellets were subjected
to injection molding by an injection molder [NS15; made by Nissei Jushi
Kogyo Inc.] under the condition of a cylinder temperature of 330 °C and
a mold temperature of 150 °C to give a molded article. The obtained molded
article was tested for deflection temperature under load, water absorption,
dimensional stability, hot water resistance, chemical resistance and
heat aging characteristics. Results are also shown in Table 2. <img id="img-00400001" orientation="unknown" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00400001.tif" inline="no" he="214"/><img id="img-00410001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00410001.tif" inline="no" he="124"/></p><p num="0083">Having now fully described the invention, it will be apparent to
one of the ordinary skill in the art that many changes and modifications
can be made thereto without departing from the spirit or scope of the
invention as set forth herein.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A polyamide composition, which comprises 100 parts by weight of
(A) a semiaromatic polyamide having dicarboxylic acid units mainly
composed of aromatic dicarboxylic acid units and diamine units mainly
composed of aliphatic diamine units having 4 to 14 carbon atoms and
containing not more than 15 µeq/g of terminal amino groups; and 0.01
to 5 parts by weight of (B) a copper compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The polyamide composition of Claim 1, wherein 60 to 100 mole % of
said dicarboxylic acid units are terephthalic acid units and 60 to 100
mole % of said diamine units are 1,9-nonanediamine units and/or
2-methyl-1,8-octanediamine units.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The polyamide composition of Claims 1 or 2, wherein said copper
compound is a copper (I) compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The polyamide composition of any one of Claims 1 to 3 which further
comprises 1 to 20 part by weight of (c) an alkali metal halide based
on 1 part by weight of (B) the copper compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The polyamide composition of Claim 4, wherein said copper compound
is copper (I) iodide and said alkali metal halide is potassium iodide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The polyamide composition of any one of Claims 1 to 5 which further
comprises (D) a filler in an amount of 1 to 60 % by weight based on the
total weight of the polyamide composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A molded article made of the polyamide composition of any one of
Claims 1 to 6.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A process for producing a polyamide composition comprising
subjecting 100 parts by weight of (A') a semiaromatic polyamide having
dicarboxylic acid units mainly composed of aromatic dicarboxylic acid
units and diamine units mainly composed of aliphatic diamine units having
4 to 14 carbon atoms, 0.01 to 5 parts by weight of (B) a copper compound
and (E) an organic compound which is reactive with terminal amino groups
of said semiaromatic polyamide (A' ) in an amount of 0.1 to 10 equivalent
of the number of terminal amino groups of said semiaromatic polyamide
(A') to melt kneading.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The process of Claim 8, wherein said organic compound, reactive
with terminal amino groups of said semiaromatic polyamide (A'), is at
least one compound selected from a carboxylic acid, a carboxylic
anhydride, an isocyanate and an epoxy compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A semiaromatic polyamide having dicarboxylic acid units mainly
composed of aromatic dicarboxylic acid units and diamine units mainly
composed of aliphatic diamine units having 4 to 14 carbon atoms and
containing not more than 15 µeq/g of terminal amino groups.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>