<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1375528-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1375528" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="29716776" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040102"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1375528-A1" status="new" fvid="23939808"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1375528</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040102</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02013305-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02013305</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020618</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-02013305-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02013305</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020618</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/00        20060101C I20060521RMWO        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/651       20060101A I20060521RMWO        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/654       20060101A I20060521RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/655       20060101A I20060521RMWO        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   4/658       20060101A I20060521RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F  10/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F  10/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F  10/00+4/60</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F  10/00+4/651</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F  10/00+4/654F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F  10/00+4/655D</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung von Olefinpolymerisationskatalysatoren</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method for the preparation of olefin polymerisation catalysts</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé de préparation de catalyseurs pour la polymérisation d'oléfines</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0258089-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0258089</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>BOREALIS POLYMERS OY</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BOREALIS POLYMERS OY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BOREALIS POLYMERS OY</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 330</street><city>06101 Porvoo</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DENIFL PETER</name><address><country>AT</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GAROFF THOMAS</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>LAINE TIMO</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>PESONEN KARI</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>WALDVOGEL PAEIVI</name><address><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DENIFL, PETER</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GAROFF, THOMAS</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LAINE, TIMO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PESONEN, KARI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WALDVOGEL, PAEIVI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DENIFL, PETER</last-name><address><street>Ritten 130</street><city>6156 Gries Am Brenner</city><country>AT</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GAROFF, THOMAS</last-name><address><street>Borgströminkuja 4 K 104</street><city>00840 Helsinki</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>LAINE, TIMO</last-name><address><street>Isosaarentie 3 C 47</street><city>00840 Helsinki</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PESONEN, KARI</last-name><address><street>Kiertotie 11</street><city>07230 Monninkylä</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Waldvogel, Päivi</last-name><address><street>Päiväläispolku 12 c</street><city>06450 Porvoo</city><country>FI</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Viering, Jentschura &amp;amp; Partner</last-name><address><street>Centroallee 263</street><city>46047 Oberhausen</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention relates to a process for the production of catalysts,
particularly of Ziegler-Natta type of catalysts for olefin polymerisation, to the
catalysts as such, and to their use in polymerising olefins.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="60" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="119"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a process for the production of catalysts,
particularly of Ziegler-Natta type of catalysts for olefin polymerisation, to the
catalysts as such, and to their use in polymerising olefins.</p><heading>BACKGROUND ART</heading><p num="0002">Ziegler-Natta (ZN) type polyolefin catalysts are well known in the field of
polymers, generally, they comprise (a) at least a catalyst component formed
from a transition metal compound of Group 4 to 6 of the Periodic Table
(IUPAC, Nomenclature of Inorganic Chemistry, 1989), a metal compound of
Group 1 to 3 of the Periodic Table (IUPAC), and, optionally, a compound of
group 13 of the Periodic Table (IUPAC) and/or an internal donor compound.
ZN catalyst may also comprise (b) further catalyst component(s), such as a
cocatalyst and/or an external donor.</p><heading>Various methods have been developed for preparing ZN catalysts:</heading><p num="0003">In one conventional method a supported ZN catalyst system is prepared by
impregnating the catalyst components on a particulate support material. For
example in WO-A-01 55 230 of Borealis, the catalyst component(s) are
supported on a porous, inorganic or organic particulate carrier material, such
as silica. In a further well known method the carrier material is based on one
of the catalyst components, e.g. on a magnesium compound, such as MgCl<sub>2</sub>.
This type of carrier material can also be formed in various ways: EP-A-713
886 of Japan Olefins describes the formation of Mg-solution by melting MgCl<sub>2</sub>
with an alcohol which is then emulsified and finally the resultant mixture is
quenched to cause the solidification of the droplets. Alternatively, EP-A-856
013 of BP discloses the formation of a solid Mg-based carrier, wherein the
Mg-component containing phase is dispersed to a continuous phase and the
dispersed Mg-phase is solidified by adding the two-phase mixture to a liquid
hydrocarbon. </p><p num="0004">The formed solid carrier particles are normally treated with a transition metal
compound and optionally with other compounds for forming the active
catalyst.</p><p num="0005">Accordingly, in case of above external carriers, the morphology of the carrier
is one of the defining factors for the morphology of the final catalyst. However
also the subsequent surface treatment of the particles may have an impact on
the morphology of the final supported catalyst.</p><p num="0006">One disadvantage encountered with the supported catalyst systems is that the
surface treatment (impregnation step) of the support with one or more
catalytically active compounds may lead to non-uniform distribution of the
active component(s) and in turn to an inhomogeneous polymer material.</p><p num="0007">WO-A-00 08073 and WO-A-00 08074 of Borealis describe a further method
for producing a solid ZN-catalyst, wherein a solution of a Mg-based compound
and one or more further catalyst compounds are formed and the reaction
product thereof is precipitated out of the solution by heating the system;
Furthermore, EP-A-926 165 of Borealis discloses another precipitating
method, wherein a mixture of MgCl<sub>2</sub> and Mg-alkoxide is precipitated together
with a Ti-compound to give a ZN catalyst.</p><p num="0008">EP-A-83 074 and EP-A-83 073 of Montedison disclose methods for producing
a ZN catalyst or a precursor thereof, wherein an emulsion or dispersion of Mg
and/or Ti compound is formed in an inert liquid medium or inert gas phase and
said system is reacted with an AI-alkyl compound to precipitate a solid
catalyst. According to examples said emulsion is then added to a larger
volume of Al-compound in hexane to cause the precipitation.

In EP-A-258 089 of Montedison an emulsion of a catalyst components, or a
precursor thereof, comprising a Mg and/or Ti compound is formed in
perfluoropolyether and the dispersed phase is reacted with a reducing and/or
halogenating agent to precipitate said catalyst components or a precursor 
thereof. According to the examples said emulsion is then added to a larger
volume of a solution of a halogenating agent and TiCl<sub>4</sub> -treatment is further
continued in the formed suspension to effect the surface treatment of the
particles.</p><p num="0009">In general, a drawback of such precipitation methods is the difficulty to control
the precipitation step and thus the morphology of the precipitating catalyst
particles.</p><p num="0010">Furthermore, the precipitation of the catalyst component(s) may often proceed
via a "tar-like" intermediate stage. Said undesired sticky precipitate
agglomerates easily and sticks to the walls of the reactor. The morphology of
the catalyst would then of course be lost.</p><p num="0011">Furthermore, in addition to above heterogeneous catalyst systems,
homogeneous catalyst systems, wherein the catalyst component(s) are used
in a form of a solution in the actual polymerisation process are also known in
the art. For instance, EP-A-536 840 of Enichem discloses i.a. the preparation
of a catalyst emulsion by contacting in an inert diluent a Mg dialkyl and Al
trichloride. This emulsified precursor is then contacted with at least one
compound of a transition metal to obtain the final catalyst in the form of an
emulsion. The emulsion is used as such for polymerisation of olefins.</p><p num="0012">The use of homogeneous catalysts in industrial applications has been limited
due to their fast deactivation behaviour. In case of emulsions also stability
problems may occur.</p><p num="0013">Accordingly, although much development work has been done in the field of
Ziegler-Natta catalysts, there remains a continuing search for alternative or
improved methods of producing ZN catalysts with desirable properties.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0014">The object of the present invention is to provide a further method for
producing solid Ziegler-Natta catalyst particles comprising at least one
catalyst component.</p><p num="0015">Another object of the present invention is to provide a new process for
producing solid particles of a Ziegler-Natta catalyst in a controlled manner,
whereby particles with a preferable morphology, such as a spherical shape,
an uniform particle size (a narrow particle size distribution) and/or
advantageous surface properties, can be obtained.</p><p num="0016">A further object of the present invention is to provide an olefin polymerisation
process using the catalyst prepared according to the process of the invention,
as well as a catalyst obtainable by the method of the invention.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0017"><sl><li>Fig. 1 illustrates the morphology of the catalyst particles of EXAMPLE 1</li><li>Fig. 2 illustrates the particle size distribution of Catalyst a of EXAMPLE 2</li><li>Fig. 3 illustrates the particle size distribution of Catalyst b of EXAMPLE 2</li></sl></p><heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0018">The invention is based on the finding that a solution which is prepared by
contacting at least: (a) a compound of group 1 to 3 of the Periodic Table
(IUPAC, Nomenclature of Inorganic Chemistry, 1989), with (b) a transition
metal compound of Group 4 to10 of the Periodic Table (IUPAC), or a
compound of an actinide or lanthanide; for forming an olefin polymerisation
catalyst component;

can be converted, in a controlled manner, to a solid particulate form with
advantageous properties:
<sl><li>by dispersing said solution to a solvent immiscible therewith and inert in
relation to said compounds,</li><li>to obtain an emulsion in which said solution forms the dispersed phase; and </li><li>by solidifying the catalyst component in the emulsion droplets.</li></sl></p><p num="0019">Surprisingly, the present conversion method enables to create the morphology
of the final catalyst <i>in situ</i> during the solidification step of the catalyst
component(s). The invention thus provides a controlled method to obtain
active catalyst particles with highly preferable morphology, e.g. with a
predetermined spherical shape, uniform particle size distribution and/or
desirable surface properties.</p><p num="0020">Moreover, the invention provides a process for producing an olefin
polymerisation catalyst, which comprises a catalyst component formed by
contacting at least: (a) a compound of group 1 to 3 of the Periodic Table
(IUPAC), with (b) a transition metal compound of group 4 to 10 of the Periodic
Table (IUPAC), or a compound of an actinide or lanthanide; in the form of
solid catalyst particles, comprising:
<sl><li>preparing a solution from said compounds;</li><li>dispersing said solution to a solvent immiscible therewith and inert in relation
to said compounds,</li><li>to obtain an emulsion in which said solution forms the dispersed phase;</li><li>and solidifying the catalyst component in the droplets; and optionally
recovering the solid catalyst particles.</li></sl></p><p num="0021">Alternatively, the invention provides a process for producing an olefin
polymerisation catalyst which comprises a catalyst component formed at least
from (a) a compound of group 1 to 3 of the Periodic Table (IUPAC) and (b) a
chlorine-containing transition metal compound of group 4 to 10 of the Periodic
Table (IUPAC) and/or a chlorine-containing compound of group 13 of the
Periodic Table (IUPAC); in the form of solid catalyst particles, comprising:
<sl><li>preparing a solution from said compounds;</li><li>dispersing said solution to a solvent immiscible therewith and inert in relation
to said compounds,</li><li>to obtain an emulsion in which said solution forms the dispersed phase;</li><li>and solidifying the catalyst component in the droplets; and optionally 
recovering the solid catalyst particles.</li></sl></p><p num="0022">In the recovery step the solid catalyst particles may be isolated, optionally
washed and dried in a manner known in the art to obtain said catalyst as
particulate solids.</p><p num="0023">The term "the continuous phase is inert in relation to said compounds" means
herein that the continuous phase is chemically inert with respect to the
solidification reactions of the catalyst component occurring in the droplets, i.e.
no significant solidification reactions of the catalyst component take place
between the contents of the continuous phase and the contents of the
dispersed phase. Thus the solid particles of the catalyst are formed in the
droplets from the compounds which originate from the dispersed phase (i.e.
are provided to the emulsion in a solution dispersed into the continuous
phase).</p><p num="0024">In one embodiment of the invention said catalyst component may be formed,
in addition to above said compounds, also from further compounds, which can
be added to the solution of the catalyst component forming compounds before
or after the dispersing step. Such further compounds, may be those
conventionally used in the art, such as an aluminium compound and/or an
internal donor compound, preferably an aluminium compound, such as an
alkyl aluminium halide.</p><p num="0025">Furthermore, in addition to the catalyst component as defined above, the
catalyst of the invention may comprise further catalyst component(s), such as
a cocatalyst and/or an external donor compound known in the art. The further
catalyst component(s) can be incorporated to the catalyst during the
preparation method of the invention, or added separately with the catalyst of
the invention at the actual polymerisation step.</p><p num="0026">Accordingly, the invention enables the inclusion of all the desired compounds
to the dispersed phase and thus the solidification of the final composition of 
the catalyst component(s). As a consequence, the obtained particles need no
subsequent surface treatment(s) normally required for supported catalyst
systems of the prior art. Thus, the preferable morphology achievable with the
present two-phase solidification method can be maintained.</p><p num="0027">Moreover, in the catalyst particles prepared according to the invention, the
active catalyst sites can be evenly distributed throughout the particle
compared e.g. to the prior art supported systems.</p><p num="0028">If desired, however, the catalyst comprising the catalyst component(s) of the
invention can further be surface treated with further compound(s) in a manner
known in the art.</p><heading><b>Dispersed phase</b></heading><p num="0029">The solution to be dispersed into the immiscible solvent can be any solution
prepared from the catalyst component(s) forming compounds, provided that it
is in a form of a liquid when dispersed into the continuous phase. Said term
"solution" is understood herein broadly to include any "solutions" prepared by
dissolving the compounds to (a) one of said compounds in liquid form, or (b)
to an inert solvent, as well as "solutions" prepared from (c) melts of said
compounds; as described herein below.</p><p num="0030">In case of an inert solvent, any suitable solvent which dissolves said
compounds may be used, preferably an organic solvent, such as aliphatic or
aromatic hydrocarbon, e.g. pentane, hexane, heptane, toluene, benzene etc.
A mixture of solvents may also be used, provided that said mixture dissolves
the compounds and is immiscible with the continuous phase at least during
the emulsion formation step.</p><heading><b>Continuous phase</b></heading><p num="0031">The solvent used to form the continuous phase is chosen, as stated above, to
be inert and immiscible at least at the conditions (e.g. temperature) used
during the dispersing step. Said solvent may also be a mixture of one or more
solvents.

Furthermore, the solvent is chosen so that the compounds and possible
intermediate(s) thereof which form the solidifying catalyst component(s), as
well as the solidified catalyst, are practically insoluble or only poorly soluble to
the continuous phase.</p><p num="0032">In a preferred embodiment of the invention said solvent forming the
continuous phase is an inert solvent including halogenated organic solvents,
particularly fluorinated organic solvents, preferably perfluorinated organic
solvents, e.g. perfluorinated hydrocarbons and functionalised derivatives
thereof, such as octadecafluorooctane and perfluorinated ethers,
octadecafluorooctane being particularly preferred.</p><heading><b>Dispersing step</b></heading><p num="0033">The emulsion can be formed by any means known in the art: by mixing, such
as by stirring said solution vigorously to said solvent forming the continuous
phase or by means of mixing mills, or by means of ultra sonic wave. A further
possibility is that the conditions are adjusted to form first a miscible
homogeneous mixture and then readjusted to cause the separation of the two
phases and the formation of the emulsion, as by changing the temperature of
the system. The emulsion state can be maintained, as by appropriate stirring.</p><p num="0034">The ratio of catalyst component(s) forming solution and the solvent immiscible
therewith is chosen so that the first solution forms the discontinuous phase
(droplets) in the two phase system.</p><p num="0035">Additionally, emulsifying agents/emulsion stabilisers can be used in a manner
known in the art for facilitating the formation and/or stability of the emulsion.
For the said purposes e.g. surfactants, e.g. a class based on acrylic polymers, 
or halogenated hydrocarbons, such as perfluorinated hydrocarbons having a
functionalised terminal, optionally formed in situ, can be used.

Additional agents and/or compounds can be added to the system in any stage
of the dispersing and/or solidification step, if needed.</p><p num="0036">The droplet size and size distribution of the formed discontinuous phase can
be selected or controlled in a manner known in the art, i.a. by the choice of the
device for emulsion formation and by the energy put into emulsification.</p><p num="0037">In the preparation process of the invention the solution may already contain all
the compounds (to be added) before the dispersing step thereof. Alternatively,
e.g. depending on the reactivity of the compounds, the dispersed phase can
be formed first from one or more of the compounds and, thereafter, the other
compound(s) can be added separately to said dispersed phase. Said other
compounds can be added in a form of a solution or already in a form of an
emulsion. Portion-wise additions of the dispersed phase are also possible.</p><heading><b>Solidification step</b> </heading><p num="0038">The solidification of the catalyst component(s) in the dispersed droplets can
be effected in various ways, e.g. by causing or accelerating the formation of
said solid catalyst forming reaction products of the compounds present in the
droplets.

This can be effected, depending on the used compounds and/or the desired
solidification rate, with or without a temperature change of the system.</p><p num="0039">In case all the reacting compounds are already present in the dispersed
droplets, the rate of the solidification reactions occurring in said droplets may
be accelerated by increasing the temperature of the dispersed phase in the
emulsion system.</p><p num="0040">In a further embodiment, the solidification reactions of the compounds are
started after the formation of the emulsion system. Accordingly, a solution of 
one or more of the starting compounds of a catalyst component(s) is first
dispersed into the inert, immiscible solvent, and thereafter, the other(s) of the
starting compounds is added to said first dispersed phase to start the
solidification reactions therein. Again, heating or cooling can be used during or
after such additions.</p><p num="0041">Alternatively the solidification may be effected by removing the solvent from
the droplets or in case of a molten liquid catalyst by cooling the system.</p> <p num="0042">The solidification may also be controlled by the reaction time.</p> <p num="0043">Moreover, the solidification may be effected during the dispersing (droplet
formation) step or after the emulsion system is formed; optionally, while
heating or cooling the system.</p> <p num="0044">If desired, the emulsion system may be subjected to a very rapid temperature
change to cause a fast/immediate (e.g. in 0.1 to 10 s, such as in few seconds)
solidification in the dispersed system.</p><p num="0045">The appropriate temperature change, i.e. an increase or a decrease in the
temperature of an emulsion system, required for the desired solidification rate
of the components cannot be limited to any specific range, but naturally
depends on the emulsion system, i.a. on the used compounds and the
concentrations/ratios thereof, and is chosen accordingly. It is also evident that
any techniques may be used to provide sufficient heating or cooling effect to
the dispersed system to cause the desired solidification.

In one embodiment the heat treatment is effected by bringing, e.g. dispersing,
such as spraying or preferably siphoning, the emulsion system to an inert
receiving medium. The temperature of the receiving system can be
significantly higher than that of the emulsion to cause an instant solidification
of the reaction product in the droplets. Temperature difference of e.g. 10 to
100°C, or 20 to 90°C, such as 50 to 80°C, e.g. 70 to 80°C can be used. The
receiving medium can be gaseous, e.g. air, or a liquid, preferably a solvent, 
and suitably the same as used as the continuous phase in the formation of the
emulsion. Thus e.g. a perfluorinated hydrocarbon as defined above or a
mixture thereof with other solvents, e.g. with an aliphatic or aromatic
hydrocarbon as defined above, can be used. Preferably the receiving medium
is mixed during the siphoning step. The siphoning techniques are known in
the art.</p><p num="0046">The solidified catalyst particles may be subjected to washing step(s).</p><p num="0047">In a still further embodiment of the invention the catalyst component(s) are
prepolymerised within the droplets to obtain the solid catalyst particles. This
can be effected by adding an olefin monomer in liquid or in gaseous form to
the dispersed phase and by polymerising said monomer within the droplets in
the presence of the catalyst composition. Alternatively, an olefin monomer(s)
can be used as a solvent for the dispersed phase which is then polymerised
after the dispersing said solution. Olefins and reaction conditions for the
prepolymerisation can be chosen in a manner known in the field.</p><p num="0048">In the method of the invention the droplet shape of the particles may be
substantially maintained. The formed particles may have an average size
range of 1 to 500 µm , e.g. 5 to 500 µm, advantageously 5 to 200 µm or 10 to
150 µm. Even an average size range of 5 to 50 µm is possible.
Advantageously, the particles are essentially spherical in shape.</p><p num="0049">One of the further advantages of the solidification of the dispersed droplets
according to the invention is that the undesirable tar formation can be
avoided.</p><heading><b>Catalyst compounds and preparation of the solution</b></heading><p num="0050">The idea of the present invention lies in the emulsion/solidification method
which provides the advantageous morphology of the final catalyst. Therefore
this invention is not limited to a specific ZN catalyst composition, but covers
the preparation of any ZN catalyst, the starting material of which can be 
provided in liquid state during the preparation step. E.g. ZN catalysts for
(co)polymerising ethene (PE catalyst) or propene (PP catalyst) can be
prepared.

The various possibilities of the compounds and combinations are within the
skills of a person in the field. Accordingly, the solution of catalyst forming
compounds can be formed by contacting:
<sl><li>1) at least one compound of group 1 to 3, preferably group 2, of the Periodic
Table (IUPAC), such as a Mg compound, having a general formula
selected from:
<sl><li><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Mg(OR<sub>1</sub>)<sub>2-n</sub>X<sub>n</sub></st32:che>
wherein each R<sub>1</sub> is independently a C<sub>1-20</sub>hydrocarbyl
group, e.g. C<sub>2-15</sub> group, preferably C<sub>3-10</sub> group, such as C<sub>4-8</sub> group, e.g.
linear or branched alkyl, aryl, aralkyl, or alkaryl, which may optionally be
substituted with halogen; each X is independently a halogen, preferably
chlorine; n is 0, 1 or 2;</li><li><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Mg(OR<sub>1</sub>)<sub>2-n</sub>(R<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub></st32:che>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> and n are as defined above in formula (I);
each R<sub>2</sub> is independently a hydrocarbyl, e.g. linear or branched C<sub>1-20</sub>alkyl;</li><li><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">MgX<sub>2</sub>.mTi(OR<sub>1</sub>)<sub>4</sub></st32:che>
wherein X and R<sub>1</sub> are as described above in
formula (I); 0.1 ≤ m ≤ 3; and/or</li><li>complexes of MgX<sub>2</sub> with electron-donor compounds;</li></sl></li><li>2) with at least one transition metal compound of Group 4 to 10, or a
compound of lanthanide or actinide, preferably a transition compound of
group 4 to 6, more preferably of group 4, of the Periodic Table (IUPAC),
such as a Ti compound. Particularly, a tetravalent Ti compound can be
used. Examples of such compounds are:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">TiX<sub>4</sub></st32:che>
wherein X is defined as above in formula (I), such as
Cl;
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Ti(OR<sub>1</sub>)<sub>4-p</sub>X<sub>p</sub></st32:che>
wherein X and R<sub>1</sub> are as defined above in formula (I) 
p is 0, 1, 2 or 3;

and optionally with further compound(s), e.g.</li><li>3) optionally with at least one compound of group 13 of the Periodic Table
(IUPAC), preferably an aluminium compound, such as
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">AI(R<sub>1</sub>)<sub>x</sub>X<sub>3-x</sub></st32:che>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> and X are as defined above in formula (I)
and is 0 ≤ x &lt; 3; e.g. dimethyl aluminium chloride, diethyl aluminium
chloride, diisobutyl aluminium chloride, ethyl aluminium dichloride (EADC)
and methyl aluminium dichloride; and/or</li><li>4) optionally with at least one (internal) electron donor, e.g. those known in
the art for (co)polymerising propylene and higher olefins including organic
compounds containing oxygen, nitrogen, sulphur and/or phosporous, such
as organic acids, organic acid anhydrides, organic acid esters, alcohols,
ethers, aldehydes, ketones, amines, amine oxides, amides, thiols, various
phosporous acid esters and amides, and the like, added as such or formed
in situ (see also WO 00 08074 and WO 00 08073)</li></sl></p><p num="0051">As the chlorine-containing compound used in an alternative embodiment of
the invention together with a compound of group 1 to 3 of the Periodic Table,
e.g. those chlorine containing Al and/or Ti compounds, such as an aluminium
alkyl compound and/or a tetravalent titanium compound each containing
chlorine as listed above, can be used.</p><p num="0052">As mentioned above the solid catalyst particles may contain further catalyst
component(s), such as cocatalysts and/or external donor(s); depending on the
used polymerisation process, in a manner known in the art. As the cocatalyst
,e.g. conventional activators based on compounds of group 13 of the Periodic
Table (IUPAC), e.g. organo aluminium, such as aluminium alkyl compounds
(e.g. triethylaluminium) compounds, can be mentioned. Additionally, in case of
the (co)polymerisation of polypropylene or higher olefins, one or more external 
donors can be used which may be selected e.g. from silanes or from the list of
internal donor of point (4) above.</p><p num="0053">It is also possible to include other catalyst component(s) than said ZN
components to the catalyst of the invention.</p><p num="0054">The used amounts/ratios of the compounds to keep the made catalyst
composition in liquid state during the emulsion formation step are also within
the skills of a person in the field. Such solutions can be prepared e.g.
according or analogously to methods described in the prior art literature. As
an example:
<sl><li>(a) by dissolving a magnesium compound, e.g. Mg halide, such as MgCl<sub>2</sub>,
optionally in elevated temperature, in a carboxylic acid, an amine or,
preferably, an alcohol, e.g. a mono alcohol, R<sub>1</sub>OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is as defined
above in formula (I), e.g. alkyl, such as n-butanol, or phenol, optionally in the
presence of an inert solvent, in a manner described e.g. in US 5 212 133, US
5 188 999, EP 713 886 and WO 98 44009; and by adding the other
compounds of the invention;</li><li>(b) by forming a solution of a Mg compound with an Al compound as such in
elevated temperature, or in the presence of an aromatic component and/or a
chlorinated hydrocarbon, analogously to the methods described in EP 536
840 and/or EP 083 073/EP 083 074; and, preferably, by adding a transition
metal compound, e.g. TiCl<sub>4</sub>, and optional other compounds to the obtained
liquid composition while keeping the solution in liquid state for the dispersing
step;</li><li>(c) by heating alkoxides of Mg and Ti, or a combination of halogenides and
alkoxides of Mg and Ti. Alternatively, Mg halogenide and Ti alkoxides can be
treated with excess of HCI to form a solution. See e.g. EP 876 318 for
preparing such Mg- and Ti based solution, wherein the other compounds of
the invention can be added; </li><li>(d) by using the principles described in EP 856 013, wherein Mg-component,
e.g. Mg alkoxides, Mg hydrocarbyl alkoxides or Mg hydrocarbyl, in hexane +
(CO<sub>2</sub> or SO<sub>2</sub>) form a Mg-based solution. To said solution the other compounds
of the invention can be added;</li><li>(e) by reacting a magnesium hydrocarbyloxy compound with a chlorine-containing
compound in a non-polar hydrocarbon solvent; and by adding a
chlorine containing tetravalent titanium compound, e.g. analogously to WO 01
55230, to form a soluble Mg-Al-Ti complex to be used in the present invention.</li></sl></p><p num="0055">The preparation of the solution may also result in a two phase liquid/liquid
form already in the preparation step of said solution. Such system can be
subjected as such to the solidification step or added to an immiscible solvent
of the invention as such or after the separation of the catalyst forming phase.</p><p num="0056">In one preferred embodiment of the invention the liquid catalyst is prepared by
contacting a magnesium dihydrocarbyl compound, e.g. magnesium dialkyl,
such as butyloctyl-Mg (BOMAG), with an alcohol R<sub>1</sub>OH, wherein R<sub>1</sub> is as
defined above, e.g. 2-ethyl-1-hexanol (EHA). To this solution an aluminium
compound of formula Al(R<sub>1</sub>)<sub>x</sub>X<sub>3-x</sub>, wherein R<sub>1</sub>, X and x are as defined above,
preferably Al alkyl halide, such as EtAlCl<sub>2</sub>, and/or a titanium compound, such
as TiCl<sub>4</sub>, is then added. In case both the Al-and the Ti-compounds are added
to Mg-R<sub>1</sub>OH complex, then preferably the Al-compound is added first. The
solution may contain additional solvents as described above, e.g. an aliphatic
or aromatic solvent, such as n-heptane. Said solution can be formed at a
temperature range between the ambient temperature to 100°C, e:g. 40 to
80°C, such as 50 to 70°C, e.g. 60°C. If TiCl<sub>4</sub> is added to the solution, this is
preferably done at or below room temperature. The obtained solution is then
dispersed, e.g. by mixing, to an immiscible solvent, e.g. to a perfluorinated
hydrocarbon as defined above. The mixing is suitably carried out at room
temperature, but e.g. lower or elevated temperatures may also be used. The
solidification may be effected by changing rapidly the temperature of said 
emulsion system, e.g. by siphoning the emulsion to a receiving medium as
disclosed above.</p><p num="0057">In a further embodiment, a magnesium alkyl is reacted with R<sub>1</sub>OH as defined
above and, optionally, with an aluminium compound, such as an alkyl
aluminium halide, e.g. EtAlCl<sub>2</sub>, to form a first solution, which is dispersed to an
inert solvent, such as perfluorinated hydrocarbon as defined above. To the
obtained dispersed phase, TiCl<sub>4</sub>-solution is then added separately to cause
the solidification of the thus formed catalyst component. The emulsion system
can be heated during and/or after the addition of the TiCl<sub>4</sub>. Additional inert
solvents as defined above can also be used in the formation of said solutions.
Furthermore, the dispersing order of the first solution and TiCl<sub>4</sub>-solution can
be changed.</p><p num="0058">Generally, in the final solid catalyst particles, the molar ratio of Mg:Ti can be
e.g. between 10:1 to 1:10, preferably 5:1 to 1:1. The molar ratio of Ti:Al can
be e.g. between 10:1 to 1:2, e.g. 3:1 to 1:1. Furthermore, a suitable molar
ratio of Mg:R<sub>1</sub>OH is between 1:1 to 1:4, preferably 1:1.5 to 1:3.</p><heading><b>Polymerisation process</b></heading><p num="0059">As mentioned above the catalyst particles of the invention can be used as
such or together with a separate cocatalyst and/or an electron donor, as a
Ziegler-Natta catalyst for the (co)polymerisation of an olefin in a manner
known in the art. It is also possible to combine said catalyst with one or more
other Zn and/or non-ZN catalysts.</p><p num="0060">The olefin to be polymerised using the catalyst system of the invention can be
any olefin polymerisable in a coordination polymerisation including an alphaolefin
alone or as a mixture with one or more comonomers. Preferable olefins
are ethylene or propene, or a mixture of ethylene or propene with one or more
alpha-olefin(s). Preferable comonomers are C2-C12 olefins, preferably C4-C10
olefins, such as 1-butene, isobutene, 1-pentene, 1-hexene, 4-methyl-1-pentene, 
1-heptene, 1-octene, 1-nonene, 1-decene, as well as diene, such as
butadiene, 1,7-octadiene and 1,4-hexadiene, or cyclic olefins, such as
norbornene, and any mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0061">Polyethylene and any copolymers thereof are particularly contemplated, as
are polypropylene homopolymers and any copolymers thereof.</p><p num="0062">Polymerisation may be effected in one or more, e.g. one, two or three
polymerisation reactors, using conventional polymerisation techniques, in
particular gas phase, solution phase, slurry or bulk polymerisation.
Polymerisation can be a batch or continuous polymerisation process.
Generally a combination of slurry (or bulk) and at least one gas phase reactor
is preferred, particularly with gas phase operation coming last.</p><p num="0063">For slurry reactors, the reaction temperature will generally be in the range of
40 to 110 °C (e.g. 60-110°C), the reactor pressure will generally be in the
range 5 to 80 bar (e.g. 50-60 bar), and the residence time will generally be in
the range 0.3 to 5 hours (e.g. 0.5 to 2 hours). The diluent used will generally
be an aliphatic hydrocarbon having a boiling point in the range -70 to +100
°C. In such reactors, polymerisation may, if desired, be effected under
supercritical conditions.</p><p num="0064">For gas phase reactors, the reaction temperature used will generally be in the
range 60 to 115 °C (e.g. 70 to 110 °C), the reactor pressure will generally be in
the range 10 to 25 bar, and the residence time will generally be 1 to 8 hours.</p><p num="0065">Generally the quantity of catalyst used will depend upon the nature of the
catalyst, the reactor types and conditions and the properties desired for the
polymer product. Conventional catalyst quantities, such as described in the
publications referred herein, may be used.</p><p num="0066">With the method of the invention a catalyst system with a good morphology is
obtained and the catalyst exhibits high catalytic activity. The morphology 
correlates with product morphology and - the so-called "replica effect". Thus
the catalyst leads to a polymer which also has advantageous properties, e.g.
high bulk density.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLES</b></heading><p num="0067">The following examples are provided by way of illustration of the invention. All
the used starting materials and solvents are commercially available:
<sl><li>(C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>9</sub>)<sub>1,5</sub>Mg(C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>17</sub>)<sub>0,5</sub> in 20 wt-% heptane solution: supplied by Crompton,
Germany (BOMAG); EtAlCl<sub>2</sub> in 18.5 wt-% toluene solution: Crompton,
Germany (EADC); triethylaluminium in 10 wt-% heptane solution (TEA-10) or</li><li>in 20 wt-% heptane solution (TEA-20): Crompton, Germany; TiCl<sub>4</sub>: Aldrich,
Germany; octadecafluorooctane: P&amp;M Scientific Industrial Association,
Russia.</li></sl>
MFR was determined according to ISO 1133 using 190°C, load as subscript.
FRR means MFR<sub>21</sub>:MFR<sub>2</sub>. The particle size distribution was analysed by
Coulter.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 1</b></heading><heading><b>Catalyst</b></heading><p num="0068">In a 20 ml septa bottle 1.2 ml (1.05 mmol) of BOMAG was added at room
temperature in inert conditions. Then 0.328 ml (2.10 mmol) of 2-ethyl-hexanol
was added and the components were allowed to react at 60 °C for 30 min
while mixing with a magnetic stirrer. After this the solution was cooled down
to room temperature, 0.745 ml (1.05 mmol) of EADC was added and the
obtained mixture was mixed at 60 °C for 30 min. After this the solution was
cooled down to room temperature and 0.115 ml (1.05 mmol) of TiCl<sub>4</sub> was
added. The obtained solution was dispersed by mixing (105 rpm) in 4.0 ml of
octadecafluorooctane to create an emulsion.</p><p num="0069">In another 150 ml glass reactor 32 ml of octadecafluorooctane was introduced
in inert conditions together with 11 ml of heptane. The solvent mixture was 
stirred by a propeller (mixing speed was 300 rpm). The temperature was
risen to 90 - 95 °C.</p><p num="0070">The solidification was effected by siphoning the catalyst complex emulsion in
small portions, during 10 min into the hot receiving solution. After the
siphoning the droplets were allowed to stabilise in the receiving vessel for 15
min. After this the receiving solution was cooled down, octadecafluorooctane
was removed by siphoning, and the catalyst was washed two times with 30 ml
portions of n-heptane. Morphology was good in the resulting catalyst material:
<sl><li>spherical particles with an average particle size of 70 µm.

Composition of the catalyst: Mg 6.99 wt-%, Ti 7.42 wt-%. The added molar
ratio of Mg:Ti:AI had been 1:1:1 and the obtained catalyst complex of the
invention shows the molar ratio of Mg:Ti:AI of 1.9:1:0.3. The spherical
particles with a smooth surface are illustrated in Figure 1.</li></sl></p><heading><b>Test polymerisations</b></heading><p num="0071">The catalyst was tested in a homo-polymerisation of ethene. Two different
polymerisation conditions were used in order to produce both high and low
molecular flow rate material (HMFR and LMFR). 5 bar of H<sub>2</sub> pressure
corresponded to LMFR polymerisation conditions, and 17.5 bar to the HMFR
conditions. TEA-10 was used as the cocatalyst. An Al/Ti molar ratio of 15 was
used in the homopolymerisations (0.9- 1.5 ml TEA).</p><p num="0072">1800 ml (1.127 kg, 15.6 mol) of pentane was introduced into a 3 l autoclave
reactor and the temperature was adjusted to 90 °C. About 30 mg of Catalyst
was added into a feed vessel together with 10 ml (6.3 g, 87 mmol) of pentane.
The cocatalyst was added into another feed vessel. The cocatalyst was first
let into the reactor and thereafter Catalyst. An additional feed vessel was
connected to provide the 5 and 17.5 bar of H<sub>2</sub> pressure (110 - 390 mmol).

The polymerisation was started by introducing H<sub>2</sub> together with the ethene
monomer. A total pressure of 13.7 bar was maintained by the ethene feed
throughout the polymerisation. The polymerisation was carried out for 1 h at 
90 °C. The polymerisation was stopped by venting off the monomer and the
pentane.</p><p num="0073">For the comparison the above polymerisation test was carried out but using a
silica supported catalyst as Reference catalyst prepared according to EP 688
794 of Borealis, example 3, except silica particles with an average particle
size of 20 µm (supplied by Grace) were used.</p><heading><b>Polymerisation results obtained using Catalyst and Reference catalyst</b></heading><p num="0074"><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">The polymerisation results in LMFR and HMFR conditions</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Unit/Catalyst</entry><entry align="center">Catalyst</entry><entry align="center">Reference catalyst</entry></row><row><entry align="center">LFMR</entry><entry align="center">Activity, kg PE/g cath</entry><entry align="center">14.60</entry><entry align="center">4.6</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">MFR<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="center">0.52</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">MFR<sub>5</sub></entry><entry align="center">3.1</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">MFR<sub>21</sub></entry><entry align="center">31.4</entry><entry align="center">22.0</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">FRR (21/2)</entry><entry align="center">31.4</entry><entry align="center">42.0</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">FRR (21/5)</entry><entry align="center">10.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">HMFR</entry><entry align="center">Activity, kg PE/g cat,h</entry><entry align="center">5.17</entry><entry align="center">2.33</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">MFR<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">66</entry><entry align="center">72</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><b>EXAMPLE 2</b></heading><heading><b>Preparation of Complex</b></heading><p num="0075">7.9 g (60.8 mmol) of 2-ethyl-1-hexanol (ROH) was added slowly to 27.8 g
(33.2 mmol) of BOMAG. The reaction temperature was kept under 35°C. This
complex was used in the following catalyst preparation. The molar ratio
ROH/BOMAG was 1.83.</p><heading><b>Catalyst a</b></heading><p num="0076">0.6ml of TiCl<sub>4</sub> (5.5 mmol Ti ) and 0,6ml of n-heptane was added to 45 ml of
octadecafluorooctane. The mixture was stirred (430 rpm) at 75°C. 5,31 g g (5.5
mmol Mg) of the above prepared Complex was added and the mixture stirred 
for 1 hour at 75°C. The catalyst was washed once with 25ml of n-heptane,
once with 25ml of n-pentane, dried at 75°C for 0,5 hour. Composition of the
catalyst was: Mg 7.48 wt-%, Ti 10.82 wt-%. Mean particle size: 54 µm. The
particle size distribution is illustrated in Figure 2.</p><heading><b>Catalyst b</b></heading><p num="0077">0.1ml of TEA-10 was added to 5.3 g (5.5 mmol) of the above Complex and the
obtained solution was mixed (mechanical stirrer, 500 rpm) at 25°C to 60 ml of
octadecafluorooctane. A separate TiCl<sub>4</sub> -emulsion was prepared by mixing
0.6ml (5.5 mmol) of TiCl<sub>4</sub> in 0.6ml n-heptane with 5ml of octadecafluorooctane.
The TiCl<sub>4</sub> -emulsion was then added to the emulsion of Complex and TEA-10.

Then the emulsion was stirred for one hour at 25°C. The catalyst was washed
with n-heptane and n-pentane and dried for 1 hour at 40-50°C. Composition of
the catalyst: Mg 7.08 wt-%, Ti 9.9 wt-%. Mean particle size: 82 µm. The
particle size distribution is illustrated in Figure 3.</p><heading><b>Catalyst c</b></heading><p num="0078">0.1ml of TEA-10 was added to 5.3 g (5.5 mmol) of the above Complex and the
obtained solution was added to 80 ml of octadecafluorooctane and the
obtained emulsion was stirred at 5°C. A separate mixture of 0.6ml (5.5 mmol)
of TiCl<sub>4</sub>, 0.6ml n-heptane and 5ml of octadecafluorooctane was mixed and
cooled to +5°C and then added to the emulsion. Then the emulsion was
stirred for one hour at room temperature. The catalyst was washed with n-heptane
and n-pentane and dried for 1 hour at 40-50°C.Composition of the
catalyst: Mg 6.89 wt-%, Ti 10.07 wt-%. Mean particle size: 98 µm.</p><heading><b>Catalyst d</b></heading><p num="0079">0,89ml of EADC was added to 5.3 g (5.5 mmol) of the above Complex, the
mixture was added to 62 ml of octadecafluorooctane and the emulsion was 
stirred at 75°C. 0,6ml (5.5 mmol) of TiCl<sub>4</sub> , was added to the emulsion. Then
the emulsion was stirred for one hour at room temperature. The catalyst was
washed with heptane and pentane and dried for 1 hour at 40-50°C.
Composition of the catalyst: Mg 7.75 wt-%, Ti 11.01 wt-%. Mean particle size:
56 µm.</p><heading><b>Test Polymerisations</b></heading><p num="0080"><b>Catalyst a, Catalyst b, Catalyst c and Catalyst d</b> were tested in ethylene
homopolymerization as follows: 500 kPa hydrogen was pressurised in 500 ml
bomb. 1.8 l of n-pentane was filled into the 3 I reactor and the temperature
was increased to 90°C. Catalyst and TEA-20 as the cocatalyst with Al/Ti mole
ratio 20 - 50 were added and ethylene was fed through the hydrogen charging
vessel. A total pressure of 14.4 kPa was kept with continuous ethylene feed,
so that ethylene partial pressure was 4.4 kPa. Polymerisation was continued
for one hour.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Homopolymerisation results obtained with <b>Catalysts a, b, c</b> and d</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>Catalyst a</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Catalyst b</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Catalyst c</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Catalyst d</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Activity, kg PE/g cat</entry><entry align="center">33.1</entry><entry align="center">26.3</entry><entry align="center">32.2</entry><entry align="center">15.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Activity, kg PE/g Ti</entry><entry align="center">306</entry><entry align="center">266</entry><entry align="center">320</entry><entry align="center">183</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MFR2</entry><entry align="center">0.46</entry><entry align="center">0.35</entry><entry align="center">0.37</entry><entry align="center">0.57</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MFR21</entry><entry align="center">13.9</entry><entry align="center">10.7</entry><entry align="center">9.37</entry><entry align="center">17.23</entry></row><row><entry align="left">FRR21/2</entry><entry align="center">29.9</entry><entry align="center">30.7</entry><entry align="center">25.3</entry><entry align="center">30.2</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process for producing an olefin polymerisation catalyst, comprising a
catalyst component formed by contacting at least: (a) a compound of
group 1 to 3 of the Periodic Table (IUPAC), with (b) a transition metal
compound of group 4 to 10 of the Periodic Table (IUPAC), or a compound
of an actinide or lanthanide;
in the form of solid catalyst particles, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>preparing a solution from the compounds;</claim-text><claim-text>dispersing said solution to a solvent immiscible therewith and inert in
relation to said compounds,</claim-text><claim-text>to obtain an emulsion in which said solution forms the dispersed phase;
and</claim-text><claim-text>solidifying the catalyst component in the dispersed droplets; and
optionally</claim-text><claim-text>recovering the solid catalyst particles.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A process for converting a solution, which is prepared by contacting at
least: (a) a compound of group 1 to 3 of the Periodic Table (IUPAC), and
(b) a transition metal compound of Group 4 to10 of the Periodic Table
(IUPAC), or a compound of an actinide or lanthanide; to a solid particulate
form for forming an olefin polymerisation, catalyst component; comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>dispersing said solution to a solvent immiscible therewith and inert in
relation to the compounds,</claim-text><claim-text>to obtain an emulsion in which said solution forms the dispersed phase;
and</claim-text><claim-text>solidifying the catalyst component in the dispersed droplets.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A process for producing an olefin polymerisation catalyst, comprising a
catalyst component contacting at least: (a) a compound of group 1 to 3 of
the Periodic Table (IUPAC) with (b) a chlorine-containing transition metal
compound of group 4 to 10 of the Periodic Table (IUPAC) and/or a
chlorine-containing compound of group 13 of the Periodic Table (IUPAC);
in the form of solid catalyst particles, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>preparing a solution from said compounds;</claim-text><claim-text>dispersing said solution to a solvent immiscible therewith and inert in
relation to the compounds,</claim-text><claim-text>to obtain an emulsion in which said solution forms the dispersed phase;
and</claim-text><claim-text>solidifying the catalyst component in the dispersed droplets; and
optionally</claim-text><claim-text>recovering the solid catalyst particles.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A process according to any of claims 1 to 3, wherein the solidification is
effected by reacting the compounds present in the droplets dispersed in
said inert continuous phase.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A process according to any of claims 1 to 3, wherein a melt is prepared
from the compounds and said melt is dispersed in said inert solvent, and
the droplets of the melt is solidified within said continuous phase.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A process according to any of claims 1 to 5, wherein the solidification is
effected by dispersing the solution prepared at least from the compound
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) and the compound (b) to said inert solvent, and by subjecting the
formed emulsion to a temperature change.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A process according to any of claims 1 to 6, wherein the solidification is
effected by first dispersing a solution of the compound (a) to the solvent
and then adding the compound (b) to the dispersed phase, and, optionally,
by subjecting the formed emulsion to a temperature change.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A process according to any of claims 1 to 7, wherein the formed emulsion
system is further dispersed into an inert receiving medium with a different
temperature to cause a rapid solidification of the dispersed catalyst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A process according to any of claims 1 to 8, wherein the dispersed phase
is formed from a solution prepared by contacting (a) a compound of a
group 2 of the Periodic Table (IUPAC), with (b) a compound of a group 4
of the Periodic Table (IUPAC), and, optionally, with (c) a further catalyst
component forming compound selected from aluminium compounds.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A process according to any of claim 9, wherein the catalyst component is
formed by contacting in a solution a Mg compound with a Ti compound
and/or an Al compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A process according to any of claims 10, wherein the catalyst component
is formed by reacting a magnesium dialkyl compound, an alcohol, an alkyl
aluminium halide and a tetra valent titanium compound in the droplets
dispersed in said inert continuous phase.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A process according to any of claims 11, wherein the catalyst component
is formed by reacting a magnesium dialkyl with an alcohol of formula
R1OH, wherein R1 is a linear or branched C2-10alkyl, and adding to the
obtained solution ethyl aluminium dichloride and thereafter titanium
tetrachloride.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A process according to any of claims 1 to 4, or 6 to12, wherein an inert
solvent is used for the preparation of said solution, which solvent is
selected from a linear or cyclic alkane or alkene, an aromatic hydrocarbon
and/or a halogen-containing hydrocarbon.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A process according to claim 1 to 1.3, wherein the inert, immiscible solvent.
as the continuous phase comprises a fluorinated hydrocarbon or a
functionalised derivative thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A process according to claim 1 to14, wherein said continuous phase
comprises a perfluorinated hydrocarbon.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A process for (co)polymerising an olefin using the catalyst produced
according to any of preceding claims and optionally a cocatalyst and/or an
external donor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A catalyst for (co)polymerisation of an olefin, comprising a catalyst
component formed by contacting at least (a) a compound of group 1 to 3 of
the Periodic Table (IUPAC) and (b) a transition metal compound of group 4
to 10 of the Periodic Table (IUPAC), or a compound of an actinide or
lanthanide, in the form of solid catalyst particles, obtainable by a method of
any of claims 1 to 16.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>