<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1394137-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1394137" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="22760733" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040303"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1394137-A2" status="new" fvid="23984562"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1394137</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20040303</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03254276-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03254276</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030704</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-20508502-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20508502</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020725</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  20/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  20/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/42        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/46        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/473       20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  20/10D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  28/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/46</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/473</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Zusamensetzung für das Zementieren von Röhrensträngen in Bohrlöchern</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Composition for cementing a pipe in a well bore</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition pour la cimentation d'un tubage dans un puits de forage</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-5897699-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5897699</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6063738-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6063738</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>AMERICAN PETROLEUM INSTITUTE: 'API Specification For Materials And Testing For Well Cements' API SPECIFICATION vol. 10, no. 5, 01 July 1990,</text><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERV INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERVICES, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Halliburton Energy Services, Inc.</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 1431</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73536</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>BRENNEIS DARREL C</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHATTERJI JITEN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>CROMWELL ROGER S</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KING BOBBY J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BRENNEIS, DARREL C.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHATTERJI, JITEN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CROMWELL, ROGER S.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KING, BOBBY J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BRENNEIS, DARREL C.</last-name><address><street>Route 2, Box 195</street><city>Marlow, Oklahoma 73055</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CHATTERJI, JITEN</last-name><address><street>2213 Scott Lane</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73572</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CROMWELL, ROGER S.</last-name><address><street>128 East Nevada</street><city>Walters, Oklahoma 73572</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KING, BOBBY J.</last-name><address><street>Route 1, Box 16V</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73533</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Wain, Christopher Paul</last-name><address><street>A.A. Thornton &amp;amp; Co. 235 High Holborn</street><city>London WC1V 7LE</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Pipe is cemented in a well bore using a low density cement composition comprised of
a hydraulic cement, sufficient water to form a slurry and hollow glass microspheres surface
treated with a mixture of organosilane coupling agents present in an amount sufficient to
produce a cement composition density of from 6 to 12 pounds per gallon.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to cementing pipe in well bores and, more
particularly, to such methods and compositions for cementing pipe in well bores
penetrating subterranean zones or formations which readily fracture at low hydrostatic
pressures.</p><p num="0002">Hydraulic cement compositions are commonly utilized in oil, gas and water well
completion and remedial operations. For example, hydraulic cement compositions are
used in primary cementing operations whereby strings of pipe such as casing are
cemented in well bores. In performing primary cementing, a hydraulic cement
composition is pumped into the annular space between the walls of a well bore and the
exterior of pipe disposed therein. The cement composition is permitted to set in the
annular space thereby forming an annular sheath of hardened substantially impermeable
cement therein. The cement sheath physically supports and positions the pipe in the well
bore and bonds the pipe to the walls of the well bore whereby the undesirable migration
of fluids between zones or formations penetrated by the well bore is prevented.</p><p num="0003">In some locations, the subterranean zones or formations into or through which
wells are drilled have high permeabilities and low compressive and tensile strengths. As
a result, the resistances of the zones or formations to shear are low and they have very
low fracture gradients. When a well fluid such as a hydraulic cement composition is
introduced into a well bore penetrating such a subterranean zone or formation, the
hydrostatic pressure exerted on the walls of the well bore can exceed the fracture gradient
of the zone or formation and cause fractures to be formed in the zone or formation into
which the cement composition is lost.</p><p num="0004">While lightweight cement compositions have been developed and used heretofore,
i.e. cement compositions having densities as low as about 12 pounds per gallon,
subterranean zones or formations are still encountered which have fracture gradients too
low for even the lightweight cement compositions to be utilized without fracturing the
formation and the occurrence of lost circulation problems. Also, the lightweight cement 
compositions utilized heretofore have often not had sufficient compressive, tensile and
bond strengths upon setting.</p><p num="0005">Thus, there are continuing needs for improved methods of cementing pipe in well
bores and low density cement compositions which have enhanced compressive, tensile
and bond strengths upon setting.</p><p num="0006">In one aspect, the present invention provides a cement composition having
enhanced compressive, tensile and bond strengths upon setting, which composition
comprises a hydraulic cement; sufficient water to form a slurry; and hollow glass
microspheres surface treated with a mixture of organosilane coupling agents present in an
amount sufficient to produce a cement composition density of from 6 to 12 pounds per
gallon.</p><p num="0007">In another aspect, the invention provides a method of cementing pipe in a well
bore penetrating a subterranean zone or formation which readily fractures at low
hydrostatic pressures, which method comprises placing a cement composition of the
invention into the annulus between said pipe and the walls of said well bore; and allowing
said cement composition to set therein.</p><p num="0008">Improved methods of cementing pipe in well bores penetrating subterranean zones
or formations which readily fracture at low hydrostatic pressures are provided by the
present invention. The methods are basically comprised of the following steps. A low
density cement composition having enhanced compressive, tensile and bond strengths
upon setting is provided. The low density cement composition is comprised of a
hydraulic cement, sufficient water to form a slurry, hollow glass microspheres which have
been surface treated with a mixture of organosilane coupling agents and optionally, a gas
and a mixture of foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants for foaming the cement
composition. The microspheres are present in the low density cement composition in an
amount sufficient to produce a density in the range of from about 6 to about 12 pounds
per gallon and when the composition is foamed, it can have a density of about 5 or below.
The cement composition is placed into the annulus between the pipe and the walls of the
well bore and the cement composition is allowed to set therein. </p><p num="0009">Because the cement composition has a low density, i.e. a density such that the
hydrostatic pressure of the cement composition exerted in the subterranean zone or
formation being cemented is less than the fracture gradient of the subterranean zone or
formation, fracturing of the zone or formation does not take place. Also, because the
cement composition of this invention has enhanced compressive, tensile and bond
strengths upon setting, a strong bond exists between the pipe and the walls of the well
bore penetrating the subterranean zone or formation which prevents formation fluids from
entering the annulus between the pipe and the well bore. The high overall strength of the
cement composition also prevents it from being shattered by contact with the drill bit and
drill string when the well is drilled to greater depths.</p><p num="0010">Examples of hydraulic cements which can be utilized in accordance with the
present invention include, but are not limited to, Portland cements, slag cements,
pozzolana cements, gypsum cements, aluminous cements, silica cements and alkaline
cements. Of these, Portland cement is preferred. The Portland cement can be of ultra
fine particle size or standard particle size with the ultra fine particle size being preferred
for use in subterranean zones or formations having high permeabilities and which fracture
at very low cement hydrostatic pressures.</p><p num="0011">The water utilized in the cement composition can be fresh water or salt water. The
term "salt water" is used herein to mean unsaturated salt solutions or saturated salt
solutions including brine and seawater. The water used is generally present in the low
density cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 58% to about 160%
by weight of the hydraulic cement in the composition.</p><p num="0012">The hollow glass microspheres utilized in the low density cement compositions
are preferably synthetic hollow glass microspheres which are commercially available
from the Minnesota, Mining and Manufacturing Co. ("3M™") under the trade name
"SCOTCHLITE™ ". These very low density microspheres are formed of a chemically
stable soda-lime borosilicate glass composition which is non-porous. The hollow glass
microspheres are included in the cement composition of this invention in an amount
sufficient to produce a cement composition density in the range of from about 5 to about
12 pounds per gallon. Generally, the hollow glass microspheres are included in the 
cement composition in an amount of from about 10% to about 21% by weight of
hydraulic cement in the composition.</p><p num="0013">The surfaces of the hollow glass microspheres utilized in the cement compositions
of this invention are pretreated with a mixture of epoxy and amine organosilane coupling
agents. The organosilane coupling agents greatly improve the wetability of the hollow
glass microspheres whereby they can readily be mixed with the aqueous cement
composition. In addition, the organosilane coupling agents attach to the surfaces of the
hollow glass microspheres and form silanol thereon. The silanol undergoes immediate
dehydration resulting in-silicon-oxygen-silicon-bonds (-Si-O-Si-) between the cement
utilized and the hollow glass microspheres thereby enhancing the compressive, tensile
and bond strengths of the cement composition upon setting.</p><p num="0014">While various organosilane coupling agents can be utilized, the coupling agents
are preferably selected from a mixture of epoxy and amine organosilane coupling agents.
Examples of such mixtures include 3-glycidoxypropyltrimethoxy silane and 3-aminopropyltriethoxy
silane or 3-glycidoxypropyltrimethoxy silane and N-2-(aminoethyl)-3-aminopropyltrimethoxy
silane. Most preferably, the organosilane
coupling agent mixture used to surface treat the hollow glass microspheres is a 1:1 by
weight mixture of 3-glycidoxypropyltrimethoxy silane and 3-aminopropyltriethoxy
silane.</p><p num="0015">The surface treatment of the hollow glass microspheres is carried out by
combining the mixture of organosilanes utilized with ethyl acetate while stirring the ethyl
acetate. Thereafter, the hollow glass microspheres are added to the ethyl acetate and
organosilane mixture therein. The resulting mixture is heated at 170°F for about 1 hour
with continuous stirring, followed by filtration and drying. Thereafter, the surface treated
hollow glass microspheres are heated to 150°F in a vacuum oven for 24 hours. Under
these conditions, the amino group of the amino organosilane reacts with the epoxy group
of the epoxy organosilane on the surfaces of the hollow glass microspheres.</p><p num="0016">The surface treated hollow glass microspheres are included in the low density
cement compositions in an amount in the range of from about 10% to about 21% by 
weight of the hydraulic cement therein to thereby produce cement composition densities
in the range of from about 6 to about 12.</p><p num="0017">In order to produce a cement composition of this invention having a density below
about 6 pounds per gallon, i.e., a density of about 5 pounds per gallon or below, the
cement composition is foamed. That is, a gas is added to the cement composition along
with a mixture of foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants which facilitate the formation
of the foam and stabilize the foamed composition.</p><p num="0018">The gas utilized for foaming the cement composition can be air or nitrogen, with
nitrogen being preferred. A cement composition having surface treated hollow glass
microspheres therein and having a density of about 6 pounds per gallon is foamed with
the gas to produce a density of about 5 pounds per gallon or below. The gas is generally
present in the cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 20% to about
80% by volume of the cement composition, preferably from about 20% to about 50%.
Prior to foaming the cement composition with the gas as described above, the mixture of
foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants is combined with the cement composition in an
amount sufficient to facilitate the formation of the foam and stabilize the resulting foamed
composition.</p><p num="0019">A variety of foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants can be utilized in
accordance with the present invention. A preferred mixture of such surfactants is
described in U.S. Patent No. 5,897,699 issued to Chatterji et al. on April 27, 1999 which
is incorporated herein by reference thereto. The surfactant mixture is basically comprised
of an aqueous solution of an alpha-olefinic sulfonate and a cocoylamidopropyl betaine.</p><p num="0020">A more preferred mixture of foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants for use in
accordance with this invention is described in U.S. Patent No. 6,063,738 issued to
Chatterji et al. on May 16, 2000 which is incorporated herein by reference thereto. The
surfactant mixture is comprised of an ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate of the formula
H(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>a</sub>(OC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub>)<sub>b</sub>OSO<sub>3</sub>NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> wherein a is an integer in the range of from about 6 to about
10 and b is an integer in the range of from about 3 to about 10; an alkyl or alkene
amidopropyl betaine having the formula R―CONHCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>N<sup>+</sup>(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup>
wherein R is a radical selected from the group of decyl, cocoyl, lauryl, cetyl and oleyl; 
and an alkyl or alkene amidopropyl dimethyl amine oxide having the formula
R―CONHCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>N<sup>+</sup>CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>O<sup>-</sup> wherein R is a radical selected from the group of
decyl, cocoyl, lauryl, cetyl and oleyl.</p><p num="0021">The ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate is generally present in the above described
mixture in an amount in the range of from about 60 to 64 parts by weight. The alkyl or
alkene amidopropyl betaine is generally present in the mixture in an amount in the range
of from about 30 to about 33 parts by weight and the alkyl or alkene amidopropyl
dimethyl amine oxide is generally present in the mixture in an amount in the range of
from about 3 to about 10 parts by weight.</p><p num="0022">In order to make the surfactant mixture more easily combinable with the cement
composition including the surface treated hollow glass microspheres, water is preferably
combined with the surfactant mixture in an amount sufficient to dissolve the surfactants.</p><p num="0023">A particularly preferred mixture of foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants as
described above for use in accordance with the present invention is comprised of
ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate wherein a in the formula thereof set forth above is an
integer in the range of from 6 to 10 and the ethoxylated alkyl ether sulfate is present in the
mixture in an amount of about 63.3 parts by weight; the alkyl or alkene amidopropyl
betaine is cocoylamidopropyl betaine and is present in the mixture in an amount of about
31.7 parts by weight; and the alkyl or alkene amidopropyl dimethylamine oxide is
cocoylamidopropyl dimethylamine oxide and is present in the mixture in an amount of
about 5 parts by weight.</p><p num="0024">The mixture of foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants utilized is generally
included in the cement composition to be foamed in an amount in the range of from about
0.8% to about 5% by volume of water in the cement composition, preferably in an
amount of from about 1% to about 2%.</p><p num="0025">The low density cement compositions of this invention having enhanced
compressive, tensile and bond strengths upon setting include a hydraulic cement,
sufficient water to form a slurry and hollow glass microspheres surface treated with a
mixture of organosilane coupling agents present in an amount sufficient to produce a
cement composition density in the range of from about 6 to about 12 pounds per gallon 
and optionally, a gas and a mixture of foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants for
foaming the cement composition whereby it has a density of about 5 pounds per gallon or
below.</p><p num="0026">The hydraulic cement, water and surface treated hollow glass microspheres as well
as the optional gas and surfactants utilized in the cement composition are as described
above and are present in the cement composition in the amounts set forth above.</p><p num="0027">A preferred method of this invention for cementing pipe in a well bore penetrating
a subterranean zone or formation which readily fractures at low hydrostatic pressures is
comprised of the steps of: (a) providing a low density cement composition having
enhanced compressive, tensile and bond strengths upon setting comprised of a hydraulic
cement, sufficient water to form a slurry and hollow glass microspheres surface treated
with a mixture of organosilane coupling agents present in an amount sufficient to produce
a cement composition density in the range of from about 6 to about 12 pounds per gallon;
(b) placing the cement composition into the annulus between the pipe and the walls of the
well bore; and (c) allowing the cement composition to set therein.</p><p num="0028">Another preferred method of this invention for cementing pipe in a well bore
penetrating a subterranean zone or formation which readily fractures at low hydrostatic
pressures is comprised of the steps of: (a) providing a low density cement composition
having enhanced compressive, tensile and bond strengths upon setting comprised of a
hydraulic cement, sufficient water to form a slurry, hollow glass microspheres surface
treated with a mixture of organosilane coupling agents present in an amount sufficient to
produce a cement composition density of about 6 pounds per gallon, a gas present in an
amount sufficient to foam the cement composition whereby the cement composition has a
density of about 5 pounds per gallon or below and a mixture of foaming and foam
stabilizing surfactants; (b) placing the cement composition into the annulus between the
pipe and the walls of the well bore; and (c) allowing the cement composition to set
therein.</p><p num="0029">A preferred low density cement composition having enhanced compressive, tensile
and bond strengths upon setting comprises: a hydraulic cement; sufficient water to form a
slurry; and hollow glass microspheres surface treated with a mixture of organosilane 
coupling agents present in an amount sufficient to produce a cement composition density
in the range of from about 6 to about 12 pounds per gallon.</p><p num="0030">Yet another low density cement composition having enhanced compressive,
tensile and bond strengths upon setting comprises: a hydraulic cement; sufficient water to
form a slurry; hollow glass microspheres surface treated with a mixture of organosilane
coupling agents present in an amount sufficient to produce a cement composition density
of about 6 pounds per gallon; a gas present in an amount sufficient to foam the cement
composition whereby the cement composition has a density of about 5 pounds per gallon
or below; and a mixture of foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants.</p><p num="0031">In order to further illustrate the methods and compositions of this invention, the
following example is given.</p><heading>EXAMPLE</heading><p num="0032">Two quantities of hollow glass microspheres were obtained from the Minnesota,
Mining and Manufacturing Co. having specific gravities of 0.15 and 0.38, respectively.
2,500 milliliters of ethyl acetate were added to each of two 5 liter flasks equipped with
stirrers and a mixture comprised of 1.25 grams of 3-glycidoxypropyltrimethoxy silane
and 1.25 grams of 3-aminopropyltriethoxy silane were added to the ethyl acetate in each
flask. The flasks were continuously stirred while 250 grams of hollow glass microspheres
having a specific gravity of 0.15 was added to the ethyl acetate in one flask and 250
grams of hollow glass microspheres having a specific gravity of 0.38 were added to the
ethyl acetate in the other flask. The mixtures of ethyl acetate organosilane coupling agent
and hollow glass microspheres were heated to 170°F and held at that temperature for 1
hour while continuously being stirred, followed by filtration and drying. The hollow
glass microspheres from each flask were then heated to 150°F in a vacuum oven for 24
hours. While being heated in the ovens, the organosilane coupling agents reacted with
each other on the surface of the hollow glass microspheres. Infrared spectroscopy of the
treated hollow glass microspheres showed the appearance of 3 new bands at 1118.89 cm<sup>-1</sup>,
1113.77 cm<sup>-1</sup> and 1105 cm<sup>-1</sup> indicating a reaction of the organosilanes with the hollow
glass microspheres. Two cement slurries were next prepared by mixing ultrafine Portland
cement with fresh water and standard Class G Portland cement with fresh water. To test 
portions of the ultra fine Portland cement slurry, organosilane surface treated hollow glass
microspheres having specific gravities of 0.15 were combined in amounts whereby test
cement compositions having densities of 6 pounds per gallon and 7 pounds per gallon
were formed. A number of the test cement compositions containing the surface treated
hollow glass microspheres and having densities of 6 pounds per gallon were tested as
were a number of such cement compositions having densities of 7 pounds per gallon.
Also, test compositions having densities of 6 pounds per gallon were foamed with air in
the presence of a mixture of foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants. The foamed test
cement compositions had densities of 5 pounds per gallon.</p><p num="0033">In a like manner, a number of test cement compositions containing standard Class
G Portland cement were combined with surface treated and non-surface treated hollow
glass microspheres. Some of the cement compositions had densities of 10.5 pounds per
gallon and others had densities of 12 pounds per gallon. A cement dispersing agent
comprised of the condensation product of formaldehyde, acetone and bisulfite was added
to some of the test cement compositions in amounts of 1% by weight of cement therein
and Class F fly ash was added to other of the test cement compositions in amounts of
50% by weight of cement in the compositions. The test cement compositions and their
components and physical properties are shown in Table I below. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1"><b>Cement Composition Physical Properties</b></entry></row> <row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry align="center" namest="2"/><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="3">3M Microspheres</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Cement

Composition

Sample

Number</entry><entry align="center">Density,

lb/gal</entry><entry align="center">Cement

Type</entry> <entry align="center">Specific

Gravity</entry> <entry align="center">% By

Weight

Of

Cement</entry> <entry align="center">Dispersant,

% by

wt.

of

cement</entry><entry align="center">Class F

Fly Ash,

% by

wt.

of

cement</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">Ultra Fine</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry><entry align="center">21</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 1</entry><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">Ultra

Fine</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry><entry align="center">21</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">Ultra

Fine</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 2</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">Ultra

Fine</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">Ultra

Fine</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">50</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 3</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">Ultra

Fine</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">50</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3 foamed</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">Ultra

Fine</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">50</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 3

foamed</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">Ultra

Fine</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">50</entry></row><row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">10.5</entry><entry align="center">Class G</entry><entry align="center">0.38</entry><entry align="center">20</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 5</entry><entry align="center">10.5</entry><entry align="center">Class G</entry><entry align="center">0.38</entry><entry align="center">20</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">Class G</entry><entry align="center">0.38</entry><entry align="center">10</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 6</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">Class G</entry><entry align="center">0.38</entry><entry align="center">10</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0034">The test cement composition samples containing organosilane coupling agent
surface treated hollow glass microspheres and other test cement composition samples
containing untreated hollow glass microspheres were tested for compressive, tensile and
bond strengths upon setting. The compressive strengths and tensile strengths of the
samples were determined in accordance with the procedures set forth in <u style="single">API Specification
For Materials And Testing For Well Cements,</u> API Specification 10, 5<sup>th</sup> Edition, dated 
July 1, 1990 of the American Petroleum Institute. The samples tested for shear bond
strength were placed in the annuluses of pipe assemblies, i.e., small pipes centered inside
larger pipes. After setting, the shear bond strength was determined by supporting the
larger pipe and applying force to the smaller inner pipe. The shear bond strength was
calculated by dividing the total force applied by the broken bonded surface area. The
results of these tests are shown in Table II below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1"><b>Compressive, Tensile And Bond Strength Test Results</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="4" align="center" namest="2">Treated Microspheres</entry><entry nameend="7" align="center" namest="5">Untreated Microspheres</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Cement

Composition

Sample

Number</entry><entry align="center">Tensile

Strength,

psi</entry><entry align="center">Compressive

Strength,

psi</entry><entry align="center">Shear

Bond,

psi</entry><entry align="center">Tensile

Strength,

psi</entry><entry align="center">Compressive

Strength,

psi</entry><entry align="center">Shear

Bond,

psi</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">26.6</entry><entry align="center">186</entry><entry align="center">28.4</entry><entry align="center">23.7</entry><entry align="center">115.5</entry><entry align="center">21.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 1</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="center">160</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">114.3</entry><entry align="center">861</entry><entry align="center">96.8</entry><entry align="center">80.9</entry><entry align="center">849</entry><entry align="center">58.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 2</entry><entry align="center">116</entry><entry align="center">868</entry><entry align="center">104</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">86</entry><entry align="center">459</entry><entry align="center">500</entry><entry align="center">92</entry><entry align="center">466</entry><entry align="center">122.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 3</entry><entry align="center">94</entry><entry align="center">467</entry><entry align="center">526</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3 foamed</entry><entry align="center">91</entry><entry align="center">207</entry><entry align="center">47.5</entry><entry align="center">77.1</entry><entry align="center">149.1</entry><entry align="center">42.6</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 3

foamed</entry><entry align="center">102</entry><entry align="center">211</entry><entry align="center">51</entry></row><row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">361</entry><entry align="center">3980</entry><entry align="center">296</entry><entry align="center">315</entry><entry align="center">2920</entry><entry align="center">158</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 5</entry><entry align="center">352</entry><entry align="center">4020</entry><entry align="center">306</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">208</entry><entry align="center">2540</entry><entry align="center">361</entry><entry align="center">191</entry><entry align="center">2280</entry><entry align="center">296</entry></row><row><entry align="center">repeat 6</entry><entry align="center">226</entry><entry align="center">2890</entry><entry align="center">373</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0035">From Tables I and II, it can be seen that the test cement compositions of this
invention containing organosilane coupling agent surface treated hollow glass
microspheres had significantly better tensile strengths, compressive strengths and shear
bond strengths than did the same cement compositions containing untreated hollow glass
microspheres.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A low density cement composition having enhanced compressive, tensile and
bond strengths upon setting, which composition comprises a hydraulic cement; sufficient
water to form a slurry; and hollow glass microspheres surface treated with a mixture of
organosilane coupling agents present in an amount sufficient to produce a cement
composition density of from 6 to 12 pounds per gallon.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 1, wherein said hydraulic cement is selected
from Portland cements, slag cements, pozzolana cements, gypsum cements, aluminous
cements, silica cements and alkaline cements.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 1 or 2, wherein said water is fresh water or salt
water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 1, 2 or 3, wherein said water is present in said
composition in an amount of from 58% to 160% by weight of said hydraulic cement
therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 1, 2, 3 or 4, wherein said surface treated hollow
glass microspheres are present in said composition in an amount of from 10% to 21% by
weight of said hydraulic cement therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The composition according to any of claims 1 to 5, wherein said mixture of
organosilane coupling agents used to surface treat said hollow glass microspheres is a
mixture of 3-glycidoxypropyltrimethoxy silane and 3-aminopropyltriethoxy silane, or a
mixture of 3-glycidoxypropyltrimethoxy silane and N-2-(aminoethyl)-3-aminopropyltrimethoxy
silane, preferably a 1:1 by weight mixture of 3-glycidoxypropyltrimethoxy
silane and 3-aminopropyltriethoxy silane.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A composition according to any of claims 1 to 6, wherein said surface treated
hollow glass microspheres are present in an amount sufficient to produce a cement
composition density of 6 pounds per gallon; and wherein the composition further
comprises a gas in an amount sufficient to foam said cement composition to a density of 5
pounds per gallon or below; and a mixture of foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 7, wherein said gas is air or nitrogen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 7 or 8, wherein said gas is present in said
cement composition in an amount of from 20% to 80% by volume of said cement
composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 7, 8 or 9, wherein said mixture of foaming and
foam stabilizing surfactants in said cement composition is comprised of an ethoxylated
alcohol ether sulfate present in said mixture in an amount of 63.3 parts by weight of said
mixture, cocoylamidopropyl betaine present in an amount of 31.7 parts by weight of said
mixture and cocoylamidopropyl dimethylamine oxide present in an amount of 5 parts by
weight of said mixture.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 7, 8, 9 or 10, wherein said mixture of foaming
and foam stabilizing surfactants is present in said cement composition in an amount of
from 0.8% to 5% by volume of said water therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A method of cementing pipe in a well bore penetrating a subterranean zone or
formation which readily fractures at low hydrostatic pressures, which method comprises
placing a cement composition as claimed in any of claims 1 to 11 into the annulus
between said pipe and the walls of said well bore; and allowing said cement composition
to set therein.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>