<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1182267-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1182267" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18609733" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020227"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1182267-A1" status="new" fvid="23378139"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1182267</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020227</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01917739-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01917739</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010330</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-0102806-W" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>0102806</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20010330</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000094727-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000094727</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000330</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/68        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/68        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C12Q   1/68E+565/518+563/107</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">VERFAHREN ZUR BESTIMMUNG DER BASENSEQUENZ EINES EINZELNEN NUKLEINSÄUREMOLEKÜLS</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">METHOD OF DETERMINING BASE SEQUENCE OF SINGLE NUCLEIC ACID MOLECULE</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">PROCEDE POUR DETERMINER UNE SEQUENCE DE BASE D'UNE MOLECULE INDIVIDUELLE D'ACIDE NUCLEIQUE</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0969083-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0969083</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5302509-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5302509</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5547839-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5547839</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1990013666-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1990013666</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1993021340-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1993021340</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000006770-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000006770</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>See also references of WO     0173121A1</text><sources><source name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GENESIS RES INST INC</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TOYOTA MOTOR CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENESIS RESEARCH INSTITUTE, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TOYOTA JIDOSHA KABUSHIKI KAISHA</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Genesis Research Institute, Inc.</last-name><address><street>4-1-35, Noritake-shinmachi Nishi-ku</street><city>Nagoya-shi, Aichi-ken 451-0051</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TOYOTA JIDOSHA KABUSHIKI KAISHA</last-name><address><street>1, Toyota-cho</street><city>Toyota-shi, Aichi 471-8571</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KONDOW TAMOTSU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MAFUNE FUMITAKA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TAKEDA YASHIHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KONDOW, TAMOTSU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MAFUNE, FUMITAKA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TAKEDA, YASHIHIRO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KONDOW, TAMOTSU</last-name><address><street>1-3-1-1002A, Echujima</street><city>Koto-ku, Tokyo 135-0044</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MAFUNE, FUMITAKA</last-name><address><street>2-7-5-1905, Shinonome</street><city>Koto-ku, Tokyo 135-0062</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TAKEDA, YOSHIHIRO</last-name><address><street>101, Bigfarm, 3-6-5, Imagawa</street><city>Urayasu-shi, Chiba 279-0022</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Leson, Thomas Johannes Alois, Dipl.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>Tiedtke-Bühling-Kinne &amp;amp; Partner GbR, TBK-Patent, Bavariaring 4</street><city>80336 München</city><country>DE</country></address> </addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><pct-or-regional-filing-data ucid="JP-0102806-W" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>JP</country> <doc-number>0102806</doc-number> <kind>W</kind> </document-id></pct-or-regional-filing-data><pct-or-regional-publishing-data ucid="WO-2001073121-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2001073121</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20011004</date></document-id></pct-or-regional-publishing-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention relates to a method for determining a nucleotide sequence
of a nucleic acid by single dye molecule detection, the method comprising:
<sl><li>(1) a step of immobilizing a nucleic acid molecule, or a primer which has a
sequence complementary to a part of the sequence of the nucleic acid molecule,
onto the surface of a solid;</li><li>(2) a step of annealing the primer or the nucleic acid molecule to the nucleic acid
molecule or the primer, respectively;</li><li>(3) a step of providing a solution which contains DNA polymerase and one type of
dye-labeled dNTP, or RNA polymerase and one type of dye-labeled NTP, to the
immobilized nucleic acid molecule, and allowing the nucleotide to react with the
3' end of the primer, whereby a nucleotide, which forms a base-pair with a base
opposed to the reaction site, is bound to the primer by action of the polymerase;</li><li>(4) a step of detecting the presence of a bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP;</li><li>(5) a step of disrupting the dye molecule of the bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP;</li><li>(6) a step of repeating the steps (3) to (5) while changing the type of dye-labeled
dNTP or NTP in turn, to sequentially bind dNTPs or NTPs which base-pair with
the nucleotides of the nucleic acid molecule; and</li><li>(7) a step of determining the nucleotide sequence of the nucleic acid molecule based
on the types of the sequentially bound dNTPs or NTPs.</li></sl><img id="img-00000001"  orientation="unknown" wi="76" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif"  inline="no"  he="53"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep"  status="new" lang="EN"><heading>TECHNICAL FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a method for determining nucleotide sequences of
single nucleic acid molecules by single molecule detection.</p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0002">The Sanger method (Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 74:5463, 1977) is routinely used
as a method for determining a nucleotide sequence of DNA. This method is also
referred to as the dideoxy chain termination method, comprising the steps of annealing a
primer to the 5' end of a DNA sample, synthesizing a complementary chain in the
presence of DNA polymerase and four deoxynucleoside triphosphates (dNTPs where N
denotes A, C, T and G) and each of 2', 3'-dideoxynucleoside triphosphates (ddNTPs
where N denotes A, C, T or G), stopping the elongation reaction at a position where
ddNTP is incorporated, and performing gel electrophoresis for the obtained reaction
product, thereby determining a nucleotide sequence of the DNA sample. The DNA
fragments formed at this time are generally labeled with a radioactive label, which
enables the identification of the position of the fragments.</p><p num="0003">Furthermore, since radioactive labeling requires a special facility, other methods
for determining nucleotide sequences which employ fluorescent labels in place of
radioactive labels to detect fluorescence by irradiation of a laser beam, have also been
developed (e.g. Japanese Patent No. 2901004, and JP-B-7-43347).</p><p num="0004">However, the use of the Sanger method involves some problems such as that it 
requires production of a large number of copies of the DNA to be sequenced by
previously incorporating the DNA into a vector, e.g. M13, and that the number of
detectable bases is limited to a maximum 1,000 bp per lane of electrophoresis. Hence,
if the nucleotide sequence of a DNA can be determined by directly identifying the bases
from the 5' end of the sequence one by one, and an isolated single DNA molecule can
be used for direct sequencing without requiring a number of replicated molecules of
DNA, then efficiency of sequencing will be significantly improved.</p><p num="0005">Thus, the object of the present invention is to provide a method for determining
nucleotide sequences of single nucleic acid molecules by single molecule detection.
This method has advantages in that it enables to detect bases of a nucleic acid one by
one, in addition to enabling direct decoding of intracellular DNA or RNA molecules.
Furthermore, this method thereby improves the speed of sequencing by one to two
orders of magnitude and enables direct sequencing without producing a number of
copies of a single-stranded nucleic acid molecule.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0006">The present invention will be summarized as follows.</p><p num="0007">In one aspect, the present invention provides a method for determining a
nucleotide sequence of a nucleic acid molecule by single dye molecule detection,
wherein the method comprises:
<sl><li>(1) a step of immobilizing a nucleic acid molecule onto the surface of a solid;</li><li>(2) a step of annealing a primer, which has a sequence complementary to a part of the
sequence of the nucleic acid molecule, to the nucleic acid molecule;</li><li>(3) a step of providing a solution which contains DNA polymerase and one type of
dye-labeled dNTP (where N is A, T or U, G or C), or RNA polymerase and one
type of dye-labeled NTP (where N is A, U, G or C), to the immobilized nucleic
acid molecule, and allowing the nucleotide to react with the 3' end of the primer, 
whereby a nucleotide, which forms a base-pair with a base opposed to the reaction
site, is bound to the primer by action of the polymerase;</li><li>(4) a step of detecting a bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP;</li><li>(5) a step of disrupting the dye molecule of the bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP;</li><li>(6) a step of repeating the steps (3) to (5) while changing the type of the dye-labeled
dNTP or NTP in turn, to sequentially bind dNTPs or NTPs complementary to the
nucleotides of the nucleic acid molecule; and</li><li>(7) a step of determining a nucleotide sequence of the nucleic acid molecule based on
the types of the sequentially bound dNTPs or NTPs.</li></sl></p><p num="0008">In another aspect, the present invention provides a method for determining a
nucleotide sequence of a nucleic acid by single dye molecule detection, wherein the
method comprises:
<sl><li>(1) a step of immobilizing onto the surface of a solid, a primer which has a sequence
complementary to a part of the sequence of a nucleic acid molecule to be
measured;</li><li>(2) a step of annealing the nucleic acid molecule to the primer;</li><li>(3) a step of providing a solution, which contains DNA polymerase and one type of
dye-labeled dNTP (where N is A, T or U, G or C), or RNA polymerase and one
type of dye-labeled NTP (where N is A, U, G or C), to the immobilized nucleic
acid molecule, and allowing the nucleotide to react with the 3' end of the primer,
whereby a nucleotide, which forms a base-pair with a base opposed to the
reaction site, is bound to the primer by action of the polymerase;</li><li>(4) a step of detecting a bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP;</li><li>(5) a step of disrupting the dye molecule of the bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP;</li><li>(6) a step of repeating the steps (3) to (5) while changing the type of the dye-labeled
dNTP or NTP in turn, to sequentially bind dNTPs or NTPs complementary to
the nucleotides of the nucleic acid molecule; and</li><li>(7) a step of determining a nucleotide sequence of the nucleic acid molecule based 
on the types of the sequentially bound dNTPs or NTPs.</li></sl></p><p num="0009">In an embodiment of the present invention, the solid surface in the above step (1)
is the inner wall of a capillary.</p><p num="0010">In another embodiment of the present invention, the above step (4) comprises
optically detecting the dye molecule of the dye-labeled dNTP or NTP. More
specifically, the detection can be performed by exciting the dye molecule by irradiation
of a laser beam and detecting the thus emitted fluorescence signal. An example of
such a detection method is a method, which employs a confocal fluorescence
microscope system.</p><p num="0011">In another embodiment of the present invention, the disruption of dye molecules
in the above step (5) is performed by irradiation of a laser beam stronger than that in
step (4).</p><p num="0012">In another embodiment of the present invention, the above dye is a fluorescent
dye.</p><p num="0013">In another embodiment of the present invention, the above solution consists of a
droplet, in which an aqueous solution containing the dye-labeled dNTP or NTP, is
entrapped within a hydrophobic liquid.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0014"><sl><li>Figure 1 is a schematic diagram showing the method of the present invention for
determining a nucleotide sequence of DNA by single dye molecule detection.</li><li>Figure 2 is a schematic diagram showing the procedure to detect a fluorescent
signal derived from a dye molecule using a confocal fluorescence microscope system.</li></sl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0015">The present invention provides a method for determining nucleotide sequences of
nucleic acid molecules comprising DNA or RNA by using a single molecule detection
method. The single molecule detection method as used herein means a method, in
which any signal molecule is detected by any analysis method. In this invention,
generally the dye molecule of a dye-labeled deoxynucleoside triphosphate (dNTP,
wherein N denotes A, T or U, G or C) or a dye-labeled nucleoside triphosphate (NTP,
wherein N denotes A, U, G or C) can be optically detected using a spectroscopic
instrument. The detection is performed by using a confocal fluorescence microscope
instrument in the Example described below (see Fig. 2).</p><p num="0016">The present invention will be described as follows by referring to Fig. 1.</p><p num="0017">The first step in the method of the present invention comprises immobilizing a
nucleic acid molecule or a primer having a sequence complementary to a part of the
sequence of the nucleic acid molecule, onto the surface of a solid.</p><p num="0018">The nucleic acid molecule can be immobilized onto the solid surface after
purification of a nucleic acid sample by standard techniques, for example by preparing
single-stranded molecules from the sample by, for example, denaturation with alkaline
treatment.</p><p num="0019">The size and type of the primers employed are not specifically limited as long as
they can be annealed to nucleic acid molecules. For example, the size of the primers
may be at least 10 nucleotides, and normally about 15 to 30 nucleotides. When a part
of the sequence of a nucleic acid molecule to be sequenced is known, a primer may be
prepared based on this known sequence and be used. Alternately, random primers or
oligo dT primers may be used as the primers. </p><p num="0020">The solid surface used may be of any material as long as a nucleic acid molecule
or a primer can be immobilized thereto. Examples of such a material include glass,
quartz and resin. Further, the solid surface may be flat, curved or in any other form.
For example, the inner wall of a capillary (e.g. made of glass, quartz or resin) can be
used as a solid surface. A capillary is appropriate for automatically injecting a solution
containing dye-labeled dNTP or NTP and polymerase enzyme into the inside of the
capillary after immobilization of nucleic acid molecules or primers within the capillary.
The internal diameter of a capillary is, for example, approximately 100 to 250µm, and
the sufficient length is generally about 10 to 50mm, but the internal diameter and length
are not limited thereto.</p><p num="0021">Preferably, the solid surface is previously treated so as to facilitate immobilization
of a nucleic acid molecule to be sequenced or a primer, and so as not to allow
unreacting dye-labeled dNTP or NTP molecules to adsorb to the surface. Binding of a
nucleic acid molecule or a primer to the solid surface can be performed by, for example,
a general UV crosslinking method. More specifically, a solution prepared by
dissolving a nucleic acid in a Carnoy's solution (methanol/acetic acid (3:1 v/v)) is
introduced into a quartz glass capillary, then dried and solidified at room temperature.
Next, 2xSSC (NaCl 1.75g, sodium citrate 0.882g/100ml) is introduced into the capillary,
followed by UV irradiation, thereby binding the nucleic acid to the solid surface. It is
preferable to immobilize one molecule of nucleic acid onto the solid surface, but in
practice, multiple nucleic acid molecules are immobilized onto the surface. In an
actual measurement, diluted nucleic acid molecules (approximately 0.1 to 100pmol/µl,
preferably 30 to 70pmol/µl) are immobilized onto the solid surface, one immobilized
nucleic acid molecule enters into the field of vision, and then sequencing is performed.</p><p num="0022">The second step comprises annealing a primer to the nucleic acid molecule on the
solid surface, or annealing the nucleic acid molecule to a primer on the solid surface. </p><p num="0023">The third step comprises providing a solution containing DNA polymerase and
one type of dye-labeled dNTP (where N is A, T or U, G or C) or containing RNA
polymerase and one type of dye-labeled NTP (where N is A, U, G or C) to the
immobilized nucleic acid molecule, and allowing a nucleotide to react with the 3' end of
the above primer. At this time, a nucleotide, which forms a base-pair with a base
opposed to the reaction site, is bound to the primer by action of the polymerase.</p><p num="0024">As used herein, the term "one type of" means a certain one of four types of
dye-labeled dNTP or NTP. As the result that this "one type" is specified, the type of
dNTP or NTP to be actually bound to a primer would be known.</p><p num="0025">In Fig. 1, a solvent is allowed to flow through a capillary cell in which a nucleic
acid molecule has been immobilized, and a solution containing DNA polymerase and
only one type of dye-labeled base dATP is introduced into the flow, in order to cause the
reaction of the base next to a DNA sequence ATG previously annealed to a target DNA.
If no incorporation reaction of the base by DNA polymerase occurs, no dye is detected
on the DNA by the single molecule detection because unreacting bases are washed away.
In this case, the same procedure is performed for a solution containing another type of
base (dGTP, dCTP or dTTP). This procedure is repeated until a base is incorporated
into the above DNA sequence and a dye is detected on the DNA. As shown in the
figure, which nucleotide follows ATG (in this case, T follows ATG) will be known by
allowing a solution containing a dye-labeled dTTP to contact with the target DNA
which has been annealed to a primer with ATG already bound to the 3' end, and then
detecting the dye. For a DNA sample having the same sequential bases, multiple bases
may be incorporated into a DNA sequence. In such a case, identification of the
number of dyes by, for example, fluorescence intensity, enables detection of the number
of sequential bases incorporated. </p><p num="0026">In the present invention, a solution containing DNA polymerase and one type of
dye-labeled dNTP (where N is A, T or U, G or C), or RNA polymerase and one type of
dye-labeled NTP (where N is A, U, G or C), can consist of a droplet in which an
aqueous solution which contains the dye-labeled dNTP or NTP is entrapped within a
hydrophobic liquid such as mineral oil. Such a droplet can be easily prepared using,
for example, a micro-injector. The size of a droplet is, for example, approximately 10
to 25µm in diameter, corresponding to several hundreds fL in volume.</p><p num="0027">Examples of a solvent to flow through a capillary cell are those in which
dye-labeled dNTP or NTP and polymerase can be dissolved, including a buffer
containing, for example, 67mM KPO<sub>4</sub> (pH7.5), 6.7mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1mM
2-mercaptoethanol. When a droplet is used, a preferred solvent is one that has no
affinity with the droplet. For example, light white oil (d=0.84g/ml; general
commercial name: mineral oil) can be used.</p><p num="0028">Examples of dyes for labeling dNTP or NTP include fluorophors or luminophors,
such as rhodamine and fluorescein (e.g. teteramethyl rhodamine, TMR, emission
wavelength: 570nm; tetramethyl rhodamine isothiocyanate, TRITC, emission
wavelength: 573nm; Rhodamine 6G, emission wavelength: 550nm; fluorescein
isothiocyanate, FITC, emission wavelength: 515nm). In addition,
4-fluoro-7-nitro-benzofurazon (NBD-F, emission wavelength: 540nm), Texas red
(emission wavelength: 605nm) or the like can be used. In the method of this invention,
the same dye may be used regardless of the type of bases, that is dNTP or NTP, or the
dye may differ according to the type of bases. To simplify the procedure, dNTP or
NTP is preferably labeled with the same dye. In binding a dye to dNTP or NTP, a
commercially available product (i.e., dye-labeled dNTP or NTP) may be used, or
otherwise, such a product may be synthesized according to a method described in
literature (e.g. J. Histochem. Cytochem. 44(5):525-529, 1996). </p><p num="0029">The fourth step comprises detecting a bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP.</p><p num="0030">As shown in Fig. 2, a bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP is detected by irradiation
of a laser beam to the nucleic acid molecule using, for example, a confocal fluorescence
microscope system, and introducing fluorescent signals emitted from the excited dye
molecule into a detector to count the number of photons and thereby detect the
fluorescent signals.</p><p num="0031">In Fig. 2, the excitation light (488nm) of an argon ion laser is reflected by a
dichroic mirror to focus on a DNA sample through an objective lens, a fluorescent
signal emitted from the dye molecules excited by the excitation light is introduced into a
confocal pin hole (e.g. 50µm in diameter) through a band pass filter, and then the
number of photons that have reached a detector (e.g. avalanche photodiode) is counted
by a multichannel counter, thereby detecting the fluorescent signal. The presence of a
band pass filter enables to selectively take fluorescent signals. Further the presence of
a pin hole eliminates unnecessary light.</p><p num="0032">The fifth step comprises disrupting dye molecules of bound, dye-labeled dNTP or
NTP.</p><p num="0033">The method of the present invention requires disruption of dye molecules, after a
dye molecule is detected after reaction of dye-labeled dNTP or NTP on a nucleic acid
molecule, but before the next dye-labeled dNTP or NTP is bound. As a means for this
purpose, for example a method of irradiation of a laser beam, which is stronger than that
in step (4) (e.g., about 10mW) can be used.</p><p num="0034">The sixth step comprises sequentially binding a dNTP or NTP, which forms a
base-pair with the nucleotide of the nucleic acid molecule, by repeating the above steps
(3) to (5) while changing the type of dye-labeled dNTP or NTP in turn. </p><p num="0035">As used herein, the word "changing the type of dye-labeled dNTP or NTP in
turn" means to keep changing the type of base introduced until binding occurs. That is,
if no binding occurs when a certain base of the four types of dye-labeled dNTP or NTP
is delivered at a nucleic acid molecule, then another certain base is delivered. If no
binding occurs again, then yet another certain base is delivered at the nucleic acid
molecule. Whether or not binding of bases occurs is confirmed by step (4), and the
dye molecule of a bound base is disrupted in step (5). The procedures from steps (3)
to (5) are repeated sequentially up to the (maximum) number of bases of the nucleic
acid molecule.</p><p num="0036">The seventh step comprises determining a nucleotide sequence of the nucleic acid
molecule based on the types of the sequentially bound dNTPs or NTPs.</p><heading>EXAMPLE</heading><p num="0037">The method of the present invention will be described in more detail, but it is not
intended that the scope of the invention is limited to the following examples.</p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0038">A Capton-coated quartz glass capillary (200µm in internal diameter x 20mm in
legnth; purchased from GL Science, Japan) was heated with a burner, thereby burning
and removing a portion of the Capton coating to provide an observation window for a
microscope. The capillary was immersed in 1M KOH, and then in a conc.
H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>/30%H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (1:2v/v) mixture, thereby eliminating oil or organic matter attached on
the glass surface and washing. Next, a template DNA was immobilized onto the inner
wall of the glass capillary by the UV crosslinking method. That is, a solution prepared
by dissolving DNA in a Carnoy's solution (methanol/acetic acid (3:1 v/v)) was
introduced into the inside of the glass capillary, then dried and solidified at room
temperature. Subsequently, 2 x SSC (NaCl 1.75g and sodium citrate 0.882g/100ml) 
was introduced into the capillary, followed by irradiation with UV, thereby binding
DNA to the solid surface. Here, the concentration of the template DNA in the
Carnoy's solution was 50pmol/µl, so that DNA could be immobilized at a density sparse
enough to confirm the reaction on a single template DNA.</p><p num="0039">Next, DNA polymerase reaction was performed for the template DNA. The
reaction solution was prepared by dissolving a primer having a sequence
complementary to the template DNA, DNA polymerase (Klenow Fragment, purchased
from TOYOBO) and a dye-labeled nucleoetide in a buffer solution (67mM KPO<sub>4</sub>,
pH7.5, 6.7mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1mM 2-mercaptoethanol). The reaction solution was allowed
to react with the template DNA, performing an incorporation reaction.</p><p num="0040">After reaction, the reaction solution was removed, and then the same solvent as
described above was allowed to flow through the capillary for washing. Then, the
inner wall of the glass capillary was observed for a bound dye using a confocal
fluorescence microscope system. That is, the dye molecule of a dye-labeled nucleotide
was excited by a laser beam, and the resulting fluorescence was observed. At this time,
the template DNA was previously immobilized on the inner wall surface of the glass
capillary at a density sparse enough to allow confirmation of an incorporation reaction
on a single template DNA.</p><p num="0041">More detailed description of experimental examples will be given, as follows.</p><heading>Reagents used:</heading><p num="0042">Template DNA No. 1 (SEQ ID NO: 1)
<img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="115" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="6"/></p><p num="0043">Template DNA No. 2 (SEQ ID NO: 2)
<img id="img-00110002" orientation="unknown" wi="99" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00110002.tif" inline="no" he="5"/></p><p num="0044">Primer No. 1 (SEQ ID NO: 3) <img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="71" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="7"/></p><p num="0045">Primer No. 2 (SEQ ID NO: 4)
<img id="img-00120002" orientation="unknown" wi="69" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00120002.tif" inline="no" he="6"/></p><p num="0046">Dye-labeled nucleotides
<sl><li>BODYPY-TMR-dUTP (purchased from FUNAKOSHI ;
absorbance wavelength 544nm, fluorescence wavelength 570nm)</li><li>TMR-dATP (purchased from Daiichi Pure Chemicals ;
absorbance wavelength 550nm, fluorescence wavelength 570nm)</li><li>TMR-dGTP (purchased from Daiichi Pure Chemicals ; absorbance wavelength
550nm, fluorescence wavelength 570nm)</li></sl></p><heading>Experiment 1 and results:</heading><p num="0047">BODYPY-TMR-dUTP nucleotide was allowed to react with a combination of the
template DNA No. 1 and the primer No. 1. In this combination of DNAs, the template
DNA has a sequence such that dUTP is incorporated onto the template DNA. The
experiment was performed according to the above described method, and as a result, it
was confirmed by observing the presence of fluorescence from a single fluorescence
molecule that BODYPY-TMR-dUTP nucleotide was incorporated onto the single
template DNA. Further, reference test 1 was conducted to confirm that the observed
fluorescence was not due to the BODYPY-TMR-dUTP nucleotide non-specifically
attached to the inner wall of a glass capillary. That is, the above reaction solution was
allowed to react with the surface of a glass capillary containing no template DNA, and
as a result, it was confirmed that BODYPY-TMR-dUTP nucleotide was not attached to
the glass capillary surface because no fluorescence was observed. Moreover,
reference test 2 was conducted using TMR-dATP nucleotide instead of
BODYPY-TMR-dUTP nucleotide. In this case, it is predicted that TMR-dATP would
not be incorporated into the single template DNA. Actually, it was confirmed that the
nucleotide was not incorporated onto the single template DNA because no fluorescence
was observed.</p><heading>Experiment 2 and results:</heading><p num="0048">The same experiment was repeated with the exception that a combination of the
template DNA No. 2 and the primer No. 2 was used. In this combination of DNAs, the
template DNA has a sequence such that dATP is incorporated onto the template DNA.
Comparison of the reaction of TMR-dATpP nucleotide to that of TMR-dGTP nucleotide
revealed that TMR-dATP was incorporated but TMR-dGTP was not incorporated onto
the single template DNA.</p><heading>Experiment 3 and results:</heading><p num="0049">A laser (10 mW, 488 nm) irradiates, for several seconds, the sample from
Experiment 1, in which BODYPY-TMR-dUTP has been incorporated by using a
combination of the single template DNA No. 1 and the primer No. 1 on the inner wall of
the capillary, thereby disrupting the dye molecule of the dye-labeled nucleotide.
Similarly, the sample from Experiment 2, in which TMR-dATP has been incorporated
by using a combination of the single template DNA No. 2 and the primer No. 2 on the
inner wall of the capillary was treated in the same manner as that described above, so
that the dye molecule fo the dye-labeled nucleotide was disrupted. For these samples,
the reaction of dye-labeled nucleotides was subsequently repeated so that the types of
nucleotides incorporated could be specified one after another.</p><heading>INDUSTRIAL APPLICABILITY</heading><p num="0050">The present invention enables to decode the bases in nucleotide sequence of a
nucleic acid, one by one.</p><heading>SEQUENCE LISTING FREE TEXT</heading><p num="0051"><sl><li>SEQ ID NO:1 - Description of Artificial Sequence: synthesized template DNA</li><li>SEQ ID NO:2 - Description of Artificial Sequence: synthesized template DNA</li><li>SEQ ID NO:3 - Description of Artificial Sequence: a primer </li><li>SEQ ID NO:4 - Description of Artificial Sequence: a primer</li></sl><img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/><img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="114"/></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for determining a nucleotide sequence of a nucleic acid by single dye
molecule detection, wherein the method comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(1) a step of immobilizing a nucleic acid molecule onto the surface of a solid;</claim-text><claim-text>(2) a step of annealing a primer, which has a sequence complementary to a part of
the sequence of the nucleic acid molecule, to the nucleic acid molecule;</claim-text><claim-text>(3) a step of providing a solution which contains DNA polymerase and one type of
dye-labeled dNTP (where N is A, T or U, G or C), or RNA polymerase and one
type of dye-labeled NTP (where N is A, U, G or C), to said immobilized nucleic
acid molecule, and allowing the nucleotide to react with the 3' end of said
primer, whereby a nucleotide, which forms a base-pair with a base opposed to
the reaction site, is bound to the primer by action of the polymerase;</claim-text><claim-text>(4) a step of detecting a bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP;</claim-text><claim-text>(5) a step of disrupting the dye molecule of the bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP;</claim-text><claim-text>(6) a step of repeating said steps (3) to (5) while changing the type of dye-labeled
dNTP or NTP in turn, to sequentially bind dNTPs or NTPs which base-pair with
the nucleotides of the nucleic acid molecule; and</claim-text><claim-text>(7) a step of determining a nucleotide sequence of the nucleic acid molecule based
on the types of the sequentially bound dNTPs or NTPs.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method for determining a nucleotide sequence of a nucleic acid by single dye
molecule detection, wherein the method comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(1) a step of immobilizing a primer, which has a sequence complementary to a part
of the sequence of a nucleic acid molecule to be measured, onto the surface of a
solid;</claim-text><claim-text>(2) a step of annealing the nucleic acid molecule to the primer;</claim-text><claim-text>(3) a step of providing a solution which contains DNA polymerase and one type of
dye-labeled dNTP (where N is A, T or U, G or C), or RNA polymerase and one
type of dye-labeled NTP (where N is A, U, G or C), to the immobilized nucleic
acid molecule, and allowing the nucleotide to react with the 3' end of the primer,
whereby a nucleotide, which forms a base-pair with a base opposed to the
reaction site, is bound to the primer by action of the polymerase;</claim-text><claim-text>(4) a step of detecting the presence of a bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP;</claim-text><claim-text>(5) a step of disrupting the dye molecule of the bound, dye-labeled dNTP or NTP;</claim-text><claim-text>(6) a step of repeating said steps (3) to (5) while changing the type of dye-labeled
dNTP or NTP in turn, to sequentially bind dNTPs or NTPs complementary to
the nucleotide of the nucleic acid molecule; and</claim-text><claim-text>(7) a step of determining a nucleotide sequence of the nucleic acid molecule based
on the types of the sequentially bound dNTPs or NTPs.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 or 2 wherein said surface of a solid is the inner wall of a
capillary.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 or 2 wherein said step (4) comprises optically detecting
the dye molecule of said dye-labeled dNTP or NTP.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method of claim 4 wherein said step (4) comprises exciting dye molecules
by irradiation of a laser beam and detecting the thus released fluorescent signal.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method of claim 5 wherein said detection is performed using a confocal
fluorescence microscope system.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 or 2 wherein said disruption of dye molecules in said step
(5) is performed by irradiation of a laser beam stronger than that in the step (4).</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 or 2 wherein said dye is a fluorescent dye.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 or 2 wherein said solution consists of a droplet in which
an aqueous solution containing said dye-labeled dNTP or NTP, is entrapped within a
hydrophobic liquid.</claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure num="1"><img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="218"/></figure><figure num="2"><img id="img-00200001" orientation="unknown" wi="158" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00200001.tif" inline="no" he="205"/></figure></drawings><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="149" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="231" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="155" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="231" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>