<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1486557-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1486557" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="33299693" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20041215"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1486557-A1" status="new" fvid="24212176"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1486557</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20041215</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04076511-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04076511</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040525</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-45984603-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>45984603</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030612</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 127/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 127/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 127/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 143/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 143/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 143/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 143/12        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 159/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 159/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 169/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 169/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 171/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 171/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  20/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  20/02        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  30/02        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  30/08        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  40/25        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 169/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M203:10B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M205:022</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M205:024</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M205:026</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M205:02B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M205:04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M205:06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M205:08</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N220:022</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N220:029</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N230:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N230:74</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Konzentrate enthaltend Viskositätsindexverbesserer</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Viscosity index improver concentrates</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Concentrat d'additif pour améliorer l'indice de viscosité</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-6034042-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6034042</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6232279-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6232279</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2002010276-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2002010276</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2004033606-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2004033606</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>INFINEUM INT LTD</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>INFINEUM INTERNATIONAL LIMITED</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Infineum International Limited</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 1, Milton Hill</street><city>Abingdon, Oxfordshire OX13 6BB</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>BANSAL JAI GOPAL</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BLOCH RICARDO ALFREDO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CLARKE DEAN B</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BANSAL, JAI GOPAL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BLOCH, RICARDO ALFREDO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CLARKE, DEAN B.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BANSAL, JAI GOPAL</last-name><address><street>900 Cranford Avenue</street><city>Westfield New Jersey, 07090</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BLOCH, RICARDO ALFREDO</last-name><address><street>1532 Ashbrook Drive</street><city>Scotch Plains New Jersey, 07076</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CLARKE, DEAN B.</last-name><address><street>1021 Hillcrest Drive</street><city>Neshanic Station New Jersey, 08853</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Mansell, Keith Rodney</last-name><address><street>Infineum UK Ltd, Law Department, P.O. Box 1, Milton Hill</street><city>Abingdon, Oxfordshire OX13 6BB</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A viscosity index (VI) improver concentrate containing at least one VI improver,
from 0 to 5 mass % of lubricating oil flow improver (LOFI) and diluent oil, wherein the
diluent oil has a kv<sub>100</sub> of at least 3.0 µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> (cSt) and a CCS at -35°C of less than 3700 mPas
(cPs), and wherein at least 98 mass % of the concentrate is composed of VI improver, LOFI
and diluent oil.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The invention relates to viscosity index improver concentrates useful in the
formulation of lubricating oil compositions. More specifically, the present invention is
directed to viscosity index improver concentrate containing at least one polymeric viscosity
index improver, and optionally a polymeric lubricating oil flow improver, in diluent oil,
wherein the diluent oil has specified kinematic viscosity and CCS characteristics.</p><p num="0002">Lubricating oil compositions for use in crankcase engine oils comprise a major
amount of base stock oil and minor amounts of additives that improve the performance and
increase the useful life of the lubricant. Crankcase lubricating oil compositions
conventionally contain polymeric components that are used to improve the viscometric
performance of the engine oil, i.e., to provide multigrade oils such as SAE 5W-30, 10W-30
and 10W-40. These viscosity performance enhancers, commonly referred to as viscosity
index (VI) improvers, include olefin copolymers, polymethacrylates, styrene/hydrogenated
diene block and star copolymers and hydrogenated isoprene linear and star polymers.</p><p num="0003">Olefin copolymers used as VI improvers conventionally comprise copolymers of
ethylene, propylene and, optionally, a diene. High ethylene content olefin copolymer VI
improvers are known to provide reduced lubricating oil resistance to cold engine starting (as
measured by "CCS" performance). However, polymer chains having long ethylene sequences
have a more crystalline polymer structure. Crystalline polymers have been found, primarily
at low temperatures, to interact with waxes in the oil and other olefin copolymer chains,
which results in uncontrollable increases in low temperature viscosity and, in extreme cases,
the gelling of the lubricating oil. These problems have been found to manifest in Ziegler
Natta polymerized olefin copolymers containing greater than about 60 mass % polymer
derived from ethylene (hereinafter referred to as "high ethylene content", or "crystalline"
olefin copolymer").</p><p num="0004">VI improvers are commonly provided to lubricating oil blenders as a concentrate in
which the VI improver polymer is diluted in oil to allow, <i>inter alia</i>, for more facile
dissolution of the VI improver in the base stock oil. A typical VI improver concentrate can
contain as little as 4 mass % active polymer, with the remainder being diluent oil. A typical
formulated multigrade crankcase lubricating oil may, depending on the thickening efficiency
(TE) of the polymer, require as much as 3 mass % of active VI improver polymer. An 
additive concentrate providing this amount of polymer can introduce as much as 15 mass %,
based on the total mass of the finished lubricant, of diluent oil.</p><p num="0005">There has been a continued demand for lubricating oil compositions providing
improved fuel economy. There has also been a continuous demand for VI improvers that
provide improved CCS performance in formulated lubricating oil compositions, without wax
and polymer chain interaction (gelling). Much effort has been made in these respects to select
the proper base stock oil and to provide a low ethylene content (amorphous) VI improver
having improved CCS performance. However, little attention has been paid to the selection
of the diluent oil used to form the VI improver concentrate. As the additive industry is highly
competitive from a pricing standpoint, and diluent oil represents one of the largest raw
material costs to the additive manufacturers, VI improver concentrates have commonly
contained the least expensive oil capable of providing suitable handling characteristics;
usually a solvent neutral (SN) 100 or SN150 Group 1 oil. Using such conventional VI
improver concentrates, the finished lubricant formulator has needed to add a quantity of
relatively high quality base stock oil, as a correction fluid, to insure the formulation CCS
dynamic viscosity remained within specification.</p><p num="0006">As lubricating oil performance standards have become more stringent, there has been
a continuing need to identify components capable of conveniently and cost effectively
improving overall lubricant performance. Therefore, it would be advantageous to be able to
provide a VI improver concentrate that delivers improved cold temperature performance,
regardless of the VI improver employed, without requiring use of correction fluids.</p><p num="0007">In accordance with a first aspect of the invention, there is provided a viscosity index
(VI) improver concentrate comprising at least one polymeric VI improving material,
optionally a polymeric lubricating oil flow improver (LOFI) material, and diluent oil, wherein
the diluent oil has a kinematic viscosity at 100°C (kv<sub>100</sub>) of at least 3.0 3µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> (Cst), and
dynamic viscosity at -35°C , as measured using a cold cranking simulator (CCS), of less than
3700 mPas (cPs), and wherein at least 98 mass % of said concentrate consists essentially of
VI improving material, LOFI material and diluent oil.</p><p num="0008">In accordance with a second aspect of the invention, there is provided a (VI) improver
concentrate, as in the first aspect, wherein the diluent oil has a Noack volatility of less than 40
mass %. The Noack volatility being measured in accordance with the procedures of ASTM
D5800. </p><p num="0009">In accordance with a third aspect of the invention, there is provided a VI improver
concentrate, as in the first or second aspect, wherein the concentrate has a kinematic viscosity
at 100°C (kv<sub>100</sub>) of from about 300 to about 2500µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> (cSt).</p><p num="0010">In accordance with a fourth aspect of the invention, there is provided a VI improver
concentrate, as in the first, second or third aspect, wherein the VI improver is a copolymer of
ethylene and another α-olefin (OCP).</p><p num="0011">In accordance with a fifth aspect of the invention, there is provided a VI improver
concentrate, as in the fourth aspect, wherein the VI improver is an amorphous OCP.</p><p num="0012">Other and further objects, advantages and features of the present invention will be
understood by reference to the following specification.</p><p num="0013">VI improvers useful in the practice of the invention include ethylene-α-olefin
copolymers (OCP) synthesized from ethylene monomer and at least one other α-olefin
comonomer. The average ethylene content of OCP useful in the present invention can be as
low as about 20% on a mass basis; preferably about 25%; more preferably about 30%. The
maximum ethylene content can be about 90% on a mass basis; preferably about 85%; most
preferably about 80%. OCP intended for use as viscosity modifiers typically comprise from
about 35 to 75 wt. % ethylene but more preferably are "amorphous" or substantially
amorphous copolymers comprising less than about 60 mass %, (e.g. 40 to 56 mass %)
ethylene. Crystalline ethylene-α-olefin copolymers are defined as those comprising greater
than about 60 mass ethylene (e.g. from about 60 to about 90 mass % ethylene). Conversely,
amorphous or substantially amorphous ethylene-α-olefin copolymers used as VI improving
materials typically comprise from about 25 to about 60 mass % ethylene; preferably from
about 30 to about 60 mass % ethylene; more preferably from about 35 to about 60 mass %
ethylene. Ethylene content can be measured by ASTM-D3900 for ethylene-propylene
copolymers containing between 35 mass % and 85 mass % ethylene. Above 85 mass %,
ASTM-D2238 can be used to obtain methyl group concentration, which is related to percent
ethylene in an unambiguous manner for ethylene-propylene copolymers. When comonomers
other than propylene are employed, no ASTM tests covering a wide range of ethylene
contents are available; however, proton and carbon-13 nuclear magnetic resonance
spectroscopy can be employed to determine the composition of such polymers. These are
absolute techniques requiring no calibration when operated such that all nuclei of a given 
element contribute equally to the spectra. For ethylene content ranges not covered by the
ASTM tests for ethylene-propylene copolymers, as well as for any ethylene-propylene
copolymers, the aforementioned nuclear magnetic resonance methods can also be used.</p><p num="0014">As noted, the ethylene-α-olefin copolymers are comprised of ethylene and at least one
other α-olefin. The "other" α-olefins typically include those containing 3 to 18 carbon atoms,
e.g., propylene, butene-1, pentene-1, etc. Preferred are α-olefins having 3 to 6 carbon atoms,
particularly for economic reasons. The most preferred OCP are those comprised of ethylene
and propylene.</p><p num="0015">As is well known to those skilled in the art, copolymers of ethylene and higher alphaolefins
such as propylene can optionally include other polymerizable monomers. Typical of
these other monomers are non-conjugated dienes such as the following non-limiting
examples:
<sl><li>a. straight chain acyclic dienes such as: 1,4-hexadiene; 1,6-octadiene;</li><li>b. branched chain acyclic dienes such as: 5-methyl-1, 4-hexadiene; 3, 7-dimethyl-1,6-octadiene;
3, 7-dimethyl-1,7-octadiene and the mixed isomers of dihydro-mycene and
dihydroocinene;</li><li>c. single ring alicyclic dienes such as: 1, 4-cyclohexadiene; 1,5-cyclooctadiene; and 1,5-cyclododecadiene;
and</li><li>d. multi-ring alicyclic fused and bridged ring dienes such as: tetrahydroindene;
methyltetrahydroindene; dicyclopentadiene; bicyclo-(2,2,1)-hepta-2, 5-diene; alkenyl,
alkylidene, cycloalkenyl and cycloalkylidene norbornenes such as 5-methylene-2-norbornene
(MNB), 5-ethylidene-2-norbornene (ENB), 5-propylene-2-norbornene, 5-isopropylidene-2-norbornene,
5-(4-cyclopentenyl)-2-norbornene; 5-cyclohexylidene-2-norbornene.</li></sl></p><p num="0016">Of the non-conjugated dienes typically used to prepare these copolymers, dienes
containing at least one of the double bonds in a strained ring are preferred. The most
preferred diene is 5-ethylidene-2-norbornene (ENB). When present, the amount of diene (on
a weight basis) in the copolymer can be from greater than 0% to about 20%; preferably from
greater than 0% to about 15%; most preferably greater than 0% to about 10%.</p><p num="0017">The molecular weight of OCP useful in accordance with the present invention can
vary over a wide range since ethylene copolymers having number-average molecular weights
(M<sub>n</sub>) as low as about 2,000 can affect the viscosity properties of an oleaginous composition.
The preferred minimum M<sub>n</sub> is about 10,000; the most preferred minimum is about 20,000. 
The maximum M<sub>n</sub> can be as high as about 12,000,000; the preferred maximum is about
1,000,000; the most preferred maximum is about 750,000. An especially preferred range of
number-average molecular weight for OCP useful in the present invention is from about
15,000 to about 500,000; preferably from about 20,000 to about 250,000; more preferably
from about 25,000 to about 150,000. The term "number average molecular weight", as used
herein, refers to the number average weight as measured by Gel Permeation Chromatography
("GPC") with a polystyrene standard.</p><p num="0018">Other VI improvers useful in the practice of the invention include homopolymers and
copolymers of diolefins containing from 4 to about 12 carbon atoms, preferably from 8 to
about 16 carbon atoms, such as 1,3-butadiene, isoprene, piperylene, methylpentadiene,
phenylbutadiene, 3,4-dimethyl-1,3-hexadiene, 4,5-diethyl-1,3-octadiene, and copolymers of
one or more conjugated diolefins and one or more monoalkenyl aromatic hydrocarbons
containing from 8 to about 16 carbon atoms such as aryl-substituted styrenes, alkoxy-substituted
styrenes, vinyl naphthalene, alkyl-substituted vinyl naphthalenes and the like.
Such polymers and copolymers include random polymers, tapered polymers and block
copolymers and may be of a star or linear structure.</p><p num="0019">Linear block copolymers useful in the practice of the present invention may be
represented by the following general formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">A<sub>z</sub>-(B-A)<sub>y</sub>-B<sub>x</sub></st32:che>
wherein:
<sl><li>A is a polymeric block comprising predominantly monoalkenyl aromatic hydrocarbon
monomer units;</li><li>B is a polymeric block comprising predominantly conjugated diolefin monomer units;</li><li>x and z are, independently, a number equal to 0 or 1; and</li><li>y is a whole number ranging from 1 to about 15.</li></sl></p><p num="0020">Useful tapered linear block copolymers may be represented by the following general
formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">A-A/B-B</st32:che>
wherein:
<sl><li>A is a polymeric block comprising predominantly monoalkenyl aromatic hydrocarbon
monomer units; </li><li>B is a polymeric block comprising predominantly conjugated diolefin monomer units;
and</li><li>A/B is a tapered segment containing both monoalkenyl aromatic hydrocarbon and
conjugated diolefin units.</li></sl></p><p num="0021">Radial or star polymers may be represented, generally, by the following general
formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">(B<sub>x</sub>-(A-B)<sub>y</sub>-A<sub>z</sub>)<sub>n</sub>-C;</st32:che>
and
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">(B'<sub>x</sub>-(A-B)<sub>y</sub>-A<sub>z</sub>)<sub>n'</sub>-C(B')<sub>n"</sub></st32:che>
wherein:
<sl><li>A, B, x, y and z are as previously defined;</li><li>n is a number from 3 to 30;</li><li>C is the core of the radial polymer formed with a polyfunctional coupling agent;</li><li>B' is a polymeric block comprising predominantly conjugated diolefin units, which
B' may be the same or different from B; and</li><li>n' and n" are integers representing the number of each type of arm and the sum of n'
and n" will be a number from 3 to 30.</li></sl></p><p num="0022">As used herein in connection with polymer block composition, predominantly means
that the specified monomer or monomer type which is the principle component in that
polymer block is present in an amount of at least 85% by weight of the block.</p><p num="0023">Polymers prepared with diolefins will contain ethylenic unsaturation, and such
polymers are preferably hydrogenated. When the polymer is hydrogenated, the
hydrogenation may be accomplished using any of the techniques known in the prior art. For
example, the hydrogenation may be accomplished such that both ethylenic and aromatic
unsaturation is converted (saturated) using methods such as those taught, for example, in U.S.
Pat. Nos. 3,113,986 and 3,700,633 or the hydrogenation may be accomplished selectively
such that a significant portion of the ethylenic unsaturation is converted while little or no
aromatic unsaturation is converted as taught, for example, in U.S. Pat. Nos. 3,634,595;
3,670,054; 3,700,633 and Re 27,145. Any of these methods can also be used to hydrogenate
polymers containing only ethylenic unsaturation and which are free of aromatic unsaturation. </p><p num="0024">Polymeric VI improvers may include mixtures of linear polymers as disclosed above,
but having different molecular weights and/or different alkenyl aromatic contents as well as
mixtures of star polymers having different molecular weights and/or different alkenyl
aromatic contents. Alternatively, mixtures of star polymers and linear polymers having
different molecular weights and/or different alkenyl aromatic contents may be used. The use
of two or more different polymers may be preferred to a single polymer depending on the
rheological properties the product is intended to impart when used to produce formulated
engine oil. Mixtures of, for example, OCP and star polymers are also known.</p><p num="0025">In general, number average molecular weights of between about 200,000 and about
1,500,000 are acceptable, and between about 350,000 and about 900,000 are preferred, and
between about 350,000 and about 800,000 are most preferred for the base polymer when the
base polymer is a star-configuration hydrogenated polymer of one or more conjugated olefins
or a star configuration polymer of one or more alpha olefins. When the base polymer is a star
configuration copolymer containing more than about 3% by weight of monoalkenyl arenes,
the number average molecular weight is preferably between about 350,000 and about 800,000.</p><p num="0026">When the base polymer is a copolymer of monoalkenyl arene and polymerized alpha
olefins, hydrogenated polymerized diolefins or combinations thereof, the amount of
monoalkenyl arene in the base polymer is preferably between about 5% and about 40% by
weight of the base polymer. For such polymers, number average molecular weights between
about 85,000 and about 300,000 are acceptable.</p><p num="0027">Useful copolymers of this type include those prepared in bulk, suspension, solution or
emulsion. As is well known, polymerization of monomers to produce hydrocarbon polymers
may be accomplished using free-radical, cationic and anionic initiators or polymerization
catalysts, such as transition metal catalysts used for Ziegler-Natta and metallocene type
catalysts.</p><p num="0028">Optionally, the VI improvers used in the practice of the invention can be provided
with nitrogen-containing functional groups that impart dispersant capabilities to the VI
improver. One trend in the industry has been to use such "multifunctional" VI improvers in
lubricants to replace some or all of the dispersant. Nitrogen-containing functional groups can
be added to a polymeric VI improver by grafting a nitrogen- or hydroxyl- containing moiety,
preferably a nitrogen-containing moiety, onto the polymeric backbone of the VI improver
(functionalizing). Processes for the grafting of a nitrogen-containing moiety onto a polymer 
are known in the art and include, for example, contacting the polymer and nitrogen-containing
moiety in the presence of a free radical initiator, either neat, or in the presence of a solvent.
The free radical initiator may be generated by shearing (as in an extruder) or heating a free
radical initiator precursor, such as hydrogen peroxide.</p><p num="0029">The amount of nitrogen-containing grafting monomer will depend, to some extent, on
the nature of the substrate polymer and the level of dispersancy required of the grafted
polymer. To impart dispersancy characteristics to both star and linear copolymers, the
amount of grafted nitrogen-containing monomer is suitably between about 0.4 and about 2.2
wt. %, preferably from about 0.5 to about 1.8 wt. %, most preferably from about 0.6 to about
1.2 wt. %, based on the total weight of grafted polymer.</p><p num="0030">Methods for grafting nitrogen-containing monomer onto polymer backbones, and
suitable nitrogen-containing grafting monomers are known and described, for example, in U.S.
Patent No. 5,141,996, WO 98/13443, WO 99/21902, U.S. Patent No. 4,146,489, U.S. Patent
No. 4,292,414, and U.S. Patent No. 4,506,056. (See also <i>J Polymer Science,</i> Part A: Polymer
Chemistry, Vol. 26, 1189-1198 (1988); <i>J. Polymer Science,</i> Polymer Letters, Vol. 20, 481-486
(1982) and <i>J. Polymer Science,</i> Polymer Letters, Vol. 21, 23-30 (1983), all to Gaylord
and Mehta and <u style="single">Degradation and Cross-linking of Ethylene-Propylene Copolymer Rubber on
Reaction with Maleic Anhydride and/or Peroxides;</u><i>J</i>. <i>Applied Polymer Science,</i> Vol. 33,
2549-2558 (1987) to Gaylord, Mehta and Mehta.</p><p num="0031">Oils of lubricating viscosity useful as the diluents of the present invention may be
selected from natural lubricating oils, synthetic lubricating oils and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0032">Natural oils include animal oils and vegetable oils (e.g., castor oil, lard oil); liquid
petroleum oils and hydro-refined, solvent-treated or acid-treated mineral oils of the paraffinic,
naphthenic and mixed paraffinic-naphthenic types. Oils of lubricating viscosity derived from
coal or shale also serve as useful base oils.</p><p num="0033">Synthetic lubricating oils include hydrocarbon oils and halo-substituted hydrocarbon
oils such as polymerized and interpolymerized olefins (e.g., polybutylenes, polypropylenes,
propylene-isobutylene copolymers, chlorinated polybutylenes, poly(1-hexenes), poly(1-octenes),
poly(1-decenes)); alkylbenzenes (e.g., dodecylbenzenes, tetradecylbenzenes,
dinonylbenzenes, di(2-ethylhexyl)benzenes); polyphenyls (e.g., biphenyls, terphenyls, 
alkylated polyphenols); and alkylated diphenyl ethers and alkylated diphenyl sulfides and
derivative, analogs and homologs thereof.</p><p num="0034">Alkylene oxide polymers and interpolymers and derivatives thereof where the
terminal hydroxyl groups have been modified by esterification, etherification, etc., constitute
another class of known synthetic lubricating oils. These are exemplified by polyoxyalkylene
polymers prepared by polymerization of ethylene oxide or propylene oxide, and the alkyl and
aryl ethers of polyoxyalkylene polymers (e.g., methyl-polyiso-propylene glycol ether having a
molecular weight of 1000 or diphenyl ether of poly-ethylene glycol having a molecular
weight of 1000 to 1500); and mono- and polycarboxylic esters thereof, for example, the acetic
acid esters, mixed C<sub>3</sub>-C<sub>8</sub> fatty acid esters and C<sub>13</sub> Oxo acid diester of tetraethylene glycol.</p><p num="0035">Another suitable class of synthetic lubricating oils comprises the esters of
dicarboxylic acids (e.g., phthalic acid, succinic acid, alkyl succinic acids and alkenyl succinic
acids, maleic acid, azelaic acid, suberic acid, sebasic acid, fumaric acid, adipic acid, linoleic
acid dimer, malonic acid, alkylmalonic acids, alkenyl malonic acids) with a variety of
alcohols (e.g., butyl alcohol, hexyl alcohol, dodecyl alcohol, 2-ethylhexyl alcohol, ethylene
glycol, diethylene glycol monoether, propylene glycol). Examples of such esters include
dibutyl adipate, di(2-ethylhexyl) sebacate, di-n-hexyl fumarate, dioctyl sebacate, diisooctyl
azelate, diisodecyl azelate, dioctyl phthalate, didecyl phthalate, dieicosyl sebacate, the 2-ethylhexyl
diester of linoleic acid dimer, and the complex ester formed by reacting one mole
of sebacic acid with two moles of tetraethylene glycol and two moles of 2-ethylhexanoic acid.</p><p num="0036">Esters useful as synthetic oils also include those made from C<sub>5</sub> to C<sub>12</sub> monocarboxylic
acids and polyols and polyol esters such as neopentyl glycol, trimethylolpropane,
pentaerythritol, dipentaerythritol and tripentaerythritol.</p><p num="0037">Silicon-based oils such as the polyalkyl-, polyaryl-, polyalkoxy- or
polyaryloxysilicone oils and silicate oils comprise another useful class of synthetic lubricants;
such oils include tetraethyl silicate, tetraisopropyl silicate, tetra-(2-ethylhexyl)silicate, tetra-(4-methyl-2-ethylhexyl)silicate,
tetra-(p-tert-butyl-phenyl) silicate, hexa-(4-methyl-2-ethylhexyl)disiloxane,
poly(methyl)siloxanes and poly(methylphenyl)siloxanes. Other
synthetic lubricating oils include liquid esters of phosphorous-containing acids (e.g., tricresyl
phosphate, trioctyl phosphate, diethyl ester of decylphosphonic acid) and polymeric
tetrahydrofurans. </p><p num="0038">The diluent oil may comprise a Group I, Group II, Group III, Group IV or Group V oil
or blends of the aforementioned oils. The diluent oil may also comprise a blend of a Group I
oil and one or more of Group II, Group III, Group IV or Group V oil. Preferably, from an
economic standpoint, the diluent oil is a mixture of a Group I oil and one or more a Group II,
Group III, Group IV or Group V oil, more preferably a mixture of a Group I oil and one or
more Group II or Group III oil.</p><p num="0039">Definitions for the oils as used herein are the same as those found in the American
Petroleum Institute (API) publication "Engine Oil Licensing and Certification System",
Industry Services Department, Fourteenth Edition, December 1996, Addendum 1, December
1998. Said publication categorizes oils as follows:
<sl><li>a) Group I oils contain less than 90 percent saturates and/or greater than 0.03 percent
sulfur and have a viscosity index greater than or equal to 80 and less than 120 using the
test methods specified in Table 1.</li><li>b) Group II oils contain greater than or equal to 90 percent saturates and less than or
equal to 0.03 percent sulfur and have a viscosity index greater than or equal to 80 and
less than 120 using the test methods specified in Table 1. Although not a separate
Group recognized by the API, Group II oils having a viscosity index greater than about
110 are often referred to as "Group II+" oils.</li><li>c) Group III oils contain greater than or equal to 90 percent saturates and less than or
equal to 0.03 percent sulfur and have a viscosity index greater than or equal to 120
using the test methods specified in Table 1.</li><li>d) Group IV oils are polyalphaolefins (PAO).</li><li>e) Group V oils are all other base stocks not included in Group I, II, III, or IV.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Property</entry><entry align="left">Test Method</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Saturates</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D2007</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity Index</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D2270</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sulfur</entry><entry align="left">ASTM D4294</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></li></sl></p><p num="0040">As noted <i>supra</i>, diluent oil useful in the practice of the invention has a CCS dynamic
viscosity at -35°C of less than 3700mPas (cPs), such as less than 3300mPas (cPs), preferably
less than 3000mPas (cPs), such as less than 2800mPas (cPs) and more preferably less than
2500mPas (cPs), such as less than 2300mPas (cPs). </p><p num="0041">Diluent oil useful in the practice of the invention also has a kinematic viscosity at
100°C (kv<sub>100</sub>) of at least 3.0 µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> (cSt),such as from about 3 to 5 µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> (cSt),, especially
from about 3 µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> to 4 µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> (cSt), such as from about 3.4 to 4 µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> (cSt) More active
polymer may be required to provide suitable viscometrics when lower viscosity diluent oil is
used.</p><p num="0042">The diluent oil preferably has a saturate content of at least 65%, more preferably at
least 75%, such as at least 85%. Most preferably, the diluent oil has a saturate content of
greater than 90%. Preferably, the diluent oil has a sulfur content of less than 1%, preferably
less than 0.6%, more preferably less than 0.3%, by mass, such as 0 to 0.3% by mass.</p><p num="0043">Preferably the volatility of the diluent oil, as measured by the Noack test (ASTM
D5880), is less than or equal to about 40 mass %, such as less than or equal to about 35
mass %, preferably less than or equal to about 32 mass %, such as less than or equal to about
28 mass %, more preferably less than or equal to about 16 mass %. Using a diluent oil having
a greater volatility makes it difficult to provide a formulated lubricant having a Noack
volatility of less than or equal to 15 mass %. Formulated lubricants having a higher level of
volatility may display fuel economy debits. Preferably, the viscosity index (VI) of the diluent
oil is at least 85, preferably at least 100, most preferably from about 105 to 140.</p><p num="0044">The VI improver concentrate may also be used to provide a polymeric
lubricating oil flow improver (LOFI), also commonly referred to as pour point depressant
(PPD). The LOFI is used to lower the minimum temperature at which the fluid will flow or
can be poured and such additives are well known. Typical of such additives are C<sub>8</sub> to C<sub>18</sub>
dialkyl fumarate/vinyl acetate copolymers, polymethacrylates and styrene/maleic anhydride
ester copolymers.</p><p num="0045">The VI improver concentrates of the present invention can contain from about 4 to
about 50 mass %, such as from about 5 to about 25 mass %, preferably from about 6 to about
20 mass %, such as from about 7 to about 15 mass % of VI improver and from about 0 to
about 5 mass % of LOFI, with the remainder comprising diluent. At least about 98 mass %,
preferably at least about 99.5 mass % of the VI improver concentrate consists essentially of
VI improver, LOFI and diluent oil. </p><p num="0046">The VI improver concentrates of the present invention can be prepared by dissolving
the VI improver polymer(s), and optional LOFI, in the diluent oil using well known
techniques. When dissolving a solid VI improver polymer to form a concentrate, the high
viscosity of the polymer can cause poor diffusivity in the diluent oil. To facilitate dissolution,
it is common to increase the surface area of the polymer by, for example, pelletizing,
chopping, grinding or pulverizing the polymer. The temperature of the diluent oil can also be
increased by heating using, for example, steam or hot oil. When the diluent temperature is
greatly increased (such as to above 100°C), heating should be conducted under a blanket of
inert gas (e.g., N<sub>2</sub> or CO<sub>2</sub>). The temperature of the polymer may also be raised using, for
example, mechanical energy imparted to the polymer in an extruder or masticator. The
polymer temperature can be raised above 150°C; the polymer temperature is preferably raised
under a blanket of inert gas. Dissolving of the polymer may also be aided by agitating the
concentrate, such as by stirring or agitating (in either the reactor or in a tank), or by using a
recirculation pump. Any two or more of the foregoing techniques can also be used in
combination. Concentrates can also be formed by exchanging the polymerization solvent
(usually a volatile hydrocarbon such as, for example, propane, hexane or cyclohexane) with
oil. This exchange can be accomplished by, for example, using a distillation column to assure
that substantially none of the polymerization solvent remains.</p><p num="0047">The concentrates of the invention are principally used in the formulation of crankcase
lubricating oils for passenger car and heavy duty diesel engines (fully formulated lubricants),
which fully formulated lubricants comprise a major amount of an oil of lubricating viscosity
and a viscosity index (VI) improver as described above, in an amount effective to meet the
requirements of the selected grade. Such fully formulated lubricants may contain the VI
improver provided by the concentrate of the invention in an amount of from about 0.1 mass %
to about 3 mass %, preferably from about 0.2 mass % to about 2 mass %, more preferably
from about 0.3 mass % to about 1.5 mass %, stated as mass percent active ingredient (AI)
based on the total mass of the formulated lubricant. The amount of VI improver needed to
provide the fully formulated lubricant with the required viscometric properties is further a
function of the TE of the VI improver employed.</p><p num="0048">In addition to the VI improver and LOFI, a fully formulated lubricant can generally
contain a number of other performance improving additives selected from ashless dispersants,
metal-containing, or ash-forming detergents, antiwear agents, oxidation inhibitors or
antioxidants, friction modifiers and fuel economy agents, and stabilizers or emulsifiers.
Conventionally, when formulating a lubricant, the VI improver and/or VI improver and LOFI, 
will be provided to the formulator in one concentrated package, and combinations of the
remaining additives will be provided in one or more additional concentrated packages,
oftentimes referred to as DI (dispersant-inhibitor) packages.</p><p num="0049">Ashless dispersants maintain in suspension oil insolubles resulting from oxidation of
the oil during wear or combustion. They are particularly advantageous for preventing the
precipitation of sludge and the formation of varnish, particularly in gasoline engines.</p><p num="0050">Metal-containing or ash-forming detergents function both as detergents to reduce or
remove deposits and as acid neutralizers or rust inhibitors, thereby reducing wear and
corrosion and extending engine life. Detergents generally comprise a polar head with a long
hydrophobic tail, with the polar head comprising a metal salt of an acidic organic compound.
The salts may contain a substantially stoichiometric amount of the metal in which case they
are usually described as normal or neutral salts, and would typically have a total base number
or TBN (as can be measured by ASTM D2896) of from 0 to 80. A large amount of a metal
base may be incorporated by reacting excess metal compound (e.g., an oxide or hydroxide)
with an acidic gas (e.g., carbon dioxide). The resulting overbased detergent comprises
neutralized detergent as the outer layer of a metal base (e.g. carbonate) micelle. Such
overbased detergents may have a TBN of 150 or greater, and typically will have a TBN of
from 250 to 450 or more.</p><p num="0051">Dihydrocarbyl dithiophosphate metal salts are frequently used as antiwear and
antioxidant agents. The metal may be an alkali or alkaline earth metal, or aluminum, lead, tin,
molybdenum, manganese, nickel or copper. The zinc salts are most commonly used in
lubricating oil and may be prepared in accordance with known techniques by first forming a
dihydrocarbyl dithiophosphoric acid (DDPA), usually by reaction of one or more alcohol or a
phenol with P<sub>2</sub>S<sub>5</sub> and then neutralizing the formed DDPA with a zinc compound. For
example, a dithiophosphoric acid may be made by reacting mixtures of primary and
secondary alcohols. Alternatively, multiple dithiophosphoric acids can be prepared where the
hydrocarbyl groups on one are entirely secondary in character and the hydrocarbyl groups on
the others are entirely primary in character. To make the zinc salt, any basic or neutral zinc
compound could be used but the oxides, hydroxides and carbonates are most generally
employed. Commercial additives frequently contain an excess of zinc due to the use of an
excess of the basic zinc compound in the neutralization reaction. </p><p num="0052">Oxidation inhibitors or antioxidants reduce the tendency of mineral oils to deteriorate
in service. Oxidative deterioration can be evidenced by sludge in the lubricant, varnish-like
deposits on the metal surfaces, and by viscosity growth. Such oxidation inhibitors include
hindered phenols, alkaline earth metal salts of alkylphenolthioesters having preferably C<sub>5</sub> to
C<sub>12</sub> alkyl side chains, calcium nonylphenol sulfide, oil soluble phenates and sulfurized
phenates, phosphosulfurized or sulfurized hydrocarbons, phosphorous esters, metal
thiocarbamates, oil soluble copper compounds as described in U.S. Patent No. 4,867,890, and
molybdenum-containing compounds and aromatic amines.</p><p num="0053">Known friction modifiers include oil-soluble organo-molybdenum compounds. Such
organo-molybdenum friction modifiers also provide antioxidant and antiwear credits to a
lubricating oil composition. As an example of such oil soluble organo-molybdenum compounds,
there may be mentioned the dithiocarbamates, dithiophosphates, dithiophosphinates, xanthates,
thioxanthates, sulfides, and the like, and mixtures thereof. Particularly preferred are
molybdenum dithiocarbamates, dialkyldithiophosphates, alkyl xanthates and alkylthioxanthates.</p><p num="0054">Other known friction modifying materials include glyceryl monoesters of higher fatty
acids, for example, glyceryl mono-oleate; esters of long chain polycarboxylic acids with diols,
for example, the butane diol ester of a dimerized unsaturated fatty acid; oxazoline
compounds; and alkoxylated alkyl-substituted mono-amines, diamines and alkyl ether amines,
for example, ethoxylated tallow amine and ethoxylated tallow ether amine.</p><p num="0055">Foam control can be provided by an antifoamant of the polysiloxane type, for
example, silicone oil or polydimethyl siloxane.</p><p num="0056">Some of the above-mentioned additives can provide a multiplicity of effects; thus for
example, a single additive may act as a dispersant-oxidation inhibitor. This approach is well
known and need not be further elaborated herein.</p><p num="0057">It may also be necessary to include an additive which maintains the stability of the
viscosity of the blend. Thus, although polar group-containing additives achieve a suitably
low viscosity in the pre-blending stage it has been observed that some compositions increase
in viscosity when stored for prolonged periods. Additives which are effective in controlling
this viscosity increase include the long chain hydrocarbons functionalized by reaction with
mono- or dicarboxylic acids or anhydrides which are used in the preparation of the ashless
dispersants as hereinbefore disclosed. </p><p num="0058">Representative effective amounts of such additional additives, when used in
crankcase lubricants, are listed below:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center">ADDITIVE</entry><entry align="center">Mass % (Broad)</entry><entry align="center">Mass % (Preferred)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ashless Dispersant</entry><entry align="center">0.1 - 20</entry><entry align="center">1 - 8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Metal Detergents</entry><entry align="center">0.1 - 15</entry><entry align="center">0.2 - 9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Corrosion Inhibitor</entry><entry align="center">0 - 5</entry><entry align="center">0 - 1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Metal Dihydrocarbyl Dithiophosphate</entry><entry align="center">0.1 - 6</entry><entry align="center">0.1 - 4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Antioxidant</entry><entry align="center">0 - 5</entry> <entry align="center">0.01 - 2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pour Point Depressant</entry><entry align="center">0.01 - 5</entry><entry align="center">0.01 - 1.5</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">Antifoaming Agent</entry> <entry align="center">0 - 5</entry><entry align="center">0.001 - 0.15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Supplemental Antiwear Agents</entry><entry align="center">0 - 1.0</entry><entry align="center">0 - 0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Friction Modifier</entry><entry align="center">0 - 5</entry><entry align="center">0 - 1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Basestock</entry><entry align="center">Balance</entry><entry align="center">Balance</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0059">This invention will be further understood by reference to the following examples. In
the following Examples, the properties of certain VI improvers are described using certain
terms of art, defined below. All weight percents expressed herein (unless otherwise
indicated) are based on active ingredient (AI) content of the additive, and/or upon the total
weight of any additive-package, or formulation which will be the sum of the AI weight of
each additive plus the weight of total oil and/or diluent.</p><p num="0060">"Shear Stability Index (SSI)" measures the ability of polymers used as V.I. improvers
in crankcase lubricants to maintain thickening power during use. SSI is indicative of the
resistance of a polymer to degradation under service conditions. The higher the SSI, the less
stable is the polymer, i.e., the more susceptible it is to degradation. SSI is defined as the
percentage of polymer-derived viscosity loss and is calculated as follows:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center"><st32:italic>SSI</st32:italic> = 100 × <st32:frac align="centre"><st32:italic>kv<st32:sub pos="post">fresh</st32:sub> - kv<st32:sub pos="post">after</st32:sub></st32:italic><st32:over><st32:italic>kv<st32:sub pos="post">fresh</st32:sub> - kv<st32:sub pos="post">oil</st32:sub></st32:italic></st32:over></st32:frac></st32:df>
wherein kv<sub>fresn</sub> is the kinematic viscosity of the polymer-containing solution before
degradation and kv<sub>after</sub> is the kinematic viscosity of the polymer-containing solution after
degradation. SSI is conventionally determined using ASTM D6278-98 (known as the Kurt-Orban
(KO) or DIN bench test). The polymer under test is dissolved in suitable base oil (for
example, solvent extracted 150 neutral) to a relative viscosity of 2 to 3 µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> (Cst) at 100°C 
and the resulting fluid is pumped through the testing apparatus specified in the ASTM D6278-98
protocol.</p><p num="0061">"Thickening Efficiency (TE)" is representative of a polymers ability to thicken oil per
unit mass and is defined as:
<img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="60" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="16"/>
wherein c is polymer concentration (grams of polymer/100 grams solution), kv<sub>oil+polymer</sub> is
kinematic viscosity of the polymer in the reference oil, and kv<sub>oil</sub> is kinematic viscosity of the
reference oil.</p><p num="0062">"Cold Cranking Simulator (CCS)" is a measure of the cold-cranking characteristics of
crankcase lubricants and is conventionally determined using a technique described in ASTM
D5293-92.</p><p num="0063">"Crystallinity" in ethylene-alpha-olefin polymers can be measured using X-ray
techniques known in the art as well as by the use of a differential scanning calorimetry (DSC)
test. DSC can be used to measure crystallinity as follows: a polymer sample is annealed at
room temperature (e.g., 20-25°C) for at least 24 hours before the measurement. Thereafter,
the sample is first cooled to -100°C from room temperature, and then heated to 150°C at
10°C/min. Crystallinity is calculated as follows:
<img id="img-00160002" orientation="unknown" wi="104" img-format="tif" img-content="mf" file="00160002.tif" inline="no" he="16"/>
wherein ΣΔH (J/g) is the sum of the heat absorbed by the polymer above its glass transition
temperature, x<sub>methylene</sub> is the molar fraction of ethylene in the polymer calculated, e.g., from
proton NMR data, 14 (g/mol) is the molar mass of a methylene unit, and 4110 (J/mol) is the
heat of fusion for a single crystal of polyethylene at equilibrium.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLES</u></heading><p num="0064">Diluent oils used in the following Examples are characterized in Table 2. VI
improvers used in the following Examples are characterized in Table 3, below: <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><u style="single">Diluent Oils and Diluent Oil Blends</u></entry></row><row><entry align="center">Dil. Oil No.</entry><entry align="center">Type</entry><entry align="center">Noack (mass %)</entry><entry align="center">kv<sub>100</sub> (µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup>)</entry><entry align="center">CCS dynamic viscosity @ -35°C mPas (Cps)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 1</entry><entry align="left">Group I</entry><entry align="center">27</entry><entry align="center">4.0</entry><entry align="center">5926</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 2</entry><entry align="left">Group I</entry><entry align="center">19.8</entry><entry align="center">5.2</entry><entry align="center">18468</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 3</entry><entry align="left">Group II</entry><entry align="center">26.2</entry><entry align="center">4.1</entry><entry align="center">5033</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 4</entry><entry align="left">Group II</entry><entry align="center">16.9</entry><entry align="center">4.3</entry><entry align="center">3332</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 5</entry><entry align="left">Group II+</entry><entry align="center">14.7</entry><entry align="center">4.5</entry><entry align="center">5948</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 6</entry><entry align="left">Group III</entry><entry align="center">15.4</entry><entry align="center">4.2</entry><entry align="center">2841</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 7</entry><entry align="left">Group II+ blend</entry><entry align="center">26.2</entry><entry align="center">4.0</entry><entry align="center">3317</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 8</entry><entry align="left">Group III/Group II+ blend</entry><entry align="center">24.5</entry><entry align="center">3.8</entry><entry align="center">2136</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 9</entry><entry align="left">Group II+ blend</entry><entry align="center">22.4</entry><entry align="center">3.6</entry><entry align="center">1038</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 10</entry><entry align="left">Group II+/Group I blend</entry><entry align="center">27.6</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry><entry align="center">1486</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 11</entry><entry align="left">Group I</entry><entry align="center">92.8</entry><entry align="center">3.1</entry><entry align="center">1840</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oil 12</entry><entry align="left">Group I/Group III blend</entry><entry align="center">20.8</entry><entry align="center">3.5</entry><entry align="center">1854</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1"><u style="single">VI Improvers</u></entry></row><row><entry align="left">VI Improver No.</entry><entry align="left">Type</entry><entry align="left">Ethylene Content*</entry><entry align="center">M<sub>n</sub></entry><entry align="center">M<sub>n</sub>/M<sub>w</sub></entry><entry align="center">SSI</entry></row><row><entry align="left">VII 1</entry><entry align="left">Amorphous OCP</entry><entry align="left">49.4 mass %</entry><entry align="center">55,000</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">VII 2</entry><entry align="left">Amorphous OCP</entry><entry align="left">49.4 mass %</entry><entry align="center">97,500</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">50</entry></row><row><entry nameend="6" align="left" namest="1">*mass % of polymer derived from ethylene monomer, based on total mass of polymer</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0065">Concentrates containing 9 mass % of polymer were prepared from the above diluent
oils and VI improver polymers, and used in combination with a common DI package to
formulate lubricants of varying grades using the indicated base stock oils. The formulated
lubricants were of the type suitable for use as either a passenger car motor oil (PCMO) or
heavy duty diesel (HDD) crankcase lubricant and had a Noack volatility below 15 mass %.
The CCS properties of the fully formulated lubricants were determined and the results
provided. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="left">VII No.</entry><entry align="left">Dil. Oil No.</entry><entry align="left">5W30 PCMO Group II+ Basestock CCS dynamic viscosity @ -30°C mPas (cP)</entry><entry align="left">10W40 PCMO Group I/II Basestock Blend CCS dynamic viscosity @ -25°C mPas (cP)</entry><entry align="left">10W30 PCMO Group I Basestock CCS dynamic viscosity @ -25°C mPas (cP)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">5685</entry><entry align="center">7129</entry><entry align="center">6564</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="center">5699</entry><entry align="center">6872</entry><entry align="center">----</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="center">5514</entry><entry align="center">6578</entry><entry align="center">----</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="center">----</entry><entry align="center">----</entry><entry align="center">6179</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0066">As shown, for each of the noted grades, the formulated lubricant prepared using the
concentrate containing a diluent oil of the invention (Oil. Nos. 7 and 8) provided improved
CCS performance using an amorphous OCP VI improver.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0067">Concentrates containing 9 mass % of VII polymer 1 were prepared from the above
diluent oils and used, in combination with a common DI package and a base stock blend of
Group I and Group II base stock oil, to formulate 10W30 grade HDD crankcase lubricants.
The CCS, Noack volatility and kinematic viscosities of the fully formulated lubricants were
determined and the results provided.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Dil. Oil No.</entry><entry align="center">CCS dynamic viscosity @ -25°C mPas (cP)</entry><entry align="center">Predicted Noack (mass %)</entry><entry align="center">kv<sub>100</sub> µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup></entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">6292</entry><entry align="center">15.9</entry><entry align="center">10.72</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">6033</entry><entry align="center">15.5</entry><entry align="center">10.78</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0068">In the noted formulations, the concentrate containing the claimed diluent oil (Oil 6)
provided improved CCS with an amorphous OCP VI improver, with comparable Noack
volatility and kinematic viscosity characteristics.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><p num="0069">Concentrates containing 9 mass % of VII polymer 1 were prepared using the above
diluent oils and used, in combination with a common DI package and a Group II+ base stock
oil, to formulate 5W30 grade PCMO crankcase lubricants. The amount of VI improver
concentrate was adjusted such that the formulated lubricants all had a Noack volatility no 
greater than 15 mass %. The CCS, and kinematic viscosities of the fully formulated
lubricants were determined and the results provided.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Dil. Oil No.</entry><entry align="center">CCS dynamic viscosity @ -25°C mPas (cP)</entry><entry align="center">Predicted Noack (mass %)</entry><entry align="center">kv<sub>100</sub> µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup></entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">6193</entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry><entry align="center">10.63</entry></row><row><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">6032</entry><entry align="center">14.8</entry><entry align="center">10.47</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">5826</entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry><entry align="center">10.61</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">5931</entry><entry align="center">14.5</entry><entry align="center">10.67</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0070">In the noted formulations, the concentrate containing the claimed diluent oils (Oils 6
and 7) provided improved CCS with an amorphous OCP VI improver, at comparable Noack
volatility and with similar kinematic viscosity characteristics.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 4</u></heading><p num="0071">Concentrates containing 9 mass % of VII polymer 1 were prepared from the above
diluent oils and used in combination with a DI package and a Group I base stock oil, to
formulate 10W30 grade PCMO crankcase lubricants. The CCS, and kinematic viscosities of
the fully formulated lubricants were determined and the results provided.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Dil. Oil No.</entry><entry align="center">CCS dynamic viscosity @ -25°C mPas (cP)</entry><entry align="center">Predicted Noack (mass %)</entry><entry align="center">kv<sub>100</sub> µm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup></entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">6554</entry><entry align="center">15.5</entry><entry align="center">10.53</entry></row><row><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="left">6268</entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry><entry align="center">10.50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="left">6198</entry><entry align="center">21.5</entry><entry align="center">10.32</entry></row><row><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="left">6179</entry><entry align="center">15.5</entry><entry align="center">10.43</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0072">In the noted formulations, the concentrate containing the claimed diluent oils (Oils 6,
8 and 11) provided improved CCS with an amorphous OCP VI improver and similar
kinematic viscosity characteristics. However, as the results further show, when using a
diluent oil having a Noack viscosity above 40 mass % (Dil. Oil 11), it may not be possible to
blend a formulated oil within the desired grade having an acceptable Noack volatility. </p><p num="0073">The disclosures of all patents, articles and other materials described herein are hereby
incorporated, in their entirety, into this specification by reference. A description of a
composition comprising, consisting of, or consisting essentially of multiple specified
components, as presented herein and in the appended claims, should be construed to also
encompass compositions made by admixing said multiple specified components. The
principles, preferred embodiments and modes of operation of the present invention have been
described in the foregoing specification. What applicants submit is their invention, however,
is not to be construed as limited to the particular embodiments disclosed, since the disclosed
embodiments are regarded as illustrative rather than limiting.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A viscosity index improver concentrate comprising at least one viscosity index
improver, from 0 to 5 mass % of lubricating oil flow improver and diluent oil, wherein the
diluent oil has a kinematic viscosity at 100°C of at least 3.0 µm2s-1 (cSt) and dynamic
viscosity at -35°C, as measured using a cold cranking simulator, of less than 3700 mPas (cPs),
and wherein at least 98 mass % of said concentrate consists essentially of said viscosity index
improver, said lubricating oil flow improver and said diluent oil.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A concentrate according to claim 1, wherein said diluent oil has a Noack volatility of
less than 40 mass %, preferably less than 35 mass % and especially less than 32 mass %.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A concentrate according to claim 1 or 2, wherein the concentrate has kinematic
viscosity at 100°C a of from 300 to 2500 µm2s-1 (cSt).</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A concentrate according to claim 1, 2 or 3, wherein the viscosity index improver is a
copolymer of ethylene and another α-olefin (OCP).</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A concentrate according to claim 4, wherein the viscosity index improver is an
amorphous OCP having an ethylene content of less than 60 mass %, based on the total mass
of OCP.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A concentrate according to any one of claims 1, 2 or 3, wherein the viscosity index
improver is selected from the group consisting of homopolymers and copolymers of diolefins
containing from 4 to 12 carbon atoms, copolymers of one or more conjugated diolefins
containing from 4 to 12 carbon atoms and one or more monoalkenyl aromatic hydrocarbons
containing from 8 to 16 carbon atoms, and hydrogenated, functionalized and hydrogenated
and functionalized derivatives thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A concentrate according to claim 6, wherein the viscosity index improver is selected
from the group consisting of linear random polymers, linear tapered polymers, linear block
copolymers, random star polymers, tapered star polymers and block star polymers.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A concentrate according to any one of the preceding claims, wherein the diluent oil is
a Group II, Group III or Group IV oil, a mixture thereof, or a mixture of a Group I oil and at
least one Group II, Group III or Group IV oil.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A concentrate according to any one of the preceding claims, containing from 4 to 50
mass % of viscosity index improver.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A concentrate according to any one of the preceding claims, wherein the diluent oil
has a dynamic viscosity at -35°C, as measured using a cold cranking simulator, of less than
3300 mPas (cPs), preferably less than 3000 mPas (cPs) and especially less than 2500 mPas
(cPs).</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A concentrate according to any one of the preceding claims, wherein the diluent oil
has a sulfur content of less than 1 mass %, preferably from 0 to 0.3 mass %.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A concentrate of according to any one of the preceding claims, wherein the diluent oil
has a saturate content of greater than 90%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A concentrate according to any one of the preceding claims, wherein the diluent oil
has a viscosity index of at least 85.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A concentrate according to any one of the preceding claims, wherein said viscosity
index improver is a multifunctional viscosity index improver.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A fully formulated lubricant comprising a major amount of an oil of lubricating
viscosity and a viscosity index improver provided by a viscosity index improver concentrate
according to any one of the preceding claims.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A method of lubricating an engine using a lubricant according to claim 15.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>