<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1219687-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1219687" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="24986192" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020703"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1219687-A1" status="new" fvid="23497167"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1219687</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020703</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01125300-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01125300</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011025</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-74278000-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>74278000</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001220</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01F  17/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01F  17/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  13/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  13/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  67/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  67/46        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01F  17/00M</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01F  17/00Z</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  13/00B8</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09B  67/00P10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C2B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Dispersionen und deren Verwendung für Tintenstrahl-Tintenzusammensetzungen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Dispersions for use in ink jet inks</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Dispersions utilisables dans les encres destinées à l'impression par jet d'encre</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-19801759-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>19801759</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="DE-19807485-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>19807485</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1113052-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1113052</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-2356634-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2356634</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3844994-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3844994</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4689078-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4689078</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5725647-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5725647</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6077339-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6077339</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BASF CORP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BASF CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Basf Corporation</last-name><address><street/><city>Mount Olive, NJ 07828-1234</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CAMPBELL DOUGLAS R</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CAMPBELL, DOUGLAS R.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CAMPBELL, DOUGLAS R.</last-name><address><street>78 Oriole Avenue</street><city>West Sandlake, NY 12196</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Abel, Manfred</last-name><address><street>BASF Aktiengesellschaft Patentabteilung ZDX - C6</street><city>67056 Ludwigshafen</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country> <country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country> <country>GR</country> <country>IE</country> <country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An aqueous ink offering good waterfastness, rub resistance, and
stability suitable for use in ink jet printers, as writing inks,
and in other printing inks includes a colorless aromatic sulfonic
acid compound, at least one pigment, and a water-soluble polyol
or polyether, particularly polyethylene glycol. Pigments are easily
dispersed in the ink compositions of the invention and the
ink compositions have excellent dispersion stability and bleed
resistance.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to aqueous inks, particularly ink
jet inks and inks for writing instruments, having colorant
dispersions with good color development and stability, and to
methods of preparing such inks.</p><heading>Background of the Invention</heading><p num="0002">The ink jet process involves directing droplets of an ink in a
specific manner from one or more small nozzles onto a substrate,
for example onto paper, wood, textiles, plastic or metal. Electronic
control combines the individual droplets into script characters
or graphic patterns. It is important in this process that
the ink contain no particles large enough to block the nozzles
through which it is directed.</p><p num="0003">In the past, aqueous ink jet inks have been colored using dyes
that are dissolved in the ink and so cannot block the nozzles.
For example, Bermes et al., U.S. Patent No. 5,431,723, describes
the preparation of liquid diazo dye preparations and their use in
the water-based ink for the inkjet process. It has been found,
however, that the inks described in U.S. Patent No. 5,431,723
have substantial disadvantages, in particular poor water resistance
and poor lightfastness.</p><p num="0004">Hoffmann et al., U.S. Patent No. 5,891,227, provides aqueous dye
preparations for preparing inks for the inkjet process, writing
inks, or printing colors that have improved water resistance and
lightfastness compared to the inks of the U.S. Patent No.
5,431,723. The dye preparations described in U.S. Patent No.
5,891,227 include aqueous dye preparations comprising, based on
the weight of the preparation, from 0.1 to 15% by weight of a
dye, with 90 to 100% of the dye being of the formula
<img id="img-00010001" orientation="unknown" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00010001.tif" inline="no" he="44"/> 
with the cation being a metal or ammonium ion; from 1 to 40% by
weight of carbon black; and from 0.1 to 15% by weight of a polyethylene
glycol. Particularly good results are obtained when the
weight ratio of the carbon black to the dye in at least 6:1.
While these inks provide good waterfastness, lightfastness, and
rubfastness, the range of color that can be achieved is limited
because of the high content of black dye and carbon black pigment.</p><p num="0005">It would be desirable to be able to formulate ink jet inks of any
color that would not clog the ink jet nozzles and yet provide the
good waterfastness, lightfastness, and rub resistance available
with the inks formulated according to the Hoffman patent.</p><heading>Summary of the Invention</heading><p num="0006">The invention provides an aqueous ink offering good waterfastness,
rub resistance, and stability. The ink is suitable for use
in ink jet printers, as writing inks, in other printing inks.
The ink includes a colorless aromatic sulfonic acid compound, at
least one pigment, and a water-soluble polyol or polyether, particularly
polyethylene glycol.</p><p num="0007">The ink compositions of the invention have excellent dispersion
stability and bleed resistance. The inks of the invention are
useful as aqueous coating or printing inks, in particular as inks
for the inkjet process or writing inks.</p><heading>Detailed Description of the Invention</heading><p num="0008">The ink may be prepared by first preparing an aqueous ink base
and then diluting the aqueous ink base with water or with mixtures
of water and water-miscible organic solvents to obtain an
ink of the desired strength or viscosity.</p><p num="0009">The ink base includes from about 0.1 to about 15% by weight of at
least one colorless aromatic sulfonic acid compound. The term
"colorless" is understood to mean that the compound does not have
significant absorption in the visible light band (400 nm to 700
nm). In particular, it is desirable that the absorption in the
visible light band be no more than about 1%.</p><p num="0010">Examples of suitable aromatic sulfonic acid compounds include,
without limitation, β-naphthol, gamma acid (7-amino-1-hydroxynaphthalene-3-sulfonic
acid), H-acid (8-amino-1-hydroxynaphthalene-3,6-disulfonic
acid), I-acid, J-acid (2-amino-5-naphthol-7-sulfonic
acid), di-J acid (bis-(5,5'-diydroxy-2,2'-naphthyl)amine-7,7'-disulfonic 
acid), 2-hydroxy-3-methylbenzoic
acid, Tobias acid (2-naphthylamine-1-sulfonic acid), and so on.</p><p num="0011">Also suitable are aromatic compounds having one or more amine
groups and one or more sulfonic acid groups. The aromatic amino
sulfonic acid compounds may have one aromatic ring or multiple
aromatic rings. When the aromatic amino sulfonic acid compound
has multiple aromatic rings, the aromatic rings can be fused or
bridged. Examples of bridged aromatic rings include, without limitation,
those bridged by an alkylene group (e.g., methylene or
isopropylene) or by an amine group. In addition to the amine and
sulfonic acid groups, the aromatic amino sulfonic acid compound
can have other substituents, including, without limitation, alkyl
groups and hydroxyl groups. Examples of suitable aromatic amino
sulfonic acids include, without limitation, diamino stilbene disulfonic
acids, including 4,4'-diaminostilbene-2,2'- disulfonic
acid compounds; sulfanilic acid; amino benzene sulfonic acids,
such as 1-amino-2-methyl-4-benzenesulfonic acid; amino-azobenzene
sulfonic acids, such as 4-amino-azobenzene-4'-sulfonic acid; and
so on.</p><p num="0012">The ink composition further includes one or more pigments. For
pigments used in ink jet ink, the pigment particle size should be
from about 10 nanometers to about 500 nanometers. The aromatic
sulfonic acid compound forms a stable dispersion of the pigments
and avoids pigment agglomeration that would lead to clogged
nozzles or a decrease in color strength. The aromatic sulfonic
acid compound improves the ease with which the pigment is dispersed.</p><p num="0013">Examples of suitable classes of organic pigments include, without
limitation, metallized and non-metallized azo pigments, azome-thine
pigments, methine pigments, anthraquinone pigments,
phthalocyanine pigments, perinone pigments, perylene pigments,
diketopyrrolopyrrole pigments, thioindigo pigments, iminoisoindoline
pigments, iminoisoindolinone pigments, quinacridone pigments
such as quinacridone reds and violets, flavanthrone pigments,
indanthrone pigments, anthrapyrimidine pigments, carbazole pigments,
monoarylide and diarylide yellows and oranges, benzimidazolone
yellows, tolyl orange, naphthol orange, quinophthalone
pigments, lithol rubines and so on. Specific examples of useful
color pigments include, without limitation, quinacridone pigments,
such as C.I. Pigment Red 202, C.I. Pigment Violet 19, and
C.I. Pigment Red 122; perylene pigments, such as C.I. Pigment Red
179; azo pigments, such as C.I. Pigment Red 170, C.I. Pigment Red
144, and C.I. Pigment Brown 23; isoindolinone pigments, such as
C.I. Pigment Orange 61, C.I. Pigment Yellow 109, and C.I. Pigment 
Yellow 110; diketopyrrolopyrrole pigments, such as C.I. Pigment
Red 254, C.I. Pigment Red 255, C.I. Pigment Red 264, C.I. Pigment
Orange 71, and C.I. Pigment Orange 73; copper phthalocyanine pigments
such as C.I. Pigment Blue 15; and anthraquinone pigments,
such as C.I. Pigment Blue 60, C.I. Pigment Red 177, C.I. Pigment
Yellow 138, and C.I. Pigment Yellow 147.</p><p num="0014">Examples of suitable inorganic pigments include, without limitation,
titanium dioxide, carbon black, iron oxides including red
iron oxide, black iron oxide, and brown iron oxide, chromium oxide
green, ferric ferrocyanide (Prussian blue), ultramarine, lead
chromate, and so on.</p><p num="0015">The ink base may include from about 1 to about 80% by weight of
one or more pigments. The amount of pigment used depends upon the
nature of the pigments. Carbon black and certain organic pigments
typically are used in the ink base in amounts of up to about 60%
by weight, based on the weight of the ink base, while other pigments
typically may be used in amounts of up to 40% by weight of
the pigment base.</p><p num="0016">The ink base may optionally further include one or more dyes.
Preferably, however, no dye is included because of poor water resistance.
If included, there may be from about 1 to about 5% dye
by weight, based on the weight of the pigment of the ink base.
Examples of suitable dyes include, without limitation, C.I. Acid
Yellow 23 (19 140), C.I. Acid Blue 9 (42 090), C.I. Direct Red
254, C.I. Direct Blue 86 (74 180), C.I. Reactive Red 24, C.I.
Reactive Blue 49, C.I. Reactive Red 72 or the dye-acid of the
reaction product of tetrazotized flavonic acid with 1-amino-8-hydroxynaphthalene-3,6-disulfonic
acid or 2-hydroxy-3-methylbenzoic
acid in each case in a molar ratio of 1:2. The dye preparations
of this invention should be essentially free from foreign salts.
This means for the purposes of the present invention that they
may additionally include minor amounts, for example from 0 to 10%
by weight, preferably from 0 to 5% by weight, in particular approaching
0% by weight, based on the weight of the preparation,
of foreign salts.</p><p num="0017">The ink base also includes at least one water soluble compound
selected from polyols and polyether compounds, especially polyethylene
glycol compounds. Polyether compounds for the purposes
of this invention are understood to include ethoxylated and/or
propoxylated ethylenediamine. Other examples of useful water
soluble compounds include water soluble diols and triols such as
ethylene glycol and its oligomers such as diethylene glycol and
triethylene glycol, propylene glycol and dipropylene glycol, 
glycerine, polyethylene glycol-polypropylene glycol block
copolymers, the reaction products of ethylene oxide and primary
amines, and the reaction products of bisphenol A with primary
amines. The preferred polyethylene glycol has a weight average
molecular weight of preferably at least about 300, more preferably
at least about 1000, and particularly preferably at least
about 2000. Additionally, the polyethylene glycol has a weight
average molecular weight of preferably up to about 9000, more
preferably up to about 6000, and particularly preferably up to
about 4000. The polyethylene glycol preferably has a weight average
molecular weight of from about 300 to about 9000, more preferably
from about 1000 to about 6000, and still more preferably
from about 2000 to about 4000.</p><p num="0018">The ink base preferably includes at least about 0.1% by weight,
more preferably at least about 0.8% by weight of at least one
water soluble polyol or polyether compound, particularly preferably
of a polyethylene glycol compound. Additionally, the ink
preferably includes up to about 15% by weight, more preferably up
to about 6% by weight, still more preferably up to about 5% by
weight of the at least one water-soluble polyol or polyether
compound, particularly polyethylene glycol compound. The ink base
includes from about 0.1 to about 15% by weight, preferably from
about 0.1 to about 6% by weight, in particular from about 0.8 to
about 5% by weight, based on the weight of the ink base, of the
at least one water-soluble polyether or polyol compound, especially
of a polyethylene glycol compound.</p><p num="0019">The ink base may further include a polypropylene glycol compound.
The polypropylene glycol preferably has a weight average molecular
weight of from about 400 to about 1000, more preferably from
about 500 to about 700. When the ink bases of this invention include
propylene glycol, the propylene glycol content will generally
be within the range from about 0.1 to about 15% by weight,
preferably within the range from about 0.1 to about 6% by weight,
based on the weight of the ink base.</p><p num="0020">The balance to 100% by weight of the ink base is generally water.</p><p num="0021">The preferred weight ratio of the pigment to the aromatic
sulfonic acid compound in the ink base and ink or coating composition
depends upon the particular pigment or pigments and the
sulfonic acid compound used. Important factors may include the
surface area of the pigment, the surface chemistry of the pigment,
the number of sulfonic acid groups of the aromatic sulfonic
acid compound, and the molecular weight of the sulfonic acid
compound. In one preferred embodiment 20 parts by weight of the 
aromatic sulfonic acid compound is used to 80 parts by weight of
pigment. More typically, the weight ratio of the from aromatic
sulfonic acid compound to the pigment will be from about 2:98 to
about 8:92.</p><p num="0022">The inks of the invention are useful as aqueous coating or printing
inks, in particular as inks for the inkjet process or writing
inks. Such inks are obtained by diluting the aqueous ink bases
of this invention with water or with mixtures of water and water-miscible
organic solvents. Examples of suitable water-miscible
organic solvents are C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>4</sub> alkanols, such as methanol, ethanol,
propanol, isopropanol, butanol, isobutanol, sec-butanol or tert-butanol;
carboxamides, such as N,N-dimethylformamide or N,N-dimethylacetamide;
lactams, such as ε-caprolactam; 2-pyrrolidinone or
N-methyl-2-pyrollidinone; urea, cyclic ureas, such as
1,3-dimethyl-2-imidazolidinone or 1,3-dimethyl-2-hexahydropyrimidone;
ketones or ketoalcohols, such as acetone, methyl ethyl
ketone or 2-methyl-2-hydroxy-4-pentanone; ethers, such as tetrahydrofuran
or dioxane; mono-, oligo- or polyalkylene glycols or
thioglycols containing C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> -alkylene units, such as ethylene
glycol, 1,2- or 1,3-propylene glycol, 1,2- or 1,4-butylene
glycol, 1,6-hexanediol, diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol,
dipropylene glycol, thiodiglycol, polyethylene glycol or polypropylene
glycol; other polyols, such as glycerol or 1,2,6-hexanetriol;
C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> -alkyl ethers of polyhydric alcohols, such as
ethylene glycol monomethyl or monoethyl ether, diethylene glycol
monomethyl or monoethyl ether or triethylene glycol monomethyl or
monoethyl ether; .γ-butyrolactone, or dimethyl sulfoxide. Examples
of preferred water-miscible organic solvents are
2-pyrrolidinone, N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinone, mono-, di- or trialkylene
glycols containing C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>6</sub> -alkylene units, especially mono-,
di- or triethylene glycol or dipropylene glycol, or dimethyl
sulfoxide. Very particular emphasis is given to N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinone,
diethylene glycol or dimethyl sulfoxide.</p><p num="0023">An aqueous coating or printing ink may obtained by diluting the
ink base with a C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>4</sub> alkanol, with or without further addition
of water, and optionally with addition of further binders.</p><p num="0024">The inks or coating or printing colors of this invention in general
include from about 2 to about 50% by weight, preferably from
about 15 to about 30% by weight, based on the weight of the ink
or color, of an ink base of this invention.</p><p num="0025">The inks or coating or printing colors of this invention may in
general further include from about 75 to about 98% by weight,
preferably from about 80 to about 95% by weight, in particular 
from about 86 to about 93% by weight, based on the weight of the
ink or color, of water.</p><p num="0026">The inks of this invention in general include up to about 30% by
weight, preferably up to about 5 to about 15% by weight, based on
the weight of the ink, of one or more water-miscible organic solvents.</p><p num="0027">The coating or printing colors of this invention in general includes
from about 1 to about 70% by weight, preferably from about
10 to about 30% by weight, based on the weight of the coating or
printing color, of C<sub>1</sub> -C<sub>4</sub> -alkanol.</p><p num="0028">Further possible constituents of the inks or coating or printing
colors of this invention are, for example and without limitation,
anionic, cationic or nonionic surfactants, biocide such as fungicides
and bactericides, corrosion inhibitors, humectants, perfume
oils, and combinations of these. The proportion of these components
is generally up to about 10% by weight, preferably up to
about 5% by weight, based on the weight of the ink or coating.
The inks or coatings of this invention are notable for high water
resistance and lightfastness in use. The ink bases of this invention
are likewise useful in marker fluids in writing implements,
in aqueous liquid toners or in coating compositions, for example
wood stain, ink ribbon colors, stamp-pad inks or ball pen pastes.
They are also useful for pulp-coloring paper.</p><p num="0029">The invention is further described in the following examples.
The examples are merely illustrative and do not in any way limit
the scope of the invention as described and claimed. All parts
are by weight unless otherwise indicated.</p><heading>Example 1.</heading><p num="0030">A mixture of 40 parts by weight of carbon black pigment, 18 parts
by weight of J-Acid (10% solution, pH adjusted to 7.0 with triethanolamine),
137 parts by weight of water, 4 parts by weight of
PLURACOL® E4000 (available from BASF Corporation), 1 part by
weight of a biocide (about 95% by weight active), a couple drops
of defoamer, and 400 parts by weight of 1.0mm glass beads was allowed
to grind for 24 hours. The resulting material was filtered
through a 30 micron-pore filter paper and then through a 20-25
micron pore filter paper. 10 parts by weight of the filtered material
was combined with 4 parts by weight of N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinone
and 26 parts by weight of water to make an ink jet 
ink. The ink jet ink was filter through a 1 micron filter and
printed on an ink jet printer. The print quality was good.</p><p num="0031">The ink was tested for bleeding in water, rub resistance, and resistance
to highlight marker. For the bleed test, a test pattern
of four one-inch squares surrounded by an unprinted area was
printed on a sheet. The test pattern was dried under ambient conditions
for one hour, then cut from the sheet. The optical
density of the printed squares was measured. The test pattern was
then immersed in water for five minutes, removed from the water,
and air dried. The optical density was measured again. The difference
between the initial density and the density after the
water soak was less than 5%, indicating that the print did not
bleed.</p><p num="0032">The same test pattern was printed and tested on a Sutherland Rub
Tester for 10 cycles. The degree of color transfer and smudging
was then visually evaluated. The printed test pattern had excellent
rub resistance.</p><p num="0033">Finally, the ink was tested for resistance to marker ink. An alphanumeric
character set on one line was printed and air dried
for one hour. A commercially-available yellow highlighter marker
was wiped over the text and the text was evaluated for smearing.
The printed text did not smear.</p><heading>Example 2.</heading><p num="0034">A mixture of 20 parts by weight of carbon black pigment, 9 parts
by weight of Gamma-Acid (10% solution, pH adjusted to 7.0 with
triethanolamine), 68.5 parts by weight of water, 2 parts by
weight of PLURACOL® E4000 (available from BASF Corporation), 0.5
part by weight of a biocide (about 95% by weight active), one
drop of defoamer, and 400 parts by weight of 1.0mm glass beads
was allowed to grind for 24 hours. The resulting material was
filtered through a 30 micron-pore filter paper and then through a
20-25 micron pore filter paper. 25 parts by weight of the filtered
material was combined with 10 parts by weight of N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinone
and 65 parts by weight of water to make an
ink jet ink. The ink jet ink was filter through a 1 micron filter
and printed on an ink jet printer. The print quality was good.
The print did not bleed when tested using the bleed test described
in Example 1. </p><p num="0035">The invention has been described in detail with reference to preferred
embodiments thereof. It should be understood, however,
that variations and modifications can be made within the spirit
and scope of the invention.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An aqueous ink composition, comprising a colorless aromatic
sulfonic acid compound, a pigment, and a water-soluble
compound selected from the group consisting of polyols, polyethers,
and combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 1, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>from about 0.1 to about 15 parts by weight of the colorless
aromatic sulfonic acid compound,</claim-text><claim-text>from about 1 to about 80 parts by weight of the pigment, and</claim-text><claim-text>at least about 0.1 part by weight of the water soluble
compound.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 1, wherein the aromatic
sulfonic acid is selected from the group consisting of
β-naphthol, gamma acid, H-acid, I-acid, J-acid, di-J acid,
2-hydroxy-3-methylbenzoic acid, Tobias acid, diamino stilbene
disulfonic acids, sulfanilic acid, amino benzene sulfonic
acids, amino-azobenzene sulfonic acids, and combinations
thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 1, wherein the pigment
has a particle size from about 10 nanometers to about 500
nanometers.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 1, wherein the water-soluble
compound comprises a polyether compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 1, wherein the water-soluble
compound comprises a polyethylene glycol compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 6, wherein the polyethylene
glycol compound has a weight average molecular
weight of at least about 300.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 6, wherein the polyethylene
glycol compound has a weight average molecular
weight of up to about 9000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 6, wherein the polyethylene
glycol compound has a weight average molecular
weight from about 2000 to about 4000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 1, comprising:<claim-text><claim-text>from about 0.1 to about 15 parts by weight of the colorless
aromatic sulfonic acid compound,</claim-text><claim-text>from about 1 to about 60 parts by weight of the pigment, and</claim-text><claim-text>from about 0.8 to about 5 parts by weight of the water soluble
compound.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 1, wherein the weight
ratio of the pigment to the colorless aromatic sulfonic acid
compound is from about 98:2 to about 80:20.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 1, wherein the weight
ratio of the pigment to the colorless aromatic sulfonic acid
compound is from about 98:2 to about 92:8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 1, wherein the ink composition
is an ink jet ink.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>An ink composition according to claim 1, wherein the ink
composition is a writing ink.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>An aqueous ink jet ink, comprising from about 2 to about 50%
by weight of an ink base, wherein the ink base comprises
from about 0.1 to about 15 parts by weight of a colorless
aromatic sulfonic acid compound,
from about 1 to about 80 parts by weight of a pigment having
a particle size from about 10 nanometers to about 500 nanometers,
and
at least about 0.1 part by weight of a water soluble compound
selected from the group consisting of polyols, polyethers,
and combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>An aqueous ink jet ink according to claim 15, comprising from
about 15% to about 30% by weight of the ink base.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>An aqueous ink jet ink according to claim 15, wherein the
water-soluble compound comprises a polyethylene glycol
compound having a weight average molecular weight of from
about 300 to about 9000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>An aqueous ink jet ink according to claim 17, wherein the
polyethylene glycol compound has a weight average molecular
weight of from about 2000 to about 4000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>An aqueous ink jet ink according to claim 15, wherein the ink
base comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>from about 0.1 to about 15 parts by weight of the colorless
aromatic sulfonic acid compound,</claim-text><claim-text>from about 1 to about 60 parts by weight of the pigment, and</claim-text><claim-text>from about 0.8 to about 5 parts by weight of the water soluble
compound.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>An aqueous ink jet ink according to claim 15, wherein the
weight ratio of the pigment to the colorless aromatic
sulfonic acid compound is from about 98:2 to about 92:8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>A method of preparing an ink, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) preparing an ink base comprising
from about 0.1 to about 15 parts by weight of a colorless
aromatic sulfonic acid compound,
from about 1 to about 80 parts by weight of a pigment
having a particle size from about 10 nanometers to about
500 nanometers, and
at least about 0.1 part by weight of a water-soluble
compound selected from the group consisting of polyols,
polyethers, and combinations thereof; and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) combining the ink base with at least one member selected
from the group consisting of water and water-miscible
organic solvents to form an ink, wherein to ink base is
from about 2 to about 50% by weight of ink.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>A method of improving the waterfastness of an ink jet ink,
comprising steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>dispersing a pigment in water in the presence of a colorless
aromatic sulfonic acid compound and a water-soluble compound
selected from the group consisting of polyols, polyethers,
and combinations thereof;</claim-text><claim-text>preparing an ink using the dispersed pigment.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>A method according to claim 22, wherein the water-soluble
compound comprises a polyethylene glycol compound having a
weight average molecular weight of from about 300 to about
9000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>A method according to claim 22, wherein the weight ratio of
the pigment to the colorless aromatic sulfonic acid compound
is from about 98:2 to about 92:8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="25"><claim-text>A method of improving the dispersion stability of a pigment
in an aqueous ink, comprising steps of:<claim-text><claim-text>dispersing the pigment in water in the presence of a colorless
aromatic sulfonic acid compound and a water-soluble
compound selected from the group consisting of polyols, polyethers,
and combinations thereof.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="26"><claim-text>A method according to claim 25, wherein the water-soluble
compound comprises a polyethylene glycol compound having a
weight average molecular weight of from about 300 to about
9000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="27"><claim-text>A method according to claim 25, wherein the weight ratio of
the pigment to the colorless aromatic sulfonic acid compound
is from about 98:2 to about 92:8.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>