<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1561802-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1561802" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34673731" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050810"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1561802-A1" status="new" fvid="24403196"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1561802</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050810</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04250559-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04250559</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040203</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-04250559-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04250559</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040203</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/12        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/22        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/37        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/37        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  17/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  17/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/12G2D1</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/22E10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/37B12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/37B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/37C8</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Eine Zusammensetzung zur Verwendung beim Waschen oder bei der Wäschebehandlung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">A composition for use in the laundering or treatment of fabrics</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Une composition destinée au lavage ou au traitement du linge</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0381487-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0381487</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0483411-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0483411</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-9087699-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>9087699</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-20030139309-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20030139309</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 1997, no. 07, 31 July 1997 (1997-07-31) -&amp; JP 09 087699 A (LION CORP), 31 March 1997 (1997-03-31) &amp; DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199723 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A97, AN 1997-255893 &amp; JP 09 087699 A (LION CORP), 31 March 1997 (1997-03-31)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PROCTER &amp; GAMBLE</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>THE PROCTER &amp; GAMBLE COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>THE PROCTER &amp;amp; GAMBLE COMPANY</last-name><address><street>One Procter &amp;amp; Gamble Plaza</street><city>Cincinnati, Ohio 45202</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BLYTH KEVIN GRAHAM</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GRAYDON ANDREW RUSSELL</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MARTIN JULIAN DAVID</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>STEPHENSON COLIN</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BLYTH, KEVIN GRAHAM</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GRAYDON, ANDREW RUSSELL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MARTIN, JULIAN DAVID</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>STEPHENSON, COLIN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BLYTH, KEVIN GRAHAM</last-name><address><street>16 Garsdale Road</street><city>Whitley Bay Tyne &amp;amp; Wear NE26 4NU</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GRAYDON, ANDREW RUSSELL</last-name><address><street>27 Denewell Avenue</street><city>Low Fell Gateshead NE9 5HD</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MARTIN, JULIAN DAVID</last-name><address><street>16 Sandringham Avenue</street><city>Benton Newcastle upon Tyne NE12 8JX</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>STEPHENSON, COLIN</last-name><address><street>76 Simonside Terrace</street><city>Heaton Newcastle upon Tyne NE65 5JY</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Brooks, Maxim Courtney</last-name><address><street>Procter &amp;amp; Gamble Technical Centres Limited, Whitley Road, Longbenton</street><city>Newcastle upon Tyne NE12 9TS</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention relates to an auxiliary composition in particulate form for
the laundering or treatment of fabrics, the auxiliary composition comprises a co-particulate
admix of: (i) clay; and (ii) silicone; and (iii) optionally, a charged
polymeric fabric-softening boosting component; and (iv) optionally one or more
adjunct components; wherein the auxiliary composition has a Flowability Index (FI)
of from 0.5 to 21, wherein FI = P x R, wherein P = the weight average primary
particle size of the clay expressed in micrometers, and R = the weight ratio of
silicone to clay.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>Technical Field</b></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a composition for use in the laundering or
treatment of fabrics. More specifically, the present invention relates to a laundry
detergent composition capable of both cleaning and softening fabric during a
laundering process.</p> <heading><b>Background</b></heading><p num="0002">Laundry detergent compositions that both clean and soften fabric during a
laundering process are known and have been developed and sold by laundry
detergent manufacturers for many years. Typically, these laundry detergent
compositions comprise components that are capable of providing a fabric-softening
benefit to the laundered fabric; such fabric-softening components include clays and
silicones.</p><p num="0003">The incorporation of clay into laundry detergent compositions to impart a
fabric-softening benefit to the laundered fabric is described in the following
references. A granular, built laundry detergent composition comprising a smectite
clay that is capable of both cleaning and softening a fabric during a laundering
process is described in US 4,062,647 (Storm, T. D., and Nirschl, J. P.; The Procter &amp;
Gamble Company). A heavy duty fabric-softening detergent comprising bentonite
clay agglomerates is described in GB 2 138 037 (Allen, E., Coutureau, M., and
Dillarstone, A.; Colgate-Palmolive Company). Laundry detergents compositions
containing fabric-softening clays of between 150 and 2,000 microns in size are
described in US 4,885,101 (Tai, H. T.; Lever Brothers Company). The fabric-softening
performance of clay-containing laundry detergent compositions is
improved by the incorporation of a flocculating aid to the clay-containing laundry
detergent composition. For example, a detergent composition comprising a smectite 
type clay and a polymeric clay-flocculating agent is described in EP 0 299 575
(Raemdonck, H., and Busch, A.; The Procter &amp; Gamble Company).</p><p num="0004">The use of silicones to provide a fabric-softening benefit to laundered fabric
during a laundering process is also known. US 4,585,563 (Busch, A., and Kosmas,
S.; The Procter &amp; Gamble Company) describes that specific organo-functional
polydialkylsiloxanes can advantageously be incorporated in granular detergents to
provide remarkable benefits inclusive of through-the-wash softening and further
textile handling improvements. US 5,277,968 (Canivenc, E.; Rhone-Poulenc
Chemie) describes a process for the conditioning of textile substrates to allegedly
impart a pleasant feel and good hydrophobicity thereto, comprising treating such
textile substances with an effective conditioning amount of a specific
polydiorganosiloxane.</p> <p num="0005">Detergent Manufacturers have attempted to incorporate both clay and silicone
in the same laundry detergent composition. For example, siliconates were
incorporated in clay-containing compositions to allegedly improve their dispensing
performance. US 4, 419, 250 (Allen, E., Dillarstone, R., and Reul, J. A.; Colgate-Palmolive
Company) describes agglomerated bentonite particles that comprise a salt
of a lower alkyl siliconic acid and/or a polymerization product(s) thereof. US 4, 421,
657 (Allen, E., Dillarstone, R., and Reul, J. A.; Colgate-Palmolive Company)
describes a particulate heavy-duty laundering and textile-softening composition
comprising bentonite clay and a siliconate. US 4, 482,477 (Allen, E., Dillarstone, R.,
and Reul, J. A.; Colgate-Palmolive Company) describes a particulate built synthetic
organic detergent composition which includes a dispensing assisting proportion of a
siliconate and preferably bentonite as a fabric-softening agent. In another example,
EP 0 163 352 (York, D. W.; The Procter &amp; Gamble Company) describes the
incorporation of silicone into a clay-containing laundry detergent composition in an
attempt to control the excessive suds that are generated by the clay-containing
laundry detergent composition during the laundering process. EP 0 381 487 (Biggin,
I. S., and Cartwright, P. S.; BP Chemicals Limited) describes an aqueous based liquid
detergent formulation comprising clay that is pretreated with a barrier material such
as a polysiloxane. </p> <p num="0006">Detergent manufacturers have also attempted to incorporate a silicone, clay
and a flocculant in a laundry detergent composition. For example, a fabric treatment
composition comprising substituted polysiloxanes, softening clay and a clay
flocculant is described in WO92/07927 (Marteleur, C. A. A. V. J., and Convents, A.
C.; The Procter &amp; Gamble Company).</p> <p num="0007">More recently, fabric care compositions comprising an organophilic clay and
functionalised oil are described in US 6,656, 901 B2 (Moorfield, D., and Whilton,
N.; Unilever Home &amp; Personal Care USA division of Conopco, Inc.). WO02/092748
(Instone, T. et al; Unilever PLC) describes a granular composition comprising an
intimate blend of a non-ionic surfactant and a water-insoluble liquid, which may a
silicone, and a granular carrier material, which may be a clay. WO03/055966
(Cocardo, D. M., et al; Hindustain Lever Limited) describes a fabric care
composition comprising a solid carrier, which may be a clay, and an anti-wrinkle
agent, which may be a silicone.</p><p num="0008">However, despite all of the above attempts, whatever improved fabric-softening
performance benefit detergent manufacturers have been able to achieve for a laundry
detergent has come at the expense of its fabric-cleaning performance and also its
processability. Therefore, there is still a need to improve the fabric-softening
performance of a laundry detergent composition without unduly negatively affecting
its fabric-cleaning performance and processability.</p><heading><b>Summary</b></heading><p num="0009">The present invention overcomes the above mentioned problem by providing
an auxiliary composition in particulate form for the laundering or treatment of
fabrics, the auxiliary composition comprises a co-particulate admix of: (i) clay; and
(ii) silicone; and (iii) optionally, a charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting
component; and (iv) optionally one or more adjunct components; wherein the
auxiliary composition has a Flowability Index (FI) of from 0.5 to 21, wherein FI = P
x R, wherein P = the weight average primary particle size of the clay expressed in
micrometers, and R = the weight ratio of silicone to clay. </p><heading><b>Description</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Clay</u></heading><p num="0010">Typically, the clay is a fabric-softening clay such as a smectite clay. Preferred
smectite clays are beidellite clays, hectorite clays, laponite clays, montmorillonite
clays, nontonite clays, saponite clays and mixtures thereof. Preferably, the smectite
clay is a dioctahedral smectite clay, more preferably a montmorillonite clay.
Dioctrahedral smectite clays typically have one of the following two general
formulae:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/"><i>Formula (I)</i>   Na<sub>x</sub>Al<sub>2-x</sub>Mg<sub>x</sub>Si<sub>4</sub>O<sub>10</sub>(OH)<sub>2</sub></st32:che>
or
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/"><i>Formula (II)</i>   Ca<sub>x</sub>Al<sub>2-x</sub>Mg<sub>x</sub>Si<sub>4</sub>O<sub>10</sub>(OH)<sub>2</sub></st32:che>
   wherein x is a number from 0.1 to 0.5, preferably from 0.2 to 0.4.</p><p num="0011">Preferred clays are low charge montmorillonite clays (also known as a sodium
montmorillonite clay or Wyoming type montmorillonite clay) which have a general
formula corresponding to formula (I) above. Preferred clays are also high charge
montmorillonite clays (also known as a calcium montmorillonite clay or Cheto type
montmorillonite clay) which have a general formula corresponding to formula (II)
above. Preferred clays are supplied under the tradenames: Fulasoft 1 by Arcillas
Activadas Andinas; White Bentonite STP by Fordamin; and Detercal P7 by Laviosa
Chemica Mineraria SPA.</p><p num="0012">The clay may be a hectorite clay. Typical hectorite clay has the general
formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/"><i>Formula (III)</i>   [(Mg<sub>3-x</sub>Li<sub>x</sub>)Si<sub>4-y</sub>Me<sup>III</sup> <sub>y</sub>O<sub>10</sub>(OH<sub>2-z</sub>F<sub>z</sub>)]<sup>-(x+y)</sup>((x+y)/n)M<sup>n+</sup></st32:che> 
   wherein y = 0 to 0.4, if y = &gt;0 then Me<sup>III</sup> is Al, Fe or B, preferably y = 0; M<sup>n+</sup> is
a monovalent (n = 1) or a divalent (n = 2) metal ion, preferably selected from Na, K,
Mg, Ca and Sr. x is a number from 0.1 to 0.5, preferably from 0.2 to 0.4, more
preferably from 0.25 to 0.35. z is a number from 0 to 2. The value of (x + y) is the
layer charge of the clay, preferably the value of (x + y) is in the range of from 0.1 to
0.5, preferably from 0.2 to 0.4, more preferably from 0.25 to 0.35. A preferred
hectorite clay is that supplied by Rheox under the tradename Bentone HC. Other
preferred hectorite clays for use herein are those hectorite clays supplied by CSM
Materials under the tradename Hectorite U and Hectorite R, respectively.</p><p num="0013">The clay may also be selected from the group consisting of: allophane clays;
chlorite clays, preferred chlorite clays are amesite clays, baileychlore clays,
chamosite clays, clinochlore clays, cookeite clays, corundophite clays, daphnite clays,
delessite clays, gonyerite clays, nimite clays, odinite clays, orthochamosite clays,
pannantite clays, penninite clays, rhipidolite clays, sudoite clays and thuringite clays;
illite clays; inter-stratified clays; iron oxyhydroxide clays, preferred iron oxyhydoxide
clays are hematite clays, goethite clays, lepidocrite clays and ferrihydrite clays; kaolin
clays, preferred kaolin clays are kaolinite clays, halloysite clays, dickite clays, nacrite
clays and hisingerite clays; smectite clays; vermiculite clays; and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0014">The clay may also be a light coloured crystalline clay mineral, preferably
having a reflectance of at least 60, more preferably at least 70, or at least 80 at a
wavelength of 460nm. Preferred light coloured crystalline clay minerals are china
clays, halloysite clays, dioctahedral clays such as kaolinite, trioctahedral clays such as
antigorite and amesite, smectite and hormite clays such as bentonite
(montmorillonite), beidilite, nontronite, hectorite, attapulgite, pimelite, mica,
muscovite and vermiculite clays, as well as pyrophyllite/talc, willemseite and
minnesotaite clays. Preferred light coloured crystalline clay minerals are described in
GB2357523A and WO01/44425.</p><p num="0015">Preferred clays have a cationic exchange capacity of at least 70meq/100g. The
cationic exchange capacity of clays can be measured using the method described in
Grimshaw, The Chemistry and Physics of Clays, Interscience Publishers, Inc., pp.
264-265 (1971). </p><p num="0016">Preferably, the clay has a weight average primary particle size, typically of
greater than 20 micrometers, preferably more than 23 micrometers, preferably more
than 25 micrometers, or preferably from 21 micrometers to 60 micrometers, more
preferably from 22 micrometers to 50 micrometers, more preferably from 23
micrometers to 40 micrometers, more preferably from 24 micrometers to 30
micrometers, more preferably from 25 micrometers to 28 micrometers. Clays having
these preferred weight average primary particle sizes provide a further improved
fabric-softening benefit. The method for determining the weight average particle size
of the clay is described in more detail hereinafter.</p><heading><i>Method For Determining The Weight Average Primary Particle Size Of The Clay:</i></heading><p num="0017">The weight average primary particle size of the clay is typically determined
using the following method: 12g clay is placed in a glass beaker containing 250ml
distilled water and vigorously stirred for 5 minutes to form a clay solution. The clay
is not sonicated, or microfluidised in a high pressure microfluidizer processor, but is
added to said beaker of water in an unprocessed form (i.e. in its raw form). 1ml clay
solution is added to the reservoir volume of an Accusizer 780 single-particle optical
sizer (SPOS) using a micropipette. The clay solution that is added to the reservoir
volume of said Accusizer 780 SPOS is diluted in more distilled water to form a
diluted clay solution; this dilution occurs in the reservoir volume of said Accusizer
780 SPOS and is an automated process that is controlled by said Accusizer 780
SPOS, which determines the optimum concentration of said diluted clay solution for
determining the weight average particle size of the clay particles in the diluted clay
solution. The diluted clay solution is left in the reservoir volume of said Accusizer
780 SPOS for 3 minutes. The clay solution is vigorously stirred for the whole period
of time that it is in the reservoir volume of said Accusizer 780 SPOS. The diluted
clay solution is then sucked through the sensors of said Accusizer 780 SPOS; this is
an automated process that is controlled by said Accusizer 780 SPOS, which
determines the optimum flow rate of the diluted clay solution through the sensors for
determining the weight average particle size of the clay particles in the diluted clay 
solution. All of the steps of this method are carried out at a temperature of 20°C. This
method is carried out in triplicate and the mean of these results determined.</p><heading><u style="single">Silicone</u></heading><p num="0018">The silicone is preferably a fabric-softening silicone. The silicone typically has
the general formula:
<img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="85" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="28"/>
   wherein, each R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> in each repeating unit, -(Si(R<sub>1</sub>)(R<sub>2</sub>)O)-, are
independently selected from branched or unbranched, substituted or unsubstituted
C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>10</sub> alkyl or alkenyl, substituted or unsubstituted phenyl, or units of -[-R<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>Si-O-]-;
x is a number from 50 to 300,000, preferably from 100 to 100,000, more
preferably from 200 to 50,000; wherein, the substituted alkyl, alkenyl or phenyl are
typically substituted with halogen, amino, hydroxyl groups, quaternary ammonium
groups, polyalkoxy groups, carboxyl groups, or nitro groups; and wherein the
polymer is terminated by a hydroxyl group, hydrogen or -SiR<sub>3</sub>, wherein, R<sub>3</sub> is
hydroxyl, hydrogen, methyl or a functional group.</p><p num="0019">Suitable silicones include: amino-silicones, such as those described in
EP150872, WO92/01773 and US4800026; quaternary-silicones, such as those
described in US4448810 and EP459821; high-viscosity silicones, such as those
described in WO00/71806 and WO00/71807; modified polydimethylsiloxane;
functionalized polydimethyl siloxane such as those described in US5668102.
Preferably, the silicone is a polydimethylsiloxane.</p><p num="0020">The silicone may preferably be a silicone mixture of two or more different
types of silicone. Preferred silicone mixtures are those comprising: a high-viscosity
silicone and a low viscosity silicone; a functionalised silicone and a non-functionalised
silicone; or a non-charged silicone polymer and a cationic silicone
polymer. </p><p num="0021">The silicone typically has a viscosity, of from 5,000cp to 5,000,000cp, or from
greater than 10,000cp to 1,000,000cp, or from 10,000cp to 600,000cp, more
preferably from 50,000cp to 400,000cp, and more preferably from 80,000cp to
200,000cp when measured at a shear rate of 20s<sup>-1</sup> and at ambient conditions (20°C
and 1 atmosphere). The silicone is typically in a liquid or liquefiable form, especially
when admixed with the clay. Typically, the silicone is a polymeric silicone
comprising more than 3, preferably more than 5 or even more than 10 siloxane
monomer units.</p><p num="0022">The silicone is in the form of an emulsion, especially when admixed with the
clay. The emulsion is preferably in the form of a water-in-oil emulsion with the
silicone forming at least part, and preferably all, of the continuous phase, and the
water forming at least part, and preferably all, of the discontinuous phase. The
emulsion typically has a volume average primary droplet size of from 0.1
micrometers to 5,000 micrometers, preferably from 0.1 micrometers to 50
micrometers, and most preferably from 0.1 micrometers to 5 micrometers. The
volume average primary particle size is typically measured using a Coulter
Multisizer™ or by the method described in more detail below.</p><p num="0023">Commercially available silicone oils that are suitable for use are DC200™
(12,500cp to 600,000cp), supplied by Dow Coming, or silicones of the Baysilone
Fluid M series supplied by GE Silicone. Alternatively, preformed silicone emulsions
are also suitable for use. These emulsions may comprise water and/or other solvents
in an effective amount to aid the emulsification of the silicone.</p><heading><i>Method For Determining The Volume Average Droplet Size Of The Silicone:</i></heading><p num="0024">The volume average droplet size of the emulsion is typically determined by the
following method: An emulsion is applied to a microscope slide with the cover slip
being gently applied. The emulsion is observed at 400X and 1,000X magnification
under the microscope and the average droplet size of the emulsion is calculated by
comparison with a standard stage micrometer. </p><heading><u style="single">Charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component</u></heading><p num="0025">The charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component is preferably
cationic. Preferably, the charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component is a
cationic guar gum.</p><p num="0026">The charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component may be a cationic
polymer that comprises (i) acrylamide monomer units, (ii) other cationic monomer
units and (iii) optionally, other monomer units. The charged polymeric fabric-softening
boosting component may be a cationically-modified polyacrylamide or copolymer
thereof; any cationic modification can be used for these polyacrylamides.
Highly preferred charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting components are copolymers
of acrylamide and a methyl chloride quaternary salt of dimethylaminoethyl
acrylate (DMA3-MeCl), for example such as those supplied by BASF,
Ludwigshafen, Germany, under the tradename Sedipur CL343.</p><p num="0027">The general structure for DMA3MeCl is:
<img id="img-00090001" orientation="unknown" wi="102" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00090001.tif" inline="no" he="25"/></p><p num="0028">The general structure of acrylamide is:
<img id="img-00090002" orientation="unknown" wi="73" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00090002.tif" inline="no" he="21"/></p><p num="0029">Preferred cationic polymers have the following general structure:
<img id="img-00090003" orientation="unknown" wi="111" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00090003.tif" inline="no" he="23"/> 
   wherein n and m independently are numbers in the range of from 100 to
100,000, preferably from 800 to 3400. The molar ratio of n:m is preferably in the
range of from 4:1 to 3:7, preferably from 3:2 to 2:3.</p><p num="0030">Suitable charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting components are described
in more detail in, and can be synthesized according to the methods described in,
DE10027634, DE10027636, DE10027638, US6111056, US6147183, WO98/17762,
WO98/21301, WO01/05872 and, WO01/05874.</p><p num="0031">The charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component preferably has an
average degree of cationic substitution of from 1% to 70%, preferably from above
10% to 70%, more preferably from 10% to 60%. If the charged polymeric fabric-softening
boosting component is a cationic guar gum, then preferably its degree of
cationic substitution is from 10% to 15%. However, if the charged polymeric fabric-softening
boosting component is a polymer having a general structure according to
formula VII above, then preferably its degree of cationic substitution is from 40% to
60%. The average degree of cationic substitution typically means the molar
percentage of monomers in the cationic polymer that are cationically substituted. The
average degree of cationic substitution can be determined by any known methods,
such as colloid titration. One such colloid titration method is described in more detail
by Horn, D., in Prog. Colloid &amp;Polymer Sci., 1978, 8, p243-265.</p><p num="0032">The charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component preferably has a
charge density of from 0.2meq/g to 1.5meq/g. The charge density is typically defined
in terms of the number of charges carried by the polymer, expressed in
milliequivalents/gram. One equivalent is the weight of the material required to give
one mole of charge; one milliequivalent is a thousandth of this.</p><p num="0033">Preferably, the charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component has a
weight average molecular weight of from above 100,000 Da to below 10,000,000 Da,
preferably from 500,000 Da to 2,000,000 Da, and preferably from 1,000,000 Da to
2,000,000. Any known gel permeation chromatography (GPC) measurement methods
for determining the weight average molecular weight of a polymer can be used to
measure the weight average molecular weight of the charged polymeric fabric-softening 
boosting component. GPC measurements are described in more detail in
Polymer Analysis by Stuart, B. H., p108-112, published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd,
UK, © 2002. A typical GPC method for determining the weight average molecular
weight of the charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component is described
below:</p><heading><i>Method For Determining The Weight Average Molecular Weight of the Charged
Polymeric Fabric-Softening Boosting Component:</i></heading><p num="0034"><sl><li>1. Dissolve 1.5g of polymer in 1 litre of deionised water.</li><li>2. Filter the mixture obtained in step 1, using a Sartorius Minisart RC25 filter.</li><li>3. According the manufacturer's instructions, inject 100 litres of the mixture
obtained in step 2., on a GPC machine that is fitted with a Suprema MAX
(8mm by 30cm) column operating at 35°C and a ERC7510 detector, with 0.2M
aqueous solution of acetic acid and potassium chloride solution being used as
an elution solvent at a flux of 0.8 ml/min.</li><li>4. The weight average molecular weight is obtained by analysing the data from
the GPC according to the manufacturer's instructions.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Flocculating aid</u></heading><p num="0035">The flocculating aid is capable of flocculating clay. Typically, the flocculating
aid is polymeric. Preferably the flocculating aid is a polymer comprising monomer
units selected from the group consisting of ethylene oxide, acrylamide, acrylic acid
and mixtures thereof. Preferably the flocculating aid is a polyethyleneoxide.
Typically the flocculating aid has a molecular weight of at least 100,000 Da,
preferably from 150,000 Da to 5,000,000 Da and most preferably from 200,000 Da to
700,000 Da.</p><heading><u style="single">Adjunct components</u></heading><p num="0036">The auxiliary composition and/or the laundry detergent composition may
optionally comprise one or more adjunct components. These adjunct components are 
typically selected from the group consisting of detersive surfactants, builders,
polymeric co-builders, bleach, chelants, enzymes, anti-redeposition polymers, soil-release
polymers, polymeric soil-dispersing and/or soil-suspending agents, dye-transfer
inhibitors, fabric-integrity agents, brighteners, suds suppressors, fabric-softeners,
flocculants, and combinations thereof.</p><heading><u style="single">Co-particulate admix</u></heading><p num="0037">The co-particulate admix comprises the clay, silicone and optionally a charged
polymeric fabric-softening boosting component. Optionally, the co-particulate admix
comprises one or more adjunct components.</p><p num="0038">The co-particulate admix is preferably obtainable or obtained by a process
comprising the steps of contacting the silicone, preferably in liquid or liquefiable
form and most preferably in an emulsified form, with the clay and optionally the
charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component to form a mixture, and then
agglomerating the mixture in a high-shear mixer and/or a low-shear mixture
optionally followed by a drying step, to form a co-particulate admix. Preferably, the
co-particulate admix is in an agglomerate form, although the co-particulate admix
could be in the form of a granule, flake, extrudate, noodle, needle or an agglomerate.</p><heading><u style="single">Auxiliary composition</u></heading><p num="0039">The auxiliary composition is for use in the laundering or treatment of fabrics
and typically either forms part of a fully formulated laundry detergent composition or
is an additive composition, suitable for addition to a fully formulated laundry
detergent composition. Preferably, the auxiliary composition forms part of a fully
formulated laundry detergent composition.</p><p num="0040">The auxiliary composition comprises an admix of clay and a silicone.
Typically, the auxiliary composition additionally comprises a charged polymeric
fabric-softening boosting component and optionally one or more adjunct
components. Preferably, the charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component
is present in the auxiliary composition in the form of an admix with the clay and the 
silicone; this means that typically, the charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting
component is present in the same particle as the clay and silicone.</p><p num="0041">Preferably, the weight ratio of the silicone to emulsifier, if present, in the
auxiliary composition is from 3:1 to 20:1.</p><p num="0042">The auxiliary composition has a Flowability Index (FI) of from 0.5 to 21,
preferably from greater than 5 to less than 10, or from 6 to 9 or even from 7 to 8, or
from greater than 10 to less than 20, or 11 to 19, or from 11 to 16, or even from 11 to
12. Auxiliary composition having a preferred Flowability Index provides a good
fabric-softening benefit whilst also good processability and capable of being easily
processed; for example by having good powder properties such as flowability and
cake strength. The Flowability Index (FI) = P x R, wherein P = the weight average
primary particle size of the clay expressed in micrometers, and R = the weight ratio
of silicone to clay. Preferably, the weight ratio of silicone to clay present in the
auxiliary composition is from 0.05 to 0.3, preferably from 0.1 to 0.2.</p><p num="0043">The auxiliary composition has good flowability properties, typically having a
Silo Peschel Flowability Grade of greater than 3, preferably greater than 5 and most
preferably greater than 7. The auxiliary composition preferably has a Bag Peschel
Flowability Grade of greater than 5, preferably greater than 7. The methods for
determining the Silo Peschel Flowability Grade and the Bag Silo Peschel Flowability
Grade are described below:</p><heading><i>Method for determining the Silo Peschelflowability grade of the auxiliary
composition.</i></heading><p num="0044">A 50g sample of the auxiliary composition is poured into a shear cell and
levelled. The shear cell is then covered and the auxiliary composition undergoes a
pre-consolidation step prior to the test by placing a 7,500g weight onto the powder.</p><p num="0045">The shear cell is then placed onto a Peschel RO 200 Automatic Rotational
Shear Tester, where it undergoes the consolidation step under a load of 250g/cm<sup>2</sup> to
orientate the particles in the sample to a constant resistance to horizontal movement
(shear). </p><p num="0046">Once the machine senses this constant resistance, a load of 250g/cm<sup>2</sup> is
applied and the force require to restart horizontal motion is measured.</p><p num="0047">This last step is repeated with 4 further different loads of 200g/cm<sup>2</sup>,
150g/cm<sup>2</sup>, 100g/cm<sup>2</sup> and 50g/cm<sup>2</sup>. The relative flowability is calculated from the
absolute flowability / bulk specific gravity of the product.</p><p num="0048">The flowability values are derived from a plot of the shear pressure vs vertical
load which is used to determine a yield locus from which Mohr's circles are drawn.
From these, the relative flowability is calculated. The Silo Peschel flowability grade
is the relative flowability.</p><heading><i>Method for determining the Bag Peschel flowability grade of the auxiliary
composition.</i></heading><p num="0049">A 50g sample of the auxiliary composition is poured into a shear cell and
levelled. The shear cell is then covered and the auxiliary composition undergoes a
pre-consolidation step prior to the test by placing a 1,500g weight onto the powder.</p><p num="0050">The shear cell is then placed onto a Peschel RO 200 Automatic Rotational
Shear Tester, where it undergoes the consolidation step under a load of 50g/cm<sup>2</sup> to
orientate the particles in the sample to a constant resistance to horizontal movement
(shear).</p><p num="0051">Once the machine senses this constant resistance, a load of 50g/cm<sup>2</sup> is applied
and the force require to restart horizontal motion is measured.</p><p num="0052">This last step is repeated with 4 further different loads of 40g/cm<sup>2</sup>, 30g/cm<sup>2</sup>,
20g/cm<sup>2</sup> and 10g/cm<sup>2</sup>. The relative flowability is calculated from the absolute
flowability / bulk specific gravity of the product.</p><p num="0053">The flowability values are derived from a plot of the shear pressure vs vertical
load which is used to determine a yield locus from which Mohr's circles are drawn.
From these, the relative flowability is calculated. The Bag Peschel flowability grade
is the relative flowability.</p><p num="0054">The auxiliary composition is preferably is in an agglomerate form or in an
extrudate form, preferably in an agglomerate form. Preferably, the auxiliary 
composition is in an agglomerate form, preferably having a weight average particle
size of from 400 micrometers to 800 micrometers, and preferably wherein no more
than 20wt% of the agglomerates have a particle size of less than 125 micrometers,
and preferably wherein no more than 20wt% of the agglomerates have a particle size
of 1180 micrometers or greater.</p><p num="0055">The auxiliary composition is typically in particulate form and suitable for
laundering or treating fabrics, and typically comprises a co-particulate admix of (i)
clay; and (ii) silicone; and (iii) optionally a charged polymeric fabric-softening
boosting component; and (iv) optionally one or more adjunct components; wherein
the clay has a weight average primary particle size of from 10 micrometers to 60
micrometers, preferably from 10 micrometers to 40 micrometers, or even from 20
micrometers to 30 micrometers, and wherein the ratio of clay to silicone is from 0.05
to 0.3, preferably from 0.1 to 0.2.</p><heading><u style="single">Laundry detergent composition</u></heading><p num="0056">The laundry detergent composition comprises the auxiliary composition, a
detersive surfactant, optionally a flocculating aid, optionally a builder and optionally
a bleach. The laundry detergent composition optionally comprises one or more other
adjunct components.</p><p num="0057">The laundry detergent composition is preferably in particulate form, preferably
free-flowing particulate form, although the composition may be in any liquid or solid
form. The composition in solid form can be in the form of an agglomerate, granule,
flake, extrudate, bar, tablet or any combination thereof. The solid composition can be
made by methods such as dry-mixing, agglomerating, compaction, spray drying, pan-granulation,
spheronization or any combination thereof. The solid composition
preferably has a bulk density of from 300g/l to 1,500g/l, preferably from 500g/l to
1,000g/l.</p><p num="0058">The composition may also be in the form of a liquid, gel, paste, dispersion,
preferably a colloidal dispersion or any combination thereof. Liquid compositions
typically have a viscosity of from 500cp to 3,000cp, when measured at a shear rate of
20s<sup>-1</sup> at ambient conditions (20°C and 1 atmosphere), and typically have a density of 
from 800g/l to 1300g/l. If tthe composition is in the form of a dispersion, then it will
typically have a volume average particle size of from 1 micrometer to 5,000
micrometers, preferably from 1 micrometer to 50 micrometers. The particles that
form the dispersion are usually the clay and, if present, the silicone. Typically, a
Coulter Multisizer is used to measure the volume average particle size of a
dispersion.</p><p num="0059">The composition may in unit dose form, including not only tablets, but also
unit dose pouches wherein the composition is at least partially enclosed, preferably
completely enclosed, by a film such as a polyvinyl alcohol film.</p><p num="0060">The composition is capable of both cleaning and softening fabric during a
laundering process. Typically, the composition is formulated for use in an automatic
washing machine, although it can also be formulated for hand-washing use.</p><p num="0061">The following adjunct components and levels thereof, when incorporated into a
laundry detergent composition of the present invention, further improve the fabric-softening
performance and fabric-cleaning performance of the laundry detergmt
composition: at least 10% by weight of the composition of alkyl benzene sulphonate
detersive surfactant; at least 0.5%, or at least 1%, or even at least 2% by weight of the
composition of cationic quaternary ammonium detersive surfactant; at least 1% by
weight of the composition alkoxylated alkyl sulphate detersive surfactant, preferably
ethoxylated alkyl sulphate detersive surfactant; less than 12% or even less than 6%,
or even 0%, by weight of the composition zeolite builder; and any combination
thereof. Preferably the laundry detergent composition comprises at least 6%, or even
at least 8%, or even at least 12%, or even at least 18%, by weight of the laundry
detergent composition of the auxiliary composition. Preferably the composition
comprises at least 0.3% by weight of the composition of a flocculating aid. The
weight ratio of clay to flocculating aid in the laundry detergent composition is
preferably in the range of from 10:1 to 200:1, preferably from 14:1 to 160:1 more
preferably from 20:1 to 100:1 and more preferably from 50:1 to 80:1. </p><heading><u style="single">Process</u></heading><p num="0062">The process for making the auxiliary composition comprises the steps of (i)
contacting a silicone with water, and optionally an emulsifier, to form a silicone in an
emulsified form; and (ii) thereafter contacting the silicone in an emulsified form with
clay to form an admix of clay and a silicone.</p><p num="0063">Preferably the silicone is in a liquid or liquefiable form when it is contacted to
the clay in step (ii). Preferably the emulsion formed in step (i) is a water-in-oil
emulsion with the silicone forming at least part of, and preferably all of, the
continuous phase of the emulsion, and the water forms at least part of, and preferably
all of, the discontinous phase of the emulsion.</p><p num="0064">Preferably the clay is subjected to a milling step prior to step (ii), preferably the
clay is milled such that the clay has a primary particle size of from 10 micrometers to
40 micrometers, preferably from 20 micrometers to 30 micrometers.</p><p num="0065">Preferably, a charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component is
contacted to the clay and silicone in step (ii). The intimate mixing of the charged
polymeric fabric-softening boosting component with the clay and silicone further
improves the fabric-softening benefit performance of the resultant auxiliary
composition.</p><p num="0066">Step (i) may be carried out at ambient temperature (e.g. 20°C), but it may be
preferred that step (i) is carried out at elevated temperature such as a temperature in
the range of from 30°C to 60°C. If an emulsifier is used in the process, then
preferably the emulsifier is contacted to water to form an emulsifier-water mixture,
thereafter the emulsifier-water mixture is contacted to the silicone. For continuous
processes, step (i) is typically carried out in an in-line static mixer or an in-line
dynamic (shear) mixer. For non-continuous processes, step (i) is typically carried out
in a batch mixer such as a Z-blade mixer, anchor mixer or a paddle mixer.</p><p num="0067">The admix of clay and silicone is preferably subsequently agglomerated in a
high-sheer mixer. Suitable high-sheer mixers include CB Loedige mixers, Schugi
mixers, Littleford or Drais mixers and lab scale mixers such as Braun mixers.
Preferably the high-sheer mixer is a pin mixer such as a CB Loedige mixer or
Littleford or Drais. The high-sheer mixers are typically operated at high speed, 
preferably having a tip speed of from 30ms<sup>-1</sup> to 35ms<sup>-1</sup>. Preferably water is added to
the high-sheer mixer.</p><p num="0068">The admix of clay and silicone are typically subsequently subjected to a
conditioning step in a low-shear mixer. Suitable low-shear mixers include
Ploughshear mixers such as a Loedige KM. Preferably the low-shear mixer has a tip
speed of from 5ms<sup>-1</sup> to 10ms<sup>-1</sup>. Optionally, fine particles such as zeolite and/or clay
particles, typically having an average particle size of from 1 micrometer to 40
micrometers or even from 1 micrometer to 10 micrometers are introduced into the
low-shear mixer. This dusting step improves the flowability of the resultant particles
by reducing their stickiness and controlling their growth.</p><p num="0069">The admix of clay and silicone is typically subjected to a sizing step, wherein
particles having a particle size of greater than 500mm are removed from the admix.
Typically these large particles are removed from the admix by sieving.</p><p num="0070">The admix of clay and silicone is preferably subjected to hot air having a
temperature of greater than 50°C or even greater than 100°C. Typically, the admix of
clay and silicone is dried at an elevated temperature (e.g. a temperature of greater
than 50°C or even greater than 100°C), preferably the admix is dried in a low-shear
apparatus such as fluid bed drier. Following this preferred drying step, the admix of
clay and silicone is preferably thereafter subjected to cold air having a temperature of
less than 15°C, preferably from 1°C to 10°C. This cooling step is preferably carried
out in a fluid bed cooler.</p><p num="0071">The admix of clay and silicone is preferably subjected to a second sizing step,
wherein particles having a particle size of less than 250 micrometers are removed
from the admix. These small particles are removed from the admix by sieving and/or
elutriation. If elutriation is used, then preferably the second sizing step is carried out
in a fluid bed such as the fluid bed dryer and/or cooler, if used in the process.</p><p num="0072">The admix of clay and silicone is preferably subjected to a third sizing step,
wherein particles having a particle size of greater than 1,400 micrometers are
removed from the admix. These large particles are removed from the admix by
sieving. </p><p num="0073">The large particles that are optionally removed from the admix during the first
and/or third sizing steps are typically recycled back to the high sheer mixer and/or to
the fluid bed dryer or cooler, if used in the process. Optionally, these large particles
are subj ected to a grinding step prior to their introduction to the high sheer mixer
and/or fluid bed dryer or cooler. The small particles that are optionally removed from
the admix during the second sizing step are typically recycled back to the high sheer
mixer and/or low shear mixer, if used in the process.</p><heading><b>Examples</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Example 1: A process for preparing a silicone emulsion</u></heading><p num="0074">81.9g of silicone (polydimethylsiloxane) having a viscosity of 100,000cp is
added to a beaker. 8.2g of 30w/w% aqueous C<sub>11</sub>-C<sub>13</sub> alkyl benzenesulphonate (LAS)
solution is then added the beaker and the silicone, LAS and water are mixed
thoroughly by hand using a flat knife for 2 minutes to form an emulsion.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2: A process for making a clay/silicone agglomerate</u></heading><p num="0075">601.2g of bentonite clay is added to a grinder and ground until the weight
average primary particle size of the clay is 22 micrometers. The clay is added to a
Braun mixer and 7.7g of cationic guar gum is also added to the Braun mixer. 90.1g of
the emulsion of example 1 is added to the Braun mixer, and all of the ingredients in
the mixer are mixed for 10 seconds at 1,100rpm (speed setting 8). The speed of the
Braun mixer is then increased to 2,000rpm (speed setting 14) and 50g water is added
slowly to the Braun mixer. The mixer is kept at 2,000rpm for 30 seconds so that wet
agglomerates are formed. The wet agglomerates are transferred to a fluid bed dried
and dried for 4 minutes at 137°C to form dry agglomerates. The dry agglomerates are
sieved to removed agglomerates having a particle size greater than 1,400
micrometers and agglomerates having a particle size of less than 250 micrometers. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 3: A clay/silicone agglomerate</u></heading><p num="0076">A clay/silicone agglomerate suitable for use in the present invention is prepared
according to the method of example 2, but the clay is ground so that it has a weight
average primary particle size of 25 micrometers, and the agglomerate comprises:
80.3wt% bentonite clay, 1.0wt% cationic guar gum, 10.9wt% silicone
(polydimethylsiloxane), 0.3wt% C<sub>11</sub>-C<sub>13</sub> alkyl benzenesulphonate (LAS) and 7.5wt%
water.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 4: A clay/silicone agglomerate</u></heading><p num="0077">A clay/silicone agglomerate suitable for use in the present invention is prepared
according to the method of example 2, but the clay is ground so that it has a weight
average primary particle size of 30 micrometers and the agglomerate comprises:
72.8wt% bentonite clay, 0.7wt% cationic guar gum, 15.9wt% silicone
(polydimethylsiloxane), 0.5wt% C<sub>11</sub>-C<sub>13</sub> alkyl benzenesulphonate (LAS) and
10.1wt% water.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 5: A laundry detergent composition</u></heading><p num="0078">A laundry detergent composition suitable for use in the present invention
comprises: 15wt% clay/silicone agglomerates of either example 3 or example 4
above; 0.2wt% polyethylene oxide having a weight average molecular weight of
300,000Da; 11wt% C11-13 linear alkylbenzenesulphonate detersive surfactant;
0.3wt% C12-14 alkyl sulphate detersive surfactant; 1wt% C<sub>12</sub>-C<sub>14</sub> alkyl, di-methyl,
ethoxy quaternary ammonium detersive surfactant; 4wt% crystalline layered sodium
silicate; 12wt% zeolite A; 2.5wt% citric acid; 20wt% sodium carbonate; 0.1wt%
sodium silicate; 0.8wt% hydrophobically modified cellulose; 0.2wt% protease;
0.1wt% amylase; 1.5wt% tetraacetlyethylenediamine; 6.5wt% percarbonate;
0.1wt% ethylenediamine-N'N-disuccinic acid, (S,S) isomer in the form of a sodium
salt; 1.2wt% 1,1-hydroxyethane diphosphonic acid; 0.1wt% magnesium sulphate;
0.7wt% perfume; 18wt% sulphate; 4.7wt% miscellaneous/water. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 6: A laundry detergent composition</u></heading><p num="0079">A laundry detergent composition suitable for use in the present invention
comprises: 12.5wt% clay/silicone agglomerates of either example 3 or example 4
above; 0.3wt% polyethylene oxide having a weight average molecular weight of
300,000Da; 11wt% C<sub>11-13</sub> linear alkylbenzenesulphonate detersive surfactant; 2.5wt%
C<sub>12</sub>-C<sub>14</sub> alkyl, di-methyl, ethoxy quaternary ammonium detersive surfactant; 4wt%
crystalline layered sodium silicate; 12wt% zeolite A; 20wt% sodium carbonate;
1.5wt% tetraacetlyethylenediamine; 6.5wt% percarbonate; 1.0wt% perfume; 18wt%
sulphate; 10.7wt% miscellaneous/water.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 7: A laundry detergent composition</u></heading><p num="0080">A laundry detergent composition suitable for use in the present invention
comprises: 12.5wt% clay/silicone agglomerates of either example 3 or example 4
above; 6.0wt% clay; 0.3wt% polyethylene oxide having a weight average molecular
weight of 300,000Da; 10wt% C<sub>11-13</sub> linear alkylbenzenesulphonate detersive
surfactant; 1wt% alkyl sulphate detersive surfactant condensed with an average of 7
moles of ethylene oxide; 4wt% crystalline layered sodium silicate; 18wt% zeolite A;
20wt% sodium carbonate; 1.5wt% tetraacetlyethylenediamine; 6.5wt% percarbonate;
1.0wt% perfume; 15wt% sulphate; 4.2wt% miscellaneous/water.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition in particulate form for the laundering or treatment of
fabrics, the auxiliary composition comprises a co-particulate admix of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) clay; and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) silicone; and</claim-text><claim-text>(iii) optionally, a charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component; and</claim-text><claim-text>(iv) optionally, one or more adjunct components;</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein the auxiliary composition has a Flowability Index (FI) of from 0.5 to 21,
wherein
FI = P x R
wherein, P = the weight average primary particle size of the clay expressed in
micrometers, and R = the weight ratio of silicone to clay.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to claim 1, wherein the silicone is a polymeric
silicone having a viscosity of from 10,000cp to 600,000cp at a shear rate of 20s-1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the silicone is
a polydimethylsiloxane.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the clay is a
fabric-softening clay.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the clay is a
montmorillonite clay.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the auxiliary
composition has a FI of from 6 to 9.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the auxiliary
composition has a FI of from 11 to 19.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the weight
average primary particle size of the clay is from 20 micrometers to 30 micrometers.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the weight
ratio of silicone to clay is from 0.05 to 0.3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the weight
ratio of the hydrophobic component to clay is from 0.1 to 0.2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the auxiliary
composition has a Silo Peschel flowability grade of greater than 3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the auxiliary
composition has a Bag Peschel flowability grade of greater than 5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the auxiliary
composition is in agglomerate form; optionally having a weight average particle size
of from 400 micrometers to 800 micrometers, and optionally wherein no more than
20% of the agglomerates have a particle size of less than 125 micrometers, and
optionally wherein no more than 20% of the agglomerates have a particle size of
1180 micrometers or greater.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim, wherein the auxiliary
composition comprises a charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to claim 15, wherein the charged polymeric
fabric-softening boosting component has a charge density of from 0.2meq/g to
1.5meq/g.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to claims 14-15, wherein the charged
polymeric fabric-softening boosting component has a weight average molecular
weight of from 1,000,000 Da. to 2,000,000 Da.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to claims 14-16, wherein the charged
polymeric fabric-softening boosting component is cationic.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition according to claims 14-17, wherein the charged
polymeric fabric-softening boosting component is a cationic guar gum.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A laundry detergent composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) an auxiliary composition according to any preceding claim; and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) a surfactant; and</claim-text><claim-text>(iii) optionally a flocculating aid; and</claim-text><claim-text>(iii) optionally a builder; and</claim-text><claim-text>(iv) optionally a bleach; and</claim-text><claim-text>(v) optionally one or more adjunct laundry detergent component.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 19, wherein the composition comprises a
flocculating aid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>A composition according to claims 19-20, wherein the flocculating aid is a
polyethylene oxide, optionally having a weight average molecular weight of from
200,000Da to 700,000Da.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>A composition according claims 19-21, wherein the composition is in free-flowing
particulate form.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>An auxiliary composition in particulate form for the laundering or treatment of
fabrics, the composition comprises a co-particulate admix of:<claim-text><claim-text>(i) clay; and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) silicone; and</claim-text><claim-text>(iii) optionally, a charged polymeric fabric-softening boosting component; and</claim-text><claim-text>(iv) optionally, one or more adjunct components;</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein the clay has a weight average primary particle size of from 10 micrometers
to 40 micrometers, and wherein the weight ratio of the silicone to clay is from 0.05 to
0.3.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>