<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-0987274-A1" country="EP" doc-number="0987274" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="8232644" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000322"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-0987274-A1" status="new" fvid="22805106"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0987274</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000322</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-98117506-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>98117506</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19980915</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-98117506-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>98117506</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19980915</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  38/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  38/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  38/06        20060101ALI20040220BMRU        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  38/06        20060101CLI20040220BMRU        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  38/07        20060101ALI20040220BMRU        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  38/07        20060101CLI20040220BMRU        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P   7/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P   7/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P   7/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P   9/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P   9/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P   9/10        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  29/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  29/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  43/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61P  43/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K   1/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K   1/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K   1/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K   5/00        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K   5/068       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K   5/072       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K   5/09        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K   5/11        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07K   5/08B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07K   5/10B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61K38:00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Faktor VIIa Inhibitore</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Factor VIIa Inhibitors</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Inhibiteurs du facteur VIIa</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-5663297-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5663297</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1989009612-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1989009612</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1990003390-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1990003390</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1991007432-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1991007432</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1995000541-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1995000541</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1995029189-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1995029189</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1996040779-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1996040779</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HOECHST MARION ROUSSEL DE GMBH</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AVENTIS PHARMA DEUTSCHLAND GMBH</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hoechst Marion Roussel Deutschland GmbH</last-name><address><street>Brüningstrasse 50</street><city>65929 Frankfurt am Main</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SAFAR PAVEL</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SAFAROVA ALENA</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WILDGOOSE PETER</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SAFAR, PAVEL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SAFAROVA, ALENA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WILDGOOSE, PETER</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SAFAR, PAVEL</last-name><address><street>12431 N. Forest Lake Way</street><city>Tucson AZ 85737</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SAFAROVA, ALENA</last-name><address><street>12431 N. Forest Lake Way</street><city>Tucson AZ 85737</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WILDGOOSE, PETER</last-name><address><street>Hintergasse 18</street><city>61440 Oberursel</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention relates to novel compounds, their preparation, their use and
pharmaceutical compositions containing the compounds which have a strong
antithrombotic effect through reversible inhibition of activated blood coagulation
factor VIIa (FVIIa).</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new"  lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">Field of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to novel compounds, their preparation, their use and
pharmaceutical compositions containing the compounds which have a strong
antithrombotic effect through reversible inhibition of activated blood coagulation
factor VIIa (FVIIa).</p><heading><u style="single">Background of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0002">Thrombus formation is normally the result of tissue injury which initiate the
coagulation cascade and has the effect of slowing or preventing blood flow in wound
healing. Other factors which are not directly related to tissue injury like
atherosclerosis and inflammation may also initiate the coagulation cascade and may
lead to pathological consequences.</p><p num="0003">Blood coagulation is a complex process involving a progressively amplified series of
enzyme activation reactions in which plasma zymogens are sequentially activated by
limited proteolysis. Mechanistically the blood coagulation cascade has been divided
into intrinsic and extrinsic pathways, which converge at the activation of factor X;
subsequent generation of the thrombin proceeds through a single common pathway
(see Scheme 1). <img id="img-00020001"  orientation="unknown"  wi="139" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00020001.tif" inline="no" he="112"/></p><p num="0004">Present evidence suggests that the intrinsic pathway plays an important role in the
maintenance and growth of fibrin formation, while the extrinsic pathway is critical in
the initiation phase of blood coagulation (H. Cole, Aust. J. Med. Chem. 16 (1995) 87;
G.J. Broze, Blood Coagulation and Fibrinolysis &amp;, Suppl.1 (1995) S7-S13). It is
generally accepted that blood coagulation is physically initiated upon formation of a
tissue factor(TF)/factor VIIa complex. Once formed, this complex rapidly initiates
coagulation by activating factors IX and X. The newly generated activated factor X, i.
e. factor Xa, then forms a one-to-one complex with factor Va and phospholipids to
form a prothrombinase complex, which is responsible for converting soluble
fibrinogen to insoluble fibrin via the activation of thrombin from its precursor
prothrombin. As time progresses, the activity of the factor VIIa/tissue factor complex
(extrinsic pathway) is suppressed by a Kunitz-type protease inhibitor protein, TFPI,
which, when complexed to factor Xa, can directly inhibit the proteolytic activity of
factor VIIa/tissue factor. In order to maintain the coagulation process in the presence 
of an inhibited extrinsic system, additional factor Xa is produced via the
thrombin-mediated activity of the intrinsic pathway. Thus, thrombin plays a dual
autocatalytic role, mediating its own production and the conversion of fibrinogen to
fibrin.</p><p num="0005">The autocatalytic nature of thrombin generation is an important safeguard against
uncontrolled bleeding and it ensures that, once a given threshold level of
prothrombinase is present, blood coagulation will proceed to completion. The ability
to form blood clots is vital to survival. In certain disease states, however, the
formation of blood clots within the circulatory system is itself a source of morbidity. It
is nevertheless not desirable in such disease states to completely inhibit the clotting
system because life threatening hemorrhage would ensue. Thus, it is most desirable
to develop agents that inhibit coagulation by inhibition of factor VIIa without directly
inhibiting thrombin.</p><p num="0006">In many clinical applications there is a great need for the prevention of intravascular
blood clots or for some anti-coagulant treatment. The currently available drugs are
not satisfactory in many specific clinical applications. For example, nearly 50 % of
patients who have undergone a total hip replacement develop deep vein thrombosis
(DVT). The currently approved therapies are fixed dose low molecular weight
heparin (LMWH) and variable dose heparin. Even with these drug regimes 10 % to
20 % of patients develop DVT and 5 % to 10 % develop bleeding complications.</p><p num="0007">Another clinical situation for which better anticoagulants are needed concerns
subjects undergoing transluminal coronary angioplasty and subjects at risk for
myocardial infarction or suffering from crescendo angina. The present,
conventionally accepted therapy, which consists of administering heparin and
aspirin, is associated with a 6 % to 8 % abrupt vessel closure rate within 24 hours of
the procedure. The rate of bleeding complications requiring transfusion therapy due
to the use of heparin also is approximately 7 %. Moreover, even though delayed 
closures are significant, administration of heparin after termination of the procedures
is of little value and can be detrimental.</p><p num="0008">The most widely used blood-clotting inhibitors are heparin and the related sulfated
polysaccharides, LMWH and heparin sulfate. These molecules exert their
anti-clotting effects by promoting the binding of a natural regulator of the clotting
process, anti-thrombin III, to thrombin and to factor Xa. The inhibitory activity of
heparin primarily is directed toward thrombin, which is inactivated approximately 100
times faster than factor Xa. Hirudin and hirulog are two additional thrombin-specific
anticoagulants presently in clinical trials. However, these anticoagulants, which
inhibit thrombin, also are associated with bleeding complications. Preclinical studies
in baboons and dogs have shown that targeting enzymes involved at earlier stages
of the coagulation cascade, such as factor Xa or factor VIIa, prevents clot formation
without producing the bleeding side effects observed with direct thrombin inhibitors
(T. Yokoyama, A.B Kelly, U.M Marzec, Hanson SR, S Kunitada, L.A Harker,
Circulation 92 (1995),485-491; L.A Harker, S.R Hanson, A.B Kelly, Thromb
Hemostas 74 (1995) 464-472; C.R Benedict, J Ryan, J Todd, K Kuwabara, P Tyburg,
Jr. J Cartwright, D. Stern, Blood 81 (1993, 2059-2066).</p><p num="0009">Specific inhibition of the factor VIIa/TF catalytic complex using monoclonal antibody
(International Application No. WO9206711) and a protein such as chloromethyl
ketone inactivated FVIIa (International Appl. No. WO9612800 and WO9747651) is
an extremely effective means of controlling thrombus formation caused by acute
arterial injury or the thrombotic complications related to bacterial septicemia. There
is also experimental evidence suggesting that inhibition of factor VIIa/TF activity
inhibits restenosis following ballon angioplasty (L.A Harker, S.R Hanson, J.N Wilcox,
A.B Kelly, Haemostasis 26 (1996) S1:76-82). Bleeding studies have been
conducted in baboons and indicate that inhibition of the factor VIIa/TF complex has
the widest safety window with respect to therapeutic effectiveness and bleeding risk
of any anticoagulant approach tested including thrombin, platelet and factor Xa 
inhibition (L.A Harker, S.R Hanson, A.B Kelly, Thromb Hemostas 74 (1995) 464-472).</p><p num="0010">A specific inhibitor of factor VIIa would have substantial practical value in the
practice of medicine. In particular, a factor VIIa inhibitor would be effective under
circumstances where the present drugs of choice, heparin and related sulfated
polysaccharides, are ineffective or only marginally effective. Thus, there exists a
need for a low molecular weight, factor VIIa-specific blood clotting inhibitor that is
effective, but does not cause unwanted side effects. The present invention satisfies
this need by providing factor VIIa activity inhibiting derivatives of formula I and by
providing related advantages as well.</p><p num="0011">The compounds of formula I are inhibitors of the blood clotting enzyme factor VIIa.
The invention also relates to processes for the preparation of the compounds of
formula I, to methods of inhibiting factor VIIa activity and of inhibiting blood clotting,
to the use of the compounds of formula I in the treatment and prophylaxis of
diseases which can be cured or prevented by the inhibition of factor VIIa activity
such as thromboembolic diseases, and restenosis and the use of the compounds of
formula I in the preparation of medicaments to be applied in such diseases. The
invention further relates to compositions containing a compound of formula I in a
mixture or otherwise in association with an inert carrier, in particular pharmaceutical
compositions containing a compound of formula I together with pharmaceutically
acceptable carrier substances and auxiliary substances. </p><heading><u style="single">Summary of the invention</u></heading><p num="0012">The present invention provides compounds that specifically inhibit factor VIIa
activity. The compounds of the invention have the formula I
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R1-A-B-D-E<sub>n</sub>-R2</st32:che>
wherein
<sl><li>R1 represents
<sl><li>hydrogen,</li><li>1 to 3 amino acids, the N-terminus of which can be substituted with a
substituent selected from the group consisting of R14CO, R15SO<sub>2</sub> and an
amino protecting group,</li><li>R12C(O) or</li><li>R13,

wherein
<dl tsize="12"><dt>R12</dt><dd>is selected from the group consisting of alkyl, alkenyl, alkynyl, alkoxy,
alkylamino, alkenylamino, alkynylamino, alkenyloxy, alkynyloxy, aryl,
heteroaryl, heterocycloalkyl, heteroarylalkyl, heterocycloalkylalkyl,
heteroalkyl, heteroalkenyl and heteroalkynyl, which radicals can be
substituted,</dd><dt>R13</dt><dd>is selected from the group consisting of an amino protecting group,
hydrogen, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,</dd><dt>R14 and R15</dt><dd>are independently selected from the group consisting of alkyl,
aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl, heterocycloalkyl and
heterocycloalkylalkyl,</dd></dl></li></sl></li><li>A is the group A1-A2-A3, wherein
<dl tsize="3"><dt>A1</dt><dd>is NR91, wherein R91 is selected from the group consisting of
hydrogen, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,</dd><dt>A2</dt><dd>is CR92R93, wherein R92 and R93 independently are selected
from the group consisting of hydrogen and the radicals alkyl,
aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl, heterocycloalkyl and
heterocycloalkylalkyl, which may be substituted,</dd><dt>A3</dt><dd>is C(O),</dd></dl></li><li>B is the group B1-B2-B3, wherein
<dl tsize="3"><dt>B1</dt><dd>is NR95, wherein R95 is selected from the group consisting of
hydrogen, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,</dd><dt>B2</dt><dd>is CR96R97, wherein R96 and R97 are independently selected
from the group consisting of hydrogen and the unsubstituted or
substituted radicals alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl,
heteroarylalkyl, heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,</dd><dt>B3</dt><dd>is C(O),</dd></dl></li><li>D is the group D1-D2-D3, wherein
<dl tsize="3"><dt>D1</dt><dd>is NR80, wherein R80 is selected from the group consisting of
hydrogen, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl, </dd><dt>D2</dt><dd>is CR81R82, wherein R81 and R82 are independently selected
from the group consisting of hydrogen and unsubstituted or
substituted alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,</dd><dt>D3</dt><dd>is C(O),</dd></dl></li><li>E<sub>n</sub> is (E1-E2-E3)<sub>n</sub>, wherein
<sl><li>n is an integer of from 0 to 3,</li></sl><dl tsize="3"><dt>E1</dt><dd>is NR70, wherein R70 is selected from the group consisting of
hydrogen, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,</dd><dt>E2</dt><dd>is CR71R72, wherein R71 and R72 are independently selected
from the group consisting of hydrogen and unsubstituted or
substituted alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,</dd><dt>E3</dt><dd>is C(O),</dd><dt>R2</dt><dd>is selected from the group consisting of NR21R22, OR23 and R24,
wherein R21, R22, R23 and R24 are independently selected from the
group consisting of hydrogen and unsubstituted or substituted alkyl,
aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl, heterocycloalkyl and
heterocycloalkylalkyl,</dd></dl>
and pharmaceutically acceptable salts thereof.</li></sl></p><p num="0013">Preferred are compounds of the formula I

wherein
<sl><li>R1 is R12 CO, wherein R12 is as defined</li><li>A is A1-A2-A3, wherein
<sl><li>A1 is -NH-,</li><li>A2 is -CR92R93-, wherein R92 is hydrogen and R93 is as defined</li><li>A3 is -CO-,</li></sl></li><li>B is B1-B2-B3, wherein
<sl><li>B1 is -NH-,</li><li>B2 is -CR96R97-, wherein R96 is hydrogen and R97 is as defined,</li><li>B3 is -CO-,</li></sl></li><li>D is D1-D2-D3, wherein
<sl><li>D1 is-NH-,</li><li>D2 is -CR81R82-, wherein R81 is hydrogen and R82 is as defined,</li><li>D3 is -CO-,</li></sl></li><li>E<sub>n</sub> is (E1-E2-E3)<sub>n</sub>, wherein
<sl><li>n is 1 or 2,</li><li>E1 is -NH-,</li><li>E2 is -CR71R72-, wherein R71 is hydrogen and R72 is as defined,</li><li>E3 is -CO-, and</li></sl></li><li>R2 is as defined.</li></sl></p><p num="0014">Particularly preferred are the above indicated preferred compounds of the formula (I)
wherein n is 1 and R2 is NHR22, wherein R22 is as defined.</p><p num="0015">Specific examples of the compounds of the invention include, for example, the
compounds listed in Table 2 below. </p><p num="0016">The compounds of the formula I can be prepared by
<sl><li>a1) attaching a compound of the formula Fmoc-E<sub>n</sub>-OH or Fmoc-D1-D2-COOH, where
Fmoc is 9-fluorenylmethoxycarbonyl and E<sub>n</sub>, D1 and D2 are as hereinbefore defined,
to a Rink-amide resin and then cleaving off the protecting group Fmoc,</li><li>a2) repeating the procedure as described in step a1) above with Fmoc-B1-B2-COOH,</li><li>a3) repeating the procedure as described in step a1) above with R1-A1-A2-COOH,
and</li><li>a4) finally cleaving off the compound obtained according to steps a1) through a3)
above by means of TFA from the resin, where TFA is trifluoroacetic acid,
or</li><li>b1) coupling the side chain carboxylic acid of Fmoc-B1-CH(R97)-COOPG, where
Fmoc is as defined in step a1) above, R97 is a radical as defined above except
hydrogen, which is substituted with a hydroxycarbonyl group, and PG is a
protecting group, to an acid sensitive benzylalcohol type of linker attached to an
amino functionalized resin,</li><li>b2) cleaving off the protecting group PG,</li><li>b3) coupling HN(R80)-D2-D3-E<sub>n</sub>-R2, where D2, D3, E<sub>n</sub>, R2 and R80 are as defined
above, to the free carboxylic acid of the compound obtained in step b2) above by
means of a suitable coupling agent,</li><li>b4) cleaving off the Fmoc group,</li><li>b5) coupling of the compound R1-A1-A2-COOH in analogy to the above described
procedure, and</li><li>b6) cleaving off the compound obtained in step b5) by means of TFA,
or</li><li>c1) coupling of protected amino acids by traditional medicinal chemistry and
deprotecting to the target molecules by standard procedures known in the art.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Detailed Description of the invention</u></heading><p num="0017">The present invention provides peptides of the formula I
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R1-A-B-D-E<sub>n</sub>-R2</st32:che>
which are compounds that inhibit factor VIIa activity but do not substantially inhibit
the activity of other proteases involved in the blood coagulation pathway.</p><p num="0018">As used herein, the term, "amino acid" is used in its broadest sense to mean the
twenty naturally occurring amino acids, which are translated from the genetic code
and comprise the building blocks of proteins, including, unless specifically stated
otherwise, L-amino acids and D-amino acids, as well as chemically modified amino
acids such as amino acid analogs, naturally-occurring amino acids that are not
usually incorporated into proteins such as norleucine, and chemically synthesized
compounds having properties known in the art to be characteristic of an amino acid.
For example, analogs or mimetics of phenylalanine or proline, which allow the same
conformational restriction of the peptide compounds as natural Phe or Pro, are
included within the definition of "amino acids" and are known to those skilled in the
art. Such analogs and mimetics are referred to herein as "functional equivalents" of
an amino acid. Other examples of amino acids and amino acids analogs are listed by
Roberts and Vellaccio (The Peptides: Analysis, Synthesis, Biology, Eds. Gross and
Meienhofer, Vol. 5, p. 341, Academic Press, Inc., N.Y. 1983, which is incorporated
herein by reference). Abbreviations of amino acids, amino acid analogs and mimetic
structures used in application are listed in Table 1. <img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="147" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="217"/><img id="img-00130001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="208"/></p><p num="0019">Further, the terms TOTU and HATU used in the Examples, mean
O-[cyan(ethoxycarbonyl)methylenamino]-1,1,3,3-tetramethyluronium
tetrafluoroborate and O-(7-azabenzotriazol-1-yl)-1,1,3,3-tetramethyluronium
hexafluorophosphate, respectively.</p><p num="0020">As used herein, the term "specific" when used in reference to the inhibition of factor
VIIa activity means that a compound of the formula I can inhibit factor VIIa activity
without substantially inhibiting the activity of other specified proteases, including
plasmin and thrombin (using the same concentration of the inhibitor). Such
proteases are involved in the blood coagulation and fibrinolysis cascade.</p><p num="0021">As used herein, the term "substituent" refers to any of various chemical groups that
is substituted onto the peptide backbone or side chain of a peptide, peptide
analogue, mimetic or organic compound disclosed herein. A substituent can include
any of a variety of different moieties known to those skilled in the art (see, for
example, Giannis and Kolter, Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl. 32:1244-1267 (1993),
which is incorporated herein by reference).</p><p num="0022">As used herein, the term "alkyl" is used in the broadest sense to mean saturated or
unsaturated, linear, branched or cyclic chains of about 1 to 13 carbon atoms. Thus,
the term "alkyl" includes, for example, methyl, ethyl, n-propyl, isopropyl, sec-butyl,
1 -methylbutyl, 2,2-dimethylbutyl, 2-methylpentyl, 2,2-dimethylpropyl, n-pentyl and
n-hexyl groups, alkylene groups, cyclic chains of carbon atoms such cyclohexyl and
cyclopentyl groups, as well as combinations of linear or branched chains and cyclic
chains of carbon atoms such as a methyl-cyclohexyl or cyclopropyl-methylene group.
In addition, it should be recognized that an alkyl as defined herein can be
substituted with a substituent. Similarly, the term "acyl" is used in its broadest sense
to mean saturated or unsaturated, linear, branched or cyclic chains of about 1 to 13
carbon atoms or aryl groups having 5 to 13 carbon atoms, which contain a carboxyl
group. Thus, the term "acyl" encompasses, for example, groups such as formyl,
acetyl, benzoyl and the like. </p><p num="0023">Preferably, the term 
<img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="1" img-format="tif" img-content="ff" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="1"/>alkyl" means saturated, linear or branched chains of from 1 to 6
carbon atoms, unsaturated linear or branched chains of from 2 to 6 carbon atoms, or
cyclic alkyl groups of from 3 to 6 carbon atoms, preferred of from 4 to 6 carbon
atoms. From the unsaturated alkyl chains, C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>-alkenyl and C<sub>2</sub>-C<sub>6</sub>-alkynyl are
preferred.</p><p num="0024">Preferably, the term <imgref idrefs="img-00150001"/>acyl" means the hereinbefore mentioned saturated or
unsaturated, linear, branched or cyclic chains having the preferred range of carbon
atoms, which contain a carboxyl group.</p><p num="0025">The term "aryl" refers to aromatic groups containing about 5 to 13 carbon atoms and
at least one "ring" group having a conjugated pi electron system. Preferable, the
term <imgref idrefs="img-00150001"/>aryl" refers to aromatic groups having 6 to 10 carbon atoms. Examples of aryls
include, for example, phenyl, naphthyl, fluorenyl, biphenylyl groups, and analogues
and derivatives thereof, all of which optionally can be substituted with one or more
substituents. The term "arylalkyl" refers to an alkyl as defined above substituted with
one or more, for example two, aryl groups. Suitable arylalkyl groups include benzyl,
phenethyl, diphenylmethyl, diphenylethyl, diphenylpropyl, naphthylmethyl,
naphtylethyl and the like, all of which optionally can be substituted.</p><p num="0026">The terms "heteroalkyl," "heteroarylalkyl" and "heteroaryl" also are used herein and
refer to an alkyl, an arylalkyl and an aryl, respectively, wherein one or more carbon
atoms are replaced with one or more heteroatoms such as a N, O or S atom. In
addition, the term "heterocycloalkyl" is used in reference to a cyclic alkyl group that
is substituted with one or more heteroatoms. Preferably, the term <imgref idrefs="img-00150001"/>heterocycloalkyl"
means a cycloalkyl group having 3 to 8 carbon atoms, of which 1 to 3 are replaced
with hetero atoms such a N, O or S atoms. Suitable heteroaryl groups,
heteroarylalkyl groups and heteroalkyl groups include, for example, pyridyl, thienyl,
indolyl, imidazolyl, furyl, piperonyl, picolyl, pyrrolidinyl, piperidyl, tetrahydrofuryl,
morpholinyl, piperazinyl and the like, all of which can optionally be substituted. </p><p num="0027">The peptides of the invention can be modified at the N-terminus and/or the C-terminus
by reaction with suitable reagents or by introduction (or by the presence of)
an amino-protecting group or carboxy-protecting group, respectively. The N-terminus
of a peptide or peptide analog can be chemically modified such that the N-terminus
amino group is substituted, for example, by an acyl group (for example acetyl,
cyclopentylcarboxy, isoquinolylcarboxy, furoyl, tosyl, benzoyl, pyrazinecarboxy or
other such group), by reaction with an isocyanate, chloroformate, alkylating agent or
by introducing other such group, all of which can be substituted by a substituent as
described above. It should be recognized that the term "amino group" is used
broadly herein to refer to any free amino group, including a primary, secondary or
tertiary amino group, present in a peptide. In comparison, the term "N-terminus"
refers to the α-amino group of the first amino acid present in a peptide written in the
conventional manner.</p><p num="0028">The N-terminus of a peptide of the invention can be protected by linking thereto an
amino-protecting group. The term "amino-protecting group" is used broadly herein to
refer to a chemical group that can react with a free amino group, including, for
example, the α-amino group present at the N-terminus of a peptide of the invention.
By virtue of reacting therewith, an amino-protecting group protects the otherwise
reactive amino group against undesirable reactions as can occur, for example,
during a synthetic procedure or due to exopeptidase activity on a final compound.
Modification of an amino group also can provide additional advantages, including,
for example, increasing the solubility or the activity of the compound. Various amino-protecting
groups are disclosed herein or otherwise known in the art and include, for
example, acyl groups such as an acetyl, tert-butyloxycarbonyl, allyloxycarbonyl,
benzyloxycarbonyl group, benzoyl groups, as well as an aminoacyl residue, which
itself can be modified by an amino-protecting group. Other amino-protecting groups
are described, for example, in The Peptides, eds. Gross and Meienhofer, Vol. 3
(Academic Press, Inc., N.Y. 1981); and by Greene and Wuts, in Protective Groups in
Organic Synthesis 2d ed., pages 309-405 (John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York (1991), 
each of which is incorporated herein by reference. The product of any such
modification of the N-terminus amino group of a peptide or peptide analog of the
invention is referred to herein as an "N-terminal derivative."</p><p num="0029">Similarly, a carboxy group such as the carboxy group present at the C-terminus of a
peptide can be chemically modified using a carboxy-protecting group. The terms
"carboxy group" and "C-terminus" are used in a manner consistent with the terms
"amino group" and "N-terminus" as defined above. A carboxy group such as that
present at the C-terminus of a peptide can be modified by reduction of the C-terminus
carboxy group to an alcohol or aldehyde or by formation of an oral ester or
by substitution of the carboxy group with a substituent such as a thiazolyl, cyclohexyl
or other group. Oral esters are well known in the art and include, for example,
alkoxymethyl groups such as methoxymethyl, ethoxymethyl, iso-propoxymethyl and
the like; the α-(C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>4</sub>)alkoxyethyl groups such as methoxyethyl, ethoxyethyl,
propoxyethyl, isopropoxyethyl and the like; the 2-oxo-1,3-dioxolen-4-ylmethyl groups
such as 5-methyl-2-oxo-1,3-dioxolen-4-ylmethyl, 5-phenyl-2-oxo-1,3-dioxolen-4-ylmethyl
and the like; the C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>3</sub> alkylthiomethyl groups such as methylthiomethyl,
ethylthiomethyl, isopropylthiomethyl and the like; the acyloxymethyl groups such as
pivaloyloxymethyl, α-acetoxymethyl and the like; the ethoxycarbonyl-1-methyl group;
the α-acyloxy-α-substituted methyl groups such as α-acetoxyethyl, the 3-phthalidyl or
5,6-dimethylphthalidyl groups, the 1-(C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>4</sub> alkyloxycarbonyloxy)eth-1-yl groups
such as the 1-(ethoxycarbonyloxy)eth-1-yl group; and the 1-(C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>4</sub>
alkylaminocarbonyloxy)eth-1-yl group such as the 1-(methylaminocarbonyloxy)eth-1-yl
group.</p><p num="0030">A peptide of the invention can be modified by linking thereto a carboxy-protecting
group. Carboxy-protecting groups are well known in the art and, by virtue of being
bound to a peptide, protect a carboxy group against undesirable reactions (see, for
example, Greene and Wuts, supra, pages 224-276 (1991), which is incorporated
herein by reference). The skilled artisan would recognize that such modifications as
described above, which can be effected upon the N-terminus amino group or 
C-terminus carboxy group of a peptide, similarly can be effected upon any reactive
amino group or carboxy group present, for example, on a side chain of an amino
acid or amino acid analog in a peptide of the invention. Methods for performing such
modifications are disclosed herein or otherwise known in the art.</p><p num="0031">The choice of including an L- or a D-amino acid in a compound of the present
invention can depend, in part, on the desired characteristics of the peptide. For
example, the incorporation of one or more D-amino acids can confer increased
stability on the compound in vitro or in vivo. The incorporation of one or more D-amino
acids also can increase or decrease the pharmacological activity of the
compound. In some cases it can be desirable to allow the compound to remain
active for only a short period of time. In such cases, the incorporation of one or more
L-amino acids in the compound can allow endogenous peptidases in an individual to
digest the compound in vivo, thereby limiting the individual's exposure to the active
compound. The skilled artisan can determine the desirable characteristics required
of compound of the invention by taking into consideration, for example, the age and
general health of an individual.</p><p num="0032">A compound of the invention can be chemically synthesized using, for example, an
automated synthesizer (see Example I). Selective modification of a reactive group
such as a group present on an amino acid side chain or an N-terminus or a
C-terminus reactive group in a peptide can impart desirable characteristics such as
increased solubility or enhanced inhibitory function to a compound of the invention.</p><p num="0033">Where solid phase synthesis methods are employed, the chemical composition of a
compound can be manipulated while the nascent peptide is attached to the resin or
after the peptide has been cleaved from the resin to obtain, for example, an N-terminal
derivative such as an N-terminus acylated, e. g. acetylated, compound.
Similar modifications also can be made to a carboxy group of a compound, including
a C-terminus carboxy group, which, for example, can be amidated. One skilled in the
art also can synthesize a compound of the invention using solution phase organic 
chemistry. A synthesized compound can be purified using well known methods such
as reverse phase-high performance liquid chromatography (RP-HPLC; see Example
I) or other methods of separation based, for example, on the size, charge or
hydrophobicity of the compound. Similarly, well known methods such as amino acid
sequence analysis or mass spectrometry (MS) can be used for characterizing the
structure of a compound of the invention (see Example I).</p><p num="0034">A composition of the present invention can be provided as a homogenous
composition or as a mixture of compounds containing various combinations of
substituents. The flexibility permitted by the choice of substituents permits a great
deal of control over the physico-chemical properties of the peptide compound
analogs. The choice of the substituent also influences the binding affinity of the
compound (see Examples).</p><p num="0035">Various compounds containing different arrangements of the substituents exhibit
different levels of inhibitory activity for factor VIIa. These compounds were
synthesized according to the procedures described in the Examples. Testing the
peptides for inhibitory activity was accomplished using the assay described in
Example 22. Using such methods, one skilled in the art can synthesize a compound
as disclosed herein, including a modification thereof, and determine the factor VIIa
inhibitory activity of the compound.</p><p num="0036">The invention provides compounds that specifically inhibit factor VII activity. Such
compounds preferably have a Ki ≤ 500 nM, more preferably ≤ 50 nM, for factor VIIa
activity and do not substantially inhibit the activity of other proteases involved in
coagulation and fibrinolysis cascade relative to the inhibition of factor VIIa (using the
same concentration of the inhibitor). Such other proteases include, for example,
factor Xa, thrombin and plasmin. </p><p num="0037">The following Table 2 shows the factor VIIa inhibitory activities of selected
compounds of the formula I (see Example 22)
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Factor VIIa inhibitory activities of selected compounds of the formula I</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Ki (µM)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Arg-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.046</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Allylaminocarbonyl-pAph-Glu-Arg-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.042</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Arg-Chg-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.238</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dap[-C(=NH)-NH<sub>2</sub>]-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.012</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Ala[3-C(=NH)-NH<sub>2</sub>]-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.021</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dab-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.055</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dap[-C(=NH)-NH<sub>2</sub>]-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.26</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Gly-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.12</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Thr(Bzl)-NH-(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>-CH(Ph)<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.17</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dab-NH-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-phenyl</entry><entry align="center">0.38</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-NH-CH<sub>2</sub>-Chx</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-2-Abu[4-C(=NH)-CH<sub>3</sub>]-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.19</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dap[-C(=NH)-CH<sub>3</sub>]-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.11</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dab[-C(=NH)-NH<sub>2</sub>]-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.012</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-2-Abu[4-CN]-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.063</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Ala[3-CN]-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry> <entry align="center">0.12</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(1-naphthyl)-methylamide</entry><entry align="center">0.031</entry></row> <row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(1-naphthyl)-1-ethylamide</entry> <entry align="center">0.021</entry> </row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(2-naphthyl)-methylamide</entry><entry align="center">0.027</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(3,4-dichlorobenzyl)-amide</entry><entry align="center">0.026</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-2-(3-chlorophenyl)-ethylamide</entry><entry align="center">0.023</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Arg[NO<sub>2</sub>]-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.014 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Cys[Bzl]-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.026</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Trp-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.017</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Phg-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></entry><entry align="center">0.017</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(9-fluorenyl)-amide, or</entry><entry align="center">0.023</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(3,5-ditrifluormethylbenzyl)-amide</entry><entry align="center">0.033</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0038">The thrombin-inhibitory activities of the above compounds can be expressed in Ki-values
which are between 500 and 1000 times as high as the above indicated factor
VIIa inhibitory activities. Also, the factor Xa inhibitory activities of the above
compounds as determined can be expressed in Ki-values which are at least 100
times as high as the above indicated factor VIIa inhibitory activities.</p><p num="0039">These results demonstrate that the compounds of the formula I are useful as
inhibitors of factor VIIa, but do not substantially inhibit the activity of factor Xa or
serine proteases such as thrombine, which are involved in the process of blood
coagulation and fibrinolysis.</p><p num="0040">A compound of the invention can be used advantageously as an anticoagulant,
which can be contacted with a blood sample to prevent coagulation. For example, an
effective amount of a compound of the invention can be contacted with a freshly
drawn blood sample to prevent coagulation of the blood sample. As used herein, the
term "effective amount" when used in reference to a compound of the invention
means an amount of a compound that inhibits factor VIIa activity. The skilled artisan
would recognize that an effective amount of a compound of the invention can be
determined using the methods disclosed herein (see Example 22) or otherwise
known in the art. In view of the disclosed utility of a compound of the invention, the
skilled artisan also would recognize that an agent such as heparin can be replaced
with a compound of the invention. Such a use of a compound of the invention can
result, for example, in a cost saving as compared to other anticoagulants. </p><p num="0041">In addition, a compound of the invention can be administered to an individual for the
treatment of a variety of clinical conditions, including, for example, the treatment of a
cardiovascular disorder or a complication associated, for example, with infection or
surgery. Examples of cardiovascular disorders include restenosis following
angioplasty, adult respiratory disstress syndrome, multi-organ failure, stroke and
disseminated intravascular coagulation clotting disorder. Examples of related
complications associated with surgery include, for example, deep vein and proximal
vein thrombosis, which can occur following surgery. Thus, a compound of the
invention is useful as a medicament for reducing or inhibiting unwanted coagulation
in an individual.</p><p num="0042">Since a compound of the invention can inhibit factor VIIa activity, such a compound
can be useful for reducing or inhibiting blood clotting in an individual. As used
herein, the term "individual" means a vertebrate, including a mammal such as a
human, in which factor VIIa is involved in the clotting cascade.</p><p num="0043">Blood clotting in an individual can be reduced or inhibited by administering to the
individual a therapeutically effective amount of a compound of the invention. As used
herein, the term "therapeutically effective amount" means the dose of a compound
that must be administered to an individual in order to inhibit factor VIIa activity in the
individual. More specifically, a therapeutically effective amount of a compound of the
invention inhibits factor VIIa catalytic activity either directly, within the
prothrombinase complex or as a soluble subunit, or indirectly, by inhibiting the
assembly of factor VIIa into the prothrombinase complex. In particular, such
compounds can inhibit factor VIIa activity with a Ki ≤ 500 nM and, preferably,
with a Ki ≤ 50 nM. A therapeutically effective amount can be determined using the
methods described, for example, in Example 22 or otherwise known in the art.</p><p num="0044">In the practice of a therapeutic method of the invention, the particular dosage to
obtain a therapeutically effective amount of a pharmaceutical composition to be
administered to the individual will depend on a variety of considerations, including, 
for example, the nature or severity of the disease, the schedule of administration and
the age and physical characteristics of the individual. An appropriate dosage can be
established using clinical approaches well known in the medical art. Thus, the
invention provides a method of specifically inhibiting factor VIIa activity by contacting
factor VIIa with a compound having the formula R1-A-B-D-E<sub>n</sub>-R2. The invention
further provides a method of reducing or inhibiting the formation of a blood clot in an
individual by administering a therapeutically effective amount of a compound of the
invention.</p><p num="0045">A compound of the invention generally will be administered to an individual as a
composition containing the compound and a pharmaceutically acceptable carrier.
The term "pharmaceutically acceptable carrier" refers to a medium or composition
that is non-toxic to an individual or has acceptable toxicity as determined by the
appropriate regulatory agency. As used herein, the term pharmaceutically
acceptable carrier encompasses any of the standard pharmaceutical carriers such
as phosphate buffered saline, water, an emulsion such as an oil/water or water/oil
emulsion, or any of various types of wetting agents. Suitable pharmaceutical carriers
and their formulations are described by Martin (in Remington's Pharmaceutical
Sciences, 15th Ed. (Mack Publishing Co., Easton 1975) which is incorporated herein
by reference). Such compositions will, in general, contain a therapeutically effective
amount of a compound of the invention together with a suitable amount of carrier so
as to comprise the proper dosage for administration to an individual. Thus, the
claimed compounds can be useful as medicaments for inhibiting factor VIIa activity
and blood clotting in an individual.</p><p num="0046">Pharmaceutically acceptable carriers also can include, for example, other mediums,
compounds or modifications to a factor VIIa inhibitor compound that enhances its
pharmacological function. A pharmaceutically acceptable medium can include, for
example, an acid addition salt such as a salt formed with an inorganic acid such as
hydrochloric acid, hydrobromic acid, phosphoric acid, sulfuric acid or perchloric acid,
or with an organic acid such as acetic acid, oxalic acid, maleic acid, malic acid, 
tartaric acid, citric acid, succinic acid or malonic acid. Other pharmaceutically
acceptable salts include, for example, inorganic nitrate, sulfate, acetate, malate,
formate, lactate, tartrate, succinate, citrate, p-toluenesulfonate, and the like,
including, but not limited to, cations based on the alkali and alkaline earth metals
such as sodium, lithium, potassium, calcium or magnesium, as well as non-toxic
ammonium, quaternary ammonium and amine cations such as ammonium,
methylammonium, dimethylammonium, trimethylammonium, tetramethylammonium,
ethylammonium, triethylammonium and tetraethylammonium.</p><p num="0047">Examples of modifications that enhance the pharmacological function of the
compound include, for example, esterification such as the formation of C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>6</sub> alkyl
esters, preferably C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>4</sub> alkyl esters, wherein the alkyl group is a straight or
branched chain. Other acceptable esters include, for example, C<sub>5</sub> to C<sub>7</sub> cycloalkyl
esters and arylalkyl esters such as benzyl esters. Such esters can be prepared from
the compounds described herein using conventional methods well known in the art
of peptide chemistry.</p><p num="0048">Pharmaceutically acceptable modifications also can include, for example, the
formation of peptide amides. Such amide modifications, which can be effected upon
the compounds of the invention, include, for example, those derived from ammonia,
primary C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>6</sub> dialkyl amines, where the alkyl groups are straight or branched
chain, or arylamines having various substitutions. In the case of secondary amines,
the amine also can be in the form of a 5 or 6 membered heterocycle containing, for
example, a nitrogen atom. Methods for preparing such amides are well known in the
art.</p><p num="0049">In another embodiment of the invention, a compound of the invention can be used in
an assay to identify the presence of factor VIIa or to isolate factor VIIa in a
substantially purified form. Preferably, the compound of the invention is labeled with,
for example, a radioisotope, and the labeled compound is detected using a routine
method useful for detecting the particular label. In addition, a compound of the 
invention can be used advantageously as a probe to detect the location or amount of
factor VIIa activity in vivo, in vitro or ex vivo.</p><p num="0050">It is understood that modifications that do not substantially affect the activity of the
various embodiments of this invention are included within the invention disclosed
herein. Accordingly, the following examples are intended to illustrate but not limit the
present invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Peptide synthesis procedures and general synthesis procedures</u></heading><p num="0051">Starting materials used in the synthesis were obtained from chemical vendors such
as Aldrich, Sigma, Fluka, Nova Biochem and Advanced Chemtech. During the
synthesis, the functional groups of the amino acid derivatives used were protected
by blocking groups to prevent side reaction during the coupling steps. Examples of
suitable protecting groups and their use are described in The Peptides, supra, 1981,
and in Vol. 9, Udenfriend and Meienhofer ed. 1987, which is incorporated herein by
reference.</p><p num="0052">General solid-phase peptide synthesis was used to produce the compounds of the
invention. Such methods are described, for example, by Steward and Young (Solid
Phase Peptide Synthesis (Freeman &amp; Co., San Francisco, 1969), which is
incorporated herein by reference).</p><p num="0053">Unless indicated otherwise, peptides were synthesized on TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> Resin
(Rapp Polymere, Tübingen, Germany). An acid sensitive linker p-[(R,S)-α-[1-(9H-Fluoren-9-yl)-methoxyformamido]-2,4-dimethoxybenzyl]-phenoxyacetic
acid (Knorr
Linker) was coupled to the solid support (Bernartowicz, et. al, Tetr. Lett. 30:4645
(1989); incorporated herein by reference). Alternatively, peptides were synthesized
on polystyrene resin cross-linked with 1 % divinylbenzene modified with an acid 
sensitive linker (Rink resin) (Rink, Tetr. Lett. 28, 3787 (1987); Sieber, Tetr. Lett. 28,
2107 (1987), each of which is incoporated herein by reference). When peptides
were synthesized by first coupling the sidechain carboxylic acid of a compound of
the formula Fmoc-B1-CH(R97)-COOPG to the resin, TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin modified
by attachment of the HMPA linker was employed. Coupling was performed using
N,N'-diisopropylcarbodiimide (DIC) in the presence of an equivalent amount of
HOBt, with the exception of Alloc-pAph-OH, where 2 equivalents of HOBt were used.
All couplings were done in either N,N-dimethylformamide (DMF) or DMF:DMSO (1:1
mixture) at room temperature (RT). Completion of coupling was monitored by
ninhydrin test. A second (double) coupling was performed where coupling in the first
instance was incomplete.</p><p num="0054">Deprotection of the Fmoc group was accomplished using 50% piperidine in DMF for
2+10 min. The amount of Fmoc released was determined from the absorbance at
300 nm of the solution after deprotection, volume of washes and weight of the resin
used in the synthesis.</p><p num="0055">The cycle of each coupling was as follows:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Step</entry><entry align="left">Action/Reagent</entry><entry align="left">Solvent</entry></row><row><entry align="right">1.</entry><entry align="left">0.5 g of functionalized Peptide Resin</entry></row><row><entry align="right">2.</entry><entry align="left">3 fold-excess amino acid derivative/HOBt/DIC</entry><entry align="left">4ml DMF</entry></row><row><entry align="right">3.</entry><entry align="left">Couple (min. 1h)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">4.</entry><entry align="left">Wash (3 x 5 ml)</entry><entry align="left">DMF</entry></row><row><entry align="right">5.</entry><entry align="left">Ninhydrin test</entry></row><row><entry align="right">6.</entry><entry align="left">Deprotection (2+10 min)</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="2">Piperidine/DMF</entry><entry align="left" namest="3">5ml 50%</entry></row><row><entry align="right">7.</entry><entry align="left">Wash (6 x 5 ml)</entry><entry align="left">DMF</entry></row><row><entry align="right">8.</entry><entry align="left">Repeat starting at step 2</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0056">After completion of peptide assembly on the resin, the final Fmoc deprotection, if
necessary, was performed. The peptide resin was then washed successively with
DMF and DCM and the peptide was then cleaved and deprotected by a mixture
TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 1.5 hour, unless specified otherwise. The resin was
washed with DCM and DCM wash combined with TFA releasate. The solution was
evaporated, the product precipitated by anhydrous diethyl ether and the solid
precipitate was isolated by filtration or centrifugation and dried in vacuum over solid
pellets of KOH. The solid was redissolved in a mixture of water and acetonitrile and
lyophylized.</p><p num="0057">The dried peptide was subjected to HPLC purification using an appropriate gradient
of 0.1% TFA in water and acetonitrile (ACN). After collecting the peak containing the
intended synthetic product, the peptide solution was lyophilized and the peptide was
subjected to an identification process, which included electrospray MS, NMR and
amino acid analysis to confirm that the correct compound was synthesized.</p><p num="0058">For HPLC analysis, a sample of the product was analyzed using Beckman HPLC
system (consisting of 126 Solvent Deliver System, 166 Programmable Detector
Module 507e Autosampler, controlled by Data Station with Gold Nouveau software)
and YMC ODS-AM 4.6x250mm column at 230 nm and flow rate 1ml/min.</p><p num="0059">For product purification, a sample of crude lyophilized peptide was dissolved in a
mixture of 0.1% aqueous TFA containing 10% to 50% ACN. The peptide solution
usually was filtered through a syringe connected to a 0.45 µm "ACRODISC" 13 CR
PTFE (Gelman Sciences; Ann Arbor MI) filter. A proper volume of filtered peptide
solution was injected into a semi-preparative C18 column (Vydac Protein and
Peptide C18, 218TP1022 (22x250mm); The Separation Group; Hesperia CA, or
YMC ODS-A column (20x250mm), YMC, Inc., Wilmington, NC). The flow rate of a
gradient or isocratic mixture of 0.1% TFA buffer and ACN (HPLC grade) as an eluent 
was maintained using a Beckman "SYSTEM GOLD" HPLC (Beckman, System Gold,
Programmable Solvent Module 126 and Programmable Detector Module 166
controlled by "SYSTEM GOLD" software). Elution of the peptide was monitored by
UV detection at 230 nm. After identifying the peak corresponding to the compound
under synthesis using MS, the compound was collected, lyophilized and biologically
tested. MS was performed using a VG Platform (Fisons Instruments) instrument in
ES+ mode. In addition, NMR was performed using a Bruker Avance DPX 300
instrument. For NMR, samples typically were measured in DMSO-d<sub>6</sub> (Aldrich).</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-OH</u></heading><p num="0060">The same procedure is applicable to Alloc-(D)-pAph-OH</p><heading>Alloc-Phe(4-CN)-OH</heading><p num="0061">5.7 g (30 mmol) of H-Phe(4-CN)-OH were dissolved in 100 ml 1M NaOH with
addition of 2M NaOH to pH=10 with ice cooling. With vigorous stirring,
allylchloroformate (7.5ml) was slowly added (pH kept at 10 by 2M NaOH). Reaction
was stirred at 0°C for 15 min and at RT for 30min, acidified with HCl to pH =2,
extracted with EtOAc (3 times), dried MgSO<sub>4</sub> and evaporated. Recrystalized from
EtOAc/hexanes.

White solid, 7.0g (85%).</p><heading>Alloc-Phe(4-C(=S)-NH<sub>2</sub>)-OH</heading><p num="0062">2.74g of Alloc-Phe(4-CN)-OH was dissolved in mixture pyridine(50 ml)/Et<sub>3</sub>N(20 ml)
and H<sub>2</sub>S was passed through for 30 min. Reaction mixture was kept overnight at RT
and evaporated. Drying on high vacuum gave 3.21 g of solid foam of the crude
thioamide, which is directly converted to the methylthioimidate. </p><heading>Alloc-Phe(4-C(=NH)-SCH<sub>3</sub>)-OH · HI</heading><p num="0063">1g of Alloc-Phe(4-C(=S)-NH<sub>2</sub>)-OH was dissolved in acetone (50 ml) and Mel (5 ml)
was added. Reaction was kept overnight at RT, volatile solvents evaporated (fast,
35°C max) and the residue treated with Et<sub>2</sub>O. After 1 hour at 0°C, ether was
decanted, product washed with Et<sub>2</sub>O and dried in vacuum. Yellow solid foam, directly
converted to amidine.</p><heading>Alloc-pAph-OH</heading><p num="0064">All of the Alloc-Phe(4-C(=NH)-SCH<sub>3</sub>)-OH · HI above was dissolved in 50 ml methanol
with 300 µl of acetic acid and 0.5 g of ammonium acetate was added. Mixture was
heated for 3 hours to 55°C, evaporated and 10 ml of acetone was added. After 2
hours at 0°C, the solid product was filtered, washed with little cold acetone, little cold
methanol and diethyl ether and dried in vacuum. Yellowish solid, yield 0.53g.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Arg-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0065">To 1g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.26mmol/g), Knorr amide linker was
attached. According to general procedures outlined in Example 1, following
protected amino acids were coupled: Fmoc-Cha-OH, Fmoc-Arg(Pmc)-OH, Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH
and Alloc-pAph. The peptide was cleaved and deprotected by mixture
TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 3 hours and processed as described in Example 1. The
crude compound was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and
characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 729.1, calc. 729.4.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 4</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Allyl-NH-CO-pAoh-Glu-Arg-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0066">To 0.5g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.26mmol/g), Knorr amide linker was
attached. According to general procedures in Example 1, following protected amino
acids were coupled: Fmoc-Cha-OH, Fmoc-Arg(Pmc)-OH, Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH and
Fmoc-Phe(4-CN). After N-terminal Fmoc deprotection, the resin was treated with
solution of 1 mmol of allylisocyanate in 3 ml of DMF for 2 hours. The resin was then
washed with DMF and triethylamine/pyridine(1:2) and treated with saturated solution
of H<sub>2</sub>S in pyridine/triethylamine overnight. The resin was washed with acetone and
the thioamide resin was reacted with methyliodide (3 ml of 10% solution of
methyliodide in acetone) for 6 hours. The methylthioimidate resin was washed with
acetone, methanol and treated with solution of 0.2g ammonium acetate, 100 µl
acetic acid in 3 ml of methanol at 55°C for 3 hours. The resin was washed with
methanol, DMF and DCM and the peptide was cleaved and deprotected by mixture
TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 3 hours and processed as described in Example 1. The
crude material was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and
characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 728.3, calc. 728.4.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 5</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Arg-Chg-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0067">To 1g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.26mmol/g), Knorr amide linker was
attached. According to general procedures in Example 1, following protected amino
acids were coupled: Fmoc-Chg-OH, Fmoc-Arg(Pmc)-OH, Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH and
Alloc-pAph. The peptide was cleaved and deprotected by mixture TFA/thioanisole
(95/5) for 3 hours and processed as described in Example 1. The crude compound
was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and characterized by MS.
(M+H)+: found 715.8, calc. 715.4.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 6</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-(D)pAph-Glu-Arg-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0068">To 1g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.26mmol/g), Knorr amide linker was
attached. According to general procedures in Example 1, following protected amino
acids were coupled: Fmoc-Cha-OH, Fmoc-Arg(Pmc)-OH, Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH and
Alloc-(D)pAph-OH (synthesized according to the same procedure as Alloc-pAph-OH
in Example 2). The peptide was cleaved and deprotected by mixture TFA/thioanisole
(95/5) for 3 hours and processed as described in Example 1. The crude compound
was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and characterized by MS.
(M+H)+: found 729.2, calc. 729.4.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 7</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Phe(4-guanido)-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0069">To 0.25g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.23mmol/g), Knorr amide linker was
attached. According to general procedures in Example 1, following protected amino
acids were coupled: Fmoc-Cha-OH, Fmoc-Phe(4-NH-C(=NBoc)-NH-Boc)-OH, Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH
and Alloc-pAph-OH. The peptide was cleaved and deprotected by
mixture TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 1 hour and processed as described in Example 1.
The crude compound was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and
characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 777.1, calc. 777.4.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 8</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dap(-C(=NH)-NH<sub>2</sub>)-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0070">To 0.25g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.23mmol/g), Knorr amide linker was
attached. According to general procedures in Example 1, following protected amino
acids were coupled: Fmoc-Cha-OH, Fmoc-Dap(-C(=N-Boc)-NH-Boc)-OH, Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH
and Alloc-pAph. The peptide was cleaved and deprotected by mixture
TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 1 hour and processed as described in Example 1. The
crude compound was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and
characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 729.1, calc. 729.4. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 9</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dap(-C(=NH)-CH<sub>3</sub>)-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0071">To 0.25g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.26mmol/g), Knorr amide linker was
attached. According to general procedures in Example 1, following protected amino
acids were coupled: Fmoc-Cha-OH, Fmoc-Dap(Alloc)-OH and Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH.
With the N-terminal Fmoc-protecting group attached, the resin was washed with
mixture DMF/NMM/HOAc (5/0.5/1), and under constant mixing with stream of argon,
Alloc group was deprotected by addition of 100mg of Pd(P(Ph)<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub> over a period of 3
hours. The resin was washed with DMF and treated with solution of 150mg of 2-methylnaphthyl
acetthioimidate in 4ml of EtOH/DMSO (3:1) for 1 hour. After washing
with DMF, the Fmoc group was deprotected (1+5 mm) and the N-terminal Alloc-pAph-OH
was coupled. The peptide was cleaved and deprotected by mixture
TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 1 hour and processed as described in Example 1. The
crude compound was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and
characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 700.1, calc. 700.4.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 10</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Ala(3-C(=NH)-NH2)-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0072">To 0.25g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.26mmol/g), Knorr amide linker was
attached. According to general procedures in Example 1, following protected amino
acids were coupled: Fmoc-Cha-OH, Fmoc-Ala(3-CN)-OH, Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH and
Alloc-Phe(4-CN)-OH. Mixture of pyridine/triethylamine (2:1) was saturated with H<sub>2</sub>S
(RT, 15-30min) and this solution added to the resin prewashed with
pyridine/triethylamine (2:1). After overnight standing, the resin was washed with
acetone and treated with solution of 20% methyliodide in acetone overnight. Resin
was then washed with acetone and methanol. The resin bound methylthioimidate is
then converted to amidine by 3 hour heating (waterbath, 55°C) of the resin with
solution of 10 eq of ammonium acetate in methanol containing 5% acetic acid. After
this final conversion, the resin was washed with methanol, DMF, DCM. The peptide 
was cleaved and deprotected by mixture TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 1 hour and
processed as described in Example 1. The crude compound was purified using
HPLC as described in Example 1 and characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 685.9,
calc. 686.4.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 11</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0073">To 0.125g of Rink resin (substitution 0.78mmol/g), after Fmoc-deprotection the
following protected amino acids were coupled according to general procedures
described in Example 1: Fmoc-Cha-OH, Fmoc-Asn-OH, Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH and
Alloc-pAph-OH. The peptide was cleaved and deprotected by mixture
TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 1 hour and processed as described in Example 1. The
crude compound was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and
characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 686.9, calc. 687.3</p><heading><u style="single">Example 12</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dab-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0074">To 0.25g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.26mmol/g), Knorr amide linker was
attached. According to general procedures in Example 1, following protected amino
acids were coupled: Fmoc-Cha-OH, Fmoc-Dab(Boc)-OH, Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH and
Alloc-pAph. The peptide was cleaved and deprotected by mixture TFA/thioanisole
(95/5) for 1 hour and processed as described in Example 1. The crude compound
was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and characterized by MS.
(M+H)+: found 673.2, calc. 673.4.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 13</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Ala(3-C(=NH)-NH<sub>2</sub>)-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0075">To 0.25g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.26mmol/g), Knorr amide linker was
attached. According to general procedures in Example 1, following protected amino
acids were coupled: Fmoc-Ala(3-CN)-OH, Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH and Alloc-Phe(4-CN)-OH.
Mixture of pyridine/triethylamine (2:1) was saturated with H<sub>2</sub>S (RT, 15-30min)
and this solution added to the resin prewashed with pyridine/triethylamine
(2:1). After overnight standing, resin is washed with acetone and treated with
solution of 20%methyliodide in acetone overnight. Resin was then washed with
acetone and methanol. The resin bound methylthioimidate is then converted to
amidine by 3 hour heating (waterbath, 55°C) of the resin with solution of 10 eq of
ammonium acetate in methanol containing 5% acetic acid. After this final conversion,
the resin was washed with methanol, DMF, DCM. The peptide was cleaved and
deprotected by mixture TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 1 hour and processed as
described in Example 1. The crude compound was purified using HPLC as described
in Example 1 and characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 533.3, calc. 533.2.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 14</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Gly-Cha-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0076">To 0.150g of Rink resin (substitution 0.78mmol/g), after Fmoc-deprotection, the
following protected amino acids were coupled according to general procedure,
described in Example 1: Fmoc-Cha-OH, Fmoc-Gly-OH, Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH and
Alloc-pAph-OH. The peptide was cleaved and deprotected by mixture
TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 1 hour and processed as described in Example 1. The
crude compound was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and
characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 630.1, calc. 630.3.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 15</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-Ph)Gly-NH<sub>2</sub></u></heading><p num="0077">For N-substituted glycines, the procedure of Zuckermann et al. (J. Am. Chem. Soc.
114:10646(1992), which is incorporated herein by reference) was used. </p><p num="0078">To 0.1g of Rink resin (substitution 0.78mmol/g), after Fmoc-deprotection,
bromoacetic acid was coupled via symmetrical anhydride in DCM/DMF. After 10
minutes, the resin was washed with DCM and the coupling repeated once more.
After washing with DCM and DMF, the resin was treated with 1M solution of
phenethyl amine in DMSO overnight. After DMF washing, the resin was reacted with
symmetrical anhydride of Fmoc-Asn(Trt)-OH in DCM/DMF.

After Fmoc-deprotection, according to general procedures in Example 1, following
protected amino acids were coupled: Fmoc-Glu(OtBu)-OH and Alloc-pAph-OH. The
peptide was cleaved and deprotected by mixture TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 1 hour
and processed as described in Example 1. The crude compound was purified using
HPLC as described in Example 1 and characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 694.9,
calc. 695.3</p><heading><u style="single">Example 16</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Thr(Bzl)-NH-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(Ph)<sub>2</sub></u></heading><heading>H-Thr(Bzl)-NH-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(Ph)<sub>2</sub> · HCl</heading><p num="0079">0.62g (2 mmol) of Boc-Thr(Bzl)-OH were dissolved in 10 ml DCM, 2 mmol of
triethylamine were added and the solution was cooled to 0°C. With stirring, 2 mmol
of isobutylchloroformate were slowly added. With cooling bath removed, the solution
was stirred for 15 minutes and 2.5 mmol of 3,3-diphenylpropyl amine in 2 ml of DMF
were added and stirred at room temperature for 1 hour. The solution was
evaporated, dissolved in ethylacetate and extracted with 0.5M KHSO<sub>4</sub>, sat. NaHCO<sub>3</sub>,
brine, dried with MgSO<sub>4</sub> and evaporated. The oily product was dissolved in 10 ml
DCM and 10 ml of 4M solution of hydrochloric acid in dioxane were added. After 10
minutes, solvents were evaporated, the product hydrochloride precipitated with
diethyl ether, filtered off, washed with diethyl ether and dried in vacuum. White solid,
MS analysis: (M+H)+: found 403.1, calc. 403.2.</p><heading>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Thr(Bzl)-NH-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(Ph)<sub>2</sub></heading><p num="0080">To 0.5g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.26mmol/g), 4-hydroxymethylphenoxyacetic
acid was attached (3eq activated with DIC/HOBt for
1.5h). Fmoc-Glu(OH)-OAllyl was attached to the resin via side chain using
DIC/HOBt/NMI in DMF overnight. Allyl protecting group was removed by shaking the
resin Pd(PPh<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub> (in DMF/AcOH/NMM (10/2/1) for 4h under argon. The deprotected
carboxy group was activated with a solution of 0.5mmol BOP, 0.5mmol HOBt,
1.5mmol DIEA and 0.5mmol of of H-Thr(Bzl)-NH-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(Ph)<sub>2</sub> · HCl in 1.5ml
DMF for 2 hours. After Fmoc deprotection, Alloc-pAph-OH was coupled according to
general procedure in Example 1. The peptide was cleaved and deprotected by
mixture TFA/thioanisole (95/5) for 1.5 hour and processed as described in Example
1. The crude compound was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and
characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 805.0, calc. 805.4.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 17</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dab-NH-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-Ph</u></heading><p num="0081">To 0.2g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.26mmol/g), 4-hydroxymethylphenoxyacetic
acid was attached (2.5eq activated with DIC/HOBt for
4h). The hydroxy group was substituted with bromine by treatment of the resin with
CBr<sub>4</sub> (5eq)/PPh<sub>3</sub> (5eq) in DCM for 4h. The bromine derivatized resin was treated with
2M solution of phenethylamine in DCM overnight.

Fmoc Dab(Boc)-OH was coupled to the resin using TFFH/DIEA (acyl fluoride
generated in situ). According to general procedure in Example 1, following protected
amino acids were coupled: Fmoc-Glu(OtBu) and Alloc-pAph-OH. The peptide was
cleaved and deprotected with TFA/triisopropylsilane (99/1) for 2h. TFA was
evaporated, the peptide was dissolved in H<sub>2</sub>O/ACN and lyophilized. The crude
material was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1 and characterized by
MS. (M+H)+ : found 624.2, calc. 624.3.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 18</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-NH-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-CN</u></heading><p num="0082">To 0.2g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> resin (substitution 0.26mmol/g), 4-hydroxymethylphenoxyacetic
acid was attached (3eq activated with DIC/HOBt for
1.5h). Fmoc-Glu(OH)-OAllyl was attached to the resin via side chain using
DIC/HOBt/NMI in DMF overnight. Allyl protecting group was removed by shaking the
resin with Pd(PPh<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub> in DMF/AcOH/NMM (10/2/1) for 4h under argon. The
deprotected carboxy group was activated with DIC (3eq)/HOBt (3eq) for 10min and
2-cyanoethylamine (3eq) in DMF was added to the resin for 3h. After Fmoc
deprotection, Alloc-pAph-OH was coupled according to general procedure in
Example 1. The peptide was cleaved and deprotected with TFA/triisopropylsilane
(99/1) for 2h. TFA was evaporated, the peptide was dissolved in H<sub>2</sub>O/ACN and
lyophilized. The crude material was purified using HPLC as described in Example 1
and characterized by MS. (M+H)+: found 473.1, calc. 473.2.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 19</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-NH-CH<sub>2</sub>-Chx</u></heading><p num="0083">To 0.1g of TentaGel S NH<sub>2</sub> (substitution 0.26mmol/g) Knorr amide linker was
attached. Fmoc-Asp(OH)-OAllyl was coupled to the linker via side chain and allyl
protecting group was removed as in Example 18. The deprotected carboxy group
was activated with DIC(5eq)/HOBt(5eq) and cyclohexylmethylamine (5eq) in DMF
was added for 2.5h. After Fmoc deprotection, Alloc-pAph-OH was coupled according
to general procedure in Example 1. The peptide was cleaved and deprotected with
TFA/triisopropylsilane (99/1) for 2h. TFA was evaporated, the peptide was dissolved
in H<sub>2</sub>O/ACN and lyophilized. The crude material was purified using HPLC as
described in Example 1 and characterized by MS. (M+H)+ : found 629.9, calc. 630.3.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 20</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-NH-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-Ph</u></heading><heading>2-(S)-[2-(S)-Allyloxycarbonylamino-3-(4-carbamimidoyl-phenyl)-propionylamino]-pentanedioic
acid 5-tert-butyl ester 1-methyl ester; hydrochloride</heading><p num="0084">To 2-(S)-allyloxycarbonylamino-3-(4-carbamimidoyl-phenyl)-propionic acid;
hydrochloride (3.48 g, 10.6 mmol) and 2-(S)-amino-pentanedioic acid 5-tert-butyl
ester 1-methyl ester; hydrochloride (2.7 g, 10.6 mmol) in 20 ml of DMF were added
at -15°C TOTU (3.83 g, 11.67 mmol) and N-ethylmorpholine (2.7 ml, 21.2 mmol).
The mixture was stirred for 1 hour and then allowed to warm to room temperature.
After evaporation ethyl acetate was added to the residue and the organic layer was
extracted with aqueous sodium hydrogen carbonate solution, potassium hydrogen
sulfate solution and water. The organic layer was evaporated. Yield: 2.8 g; (50%),
MS 491.3 (M + H)+.</p><heading>2-(S)-[2-(S)-Allyloxycarbonylamino-3-(4-carbamimidoyl-phenyl)-propionylamino]-pentanedioic
acid 5-tert-butyl ester</heading><p num="0085">To 2-(S)-[2-(S)-Allyloxycarbonylamino-3-(4-carbamimidoyl-phenyl)-propionylamino]-pentanedioic
acid 5-tert-butyl ester 1-methyl ester; hydrochloride (3.06 g, 5.8 mmol)
in 100 ml of water and 30 ml of THF was added lithium hydroxide hydrate (0.49 g,
11.6 mmol). The solution was stirred at room temperature for 12 hours, evaporated
and freeze-dried. The residue was purified by chromatography on Sephadex LH20
employing n-butanol (17): glacial acetic acid (1): water (2) as eluent. Pure fractions
were combined. The solvent was evaporated, the residue was taken up in water and
the aqueous solution was freeze-dried. Yield: 2.7 g; (97%), MS 477.4 (M + H)+.</p><heading>4-(S)-[2-(S)-Allyloxycarbonylamino-3-(4-carbamimidoyl-phenyl)-propionylamino]-4-(2-carbamoyl-1-(S)-(2-phenylethylcarbamoyl)-ethylcarbamoyl)-butyric
acid;
hydrochloride

(Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-NH-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-Ph)</heading><p num="0086">To 2-(S)-[2-(S)-Allyloxycarbonylamino-3-(4-carbamimidoyl-phenyl)-propionylamino]-pentanedioic
acid 5-tert-butyl ester (48 mg, 0.1 mmol) and 2-(S)-Amino-N1-phenethyl-succinamide;
hydrochloride (27 mg, 0.1 mmol) in 5 ml of DMF were added
at 0°C HATU (39 mg, 0.1 mmol) and collidine (24.2 mg, 0.2 mmol). The mixture was
stirred for 1 hour and then allowed to warm to room temperature. After evaporation
the residue was purified by chromatography on Sephadex LH20 employing n-butanol
(17): glacial acetic acid (1): water (2) as eluent. Pure fractions were combined. The
solvent was evaporated, the residue was taken up in water and the aequous solution
was freeze-dried. Yield: 45 mg; (66%), MS 638.4 (M + H)+.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 21</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-NH-(3-chlorobenzyl)</u></heading><p num="0087">To 2-(S)-[2-(S)-Allyloxycarbonylamino-3-(4-carbamimidoyl-phenyl)-propionylamino]-pentanedicic
acid 5- tert-butyl ester (50 mg, 0.105 mmol) and 2-(S)-Amino-N1-(3-chlorobenzyl)-succinamide;
trifluoroacetate (61mg, 0.16 mmol) in 5 ml of DMF were
added at 0°C TOTU (36 mg, 0.11 mmol) and N-ethylmorpholine (57 µl, 0.4 mmol).
The mixture was stirred for 1 hour and then allowed to warm to room temperature.
After evaporation the residue was purified by chromatography on Sephadex LH20
employing n-butanol (17): glacial acetic acid (1): water (2) as eluent. Pure fractions
were combined. The solvent was evaporated, the residue was taken up in water and
the aequous solution was freeze-dried. Yield of 4-(S)-[2-(S)-allyloxycarbonylamino-3-(4-carbamimidoyl-phenyl)-propionylamino]-4-(2-carbamoyl-1-(S)-(3-chlorobenzylcarbamoyl)-ethylcarbamoyl)-butyric acid (Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-NH-(3-chlorobenzyl):
28 mg; (41%), MS m/z 658.3 (M + H)<sup>+</sup>.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 22</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Determination of Ki for FVIIa inhibitor</u></heading><p num="0088">The inhibitory activity (Ki) of each compound towards factor VIIa/tissue factor activity
was determined using a chromogenic assay esentially as described previously 
(Ostrem J A, Al-Obeidi F, Safar P, Safarova A, Stringer S K, Patek M, Cross M T,
Spoonamore J, LoCascio J C, Kasireddy P, Thorpe D S, Sepetov N, Lebi M,
Wildgoose P, Strop P, Discovery of a novel, potent, and specific family of factor Xa
inhibitors via combinatorial chemistry. Biochemistry 1998,37,1053-1059). Kinetic
assays were conducted at 25 °C in half-area microtiter plates (Costar Corp.,
Cambridge, MA) using a kinetic plate reader (Molecular devices Spectramax 250). A
typical assay consisted of 25 µl human factor VIIa and TF (5 nM and 10 nM,
respective final concentration) combined with 40 µl of inhibitor dilutions in 10%
DMSO/TBS-PEG buffer ( 50 mM Tris, 15mM NaCl, 5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>; 0.05% PEG 8k pH
8.15). Following a 15 minute preincubation period, the assay was initiated by the
addition of 35 µl of the chromogenic substrate S-2288 (D-Ile-Pro-Arg-pNA,
Pharmacia Hepar Inc, 500 µM final concentration.). The apparent inhibition
constants were calculated from the slope of the progress curves during the linear
part of the time course, typically between 1 and 5 min following addition of substrate
to the assay. The true Ki was subsequently determined for each compound by
correcting for subtrate concentration (S) and the Km using the formula <st32:f xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">Ki= Ki app/ (1
+ (Ss)/Km)</st32:f> (Segal IH (1975) Enzyme Kinetics, John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, New
York, pp 100-125)</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A compound of the formula I
R1-A-B-D-En-R2
wherein
<claim-text><claim-text>R1 represents
<claim-text><claim-text>hydrogen,</claim-text><claim-text>1 to 3 amino acids, the N-terminus of which can be substituted with a
substituent selected from the group consisting of R14CO, R15SO2 and
an amino protecting group,</claim-text><claim-text>R12C(O) or</claim-text><claim-text>R13,
wherein
R12is selected from the group consisting of alkyl, alkenyl, alkynyl,
alkoxy, alkylamino, alkenylamino, alkynylamino, alkenyloxy,
alkynyloxy, aryl, heteroaryl, heterocycloalkyl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkylalkyl, heteroalkyl, heteroalkenyl and
heteroalkynyl, which radicals can be substituted,R13is selected from the group consisting of an amino protecting
group, hydrogen, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,R14 and R15are independently selected from the group consisting of
alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl, heterocycloalkyl
and heterocycloalkylalkyl,</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>A is the group A1-A2-A3, whereinA1is NR91, wherein R91 is selected from the group consisting of
hydrogen, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,A2is CR92R93, wherein R92 and R93 independently are selected
from the group consisting of hydrogen and the radicals alkyl,
aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl, heterocycloalkyl and
heterocycloalkylalkyl, which may be substituted,A3is C(O),</claim-text><claim-text>B is the group B1-B2-B3, wherein
B1is NR95, wherein R95 is selected from the group consisting of
hydrogen, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,B2is CR96R97, wherein R96 and R97 are independently selected
from the group consisting of hydrogen and the unsubstituted or
substituted radicals alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl,
heteroarylalkyl, heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,B3is C(O),</claim-text><claim-text>D is the group D1-D2-D3, wherein
D1is NR80, wherein R80 is selected from the group consisting of
hydrogen, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,D2is CR81R82, wherein R81 and R82 are independently selected
from the group consisting of hydrogen and unsubstituted or
substituted alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,D3is C(O),</claim-text><claim-text>En is (E1-E2-E3)n, wherein
<claim-text><claim-text>n is an integer of from 0 to 3,</claim-text></claim-text>E1is NR70, wherein R70 is selected from the group consisting of
hydrogen, alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,E2is CR71R72, wherein R71 and R72 are independently selected
from the group consisting of hydrogen and unsubstituted or
substituted alkyl, aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl,
heterocycloalkyl and heterocycloalkylalkyl,E3is C(O),R2is selected from the group consisting of NR21R22, OR23 and R24,
wherein R21, R22, R23 and R24 are independently selected from the
group consisting of hydrogen and unsubstituted or substituted alkyl,
aryl, arylalkyl, heteroaryl, heteroarylalkyl, heterocycloalkyl and
heterocycloalkylalkyl,
and pharmaceutically acceptable salts thereof.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The compound of claim 1, wherein the radicals of R12 can be substituted with
a substituent selected from the group consisting of halogen, CF3, hydroxy,
nitro, amino, cyano, carboxy, aminocarbonyl, alkylsulfonyl, aminosulfonyl,
alkoxy, alkylcarbonylamino and mono- or di-alkylamino.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The compound of claim 1, wherein R92 and R93 independently are selected
from the group consisting of alkyl, phenyl, phenylalkyl and pyridylalkyl, which
can be substituted with a substituent selected from the group consisting of
alkyl, alkoxy, alkylamino, dialkylamino, tetraalkylammonium, aminoalkylaryl,
aminoarylalkyl, hydroxycarbonyl, halogen, hydroxy, amino, aminocarbonyl,
amidoxime, acylimido, amidino, guanidino, alkoxycarbonylamino,
alkoxycarbonylamidino, alkoxycarbonylguanidino, triazolyl and alkylsulfonyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The compound of claim 1, wherein the radicals of R96 and R97 can be
substituted with a substituent selected from the group consisting of
hydroxycarbonyl, aminocarbonyl, alkylated aminocarbonyl, alkoxycarbonyl,
tetrazol, hydroxysulfonyl, aminosulfonyl and phosphonic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The compound of claim 1, wherein the radicals of R81 and R82 can
independently be substituted with a substituent selected from the group
consisting of amino, aminocarbonyl, amidino, guanido, aminoalkyl, hydroxy,
mercapto, which can be substituted with a protecting group, and acetimido,
nitro and cyano.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The compound of claim 1, wherein the radicals of R71 and R72 can
independently be substituted with a substituent selected from the group
consisting of alkyl, alkoxy, halogen, CF3, nitro, cyano, alkylsulfonyl and
alkylcarbonyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The compound of claim 1, wherein the radicals of R21, R22, R23 and R24 can
independently be substituted with halogen, CF3, hydrogen, nitro, cyano,
alkoxy, alkylsulfonyl, aminosulfonyl and =O.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The compound of claim 1, wherein the mentioned linear or branched alkyl
chains have 1 to 6 carbon atoms, the unsaturated linear or branched alkenyl
and alkynyl chains have 2 to 6 carbon atoms, the cyclic alkyl groups have 3 to
8 carbon atoms, the heterocycloalkyl groups have 3 to 8 carbon atoms of
which 1 to 3 are replaced with N, O or S atoms, and the aryl groups have 5 to
13 carbon atoms.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The compound of claim 1, wherein
<claim-text><claim-text>R1 is R12CO, wherein R12 is as defined,</claim-text><claim-text>A is A1-A2-A3, wherein
<claim-text><claim-text>A1 is -NH-,</claim-text><claim-text>A2 is -CR92R93-, wherein R92 is hydrogen and R93 is as defined,</claim-text><claim-text>A3 is -CO-,</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>B is B1-B2-B3, wherein
<claim-text><claim-text>B1 is -NH-,</claim-text><claim-text>B2 is -CR96R97-, wherein R96 is hydrogen and R97 is as defined,</claim-text><claim-text>B3 is -CO-,</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>D is D1-D2-D3, wherein
<claim-text><claim-text>D1 is-NH-,</claim-text><claim-text>D2 is -CR81R82-, wherein R81 is hydrogen and R82 is as defined,</claim-text><claim-text>D3 is -CO-,</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>En is (E1-E2-E3)n, wherein
<claim-text><claim-text>n is 1 or 2,</claim-text><claim-text>E1 is -NH-,</claim-text><claim-text>E2 is -CR71R72-, wherein R71 is hydrogen and R72 is as defined,</claim-text><claim-text>E3 is -CO-, and</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>R2 is as defined.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The compound of claim 9, wherein n is 1 and R2 is NHR22, wherein R22 is as
defined.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The compound of claim 10, wherein R1 is allyloxycarbonyl or
allylaminocarbonyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The compound of claim 10, wherein A represents (L)-4-amidinophenylalanine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The compound of claim 10, wherein B represents (L)-glutamic acid, an (L)-glutamic
acid ester, or a pharmaceutically acceptable salt of (L)-glutamic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The compound of claim 10, wherein D represents a residue selected from the
group consisting of Arg, Dap, Dab, Orn, Lys, Dap[-C(=NH)-NH2],
Dab[-C(=NH)-NH2], Lys[-C(=NH)-NH2], Asn, Ser, Thr, Ser(Bzl), Arg(NO2), Trp,
Phg, Ala, Val, Ile, Leu, Phe, 2-Abu, Ala(3-CN), Ala(3-amidino), 2-Abu(4-CN),
2-Abu(4-amidino).</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The compound of claim 10, wherein E represents a residue selected from the
group consisting of Cha, Chg, Phe[4-C(-S-CH2-CH2-S-)-Ph].</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The compound of claim 10, wherein R22 represents a radical selected from
the group consisting of hydrogen, benzyl, phenethyl, 3-phenylpropyl,
fluorenyl, diphenylmethyl, diphenylethyl, diphenylpropyl, which radicals may
be substituted with a substituent selected from the group consisting of F, Cl,
Br, hydroxy, methoxy, nitro, cyano, alkylsulfonyl, aminosulfonyl, and
trifluoromethyl, which can be further substituted.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The compound of claim 10, wherein
R1is allyloxycarbonyl or allylaminocarbonyl,A is(L)-4-amidinophenylalanine,B isselected from the group consisting of glutamic acid, glutamic acid ester
and a pharmaceutically acceptable salt of glutamic acid,D isa residue selected from the group consisting of Arg, Dap, Dab, Orn,
Lys, Dap[-C(=NH)-NH2], Dab[-C(=NH)-NH2], Lys[-C(=NH)-NH2], Asn,
Ser, Thr, Ser(Bzl), Arg(NO2), Trp, Phg, Ala, Val, Ile, Leu, Phe, 2-Abu,
Ala(3-CN), Ala(3-amidino), 2-Abu(4-CN), 2-Abu(4-amidino),E isa residue selected from the group consisting of Cha, Chg and Phe[4-C(-S-CH2-CH2-S-)-Ph],R22is hydrogen or a radical selected from the group consisting of benzyl,
phenethyl, 3-phenylpropyl, fluorenyl, diphenylmethyl, diphenylethyl and
diphenylpropyl, which radicals may be substituted with a substituent
selected from the group consisting of F, Cl, Br, hydroxy, methoxy, nitro,
cyano, alkylsulfonyl, aminosulfonyl and trifluoromethyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The compound of claim 10, which is
<claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Arg-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Allylaminocarbonyl-pAph-Glu-Arg-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Arg-Chg-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dap[-C(=NH)-NH2]-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Ala[3-C(=NH)-NH2]-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dab-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dap[-C(=NH)-NH2]-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Gly-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Thr(Bzl)-NH-(CH2)2-CH(Ph)2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dab-NH-CH2-CH2-phenyl,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-NH-CH2-Chx,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-2-Abu[4-C(=NH)-CH3]-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dap[-C(=NH)-CH3]-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Dab[-C(=NH)-NH2]-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-2-Abu[4-CN]-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Ala[3-CN]-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(1-naphthyl)-methylamide,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(1-naphthyl)-1-ethylamide,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(2-naphthyl)-methylamide,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(3,4-dichlorobenzyl)-amide,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-2-(3-chlorophenyl)-ethylamide,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Arg[NO2]-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Cys[Bzl]-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Trp-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Phg-Cha-NH2,</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(9-fluorenyl)-amide, or</claim-text><claim-text>Alloc-pAph-Glu-Asn-(3,5-ditrifluormethylbenzyl)-amide,</claim-text></claim-text>
and pharmaceutically acceptable salts, amides, esters thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A process for the preparation of a compound as defined in claim 1, which
comprises
<claim-text><claim-text>a1) attaching a compound of the formula Fmoc-En-OH or Fmoc-D1-D2-COOH,
where Fmoc is 9-fluorenylmethoxycarbonyl and En, D1 and D2 are defined
as in claim 1, to an acid sensitive linker coupled to a solid support, and
cleaving off the protecting group Fmoc,</claim-text><claim-text>a2) repeating the procedure as described in step a1) above with Fmoc-B1-B2-COOH,</claim-text><claim-text>a3) repeating the procedure as described in step a1) above with R1-A1-A2-COOH,
and</claim-text><claim-text>a4) finally cleaving off the compound obtained according to steps a1) through
a3) above by means of TFA from the resin, where TFA is trifluoroacetic
acid,
or</claim-text><claim-text>b1) coupling the side chain carboxylic acid of Fmoc-B1-CH(R97)-COOPG,
where Fmoc is as defined in step a1) above, R97 is a radical as defined in
claim 1 except hydrogen, which is substituted with a hydroxycarbonyl
group, and PG is a protecting group, to an acid sensitive benzylalcohol
type of linker attached to an amino functionalized resin,</claim-text><claim-text>b2) cleaving off the protecting group PG,</claim-text><claim-text>b3) coupling HN(R80)-D2-D3-En-R2, where D2, D3, En, R2 and R80 are as
defined in claim 1, to the free carboxylic acid of the compound obtained in
step b2) above by means of a suitable coupling agent,</claim-text><claim-text>b4) cleaving off the Fmoc group,</claim-text><claim-text>b5) coupling of the compound R1-A1-A2-COOH in analogy to the above
described procedure, and</claim-text><claim-text>b6) cleaving off the compound obtained in step b5) by means of TFA,
or</claim-text><claim-text>c1) coupling of protected amino acids by traditional medicinal chemistry and
deprotecting to the target molecules by standard procedures known in the
art.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>A pharmaceutical composition having factor VIIa inhibiting activity, which
comprises an effective amount of a compound as defined in claim 1 or a
pharmaceutically acceptable salt thereof, and a suitable carrier therefor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>A method of reducing or inhibiting blood clotting, inflammatory response or
vascular restenosis in a patient in need thereof which comprises
administering to a patient an effective amount of a compound as defined in
claim 1, or a pharmaceutically acceptable salt thereof</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>Use of a compound as defined in claim 1 or a pharmaceutically acceptable
salt thereof, for the preparation of a medicament having blood clotting,
inflammatory response or vascular restenosis reducing or inhibiting activity.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="155" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="243" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="155" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="242" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90020001" orientation="portrait" wi="155" status="new" file="90020001.tif" he="238" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90030001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90030001.tif" he="238" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90040001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90040001.tif" he="238" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>