<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1065290-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1065290" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26503961" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010103"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1065290-A1" status="new" fvid="23027797"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1065290</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010103</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00401832-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00401832</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000627</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-18676999-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>18676999</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990630</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-21151999-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>21151999</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990727</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  19/03        20060101AFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  19/03        20060101CFI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  19/05        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  19/05        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22C  19/05P4</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22C  19/05P5</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Hitzebeständige Nickelbasislegierung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Heat resistant nickel base alloy</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Alliage à base de nickel résistant à la chaleur</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="JP-5239577-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>5239577</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-54014311-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>54014311</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-55082738-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>55082738</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-2515185-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>2515185</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4671931-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4671931</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1995027803-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1995027803</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 198211 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class M27, AN 1982-20871E XP002148828 &amp; JP 57 023050 A (SUMITOMO CHEM CO LTD), 6 February 1982 (1982-02-06)</text><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 003, no. 037 (C-041), 29 March 1979 (1979-03-29) -&amp; JP 54 014311 A (MITSUBISHI METAL CORP), 2 February 1979 (1979-02-02)</text><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 004, no. 129 (C-024), 10 September 1980 (1980-09-10) -&amp; JP 55 082738 A (HITACHI LTD), 21 June 1980 (1980-06-21)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 017, no. 704 (C-1146), 22 December 1993 (1993-12-22) -&amp; JP 05 239577 A (SUMITOMO METAL IND LTD), 17 September 1993 (1993-09-17)</text><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>RYBNIKOV A I ET AL: "Service life of heat-resistant alloys with protective coatings in thermocyclic loading" SURFACE AND COATINGS TECHNOLOGY, JAN. 1996, ELSEVIER, SWITZERLAND, vol. 78, no. 1-3, pages 103-112, XP000940850 ISSN: 0257-8972</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SUMITOMO METAL IND</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SUMITOMO METAL INDUSTRIES, LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SUMITOMO METAL INDUSTRIES, LTD.</last-name><address><street>5-33, Kitahama 4-chome, Chuo-ku</street><city>Osaka-shi, Osaka 541-0041</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ANRAKU TOSHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NISHIYAMA YOSHITAKA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OGAWA KAZUHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OKADA HIROKAZU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SAWARAGI YOSHIATSU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ANRAKU, TOSHIRO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NISHIYAMA, YOSHITAKA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OGAWA, KAZUHIRO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OKADA, HIROKAZU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SAWARAGI, YOSHIATSU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ANRAKU, TOSHIRO</last-name><address><street>6-10-404, Aokicho</street><city>Nishinomiya-shi, Hyogo 662-0862</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NISHIYAMA, YOSHITAKA</last-name><address><street>2-3-506, Koshien-Abikicho</street><city>Nishinomiya-shi, Hyogo 663-8156</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OGAWA, KAZUHIRO</last-name><address><street>2-57, Uegahara 7-bancho</street><city>Nishinomiya-shi, Hyogo 662-0881</city><country>JP</country> </address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OKADA, HIROKAZU</last-name><address><street>5-2-12-904, Fujiwaradai-Kitamachi, Kita-ku</street> <city>Kobe-shi, Hyogo 651-1301</city> <country>JP</country> </address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SAWARAGI, YOSHIATSU</last-name><address><street>26-2, Tendocho</street><city>Nishinomiya-shi, Hyogo 663-8104</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Uchida, Kenji</last-name><address><street>S.A. Fedit-Loriot et Autres Conseils en Propriété Industrielle, 38, avenue Hoche</street><city>75008 Paris</city><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>BE</country><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A heat resistant Ni base alloy comprises, on a mass% basis, 0.1% or
less C, 2% or less Si, 2% or less Mn, 0.005% or less S, 10 to 25% Cr, 2.1 to
less than 4.5% Al, 0.08% or less N, 0.001 to 1% in total of one or more
elements of B: 0.03% or less, Zr: 0.2% or less and Hf: 0.8% or less, and 2.5 to
15% in total of one or more elements of Mo: 0.01 to 15% and W: 0.01 to 9%.
The alloy is suitable as a material for a pipe used in ethylene cracking
furnace.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>TECHNICAL FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a heat resistant Ni base alloy
having high strength at high temperature and excellent in hot workability,
weldability, and carburization resistance. The alloy of the present
invention is suitable in particular as a material of pipes used in naphtha
reforming furnaces and ethylene cracking furnaces for producing
petrochemical fundamental products such as ethylene and propylene by
cracking with steam hydrocarbon materials such as naphtha, propane,
ethane, and gas oil at a high temperature of 800°C or more.</p><heading>RELATED BACKGROUND ART</heading><p num="0002">The service temperature of the pipes used in ethylene cracking
furnaces tends to be higher from the viewpoint of improving an ethylene
yield ratio.</p><p num="0003">Materials of such cracking furnace pipes require high-temperature
strength, carburization resistance and heat resistance because their inside
is exposed to a carburization atmosphere.</p><p num="0004">On the other hand, carbon is deposited on the inside surface of a
cracking furnace pipe during the operation (this phenomenon is called
coking), and as the amount of carbon deposited on the inside of the pipe
increases, disadvantages in operation occur, such as an increase in the
internal pressure of the pipe and a reduction in the heating efficiency.
Therefor, coking resistance is required. In the actual operation, the so-called
decoking operation for removing deposited carbon by air or steam is
periodically conducted, but the suspension of the operation and the working 
load are great problems.</p><p num="0005">Such coking and its related problems are more serious when the
cracking furnace pipe has a smaller diameter which is advantageous for
improving the yield.</p><p num="0006">JP Publication No.A 2-8336 discloses the technique of inhibiting
coking in which more than 28% Cr is contained in an alloy to form a strong
and stable Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer on the surface of the alloy in order to prevent the
coking-promoting catalytic elements of Fe and Ni from being exposed to the
surface of the alloy.</p><p num="0007">On the other hand, increasing of the Si content in an alloy is known
to be effective for improving carburization resistance, as disclosed in e.g. JP
Publication No. A 57-23050.</p><p num="0008">In the prior art described above, however, there are problems as
follows:</p><p num="0009">When the high-Cr alloy disclosed in JP Publication No. A 2-8336 is
applied as a structural member with high-temperature strength for the
prevention of coking, the metal structure should be austenitized by
increasing the Ni content in the alloy, but, as the result, its high-temperature
strength becomes lower than that of the conventional alloy.
Therefore, the application thereof as a structural member with high-temperature
strength is difficult.</p><p num="0010">JP Publication No. A 2-8336 discloses that an alloy poor in high-temperature
strength is combined for use with another member with high-temperature
strength to form a cladded tube, but the cladded tube is
problematic in respect to the production cost and reliability.</p><p num="0011">The present inventors found previously that the carburization
resistance and coking resistance can be significantly improved by forming a 
strong and tight Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> layer on the surface of a metal by increasing the
content ofAl in an alloy, compared with the conventional alloy, and the γ'
phase is finely precipitated in the matrix during the service at high
temperature by increasing the content of Ni in such a high-Al alloy, and the
creep rupture strength can also be significantly improved. The patent for
this alloy was applied as a Ni base alloy suitable as a pipe in an ethylene
cracking furnace in Japanese Patent Application No. 3-308709 (Publication
No. A4-358037) and Japanese Patent Application No. 4-41402 (Publication
No. A5-239577) respectively. However, in consideration of mass production
on a commercial scale, an large amount of hot working was required for the
production of the Ni base alloy with high-Al but the hot workability of such
alloy was not satisfactory.</p><p num="0012">With respect to the Ni base alloy with an increased content ofAl,
alloys excellent in oxidation resistance are disclosed in JP Publication No. B
3-46535 and A 60-238434. However, the alloys disclosed in these
publications are also poor in hot workability and weldability, because
adequate attention was not paid to these characteristics on the design of
alloying components. Further, alloys excellent in carburization resistance
and high-temperature strength are also disclosed in JP Publication No. A
7-54087 and A 9-243284, but attention was not actually paid to hot
workability and weldability.</p><heading>DISCLOSURE OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0013">The object of the present invention is to provide a heat resistant
alloy which is excellent in carburization resistance and coking resistance
under the environment where ethylene cracking furnace pipes are used,
more specifically, carburization, oxidation and temperature change are 
repeated; and also which is excellent in hot workability and weldability and
has excellent high-temperature strength.</p><p num="0014">The summary of the present invention is as follows:
<sl><li>(1) A heat resistant Ni base alloy excellent in hot workability,
weldability, and carburization resistance comprising, on a mass% basis, C:
0.1% or less, Si: 2% or less, Mn: 2% or less, S: 0.005% or less, Cr: 10 to 25%,
Al: 2.1 to less than 4.5%, N: 0.08% or less, 0.001 to 1% in total of one or more
elements of B: 0.03% or less, Zr: 0.2% or less and Hf: 0.8% or less, 2.5 to 15%
in total of either one or both of Mo: 0.01 to 15% and W: 0.01 to 9%, Ti: 0 to
3%, Mg: 0 to 0.01%, Ca: 0 to 0.01%, Fe: 0 to 10%, Nb: 0 to 1%, V: 0 to 1%, Ta:
0 to 2%, Y: 0 to 0.1%, La: 0 to 0.1%, Ce: 0 to 0.1%, Nd: 0 to 0,1%, Cu: 0 to 5%,
Co: 0 to 10%, and the balance being substantially Ni.</li><li>(2) The heat resistant Ni base alloy according to above (1), wherein
the Ti content is 0.005 to 3% by mass.</li><li>(3) The heat resistant Ni base alloy according to above (1), wherein
the Ti content is 0.005 to 3% and either one or both of Mg and Ca are
contained in an amount of 0.0005 to 0.01% and 0.0005 to 0.01%,
respectively.</li><li>(4) The heat resistant Ni base alloy according to above (1), wherein
the Ti content is 0.005 to 3%, either one or both of Mg and Ca are contained
in an amount of 0.0005 to 0.01% and 0.0005 to 0.01%, respectively, and Fe
content is 0.1 to 10%.</li><li>(5) A heat resistant Ni base alloy comprising, on a mass% basis, C:
0.07% or less, Si: 0.01 to 1%, Mn: 1% or less, S: 0.0025% or less, Cr: 12 to
19%, Al: 2.1 to less than 3.8%, N: 0.045% or less, 0.001 to 1% in total of one
or more elements of B: 0.03% or less, Zr: 0.2% or less and Hf: 0.8% or less,
Mo: 2.5 to 12%, Ti: 0.005 to 1%, Ca: 0.0005 to 0.01%, Fe: 0.1 to 10%, and the 
balance being essentially Ni.</li></sl></p><p num="0015">In order to obtain the alloy which satisfies the essential
characteristics required as a commercial production alloy such as hot
workability and weldability without lowering carburization resistance and
coking resistance at high temperatures, the present inventors carried out
extensive experiments on alloys with various chemical compositions and
reached the following findings as a result.
<sl><li>a) Even if the Ni base alloy does not contain Al in an amount of 4.5%
or more unlike the conventional alloy, an alumina-based oxide layer can be
formed on the surface of the alloy contenting less than 4.5% Al by means of
containing not less than 10% Cr and reducing the N content, whereby
excellent carburization resistance and coking resistance can be attained and
also high-temperature strength is improved.</li><li>b) The N in an alloy containing not less than 1% Al easily forms Al
nitride, and the alumina-based oxide layer tends to lose its protective
property from this nitride precipitation which acts as the initiation point.</li><li>c) By reducing the Al content to less than 4.5%, hot workability and
weldability of the Ni base alloy containing Al are improved, but compared
with conventional Fe-Cr-Ni alloys or Ni-Cr alloys, are still unsatisfactory in
consideration of mass production. This is because Ni-Al intermetallic
compounds precipitate at the time of hot working or welding, and the inside
of the grains of the alloy are significantly reinforced so that the grain
boundaries are relatively weakened, which result in both a reduction of hot
workability and an occurrence of a hot cracking at the time of welding.
Accordingly, the reinforcement of the grain boundaries which can compete
with the reinforcement of the inside of the grains is important and effective
for improving hot workability and weldability. </li><li>d) On the other hand, in the Ni base alloy containing a large amount
ofAl, the grain boundaries are weakened and S is one of the main factors in
weakening the grain boundaries. Therefore, it is important for improving
hot workability to limit the S content to 0.005% or less, and further
improving effects can be expected by limiting the S content to 0.003% or
less.</li><li>e) Further, the elements of B, Zr and Hf enhance the binding force of
grains on the grain boundaries and are effective for reinforcing the grain
boundaries. Therefore, it is preferable that one or more of these elements
are contained while the S content is reduced.</li><li>f) The reduction of S content as described above and the
incorporation of one or more elements of B, Zr and Hf are effective for
preventing the reduction of hot workability and the occurrence of hot
cracking at the time of welding, but these measures only are still not
satisfactory. Further, it is also important to reduce the N content to the
lowest degree. This is because the N in the Ni base alloy containing a
large amount of Al easily forms Al nitride as described above, and these
nitrides precipitation significantly inhibit hot workability and weldability.</li></sl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0016">The following describe the chemical composition of the alloy of the
present invention and its effects. The term "%" for alloying elements
means % by mass.</p><heading>C:</heading><p num="0017">C is a very effective element which forms carbides to improve tensile
strength and creep rupture strength required for heat-resistant steel.
However, if the C content exceeds 0.1%, the ductility and toughness of the </p><p num="0018">alloy are significantly lowered, and further the formation of an alumina
layer on the Al-containing Ni base alloy is inhibited, and thus the upper
limit is defined as 0.1%. The C content is preferably 0.09% or less. The C
content is more preferably 0.07% or less.</p><heading>Si:</heading><p num="0019">Si is an element which is important as a deoxidation element and
further contributes to improvements in oxidation resistance and
carburization resistance, but its effect on the Al-containing Ni base alloy is
relatively low. For the Ni base alloy containing a large amount of Al,
however, Si has a strong action of lowering hot workability and weldability,
and thus the Si content is preferably lower when particularly, hot
workability in manufacturing is regarded as important. However, in
consideration of the contribution of Si to oxidation resistance and
carburization resistance, the Si content must be 2% or less. Desirably, the
content of Si should be 0.01 to 1.5%, more desirably 0.01 to 1%.</p><heading>Mn:</heading><p num="0020">Mn is an effective element as a deoxidization element but is an
element promoting the formation of a spinel type oxide layer which is a
major factor for deterioration of coking resistance, and thus its content
should be reduced to 2% or less. Desirably, the content of Mn should be 1%
or less.</p><heading>S:</heading><p num="0021">S is a very harmful element which is segregated on grain boundaries
to weak the binding force of grains and to deteriorate hot workability, and
thus, the regulation of its content upper limit is very important. Since the
reinforcement of the grain boundaries is particularly important in the Al-containing
Ni base alloy, S is preferably reduced to the lowest degree. To 
improve hot workability and weldability, the S content should be 0.005% or
less. Desirably, the content of S should be 0.003% or less. More desirably,
the content of S should be 0.0025% or less.</p><heading>Cr:</heading><p num="0022">Cr is an effective element for improving oxidation resistance and
coking resistance, and has an action of forming an alumina layer uniformly
at an initial stage of its formation. Further, this element also forms
carbides which contribute to the improvement of creep rupture strength.
In addition, Cr contributes to the improvement of hot workability in the
alloying system defined in the present invention. To achieve these effects,
this element should be contained in an amount of 10% or more. On the
other hand, when Cr is contained in excess, the formation of a uniform
alumina layer is conversely inhibited, while mechanical properties such as
toughness and workability are further inhibited. Accordingly, the Cr
content is defined as 10 to 25%. Preferably, the content of Cr should be 12
to 23%. More preferably, the content of Cr should be 12 to less than 20%.</p><heading>Al:</heading><p num="0023">Al is a very effective element for improving carburization resistance
and coking resistance and further improving high-temperature strength.
To achieve these effects, a corundum type alumina scale must be uniformly
formed. On the other hand, a precipitation reinforcing action by forming
the γ' phase [Ni<sub>3</sub>(Al, Ti) intermetallic compound] can be expected. To
achieve these effects, an Al content of at least 1.5% is necessary. On the
other hand, if the Al content is 4.5% or more, hot workability is significantly
lowered. Accordingly, the Al content must be 2.1% or more to less than
4.5%. Preferably, the content of Al should be 2.1% to less than 4%, and
more preferably 2.1% to less than 3.8%. </p><heading>N:</heading><p num="0024">The N content is one of the essential prescriptions in the present
invention. In the conventional heat-resistant steel, N is effective and
positively used for increasing the high temperature strength due to the
solid-solution strengthening. However, in the Al-containing nickel base
alloy, N cannot be expected to attain the solid-solution strengthening
because of precipitation thereof as a nitride such as AlN in the alloy, and
this element further significantly reduces hot workability and weldability.
In addition, there is a problem that the protective layer is destroyed by the
nitride as the starting point, resulting in the deterioration of carburization
resistance. However, since an excessive reduction in the N content causes
an increase in costs for refining, the N content must be 0.08% or less.
However, this element should essentially be reduced to the lowest degree,
desirably 0.055% or less. More preferably, the content of N should be
0.045% or less.</p><heading>B, Zr, Hf:</heading><p num="0025">These elements are effective mainly for reinforcing grain boundaries
in the alloy and contribute to improvements in hot workability and
weldability, and thus one or more of these elements should be contained.
However, if these elements are contained in excess, a reduction in creep
rupture strength is caused, and thus the upper limits of these elements
must be 0.03% for B, 0.20% for Zr, and 0.8% for Hf respectively, and their
content in total must be 1%. Further, their content in total must be at
least 0.001% in order to achieve the effects described above.</p><heading>Mo, W:</heading><p num="0026">Mo and W are effective mainly as solid solution strengthening
elements, and by reinforcing the austenitic phase of the alloy, creep rupture 
strength is increased. If these elements are contained in excess, not only
intermetallic compounds leading to a reduction in toughness are
precipitated but carburization resistance and coking resistance are also
deteriorated. If these elements are contained, the upper limit in terms of
the total of one or more elements of Mo and W should be 15% or less.
Particularly, for application to members whose creep rupture strength is
regarded as important, it is effective to positively add Mo and W to
demonstrate this effect. As compared with Mo, W causes a more
significant reduction in hot workability and weldability due to the
precipitation of intermetallic compounds, and thus the upper limit of W
should be lower than that of Mo. Accordingly, the total content of Mo
and/or W must be 2.5 to 15% wherein the Mo content is 0.01 to 15% and the
W content is 0.01 to 9%.</p><heading>Ni:</heading><p num="0027">Ni is an indispensable element for achieving a stable austenitic
structure and for ensuring carburization resistance, and should be
contained desirably in a higher amount to increase the effect of
precipitation reinforcement particularly by the γ' phase.</p><p num="0028">To solve the problem of the present invention, the alloy should have
at least the chemical composition described above, but the following
elements may be contained as necessary.</p><heading>Ti:</heading><p num="0029">Ti is an element for promoting the precipitation of γ' phase to
improve creep rupture strength. Further, this element also contributes to
the reinforcement of grain boundaries. To achieve these effects, Ti is
contained preferably in an amount of 0.005% or more. However, if it is
contained in excess, the γ' phase is precipitated in excess, and thus, hot 
workability and weldability are significantly deteriorated. Accordingly, if
Ti is contained, the content of Ti should be 3% or less. Preferably, the
content of Ti should be 1% or less.</p><heading>Mg and Ca:</heading><p num="0030">These elements have an action of fixing a harmful S for hot
workability as sulfides, thus increasing the strength of grain boundaries
and improving hot workability, and therefore, these elements may be
contained as necessary. To achieve these effects, each of these elements
should be contained preferably in an amount of 0.0005% or more. However,
if they are contained in excess, hot workability and weldability are
conversely deteriorated. Accordingly, the upper limit for each of Mg and Ca
should be preferably 0.01%. If these elements are to be contained,
preferably, they should be contained, such that [(1.178 Mg + Ca)/S] is in the
range of 0.5 to 3.</p><heading>Fe:</heading><p num="0031">Fe improves creep elongation, increases creep rupture strength, and
contributes to improvements in hot workability and workability at normal
temperature. To achieve these effects, this element should be contained
preferably in an amount of 0.1% or more. However, if it is contained in
excess, both creep rupture strength and hot workability are lowered
conversely, and thus, when it is to be contained, preferably, its content
upper limit should be 10%.</p><heading>Nb, V and Ta:</heading><p num="0032">These elements contribute to the improvement of creep rupture
strength as carbides and nitrides or as solid solutions in the austenitic
phase or the γ' phase. To achieve these effects, each of these elements
should be contained preferably in an amount of 0.01% or more. However, if 
these elements are contained in excess, a reduction in toughness is caused,
and thus, when these are to be contained, the upper content limits of these
elements should be preferably 1% for Nb or V, respectively and 2% for Ta.
When two or more of these elements are used in combination, their content
in total should be desirably 3% or less.</p><heading>La, Ce and Nd:</heading><p num="0033">These elements may be contained as necessary because they have
not only the effect of preventing the exfoliation of an alumina layer under
the conditions where the alloy is repeatedly heated and cooled, but also the
effect of improving carburization resistance and coking resistance for use
under the environment where the temperature is fluctuated. To achieve
these effects, each of these elements should be contained preferably in an
amount of 0.002% or more. However, when these are contained in excess,
the effect of preventing the exfoliation of an alumina layer is saturated and
further the workability is worsened. Accordingly, the upper limits of La,
Ce and Nd content should be preferably 0.1%, respectively. These
elements may be contained alone or in combination thereof.</p><heading>Cu, Co:</heading><p num="0034">Cu and Co may be substituted as necessary for a part of Ni to
stabilize mainly the austenitic phase. However, if these elements are
added in excess, toughness and workability are deteriorated. Accordingly,
the upper limit of Cu content must be 5% or less. The Cu content should be
preferably 3% or less, more preferably 1.5% or less. In addition, the upper
limit of Co content must be 10%. The content of Co is preferably 8% or less,
more preferably 5% or less. Further, Co has an action of improving creep
strength by the solid solution strengthening. The lower limit of each of
these elements should be preferably 0.01% or more. </p><p num="0035">Among alloys in the range of those chemical compositions described
above, an alloy particularly excellent in various characteristics has
preferably the following chemical composition:</p><p num="0036">C: 0.07% or less, Si: 0.01 to 1% or less, Mn: 1% or less, S: 0.0025% or
less, Cr: 12 to less than 20%, Al: 2.1 to less than 3.8%, and N: 0.045% or less,
0.001 to 1% in total of one or more metals of B: 0 to 0.03%, Zr: 0 to 0.2% and
Hf: 0 to 0.8%, and Mo: 2.5 to 12%, Ti: 0.005 to 1%, Ca: 0.0005 to 0.01%, and
Fe: 0.1 to 10%.</p><p num="0037">The alloy of the present invention can be obtained by conventional
melting and refining process and then casting, and the alloy as casting can
also be used. Usually, this alloy after casting is formed into products such
as pipes by way of various processing steps such as forging, hot working and
cold working. The alloy may be formed into products by powder
metallurgical method. Heat treatment promotes the uniformity of the
metal structure and contributes to improvements in the performance of the
alloy of the present invention. In this case, the uniformization heat
treatment is preferably carried out at 1100 to 1300°C, but the alloy as
casting or processing can also be used.</p><heading>Embodiment</heading><p num="0038">Alloys with the chemical compositions shown in Table 1 were melt
in a 50 kg vacuum high-frequency furnace, then formed by forging into plate
materials with a thickness of 15 mm, and subjected to solution heat
treatment at 1250°C and then test specimens were prepared. <img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="126" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="237"/></p><p num="0039">To evaluate carburization resistance, high-temperature strength, hot
workability and weldability, each test was conducted in the following
manner.
<sl><li>(1) Pack carburization test (evaluation of carburization resistance)

Test specimen: 4 mm in thickness, 20 mm in width and 30 mm in length

Test method: A test specimen was inserted into a caruburizing agent,
heated at 1150°C and kept therein for 48 hours, and then the C content in
the center in the direction of plate thickness of the test specimen was
analyzed by inductively coupled plasma (ICP).

Evaluation: Judged to be excellent in carburization resistance when the
amount of carburized C is 0.2% or less.</li><li>(2) Creep rupture test (evaluation of high-temperature strength)

Test specimen: 6.0 mm in diameter and 30 mm in mark distance

Test method: To measure an rupture time under the conditions of a
temperature of 1150°C and a loading stress of 0.9 kgf/mm<sup>2</sup>.

Evaluation: Judged to be excellent in high-temperature strength when the
rupture time is 500 hours or more.</li><li>(3) Greeble test (evaluation of hot workability)

Test specimen: A round bar test specimen with a diameter of 10 mm in a
parallel part and a length of 130 mm

Test method: After the specimen was heated at 1200°C for 5 minutes,
cooled at 100°C/min. to 1000°C and then drawn at a strain rate of 5 /s.
After rupture, the sample was cooled with He gas, and then the reduction of
area was measured.

Evaluation: Judged to be excellent in hot workability when the ratio of
reduction of area is 60% or more.</li><li>(4) Longitude-varestraint test (evaluation of weldability)
 
Test specimen: 12 mm in thickness, 50 mm in width and 200 mm in length

Test method: The test specimen was subjected to TIG welding at an
electric current of 200 A, a voltage of 17 V, and a welding rate of 15 cm/min.
After that, 2% bending strain was applied to the specimen, to determine the
total cracking length of the heat-affected zone (HAZ).

Evaluation: Judged to be excellent when the total cracking length is 5 mm
or less.</li></sl></p><p num="0040">The test results are shown in Table 2.
<img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="138" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="118"/></p><p num="0041">As is evident from Table 2, the alloys 1 to 16 of the present invention
containing Al in a range of 2.1 to less than 4.5% are excellent in any items of
hot workability, carburization resistance, weldability and creep rupture
strength. On the other hand, in the comparative alloy A whose C and Al
contents are outside from the ranges defined in the present invention, the
amount of carburized C is as significantly high as 0.55%, and the rupture
time is as extremely short as 120 hours, and this alloy is not excellent in
both carburization resistance and creep rupture strength. In addition, the
comparative alloy B whose Al content exceeds the upper limit defined in the
present invention shows a greeble reduction of area as low as 25%, and the
total cracking length in the HAZ in the longitude-varestraint test is 20 mm,
and this alloy can be seen to be inferior in both hot workability and
weldability. In addition, both the comparative alloy C with a high S
content and the comparative alloy D with a high N content are poor in hot
workability and weldability. The comparative alloy E whose Cr content is
less than the lower limit defined in the present invention is inferior in
carburization resistance. Further, the comparative alloys F whose Si
content is high and the comparative alloy G containing none of B, Zr and Hf
are not excellent in hot workability and weldability.</p><heading>INDUSTRIAL APPLICABILITY</heading><p num="0042">The alloy of the present invention is an alloy having creep rapture
strength satisfactory for use as a high-temperature strength member
excellent in hot workability, weldability, carburization resistance and
coking resistance. In particular, the alloy of the present invention
demonstrates the above-described excellent characteristics under the
environment of thermal cracking and heating cycle where carburization, 
oxidation and temperature change are repeated such as in pipes used
particularly in ethylene cracking furnaces. As a result, the alloy of the
present invention can be used to enable operation at a higher temperature,
to prolong the period of continuous operation, and to extend the span for
replacing with a new material due to the improvement of durability.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A heat resistant Ni base alloy comprising on a mass% basis:
<claim-text><claim-text>C: 0.1% or less,</claim-text><claim-text>Si: 2% or less,</claim-text><claim-text>Mn: 2% or less,</claim-text><claim-text>S: 0.005% or less,</claim-text><claim-text>Cr: 10 to 25%,</claim-text><claim-text>Al: 2.1 to less than 4.5%,</claim-text><claim-text>N: 0.08% or less,</claim-text><claim-text>0.001 to 1% in total of one or more elements of B: 0.03% or less,
Zr: 0.2% or less and Hf: 0.8% or less,</claim-text><claim-text>2.5 to 15% in total of one or more elements of Mo: 0.01 to 15% and
W: 0.01 to 9%,</claim-text><claim-text>Ti: 0 to 3%,</claim-text><claim-text>Mg: 0 to 0.01%,</claim-text><claim-text>Ca: 0 to 0.01%,</claim-text><claim-text>Fe: 0 to 10%,</claim-text><claim-text>Nb: 0 to 1%,</claim-text><claim-text>V: 0 to 1%,</claim-text><claim-text>Ta: 0 to 2%,</claim-text><claim-text>Y: 0 to 0.1%,</claim-text><claim-text>La: 0 to 0.1%,</claim-text><claim-text>Ce: 0 to 0.1%,</claim-text><claim-text>Nd: 0 to 0.1%,</claim-text><claim-text>Cu: 0 to 5%,</claim-text><claim-text>Co: 0 to 10%, and</claim-text><claim-text>the balance being substantially Ni.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The heat resistant Ni base alloy according to claim 1, wherein the
Ti content is 0.005 to 3% by mass.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The heat resistant Ni base alloy according to claim 1, wherein the
Ti content is 0.005 to 3% and either one or both of Mg and Ca are contained
in an amount of 0.0005 to 0.01% and 0.0005 to 0.01%, respectively.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The heat resistant Ni base alloy according to claim 1, wherein the
Ti content is 0.005 to 3%, either one or both of Mg and Ca are contained in
an amount of 0.0005 to 0.01% and 0.0005 to 0.01%, respectively and the Fe
content is 0.1 to 10%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A heat resistant Ni base alloy comprising on a mass% basis,
<claim-text><claim-text>C: 0.07% or less,</claim-text><claim-text>Si: 0.01 to 1%,</claim-text><claim-text>Mn: 1% or less,</claim-text><claim-text>S: 0.0025% or less,</claim-text><claim-text>Cr: 12 to 19%,</claim-text><claim-text>Al: 2.1 to less than 3.8%,</claim-text><claim-text>N: 0.045% or less,</claim-text><claim-text>0.001 to 1% in total of one or more metals of B: 0.03% or less,
Zr: 0.2% or less and Hf: 0.8 or less,</claim-text><claim-text>Mo: 2.5 to 12%,</claim-text><claim-text>Ti: 0.005 to 1%,</claim-text><claim-text>Ca: 0.0005 to 0.01%,</claim-text><claim-text>Fe: 0.1 to 10%, and</claim-text><claim-text>the balance being essentially Ni.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>