<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2003025107-A1" country="WO" doc-number="2003025107" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26760019" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20030327"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2003025107-A1" status="new" fvid="78543289"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2003025107</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030327</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-0219458-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>0219458</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20020619</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-32230801-P" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>32230801</doc-number><kind>P</kind><date>20010914</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-7801002-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>7801002</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020219</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>C11D   3/16</main-classification><further-classification>D06B  19/00</further-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/37        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/37        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/48        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/48        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/50        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/50        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   7/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   7/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   7/22        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   7/32        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   7/36        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   7/50        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   7/50        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">D06L   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">D06L   1/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D  11/00B2A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/00B13</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/00B6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/37C6F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/37C8F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/50</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   7/10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   7/32E</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   7/36</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   7/50A8</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">D06L   1/12</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">SURFACTANT-FREE CLEANING COMPOSITIONS AND PROCESSES FOR THE USE THEREOF</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">COMPOSITIONS DE NETTOYAGE EXEMPTES DE TENSIOACTIF ET METHODES D'UTILISATION DE CES COMPOSITIONS</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-4035148-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4035148</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5643861-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5643861</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5904735-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5904735</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5962391-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5962391</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CLEAN CONTROL CORP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CLEAN CONTROL CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HAMMOCK CORY S</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HAMMOCK, CORY, S.</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors> </parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Surfactant-free cleaning compositions are provided for use in removing soil and stains from fiber surfaces such as carpets, upholstery and the like as well as for preventing redeposition of soil and stains on such surfaces. Additionally, processes are provided for cleaning such soiled and/or stained fiber surfaces utilizing aqueous forms of such surfactant-free cleaning compositions having a surface tension of greater than about 38 dynes per centimeter.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new"  lang="FR"><p>L'invention concerne des compositions de nettoyage exemptes de tensioactif pouvant être utilisées pour enlever les salissures et les taches de surfaces en fibre, telles que des tapis, des garnitures et analogues, ainsi que pour empêcher un nouveau dépôt de salissures et de taches sur lesdites surfaces. L'invention concerne en outre des méthodes de nettoyage de surfaces en fibre souillées et/ou tachées avec des formes aqueuses desdites compositions de nettoyage exemptes de tensioactif ayant une tension superficielle supérieure à environ 38 dynes par centimètre.</p> </abstract> <description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="2"/>--><p num="p0001"> SURFACTANT-FREE CLEANING COMPOSITIONS AND PROCESSES FOR THE USE THEREOF</p> <p num="p0002">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</p><p num="p0003">This application claims the benefit under 35 U.S.C. §119(e) of provisional patent application Serial Number 60/322,308 filed September 14, 2001.</p><p num="p0004">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</p><p num="p0005">1. Technical Field</p><p num="p0006">The present invention relates to the field of cleaning compositions and to processes for utilizing such compositions to clean caφets, upholstery and other fiber surfaces. More particularly, the present invention is directed to surfactant- free cleaning compositions for use in removing soil and stains from caφets, upholstery and the like as well as for preventing redeposition of soil and stains on such surfaces and to processes for cleaning such soiled and/or stained surfaces utilizing surfactant-free cleaning compositions.</p><p num="p0007">2. Background Art</p><p num="p0008">Commercial caφets, upholstery and other fiber surfaces are routinely treated with soil repellant finishes that form low energy hydrophobic barriers intended to prevent staining caused by various household soils. In this regard, common household soils may be either hydrophilic or hydrophobic in nature and generally have an intrinsic surface energy above that of normal caφet and upholstery soil repellant finishes. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>-->
 Heretofore, it has been common practice to supply cleaning compositions for treatment of caφets, upholstery and such fiber surfaces in the form of solutions containing micelle-forming surfactants and polymer-micelle-forming surfactant complexes therein. The use of these micelle-forming surfactant ingredients have been demonstrated to provide certain advantageous properties to cleaning composition in terms of emulsification and dispersion of soils. However, the micelle-forming surfactants also have been found to exhibit certain disadvantageous properties which tend to outweigh their generally recognized benefits.</p><p num="p0009">Specifically, the micelle-forming surfactants which have been utilized in prior art cleaning compositions have functioned to reduce the water/oil interfacial tension at the surface of the fiber substrate for pmposes of encapsulating oil particles for removal in much the same manner as is typical for most consumer cleaning products such as hard surface cleaners, fabric cleaners, personal care products and the like. This lowering of the surface tension (i.e., the force per unit length on the surface that opposes the expansion of the surface area) when prior art aqueous cleaning solutions has been utilized have been found to be counteφroductive in practice resulting in the- cleaning solution causing many soils and/or stains to penetrate into and "wet" the fiber surface, thereby, to cause the soiled section or stain in the fiber surface to spread over a larger area rather than to be removed. Additionally, this "wetting" tends to cause fibers to untwist, particularly under mechanical force, thereby causing increased fiber damage and wear.</p><p num="p0010">Thus, it has been recognized previously that cleaning compositions are needed to apply to a soiled area or stain in a fiber surface that will not "wet" the fiber when applied and will provide adequate soil suspending properties in order to solve the problems which have been encountered with the prior art surfactant containing cleaning compositions.</p><p num="p0011">DISCLOSURE THE INVENTION It is an object of the present invention to overcome the problems which have been encountered with prior art surfactant containing cleaning compositions 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
and, particularly, the above-noted wetting and soil spreading problems which have been encountered employing previous cleaning compositions containing micelle forming surfactants.</p><p num="p0012">It is another object of the present invention to provide surfactant- free cleaning compositions for use in removing soils and stains from fiber surfaces such as caφets and upholstery, as well as a variety of other fiber surfaces, particularly stain resistant surfaces.</p><p num="p0013">Another object of the present invention is to provide processes for cleaning fiber surfaces, particularly, stain resistant caφet and upholstery surfaces, utilizing a surfactant-free cleaning composition.</p><p num="p0014">A further object is to provide processes for treating caφets and upholstery having soil repellant and/or stain resistant finishes applied thereto with surfactant- free cleaning compositions to enhance the removal of stains and soil from the caφets and upholstery and to prevent subsequent redeposition of soil thereon without interfering with the operation of the soil repellant and/or stain resistant finishes. In this regard, it is a particular object of the present invention to provide surfactant-free cleaning compositions which promote higher surface tension characteristics than prior art cleaning compositions when applied to fiber surfaces treated with standard soil repellant and stain resistant finishes so that the resistant finishes are able to perform effectively in providing soil and stain repellant/resistant properties by keeping any soil and/or stains contained on the surface of the fiber and available for subsequent removal by absoφtion or extraction.</p><p num="p0015">These and other objects will become apparent hereinafter to those skilled in the art.</p><p num="p0016">BEST MODE FOR CARRYING OUT THE INVENTION</p><p num="p0017">It has been found that the above-noted objectives can be accomplished by providing surfactant-free, aqueous cleaning compositions including a polymeric dispersing agent, at least one alkali counter ion and a polymeric anti-redeposition agent. The compositions may optionally further include ingredients such as 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
chelating agents, fragrance materials, fragrance solubilizing agents and preservative agents.</p><p num="p0018">Exemplary of suitable polymeric dispersing agents for use in the compositions of the present invention are water-soluble polymeric and co- polymeric compounds such as polyacrylic acid; polyacrylic acid/maleic acid copolymers; polymethacrylic acid, polyaspartic acid and the like. Exemplary of suitable polymeric anti-redeposition agents for use in the compositions of the present invention are water-soluble polymeric and co- polymeric compounds such as polyvinylpyrrohdone; polyvinylbetaine; polyvinyl pyrrolidone/vinylacetate copolymers; polyvinylpyrrolidone/dimethylaminoethylmethacrylate copolymers; polyvinylpyrrolidone/acrylic acid copolymers; polymethylvinylether/maleic anhydride copolymers; polyvinylpyridine-n-oxide and the like which form complexes with anionic and cationic substrates and, to a lesser degree, with nonionic substrates such as household soils, dirt, stains and the like.</p><p num="p0019">Suitable alkali counter ions for use in the compositions of the present invention include sodium ions, potassium ions, calcium ions, magnesium ions, ammonium and amine ions (for example, from ammonium hydroxide, isopropylamines, and alkanolamines), and the like.</p><p num="p0020">With regard to the optional ingredients for inclusion in the cleaning compositions of this invention, suitable chelating agents include water soluble compounds such as ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid; diethylenediaminepentaacetic acid; nitrilotriacetic acid; hydroxyethylenediaminetriacetic acid; iminodisuccinate acid; aminotrismethylenephosphonic acid; hexamethylenediaminetetramethylenephosphonic acid; diethylenetriaminepentamethylene-phosphonic acid and the like.</p><p num="p0021">Concerning suitable fragrance materials for use in the surfactant-free cleaning compositions of the present invention, it should be noted that any desirable known scenting or fragrance types may be employed to produce such compositions provided that the fragrance or scent passes standard screening for challenge testing and storage stability and, furthermore, that users/customers 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
would be satisfied with the aesthetics (i.e., color, smell and the like) of cleaning composition containing the fragrance. Examples of suitable fragrance materials for use herein include, but are not limited to, teφene compounds such as monocyclic teφenes such as limonene; dicyclic teφenes such as pinene; and acyclic teφenes such as myrcene and the like. Also, oxygenated teφene derivatives such as alcohols, aldehydes, esters, ethers, ketones and the like; as well as oxygenated aromatic derivatives such as alcohols, aldehydes, esters, ethers, ketones and the like may be employed as the fragrance material in the present compositions.</p><p num="p0022">Exemplary of preferred teφene compounds for use herein are oils derived from citrus peels such as lemons, oranges, limes, tangerines, grapefruits and the like. Such oils are comprised of about 70 - 90% (by weight) teφenes (limonene, pinene, and myrcene) with smaller amounts of alcohols (teφineol, linalool, geraniol, octanol, and nonanol) and aldehydes (citral and citronellal). Examples of an oxygenated teφene derivative suitable for use as a fragrance in the compositions of this invention are oils of eucalyptus globulus, which are comprised of about 80% (by weight) teφene ether (cineol) with smaller amounts of other teφene compounds. An example of an oxygenated aromatic derivative would be oil of wintergreen, which is comprised of about 98% (by weight) aromatic ester (methyl salicylate).</p><p num="p0023">Suitable fragrance solubilizing agents include a variety of solvents including alcohols such as methyl alcohol, ethyl alcohol, isopropyl alcohol, propyl alcohol and the like; glycol ethers (including methyl, ethyl, propyl, isopropyl, butyl, phenyl, and ethylhexyl ethers) and glycol ether esters of glycols (such as ethylene glycol, diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol, propylene glycol, dipropylene glycol, tripropylene glycol and the like) including diethylene glycol mono butyl ether and diethylene glycol mono butyl ether acetate and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="p0024">As with fragrance materials for use herein, any desirable known preservative may be employed to produce the compositions of this invention provided that the preservative passes standard screening for challenge testing and storage stability and, furthermore, that users/customers would be satisfied with 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
 the aesthetics (i.e., color, smell and the like) of cleaning composition containing the preservative. Suitable preservative agents for use in the present invention include a variety of chemical compounds with the ability to impart to chemical formulas a resistance to microbial contamination in order to assure product safety and integrity over the useful life of the product. Such preservative agents include l,3-dihydroxymethyl-5-5-dimethylhydantoin (DMDM Hydantoin); 1,2- benzisothiazolin-3-one; 5-chloro-2-methyl-4-isothiazolin-3-one; 2-methyl-4- isothiazolin-3-one; 3-iodo-2-propynyl butyl carbamate; phenoxyethanol; 2- bromo-2-nitropropane-l,3-diol; methyl paraben; propyl paraben; isopropyl paraben; butyl paraben; isobutyl paraben; diazolidinyl urea and hydroxymethylglycinate and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="p0025">Generally, in formulating aqueous, surfactant-free cleaning compositions of the present invention, the following ranges of ingredients (as weight percentages per total weight of aqueous cleaning composition) may satisfactorily be used: Formulation Ranges (as applied to a fiber surface</p><p num="p0026"><img id="imgf000007_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="144"  img-format="tif"  img-content="table"  file="imgf000007_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="106"/><!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>-->
 Surfactant-free, aqueous cleaning compositions containing the above tabulated ranges of ingredients may be prepared from preformed concentrated stock solutions. In practice, these concentrated stock solutions are intended to be diluted with water by an end user at the site of application of the cleaning composition to a desired level depending on the particular soil extraction device or technique to be employed by the end user to treat the fiber surface. The concentrated stock solutions contain predetermined quantities (on a weight basis) of the desired ingredients so that upon dilution the resulting aqueous compositions will contain such ingredients in quantities (on a weight percent basis) corresponding to the above tabulated operating and/or preferred ranges of ingredients to be incoφorated in the aqueous cleaning compositions. The concentrated stock solutions are normally diluted by a factor of from about 1 :2 to about 1 :256 to produce the aqueous composition for application to caφets, upholstery and other fiber surfaces. Preferably, the concentrated stock solutions are diluted by a factor of from about 1 :4 to about 1:128 and, most preferably, from about 1:16 to about 1:64.</p><p num="p0027">In a preferred embodiment of the present invention, the surfactant- free, aqueous cleaning compositions of this invention contain polymeric dispersing agents, polymeric anti-redeposition agents and a sufficient amount of an alkali counter ion to maintain the pH of the aqueous composition in a range of about 5.0 - 12.0, most preferably 9.0 - 10.0. In this regard, it has been found that such compositions have the advantage of demonstrating soil suspending activity without the use of micelle- forming surfactants found in prior art caφet and upholstery cleaning products. This is a significant commercial advantage since products containing the micelle-forming surfactants have received low customer satisfaction ratings due to problems relating to their use (i.e., stains reappearing and degradation of fiber appearance/pile). In the present compositions, the absence of micelle- forming surfactants enhances the method of stain removal; as well as, the subsequent removal of residual cleaner known to have a negative impact on the inherent caφet and upholstery anti-soil properties.</p><p num="p0028">Most preferably, caφet cleaning compositions in accordance with the present invention comprise mixtures of the following ingredients: 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>-->
 a) a water-soluble chelating agent such as water-soluble ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid; b) a dispersing agents such as water-soluble polyacrylic acids; c) a anti-redeposition agent such as water-soluble polyvinylpyrrohdone; d) a sufficient amount of alkali counter ions such as sodium (Na), potassium (K), ammonium hydroxide (NH <sub>4</sub> OH), isopropylamine and alkanolamines to maintain the pH of the composition in a range of about 5.0 to about 12.0; preferably in a range of about 9.0-10.0; and e) a fragrance compound such as teφenes or teφene derivatives; f) a fragrance solubilizing agent such as various alcohol or glycol ethers; and g) a preservative such as DMDM Hydantoin.</p><p num="p0029">The polymeric dispersing agents are included in the present surfactant-free cleaning compositions to take advantage of the lower energy of the fiber surface to force the soil off the surface and into the dispersing agent. In this invention it is of less importance to emulsify oil than it is to limit the penetration of dispersed soil into the fiber in order to achieve enhanced soil removal results as compared with prior art surfactant containing cleaning compositions.</p><p num="p0030">Specifically, the aqueous compositions of the present invention are formulated to provide high energy cleaners having surface tensions of greater than about 38 dynes/centimeter (cm) for application onto low energy fiber surfaces (i.e., less than about 35 dynes/cm) thereby establishing an energy barrier which is employed to maintain separation between the surface of the fiber and the surfactant- free cleaning composition. The formation of this energy barrier allows for the efficient transfer of a stain from the surface of a fiber into an aqueous liquid phase and, also, enables the dissolution of charged particles (such as dirt and acid dye), polar soils (such as sugars and starches) and non-polar soils (such as oil) from the surface of the fiber into a solution of the cleaning compositions of this invention. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="10"/>-->
 Thus, the surfactant- free, aqueous cleaning compositions of the present invention containing polymeric dispersing and anti-redeposition agents rely on a basic principle of operation in order to achieve the functional advantages of the present cleaning compositions as compared with prior art cleaning compositions. That is, the energy barrier formed between a fiber surface and the cleaning compositions of this invention prevent redeposition of dirt and dye particles onto a fiber and facilitates quicker adsoφtion of the solublized soil into a clean cloth used to remove the unwanted soil and reduce the amount of residual cleaning solution left on the fiber after completion of the cleaning task.</p><p num="p0031">It should be noted that the advantages achieved employing the higher surface tension cleaners of the present invention, while being most pronounced on fibers with a soil-repellant finish, are also realized to a lesser degree on non- treated synthetic fibers (i.e., nylon, polyester, polypropylene and acrylic), which are intrinsically low energy surfaces and essentially non-absorbent to water based liquids.</p><p num="p0032">In the process of the present invention, a surfactant- free cleaning composition having a surface tension of at least about 38 dynes per cm (preferably, above 60 dynes per cm) is applied to a soiled or stained fiber surface such as caφets, upholstery and the like in order to prevent the problems which have been encountered with prior art low surface tension cleaning compositions which penetrate the typical topical hydrophobic fluorochemical soil repellant and/or stain resistant finish treatments on the fiber surface. The cleaning composition may be applied to a stained or soiled area employing a hand held sprayer, a pull/push applicator, a woven or non-woven fabric wipe or a similar device as long as a low force is used. Application of the present cleaning compositions under a high force will reduce the effectiveness of the invention due to increased penetration of the solution into the fiber.</p><p num="p0033">Thus, in the processes of the present invention, the cleaning compositions may be used with a hand-held, upright, or commercial type extraction device. Such applications are normally accomplished by incoφorating a suitable concentrated version of the cleaning composition into an applicator and diluting the concentrate sufficient to enable the diluted cleaning composition to perform 
<!-- EPO <DP n="11"/>-->
 the cleaning function satisfactorily when applied to a fiber surface. In operation, the benefits of a surfactant-free formulation are realized since cleaning compositions that do not penetrate the fiber not only provide better stain and soil cleaning benefits on the fiber surface, but also are more readily extracted by extraction devices.</p><p num="p0034">Functionally, the absence of surfactants in the compositions of the present invention greatly enhances the effectiveness of these cleaning compositions as compared with prior art surfactant containing cleaning compositions since the presence of surfactants in the prior art products reduces the surface tension of the cleaning composition and significantly reduces the dispersing properties of the composition. In this regard, the surfactant- free compositions of the present invention are formulated to exhibit higher surface tension characteristics than prior art cleaning compositions when applied to a fiber surface whereby any soiled or stained areas are contained on the surface and are available for subsequent removal from the surface by known absoφtion or extraction techniques.</p><p num="p0035">Example 1</p><p num="p0036">A 2500 gram (g) sample of a surfactant- free aqueous cleaning composition in accordance with the present invention was prepared by blending, in laboratory scale apparatus, the following ingredients:</p><p num="p0037"><img id="imgf000011_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000011_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="69"/><!-- EPO <DP n="12"/>-->
 The mixing procedure employed in producing the 2500g sample included initially weighing and incoφorating 2449.17g water into a 5000 mL polypropylene beaker and then placing the beaker containing the water on a steel mixer base, inserting a Talboy agitator into the beaker and initiating agitation. Then, 30.00g EDTA (tetrasodium salt), 9.50g polyacrylic acid (sodium salt), 2.50g polyvinylpyrrohdone and a preservative (DMDM Hydantoin) were incoφorated, in listed order, into the water under agitation. The resulting mixture was blended for 5 minutes. Separately, 7.50g ethyl alcohol and 0.08g fragrance (#181335 Lemon) were weighed and mixed in a 50 mL Pyrex beaker and this mixture was pre-blended with a spatula in the 50 mL beaker after which the resulting pre-blend was introduced into the original mixture in the 5000 mL polypropylene beaker. The combined mixture was then blended for 10 minutes after which an 8 ounce (oz) portion of the 2500 mL sample mixture was collected and transferred for Quality Control (QC) testing. Other portions of the mixture were collected and introduced into 32 oz. high density polyethylene (HDPE) containers with a suitable closure (28-400 High Flow Pull Push manufactured by Creative Packaging Coφ. or a Model 0176 spray/stream/off trigger sprayer manufactured by Owens-Brockway) to be used as Test Samples for the performance testing detailed hereinafter in Examples 2 and 4.</p><p num="p0038">The QC testing of the 8 ounce sample resulted in the following data:</p><p num="p0039">Quality Control</p><p num="p0040"><img id="imgf000012_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000012_0001.tif" inline="no" he="61"/><!-- EPO <DP n="13"/>-->
 Example 2</p><p num="p0041">To simulate use of the surfactant- free aqueous cleaning compositions of the present invention for stain removal on stain-resistant caφeting and to demonstrate the improved stain removal results achieved with the compositions of the present invention as compared with prior art commercial products , Test Samples of the cleaning composition produced in Example 1, packaged in a 32 ounce container with a high flow pull/push applicator, were applied to a variety of laboratory staining agents and were blotted and the resulting stain ratings were compared with the stain rating results achieved employing various commercially available prior art cleaning compositions as Controls under the same test conditions.</p><p num="p0042">For puφoses of this comparative test, a series of 1 Vi" stains were applied to a test caφet at 2<sup>I</sup> 2<sup>1</sup>' intervals by pipette transfer of approximately 6mL of various staining agents tabulated below onto the caφet surface. The stains were conditioned for 24 hours at 23 °C (70% relative humidity) and excess stain was scraped from the surface with a scraper.</p><p num="p0043">Then, a 7g test sample of the cleaning composition produced in Example 1 was applied to each of the stained areas on the caφet surface using a high flow pull/push applicator. For puφoses of providing control samples for comparative testing, two additional 7g samples comprising two commercially available prior art cleaning products (i.e., one sample being prepared with RESOLVE® "Spot and Stain" and the other being prepared with BISSELL "Tough Stain Precleaner"™) were applied to in a similar manner to comparable stained areas on separate caφets. Three minutes after application, all of the stained areas were blotted with no more than two paper towels (as necessary). Then, additional 7g test samples of each of the cleaning compositions were reapplied to the stained areas and these areas were again blotted until no further transfer of stain from the caφet to the towels was noted (~10 minutes). If necessary, a scraper was employed to agitate any un-dissolved dried particles remaining on the caφets. A final 7g Test Sample of each of the cleaning composition samples was reapplied to the stained areas and these areas were blotted again until no transfer was noted 
<!-- EPO <DP n="14"/>-->
 (~5 minutes). Thereafter, the caφet was conditioned for 24 hours at 23°C and the following tabulated comparative stain rating results were determined based on visual inspection of the caφet after treatment:</p><p num="p0044">Table I - Stain Rating Results</p><p num="p0045"><img id="imgf000014_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000014_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="135"/></p><p num="p0046">Rating Scale: 5 - no stain remaining 4 - 75% of stain removed 3 - 50% of stain removed 2 - 25% of stain removed 1 - 0% of stain removed 
<!-- EPO <DP n="15"/>-->
 Example 3</p><p num="p0047">Typically, the surfactants employed in prior art cleaning compositions have been incoφorated for puφoses of lowering the surface tension of aqueous cleaning solutions when the surfactants are added at concentrations above critical micelle concentrations (CMC) of the surfactants.</p><p num="p0048">In this Example, the surface tension characteristics of various conventional prior art cleaning compositions were measured in comparison with the surface tension exhibited by the cleaning compositions of the present invention. As determined by measurement with a calibrated CSC-DuNoϋy Tensiometer (Model 70535; SN 12516), the prior art cleaning compositions have exhibited surface tensions below 35, and typically between 22 and 35, dynes per centimeter (cm) as compared with the cleaning compositions of the present invention which exhibit surface tensions of at least about 38.0 and higher as is demonstrated in the following Table II.</p><p num="p0049">Table II. Surface Tension Measurements</p><p num="p0050"><img id="imgf000015_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="123" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000015_0001.tif" inline="no" he="47"/></p><p num="p0051">Since the surface tension of the prior art aqueous surfactant solutions are typically below 35 dynes per cm, it has been found that the standard soil repellent finishes on fiber surfaces such as caφets, upholstery and the like have been unable to prevent surfactant containing cleaning solutions from penetrating the soil repellent finishes applied on caφet surfaces resulting in several problems including the following:</p><p num="p0052">1. as the stain/soil is emulsified and dispersed, instead of being removed, the stain soil is carried deeper into the fiber, backing and padding of a caφet as the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="16"/>-->
low energy of the fiber finish is overcome. This can actually cause the soil to appear to be removed, only to be discovered that the stain/soil has actually only migrated to the padding and will later often re-migrate back to the surface as the fiber dries (or during subsequent application of cleaner).</p><p num="p0053">2. as the surfactant solution penetrates a caφet fiber, the visual appearance of the fiber is changed due to loss of twist and inflection of the angle of caφet pile. While all of the cleaners tested herein had some effect on the fiber pile, surfactant-containing cleaners caused greater fiber damage. The cleaning compositions of the present invention as produced in accordance with Example 1 caused less initial damage and the fibers had greater ability to recover to near original appearance. The loss of twist is accompanied by an increased loss of fiber, as mechanical force is applied to the caφet to remove stains and soil.</p><p num="p0054">3. once the surfactant solution has penetrated completely into the caφet fiber, backing and padding, the solution is more difficult to remove by either blotting or extraction. This results in longer drying times and decreased customer satisfaction.</p><p num="p0055">Thus, it has been found that the surfactant-free cleaning compositions of the present invention as exemplified by the compositions produced in accordance with the procedures set forth in Example 1 outperformed the prior art surfactant containing cleaning compositions which were tested such as the Control Samples set forth in Example 2. Also, when the stained areas discussed in Example 2 were cut away and inspected, it was noted that a significant portion of many stains in the Control Samples had migrated , spreading the stains out from the center to the base of the fiber strands and caφet backing.</p><p num="p0056">Example 4</p><p num="p0057">This Example is intended to demonstrate the use of the surfactant-free aqueous cleaning compositions of the present invention to clean caφeting and to illustrate the enhanced affect the use of these compositions has on the attraction of common dirt to a cleaned area of caφet fiber (i.e., to prevent re-soiling). Re- soiling performance of the compositions of this invention has been determined 
<!-- EPO <DP n="17"/>-->
 herein by application of the cleaning composition of Example 1 to test caφet and subsequent application of test soil, followed by vacuuming.</p><p num="p0058">The re-soil testing procedure employed in this Example 4 included adjusting the nozzle of a spray/steam/off trigger sprayer to a medium spray pattern (typically about 70% closed for an adjustable sprayer that can be adjusted anywhere from a fine mist through medium, coarse and, finally, to a stream spray pattern when fully opened). Then, 15 grams of each test caφet cleaning composition was sprayed onto an approximately 3" X 15" area of caφet (at an application rate of 0.3 grams per inch). After 3 minutes, the treated area was thoroughly blotted with paper towels (using one paper towel per 5 grams of cleaning composition applied). The caφet sample was then conditioned for 24 hours at 23°C (-70% relative humidity). Thereafter, a 1/8" layer of Scotts Potting Soil was applied evenly to the caφet sample and excess soil was shaken from the caφet. The results of this soil application to the previously cleaned caφet were observed and recorded employing the rating scale set forth below and then one- half of the re-soiled caφet was vacuumed by passing the a vacuum cleaner over the caφet surface three times and the vacuumed area of the re-soiled caφet was observed and graded utilizing the same rating scale set forth below. The results of this re-soil testing were as follows:</p><p num="p0059">Table III - Re-soiling Results</p><p num="p0060"><img id="imgf000017_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="146" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000017_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="68"/></p><p num="p0061">Re-soil Rating: 5 - no soil remaining 
<!-- EPO <DP n="18"/>-->
 4 - slight soil remaining 3 - noticeable soil remaining 2 - considerable soil remaining 1 - severe soil remaining</p><p num="p0062">Based on visual observation and ratings of the re-soil testing, it was determined that the surfactant-free aqueous cleaning compositions of the present invention outperformed the commercially available prior art Control products. Also, when the soiled areas were closely inspected, it was noted that a significant level of imbedded soil was left under the surface of the caφet fiber when the Control products were applied to the caφet surface. It is believed that this imbedded soil resulted from the presence of surfactants in the Control products, thus having an adverse influence on the re-soil rating as compared with the surfactant-free cleaning compositions of the present invention which did not leave such imbedded soil under the surface of in the caφet fiber.</p><p num="p0063">Example 5</p><p num="p0064">To simulate the use of the surfactant- free aqueous cleaning compositions of the present invention to disperse common dirt and to demonstrate the improved dispersion achieved with the compositions of the present invention as compared with prior art commercial products , a 20g test sample of the aqueous cleaning composition produced in Example 1 was introduced into a 24 mL KIMAX Sample Vial (VWR Cat # 66010-429)along with a dirt sample comprising 0.2g Georgia Red Clay which was obtained from a household yard and was prepared by air drying at 23 °C and 70% relative humidity and, then, grinding with a mortar and pestle. For puφoses of providing control samples for comparative testing, two additional 20g samples comprising two commercially available prior art cleaning products (i.e., one sample being prepared with RESOLVE® "Spot and Stain" and the other being prepared with BISSELL "Tough Stain Precleaner"™) were mixed with dirt samples in a similar manner in separate Sample Vials. After the test sample and the control sample cleaning solutions and the dirt sample were introduced into the Sample Vials, the Sample Vials were each 
<!-- EPO <DP n="19"/>-->
 capped and held without shaking for 15 seconds. Then, each of the Sample Vials was inverted three times, followed by a 60 second holding period without shaking and then each of the Sample. Vials was again inverted three times. Based on visual observations, the dispersion rate of the dirt in each of the tested cleaning solutions was determined and recorded after a 1 minute, a 15 minutes and a 60 minutes interval and is tabulated as follows:</p><p num="p0065">Soil Dispersion Results</p><p num="p0066"><img id="imgf000019_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="145" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000019_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="54"/></p><p num="p0067">Soil Dispersion Rating: 5 - 100% dispersed 4 - 75% dispersed 3 - 50 % dispersed 2 - 25% dispersed 1 - 10% dispersed 0 - 0% dispersed</p><p num="p0068">As a result of the visual observation and ratings of this red clay dispersion testing , it was demonstrated that the cleaning compositions of the present invention significantly out-performed both of the commercially available, prior art control products tested in regard to dispersion properties - without the use of surfactants.</p><p num="p0069">While the present invention has been described with reference to specific embodiments, examples and ranges, it will be clear to those skilled in the art that modification may be made without departing from the invention which is specifically set forth in the following claims. 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="20"/>--><claim-text>What is claimed is:</claim-text><claim-text>1. A surfactant-free cleaning composition comprising: a) a water soluble dispersing agent; b) a water soluble anti-redeposition agent; c) at least one alkali counter ion; d) a water soluble chelating agent; e) a fragrance material; and f) a fragrance solubilizing agent; and g) a preservative agent.</claim-text><claim-text>2. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 1 comprising a concentrated aqueous stock solution.</claim-text><claim-text>3. The surfactant-free cleaning composition of claim 1 in aqueous form having a surface tension greater than about 38 dynes per centimeter.</claim-text><claim-text>4. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 3 wherein the water-soluble dispersing agent is selected from the group consisting of polyacrylic acid; polyacrylic acid/maleic acid copolymers; polymethacrylic acid, polyaspartic acid and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>5. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 3 wherein the water-soluble anti-redeposition agent is selected from the group consisting of polyvinylpyrrohdone; polyvinylbetaine; polyvinyl pyrrolidone/vinylacetate copolymers; polyvinylpyrrolidone/dimethylaminoethylmethacrylate copolymers; polyvinylpyrrolidone/acrylic acid copolymers; polymethylvinylether/maleic anhydride copolymers; polyvinylpyridine-n-oxide and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>6. The surfactant-free cleaning composition of claim 3 wherein the alkali counter ion is selected from the group consisting of sodium ions, potassium ions, calcium ions, magnesium ions, ammonium ions and amine ions and mixtures thereof. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="21"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>7. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 3 wherein the water soluble chelating agent is selected from the group consisting of ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid; diethylenediaminepentaacetic acid; nitrilotriacetic acid; hydroxyethylenediammetriacetic acid; iminodisuccinate acid; aminotrismethylenephosphonic acid; hexamethylenediaminetetramethylenephosphonic acid; diethylenetriaminepentamethylene-phosphonic acid and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>8. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 3 wherein the fragrance material is selected from the group consisting of teφene compounds, oxygenated teφene derivatives, oxygenated aromatic derivatives and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>9. The surfactant-free cleaning composition of claim 3 wherein the fragrance solubilizing agent is selected from the group consisting of alcohols, glycol ethers and glycol ether esters of glycol and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>10. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 3 wherein the amount of alkali counter ion present in the cleaning composition is sufficient to maintain a pH range of about 5.0 to about 12.0 in the aqueous composition.</claim-text><claim-text>11. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 3 wherein the preservative agent is selected from the group consisting of 1,3-dihydroxymethyl- 5-5-dimethylhydantoin (DMDM Hydantoin); l,2-benzisothiazolin-3-one; 5- chloro-2-methyl-4-isothiazolin-3-one; 2-methyl-4-isothiazolin-3-one; 3-iodo-2- propynyl butyl carbamate; phenoxyethanol; 2-bromo-2-nitropropane-l,3-diol; methyl paraben; propyl paraben; isopropyl paraben; butyl paraben; isobutyl paraben; diazolidinyl urea and hydroxymethylglycinate and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>12. An aqueous, surfactant- free cleaning composition having a surface tension of greater than about 38 dynes per centimeter comprising: a) a water-soluble polymeric dispersing agent; and b) a water-soluble polymeric anti-redeposition agent; and c) an alkali counter ion; and 
<!-- EPO <DP n="22"/>-->
 d) optionally, a chelating agent; and e) optionally, a fragrance material; and f) optionally, a fragrance solubilizing agent; and g) optionally a preservative agent.</claim-text><claim-text>13. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 12 wherein the water-soluble dispersing agent is selected from the group consisting of polyacrylic acid; polyacrylic acid/maleic acid copolymers; polymethacrylic acid, polyaspartic acid and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>14. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 12 wherein the water-soluble anti-redeposition agent is selected from the group consisting of polyvinylpyrrohdone; polyvinylbetaine; polyvinyl pyrrolidone/vinylacetate copolymers; polyvinylpyrrolidone/dimethylaminoethylmethacrylate copolymers; polyvinylpyrrolidone/acrylic acid copolymers; polymethylvinylether/maleic anhydride copolymers; polyvinylpyridine-n-oxide and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>15. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 12 wherein the alkali counter ion is selected from the group consisting of sodium ions, potassium ions, calcium ions, magnesium ions, ammonium ions and amine ions and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>16. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 12 wherein the water soluble chelating agent is selected from the group consisting of ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid; diethylenediaminepentaacetic acid; nitrilotriacetic acid; hydroxyethylenediammetriacetic acid; iminodisuccinate acid; aminotrismethylenephosphonic acid; hexamethylenediaminetetramethylenephosphonic acid; diethylenetriaminepentamethylene-phosphonic acid and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>17. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 12 wherein the fragrance material is selected from the group consisting of teφene compounds, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="23"/>-->
oxygenated teφene derivatives, oxygenated aromatic derivatives and the like and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>18. The surfactant-free cleaning composition of claim 12 wherein the fragrance solubilizing agent is selected from the group consisting of alcohols, glycol ethers, glycol ether esters of glycol and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>19. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 12 wherein the amount of alkali counter ion present in the cleaning composition is sufficient to maintain a pH range of about 5.0 to about 12.0 in the aqueous composition.</claim-text><claim-text>20. The surfactant- free cleaning composition of claim 12 wherein the preservative agent is selected from the group consisting of 1,3-dihydroxymethyl- 5-5-dimethylhydantoin (DMDM Hydantoin); l,2-benzisothiazolin-3-one; 5- chloro-2-methyl-4-isothiazolin-3-one; 2-methyl-4-isothiazolin-3-one; 3-iodo-2- propynyl butyl carbamate; phenoxyethanol; 2-bromo-2-nitropropane-l,3-diol; methyl paraben; propyl paraben; isopropyl paraben; butyl paraben; isobutyl paraben; diazolidinyl urea and hydroxymethylglycinate and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>21 An aqueous, surfactant- free cleaning composition having a surface tension of greater than about 38 dynes per centimeter comprising the following ingredients (in weight percentages per total weight of the aqueous composition): a) 0.01 - 10.0%) dispersing agent b) 0.001 - 5.0%) anti-redeposition agent c) sufficient alkali counter ion to adjust the pH of the aqueous composition to about 5.0 - 12.0 d) 0.01 - 10.0% chelating agent e) 0.0001 - 2.0% fragrance material f) 0.05 - 25.0%) fragrance solubilizing agent g) sufficient water to adjust the weight percent of the aqueous composition to 100%. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="24"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>22. A process for cleaning a fiber surface comprising applying an effective amount of an aqueous, surfactant- free cleaning composition having a surface tension of at least greater than 38 dynes per centimeter to a stained or soiled area on the fiber surface.</claim-text><claim-text>23. The process of claim 22 wherein the aqueous cleaning composition comprises: a polymeric dispersing agent; an anti-redeposition agent and an alkali counter ion.</claim-text><claim-text>24. The process of claim 23 wherein the aqueous cleaning composition further comprises one or more of the following ingredients: a chelating agent; a fragrance material; a fragrance solubilizing agent; and a preservative agent.</claim-text><claim-text>25. The process of claim 23 wherein the dispersing agent is selected from the group consisting of polyacrylic acid; polyacrylic acid/maleic acid copolymers; polymethacrylic acid, polyaspartic acid and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>26. The process of claim 23 wherein the anti-redeposition agent is selected from the group consisting of polyvinylpyrrohdone; polyvinylbetaine; polyvinyl pyrrolidone/vinylacetate copolymers; polyvinylpyrrolidone/dimethylaminoethylmethacrylate copolymers; polyvinylpyrrolidone/acrylic acid copolymers; polymethylvinylether/maleic anhydride copolymers; polyvinylpyridine-n-oxide and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>27. The process of claim 23 wherein the alkali counter ion is selected from the group consisting of sodium ions, potassium ions, calcium ions, magnesium ions, ammonium ions and amine ions and mixtures thereof. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="25"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>28. The process of claim 24 wherein the chelating agent is selected from the group consisting of ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid; diethylenediaminepentaacetic acid; nitrilotriacetic acid; hydroxyethylenediaminetriacetic acid; iminodisuccinate acid; aminotrismethylenephosphonic acid; hexamethylenediaminetetramethylenephosphonic acid; diethylenetriaminepentamethylene-phosphonic acid and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>29. The process of claim 24 wherein the fragrance material is selected from the group consisting of teφenes, oxygenated teφene derivatives, oxygenated aromatic derivatives and the like and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>30. The process of claim 24 wherein the fragrance solubilizing agent is selected from the group consisting of alcohols, glycol ethers and glycol ether esters and the like</claim-text><claim-text>31. The process of claim 24 wherein the amount of alkali counter ion present in the cleaning composition is sufficient to maintain a pH range of about 5.0 to about 12.0 in the aqueous composition.</claim-text><claim-text>32. The process of claim 24 wherein the preservative agent is selected from the group consisting of l,3-dihydroxymethyl-5-5-dimethylhydantoin (DMDM Hydantoin); l,2-benzisothiazolin-3-one; 5-chloro-2-methyl-4- isothiazolin-3-one; 2-methyl-4-isothiazolin-3-one; 3-iodo-2-propynyl butyl carbamate; phenoxyethanol; 2-bromo-2-nitropropane-l,3-diol; methyl paraben; propyl paraben; isopropyl paraben; butyl paraben; isobutyl paraben; diazohdinyl urea and hydroxymethylglycinate and mixtures thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>33. A concentrated aqueous stock solution for forming an aqueous, surfactant-free cleaning composition comprising: a) a water-soluble polymeric dispersing agent; and b) a water-soluble polymeric anti-redeposition agent; and 
<!-- EPO <DP n="26"/>-->
c) an alkali counter ion; and d) optionally, a chelating agent; and e) optionally, a fragrance material; and f) optionally, a fragrance solubilizing agent; and g) optionally a preservative agent. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>