<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1094086-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1094086" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="23688385" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010425"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1094086-A1" status="new" fvid="23126802"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1094086</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010425</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00123003-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00123003</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001023</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-42587199-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>42587199</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991023</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 293/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 293/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09J 153/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09J 153/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F 293/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F 293/00B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09J 153/00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Acrylatblockcopolymer und die Verwendung und Herstellung davon</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Acrylic block copolymer and its use and production process</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Copolymère acrylique à blocs, son utilisation et sa production</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-4328004-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>4328004</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0243120-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0243120</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0408420-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0408420</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0686653-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0686653</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-10287721-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>10287721</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4503188-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4503188</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5399620-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5399620</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5498675-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5498675</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5763548-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5763548</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1986000626-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1986000626</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 1999, no. 01, 29 January 1999 (1999-01-29) &amp; JP 10 287721 A (NIPPON SHOKUBAI CO LTD), 27 October 1998 (1998-10-27)</text><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NIPPON CATALYTIC CHEM IND</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NIPPON SHOKUBAI CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Nippon Shokubai Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>1-1, Koraibashi 4-chome, Chuo-ku</street><city>Osaka-shi, Osaka 541-0043</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KOBAYASHI NOBUHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YOSHIDA MASATOSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KOBAYASHI, NOBUHIRO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YOSHIDA, MASATOSHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KOBAYASHI, NOBUHIRO</last-name><address><street>2-8-12-512, Kitamidorigaoka</street><city>Toyonaka-shi, Osaka 560-0001</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>YOSHIDA, MASATOSHI</last-name><address><street>2-11-17, Gakuenkita</street><city>Nara-shi, Nara 631-0036</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Henkel, Feiler, Hänzel &amp;amp; Partner</last-name><address><street>Möhlstrasse 37</street><city>81675 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention provides an acrylic block copolymer and its
use and production process, wherein the acrylic block copolymer exhibits
high heat resistance despite having a low viscosity. The acrylic block
copolymer comprises a (meth)acrylic ester structural unit as an essential
component in a ratio of 50 to 100 weight % of the entirety of the acrylic
block copolymer and has a holding power of not less than 100 minutes as
specifically determined. This acrylic block copolymer is fit for hot-melt
pressure sensitive adhesives. In a production process for this acrylic block
copolymer, the second radical polymerization step among the elementary
steps of the multistep radical polymerization includes the step of
uniformly mixing a polymer solution, resultant from the first radical
polymerization step, with a polymerizable monomer which is to be used
in the second radical polymerization step.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><heading><u style="single">A. TECHNICAL FIELD</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a new acrylic block copolymer and
its use and production process, wherein the acrylic block copolymer
exhibits high heat resistance despite having a low viscosity.</p><heading><u style="single">B. BACKGROUND ART</u></heading><p num="0002">As to acrylic block copolymer, there is a known star-shaped block
copolymer that has a structure in which at least three polymer chains are
radially extended from a central polyvalent mercaptan segment wherein
the central polyvalent mercaptan segment is a residual portion resultant
from dissociation of protons from mercapto groups of a polyvalent
mercaptan. This star-shaped block copolymer generally has more
excellent heat resistance than simple chain polymers. Herein, the heat
resistance means the cohesion or strength of polymers at high
temperature, for example, the holding power at high temperature in the
field of pressure sensitive adhesives. The increase of the molecular
weight is an effective method to enhance the heat resistance. In the case
of the simple chain polymers, however, the simple increase of the
molecular weight leads to great increase of viscosity and therefore causes
problems of workability. In comparison, because of the above structure,
the star-shaped block copolymer can have its heat resistance enhanced
without so much increase of its viscosity. Thus, the star-shaped block
copolymer is favorably used for purposes to which the heat resistance is 
demanded, such as hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesives.</p><p num="0003">The star-shaped block copolymer is generally synthesized by a
process comprising the multistep radical polymerization which involves
the use of a polyvalent mercaptan having a valence of 2 to 6 as an
initiator wherein the elementary steps of the multistep radical
polymerization differ in polymerizable monomers as used therein (JP-A-07-179538).</p><p num="0004">However, also as to the star-shaped block copolymer, in the case
where higher heat resistance is demanded thereto, the above method
involving the increase of the molecular weight might enhance the heat
resistance in some degree, but the increase of the viscosity would be still
so great that problems of workability would occur.</p><p num="0005">Thus, the present applicant diligently studied and variously devised:
what the star-shaped structure of the star-shaped block copolymer should
be for the purpose of causing the star-shaped block copolymer to exhibit
high heat resistance without increasing its molecular weight; and
processes for realizing it. As a result, the applicant found that if polymers
having star-shaped structures get bonded to each other, it is possible to
make them exhibit high heat resistance even without increasing their
molecular weights, and further, the applicant experimentally confirmed
that if at least one of the elementary steps of the multistep radical
polymerization involves the joint use of a trace of polyfunctional
monomer with the polymerizable monomer, the above linkage structure
is easily and surely obtainable. Thus, the applicant made an earlier
application for a patent on such a star-shaped block copolymer having
such a linkage structure and its production process (JP-A-10-287721).</p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><heading><u style="single">A. OBJECT OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0006">An object of the present invention is to provide an acrylic block
copolymer and its use and production process, wherein the acrylic block
copolymer exhibits still higher heat resistance than the star-shaped block
copolymer according to the above earlier patent application.</p><heading><u style="single">B. DISCLOSURE OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0007">The present inventors completed the present invention by finding
that the above problems can be solved by making the below-mentioned
improvements upon the aforementioned process on which the present
applicant made an earlier application for a patent.</p><p num="0008">An acrylic block copolymer, according to the present invention,
comprises a (meth)acrylic ester structural unit as an essential component
in a ratio of 50 to 100 weight % of the entirety of the acrylic block
copolymer and has a holding power of not less than 100 minutes,

   wherein the holding power is determined by a process including the
steps of: preparing a sample by melt-coating a hot-melt pressure sensitive
adhesive in a thickness of 25 µm onto a 38-µm-thick PET film, wherein
the hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive includes the acrylic block
copolymer; and then attaching the sample onto a stainless steel sheet
such that the adhesion area would be 1.27 cm × 1.27 cm; and then pressing
the sample onto the stainless steel sheet by once running a 2-kg-heavy
roller thereon back and forth; and then adjusting the temperature of the
product to 60 °C for 30 minutes; and then applying a load of 1 kg to the
sample; and then measuring how long the sample has not fallen off from
the stainless steel sheet since the application of the load.</p><p num="0009">A hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive, according to the present
invention, comprises an acrylic block copolymer as an essential 
component, wherein the acrylic block copolymer includes a (meth)acrylic
ester structural unit as an essential component in a ratio of 50 to 100
weight % of the entirety of the acrylic block copolymer and has a holding
power of not less than 100 minutes,

   wherein the holding power is determined by a process including the
steps of: preparing a sample by melt-coating a hot-melt pressure sensitive
adhesive in a thickness of 25 µm onto a 38-µm-thick PET film, wherein
the hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive includes the acrylic block
copolymer; and then attaching the sample onto a stainless steel sheet
such that the adhesion area would be 1.27 cm × 1.27 cm; and then pressing
the sample onto the stainless steel sheet by once running a 2-kg-heavy
roller thereon back and forth; and then adjusting the temperature of the
product to 60 °C for 30 minutes; and then applying a load of 1 kg to the
sample; and then measuring how long the sample has not fallen off from
the stainless steel sheet since the application of the load.</p><p num="0010">A production process for an acrylic block copolymer, according to the
present invention, comprises the multistep radical polymerization in the
presence of a polyvalent mercaptan wherein the elementary steps of the
multistep radical polymerization differ in polymerizable monomers as
used therein, wherein at least one of the elementary steps of the
multistep radical polymerization involves the joint use of a
polyfunctional monomer with the polymerizable monomer, wherein:
<sl><li>the second radical polymerization step among the elementary steps
of the multistep radical polymerization includes the steps of: all at once
mixing a polymer solution, resultant from the first radical
polymerization step, with a polymerizable monomer which is to be used
in the second radical polymerization step; and then polymerizing the 
resultant mixture in the presence of the polyfunctional monomer; or</li><li>the second radical polymerization step among the elementary steps
of the multistep radical polymerization includes the step of gradually
adding a polymer solution, resultant from the first radical polymerization
step, and a polymerizable monomer, which is to be used in the second
radical polymerization step, to a vessel to mix them, while polymerizing
the resultant mixture in the presence of the polyfunctional monomer.</li></sl></p><p num="0011">These and other objects and the advantages of the present invention
will be more fully apparent from the following detailed disclosure.</p><heading><b>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWING</b></heading><p num="0012"><sl><li>Fig. 1 is a diagram of a model of a star-shaped block copolymer as an
acrylic block copolymer according to the present invention.</li></sl></p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0013">The acrylic block copolymer, according to the present invention, has
a holding power of not less than 100 minutes, preferably not less than 300
minutes, more preferably not less than 500 minutes, most preferably not
less than 1,000 minutes, as determined below. Therefore, this acrylic
block copolymer does not only have high holding power, but also exhibits
a viscosity that is not so high, and further exhibits extremely high heat
resistance at high temperature. Accordingly, this copolymer is, for
example, extremely useful to obtain a hot-melt pressure sensitive
adhesive having high holding power.</p><p num="0014">Holding power (1): as determined by a process including the steps of:
preparing a sample by melt-coating a hot-melt pressure sensitive
adhesive in a thickness of 25 µm onto a 38-µm-thick PET film, wherein
the hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive includes the acrylic block
copolymer; and then attaching the sample onto a stainless steel sheet 
such that the adhesion area would be 1.27 cm × 1.27 cm; and then pressing
the sample onto the stainless steel sheet by once running a 2-kg-heavy
roller thereon back and forth; and then adjusting the temperature of the
product to 60 °C for 30 minutes; and then applying a load of 1 kg to the
sample; and then measuring how long the sample has not fallen off from
the stainless steel sheet since the application of the load.</p><p num="0015">The acrylic block copolymer, according to the present invention, is a
copolymer which comprises a (meth)acrylic ester structural unit as an
essential component in a ratio of 50 to 100 weight %, preferably 80 to 100
weight %, of the entirety of the acrylic block copolymer. The
(meth)acrylic ester structural unit means a unit constituting the
copolymer which unit is derived from a (meth)acrylic ester when its
carbon-carbon double bond is opened and then assembled into the
copolymer. Specific examples of the (meth)acrylic ester include the
below-mentioned ones.</p><p num="0016">As is shown in Fig. 1, a preferable embodiment of the acrylic block
copolymer according to the present invention is a star-shaped block
copolymer comprising a plurality of star-shaped structures 1 (in Fig. 1,
two star-shaped structures 1) in which at least three chain polymer
segments 2 (in Fig. 1, four chain polymer segments 2) are radially
extended from a central polyvalent mercaptan segment 3, wherein the
plurality of star-shaped structures 1 are bonded to each other at their
chain polymer segments 2, and wherein the central polyvalent mercaptan
segment 3 is a residual portion resultant from dissociation of protons
from mercapto groups of a polyvalent mercaptan. In Fig. 1, the portion
where the two star-shaped structures 1, 1 are bonded to each other at their
chain polymer segments 2 is marked with a dot, and this portion is a 
bonding structure 4 as derived from the below-mentioned polyfunctional
monomer which is a bonding material.</p><p num="0017">As is mentioned below, the acrylic block copolymer according to the
present invention is favorably usable for hot-melt pressure sensitive
adhesives. However, this copolymer is, besides, similarly favorably
usable for solvent type pressure sensitive adhesives or emulsion type
pressure sensitive adhesives.</p><p num="0018">Although there is no especial limitation, the acrylic block
copolymer according to the present invention is preferably produced by
the production process according to the present invention for an acrylic
block copolymer which process is the same as the aforementioned
conventional production process for a star-shaped block copolymer as an
acrylic block copolymer, comprising the multistep radical polymerization
involving the use of the polyvalent mercaptan, except that the below-mentioned
polyfunctional monomer is jointly used with the below-mentioned
polymerizable monomer in at least one of the elementary
steps of the multistep radical polymerization, and further that the below-mentioned
special second radical polymerization step is involved.</p><p num="0019">In the production process according to the present invention for an
acrylic block copolymer, radical polymerization of the first polymerizable
monomer is carried out in the presence of the polyvalent mercaptan,
when the radical polymerization of the first monomer is initiated with
mercapto groups of the polyvalent mercaptan, so that the first monomer
forms chain polymer segments of the star-shaped block copolymer as the
acrylic block copolymer. In this step, some of the mercapto groups of the
polyvalent mercaptan remain not initiating this radical polymerization.
Thus, next, the second polymerizable monomer is added to carry out the 
second radical polymerization step, when the radical polymerization of
the second monomer is initiated with the residual mercapto groups of
the polyvalent mercaptan, so that the second monomer forms chain
polymer segments, having compositions different from those of chain
polymer segments resultant from the first step, into the star-shaped block.</p><p num="0020">In the production process according to the present invention for an
acrylic block copolymer, the polyfunctional monomer is jointly used with
the polymerizable monomer in at least one of the elementary steps of the
multistep radical polymerization, therefore the star-shaped structures as
obtained in the above way can be bonded to each other through the
polyfunctional monomer, when there is also an expectable effect that
homopolymers of the polymerizable monomers, which are by-products
of the radical polymerization (chain polymers resultant from
polymerization as not initiated with mercapto groups), are also bonded to
chain polymer segments of the star-shaped block copolymer as the acrylic
block copolymer through the polyfunctional monomer.</p><p num="0021">In the production process according to the present invention for an
acrylic block copolymer, it is necessary that the second radical
polymerization step among the elementary steps of the multistep radical
polymerization includes the steps of: all at once mixing a polymer
solution, resultant from the first radical polymerization step, with a
polymerizable monomer which is to be used in the second radical
polymerization step; and then polymerizing the resultant mixture, or
that the second radical polymerization step among the elementary steps
of the multistep radical polymerization includes the step of gradually
adding a polymer solution, resultant from the first radical polymerization
step, and a polymerizable monomer, which is to be used in the second 
radical polymerization step, to a vessel to mix them, while polymerizing
the resultant mixture. If such a mixing method is carried out, the
polymer solution resultant from the first radical polymerization step will
be uniformly mixed with the polymerizable monomer which is to be
used in the second radical polymerization step.</p><p num="0022">This second radical polymerization step needs to be carried out in
the presence of the polyfunctional monomer. More specifically, it may be
carried out as follows: the polymer solution resultant from the first
radical polymerization step is uniformly mixed with the polymerizable
monomer, which is to be used in the second radical polymerization step,
and with the polyfunctional monomer, and then the polymerization is
carried out in a polymerization vessel while the resultant mixture is
dropwise added thereto; or the polymerization is carried out in a
polymerization vessel while each of the polymer solution, resultant from
the first radical polymerization step, the polymerizable monomer, which
is to be used in the second radical polymerization step, and the
polyfunctional monomer is uniformly dropwise added to the
polymerization vessel.</p><p num="0023">During the above all-at-once mixing or addition mixing, it is
preferable that the progress of the polymerization of the polymer solution
resultant from the first radical polymerization step is terminated at a
conversion of not less than 50 %, preferably not less than 70 %. Examples
of methods to terminate the polymerization include methods in which a
polymerization inhibitor is added to the polymer solution resultant from
the first radical polymerization step, or the temperature of the polymer
solution is lowered.</p><p num="0024">Examples of the above polymerization inhibitor, as used to 
terminate the polymerization, include: phenols such as hydroquinone,
2,5-bis(1,1,3,3-tetramethylbutyl)hydroquinone, 2,5-bis(1,1-dimethylbutyl)hydroquinone,
methoxyphenol, 6-tertiary-butyl-2,4-xylenol,
and 3,5-di-tertiary-butylcatechol; N-nitrosophenylhydroxylamine
aluminum salt, and phenothiazine. These may be used either alone
respectively or in combinations with each other. The amount of the
polymerization inhibitor, as used, is usually in the range of 1 to 10,000
weight ppm, preferably 10 to 1,000 weight ppm, more preferably 20 to 200
weight ppm, of the polymerizable monomer as used in the first radical
polymerization step. In the case where the amount of the polymerization
inhibitor, as used, is smaller than 1 weight ppm, it might be impossible to
efficiently terminate the polymerization. On the other hand, in the case
where the amount of the polymerization inhibitor, as used, is larger than
10,000 weight ppm, the polymerization in the second radical
polymerization step might not be initiated.</p><p num="0025">The polymerization in the first radical polymerization step can
substantially be terminated if the temperature of the polymer solution is
lowered to not higher than 40 °C. The reason therefor is that the
decomposition rate of the polymerization initiator depends on the
temperature, therefore it is considered that almost no radical forms if the
temperature of the polymer solution falls down to not higher than 40 °C.
The depression of the temperature of the polymer solution to not higher
than 20 °C is enough to more surely terminate the polymerization.</p><p num="0026">The above polymerization process by which the present invention is
featured, namely, the process comprising the steps of mixing the polymer
solution, resultant from the first radical polymerization step, with the
polymerizable monomer, which is to be used in the second radical 
polymerization step, and then polymerizing the resultant mixture in the
second radical polymerization step, can give a higher functional star-shaped
block copolymer as the acrylic block copolymer than conventional
polymerization processes comprising the step of adding in sequence the
polymerizable monomer, which is to be used in the second radical
polymerization step, to the entire polymer solution resultant from the
first radical polymerization step. The reason why the high functional
star-shaped block copolymer is obtainable by this new polymerization
process is not certain, but is inferred to be that the polymerization process
by which the present invention is featured enhances the ratio of
formation of the star-shaped block copolymer as shown in Fig. 1.</p><p num="0027">Hereinafter, a detailed explanation is given about raw materials used
for the production process according to the present invention for an
acrylic block copolymer.</p><p num="0028">The polymerizable monomer, as used in the present invention,
comprises a (meth)acrylic ester as an essential component in a ratio of 50
to 100 weight % of the entirety of the polymerizable monomer. Examples
of the (meth)acrylic ester include alkyl (meth)acrylates having 1 to 30
carbon atoms, hydroxyethyl (meth)acrylate, hydroxypropyl (meth)acrylate,
glycidyl (meth)acrylate, methoxyethyl (meth)acrylate, ethoxyethyl
(meth)acrylate, and ethoxyethoxyethyl (meth)acrylate. These may be used
either alone respectively or in combinations with each other.</p><p num="0029">As to the polymerizable monomer, any other polymerizable
monomer is usable jointly with the (meth)acrylic ester if it is to form a
homopolymer or copolymer by radical polymerization. Examples of the
above other polymerizable monomer include: (meth)acrylamides,
typically, such as (meth)acrylamide, N-methyl(meth)acrylamide, and N-propyl(meth)acrylamide; 
(meth)acrylic acid; styrenic monomers, typically,
such as α-methylstyrene, vinyltoluene, and styrene; maleimide
monomers, typically, such as phenylmaleimide and
cyclohexylmaleimide; vinyl ether monomers, typically, such as methyl
vinyl ether, ethyl vinyl ether, and isobutyl vinyl ether; fumaric acid,
monoalkyl fumarates, dialkyl fumarates; maleic acid, monoalkyl
maleates, dialkyl maleates; itaconic acid, monoalkyl itaconates, dialkyl
itaconates; (meth)acrylonitrile, butadiene, isoprene, vinyl chloride,
vinylidene chloride, vinyl acetate, vinyl ketones, vinylpyridine,
vinylpyrrolidone, and vinylcarbazole. These may be used either alone
respectively or in combinations with each other. The above other
polymerizable monomer is usable in a ratio less than 50 weight % of the
entirety of the polymerizable monomer.</p><p num="0030">In the production process according to the present invention, the
multistep radical polymerization is carried out in the presence of a
polyvalent mercaptan wherein the elementary steps of the multistep
radical polymerization differ in polymerizable monomers as used
therein. Herein, the different polymerizable monomers mean not only
polymerizable monomers having different chemical structures, but also
combinations of polymerizable monomers having the same chemical
structure, but different mixing ratios. Examples of the mode, in which
the elementary steps of the multistep radical polymerization differ in
polymerizable monomers as used therein, include such that: a
combination of polymerizable monomers comprising 90 weight parts of
methyl methacrylate and 10 weight parts of butyl acrylate is used in the
first radical polymerization step, while a combination of polymerizable
monomers comprising 10 weight parts of methyl methacrylate and 90 
weight parts of butyl acrylate is used in the second radical polymerization
step. This example of the above mode provides high performance in
practical use, because there is a great difference between Tg of chain
polymer segments of the resultant copolymer.</p><p num="0031">Examples of the polyvalent mercaptan, as used in the present
invention, include: diesters as formed from diols (e.g. ethylene glycol and
1,4-butanediol) and carboxyl-group-containing mercaptans, such as
ethylene glycol dithioglycolate, ethylene glycol dithiopropionate, 1,4-butanediol
dithioglycolate, and 1,4-butanediol dithiopropionate; triesters
as formed from triols (e.g. trimethylolpropane) and carboxyl-group-containing
mercaptans, such as trimethylolpropane trithioglycolate and
trimethylolpropane trithiopropionate; polyesters as formed from
compounds having four hydroxyl groups (e.g. pentaerythritol) and
carboxyl-group-containing mercaptans, such as pentaerythritol
tetrakisthioglycolate and pentaerythritol tetrakisthiopropionate; polyester
compounds as formed from compounds having six hydroxyl groups (e.g.
dipentaerythritol) and carboxyl-group-containing mercaptans, such as
dipentaerythritol hexakisthioglycolate and dipentaerythritol
hexakisthiopropionate; polyester compounds as formed from other
compounds having at least three hydroxyl groups and carboxyl-group-containing
mercaptans; compounds having at least three mercapto
groups, such as trithioglycerol; triazine polythiols, such as 2-di-n-butylamino-4,6-dimercapto-S-triazine
and 2,4,6-trimercapto-S-triazine;
compounds as obtained by adding hydrogen sulfide to a plurality of epoxy
groups of polyvalent epoxy compounds to thereby introduce a plurality of
mercapto groups; ester compounds as obtained by esterifying a plurality of
carboxyl groups of polyvalent carboxylic acids with mercaptoethanol. 
These may be used either alone respectively or in combinations with each
other. Herein, the carboxyl-group-containing mercaptans are compounds
having one mercapto group and one carboxyl group, such as thioglycolic
acid, mercaptopropionic acid, and thiosalicylic acid.</p> <p num="0032">The polyfunctional monomer, as used in the process according to
the present invention, is a compound having at least two polymerizable
unsaturated groups per molecule. A monomer of which the number of
the polymerizable unsaturated groups per molecule is 2 is referred to as
bifunctional monomer, and a monomer of which the number of the
polymerizable unsaturated groups per molecule is 3 is referred to as
trifunctional monomer. The polyfunctional monomer, as used in the
present invention, needs to be the compound having at least two
polymerizable unsaturated groups (i.e. bifunctional or more
polyfunctional monomer) in view of bonding the block copolymers to
each other, but it is generally preferable that the number of the
polymerizable unsaturated groups is not too large, for example, the bi- or
trifunctional monomer is preferably used, because compounds having at
least four polymerizable unsaturated groups might be considered more
preferable in view of increasing the number of the bonding structures to
bond the block copolymers to each other, but because when the number
of the polymerizable unsaturated groups is not smaller than 4, the
resultant copolymer would form a network structure to easily become a
gel during the polymerization.</p><p num="0033">Examples of the polyfunctional monomer, as used in the production
process according to the present invention, include: diester compounds as
formed from diols and (meth)acrylic acid, such as ethylene glycol
di(meth)acrylate, polyethylene glycol di(meth)acrylate, propylene glycol 
di(meth)acrylate, polypropylene glycol di(meth)acrylate, 1,3-butylene
glycol di(meth)acrylate, 1,6-hexanediol di(meth)acrylate, neopentyl glycol
di(meth)acrylate, 2-hydroxy-1,3-di(meth)acryloxypropane, 2,2-bis[4-(acryloxyethoxy)phenyl]propane,
2,2-bis[4-(methacryloxyethoxy)phenyl]propane,
2,2-bis[4-(acryloxypolyethoxy)phenyl]propane,
2,2-bis[4-(methacryloxypolyethoxy)phenyl]propane,
and 2-hydroxy-1-acryloxy-3-methacryloxypropane;
polyester compounds as formed from compounds
having at least three hydroxyl groups per molecule and (meth)acrylic
acid, such as trimethylolpropane tri(meth)acrylate, tetramethylolmethane
tri(meth)acrylate, tetramethylolmethane tetra(meth)acrylate,
pentaerythritol tetrakis(meth)acrylate, and dipentaerythritol
hexakis(meth)acrylate; allyl (meth)acrylate; and divinylbenzene. These
may be used either alone respectively or in combinations with each other.</p><p num="0034">In the production process according to the present invention, the
weight ratio of the polyfunctional monomer to the polyvalent mercaptan
(weight of polyfunctional monomer/weight of polyvalent mercaptan) is
preferably less than 2, more preferably in the range of 0.05 to 1 both
inclusive. Because, in the case where this weight ratio is not less than 2,
the number of polyfunctional monomer units as included per molecule
of the block copolymer is so large that the resultant copolymer might
form a network structure to become a gel during the polymerization.</p><p num="0035">In the production process according to the present invention, the
weight ratio of the polyfunctional monomer to the polymerizable
monomers (weight of polyfunctional monomer/total of polymerizable
monomers) is preferably less than 0.05, more preferably in the range of
0.001 to 0.01, but not including 0.01. Because, in the case where this 
weight ratio is not less than 0.05, the viscosity during the production is
high unfavorably for the productivity, and because, in the case where the
above weight ratio is further increased, the resultant copolymer might
form a network structure to become a gel during the polymerization.
Herein, the total of the polymerizable monomers is the total of the
weights of the polymerizable monomers as used in their respective
elementary steps of the multistep radical polymerization.</p><p num="0036">In the production process according to the present invention, the
radical polymerization may be carried out by conventional radical
polymerization methods such as bulk polymerization, solution
polymerization, suspension polymerization, and emulsion
polymerization. The polymerization temperature is preferably in the
range of 30 to 200 °C, more preferably 50 to 150 °C. Conventional radical
polymerization initiators may be used for the polymerization, and
examples thereof include: azo initiators such as 2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile
and 2,2'-azobis(2-methylbutyronitrile); and peroxide polymerization
initiators such as benzoyl peroxide. The amount of the polymerization
initiator as used is preferably not larger than 1/3, more preferably not
larger than 1/5, in terms of weight ratio to the polyvalent mercaptan.
Because, in the case where the polymerization initiator is used in an
amount larger than the above ratio, not only the polymer segments
which are extended from the polyvalent mercaptan segment, but also a
large amount of polymers which are extended from the polymerization
initiator are formed, with the result that the production efficiency of the
block copolymer is easily lowered, and further that the properties of the
resultant block copolymer were easily deteriorated.</p> <p num="0037">Other raw materials, which might be used in the process according 
to the present invention, are not especially limited, but common raw
materials which are used in conventional production processes for star-shaped
block copolymers may be used without modification.</p> <p num="0038">The hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive, according to the present
invention, comprises an acrylic block copolymer as an essential
component, wherein the acrylic block copolymer includes a (meth)acrylic
ester structural unit as an essential component in a ratio of 50 to 100
weight % of the entirety of the acrylic block copolymer. Herein, the
below-determined holding power (2) of the hot-melt pressure sensitive
adhesive comprising the acrylic block copolymer is not less than 100
minutes, preferably not less than 300 minutes, more preferably not less
than 500 minutes, most preferably not less than 1,000 minutes.</p> <p num="0039">Holding power (2): as determined by a process including the steps of:
preparing a sample by melt-coating a hot-melt pressure sensitive
adhesive in a thickness of 25 µm onto a 38-µm-thick PET film, wherein
the hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive includes the acrylic block
copolymer; and then attaching the sample onto a stainless steel sheet
such that the adhesion area would be 1.27 cm × 1.27 cm; and then pressing
the sample onto the stainless steel sheet by once running a 2-kg-heavy
roller thereon back and forth; and then adjusting the temperature of the
product to 60 °C for 30 minutes; and then applying a load of 1 kg to the
sample; and then measuring how long the sample has not fallen off from
the stainless steel sheet since the application of the load.</p><p num="0040">The mixing ratio of the acrylic block copolymer in the hot-melt
pressure sensitive adhesive according to the present invention is not
especially limited, but is preferably in the range of 1 to 100 weight %,
more preferably 10 to 100 weight %, still more preferably 20 to 100 weight 
%, most preferably 40 to 100 weight %, of the entirety of the hot-melt
pressure sensitive adhesive. In the case where the mixing ratio is out of
the above range, a hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive which exhibits
good heat resistance (at high temperature) despite having a low viscosity
might not be obtainable.</p><p num="0041">Even if the hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive according to the
present invention comprises the acrylic block copolymer only, this hot-melt
pressure sensitive adhesive exhibits sufficient performance as a hot-melt
pressure sensitive adhesive, but may further comprise conventional
tackifiers, waxes, and conventional pressure sensitive adhesives.</p><p num="0042">The tackifier serves to reduce the viscosity during the hot-melt
operation and to enhance the cohesion during the use. Examples of the
tackifier include rosin resins, terpene resins, aliphatic petroleum resins,
aromatic petroleum resins, coumarone-indene resins, alkylphenol resins,
and xylene resins. These may be used either alone respectively or in
combinations with each other.</p><p num="0043">The amount of the tackifier which is used is, for example, in the
range of 10 to 200 weight parts, preferably 10 to 100 weight parts, per 100
weight parts of the acrylic block copolymer. In the case where the amount
of the tackifier is smaller than the above range, the viscosity might not be
reduced or the cohesion might not be enhanced. On the other hand, in
the case where the amount of the tackifier is larger than the above range,
there is a possibility that, when the hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive
is used, the tack might be poor or the cohesion might be deficient.</p><p num="0044">The tackifier is, for example, combined into the hot-melt pressure
sensitive adhesive by mixing the tackifier with the reaction mixture
containing the acrylic block copolymer obtained by the above production 
process. The hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive may be obtained by
mixing the tackifier before or after the reaction mixture is devolatilized.</p><p num="0045">The wax is effective for reducing the viscosity during the hot-melt
operation. Examples of the wax include natural wax, paraffin wax,
polypropylene wax, polyethylene wax, and polymers of (meth)acrylates
having saturated alkyl groups with not fewer than 18 carbon atoms.
These may be used either alone respectively or in combinations with each
other.</p><p num="0046">The amount of the wax which is used is, for example, in the range of
0.01 to 100 weight parts, preferably 0.1 to 10 weight parts, per 100 weight
parts of the acrylic block copolymer. In the case where the amount of the
wax is smaller than the above range, the viscosity might not be reduced.
On the other hand, in the case where the amount of the wax is larger
than the above range, the adhesion or the pressure sensitive adhesion
tends to be deteriorated.</p><p num="0047">The wax is, for example, combined into the hot-melt pressure
sensitive adhesive by mixing the wax with the reaction mixture
containing the acrylic block copolymer obtained by the above production
process. The hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive may be obtained by
mixing the wax before or after the reaction mixture is devolatilized.</p><heading>(Effects and Advantages of the Invention):</heading><p num="0048">The new acrylic block copolymer, according to the present
invention, can exhibit higher heat resistance even without increasing its
molecular weight. Especially, if this acrylic block copolymer is a star-shaped
block copolymer, it has a structure in which star-shaped structures
are bonded to each other at their chain polymer segments, therefore this
copolymer can exhibit still higher heat resistance even without increasing 
its molecular weight.</p><p num="0049">The hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive, according to the present
invention, can exhibit still higher heat resistance, because this hot-melt
pressure sensitive adhesive comprises the above acrylic block copolymer
according to the present invention as an essential component.</p><p num="0050">Because the production process for an acrylic block copolymer,
according to the present invention, involves the joint use of a
polyfunctional monomer with a polymerizable monomer as monomers
in a polymerization reaction, this process can bond the resultant star-shaped
structures to each other through the polyfunctional monomer,
thereby easily and surely giving the star-shaped block copolymer as the
above new acrylic block copolymer according to the present invention.
Furthermore, during the polymerization in this process, a polymer
solution resultant from the first radical polymerization step is mixed
with a polymerizable monomer which is to be used in the second radical
polymerization step, thus carrying out the second radical polymerization
step in the presence of the polyfunctional monomer. Therefore, this
process can easily and surely give the star-shaped block copolymer as the
acrylic block copolymer wherein the star-shaped block copolymer exhibits
high heat resistance at high temperature.</p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</b></heading><p num="0051">Hereinafter, the present invention is more specifically illustrated by
the following examples of some preferred embodiments in comparison
with comparative examples not according to the invention. However,
the invention is not limited to the below-mentioned examples.</p><p num="0052">Hereinafter, unless otherwise noted, the units "%" and "part(s)" are
by weight. Incidentally, the number-average molecular weight (Mn) and 
the weight-average molecular weight (Mw) were determined in terms of
polystyrene by gel permeation chromatography (GPC).</p><p num="0053">The properties of the hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive were
measured in the following way.
<sl><li>Sample: as prepared by melt-coating the hot-melt pressure sensitive
adhesive in a thickness of 25 µm onto a 38-µm-thick PET film with a GPD
coater (made by Yuri Roll Machine Co., Ltd.).</li><li>Probe tack: as measured with a probe tack tester (made by Nichiban
Co., Ltd.) under conditions of: measurement temperature = 23 °C; relative
humidity = 60 %; contact period = 1 second; peeling rate = 1 cm/second.</li><li>180°-peel strength: as measured by a process including the steps of:
attaching the sample of 25 mm in width onto a stainless steel material
(adherend); and then pressing the sample by once running a 2-kg-heavy
roller thereon back and forth; and, 20 minutes later, peeling off the
sample from the stainless steel material at an angle of 180° and a tensile
rate of 300 mm/minute under conditions of: measurement temperature
= 23 °C; relative humidity = 60 %.</li><li>Holding power: as determined by a process including the steps of:
attaching the sample onto a stainless steel sheet such that the adhesion
area would be a predetermined value (1.27 cm × 1.27 cm); and then
pressing the sample onto the stainless steel sheet by once running a 2-kg-heavy
roller thereon back and forth; and then adjusting the temperature
of the product to a predetermined temperature (60 °C) for 30 minutes; and
then applying a load of 1 kg to the sample; and then measuring how long
the sample has not fallen off from the stainless steel sheet since the
application of the load, or measuring to what degree (unit: mm) the
position of the attached sample on the stainless steel sheet has varied in 
24 hours after the application of the load in the case where the sample has
not fallen off from the stainless steel sheet even if 24 hours have passed
since the application of the load.</li></sl></p><heading>-EXAMPLE 1-</heading><p num="0054">This is an example in which: a polymer solution, resultant from the
first radical polymerization step, and a polymerizable monomer, which
was to be used in the second radical polymerization step, were mixed all
together at once, and the polyfunctional monomer was used both in the
first and second radical polymerization steps.</p><heading><u style="single">First radical polymerization step</u>:</heading><p num="0055">First, 177.3 g of methyl methacrylate, 1.8 g of acrylic acid (both as first
(polymerizable) monomers), 0.9 g of tetraethylene glycol diacrylate (as
polyfunctional monomer) (made by Shin-Nakamura Chemical Industrial
Co., Ltd.; hereinafter abbreviated as TEGDA), and 140 g of ethyl acetate (as
solvent) were placed into a four-necked flask of 2 liters as equipped with a
stirrer, a nitrogen-introducing tube, dropping funnels, a thermometer,
and a condenser, and the internal temperature of the flask was then
elevated to 85 °C under nitrogen atmosphere. Then, after the internal
temperature had reached 85 °C, 3 g of pentaerythritol tetrakisthioglycolate
(as polyvalent mercaptan), 0.6 g of 2,2'-azobis(2-methylbutyronitrile) (as
radical polymerization initiator) (trade name: ABN-E, made by Japan
Hydrazine Co., Inc.; hereinafter abbreviated as ABN-E), and 20 g of ethyl
acetate (as solvent) were added to initiate polymerization.</p><p num="0056">At each of 50 minutes and 80 minutes later than the initiation of the
polymerization, 1.5 g of pentaerythritol tetrakisthioglycolate (as
polyvalent mercaptan), 0.3 g of ABN-E (as radical polymerization
initiator), and 10 g of ethyl acetate (as solvent) were added. </p><p num="0057">One hundred and forty minutes later, when the conversion of
methyl methacrylate had reached 84.9 %, methoxyphenol (as
polymerization inhibitor) was added in an amount of 0.018 g (100 weight
ppm), and cooling was carried out, thus completing the first radical
polymerization step.</p><heading><u style="single">Second radical polymerization step</u>:</heading><p num="0058">Next, 415. 8 g of butyl acrylate, 4.2 g of acrylic acid (both as second
(polymerizable) monomers), 0.9 g of TEGDA (as polyfunctional
monomer), and 0.6 g of ABN-E (as radical polymerization initiator) were
added to a polymer solution, resultant from the first radical
polymerization step, to prepare a mixed solution.</p><p num="0059">Next, 400 g of ethyl acetate (as solvent) was placed into another flask
and then heated to 80 °C so as to be refluxed. Then, a portion (30 weight
%) of the mixed solution as obtained above was added into this ethyl
acetate under reflux to initiate the second radical polymerization reaction.</p><p num="0060">After 10 minutes from the initiation of the reaction, the rest of the
mixed solution was dropwise added over a 2-hour period.</p><p num="0061">At each of 30 minutes and 60 minutes later than the completion of
the dropwise addition, 0.2 g of ABN-E (as radical polymerization initiator)
and 5 g of ethyl acetate (as solvent) were added. The reaction solution
was reacted under reflux for another 2 hours to end the polymerization.</p><heading><u style="single">Post-treatment step</u>:</heading><p num="0062">Volatile components, such as ethyl acetate (solvent) and residual
monomers, were removed from the resultant reaction solution with a
twin-screw extruder, thus obtaining a colorless transparent star-shaped
block copolymer as an acrylic block copolymer.</p><heading><u style="single">Measurement</u>:</heading><p num="0063">The resultant star-shaped block copolymer had a number-average
molecular weight (Mn) of 31,000 and a weight-average molecular weight
(Mw) of 241,000. This star-shaped block copolymer itself was regarded as a
hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive. The pressure sensitive adhesive
properties thereof are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>-EXAMPLE 2-</heading><p num="0064">This is an example in which: a polymer solution, resultant from the
first radical polymerization step, and a polymerizable monomer, which
was to be used in the second radical polymerization step, were mixed all
together at once, and the polyfunctional monomer was used only in the
second radical polymerization step.</p><p num="0065">A star-shaped block copolymer was obtained as an acrylic block
copolymer in the same way as of Example 1 except that the TEGDA (as
polyfunctional monomer) was not used in the first radical
polymerization step.</p><p num="0066">The pressure sensitive adhesive properties of this star-shaped block
copolymer are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>-EXAMPLE 3-</heading><p num="0067">This is an example in which: a polymer solution, resultant from the
first radical polymerization step, and a polymerizable monomer, which
was to be used in the second radical polymerization step, were dropwise
added separately from each other to mix them together, and the
polyfunctional monomer was used both in the first and second radical
polymerization steps.</p><p num="0068">The polymer solution, resultant from the same first radical
polymerization step as of Example 1, was subjected to the second radical
polymerization step as follows: </p><p num="0069">First, 415. 8 g of butyl acrylate, 4.2 g of acrylic acid (both as second
(polymerizable) monomers), 0.9 g of TEGDA (as polyfunctional
monomer), and 0.6 g of ABN-E (as radical polymerization initiator) were
mixed to prepare a polymerizable monomer solution which was to be
used in the second radical polymerization step.</p><p num="0070">Next, 400 g of ethyl acetate (as solvent) was placed into another flask
and then heated to 80 °C so as to be refluxed. Then, a portion (30 weight
%) of the above polymer solution, resultant from the first radical
polymerization step, and a portion (30 weight %) of the polymerizable
monomer solution, as prepared above, were added separately from each
other into this ethyl acetate under reflux to initiate the second radical
polymerization reaction. After 10 minutes from the initiation of the
reaction, the rest of the above polymer solution and the rest of the above
polymerizable monomer solution were dropwise added separately from
each other over a 2-hour period.</p><p num="0071">At each of 30 minutes and 60 minutes later than the completion of
the dropwise addition, 0.2 g of ABN-E (as radical polymerization initiator)
and 5 g of ethyl acetate (as solvent) were added. The reaction solution
was reacted under reflux for another 2 hours to end the second radical
polymerization step.</p><p num="0072">Thereafter, the procedure was carried out in the same way as of
Example 1, thus obtaining a star-shaped block copolymer as an acrylic
block copolymer.</p><p num="0073">The pressure sensitive adhesive properties of this star-shaped block
copolymer are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>-COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 1-</heading><p num="0074">This is an example of JP-A-10-287721 in which: the polyfunctional 
monomer was used only in the first radical polymerization step, and a
polymerizable monomer, which was to be used in the second radical
polymerization step, was dropwise added to a polymer solution resultant
from the first radical polymerization step.</p><p num="0075">The second radical polymerization step was initiated subsequently to
the attainment of the conversion of methyl methacrylate to 84.9 % in the
first radical polymerization step of Example 1. First, 415.8 g of butyl
acrylate, 4.2 g of acrylic acid (both as second (polymerizable) monomers),
and 400 g of ethyl acetate (as solvent) were dropwise added from the
dropping funnels to the resultant reaction solution over a 2-hour period.</p><p num="0076">At each of 30 minutes and 60 minutes later than the completion of
the dropwise addition, 0.2 g of ABN-E (as radical polymerization initiator)
and 5 g of ethyl acetate (as solvent) were added. Another 60 minutes
later, 0.6 g of azobisisobutyronitrile (as radical polymerization initiator)
(trade name: ABN-R, made by Japan Hydrazine Co., Inc.) and 10 g of ethyl
acetate (as solvent) were added. The reaction solution was reacted under
reflux for another 2 hours and then cooled down to room temperature to
complete the polymerization reaction.</p><p num="0077">Volatile components, such as ethyl acetate (solvent) and residual
monomers, were removed from the resultant reaction solution with a
twin-screw extruder, thus obtaining a colorless transparent star-shaped
block copolymer. The resultant copolymer had a number-average
molecular weight (Mn) of 29,500 and a weight-average molecular weight
(Mw) of 156,000. This star-shaped block copolymer itself was regarded as a
hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive. The pressure sensitive adhesive
properties thereof are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>-COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 2-</heading><p num="0078">This is an example of JP-A-10-287721 in which: the polyfunctional
monomer was used only in the second radical polymerization step, and a
polymerizable monomer, which was to be used in the second radical
polymerization step, was dropwise added to a polymer solution resultant
from the first radical polymerization step.</p><p num="0079">A star-shaped block copolymer was obtained in the same way as of
Comparative Example 1 except that the types of the first and second
(polymerizable) monomers, the amount of the polyvalent mercaptan, the
type and amount of the polyfunctional monomer, and the step involving
the use of the polyfunctional monomer were changed to those of Table 1,
which further shows the results of the properties of the resultant
copolymer as measured in the same way as above. <tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2"/><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="4">Example</entry><entry nameend="8" align="center" namest="7">Comparative Example</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2"/><entry align="center" namest="4">1</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">2</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">3</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">1</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">2</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="10">Composition of polymer</entry><entry align="center">First monomer</entry><entry align="center">Methyl methacrylate</entry><entry align="center">177.3</entry><entry align="center">177.3</entry><entry align="center">177.3</entry><entry align="center">177.3</entry><entry align="center">177.3</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="3">Acrylic acid</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">1.8</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">1.8</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">1.8</entry><entry align="center"  namest="7">1.8</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">1.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">Second monomer</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">Ethyl acrylate </entry><entry align="center" namest="4">---</entry><entry align="center"  namest="5">---</entry><entry align="center"  namest="6">---</entry><entry align="center"  namest="7">---</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">---</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="3">Butyl acrylate</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">415.8</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">415.8</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">415.8</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">415.8</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">415.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="3">2-Ethylhexyl acrylate</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">---</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">---</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">---</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">---</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">---</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="3">Acrylic acid</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">4.2</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">4.2</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">4.2</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">4.2</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">4.2</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Polyvalent mercaptan (parts)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">6</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">6</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">6</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">6</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">8</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Polyfunctional monomer (parts)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">TEGDA<!--footnotes removed--> 0.9 + 0.9</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">TEGDA<!--footnotes removed--> 0.9</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">TEGDA<!--footnotes removed--> 0.9 + 0.9</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">TEGDA<!--footnotes removed--> 0.9</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">TEGDA<!--footnotes removed--> 0.9</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Step(s) in which polyfunctional monomer is used</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">First step and second step</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">Second step</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">First step and second step</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">First step </entry><entry align="center" namest="8">Second step</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Polyfunctional monomer /all monomers (wt)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">0.003</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">0.0015</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">0.003</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">0.0015</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">0.0015</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Polyfunctional monomer /polyvalent mercaptan (wt)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">0.3</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">0.15</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">0.3</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">0.15</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">0.15</entry></row><row><entry align="left" namest="1">Properties of polymer</entry><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Number-average molecular weight (Mn)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">31,000</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">26,700</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">29,800</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">29,500</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">28,600</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Weight-average molecular weight (Mw)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">241,000</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">216,000</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">239,000</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">156,000</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">269,000</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Probe tack (gf)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">610</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">650</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">630</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">700</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">770</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">180°-peel strength (g/25 mm)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">730</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">790</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">750</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">820</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">790</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Holding power<!--footnotes removed--> (mm, minutes)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">(0.1 mm) over 1440 minutes</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">420 minutes</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">(0.2 mm) over 1440 minutes</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">12 minutes</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">10 minutes</entry></row><row><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Viscosity (cps) at 180 °C</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">45,700</entry><entry align="center" namest="5">33,400</entry><entry align="center" namest="6">39,800</entry><entry align="center" namest="7">30,500</entry><entry align="center" namest="8">27,500<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0080">Both in Comparative Examples 1 and 2, the star-shaped block
copolymers were obtained by the multistep radical polymerization
involving the use of the polyvalent mercaptan. Comparative Examples 1
and 2 are only different from Examples 1 to 3 in that the uniform mixing 
of the polymer solution, resultant from the first radical polymerization
step, with the polymerizable monomer, which is to be used in the second
radical polymerization step, is not carried out in the second radical
polymerization step in Comparative Examples 1 and 2.</p><p num="0081">From the comparison of Example 1 with Comparative Example 1
and the comparison of Example 2 with Comparative Example 2, it would
be well understood that if the adhesion area is set to 1.27 cm × 1.27 cm,
falling-off occurs after about 10 minutes in the Comparative Examples,
whereas the star-shaped block copolymers which are acrylic block
copolymers according to the present invention exhibit high holding
power without causing the falling-off even after 420 to 1,440 minutes.</p><p num="0082">Various details of the invention may be changed without departing
from its spirit not its scope. Furthermore, the foregoing description of the
preferred embodiments according to the present invention is provided
for the purpose of illustration only, and not for the purpose of limiting
the invention as defined by the appended claims and their equivalents.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An acrylic block copolymer, which comprises a (meth)acrylic
ester structural unit as an essential component in a ratio of 50 to 100
weight % of the entirety of the acrylic block copolymer and has a holding
power of not less than 100 minutes,
wherein the holding power is determined by a process including the
steps of: preparing a sample by melt-coating a hot-melt pressure sensitive
adhesive in a thickness of 25 µm onto a 38-µm-thick PET film, wherein
the hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive includes the acrylic block
copolymer; and then attaching the sample onto a stainless steel sheet
such that the adhesion area would be 1.27 cm × 1.27 cm; and then pressing
the sample onto the stainless steel sheet by once running a 2-kg-heavy
roller thereon back and forth; and then adjusting the temperature of the
product to 60 °C for 30 minutes; and then applying a load of 1 kg to the
sample; and then measuring how long the sample has not fallen off from
the stainless steel sheet since the application of the load.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>An acrylic block copolymer according to claim 1, which is a star-shaped
block copolymer comprising a plurality of star-shaped structures
in which at least three chain polymer segments are radially extended
from a central polyvalent mercaptan segment, wherein the plurality of
star-shaped structures are bonded to each other at their chain polymer
segments, and wherein the central polyvalent mercaptan segment is a
residual portion resultant from dissociation of protons from mercapto
groups of a polyvalent mercaptan.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>An acrylic block copolymer according to claim 1 or 2, wherein
the holding power is not less than 1,000 minutes.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive, which comprises an
acrylic block copolymer as an essential component, wherein the acrylic
block copolymer includes a (meth)acrylic ester structural unit as an
essential component in a ratio of 50 to 100 weight % of the entirety of the
acrylic block copolymer and has a holding power of not less than 100
minutes,
wherein the holding power is determined by a process including the
steps of: preparing a sample by melt-coating a hot-melt pressure sensitive
adhesive in a thickness of 25 µm onto a 38-µm-thick PET film, wherein
the hot-melt pressure sensitive adhesive includes the acrylic block
copolymer; and then attaching the sample onto a stainless steel sheet
such that the adhesion area would be 1.27 cm × 1.27 cm; and then pressing
the sample onto the stainless steel sheet by once running a 2-kg-heavy
roller thereon back and forth; and then adjusting the temperature of the
product to 60 °C for 30 minutes; and then applying a load of 1 kg to the
sample; and then measuring how long the sample has not fallen off from
the stainless steel sheet since the application of the load.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A production process for an acrylic block copolymer, which
comprises the multistep radical polymerization in the presence of a
polyvalent mercaptan wherein the elementary steps of the multistep
radical polymerization differ in polymerizable monomers as used
therein, wherein at least one of the elementary steps of the multistep
radical polymerization involves the joint use of a polyfunctional
monomer with the polymerizable monomer, wherein the second radical
polymerization step among the elementary steps of the multistep radical
polymerization includes the steps of: all at once mixing a polymer
solution, resultant from the first radical polymerization step, with a
polymerizable monomer which is to be used in the second radical
polymerization step; and then polymerizing the resultant mixture in the
presence of the polyfunctional monomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A production process for an acrylic block copolymer, which
comprises the multistep radical polymerization in the presence of a
polyvalent mercaptan wherein the elementary steps of the multistep
radical polymerization differ in polymerizable monomers as used
therein, wherein at least one of the elementary steps of the multistep
radical polymerization involves the joint use of a polyfunctional
monomer with the polymerizable monomer, wherein the second radical
polymerization step among the elementary steps of the multistep radical
polymerization includes the step of gradually adding a polymer solution,
resultant from the first radical polymerization step, and a polymerizable
monomer, which is to be used in the second radical polymerization step,
to a vessel to mix them, while polymerizing the resultant mixture in the
presence of the polyfunctional monomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A production process according to claim 5 or 6, wherein the
weight ratio of the polyfunctional monomer to the polyvalent mercaptan
(weight of polyfunctional monomer/weight of polyvalent mercaptan) is
less than 2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A production process according to any one of claims 5 to 7,
wherein the weight ratio of the polyfunctional monomer to the total of
the polymerizable monomers (weight of polyfunctional monomer/total
weight of polymerizable monomers) is less than 0.05.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>