<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1029903-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1029903" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22960855" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000823"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1029903-A1" status="new" fvid="22901158"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1029903</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000823</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00301278-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00301278</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000218</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-25357699-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>25357699</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990219</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C20</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Lösungsmittel zur Auslaufbeschränkung für pigmentierte Tinten und für auf Farbstoffen basierende Tinten</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Bleed control solvents for pigmented and dye-based inks</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Solvants pour le contrôle des bavures pour encres pigmentées et pour encres à base de colorants</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0801118-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0801118</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0859037-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0859037</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0872344-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0872344</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-2316412-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2316412</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HEWLETT PACKARD CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HEWLETT-PACKARD COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hewlett-Packard Company</last-name><address><street>3000 Hanover Street</street><city>Palo Alto, California 94304</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>REHMAN ZIA</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>REHMAN, ZIA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>REHMAN, ZIA</last-name><address><street>3010 NE Glacier Way</street><city>Corvallis, OR 97330</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Colgan, Stephen James</last-name><address><street>CARPMAELS &amp;amp; RANSFORD 43 Bloomsbury Square</street><city>London WC1A 2RA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Two classes of solvents, organic esters and diols and triols, help to reduce bleed
between black (pigment-containing) inks and color (water-soluble dye-based) inks
when used in formulating inks that contain self-dispersed pigments. The solvents help
self-dispersed pigments to agglomerate by producing successful mutual collisions
when the electrostatic potential is reduced with positively charged color inks. It
appears that these solvents may be changing the dielectric constant of the ink, thereby
reducing the repulsion potential of the pigment particles themselves.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">TECHNICAL FIELD</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to generally to ink-jet inks, and, more particularly,
to ink-jet inks with improved bleed control.</p><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND ART</u></heading><p num="0002">In ink development work with a new technology, one of the most important
parameters to be considered is the bleed control between black and color inks, often
referred to as "K/C control" or "K/C bleed". Using self-dispersed pigments as the colorant
tends to result in relatively poor bleed control, compared to pigments that use a
separate dispersant molecule. In these inks, the black ink contains the pigment, while
the color inks contain one or more appropriate water-soluble dyes (cyan, yellow, magenta).</p><p num="0003">One might ask why it is so difficult to control bleed wit self-dispersed pigments
even tough they have a negative charge and the color ink is low pH. The answer
to this question is crucial in inventing a solvent system tat can reduce bleed.
Self dispersed pigments, such as available from Cabot Corp., have negatively-charged
groups that are covalently-bonded to the pigment surface. Theoretically, either a positive
charge from cations, or a proton from a low pH color ink in the vicinity of two
negatively-charged black, self-dispersed pigment particles should lower their electrostatic
potential and allow the pigments to come closer and agglomerate. This apparently 
does not happen to the desired extent with the self-dispersed pigment and they
don't crash with the same intensity on the paper. Without subscribing to any particular
theory, it appears tat their mutual collisions do not lead to agglomeration; in other
words, their collisions are elastic in nature in that the two colliding particles bounce
back away from each other. This is in contrast to a pigment-based ink using a separate
dispersant, such as disclosed in U.S. Patent 5,500,082, issued to H. Matrick et al. Such
dispersant molecules with large "tentacles" (long chain carbons) sticking out and
which have a more chance to "stick together" in the event of a collision.</p><p num="0004">Thus, there is a need to provide an ink containing a self-dispersing pigment that
evidences improved bleed control.</p><heading><u style="single">DISCLOSURE OF INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0005">In accordance with the present invention, two classes of solvents that help to
reduce bleed are used in formulating inks that contain self-dispersed pigments. The two
classes are organic esters and certain diols and triols.</p><p num="0006">The solvents disclosed herein help self-dispersed pigments to agglomerate by
producing successful mutual collisions when the electrostatic potential is reduced with
positively charged color inks. The details of this mechanism are not understood
clearly yet. These solvents could be changing the dielectric constant of the ink,
thereby reducing the repulsion potential of the pigment particles themselves.</p><heading><u style="single">BEST MODES FOR CARRYING OUT THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0007">In accordance with the present invention, bleed control between black (K) inks
containing self-dispersed pigments and color (CYM - cyan, yellow, magenta) inks
containing water-soluble dyes is improved by incorporating either an organic ester or a
diol in the black ink formulation. </p><heading><u style="single">1. Organic Esters</u></heading><p num="0008">Non-surfactant organic esters having the formula R-COOR' may be suitably
employed in the practice of the present invention, where R and R' are independently
hydrogen, alkanes, alkenes, alkynes, alkoxies, carboxylates, and mixtures thereof, including
both straight chain and branched chain structures and further including all
stercoisomers. Examples of the ester group (-COOR') include citrate, succinate, lactate,
formate, gluconate, tartrate, malonate, fumarate, malate, sebacate, laurate, glutarate,
acetate, oxylate, adipicate, pimelicate, subericate, azelaicate and mixtures
thereof. The number of carbon atoms in the R and R' groups ranges from 1 to 5. The
organic esters that are useful in the practice of the present invention are those that are
solvents, not surfactants.</p><p num="0009">Examples of such non-surfactant organic esters include triethyl citrate, triethyl
citrate, triethyl citrate, and acetyl triethyl citrate; these esters are available under the
tradenames Citroflex 2, Citroflex 1, Citroflex A1, Citroflex A2, respectively, all from
Morflex Inc.</p><p num="0010">The concentration of the organic esters employed in the practice of the present
invention is within the range of about 0.5 to 7 wt%, preferably about 2 to 4 wt%, and
most preferably about 3 wt%, of the ink composition.</p><heading><u style="single">2. Diols and Triols</u></heading><p num="0011">Several diols and triols were tested and showed substantial improvement in
black/color bleed. These diols are 2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol (hexylene glycol), 1,2-octanediol,
2-methyl-1,3-propanediol, 3-methyl-1,5-pentanediol, 2,5-dimethyl-2,5-hexanediol,
and 1,2-hexanediol. The triol is 3-methyl-1,3,5-pentanetriol.</p><p num="0012">The concentration range of the diols/triols, other than 1,2-octanediol, employed
in the practice of the present invention is within the range of about 0.1 to 10
wt%, preferably about 1 to 7 wt%, and most preferably about 2 to 5 wt%, of the ink
composition. The concentration range of 1,2-octanediol is within the range of about
0.25 to 1 wt%, preferably about 0.5 wt%, of the ink composition. </p><p num="0013">Not all diols are useful in reducing bleed between black and color inks. Examples
of such diols include 3-hexyne-2,5-diol, and 2,5-dimethyl-3-hexyne-2,5-diol.</p><heading><u style="single">3. Ink Compositions - Black Inks</u></heading><p num="0014">The black inks of the invention comprise a pigment and a vehicle. Specifically,
the black inks of the present invention comprise about 5 to 50 wt%, preferably about
10 to 25 wt%, water-miscible organic co-solvent, about 0.05 to 10 wt%, preferably
about 0.5 to 10 wt%, pigment, about 0.005 to 50 wt%, preferably about 0.1 to 10 wt%,
more preferably about 0.5 to 5 wt%, durable latex polymer, about 0.005 to 50
wt%, preferably about 0.1 to 10 wt%, more preferably about 0.5 to 5 wt%, primer latex
polymer, and water, in addition to the ester or diol/triol additive discussed above.
Other components and additives to the ink may also be present, as discussed below.</p><heading><u style="single">3A. Self-Dispersed Pigments</u></heading><p num="0015">In one embodiment, the colorant employed in the ink is a self-dispersing pigment.
Such pigments suitable for use in the practice of the present invention include
all chemically-modified, water-dispersible pigments known for use in ink-jet printing.
These chemical modifications impart water-dispersibility to the pigment precursors
that encompass all organic pigments.</p><p num="0016">For self-dispersibility or water solubility, the pigments herein are modified by
the addition of one or more organic groups comprising at least one aromatic group or
a C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>12</sub> alkyl group and at least one ionic or ionizable group. The ionizable group is
one that forms its ionic groups in the aqueous medium. The ionic group may be anionic
or cationic. The aromatic groups may be further substituted or unsubstituted. Examples
include phenyl or naphthyl groups and the ionic group is sulfonic acid, sulfinic
acid, phosphonic acid, carboxylic acid, ammonium, quaternary ammonium, or phosphonium
group.</p><p num="0017">Depending on the process selected, the pigment can either be anionic or cationic
in character. As commercially available, the anionic chromophores are usually 
associated with sodium or potassium cations, and the cationic chromophores are usually
associated with chloride or sulfate anions.</p><p num="0018">For modification, one preferred method is treatment of a carbon black pigment
with aryl diazonium salts containing at least one acidic functional group. Examples of
axyl diazonium salts include those prepared from sulfinic acid, 4-aminobenzoic acid,
4-aminosalicylic acid, 7-amino-4-hydroxy-2-naphthylenesulfonic acid, aminophenylboronic
acid, aminophenylphosphonic acid, and metalinic acid.</p><p num="0019">Ammonium, quaternary ammonium groups, quaternary phosphonium groups,
and protonated amine groups represent examples of cationic groups that can be attached
to the same organic groups discussed above.</p><p num="0020">Reference is made to U.S. Patents 5,707,432; 5,630,868; 5,571,311; and
5,554,739 for a discussion of modified carbon black pigments and methods of attaching
the functionalized groups.</p><p num="0021">The following water-insoluble pigments are useful in the practice of the invention;
however, this listing is not intended to limit the invention. The following
pigments are available from Cabot: Monarch® 1400, Monarch® 1300, Monarch®
1100, Monarch® 1000, Monarch® 900, Monarch® 880, Monarch® 800, and Monarch®
700. The following pigments are available from Ciba-Geigy: Igralite® Rubine
4BL. The following pigments are available from Columbian: Raven 7000, Raven
5750, Raven 5250, Raven 5000, and Raven 3500. The following pigments are available
from Degussa: Color Black FW 200, Color Black FW 2, Color Black FW 2V,
Color Black FW 1, Color Black FW 18, Color Black S 160, Color Black S 170, Special
Black 6, Special Black 5, Special Black 4A, Special Black 4, Printex U, Printex
V, Printex 140U, and Printex 140V. The following pigment is available from DuPont:
Tipure® R-101. The following pigment is available from Hoechst: Permanent Rubine
F6B. The following pigment is available from Sun Chemical: LHD9303 Black.</p><p num="0022">Self-dispersing pigments are also commercially available from Cabot as Cab-O-Jet®
200 and Cab-O-Jet® 300.</p><p num="0023">In another embodiment herein, the black pigment is dispersed in the ink composition
with the aid of a dispersing agent. Such black pigments include any black 
pigment that is dispersed with a dispersant having an anionic functionality, for example,
the Joncryl polymers available from S.C. Johnson Polymer. Of course, any other
dispersant exhibiting anionic charges may be employed in the practice of the present
invention. For a more complete discussion of black pigments and anionic dispersants,
see U.S. Patents 5,181,045 and 5,785,743.</p><heading><u style="single">3B. Latex Polymers</u></heading><p num="0024">Ink-jet inks have recently been developed that utilize latex polymers to
achieve smearfastness. Examples of such latex polymers are disclosed in, for example,
application Serial Number 09/120,270 and application Serial No. 09/120,046, both
filed July 21, 1998.</p><p num="0025">There are two types of such latex polymers employed in the practice of the
present invention. The first type is referred to as "durable core/shell" polymers and are
given by the formula
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">[(A)<sub>m</sub> (B)<sub>n</sub> (C)<sub>p</sub> (D)<sub>q</sub> (E)<sub>r</sub>]<sub>x</sub></st32:che>
wherein A, B, C, D, and E represent functionalities as follows:
<sl><li>A = at least one hydrophobic component contributing to improved durable,
film-forming properties selected from moieties which, when homopolymerized
to a solid state, have a glass transition temperature (T<sub>g</sub>) in the
range between -150°C to +25°C;</li><li>B = at least one hydrophobic and solvent barrier moiety used to adjust
the T<sub>g</sub> of the hydrophobic component of the polymer (I) which, when homopolymerized
to a solid state, has a T<sub>g</sub> greater than +25°C;</li> <li>C = at least one hydrophilic component, selected from a wide variety
of water-soluble monomers (optional);</li><li>D = at least one UV absorber (optional);</li><li>E = a moiety having at least one highly polar functional group (optional); </li><li>m = 5 to 95 wt%;</li><li>n = 5 to 95 wt%;</li> <li>p = 0 to 60 wt%;</li> <li>q = 0 to 50 wt%;</li> <li>r = 0 to 40 wt%;</li><li><st32:f xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">m + n + p + q + r = 100 wt%</st32:f>; and</li><li>x = 1 to 100,000.</li></sl></p><p num="0026">Preferably, the final T<sub>g</sub> of the polymer(s) (I) is within the range of about -25°
to +110°C, and more preferably, the final T<sub>g</sub> is within the range of about -15° to
+90°C, and most preferably within the range of about -10°C to +75°C.</p><p num="0027">The molecular weight (weight avenge) of polymer (I) is between about 1,000
and 2,000,000, preferably between about 5,000 and 500,000, and most preferably
between about 10,000 and 70,000.</p><p num="0028">Either the C moiety or the E moiety must be present in the polymer to provide
a polymer having either a hydrophilic portion or a highly polar portion. Alternatively,
one or more surfactants may be used in conjunction with polymer (I), whether in the
presence or the absence of the C or E, or both, moieties. The surfactant(s) may be anionic,
cationic, non-ionic, or zwitterionic.</p><p num="0029">The second type of latex polymers is referred to as "primer core/shell" polymers,
which also have a hydrophilic portion and a hydrophobic portion and have the
following general structure given by formula (II)
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">[(A)<sub>m</sub> (B)<sub>n</sub> (C)<sub>p</sub> (E)<sub>r</sub>]<sub>y</sub></st32:che>
wherein A, B, C, and E are as described above and where m, n, and r are as follows:
<sl><li>m = 0 to 90 wt%, preferably 10 to 60 wt%, and more preferably 15 to
50 wt%;</li><li>n = 0 to 90 wt%, preferably 10 to 60 wt%, and more preferably 15 to 50
wt%; </li><li>p = 0 to 90 wt%, preferably 10 to 60 wt%, and more preferably 15 to
50 wt%;</li><li>r = 0.01 to 100 wt%, preferably 0.01 to 60 wt%, and more preferably 1
to 40 wt%;</li><li><st32:f xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">m + n + r = 100 wt%</st32:f>; and</li><li>y = 1 to 100,000, preferably 10 to 10,000, and more preferably 100 to
1,000.</li></sl>
Preferably, either m or n is non-zero.</p><p num="0030">TheT<sub>g</sub> of the primer core/shell polymers is within the range of about -100° to
+100°C, preferably within the range of about -25° to +25°C, and more preferably
within the range of about 0° to +25°C.</p><p num="0031">The molecular weight (weight average) of polymer (II) is between about 100
and 2,000,000, preferably between about 1,000 and 500,000, and most preferably
between about 5,000 and 300,000.</p><p num="0032">The durable and primer core/shell polymers are used with pigment colorants to
disperse them in aqueous-based inks.</p><heading><u style="single">3C. Vehicle</u></heading><p num="0033">The vehicle comprises one or more co-solvents and water. The co-solvents
comprise one or more organic, water-miscible solvents commonly employed in ink-jet
printing. Classes of co-solvents employed in the practice of this invention include, but
are not limited to, aliphatic alcohols, aromatic alcohols, diols, glycol ethers,
poly(glycol) ethers, caprolactams, formamides, acetamides, and long chain alcohols.
Examples of compounds employed in the practice of this invention include, but are
not limited to, primary aliphatic alcohols of 30 carbons or less, primary aromatic alcohols
of 30 carbons or less, secondary aliphatic alcohols of 30 carbons or less, secondary
aromatic alcohols of 30 carbons or less, 1,2-alcohols of 30 carbons or less, 1,3-alcohols
of 30 carbons or less, 1,ω-alcohols of 30 carbons or less, ethylene glycol alkyl
ethers, propylene glycol alkyl ethers, poly(ethylene glycol) alkyl ethers, higher
homologs of poly(ethylene glycol) alkyl ethers, poly(propylene glycol) alkyl ethers, 
higher homologs of poly(propylene glycol) alkyl ethers, N-alkyl caprolactams, unsubstituted
caprolactams, substituted formamides, unsubstituted formamides, substituted
acetamides, and unsubstituted acetamides. Specific examples of co-solvents that are
preferably employed in the practice of this invention include, but are not limited to, N-methyl
pyrrolidone, 1,5-pentanediol, 2-pyrrolidone, diethylene glycol, 1,3,5-(2-methyl)-pentanetriol,
tetramethylene sulfone, 3-methoxy-3-methylbutanol, glycerol,
and 1,2-alkyldiols.</p><p num="0034">The balance of the ink is water, together with other additives commonly added
to ink-jet inks, which are employed to optimize the properties of the ink for specific applications.
For example, as is well-known to those skilled in the art, biocides may be
used in the ink composition to inhibit growth of microorganisms, sequestering agents
such as EDTA may be included to eliminate deleterious effects of heavy metal impurities,
and buffer solutions may be used to control the pH of the ink. Other known additives
such as viscosity modifiers and other acrylic or non-acrylic polymers may be
added to improve various properties of the ink compositions as desired. The purity of
all components is that normally employed in conventional commercial practice of
formulating ink-jet inks.</p><p num="0035">The pH of the pigment-based dye may be adjusted to a slightly basic value,
say about 8.5, with potassium hydroxide, sodium hydroxide, sodium carbonate, or triethanol
amine.</p><heading><u style="single">4. Ink Compositions - Color Inks</u></heading><p num="0036">The color inks of the invention comprise at least one water-miscible dye and a
vehicle. Specifically, the color inks of the present invention comprise anionic dyes,
such as direct, acid, and basic dyes. Examples of anionic dyes include, but are not
limited to Food Black 2, Direct Black 19, Acid Blue 9, Direct Blue 199, Direct Red
227, and Acid Yellow 23. Examples of cationic dyes include, but are not limited to,
Basic Blue 3, Basic Violet 7, Basic Yellow 13, and Basic Yellow 51. The concentration
of such a dye preferably ranges from about 0.1 to 7 wt%. Less than about 0.1
wt% results in an ink of unacceptable lightness, while greater than about 7 wt% results 
in clogging of the orifices in the ink-jet pen. More preferably, the dye is present
within the range of about 0.1 to 4 wt% of the ink-jet ink composition. A mixture of
dyes may also be employed.</p><p num="0037">The vehicle and additive(s) for an ink-jet ink containing at least one water-miscible
dye are the same as for the pigment-based ink.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLES</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Example 1. Organic Ester</u>.</heading><p num="0038">A black ink was formulated with the following components:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="8"><dt>6 wt%</dt><dd>2-pyrollidone</dd><dt>7 wt%</dt><dd>3-hexyne-2,5-diol</dd><dt>3.5 wt%</dt><dd>triethyl citrate</dd><dt>3.8 wt%</dt><dd>LEG-1 (liponic ethylene glycol, available from Liponics)</dd><dt>3 wt%</dt><dd>durable latex polymer QX25A, comprising (hexyl acrylate)<sub>40</sub>
(methyl methacrylate)<sub>40</sub> (methyl polyethylene glycol (mw=2000)
methacrylate)<sub>20</sub></dd><dt>1 wt%</dt><dd>primer latex polymer QX26B, comprising (methyl
methacrylate)<sub>32</sub> (hexyl acrylate)<sub>46</sub> (methyl polyethylene glycol (mw=350)
methacrylate)<sub>12</sub> (acrylic acid)<sub>10</sub></dd><dt>3 wt%</dt><dd>pigment (Monarch 700 treated with p-aminobenzoic acid
(PABA) and amino dodecanoic acid (ADDA)</dd><dt>balance</dt><dd>water.</dd></dl>
The pH of the ink was adjusted to 8.5 with potassium hydroxide.</p><p num="0039">The color inks (cyan, yellow, and magenta) contained water-soluble dyes, and
comprised proprietary, development compositions.</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Example 1</u>.</heading><p num="0040">The CYMK inks of Example 1 were formulated, except that the triethyl citrate
was omitted from the black ink. </p><heading><u style="single">Results between Example 1 and Comparative Example 1</u>.</heading><p num="0041">Both CYMK sets of inks were printed on Gilbert Bond and Champion Data
Copy papers. A set of printing patterns, developed by Hewlett-Packard for testing bleed
control, was used. In testing bleed control, black and color inks are printed in various
combinations of adjacent patterns.</p><p num="0042">The ink of Example 1 was observed to evidence better black-to-color bleed
control than the ink of Comparative Example 1. Further, the ink of Example 1 bad better
long- and short-term decap than the ink of Comparative Example 1. The ink of Example
1 evidenced good start-up and printability.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2. Diol</u>.</heading><p num="0043">A black ink was formulated with the following components:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="8"><dt>6 wt%</dt><dd>2-pyrollidone</dd><dt>7 wt%</dt><dd>3-hexyne-2,5-diol</dd><dt>3 wt%</dt><dd>2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol</dd><dt>3.8 wt%</dt><dd>LEG-1</dd><dt>3 wt%</dt><dd>durable latex polymer QX25A (same as Example 1)</dd><dt>1 wt%</dt><dd>primer latex polymer QX26B (same as Example 1)</dd><dt>3 wt%</dt><dd>pigment (same as Example 1)</dd><dt>balance</dt><dd>water.</dd></dl>
The pH of the ink was adjusted to 8.5 with potassium hydroxide.</p><p num="0044">The color inks (cyan, yellow, and magenta) contained water-soluble dyes, and
comprised proprietary, development compositions.</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Example 2</u>.</heading><p num="0045">The CYMK inks of Example 2 were formulated, except that the 2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol
was omitted from the black ink. </p><heading><u style="single">Results between Example 2 and Comparative Example 2</u>.</heading><p num="0046">Both CYMK sets of inks were printed on Gilbert Bond and Champion Data
Copy papers. A set of printing patterns, developed by Hewlett-Packard for testing bleed
control, was used. In testing bleed control, black and color inks are printed in various
combinations of adjacent patterns.</p><p num="0047">The ink of Example 2 was observed to evidence better black-to-color bleed
control than the ink of Comparative Example 2. Further, the ink of Example 2 had better
long- and short-term decap than the ink of Comparative Example 2. The ink of Example
2 evidenced good start-up and printability.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 3. Diol</u>.</heading><p num="0048">A black ink was formulated with the following components:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="8"><dt>6 wt%</dt><dd>2-pyrollidone</dd><dt>7 wt%</dt><dd>3-hexyne-2,5-diol</dd><dt>0.5 wt%</dt><dd>1,2-octanediol</dd><dt>3.8 wt%</dt><dd>LEG-1</dd><dt>3 wt%</dt><dd>durable latex polymer QX25A (same as Example 1)</dd><dt>1 wt%</dt><dd>primer latex polymer QX26B (same as Example 1)</dd><dt>3 wt%</dt><dd>pigment (same as Example 1)</dd><dt>balance</dt><dd>water.</dd></dl>
The pH of the ink was adjusted to 8.5 with potassium hydroxide.</p><p num="0049">The color inks (cyan, yellow, and magenta) contained water-soluble dyes, and
comprised proprietary, development compositions.</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Example 3</u>.</heading><p num="0050">The CYMK inks of Example 3 were formulated, except that the 1,2-octanediol
was omitted from the black ink. </p><heading><u style="single">Results between Example 3 and Comparative Example 3</u>.</heading><p num="0051">Both CYMK sets of inks were printed on Gilbert Bond and Champion Data
Copy papers. A set of printing patterns, developed by Hewlett-Packard for testing bleed
control, was used. In testing bleed control, black and color inks are printed in various
combinations of adjacent patterns.</p><p num="0052">The ink of Example 3 was observed to evidence better black-to-color bleed
control than the ink of Comparative Example 3. Further, the ink of Example 3 had better
long- and short-term decap than the ink of Comparative Example 3. The ink of Example
3, however, evidenced feathering if the 1,2-octanediol was used at higher concentration
levels, greater than about 1 wt%.</p><heading><u style="single">INDUSTRIAL APPLICABILITY</u></heading><p num="0053">The organic esters and diols/triols, as disclosed herein, is expected to find use in
ink-jet inks for control of bleed between black and color inks.</p><p num="0054">Thus, there have been disclosed ink-jet ink compositions to which certain
organic esters or diols/triols have been added for the control of bleed between black and
color inks. It will be apparent to those skilled in this art that various changes and
modifications of an obvious nature may be made, and all such changes and
modifications are intended to fall within the scope of the appended claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An ink-jet ink composition for ink-jet printing in combination with at least
one water-soluble dye-based ink, said ink-jet ink composition containing a self-dispersing
pigment and a vehicle, said ink-jet ink composition further containing at least
one solvent selected from the group consisting of organic esters, diols, and triols,
present in an effective amount to reduce bleed between pigment-based inks and water-soluble
dye-based inks.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink of Claim 1 wherein said organic ester is R-COOR', where R
and R' are independently hydrogen, alkanes, alkyls, alkenes, alkynes, alkoxys,
carboxylates, and mixtures thereof, including both straight chain and branched chain
structures and further including all steroisomers and wherein R and R' each have from
1 to 5 carbon atoms.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink of Claim 2, wherein said -COOR' group is selected from the
group consisting of citrate, succinate, lactate, formate, gluconate, tartrate, malonate,
fumarate, malate, sebacate, laurate, glutarate, acetate, oxylate, adipicate, pimelicate,
subericate, azelaicate and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink of Claim 3 wherein said organic ester comprises at least one
ester selected from the group consisting of triethyl citrate, triethyl citrate, triethyl
citrate, and acetyl triethyl citrate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink of Claim 2 wherein said organic ester has a concentration in
said ink-jet ink ranging from about 0.5 to 7 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink of Claim 1 wherein said diol comprises at least one diol
selected from the group consisting of 2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol, 1,2-octanediol, 2-methyl-1,3-propanediol,
3-methyl-1,5-pentanediol, 2,5-dimethyl-2,5-hexanediol, 1,2-hexanediol,
and wherein said triol consists essentially of 3-methyl-1,3,5-pentanetriol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink of Claim 6 wherein said diol or said triol, other than 1,2-octanediol,
each has a concentration in said ink-jet ink ranging from about 0.1 to 10
wt% and wherein said 1,2-octanediol has a concentration ranging from about 0.25 to 1
wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The ink-jet ink of Claim 1 further containing at least one latex polymer
selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a)
[(A)m (B)n (C)p (D)q (E)r]x
wherein A, B, C, D, and E represent functionalities as follows:
<claim-text><claim-text>A = at least one hydrophobic component contributing to improved durable,
film-forming properties selected from moieties which, when homo-polymerized
to a solid state, have a glass transition temperature (Tg) in the
range between -150°C to +25°C;</claim-text><claim-text>B = at least one hydrophobic and solvent barrier moiety used to adjust
the Tg of the hydrophobic component of the polymer (I) which, when homo-polymerized
to a solid state, has a Tg greater than +25°C;</claim-text><claim-text>C = at least one hydrophilic component, selected from a wide variety
of water-soluble monomers (optional);</claim-text><claim-text>D = at least one UV absorber (optional);</claim-text><claim-text>E = a moiety having at least one highly polar functional group (optional);</claim-text><claim-text>m = 5 to 95 wt%;</claim-text><claim-text>n = 5 to 95 wt%;</claim-text><claim-text>p = 0 to 60 wt%;</claim-text><claim-text>q = 0 to 50 wt%;</claim-text><claim-text>r = 0 to 40 wt%;</claim-text><claim-text>m + n + p + q + r = 100 wt%; and</claim-text><claim-text>x = 1 to 100,000; and</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>(b)
[(A)m (B)n (C)p (E)r]y
wherein A, B, C, and E are as described above and where m, n, p, and r of formula
(II) are as follows:
<claim-text><claim-text>m = 0 to 90 wt%;</claim-text><claim-text>n = 0 to 90 wt%;</claim-text><claim-text>p = 0 to 90 wt%;</claim-text><claim-text>r = 0.01 to 100 wt%;</claim-text><claim-text>m + n + p + r = 100 wt%; and</claim-text><claim-text>y = 1 to 100,000.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method for reducing bleed between pigment-based inks containing a self-dispersing
pigment and a vehicle and water-soluble dye-based inks, said method
comprising adding to said ink-jet ink containing said self-dispersing pigment said
effective amount of said solvent selected from the group consisting of organic esters,
diols, and triols of Claim 1.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="156" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="242" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="157" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="238" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>