<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1069165-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1069165" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26511848" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010117"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1069165-A1" status="new" fvid="23019973"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1069165</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010117</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00305813-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00305813</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000710</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-19993199-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>19993199</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990714</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000138776-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000138776</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000511</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/16        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41M   5/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/16B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Tintenzusammensetzung, Schreibgerät, enthaltend diese Zusammensetzung und Verfahren zur Bildherstellung auf aufnehmender Oberfläche</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Ink composition, writing instrument containing same and method of forming image on receiving surface</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition d'encre, instrument d'écriture contenant cette encre et procédé pour former une image sur une surface réceptrice</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0393901-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0393901</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="FR-1492825-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>FR</country><doc-number>1492825</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-2058113-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2058113</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5667571-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5667571</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5972083-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5972083</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ADGER KOGYO CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ADGER KOGYO CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ADGER KOGYO CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>1175-6, Aza Teigai, Sezakicho</street><city>Soka-shi, Saitama-ken 340</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>IIJIMA ZENSHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>IIJIMA, ZENSHIRO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>IIJIMA, ZENSHIRO</last-name><address><street>c/o ADGER KOGYO Co. Ltd., 1175-6, Aza-Teigai</street><city>Sezaki-cho, Soka-shi, Saitama-ken</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Rackham, Anthony Charles</last-name><address><street>LLOYD WISE, TREGEAR &amp;amp; CO., Commonwealth House, 1-19 New Oxford Street</street><city>London WC1A 1LW</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country> </ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An ink containing a coloring agent dissolved in a
mixed solvent including a first solvent which is liquid at
20°C and which is polyalkylene glycol or an ethylene
glycol monoether and a second solvent selected from
monohydric alcohols, ketones, esters and halogenated
hydrocarbons. An image of the ink formed on an ink
permeable sheet penetrates through the sheet and is
transferred to a surface of a desired object overlaid with
the sheet.</p> </abstract> <description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention relates generally to an ink
composition for use in handicraft, tailor or embroidery
fields and, more specifically to an ink useful for forming
a copy image, corresponding to an original image on an ink
permeable sheet, on a receiving surface of an object such
as textile, leather, paper, plastic or metal. The present
invention is also directed to a writing instrument
containing the above ink composition and to a method of
forming an image on a receiving surface of an object.</p> <p num="0002">A tracing paper having an solid ink layer on one
surface thereof has been hitherto used to form, on a
receiving surface, a copy image corresponding to an
original image of a sheet. The tracing paper is
interposed between the receiving surface and the sheet
with the ink layer being in contact with the receiving
surface. The original image is then traced with a rigid,
sharp-tipped member so that the ink at pressed portions is
transferred to the receiving surface to form a copy image
thereon. This method has a problem because it is
difficult or troublesome to maintain the relative position
between the receiving surface and the image sheet
unchanged throughout the course of the tracing step.</p><p num="0003">U. S. Patent No. 5,972,083 assigned to Adger Kogyo
Co., Ltd. discloses a method of making a copy image on a
receiving surface of an object without using a tracing
paper. In this method, a surface bearing an original
pattern is overlaid with a transparent or translucent thin
sheet. The original pattern is then traced using a pen
containing a specific ink to form a copy pattern on the
sheet. The receiving surface of the object is overlaid
with the copy pattern-bearing sheet and the assembly is
heated with an iron, whereby the ink of the copy pattern 
penetrates through the sheet and is transferred to the
receiving surface to form the image thereon. The ink used
in this method contains an organic solvent in which a
first, white coloring agent selected from salicylic acid
and acetylsalicylic acid and a second coloring agent
giving a color other than white are dissolved. This
method has a problem because of the necessity of an
ironing step.</p><p num="0004">U. S. Patent No. 4,368,076 assigned to Adger Kogyo
Co., Ltd. discloses an erasable ink composition containing
cobalt thiocyanate dissolved in an aqueous solvent
containing polyalkylene glycol having a molecular weight
of 100-1000.</p><p num="0005">An objective problem of the present invention is to
provide an ink composition useful for forming a copy image,
corresponding to an original pattern, on a receiving
surface of an object without using a tracing paper or heat.</p><p num="0006">In accordance with one aspect of the present
invention, there is provided an ink composition comprising
a mixed solvent including a first solvent which is liquid
at 20°C and which is selected from the group consisting of
polyalkylene glycol, ethylene glycol monoethers and
mixtures thereof and a second solvent selected from the
group consisting of monohydric alcohols, ketones, esters,
halogenated hydrocarbons and mixtures thereof, and a
coloring agent dissolved in said mixed solvent.</p><p num="0007">In another aspect, the present invention provides a
writing instrument comprising an ink container containing
the above ink composition, and a rigid pen tip from which
the ink composition in said ink container is exuded upon
writing.</p><p num="0008">The present invention also provides a writing
instrument comprising an ink container containing an ink
composition, and a rigid pen tip from which said ink
composition in said ink container is exuded upon writing, 
said ink composition comprising a solvent selected from
the group consisting of monohydric alcohols, ketones,
esters, halogenated hydrocarbons and mixtures thereof, and
a coloring agent dissolved in said solvent.</p><p num="0009">The present invention further provides a method of
making a copy image, corresponding to an original pattern
on an ink permeable sheet, on a receiving surface of an
object, comprising the steps of:
<sl><li>(a) overlaying said sheet on said receiving surface;
and</li><li>(b) tracing said original pattern on said sheet with
the above writing instrument.</li></sl></p><p num="0010">The present invention further provides a method of
making a copy image, corresponding to an original pattern
on an ink permeable sheet, on a receiving surface of an
object, comprising the steps of:
<sl><li>(a) applying the above ink composition on said
original pattern of said sheet;</li><li>(b) overlaying said sheet on said receiving surface;
and then</li><li>(c) tracing said original pattern on said sheet with
a rigid member so that said ink composition is transferred
from said sheet on said receiving surface to form the copy
image thereon.</li></sl></p><p num="0011">The present invention will now be described in
detail below.</p><p num="0012">The ink composition according to the present
invention contains a coloring agent dissolved in a mixed
organic solvent including a first solvent which is liquid
at 20°C and which is at least one member selected from
polyalkyylene glycol and ethylene glycol monoethers, and a
second solvent which is at least one member selected from
monohydric alcohols, ketones, esters and halogenated
hydrocarbons.</p><p num="0013">The use of the mixed solvent permits the ink 
composition to quickly penetrate through a sheet, such as
paper or cloth, on which an original pattern is provided
(such a sheet will be hereinafter referred to simply as
sheet), while minimizing blurs. The mixed solvent can
also impart dry-preventing property to the ink and can be
good solvent to the coloring agent.</p><p num="0014">The polyalkyylene glycol generally has a molecular
weight of not greater than 400, preferably not greater
than 300, more preferably not greater than 250. A mixture
of polyalkylene glycols having different molecular weights
may be used as long as the mixture is liquid at 20°C.
Polyethylene glycol is preferably used. Ethylene glycol
monoethers are also called cellosolves. Methyl cellosolve
and ethyl cellosolve are preferably used.</p><p num="0015">Illustrative of suitable monohydric alcohols are
ethanol, methanol, propanol, isopropanol, isobutanol,
butanol, secondary amyl alcohol and tertiary amyl alcohol.
Illustrative of suitable ketones are acetone and methyl
ethyl ketone. Illustrative of suitable esters include
ethyl acetate. Illustrative of suitable halogenated
hydrocarbons are methylene chloride, ethylene chloride and
trichloroethylene. The use of monohydric alcohol,
especially ethanol, is particularly preferred for reasons
of safety, freedom of odor, solubility and volatility.</p><p num="0016">The weight ratio of the first solvent to the second
solvent varies depending upon intended penetrating
efficiency of the ink through the sheet, but may generally
range from 0.1:99.9 to 90:10.</p><p num="0017">Dissolved in the mixed organic solvent is a coloring
agent. Any coloring agent can be used as the coloring
agent as long as it is soluble in the mixed solvent and
can give, by itself or in combination with a developer, a
legible pattern of, for example, white, red, blue, green
or black, on a white, light-colored, or dark colored
receiving surface. Depending upon the intended use, the 
coloring agent may be erasable when the pattern thereof is
treated with any suitably means such as heat, water or an
organic solvent or when the pattern is allowed to stand
for a certain period of time (e.g. 1 hours or more).</p><p num="0018">The coloring agent may be of an independent type
which by itself gives a color of the ink or of a dependent
type which gives a color when combined with a developer.</p><p num="0019">Examples of non-erasable, independent-type coloring
agents include various types of solvent-soluble dyes such
as Basic Red 12, Solvent Red 8, Valifast Red 3312,
Valifast Yellow 1110, Valifast Blue 2606, Basic Brown 1,
Basic Green 4, Basic Blue 28 and Crystal Violet.</p><p num="0020">Examples of erasable, independent-type coloring
agents include cobalt thiocyanate, ferric thiocyanate,
salicylic acid and acetyl salicylic acid.</p><p num="0021">Examples of dependent-type coloring agents include
various acid-base indicators such as methyl red, propyl
red, naphthyl red; and lactone dyes such as crystal violet
lactone and rhodamine lactone. Examples of developers for
the dependent-type coloring agents include acidic
substances such as citric acid, malic acid, salicylic acid
and acetylsalicylic acid (the two salicylic compounds will
be hereinafter referred to as (acetyl)salicylic acid); and
aromatic bases such as amines (e.g. triethanol amine).</p><p num="0022">For example, methyl red colors red at a pH of below
4.4 and becomes orange at a pH of above 6.2. In the
presence of (acetyl)salicylic acid, therefore, an ink
image of methyl red colors red. When (acetyl)salicylic
acid disappears by sublimation, the image turns orange.
The orange image is turned light yellow when wiped with a
wet cloth. An ink containing crystal violet lactone and
(acetyl)salicylic acid gives a blue image which may be
erased when wiped with a wet cloth or upon lapse of time.
In this case, the life of the blue image can be increased,
when (acetyl)salicylic acid is used in conjunction with 
citric acid.</p><p num="0023">The coloring agent is used in an amount sufficient
to provide a clear image on a receiving surface of an
object and is generally in the range of 0.01-25 % by
weight, based on the weight of the ink composition, though
the amount varies depending on the kind of the coloring
agent. For example, the amount of the non-erasable,
independent-type coloring agent is generally 0.1-15 % by
weight; the amount of the erasable, independent-type
coloring agent is generally 0.3-25 % by weight; and the
amount of the dependent-type coloring agent is generally
0.01-10 % by weight, each based on the weight of the ink
composition.</p><p num="0024">(Acetyl)salicylic acid) gives a white pattern.
Because of solubility in water and of sublimability of the
(acetyl)salicylic acid, the white pattern is erasable when
wiped with a wet cloth or when heated for a suitable
period of time. Further, because of its acidity,
(acetyl)salicylic acid can serves as a developer as
described above. Further, it has been found that
(acetyl)salicylic acid serves to improve penetration
efficiency of the ink through the sheet and transferring
efficiency of the ink image from the sheet to a receiving
surface of an object.</p><p num="0025">Thus, in a preferred embodiment according to the
present invention, (acetyl)salicylic acid is contained in
the ink composition together with a coloring agent giving
a color image other than white, even when the coloring
agent does not require an acidic developer for the
development of its color. (Acetyl)salicylic acid is used
in an amount of at least 1 % by weight, preferably at
least 5 % by weight, based on the weight of the mixed
solvent. The upper limit of (acetyl)salicylic acid is the
saturated concentration. The solubility of
(acetyl)salicylic acid increases when the first solvent is 
used as a mixture with the second solvent.</p><p num="0026">For reasons of transferability, it is preferred that
the ink composition be substantially water free.</p><p num="0027">The ink composition according to the present
invention can form an ink image on a receiving surface of
an any desired object such as a textile, a leather, a
paper, a plastic or a metal. The receiving surface may
have any color inclusive of white and black.</p><p num="0028">In one preferred embodiment according to the present
invention, a copy image, corresponding to an original
pattern printed on paper or other ink permeable sheet, is
formed on a receiving surface of an object, by overlaying
the sheet on the receiving surface, and tracing the
original pattern with a writing instrument having an ink
container containing the above ink composition. By this
simple step, the ink exuded from the writing instrument on
one, top surface of the sheet can penetrate through the
sheet, can arrive at the other surface of the sheet and
can be transferred to the receiving surface. In this case,
it is important that the writing instrument should have a
rigid pen tip from which the ink composition is exuded
upon writing and which can transmit the writing pressure
to the sheet in order to effectively transfer the ink to
the receiving surface. The rigid pen tip may be, for
example, a pen tip formed of a hard material such as
plastic, metal or ceramic and having one or more axially
extending fine ink passages, a pen tip formed from fibers
which are fuse bonded to each other or bonded with a
hardenable adhesive or a pen tip having a rotatable ball
at the tip. A soft pen tip made of a soft felt or sponge
is not suitable. It is also desirable that the ink
composition have a weight ratio of the first solvent to
the second solvent of 30:70 or less, more preferably
0.5:99.5 to 20:80, most preferably 1:99 to 10:90, for
reasons of pressure transferability of the ink image. </p><p num="0029">In another embodiment, a writing instrument having a
rigid pen tip is charged with an ink composition
containing a coloring agent dissolved in a solvent
selected from monohydric alcohols, ketones, esters,
halogenated hydrocarbons and mixtures thereof. When a
receiving surface is overlaid with a sheet having an
original pattern and when the pattern is traced using the
above writing instrument, the ink image is transferred
from the sheet to the receiving surface. Because of the
absence of the first solvent, however, blurs tend to form.
If the blurs can be ignored, the above writing instrument
is suitably used for forming a copy image.</p><p num="0030">In a further embodiment, a copy image, corresponding
to an original pattern on an ink permeable sheet, is
formed on a receiving surface of an object, by applying
the above ink composition on the original pattern of the
sheet. The receiving surface is overlaid with the ink-applied
sheet and the original pattern on the sheet is
traced with a rigid tip member so that the ink composition
is transferred from the sheet to the receiving surface to
form the copy image thereon. The rigid tip member may be
a metallic pen or a stencil pen formed of any rigid
material, such as plastic, metal or wood, capable of
applying a writing pressure to the traced portions.
Application of the ink composition to the original image
of the sheet may be performed by tracing the original
pattern with a writing instrument having an ink container
for containing the ink composition and a pen tip adapted
for exuding the ink therefrom upon writing. The pen tip
may be soft, like a felt tip. It is preferred that the
tracing of the original pattern of the sheet with the
wiring instrument be carried out after the sheet has been
placed on the receiving surface. It is desirable that the
ink composition have a weight ratio of the first solvent
to the second solvent of 5:95 to 90:10, more preferably 
10:90 to 70:30, most preferably 20:80 to 70:30, for
reasons of pressure transferability of the ink image.</p><p num="0031">The following examples will further illustrate the
present invention. Parts are by weight.</p><heading>Example 1-1</heading><p num="0032">Ethanol (97 parts) was mixed with 3 parts of
polyethylene glycol (average molecular weight: 200) to
obtain a mixed solvent.</p><p num="0033">Crystal violet (0.3 part) was dissolved in 20 parts
of the mixed solvent to form a blue ink. The ink was
charged in an ink tank of a pen having a rigid plastic pen
tip. A white cloth was overlaid with a paper having an
original pattern. Then, the original pattern was traced
with the above pen. A clear blue copy image was found to
be formed on the white cloth.</p><heading>Example 1-2</heading><p num="0034">Methyl red (0.05 part) was dissolved in 20 parts of
the mixed solvent obtained in Example 1-1 to form an
orange ink. Using this ink, the procedure of Example 1-1
was repeated. A clear orange copy image was found to be
formed on the cloth. The copy image did not disappear
spontaneously but was turned light yellow when wiped with
a wet cloth.</p><heading>Example 1-3</heading><p num="0035">Cobaltous thiocyanate (1 part) was dissolved in 20
parts of the mixed solvent obtained in Example 1-1 to form
a light blue ink. Using this ink, the procedure of
Example 1-1 was repeated. A clear blue copy image was
found to be formed on the cloth. The copy image was
erased when wiped with a wet cloth.</p><heading>Example 1-4</heading><p num="0036">Valifast Red 3312 (0.2 part) was dissolved in 20
parts of the mixed solvent obtained in Example 1-1 to form
a red ink. Using this ink, the procedure of Example 1-1
was repeated. A clear red copy image was found to be
formed on the cloth.</p><heading>Example 2-1</heading><p num="0037">Ethanol (92 parts) was mixed with 8 parts of
polyethylene glycol (average molecular weight: 200), to
which 20 parts of salicylic acid was dissolved to obtain a
mixed solvent.</p><p num="0038">Crystal violet lactone (0.4 part) was dissolved in
20 parts of the mixed solvent to form a blue ink. Using
this ink, the procedure of Example 1-1 was repeated. A
clear blue copy image was found to be formed on the white
cloth. The copy image spontaneously disappeared after two
days.</p><heading>Example 2-2</heading><p num="0039">Methyl red (0.1 part) was dissolved in 20 parts of
the mixed solvent obtained in Example 2-1 to form a red
ink. Using this ink, the procedure of Example 2-1 was
repeated. A clear red copy image was found to be formed
on the cloth. The copy image spontaneously turned orange
after two days and was turned light yellow when wiped with
a wet cloth.</p><heading>Example 2-3</heading><p num="0040">Cobaltous thiocyanate (2 parts) was dissolved in 20
parts of the mixed solvent obtained in Example 2-1 to form
a light blue ink. Using this ink, the procedure of
Example 2-1 was repeated. A clear blue copy image was
found to be formed on the cloth. The copy image was
erased when wiped with a wet cloth. </p><heading>Example 2-4</heading><p num="0041">Valifast Blue 2606 (0.1 part) was dissolved in 20
parts of the mixed solvent obtained in Example 2-1 to form
a blue ink. Using this ink, the procedure of Example 1-1
was repeated. A clear blue copy image was found to be
formed on the cloth.</p><p num="0042">Copy images of Examples 2-1 to 2-4 were sharper than
those of Examples 1-1 to 1-4.</p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="0043">Examples 2-1 to 2-4 were each repeated in the same
manner as described except that ethyl cellosolve (ethylene
glycol monoethyl ether) was substituted for the
polyethylene glycol. The results were almost the same as
those in Examples 2-1 to 2-4.</p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0044">Examples 2-1 to 2-4 were each repeated in the same
manner as described except that isopropanol was
substituted for the ethanol. The results were almost the
same as those in Examples 2-1 to 2-4.</p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="0045">Using the mixed solution obtained in Example 2-1 as
an ink, the procedure of Example 2-1 was repeated. A
white copy image was found to be formed on a black cloth
used in place of the white cloth.</p><heading>Example 6</heading><p num="0046">Examples 2-1 to 2-4 were each repeated in the same
manner as described except that acetylsalicylic acid was
substituted for the salicylic acid. The results were
almost the same as those in Examples 2-1 to 2-4.</p><heading>Example 7-1</heading><p num="0047">Ethanol (60 parts) was mixed with 40 parts of
polyethylene glycol (average molecular weight: 200), to
which 50 parts of salicylic acid was dissolved to obtain a
mixed solvent.</p><p num="0048">Crystal violet lactone (0.3 part) was dissolved in
20 parts of the mixed solvent to form a blue ink. The ink
was charged in an ink tank of a felt tip pen. A white
cloth was overlaid with a paper having an original pattern.
Then, the original pattern was traced with the above pen
and then with a rigid sharp-tipped member (stencil pen).
A clear blue copy image was found to be formed on the
white cloth. The copy image spontaneously disappeared
after four days.</p><heading>Example 7-2</heading><p num="0049">Methyl red (0.05 part) was dissolved in 20 parts of
the mixed solvent obtained in Example 7-1 to form a red
ink. Using this ink, the procedure of Example 7-1 was
repeated. A clear red copy image was found to be formed
on the cloth. The copy image was turned light orange when
wiped with a wet cloth.</p><heading>Example 7-3</heading><p num="0050">Cobaltous thiocyanate (1 parts) was dissolved in 20
parts of the mixed solvent obtained in Example 7-1 to form
a light blue ink. Using this ink, the procedure of
Example 7-1 was repeated. A clear blue copy image was
found to be formed on the cloth. The copy image was
erased when wiped with a wet cloth.</p><heading>Example 7-4</heading><p num="0051">Valifast Red 3312 (0.2 part) was dissolved in 20
parts of the mixed solvent obtained in Example 7-1 to form
a red ink. Using this ink, the procedure of Example 7-1
was repeated. A clear red copy image was found to be 
formed on the cloth.</p><heading>Example 8</heading><p num="0052">Ethanol (70 parts) was mixed with 30 parts of
ethylene glycol monoethyl ether (ethyl cellosolve), to
which 45 parts of acetylsalicylic acid was dissolved to
obtain a mixed solvent. In this mixed solvent, the
coloring agents used in Examples 7-1 to 7-4 were each
dissolved to obtain ink compositions. Clear copy images
were found to be obtained.</p><heading>Example 9</heading><p num="0053">Crystal violet lactone (0.4 part) and 3 parts of
citric acid were dissolved in 20 parts of ethanol to form
a blue ink. Using this ink, the procedure of Example 1-1
was repeated. A blue copy image having slight blurs was
found to be formed on the cloth. The blue image was
erased when wiped with a wet cloth.</p><heading>Example 10</heading><p num="0054">Methyl red (0.1 part) was dissolved in 20 parts of
ethanol to form an orange ink. Using this ink, the
procedure of Example 1-1 was repeated. An orange copy
image having slight blurs was found to be formed on the
cloth.</p><heading>Comparative Example 1</heading><p num="0055">In a mixed solvent consisting of 80 parts of
isopropanol and 20 parts of ethylene chloride were
dissolved 30 parts of salicylic acid, 0.8 part of
polyethylene glycol (molecular weight: 600,000 to
1,110,000) and 0.1 part of methyl red to obtain a red ink.
Using this ink, the procedures of Example 1-1 and Example
7-1 were repeated. However, a clear red copy image was
not able to be formed on the cloth. </p><heading>Comparative Example 2</heading><p num="0056">In a mixed solvent consisting of 70 parts of
isopropanol and 30 parts of ethylene chloride were
dissolved 20 parts of acetylsalicylic acid, 0.8 part of
polyethylene glycol (molecular weight: 600,000 to
1,110,000) and 0.2 part of crystal violet lactone to
obtain a blue ink. Using this ink, the procedures of
Example 1-1 and Example 7-1 were repeated. However, a
clear blue copy image was not able to be formed on the
cloth.</p><heading>Comparative Example 3</heading><p num="0057">In 100 g of water were dissolved 15 g of cobaltous
thiocyanate, to which 10 g of polyethylene glycol
(molecular weight: 200) were added. Using the thus
obtained blue ink, the procedures of Example 1-1 and
Example 7-1 were repeated. However, a clear blue copy
image was not able to be formed on the cloth.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An ink composition comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>a mixed solvent including a first solvent which is
liquid at 20°C and which is selected from the group
consisting of polyalkylene glycol, ethylene glycol
monoethers and mixtures thereof and a second solvent
selected from the group consisting of monohydric alcohols,
ketones, esters, halogenated hydrocarbons and mixtures
thereof, and</claim-text><claim-text>a coloring agent dissolved in said mixed solvent.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>An ink composition as claimed in claim 1,
wherein said coloring agent gives an erasable pattern.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>An ink composition as claimed in claim 2,
wherein said coloring agent is selected from the group
consisting of salicylic acid, acetylsalicylic acid, methyl
red, crystal violet lactone and cobalt thiocyanate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>An ink composition as claimed in claim 1,
wherein said coloring agent gives a color other than white
and wherein said ink composition further comprises
salicylic acid and/or acetylsalicylic acid dissolved in
said mixed solvent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An ink composition as claimed in any one of
preceding claims, wherein the weight ratio of said first
solvent to said second solvent is 0.5:99.5 to 30:70.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>An ink composition as claimed in any one of
preceding claims, wherein said second solvent includes
ethanol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>An ink composition as claimed in claim 4,
wherein the weight ratio of said first solvent to said
second solvent is 10:90 to 90:5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>An ink composition as claimed in claim 7,
wherein said coloring agent gives an erasable pattern.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>An ink composition as claimed in claim 8,
wherein said coloring agent is selected from the group
consisting of methyl red, crystal violet lactone and
cobalt thiocyanate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An ink composition as claimed in any one of
claims 7-9, wherein said second solvent includes ethanol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A writing instrument comprising an ink
container containing an ink composition according to claim
5 or 6, and a rigid pen tip from which said ink
composition in said ink container is exuded upon writing.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A writing instrument comprising an ink
container containing an ink composition according to any
one of claims 7-10, and a pen tip from which said ink
composition in said ink container is exuded upon writing.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A writing instrument comprising an ink
container containing an ink composition, and a rigid pen
tip from which said ink composition in said ink container
is exuded upon writing, said ink composition comprising a
solvent selected from the group consisting of monohydric
alcohols, ketones, esters, halogenated hydrocarbons and
mixtures thereof, and a coloring agent dissolved in said
solvent.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A method of making a copy image, corresponding
to an original pattern on an ink permeable sheet, on a
receiving surface of an object, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) overlaying said sheet on said receiving surface;
and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) tracing said original pattern on said sheet with
a writing instrument according to claim 11 or 13.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A method of making a copy image, corresponding
to an original pattern on an ink permeable sheet, on a
receiving surface of an object, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) applying an ink composition according to any one
of claims 7-10 on said original pattern of said sheet;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) overlaying said sheet on said receiving surface;
and then</claim-text><claim-text>(c) tracing said original pattern on said sheet with
a rigid member so that said ink composition is transferred
from said sheet on said receiving surface to form the copy
image thereon.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>