<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1358935-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1358935" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="29215688" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20031105"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1358935-A1" status="new" fvid="23892493"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1358935</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20031105</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03008826-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03008826</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030424</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-13705302-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>13705302</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020501</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  23/89        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  23/89        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  37/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J  37/02        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07B  61/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07B  61/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 209/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 209/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 209/36        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 209/48        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 211/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 211/05        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 211/07        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 211/50        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C 211/51        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  23/89D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B01J  23/89G6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C 209/16</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C 209/36</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C 209/48</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01J23:89F</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L01J37:02M2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07C211:05</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07C211:07</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07C211:51</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Zink-modifizierte Pd/Ni Katalysatoren</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Zinc modified Pd/Ni catalysts</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Catalyseurs Pd/Ni modifiés avec du zinc</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1036784-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1036784</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3781227-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3781227</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4238365-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4238365</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4792622-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4792622</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5932769-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5932769</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6005143-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6005143</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>AIR PROD &amp; CHEM</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AIR PRODUCTS AND CHEMICALS, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>AIR PRODUCTS AND CHEMICALS, INC.</last-name><address><street>7201 Hamilton Boulevard</street><city>Allentown, PA 18195-1501</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DING HAO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DING, HAO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DING, HAO</last-name><address><street>2243 Dubonnet Drive</street><city>Macungie, PA 18062</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Schwabe - Sandmair - Marx</last-name><address><street>Stuntzstrasse 16</street><city>81677 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>This invention relates to improved catalytic compositions suited for use in
hydrogenation processes and to an improved process for hydrogenating organic
compounds as in amination of alcohols or hydrogenation of nitro groups to the amine
using the catalyst. The catalytic composition is more particularly an improvement in
nickel catalysts promoted with palladium carried on a support. The improvement resides
in including a promoting effect of a metal M and/or its oxide, selected from Zn, Cd, Cu,
and Ag, typically from about 0.01 to 10% by weight of the support.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">Processes for the hydrogenation of organic compounds including those having
functional groups have been widely practiced. Amination of alcohols, hydrogenation of
nitriles to amines, hydrogenation of nitro groups as in the conversion of nitroaromatics to
aromatic amines are commonplace industrial reactions. Catalysts used for the industrial
hydrogenation of these compounds typically are based upon Group VIII metals.
However, cobalt and nickel often are the primary metals employed. Promoter metals
have been added to these catalytic metals to alter reactivity, byproduct formation and the
like.</p><p num="0002">Representative patents and articles illustrating hydrogenation processes and the
catalytic metals used therefor are as follows:</p><p num="0003">U.S. 3,127,356 discloses an improved process for preparing catalysts for the
hydrogenation of organic compounds such as organic nitro compounds. Platinum,
palladium or nickel is deposited on an inert support, and then, an oleophilic carbon is
added to the system. Subsequently the metal is reduced to an activated state. Activating
components, e.g., oxides of iron, nickel magnesium, manganese, chromium, vanadium,
and tungsten may be added at various stages.</p><p num="0004">U.S. 4,792,626 discloses a process for the hydrogenation of dinitrotoluene to
toluenediamine in the presence of a modified Raney nickel catalyst. The Raney catalyst
is the product of an alkali treatment of an alloy of from 50-95 wt% aluminum and 4-45
wt% nickel or cobalt. These metals are modified with metals from the 1<sup>st</sup>, 4<sup>th</sup>, 5<sup>th</sup>, 6<sup>th</sup>, 7<sup>th</sup>
and 8<sup>th</sup> subgroups of the periodic table. Iron, ruthenium, chromium, molybdenum,
tungsten, niobium, tantalum, vanadium, titanium, copper, zirconium and hafnium are 
preferred. A small proportion of carbon monoxide is added to the reaction to prevent
formation of N-alkyl toluenediamine.</p><p num="0005">Boccuzzi, F., Guglielminotti, E; Pinna, F., Signoretto, M.; <i>Surface Composition of
Pd-Fe Catalysts supported on Silica,</i> J. Chem. Soc., Faraday Trans. (1995), 91 (18),
3237-44, disclose the formation of highly dispersed Pd-Fe bimetallic aggregates as
catalysts for hydrogenation reactions.</p><p num="0006">U.S. 3,935,264 discloses the hydrogenation of dinitrotoluene (DNT) to
toluenediamine (TDA) in the presence of an aliphatic alcohol. Preferred catalytic metals
include nickel, platinum, palladium and mixtures. Raney nickel is the preferred catalytic
metal. Carbon monoxide addition is found to be effective in minimizing the formation of
N-alkyl toluenediamine type byproducts in the catalytic hydrogenation of DNT.</p><p num="0007">U.S. 6,005,143 discloses the hydrogenation of dinitrotoluene in a monolith
catalytic reactor. The catalytic metal employed in the monolith catalytic reactor is a
Pd/Ni bimetallic. In these catalysts, the metal loading is about 10% nickel and 1%
palladium.</p><p num="0008">U.S. 4,743,577 discloses metallic catalysts for hydrogenation and
decarbonylation reactions. The catalytic metals are based upon a porous, sintered
support and a catalytic metal. Catalytic metals are dispersed upon the support in thin
layers or electroplated from a salt solution. Catalyst metals are selected from among
palladium, nickel, rhodium, platinum, copper, ruthenium, cobalt and mixtures.</p><p num="0009">U.S. 5,296,631 discloses a process for producing N-alkyl-N-methyl amines
wherein a higher alcohol is reacted with methylamine. The catalyst employed is either
one comprised of copper, zinc and ruthenium or one comprised of copper, zinc and
palladium.</p><p num="0010">JP S47-91069 discloses the liquid phase hydrogenation of nitriles to amines
using a catalyst comprised of nickel and palladium carried on an alumina support. Pd/Ni 
ratios range from about 0.1 to about 0.8. The proportion of primary amine is related to
the level of palladium in the catalyst.</p><p num="0011">JP HEI 11-47597 discloses a hydrogenation catalyst employing a porous lithium
aluminate possessing spinel as a support. A wide range of catalytic metals are
suggested which include ruthenium, rhodium, silver, palladium carried on the support.
Divalent metals such as magnesium zinc, cobalt nickel and copper are suggested as an
additive.</p><p num="0012">Some of the problems associated with prior art palladium promoted nickel
hydrogenation catalysts, i.e., Pd/Ni bimetallic catalysts, include that of relatively low
selectivity and deactivation. Deactivation can be caused by a sintering of the metal
and/or fouling caused by undesirable byproduct formation. Ring hydrogenated products
(lights) and oligomer products (heavies) are believed to be the common byproducts
causing fouling of the catalysts.</p><heading>BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0013">This invention relates to improved catalytic compositions suited for use in
hydrogenation processes and to an improved process for hydrogenating organic
compounds as in amination of alcohols or hydrogenation of nitro groups to the amine
using the catalyst. The catalytic composition is more particularly an improvement in
palladium/nickel catalysts which are carried on a support. The improvement resides in
including a promotingly effective amount of a metal M selected from Zn, Cd, Cu, and Ag,
typically from about 0.01 to 10% by weight of the support.</p><p num="0014">Significant advantages may be achieved by the use of the catalytic compositions
in hydrogenation processes and these include:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>an ability to achieve high selectivity of desired product;</li><li>an ability to achieve excellent rates of reaction during hydrogenation; and, </li><li>an ability to achieve excellent catalyst life partially due to minimal byproduct
formation.</li></ul></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0015">As illustrated in the Background of the Invention, Pd/Ni as bimetallics are known
and widely used as catalysts for a number of hydrogenation reactions, such as the
hydrogenation of nitroaromatic compounds to aromatic amines. The hydrogenation of
dinitrotoluene (DNT) to toluenediamine (TDA) and the hydrogenation of nitriles are
representative.</p><p num="0016">These catalytic metals are carried on a support, whether active or not, such as
alumina or silica. Other materials that may be used as supports include titania, lithium
aluminate, zeolites, kiesulguhr, diatomaceous earth, carbon and so forth. Monolith
substrates having from 100 to 1200 cells per inch, preferably from 400 to 800 cells per
inch may be used in an embodiment of the invention. Monolith substrates may be made
from carbon, cordierite, ceramics and numerous other components. Such substrates
may be used to anchor the above mentioned support materials for fixed bed applications.</p><p num="0017">The active metals, i.e., Ni and Pd, for effecting the hydrogenation reactions are
impregnated into or on the support by conventional methods such as incipient wetness
or other methods of impregnation and deposition. In the case of monolithic catalysts,
washcoat support materials, such as alumina, lithium aluminate and the like, are added
to the surface of monolith substrate as catalyst support. The active metals are added
and subsequently fixed to the washcoat support to form a catalyst. Typically the metals
are applied to or incorporated into the support material using the metal oxides which
subsequently get reduced to the active metal.</p><p num="0018">The active metals are incorporated into the support, e.g., by impregnation in
various amounts. The level of nickel, as metal, incorporated into the support will range 
from about 10 to 25 wt%, preferably from 15 to 20 wt%; the palladium in the support will
range from about 0.01 to 20 wt%, preferably from 0.5 to 1.5 wt%, and the amount of
promoting metal M in the support will range from about 0.001 to 10 wt%, preferably from
0.1 to 2 wt%. Typically, the weight ratio of nickel to palladium will range from 1-100:1,
preferably from 10-40:1 and the weight ratio of nickel to promoting metal M will range
from about 10-1000:1, preferably from 10-200:1 and the weight ratio of palladium to
metal M will range from 0.5-10:1.</p><p num="0019">The catalysts described herein are well suited for hydrogenation reactions
associated with the catalytic hydrogenation of organic compounds employing
palladium/nickel catalysts. Hydrogenation reactions that can be carried out using the
improved catalysts include the hydrogenation of unsaturated hydrocarbons, amination of
alcohols, conversion of nitro groups to amines and the hydrogenation of nitriles.
Unsaturated hydrocarbons which may be hydrogenated are aromatic compounds, olefins
and alkynes.</p><p num="0020">Examples of alkanols suited for amination by reaction with ammonia in the
presence of hydrogen include lower C<sub>1-8</sub> alkanols, such as methanol, ethanol, <i>i</i> and <i>n</i>-propanol,
butanol, and so forth, and cycloaliphatic alcohols, such as cyclohexanol.
Nitriles which can be hydrogenated include the C<sub>1-8</sub> aliphatic nitriles, e.g., acetonitrile,
propionitrile, butyronitrile, acrylonitrile and so forth. One of the important industrial
applications for these catalysts is the hydrogenation of aromatic nitro compounds to form
the aromatic amines Examples include the hydrogenation of mononitrotoluene and
dinitrotoluene (DNT).</p><p num="0021">Although not intending to be bound by theory, in the case of DNT hydrogenation,
the presence of Pd keeps Ni at a reduced state at effective DNT conversion
temperatures Therefore, such catalysts provide good DNT hydrogenation activity to
TDA. However, Pd is also active in ring hydrogenation, causing the formation of light 
byproducts (lights) in the process. The metals M tend to reduce the lights and
byproducts formed in the hydrogenation process.</p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0022"><u style="single">Modification Of Pd/Ni Bimetallic Monolith Catalyst With Zinc</u> -- Five zinc modified
Pd/Ni impregnated monolith catalysts were prepared as follows. A commercial Pd/Ni
monolith catalyst comprised of a cordierite monolith substrate that contained 20 wt% of
alumina washcoat support having Pd in an amount of 1.0 wt% with respect to the
washcoat support and Ni in an amount of 20.0 wt% with respect to the washcoat support
was dipped into an aqueous solution containing 2 wt% Zn(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(6H<sub>2</sub>O) at room
temperature. The resulting wet monolith catalyst was dried at 110°C for 4 hours and
then calcined at 380°C for 6 hours. Different Zn loadings were achieved by changing the
concentration of Zn(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(6H<sub>2</sub>O) in the dipping solution from 0.2 wt% to 20 wt%. Zn
loadings in the five monolith catalysts resulting from zinc addition were 0.29%, 0.48%,
0.80%, 3.0%, 4.8% with respect to the weight of the washcoat support. Zinc levels were
determined by Inductive Coupled Plasma (ICP).</p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0023"><u style="single">Modification Of Pd/Ni Bimetallic Monolith Catalyst With Copper</u> -- The procedure
of Example 1 was followed except that copper modification was achieved by utilizing a 2
wt% Cu(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> solution. 1.0% Cu with respect to the weight of the washcoat support
was added. </p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="0024"><u style="single">Modification Of Pd/Ni Bimetallic Monolith Catalyst With Silver</u> -- Silver
modification was achieved with 2 wt% AgNO<sub>3</sub> solution using the method described in
Example 1. 1.0% Ag with respect to the weight of the washcoat support was added.</p> <heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0025"><u style="single">Influence Of Zn Concentration On DNT Hydrogenation Selectivity</u> -- The
effectiveness of the five zinc modified Pd/Ni monolith catalysts prepared in Example 1 for
performance and selectivity control in the hydrogenation of dinitrotoluene (DNT) was
determined using a batch reactor.</p><p num="0026">A toluenediamine/water (TDA/water) heel was first charged to the batch reactor
and the monolith catalyst placed in the reactor. The mixture was brought to reaction
conditions (140°C, 600 psi H<sub>2</sub>). DNT was then pumped in at four different rates (1, 2, 4,
8 g/min) for a total duration of 1 hour. The activity of the catalyst (hydrogenation rate)
was recorded during this period of time. The DNT feeding was stopped after 1 hour and
the TDA product mixture was kept at reaction conditions for additional 2 days, during
which the selectivity of the catalyst was checked by GC through periodical sampling the
reactor.</p><p num="0027">It was found that the presence of Zn in the Pd/Ni monolith catalyst effectively
suppressed formation of lights and tars (byproducts) even at concentrations as low as
0.3 wt% based on support. As a generalized trend, a higher concentration of Zn in the
monolith catalyst gave even better selectivity control up to around 0.8 wt%. Then the
control leveled off with virtually no lights formation, and yet the activity of the catalyst was
not compromised even at high Zn loading of 5 wt%. Table 1 presents data showing the
DNT hydrogenation selectivity enhancement by the Zn modified catalysts. <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Zn%</entry><entry align="center">Lights%</entry> <entry align="center">Tars%</entry> </row> <row><entry align="center">0.00</entry><entry align="center">7.50</entry><entry align="center">1.00</entry></row><row><entry align="center">0.29</entry><entry align="center">2.90</entry><entry align="center">2.30</entry></row><row><entry align="center">0.48</entry><entry align="center">2.20</entry><entry align="center">1.00</entry></row><row><entry align="center">0.80</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">0.10</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3.00</entry><entry align="center">0.29</entry><entry align="center">0.44</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4.80</entry><entry align="center">0.19</entry><entry align="center">0.54</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="0028"><u style="single">Influence Of Different Metal Promoters On DNT Hydrogenation Selectivity</u> -- The
procedure of Example 4 was followed to determine the effectiveness of the Cu and Ag
modified monolith catalysts formed in Examples 2 and 3. The amounts of light products
generated with each modified catalyst were compared against the unmodified Pd/Ni
catalyst. Table 2 shows the effect of metal promoters on light products formation. The
data in Table 2 demonstrates that Cu and Ag were effective promoters to suppress the
formation of light products in the DNT hydrogenation process. However, their
effectiveness was less than that of zinc as illustrated in Table 2.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Lites%</entry><entry align="center">Tar%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Pd/Ni</entry><entry align="center">7.50</entry><entry align="center">1.00</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Pd/Ni/Zn</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">0.10</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Pd/Ni/Cu</entry><entry align="center">1.50</entry><entry align="center">1.10</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Pd/Ni/Ag</entry><entry align="center">2.00</entry><entry align="center">2.30</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0029">In summary, a Zn modified Pd/Ni catalyst resulted in overall lights formation of
0.3% in 48h (total byproduct: &lt;1%). This high level of selectivity was unexpected as the
unmodified catalyst typically resulted in 7.5% lights (total byproduct: 9%) under the same
conditions (140°C, 600 psi H<sub>2</sub>). The Cu and Ag catalysts are also significantly better 
than the non-modified Pd/Ni catalyst but not as good or as effective in promoting
selectivity as zinc.</p><heading>Example 6</heading><p num="0030"><u style="single">Synthesis Of Ni(20%)/Pd(1%)/Zn(1%) On Alumina Support</u> -- An alumina
supported catalyst containing palladium, nickel and zinc was prepared as follows.
Initially 1.8g zinc nitrate hexahydrate was dissolved in approximately 4 ml HPLC grade
H<sub>2</sub>O and then 39.6g nickel nitrate hexahydrate and 5 ml HPLC grade water were added
to the zinc solution. The mixture was stirred on a hotplate. When completely dissolved,
4.9g palladium nitrate solution (8.2%Pd) was added to the zinc/nickel solution. 31.2g
gamma alumina (heat treated Catalpal® B alumina) was then blended in until alumina
was uniform in color. The mixture was transferred to a porcelain dish, dried at 110°C in
air for 1 hr and further calcined at 380°C in air for 4 hrs.</p><heading>Example 7</heading><p num="0031"><u style="single">Hydrogenation Of Butyronitrile Using Ni(20%)/Pd(1%)/Zn(1%) On Alumina</u><u style="single">Support</u> -- 1.2g of the catalyst of Example 6, was reduced initially by hydrogen at 500°C
and added to a 500 ml Parr reactor. Butyronitrile (80g, 98%, Aldrich) was then charged
to the reactor. The reactor was brought to a temperature of 125°C and pressurized to
500 psig with H<sub>2</sub>. The reactor was stirred at 1500 rpm. The hydrogenation reaction was
stopped when hydrogen no longer was consumed. Multiple uses of the same catalyst
were achieved by discharging the reaction product through a internal filter and
recovering the used catlyst. The used catalyst then was recharged to the reactor and
fresh feed added. The final products were analyzed by GC and the results are shown in
Table 3. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Use</entry><entry align="center">T<sub>95 (min)</sub></entry><entry align="center">Conv (%)</entry><entry align="center">Butylamine (%)</entry><entry align="center">Dibutylamine (%)</entry><entry align="center">Tributylamine (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">196</entry><entry align="center">99.7</entry><entry align="center">69.3</entry><entry align="center">28.7</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">127</entry><entry align="center">98.3</entry><entry align="center">64.9</entry><entry align="center">28.2</entry><entry align="center">0.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">125</entry><entry align="center">99.8</entry><entry align="center">66.2</entry><entry align="center">30.9</entry><entry align="center">0.8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">122</entry><entry align="center">99.8</entry><entry align="center">67.3</entry><entry align="center">31.6</entry><entry align="center">0.9</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0032">The results show excellent conversion of the nitrile to the primary amine. Minimal
amounts of tertiary amine were formed.</p><heading>Example 8</heading><p num="0033"><u style="single">Ethanol Amination Using Ni(20%)/Pd(1%)/Zn(1%) On Alumina Support</u> -- A
Ni(20%)/Pd(1%)/Zn(1%) catalyst as prepared in Example 6 was first pressed into pellets
and then screened for particle size using 12 and 18 mesh screens. Approximately 10cc
of catalyst was weighed out and placed in a tube reactor. The temperature of the reactor
was slowly increased to 410°C over a 2-hour period. To reduce the catalyst metal, the
catalyst was kept at this temperature under 100 psi hydrogen with a flow rate of 80
ml/min for 4 hours. Once the catalyst metal was reduced, the temperature was lowered
to 185°C and ethanol (7.0 ml/hr) was fed to the reactor along with ammonia and
hydrogen (NH<sub>3</sub>/ethanol/H<sub>2</sub> = 2/1/1.5 molar ratio). The sample stream was analyzed by
GC equipped with a FID detector. The data is shown in Table 4. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Time on Stream</entry><entry align="center">EtOH Conv. (%)</entry><entry align="center">MEA (%)</entry><entry align="center">DEA (%)</entry><entry align="center">TEA (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">24hr</entry><entry align="center">84.602</entry><entry align="center">34.551</entry><entry align="center">47.421</entry><entry align="center">18.028</entry></row><row><entry align="center">48 hr</entry><entry align="center">83.550</entry><entry align="center">34.635</entry><entry align="center">47.716</entry><entry align="center">17.649</entry></row><row><entry align="center">72hr</entry><entry align="center">82.587</entry><entry align="center">35.209</entry><entry align="center">47.069</entry><entry align="center">17.722</entry></row><row><entry align="center">144hr</entry><entry align="center">82.143</entry><entry align="center">34.479</entry><entry align="center">47.501</entry><entry align="center">18.020</entry></row><row><entry align="center">168hr</entry><entry align="center">80.714</entry><entry align="center">35.834</entry><entry align="center">46.669</entry><entry align="center">17.497</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0034">The results show excellent conversion and catalysts life were achieved using the
zinc modified Pd/Ni catalyst.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>In a palladium/nickel catalytic composition carried on a support which is
suited for use in a hydrogenation process, the improvement which resides in the
inclusion of a promotingly effective amount of a metal M selected from the group
consisting of zinc, cadmium, copper, and silver.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The catalytic composition of Claim 1 wherein the nickel is present in an
amount from about 10 to 25 percent by weight of the support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The catalytic composition of Claim 2 wherein the palladium is present in
an amount from 0.01 to 20 percent by weight of the support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The catalytic composition of Claim 3 wherein the metal M is present in an
amount from about 0.001 to 10 wt% of the support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The catalytic composition of Claim 4 wherein the weight ratio of nickel to
palladium is from 1-100:1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The catalytic composition of Claim 5 wherein the weight ratio of nickel to
metal M is from about 10-1000:1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The catalytic composition of Claim 6 wherein the weight ratio of palladium
to metal M is from 0.5-10:1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The catalytic composition of Claim 7 wherein the metal M is zinc.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The catalytic composition of Claim 8 wherein the support is selected from
the group consisting of alumina, lithium aluminate, carbon, silica, titania, zeolite,
kiesulguhr or cordierite monolith with above supports as washcoat.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The catalytic composition of Claim 9 wherein the nickel is present in an
amount of from 15 to 20% by weight of the support, the palladium is present in an
amount from 0.5 to 1.5% by weight and the zinc is present in an amount from 0.1 to 2%
by weight.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>In a process for the catalytic hydrogenation of organic compounds
wherein the organic compound is contacted with hydrogen in the presence of a catalytic
amount of a palladium/nickel catalyst, the improvement which comprises employing the
catalyst composition of Claim 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The process of Claim 11 wherein the nickel is present in an amount from
10 to 25 percent by weight of the support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The process of Claim 12 wherein the palladium is present in an amount
from 0.01 to 20 percent by weight of the support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The process of Claim 13 wherein the amount of the metal M is present in
an amount from about 0.001 to 10 percent of the support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The process of Claim 14 wherein the weight ratio of nickel to palladium is
from 1-25:1, the weight ratio of nickel to metal M is from about 10-200:1 and the weight
ratio of palladium to metal M is from 0.5-10:1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The process of Claim 14 wherein the catalyst is present in the monolithic
form.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16 wherein the organic compound is selected from
the group consisting of a nitrile or a nitroaromatic and the nitrile is an aliphatic nitrile
having from 1-8 carbon atoms.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The process of Claim 17 wherein the nitrile is selected from the group
consisting of acetonitrile, propionitrile and butyronitrile.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16 wherein the organic compound is a nitroaromatic
compound selected from the group consisting of mononitrobenzene and dinitrotoluene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The process of Claim 11 wherein the hydrogenation process comprises
the amination of an alcohol in the presence of hydrogen.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>The process of Claim 20 wherein the nickel is present in an amount from
15 to 20 percent by weight of the support</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>The process of Claim 21 wherein the palladium is present in an amount
from 0.1 to 1.5 percent by weight of the support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>The process of Claim 22 wherein the metal M is present in an amount
from about 0.1 to 2 percent of the support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>The process of Claim 23 wherein the weight ratio of nickel to palladium is
from 1-25:1, the weight ratio of nickel to metal M is from about 10-200:1 and the weight
ratio of palladium to metal M is from 0.5-10:1.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>