<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1375592-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1375592" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="29717445" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040102"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1375592-A1" status="new" fvid="23939229"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1375592</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040102</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03253812-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03253812</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030617</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002175661-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002175661</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020617</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L   5/00        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L   5/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  89/00        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  89/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/16        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  67/04+B6</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Biologisch abbaubare Polylactidzusammensetzungen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Biodegradable polylactide resin composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Compositions biodégradables à base de de polylactide</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1033127-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1033127</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5798435-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5798435</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6121410-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6121410</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6388047-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6388047</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1991006286-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1991006286</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999011699-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999011699</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2001045742-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2001045742</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2003035753-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2003035753</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source name="EXA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 200159 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A23, AN 2001-536217 XP002253283 &amp; WO 01 42367 A (JAPAN NAT INST ADV IND SCI &amp; TECHNOLOGY), 14 June 2001 (2001-06-14)</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>LI J K ET AL:  "A NOVEL BIODEGRADABLE SYSTEM BASED ON GELATIN NANOPARTICLES AND POLY(LACTIC-CO-GLYCOLIC ACID) MICROSPHERES FOR PROTEIN AND PEPTIDE DRUG DELIVERY" JOURNAL OF PHARMACEUTICAL SCIENCES, AMERICAN PHARMACEUTICAL ASSOCIATION. WASHINGTON, US, vol. 86, no. 8, 1 August 1997 (1997-08-01), pages 891-895, XP000693967 ISSN: 0022-3549</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>MU L ET AL:  "Fabrication, characterization and in vitro release of paclitaxel (TaxolR)) loaded poly (lactic-co-glycolic acid) microspheres prepared by spray drying technique with lipid/cholesterol emulsifiers" JOURNAL OF CONTROLLED RELEASE, ELSEVIER SCIENCE PUBLISHERS B.V. AMSTERDAM, NL, vol. 76, no. 3, 19 October 2001 (2001-10-19), pages 239-254, XP004306407 ISSN: 0168-3659</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NAT INST OF ADVANCED IND SCIEN</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF ADVANCED INDUSTRIAL SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology</last-name><address><street>3-1, Kasumigaseki 1-chome, Chiyoda-ku</street><city>Tokyo 100-8921</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>RAKU TAKAO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TOKIWA YUTAKA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>RAKU, TAKAO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TOKIWA, YUTAKA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>RAKU, TAKAO</last-name><address><street>Tsukuba Central 6, 1-1, Higashi, 1-chome</street><city>Tsukuba-shi, Ibaraki 305-8566</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TOKIWA, YUTAKA</last-name><address><street>Tsukuba Central 6, 1-1, Higashi, 1-chome</street><city>Tsukuba-shi, Ibaraki 305-8566</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Maschio, Antonio</last-name><address><street>D Young &amp;amp; Co, 21 New Fetter Lane</street><city>London EC4A 1DA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>This invention provides a novel rapidly biodegradable polylactide resin composition while
maintaining the good mechanical strength and physical properties of polylactide. This
biodegradable polylactide resin composition comprises at least one protein selected from silk, gelatin,
keratin, elastin, gluten, zein, or soybean. This composition further comprises degraded mannan,
and furthermore, a filler.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">Technical Field</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a novel biodegradable polylactide resin composition, and
more particularly to a novel biodegradable polylactide resin composition, which has significantly
enhanced the biodegradability of polylactide without deteriorating its good mechanical and physical
properties.</p><heading><u style="single">Background Art</u></heading><p num="0002">Polylactide can be produced from plants and its strength and physical properties are
relatively better than those of other biodegradable resins. Accordingly, polylactide has rapidly
become a focus of attention as a material alternative to existing plastics or fibers that are made from
petroleum.</p><p num="0003">However, the biodegradability of polylactide is lower than that of other commonly known
biodegradable plastics such as polyhydroxybutyric acid, polycaprolactone, or polybutylene succinate.
For example, the quantities of biodegradable plastic-degrading bacteria in these plastics can be
represented by the following sequence: polyhydroxybutyric acid ≥ polycaprolactone &gt; polybutylene
succinate &gt; polylactide. Unlike another commonly known biodegradable plastic, i.e., aliphatic
polyester, polylactide is aliphatic polyester formed by an α-ester bond. Thus, polylactide has
specific properties. For example, it is not degraded by a lipase, esterase, or polyhydroxybutyric
acid-degrading enzyme.</p><p num="0004">Accordingly, polylactides, which are excellent in terms of ready biodegradability, are
strongly desired particularly in markets in the fields of agriculture or civil engineering where rapidly
biodegradable products such as multi-purpose films or vegetation nets are strongly desired.</p><p num="0005">Meanwhile, techniques have been proposed in the past wherein a naturally occurring
polymer such as starch is blended into biodegradable aliphatic polyester in order to improve cost, 
formability, and biodegradability of products (e.g., JP Patent Publication (Kokai) Nos. 5-320524 A
(1993) and 5-331315 A (1993)).</p><p num="0006">When these blending techniques as such are applied to polylactide, however, the good
mechanical strength or physical properties thereof are lost. Thus, a polylactide resin composition
useful as a material for multi-purpose films, vegetation nets, etc. could not be obtained.</p><p num="0007">An object of the present invention is to provide a novel rapidly biodegradable polylactide
resin composition by overcoming drawbacks of the prior art while maintaining good mechanical
strength and physical properties of polylactide.</p><p num="0008">The present inventors have conducted concentrated studies in order to attain the above
object. As a result, they have found that a polylactide resin composition having excellent
biodegradability can be obtained while maintaining good physical properties and strengths of
polylactide with the addition of a specific protein to polylactide or a mannan-containing polylactide
composition. This has led to the completion of the present invention.</p><heading><u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0009">Specifically, the present invention provides the following:
<sl><li>(1) a biodegradable polylactide resin composition, which comprises at least one protein
selected from silk, gelatin, keratin, elastin, casein, gluten, zein, or soybean protein;</li><li>(2) a biodegradable polylactide resin composition, which further comprises degraded
mannan;</li><li>(3) the biodegradable polylactide resin composition according to (1) or (2) above, which
further comprises a filler; and</li><li>(4) the biodegradable polylactide resin composition according to any of (1) to (3) above,
which comprises 0.01 to 5% by weight of the protein based on polylactide.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Preferred Embodiments of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0010">The biodegradable polylactide resin composition according to the present invention
comprises at least one protein selected from silk, gelatin, keratin, elastin, casein, gluten, zein, and
soybean protein added to polylactide. </p><p num="0011">The polylactide used in the present invention is preferably poly-L-lactic acid, and
poly-D-lactic acid may also be used. Alternatively, a mixture or copolymer of poly-L-lactic acid
and poly-D-lactic acid may be used. Further, a copolymer, which incorporates therein a unit having
biodegradability such as β-propiolactone, β-butyrolactone, pivalolactone, γ-butyrolactone,
γ-methyl-γ-butyrolactone, γ-ethyl-γ-butyrolactone, glycolide, lactide, δ-valerolactone,
β-methyl-δ-valerolactone, ε-caprolactone, ethylene oxide, or propylene oxide, may be used. In
addition, generally commercially available biodegradable resins such as polyhydroxybutyric acid,
polybutylene succinate, a polybutylene succinate-adipate copolymer, polycaprolactone, or polyester
carbonate may be suitably blended into polylactide for the purpose of improving the physical
properties thereof. The molecular weight of polylactide or a modified polymer thereof is 1,000 to
1,000,000, and preferably 10,000 to 100,000.</p><p num="0012">Examples of silk used in the present invention include a cocoon, a silk fibroin powder
prepared by boiling a cocoon and removing water-soluble sericin, waste generated in the process of
spinning silk fibers, waste generated in the process of producing silk fabric, waste of silk fabric, and
a finely-cut silk fiber. Alternatively, the silk may comprise a finely shredded web, egg, larva,
chrysalis, or adult silkworm moth insect or spider. For example, an oligomer that is prepared by
hydrolyzing this silk, silkworm moth, spider, or waste thereof with an enzyme such as a protease or
lipase or a chemical catalyzer such as acid or alkali may also be used.</p><p num="0013">Gelatin that is used in the present invention is generally derived from bovine sources,
however, gelatin derived from poultry, porcine, fish, human, or similar sources may also be used
without particular limitation on its origin. Gelatin is generally made from bone, but it may be made
from skin, eyes, or the like. Although the use of gelatin is preferable, pulverized bone, ossein,
collagen, or the like, which are raw materials for gelatin, can also be used. For example, an
oligomer, which is prepared by hydrolyzing this gelatin, pulverized bone, ossein, or collagen with an
enzyme such as a protease or lipase or a chemical catalyzer such as acid or alkali, may also be used.</p><p num="0014">Keratin that is used in the present invention is generally derived from poultry sources.
However, keratin derived from bovine, porcine, fish, human, or similar sources may also be used
without particular limitation on its origin. Keratin is generally made from poultry feathers, but it
may be made from horns, hair, scales, or the like. For example, an oligomer, which is prepared by 
hydrolyzing this keratin with an enzyme such as a protease or lipase or a chemical catalyzer such as
acid or alkali, may also be used.</p><p num="0015">Elastin that is used in the present invention is generally derived from bovine sources,
however, elastin derived from poultry, porcine, fish, human, or similar sources may also be used
without particular limitation on its origin. Elastin is generally made from the bovine neck ligament,
but it may be made from arteries, skin, lungs, or the like. For example, an oligomer, which is
prepared by hydrolyzing this elastin with an enzyme such as a protease or lipase or a chemical
catalyzer such as an acid or alkali, may also be used.</p><p num="0016">Casein that is used in the present invention is generally derived from a milk protein,
however, its origin is not particularly limited. For example, an oligomer, which is prepared by
hydrolyzing this casein with an enzyme such as a protease or lipase or a chemical catalyzer such as
acid or alkali, may also be used.</p><p num="0017">Gluten that is used in the present invention is generally derived from wheat, however, its
origin is not particularly limited. For example, an oligomer, which is prepared by hydrolyzing this
gluten with an enzyme such as a protease or lipase or a chemical catalyzer such as acid or alkali, may
also be used.</p><p num="0018">Zein that is used in the present invention is a main protein of maize, however, the type of
maize is not particularly limited. For example, an oligomer, which is prepared by hydrolyzing this
zein with an enzyme such as a protease or lipase or a chemical catalyzer such as acid or alkali, may
also be used.</p><p num="0019">The type of soybean protein that is used in the present invention is not particularly limited.
Preferably, soybean protein is used in a powder state. Also, soybeans, which are simply ground
without any special purification, for example, those separated through a 170 µm-sieve, are preferably
used.</p><p num="0020">At least one protein, which is selected from the silk, gelatin, keratin, elastin, casein, gluten,
zein, or soybean protein, is used solely or in combinations of two or more. Although the forms of
these proteins are not particularly limited, it is preferable if they are finely ground and used as
powders of 0.1 to 5000 µm for easy mixing with polylactide. It should be noted that the particle
sizes are not particularly limited. </p><p num="0021">The protein content is not particularly limited, and it is 0.01 to 5% by weight, preferably 0.1
to 5% by weight, and more preferably 0.2 to 3% by weight, based on polylactide, from the viewpoint
of maintenance of mechanical properties.</p> <p num="0022">When the protein content is less than 0.01% by weight, the effect of accelerating
biodegradability is significantly deteriorated. In contrast, protein content exceeding 5% by weight
is undesirable since the mechanical properties and water resistance thereof are deteriorated.</p><p num="0023">The biodegradable polylactide resin composition according to the present invention
comprises, as essential components, the polylactide and the protein. In order to accelerate
biodegradability, the addition of degraded mannan is preferable.</p><p num="0024">The term "degraded mannan" used herein refers to a degradation product of mannan which
is a compound having mannose as a constituent.</p><p num="0025">Mannan is a polysaccharide that is mainly constituted of mannose, and examples thereof
are classified as follows.</p><p num="0026">Plant-derived mannan: examples thereof include those obtained from a coprameal of a
coconut palm, coconut husk, a plant of a palm family, <i>Huacra Palm,</i> from South Africa, Chinese
yam mannan, and yam mannan.</p> <p num="0027">Glucomannan: a polysaccharide constituted by glucose and mannose, and examples thereof
include those obtained from rhizomes of konjak yam, lily, narcissus, or lycoris.</p> <p num="0028">Galactomannan: a polysaccharide constituted by galactose and mannose, and examples
thereof include those obtained from Locust bean gum, spino gum, galactomannan of coffee bean,
soybean derived from soybean seed coat, tamson gum, Tara gum, or Guar gum.</p> <p num="0029">Mannan comprises two or more saccharides as constituents besides mannose, and examples
thereof include D-galacto-D-gluco-D-mannan contained in a xylem of a conifer and mannan
obtained from xanthane gum, etc.</p><p num="0030">The degraded mannan used in the present invention can be obtained by degrading the
aforementioned various mannans in a desirable method. Examples of known methods for
degrading mannan include: a biochemical degradation method wherein degradation is carried out
directly using polysaccharide degrading enzymes (e.g., mannanase, galactomannanase, or
glucomannanase) or bacteria producing the enzymes; a chemical degradation method wherein 
degradation is carried out using acid, alkali, or the like; and a physical degradation method wherein
high-speed stirring, a shearing machine, or the like is employed. In the present invention, degraded
mannan that is degraded and produced by these methods may be obtained by any desirable
degradation methods, and it is not necessarily obtained through any of the aforementioned
degradation methods.</p><p num="0031">Specific examples of degraded mannan include: β-1,4-mannooligosaccharides such as
β-1,4-mannobiose, β-1,4-mannotriose, β-1,4-mannotetraose, or methyl β-mannoside;
β-1,6-galactomannooligosaccharides prepared by binding one or two branched galactose to
β-1,4-mannobiose, β-1,4-mannotriose, or β-1,4-mannotetraose; degraded galactomannan of
oligosaccharide, etc., obtained by degrading α-1,4-galactomannooligosaccharide,
α-1,6-galactomannooligosaccharide, α-1,3-galactomannooligosaccharide, copra cake, Guar gum, or
Locust bean gum with mannanase; oligosaccharide prepared by binding glucose or maltose to
β-1,4-mannobiose, mannotriose, or mannotetraose through a β-1,4-bond; and degraded
glucomannan contained in konjak.</p><p num="0032">The biodegradable polylactide resin composition according to the present invention
preferably comprises a filler in order to accelerate crystallization at the time of thermoforming,
thereby improving the thermal tolerance and mechanical strength of the formed product. Examples
of a filler include calcium carbonate, magnesium carbonate, calcium hydroxide, calcium oxide,
magnesium oxide, aluminum oxide, silicon oxide, iron oxide, boron nitride, titanium oxide, talc,
pyrophyllite clay, silicate pigment, polishing powder, mica, sericite, bentonite, pearlite, zeolite,
wollastonite, fluorite, dolomite, quick lime, slaked lime, kaolin, chlorite, and diatomaceous earth.</p><p num="0033">If necessary, the biodegradalbe polylactide resin composition can suitably comprise
auxiliary components such as a pigment, antioxidant, antistatic agent, delustering agent, coloring
agent, aromatic, antiaging agent, fluorescent brightening agent, ultraviolet absorber, ultraviolet
stabilizer, slip additive, filler, carbon black, thickener, chain extender, crosslinking agent, plasticizer,
stabilizer, or viscosity stabilizer.</p><p num="0034">Further, starch or processed starch, pectin, chitin, chitosan, alginic acid, xylose, cellulose, or
a cellulose derivative such as carboxymethylcellulose can be incorporated within a range that does
not impede the function and the effect of the present invention. </p><p num="0035">The biodegradable polylactide resin composition according to the present invention can be
prepared by adding silk, gelatin, keratin, elastin, or soybeans solely or in combinations of two or
more to polylactide, followed by mixing while heating. More preferably, degraded mannan, a filler,
or the like is added. In this case, a method for mixing while heating is not particularly limited.
Examples thereof include: a method wherein at least one of silk powder, gelatin, keratin, elastin,
casein, gluten, zein, or soybean protein is added to polylactide while heating it, followed by mixing
using a kneading machine such as a roll mill; a method wherein they are kneaded in an extruding
machine; blow molding; and foaming. Heating temperature is not particularly limited, and it is
generally in the range of 140 to 200°C.</p><p num="0036">The biodegradable polylactide resin composition according to the present invention has
significantly improved the biodegradability of polylactide while maintaining the good mechanical
strength and physical properties thereof.</p><p num="0037">This biodegradable polylactide resin composition can be processed into a plate, cylinder,
foam, or bottle by, for example, injecting it into an extrusion template at the time of heating.
Alternatively, the composition can be dissolved in a solvent to form it into a membrane, sheet, or
film.</p><p num="0038">Accordingly, the polylactide resin composition of the present invention can be suitably
used for various applications. Examples thereof include: materials for agriculture and horticulture
such as films for vinyl houses, films for tunnels, mulch films, vegetation films, seedling pots, plant
seeders, or covering materials for fertilizers or pesticides; packaging materials such as vegetation
nets, sandbags, mold forms for construction, sheets for civil engineering, trays for civil engineering
materials such as large head nails, foamed trays, stretch films, shrink films, beverage bottles, or
toothbrush blisters; materials for fisheries such as fish nets, laver nets, nets for cultivation, fishing
lines, or fishing bait bags; waterproof sheets for disposable diapers or sanitary items; medical
equipment such as packaging materials or injection syringes; daily necessities and miscellaneous
goods such as garbage bags, shopping bags, plastic bags, draining nets, plates, laminated containers
for forks and spoons, binding tape, handles of toothbrushes or razors, shampoo or rinse bottles,
cosmetics bottles, pens, or markers; medical materials such as bone connecting materials, surgical 
dressing, and wound covering materials; and other various applications such as air filters, magnetic
cards, labels, release papers, or golf tees.</p><p num="0039">Products formed of the polylactide resins rapidly degrade and disappear in nature such as
soil or water through the activities of microorganisms (bacteria) or enzymes, without generating
harmful substances. Accordingly, they can be buried in soil or compost, or poured in water in a
ground or unchanged state after use for their disposal.</p><p num="0040">The present invention is hereafter described in more detail with reference to examples and
comparative examples, although the technical scope of the present invention is not limited thereto.</p><heading><u style="single">Examples</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u>: Production of a polylactide plate comprising polylactide and silk powder</heading><p num="0041">Poly-L-lactic acid (Lacty #9000, Shimadzu) was used. This polylactide, silk powder, and
talc were mixed at a ratio of 96:2:2 by weight, and the mixture was then kneaded in a kneading
machine, which was heated at 185°C. Further, the product was pelletized and then made into a
sheet (thickness: 0.5 mm) using a heat press. Furthermore, dumbbell-shaped samples were cut
from the sheet and then subjected to performance tests.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u>: Production of a polylactide plate comprising polylactide and gelatin</heading><p num="0042">Poly-L-lactic acid (Lacty #9000) was used. This polylactide, gelatin, and
mannooligosaccharide were mixed at a ratio of 96:2:2 by weight. The mixture was made into a
sheet, dumbbell-shaped samples were prepared therefrom, and the samples were then subjected to
performance tests in the same manner as in Example 1.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 3</u>: Production of a polylactide plate comprising polylactide and keratin</heading><p num="0043">Poly-L-lactic acid (Lacty #9000) was used. This polylactide, keratin, and
mannooligosaccharide were mixed at a ratio of 96:2:2 by weight. The mixture was made into a
sheet, dumbbell-shaped samples were prepared therefrom, and the samples were then subjected to
performance tests in the same manner as in Example 1.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 4</u>: Production of a polylactide plate comprising polylactide and elastin</heading><p num="0044">Poly-L-lactic acid (Lacty #9000) was used. This polylactide, elastin, and
mannooligosaccharide were mixed at a ratio of 96:2:2 by weight. The mixture was made into a 
sheet, dumbbell-shaped samples were prepared therefrom, and the samples were then subjected to
performance tests in the same manner as in Example 1.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 5</u>: Production of a polylactide plate comprising polylactide and casein</heading><p num="0045">Poly-L-lactic acid (Lacty #9000) was used. This polylactide, casein, and talc were mixed
at a ratio of 96:2:2 by weight. The mixture was made into a sheet, dumbbell-shaped samples were
prepared therefrom, and the samples were then subjected to performance tests in the same manner as
in Example 1.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 6</u>: Production of a polylactide plate comprising polylactide and gluten</heading><p num="0046">Poly-L-lactic acid (Lacty #9000) was used. This polylactide, gluten, and talc were mixed
at a ratio of 96:2:2 by weight. The mixture was made into a sheet, dumbbell-shaped samples were
prepared therefrom, and the samples were then subjected to performance tests in the same manner as
in Example 1.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 7</u>: Production of a polylactide plate comprising polylactide and zein</heading><p num="0047">Poly-L-lactic acid (Lacty #9000) was used. This polylactide, zein, and talc were mixed at
a ratio of 96:2:2 by weight. The mixture was made into a sheet, dumbbell-shaped samples were
prepared therefrom, and the samples were then subjected to performance tests in the same manner as
in Example 1.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 8</u>: Production of a polylactide plate comprising polylactide and soybean protein powder</heading><p num="0048">Poly-L-lactic acid (Lacty #9000) was used. This polylactide, soybean protein powder,
and mannooligosaccharide were mixed at a ratio of 96:2:2 by weight. The mixture was made into a
sheet, dumbbell-shaped samples were prepared therefrom, and the samples were then subjected to
performance tests in the same manner as in Example 1.</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Example 1</u></heading><p num="0049">In the same manner as in Example 1, a polylactide composition was prepared without using
silk powder, the composition was made into a sheet, dumbbell-shaped samples were prepared
therefrom, and the samples were then subjected to performance tests (Lacty #9000:talc = 98:2).</p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Example 2</u></heading><p num="0050">In the same manner as in Example 2, a polylactide composition was prepared without using
gelatin, the composition was made into a sheet, dumbbell-shaped samples were prepared therefrom, 
and the samples were then subjected to performance tests (Lacty #9000:mannooligosaccharide =
98:2).</p><p num="0051">The sheet-like polylactide resin compositions prepared in the examples and comparative
examples were assayed concerning the following items to evaluate their physical properties and
functions. The results are shown in Table 1.</p><heading>1. Mechanical properties</heading><p num="0052">Breaking strengths and breaking elongations were assayed in accordance with the method
specified by JIS K-7113. Assay was carried out at a temperature of 17°C and a humidity of 50%.
The results are shown in Table 1. Breaking strengths and breaking elongations were determined by
the following equation.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Breaking strength (N/cm<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>) = breaking load (N) / cross section (cm<st32:sup pos="post">2</st32:sup>)<st32:break type="required"/>
Breaking elongation (%) [(breaking elongation - span length) / span length] x 100</st32:df><tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Ex.1</entry><entry align="center">Ex.2</entry><entry align="center">Ex.3</entry><entry align="center">Ex.4</entry><entry align="center">Ex. 5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Thickness (mm)</entry><entry align="center">0.501</entry><entry align="center">0.492</entry><entry align="center">0.502</entry><entry align="center">0.495</entry><entry align="center">0.498</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Breaking strength (N/cm<sup>2</sup>)</entry><entry align="center">4850.8</entry><entry align="center">4820.3</entry><entry align="center">4820.1</entry><entry align="center">4840.5</entry><entry align="center">4895.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Breaking elongation (%)</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">1.6</entry></row><row><entry nameend="6" align="right" namest="1"/></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Ex.6</entry><entry align="center">Ex. 7</entry><entry align="center">Ex. 8</entry><entry align="center">Comp. Ex. 1</entry><entry align="center">Comp. Ex. 2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Thickness (mm)</entry><entry align="center">0.502</entry><entry align="center">0.498</entry><entry align="center">0.501</entry><entry align="center">0.503</entry><entry align="center">0.497</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Breaking strength (N/cm<sup>2</sup>)</entry><entry align="center">4880.3</entry><entry align="center">4780.2</entry><entry align="center">4870.3</entry><entry align="center">4750.2</entry><entry align="center">4730.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Breaking elongation (%)</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">1.4</entry></row><row><entry>(Results of Example 1, Example 2, Example 3, Example 4, Example 5, Example 6, Example 7, Example 8, Comparative Examples 1, and Comparative Example 2 indicate the averages of 10 samples)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>2. Evaluation of biodegradability</heading><p num="0053">Flat films (8 cm x 8 cm, 5 mm-thick, Example 1, Example 2, Comparative Example 1, and
Comparative Example 2) were buried in soil (Tsukuba, Ibaraki), and biodegradabilities were
investigated based on changes in weights. Decreased weights (rate of weight decrease, %)
indicated levels of the biodegradation of the flat films. The results are shown in Table 2.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry nameend="6" namest="1">Biodegradability by being buried in soil</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="2">Rate of weight decrease, %</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Ex. 1</entry><entry align="center">Ex. 2</entry><entry align="center">Ex. 3</entry><entry align="center">Ex.4</entry><entry align="center">Ex. 5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">0 hour</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1 month later</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">22</entry><entry align="center">21</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2 months later</entry><entry align="center">33</entry><entry align="center">38</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">31</entry><entry align="center">28</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3 months later</entry><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">55</entry><entry align="center">42</entry><entry align="center">38</entry><entry align="center">34</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="6" align="center" namest="2">Rate of weight decrease, %</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Ex. 6</entry><entry align="center">Ex. 7</entry><entry align="center">Ex. 8</entry><entry align="center">Comp. Ex. 1</entry><entry align="center">Comp. Ex. 2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">0 hour</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1 month later</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">22</entry><entry align="center">19</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">18</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2 months later</entry><entry align="center">27</entry><entry align="center">28</entry><entry align="center">28</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3 months later</entry><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">37</entry><entry align="center">39</entry><entry align="center">23</entry><entry align="center">33</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A biodegradable polylactide resin composition, which comprises at least one protein
selected from silk, gelatin, keratin, elastin, casein, gluten, zein, or soybean protein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A biodegradable polylactide resin composition, which further comprises degraded
mannan.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The biodegradable polylactide resin composition according to claim 1 or 2, which further
comprises a filler.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The biodegradable polylactide resin composition according to any of claims 1 to 3,
which comprises 0.01 to 5% by weight of the protein based on polylactide.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>