<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2004043343-A2" country="WO" doc-number="2004043343" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="30770736" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20040527"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2004043343-A2" status="new" fvid="78769451"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2004043343</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20040527</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-0332414-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>0332414</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20031014</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-28919002-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>28919002</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021105</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>A61K    /</main-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   6/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   6/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K   6/00C</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">HEMOSTATIC AND ACID ETCH COMPOSITIONS CONTAINING SUCRALOSE</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">COMPOSITIONS D'ATTAQUE CHIMIQUE HEMOSTATIQUES ET ACIDES CONTENANT DU SUCRALOSE</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-4551100-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4551100</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5635162-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5635162</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5785955-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5785955</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ULTRADENT PRODUCTS INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ULTRADENT PRODUCTS, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ALLRED PETER M</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>JENSEN STEVEN D</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ALLRED, PETER, M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>JENSEN, STEVEN, D.</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Hemostatic compositions and dental etching compositions for oral use include sucralose in order to mask or disguise their otherwise sour or bitter taste. The sucralose, hemostatic and/or dental etching agent are dispersed within an aqueous carrier, which may be liquid or viscous as desired. In order to increase the stickiness and the viscosity of the carrier, a higher molecular weight polyol and/or a finely divided inorganic filler may be included. Sucralose is selected as a sweetener because it has been found to have enhanced stability in the presence of strongly acidic compositions compared to other non-nutritive sweeteners known in the art. In addition, sucralose does not leave behind a bitter after taste. For this reason, sucralose is uniquely suited for masking or disguising the profoundly sour or bitter taste of hemostatic agents and/or dental etching agents.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>L'invention porte sur des compositions d'attaque chimique hémostatiques et dentaires destinées à un usage par voie orale et comprenant du sucralose afin de masquer ou déguiser le goût acide ou amer. L'agent d'attaque chimique hémostatique et/ou dentaire contenant du sucralose est dispersé dans un excipient aqueux qui peut être liquide ou visqueux, au choix. Afin d'accroître l'adhésivité et la viscosité de l'excipient, on peut ajouter un polyol de poids moléculaire supérieur et/ou une charge inorganique finement broyée. Le sucralose est sélectionné comme édulcorant du fait qu'il s'avère avoir une meilleure stabilité en présence de compositions extrêmement acides comparé à d'autres édulcorants non nutritifs connus dans la technique. De plus, le sucralose ne laisse pas un arrière-goût amer. C'est pour cette raison qu'il est parfaitement approprié pour masquer ou déguiser le goût profondément acide ou amer des agents hémostatiques et/ou des agents d'attaque chimique dentaires.</p></abstract><description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="2"/>--><p num="p0001"> HEMOSTATIC AND ACID ETCH COMPOSITIONS CONTAINING SUCRALOSE</p><p num="p0002">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</p><p num="p0003">1. The Field of the Invention The present invention is in the field of hemostatic and acid etch compositions, more particularly hemostatic compositions for use in providing hemostasis in oral tissues and etching compositions used in etching teeth.</p><p num="p0004">2. The Relevant Technology</p><p num="p0005">In the course of performing certain dental procedures it is often desirable to use a hemostatic composition in order to stop the bleeding of oral tissues. For example, during dental reconstruction or preparation of dental crowns it is common for dentists to cut gingival or gum tissue in order to fully expose the tooth prior to taking an impression of the tooth. In order to make an accurate impression of the tooth it is advantageous for it to be clean and dry. For this reason, a hemostatic composition may be used to reduce or eliminate bleeding so that a more accurate impression of the patient's tooth can be taken.</p><p num="p0006">In the case of invasive dental procedures, such as preparing the tooth to receive a crown or forming a deep dental preparation that is to be filled with a restorative composition, sufficient enamel and dentin may be removed so as to expose the pulp chamber. It may be desirable in some cases to apply a hemostatic composition to stop or slow bleeding of the exposed pulp.</p><p num="p0007">Whereas hemostatic compositions of various types have been used successfully to stop or slow the bleeding of oral tissues during a variety of dental or oral procedures, hemostatic compositions can be very unpleasant tasting. Hemostatic compositions tend to be quite acidic (i.e., typically having a pH of about 1-2), which makes them have a profound sour or bitter flavor. It is therefore preferable to avoid contacting the patient's tongue with the hemostatic composition during the procedure in question. Allowing the hemostatic composition to contact the person's tongue is not only unpleasant to the patient, it may even cause the patient to flinch or experience a gag reflex, both of which can hinder the dental procedure. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>-->
 A similar problem exists in the case of dental etching compositions used to etch a patient's tooth during a dental procedure. Dental etching compositions are typically used to create a superior bonding surface in dentin, enamel or both to which a restorative composition can better adhere. However, since dental etching compositions are by nature very acidic (i.e., typically having a pH of about 0-2), they also have a profound sour or bitter flavor and cause similar problems associated with hemostatic compositions.</p><p num="p0008">In view of the foregoing, it would be an advancement in the art to provide better tasting hemostatic and dental etching compositions. More particularly, it would a an important advancement in the art to provide hemostatic and dental etching compositions that were more palatable to the patient in order to reduce the tendency of such compositions to startle the patient or induce a gag reflex if such compositions happen to contact the patient's tongue.</p><p num="p0009">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION The present invention is directed to hemostatic compositions and dental etching compositions that contain sucralose, which is a non-nutritive sweetener. The inclusion of sucralose adds a pleasant taste that at least partially offsets the otherwise sour or bitter taste of the acidic hemostatic and/or acidic dental etching agents. This, in turn, reduces the chance that a patient will be surprised or startled in the event the hemostatic composition or dental etching composition were to contact the patient's tongue. Thus, an advantage of including sucralose within such compositions is that it creates a more pleasant experience for the patient. It may also reduce the tendency of the patient to flinch or gag if the otherwise sour or bitter composition were to contact the patient's tongue. One advantage of sucralose is that it is many times sweeter than sugar, which greatly reduces the amount of sweetener that must be added to offset the sour or bitter taste of the hemostatic or dental etching agent. This results in less residue that must otherwise be removed from the patient's tooth. Another advantage of using sucralose over certain sweeteners (e.g., aspartame) is that sucralose has been found by the inventors to be stable in the presence of hemostatic or dental etching agents, both of 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
which are highly acidic in water. Thus, sucralose is effective in disguising the sour or bitter taste of such agents even after being mixed and stored with such agents over time (e.g., weeks, months or even years). Sucralose has also been found by the inventors to leave no bitter or unpleasant after taste, which is an advantage over certain non-nutritive sweeteners, such as sodium saccharine.</p><p num="p0010">The sucralose and hemostatic or dental etching agent are mixed together within an appropriate carrier, such as an aqueous liquid or gel. Water is typically used as part of the carrier in order to dissolve the sucralose, hemostatic agent and/or dental etching agent within the carrier. In the case where a sticky or viscous composition is desired, one or more thickening or tackifying agents may be included, examples of which include finely divided gel-forming metal oxides (e.g., fumed silica, precipitated or fumed aluminum oxide), organic thickeners (e.g., pemulen), or other gelling agents known in the art.</p><p num="p0011">The inventive compositions may also include other adjuvents and active ingredients such as flavorants, desensitizing agents (e.g., KNO<sub>3</sub>), anticariogenic agents (e.g., fluoride compounds), antimicrobial agents (e.g., antibiotics), stabilizing agents (e.g., EDTA), and the like. The carrier is preferably substantially free of abrasives.</p><p num="p0012">Depending on the desired treatment regimen, the hemostatic or dental etching compositions according to the invention may vary as desired in potency, fluidity or stickiness in order to optimize the performance of the composition for a given treatment regimen.</p><p num="p0013">Examples of hemostatic agents that may be used within the inventive hemostatic compositions include, but are not limited to, ferric sulfate, ferric subsulfate, ferric chloride, zinc chloride, aluminum chloride, aluminum sulfate, aluminum chlorohydrate, aluminum acetate, alum, salts of manganese, salts of bismuth, permanganates, and tannin.</p><p num="p0014">Examples of dental etching agents include, but are not limited to, mineral acids, such as phosphoric acid, nitric acid, hydrochloric acid and sulfuric acid, and 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
organic acids, such as glycolic acid, malic acid, maleic acid, acetic acid, citric acid, and EDTA.</p><p num="p0015">Hemostatic compositions according to the invention will typically have a pH of less than about 3, preferably less than about 2.5, more preferably a pH less than about 2, and most preferably a pH in a range of about 1-2. Dental etching compositions according to the invention will preferably have a pH of less than about 2, more preferably a pH less than about 1, and most preferably a pH in a range of about 0-1.</p><p num="p0016">These and other features of the present invention will become more fully apparent from the following description and appended claims, or may be learned by the practice of the invention as set forth hereinafter.</p><p num="p0017">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OP THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS I. INTRODUCTION</p><p num="p0018">As summarized above, the invention is generally related to acidic hemostatic compositions and dental etching compositions that contain sucralose, a chlorinated sucrose derivative that has greatly enhanced sweetness compared to sucrose. The purpose of the sucralose is to mask or disguise the extremely sour or bitter taste associated with hemostatic agents and/or dental etching agents.</p><p num="p0019">Hemostatic compositions within the scope of the invention encompass virtually any hemostatic composition suitable for providing hemostasis in oral tissues so long as it contains sucralose. Likewise, dental etching compositions within the scope of the invention encompass virtually any dental etching composition suitable for etching teeth so long as it contains sucralose. The inventive compositions generally comprise at least one of a hemostatic agent or dental etching agent dispersed in an aqueous carrier. The carrier may be a liquid or gel and have any desired viscosity.</p><p num="p0020">Examples of hemostatic compositions that have the consistency of a low viscosity liquid or fluid are ASTRINGEDENT, ASTRINGEDENT X, and</p><p num="p0021">BUFFERED ALUMINUM CHLORIDE, which are sold by Ultradent Products, Inc. which is located in South Jordan, Utah. Examples of more viscous hemostatic 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
compositions are VISCOSTAT and VISCOSTAT PLUS, which are also available from Ultradent Products, Inc. ASTRINGEDENT, ASTRINGEDENT X, BUFFERED ALUMINUM CHLORIDE, VISCOSTAT, and VISCOSTAT PLUS can be modified according to the teachings disclosed herein to include sucralose in order to improve their taste.</p><p num="p0022">Additional examples of hemostatic compositions that may be modified according to the present invention are set forth in U.S. Patent No. 4,551,100 to Fischer, U.S. Patent No. 5,635,162 to Fischer, and U.S. Patent No. 5,785,955 to Fischer. For purposes of generally disclosing hemostatic compositions, the foregoing patents are incorporated herein by reference.</p><p num="p0023">Examples of dental etching compositions that may be modified according to the invention so as to include sucralose include ULTRA-ETCH and ULTRA-ETCH AB, both of which are available from Ultradent Products, Inc.</p><p num="p0024">The term "about" when used in combination with a numeric value shall mean ± 10% of the numeric value. Thus, the effect of the term "about" is to define a range that is ± 10% of the given numeric value. II. ACIDIC COMPOSITIONS CONTAINING SUCRALOSE</p><p num="p0025">The acidic dental compositions according to the invention include sucralose, at least one acidic agent such as a hemostatic agent and/or a dental etching agent, and an aqueous carrier into which the sucralose and acidic agent are dispersed. The compositions may include other ingredients as needed to yield a composition having desired properties. The acidic dental compositions are preferably formulated so as to be safe for introduction into the oral cavity of a patient. A. Sucralose More proper chemical names for "sucralose" include: l,6-dichloro-l,6- dideoxy-β-D-fructo-furanosyl-4-chloro-4-deoxy-α-D-galactopyranoside; 4, 1 &amp;- trichloro-4,r,6'-trideoxy-galacto-sucrose; r,4,6'-trichloro-galactosucrose; and TGS. Sucralose has the general formula C12H19C13O8 and a molecular weight of 397.64. Publications which disclose methods for preparing sucralose include European Patent Application 0 030 804 to Tate et al. and U.S. Patent No. 4,343,934 to Jenner et al. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
U.S. Patent No. 4,435,440 to Hough et al. describes the usefulness of sucralose as a sweetener. The foregoing references are incorporated herein by reference.</p><p num="p0026">Sucralose is non-nutritive so it has none of the disadvantages associated with nutritive sweeteners, e.g., promoting tooth decay. However, it tastes very much like sugar while being approximately 600 times sweeter than sugar. Because sucralose is so sweet tasting, even a small amount of sucralose is sufficient to disguise the bitter taste of the bleaching agent. Additionally, sucralose has been found to be surprisingly stable for extended periods of time when mixed with a bleaching agent. Sucralose, unlike sodium saccharine, does not itself leave a bitter after taste. Nor is it suspected of being a carcinogen. Hence, the inventive bleaching compositions of the present invention are better tasting, with stable taste properties over time, compared to compositions that use, e.g., aspartame, and safer to use, compared to compositions that use, e.g., sodium saccharine.</p><p num="p0027">In order to impart a desired sweetening effect to the acidic compositions in order to disguise or mask the sour or bitter taste of the acidic agent(s) contained therein (e.g., hemostatic and/or dental etching agents), the inventive compositions according to the invention may contain any suitable quantity of sucralose. The amount of sucralose may vary depending on the desired sweetening effect and the concentration of the acidic agents contained in the acidic composition. As the concentration of the acidic agent is increased, a larger concentration of sucralose will typically be used to offset the increased level of sourness or bitterness imparted by the acidic agent(s) to the composition.</p><p num="p0028">In general, the acidic compositions according to the invention will preferably contain sucralose in an amount in a range of about 0.01% to about 15% by weight of the composition, more preferably in a range of about 0.05% to about 10% by weight of the composition, and most preferably in a range of about 0.1% to about 5% by weight of the composition. The foregoing concentrations take into consideration the fact that sucralose is typically commercially available as an aqueous solution, the water forming part of the carrier once the aqueous sucralose solution has been added to a composition according to the invention. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>-->
 The stability of the sucralose within the acidic compositions according to the invention is generally sufficient such that the acidic compositions can be stored for long periods of time and used as desired, while maintaining sufficient sweetness of the sucralose so as to mask the generally sour or bitter taste of the hemostatic and/or dental etching agent. For example, an acidic composition containing sucralose which is formed in accordance with the invention is likely after 1 year to still have substantially the same concentration of sucralose as it contained when originally manufactured. In any event, the sucralose content would be expected after 1 year to be at least 85% of the amount contained in the composition when initially manufactured. Similarly, the sucralose content would be expected after about 4 to 6 months to be at least 90% of the amount contained in the composition when originally manufactured.</p><p num="p0029">In any event, the ultimate shelf life of a particular composition according to the invention is not limited by the stability of the sucralose within the composition. It is certainly the case that even if the sucralose loses a significant or even a substantial portion of its sweetening ability over time, the compositions will still function as intended even though they may be more sour or bitter.</p><p num="p0030">B. Hemostatic Agents</p><p num="p0031">Hemostatic agents for use in the inventive compositions can be selected from a wide variety of hemostatic compounds or agents known in the art, which can be used singly or in a variety of different combinations. Examples include, but are not limited to, metal salts, such as the salts of aluminum, iron, zinc, manganese, and bismuth, as well as ions that contain one or more of these metals (e.g., permanganates).</p><p num="p0032">Non-limiting examples of suitable hemostatic agents that may be used within hemostatic compositions within the scope of the invention include ferric sulfate, ferric subsulfate, ferric chloride, other iron (III) salts, zinc chloride, aluminum chloride, aluminum sulfate, aluminum chlorohydrate, aluminum acetate, alums (e.g., aluminum potassium sulfate and aluminum ammonium sulfate), tannins, and polyphenolic compounds. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>-->
 A currently preferred hemostatic agent for use in formulating hemostatic compositions according to the invention is a ferric salt compound. Preferred ferric salts include ferric sulfate, which has the formula Fe<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>, and ferric subsulfate, which has the formula Fe<sub>4</sub>(OH) (SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>5</sub>. Both ferric and sulfate ions are present within the human body. Thus, the probability of allergic reactions to ferric sulfate or ferric subsulfate is low. The ferric salts are coagulative hemostats, and when contacted with blood, the ferric salts cause an instant precipitation of blood proteins, which forms a coagulum.</p><p num="p0033">The hemostatic agent may also facilitate tissue retraction by reducing the elasticity of collagen fibers within the gingival cuff. This can be beneficial in some cases as it can prevent premature closure of the sulcular space during impression placement and solidification. In addition, the hemostatic agent facilitates reduced sulcular fluid movement through intact epithelium, whether for impression making or during bonding or luting stages of the final restoration placement procedure. Finally, the hemostatic agent can be useful in stopping the bleeding of wounds in soft tissues in general.</p><p num="p0034">When the acidic compositions according to the invention contain a hemostatic agent, the hemostatic agent is included in an effective amount so as to provide hemostatic properties to the composition. The hemostatic agent is preferably included within the hemostatic composition in an amount in a range of about 1% to about 40% by weight of the hemostatic composition, more preferably in a range of about 5% to about 35%o by weight, and most preferably in a range of about 10%&gt; to about 30%&gt; by weight of the hemostatic composition.</p><p num="p0035">Hemostatic compositions according to the invention will typically have a pH of less than about 3, preferably less than about 2.5, more preferably less than about 2, and most preferably have a pH in a range of about 1 to about 2.</p><p num="p0036">C. Dental Etching Agents</p><p num="p0037">Dental etching agents for use in the inventive compositions can be selected from a wide variety of acidic compounds that are capable of etching. Examples of dental etching agents include, but are not limited to, mineral acids, such as phosphoric 
<!-- EPO <DP n="10"/>-->
acid, nitric acid, hydrochloric acid and sulfuric acid, and organic acids, such as glycolic acid, malic acid, maleic acid, acetic acid, citric acid, and EDTA.</p><p num="p0038">When the acidic compositions according to the invention contain a dental etching agent, the etching agent is included in an effective amount so as to etch at least one of dentin or enamel. The etching agent is preferably included within the dental etching composition in an amount in a range of about 10% to about 60%) by weight of the etching composition, more preferably in a range of about 20% to about 50% by weight, and most preferably in a range of about 25%&gt; to about 45%&gt; by weight of the etching composition. Dental etching compositions within the scope of the invention will preferably have a pH of less than about 2, more preferably less than about 1, and most preferably have a pH in a range of 0 to about 1. D. Carrier The compositions according to the invention typically include an aqueous carrier. The water can be present as part of the other components of the composition or it can be added separately. The water may be deionized if desired prior to use in the composition. In general, water is included in an amount in a range from about 1% to about 80% by weight of the acidic composition, more preferably in a range of about 40%&gt; to about 60%&gt; by weight. The various components may be mixed together in the desired amounts using standard mixing procedures to form the composition of the invention. If a solid hemostatic agent, such as a solid ferric salt, is used in formulating the compositions according to the invention, it is preferably to first dissolve the solid hemostatic agent in water before adding the other components of the composition. The various polyols can be added to the compositions according to the invention. Examples of suitable polyols include polyethylene glycol, glycerin, propylene glycol, dipropylene glycol, polypropylene glycol, sorbitol, and the like. Polyols used can have a wide variety of molecular weights, with higher molecular weight polyols generally increasing the viscosity of the acidic compositions according to the invention. For example, polyols having an average molecular weight (number 
<!-- EPO <DP n="11"/>-->
average) of at least about 600 may be included in order to increase the viscosity of the resulting composition. It should be understood that polyols having an average molecular weight of up to 100,000 or more may also be used. In some cases it may be desirable to mix two or more different polyols together having different molecular weights in order to yield a composition having the desired properties. When a polyol is included within the composition according to the invention, they are preferably included in an amount in a range from about 0.1% to about 50% by weight of the composition, and more preferably in a range of about 5% to about 40% by weight.</p><p num="p0039">It is within the scope of the invention to include one or more thickening agents within the compositions according to the invention in order to yield a composition having the desired viscosity and/or thixotropic nature. Higher molecular weight polyols are examples of thickening agents that may be used in accordance with the invention. One organic polymer thickening agent that is relatively stable in the presence of weakly acidic compositions is PEMULEN. Other polymeric thickening agents may be used with the caveat that many thickening agents tend to break down and are unstable in the presence of strong acids.</p><p num="p0040">Accordingly, it may be desirable to instead include inorganic fillers, preferably finely divided organic particulate fillers that are able to impart a thickening effect. Examples of inorganic fillers that may be used to impart a thickening effect include silica-based particulates such as colloidal silica, fumed silica, ground silica, precipitated silica, and the like. Silica-based fillers are able to provide a thixotropic property to the compositions, resulting in sheer thinning when agitated (such as when dispensed through a needle or agitated after being placed) and then thickening when agitation ceases, thereby resulting in a composition that becomes more viscous. This provides improved application control of the acidic compositions when applied using an applicator device such as the dento-infusor device as compared to non-viscous compositions it helps to keep the composition in place where applied.</p><p num="p0041">Examples of other useful inorganic fillers include metal oxides such as aluminum oxide and titanium dioxide. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="12"/>-->
 When an inorganic filler is included in the composition according to the invention, they are preferably included in an amount in a range from about 0.1% to about 30% by weight of the composition, more preferably in a range of about 0.1% to about 10%) by weight. E. Other Additives</p><p num="p0042">The inventive compositions may also include other adjuvents and active ingredients such as flavorants, desensitizing agents (e.g., KNO<sub>3</sub>), anticariogenic agents (e.g., fluoride compounds), antimicrobial agents (e.g., antibiotics), stabilizing agents (e.g., EDTA), and the like. The carrier is preferably substantially free of abrasives.</p><p num="p0043">IV. EXAMPLES</p><p num="p0044">The following examples set forth various exemplary hemostatic compositions and dental etching compositions according to the invention. These examples are intended to be purely exemplary and should not be viewed as limiting the scope of the present invention. Examples that were actually made are set forth in past tense, while hypothetical examples are set forth in present tense.</p><p num="p0045">EXAMPLE 1 A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below: Ingredient Amount (Weight %)</p><p num="p0046">Ferric Sulfate 34.4</p><p num="p0047">Deionized Water 53.2</p><p num="p0048">Polyethylene Glycol (8000 m.w.) 9</p><p num="p0049">Fumed Silica 3.4 The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01 %&gt; to 15%) by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01% increments throughout the range. At least some of the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="13"/>-->
modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year.</p><p num="p0050">EXAMPLE 2 A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below:</p><p num="p0051">Ingredient Amount (Weight %&gt;) Ferric Sulfate 22.7</p><p num="p0052">Deionized Water 47.9</p><p num="p0053">Polyethylene Glycol (8000 m.w.) 26</p><p num="p0054">Fumed Silica 3.4</p><p num="p0055">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01% to 15% by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01%&gt; increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="14"/>--></p><p num="p0056">EXAMPLE 3 A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below:</p><p num="p0057">Ingredient Amount (Weight %)</p><p num="p0058">Ferric Sulfate 20.6</p><p num="p0059">Deionized Water 32.7</p><p num="p0060">Polyethylene Glycol (8000 m.w.) 32.3</p><p num="p0061">Polyethylene Glycol (1450 m.w.) 11.3</p><p num="p0062">Fumed Silica 3.1 The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose<sup>'</sup> in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01%&gt; to 15% by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01% increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year.</p><p num="p0063">EXAMPLE 4 A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below:</p><p num="p0064">Ingredient Amount (Weight %&gt;) Ferric Sulfate 22.7</p> <p num="p0065">Deionized Water 52.9</p><p num="p0066">Polyethylene Glycol (8000 m.w.) 21</p><p num="p0067">Fumed Silica 3.4</p><p num="p0068">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="15"/>-->
starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01%&gt; to 15%o by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01%) increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year. <sup>'</sup> EXAMPLE 5</p><p num="p0069">A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below.</p> <p num="p0070">Ingredient Amount (Weight %)</p> <p num="p0071">Aluminum Chloride 22.7 Deionized Water 52.9</p> <p num="p0072">Polyethylene Glycol (8000 m.w.) 21</p><p num="p0073">Fumed Silica 3.4</p><p num="p0074">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01% to 15% by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01% increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="16"/>-->
 EXAMPLE 6 A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below:</p><p num="p0075">Ingredient Amount (Weight &gt; Ferric Sulfate 10</p><p num="p0076">Deionized Water 77.6</p><p num="p0077">Polyethylene Glycol (8000 m.w.) 2.4</p><p num="p0078">Fumed Silica 10</p><p num="p0079">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01% to 15% by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01% increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year. EXAMPLE 7</p><p num="p0080">A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below:</p><p num="p0081">Ingredient Amount (Weight %&gt;)</p><p num="p0082">Ferric Sulfate 34.4 Deionized Water 51.2</p><p num="p0083">Polyethylene Glycol (8000 m.w.) 13.9</p><p num="p0084">Fumed Silica 0.5</p><p num="p0085">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic 
<!-- EPO <DP n="17"/>-->
compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01% to 15% by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01% increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year.</p><p num="p0086">EXAMPLE 8 A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below:</p><p num="p0087">Ingredient Amount (Weight %)</p><p num="p0088">Ferric Sulfate 20</p><p num="p0089">Deionized Water 65 Fumed Silica 15</p><p num="p0090">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01% to 15%) by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01 %&gt; increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="18"/>--></p><p num="p0091">EXAMPLE 9 A starting hemostatic composition was <sup>'</sup> made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below:</p><p num="p0092">Ingredient Amount (Weight %) Ferric Sulfate 28</p><p num="p0093">Deionized Water 63</p><p num="p0094">Fumed Silica 9</p><p num="p0095">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01% to 15%) by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01%&gt; increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year.</p><p num="p0096">EXAMPLE 10 A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below:</p><p num="p0097">Ingredient Amount (Weight %)</p><p num="p0098">Ferric Sulfate 20</p><p num="p0099">Deionized Water 75 Fumed Silica 5</p><p num="p0100">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01%) to 15%) by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of 
<!-- EPO <DP n="19"/>-->
sucralose increasing by 0.01% increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year.</p><p num="p0101">EXAMPLE 11 A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below: Ingredient Amount (Weight %&gt;)</p><p num="p0102">Ferric Sulfate 18</p><p num="p0103">Deionized Water 79</p><p num="p0104">Fumed Silica 3</p><p num="p0105">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01% to 15%) by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01%&gt; increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year. EXAMPLE 12</p><p num="p0106">A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below: 
<!-- EPO <DP n="20"/>-->
 Ingredient Amount (Weight %&gt;)</p><p num="p0107">Ferric Sulfate 20</p><p num="p0108">Deionized Water 54</p><p num="p0109">Fumed Silica 26 The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01% to 15% by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01% increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year.</p><p num="p0110">EXAMPLE 13 A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below:</p><p num="p0111">Ingredient Amount (Weight %) Aluminum Chloride 18</p><p num="p0112">Deionized Water 37</p><p num="p0113">Polyethylene Glycol (8000 m.w.) 45</p><p num="p0114">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01% to 15%) by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01%» increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose 
<!-- EPO <DP n="21"/>-->
increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year.</p><p num="p0115">EXAMPLE 14 A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below:</p><p num="p0116">Ingredient Amount (Weight %)</p><p num="p0117">Ferric Sulfate 20</p><p num="p0118">Deionized Water 54 Polyethylene Glycol (8000 m.w.) 26</p><p num="p0119">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01 %&gt; to 15% by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01% increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year.</p><p num="p0120">EXAMPLE 15 A starting hemostatic composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below: 
<!-- EPO <DP n="22"/>--></p><p num="p0121">Ingredient Amount (Weight %)</p><p num="p0122">Ferric Sulfate 15</p><p num="p0123">Deionized Water 25</p><p num="p0124">Polyethylene Glycol (8000 m.w.) 30</p><p num="p0125">Polyethylene Glycol (1500 m.w.) 30</p><p num="p0126">The pH of the starting hemostatic composition was less than 3. Modified hemostatic compositions are formed by adding sucralose in varying amounts to the starting hemostatic composition in order to yield a plurality of modified hemostatic compositions that contain sucralose in varying concentrations within a range of 0.01 %&gt; to 15% by weight of the modified hemostatic compositions, with the concentration of sucralose increasing by 0.01% increments throughout the range. At least some of the modified hemostatic compositions are subjectively better tasting than the starting hemostatic composition, with increasing sweetness as the concentration of sucralose increases. The sucralose remains stable for at least one year when the modified hemostatic compositions (pH &lt; 3) are stored at room temperature such that a substantial portion of the sucralose still exists after one year.</p><p num="p0127">EXAMPLE 16 A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 99 parts by weight of VISCOSTAT brand hemostatic composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 1 part by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25% sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than VISCOSTAT that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0128">EXAMPLE 17 A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 98 parts by weight of VISCOSTAT brand hemostatic composition sold by Ultradent Products, Inc. and 2 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25%&gt; 
<!-- EPO <DP n="23"/>-->
sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than VISCOSTAT that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0129">EXAMPLE 18</p><p num="p0130">A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 96 parts by weight of VISCOSTAT brand hemostatic composition sold by Ultradent Products, Inc. and 4 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25%o sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than VISCOSTAT that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0131">EXAMPLE 19</p><p num="p0132">A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 99 parts by weight of VISCOSTAT PLUS brand hemostatic composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 1 part by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25%o sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than VISCOSTAT PLUS that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0133">EXAMPLE 20 A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 98 parts by weight of VISCOSTAT PLUS brand hemostatic composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 2 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose 
<!-- EPO <DP n="24"/>-->
solution (25% sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than VISCOSTAT PLUS that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0134">EXAMPLE 21 A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 96 parts by weight of VISCOSTAT PLUS brand hemostatic composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 4 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25%» sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than VISCOSTAT PLUS that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0135">EXAMPLE 22 A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 99 parts by weight of ASTRINGEDENT brand hemostatic composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 1 part by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25%o sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than ASTRINGEDENT that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0136">EXAMPLE 23 A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 98 parts by weight of ASTRINGEDENT brand hemostatic composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 2 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose 
<!-- EPO <DP n="25"/>-->
solution (25% sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than ASTRINGEDENT that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0137">EXAMPLE 24</p><p num="p0138">A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 96 parts by weight of ASTRINGEDENT brand hemostatic composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 4 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25%o sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than ASTRINGEDENT that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0139">EXAMPLE 25</p><p num="p0140">A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 99 parts by weight of ASTRINGEDENT X brand hemostatic composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 1 part by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25%) sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than ASTRINGEDENT X that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0141">EXAMPLE 26 A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 98 parts by weight of ASTRINGEDENT X brand hemostatic composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 2 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose 
<!-- EPO <DP n="26"/>-->
solution (25% sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than ASTRINGEDENT X that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0142">EXAMPLE 27</p><p num="p0143">A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 96 parts by weight of ASTRINGEDENT X brand hemostatic composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 4 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25% sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than ASTRINGEDENT X that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0144">EXAMPLE 28</p><p num="p0145">A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 94 parts by weight of ASTRINGEDENT X brand hemostatic composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 6 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25%o sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than ASTRINGEDENT X that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0146">EXAMPLE 29 A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 99 parts by weight of BUFFERED ALUMINUM CHLORIDE brand product available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 1 part by weight of an aqueous sucralose 
<!-- EPO <DP n="27"/>-->
solution (25%o sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than BUFFERED ALUMINUM CHLORIDE that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0147">EXAMPLE 30</p><p num="p0148">A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 98 parts by weight of BUFFERED ALUMINUM CHLORIDE brand product available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 2 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25% sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than BUFFERED ALUMINUM CHLORIDE that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0149">EXAMPLE 31</p><p num="p0150">A hemostatic composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 96 parts by weight of BUFFERED ALUMINUM CHLORIDE brand product available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 4 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25%&gt; sucralose in water). The pH of the hemostatic composition was between 1 and 2. The resulting hemostatic composition was found to be better tasting than BUFFERED ALUMINUM CHLORIDE that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the hemostatic composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0151">EXAMPLE 32 A dental etching composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 99 parts by weight of ULTRA-ETCH brand etching composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 1 part by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution 
<!-- EPO <DP n="28"/>-->
(25%&gt; sucralose in water). The pH of the etching composition was between 0 and 1. The resulting etching composition was found to be better tasting than ULTRA-ETCH that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the etching composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0152">EXAMPLE 33 A dental etching composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 98 parts by weight of ULTRA-ETCH brand etching composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 2 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25% sucralose in water). The pH of the etching composition was between 0 and 1. The resulting etching composition was found to be better tasting than ULTRA-ETCH that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the etching composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0153">EXAMPLE 34 A dental etching composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 99 parts by weight of ULTRA-ETCH AB brand etching composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 1 part by weight of an aqueous sucralose solution (25%o sucralose in water). The pH of the etching composition was between 0 and 1. The resulting etching composition was found to be better tasting than ULTRA- ETCH AB that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the etching composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0154">EXAMPLE 35 A dental etching composition according to the invention was made by mixing together 98 parts by weight of ULTRA-ETCH AB brand etching composition available from Ultradent Products, Inc. and 2 parts by weight of an aqueous sucralose 
<!-- EPO <DP n="29"/>-->
solution (25% sucralose in water). The pH of the etching composition was between 0 and 1. The resulting etching composition was found to be better tasting than ULTRA- ETCH AB that did not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the etching composition that were stored at room temperature and at 37°C, respectively, such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0155">EXAMPLE 36 An etching composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below: Ingredient Amount (Weight %)</p><p num="p0156">Phosphoric acid (85% solution in water) 15% Glycolic acid 6%&gt;</p><p num="p0157">Sucralose (25%&gt; solution in water) 2%&gt;</p><p num="p0158">Water 77% The pH of the etching composition was between 0 and 1. The resulting etching composition was found to be better tasting than etching compositions that do not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the etching composition that were stored at room temperature such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year. EXAMPLE 37</p><p num="p0159">An etching composition was made by mixing the following ingredients in the amounts listed below:</p><p num="p0160">Ingredient Amount (Weight %&gt;</p><p num="p0161">Phosphoric acid (85%&gt; solution in water) 15%o Glycolic acid 6%</p><p num="p0162">Sucralose (25%&gt; solution in water) 2%&gt;</p><p num="p0163">Water 75%</p><p num="p0164">Nitric acid (1 Molar) 2%</p><p num="p0165">The pH of the etching composition was between 0 and 1. The resulting etching composition was found to be better tasting than etching compositions that do 
<!-- EPO <DP n="30"/>-->
not contain any sucralose. The sucralose remained stable for over one year in samples of the etching composition that were stored at room temperature such that the sucralose was still able to impart a sweetening effect after one year.</p><p num="p0166">The acidic compositions according to the invention can be used in the same manner to treat teeth as hemostatic or dental etching compositions known in the art but which do not include sucralose. Both viscous and non-viscous hemostatic or dental etching compositions can be used to stop bleeding during a wide variety of dental procedures.</p><p num="p0167">The present invention may be embodied in other specific forms without departing from its spirit or essential characteristics. The described embodiments are to be considered in all respects only as illustrative and not restrictive. The scope of the invention is, therefore, indicated by the appended claims rather than by the foregoing description. All changes which come within the meaning and range of equivalency of the claims are to be embraced within their scope. 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="31"/>--><claim-text/><claim-text>1. An oral composition for use in providing hemostasis in oral tissues or in etching teeth, comprising: water; an acidic agent comprising at least one of a hemostatic agent or a dental etching agent; and sucralose in an amount so as to impart a sweetening effect, the oral composition having a pH of less than about 2.5.</claim-text><claim-text>2. An oral composition as defined in claim 1, the acidic agent comprising at least one hemostatic agent. 3. An oral composition as defined in claim 2, the hemostatic agent comprising at least one iron (III) compound.</claim-text><claim-text>4. An oral composition as defined in claim 3, the iron (III) compound comprising at least one of ferric sulfate, ferric subsulfate or ferric chloride.</claim-text><claim-text>5. An oral composition as defined in claim 2, the hemostatic agent comprising at least one salt of aluminum, zinc, manganese or bismuth.</claim-text><claim-text>6. An oral composition as defined in claim 2, the hemostatic agent comprising at least one of zinc chloride, aluminum chloride, aluminum sulfate, aluminum chlorohydrate, aluminum acetate, alum, permanganate, or tannin.</claim-text><claim-text>7. An oral composition as defined in claim 2, the hemostatic agent having a concentration in a range of about 1%&gt; to about 40%&gt; by weight of the oral composition.</claim-text><claim-text>8. An oral composition as defined in claim 2, the hemostatic agent having a concentration in a range of about 5% to about 35% by weight of the oral composition. 9. An oral composition as defined in claim 2, the hemostatic agent having a concentration in a range of about 10%&gt; to about 30%&gt; by weight of the oral composition.</claim-text><claim-text>10. An oral composition as defined in claim 2, the oral composition having a pH of less than about 2. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="32"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>11. An oral composition as defined in claim 2, the oral composition having a pH in a range of about 1 to about 2.</claim-text><claim-text>12. An oral composition as defined in claim 1, the acidic agent comprising at least one dental etching agent. 13. An oral composition as defined in claim 12, the dental etching agent comprising at least one component selected from the group consisting of mineral acids, phosphoric acid, nitric acid, hydrochloric acid, and sulfuric acid.</claim-text><claim-text>14. An oral composition as defined in claim 12, the dental etching agent comprising at least one component selected from the group consisting of organic acids, glycolic acid, malic acid, maleic acid, acetic acid, citric acid, and EDTA.</claim-text><claim-text>15. An oral composition as defined in claim 12, the dental etching agent having a concentration in a range of about 10%&gt; to about 60%&gt; by weight of the oral composition.</claim-text><claim-text>16. An oral composition as defined in claim 12, the dental etching agent having a concentration in a range of about 20% to about 50%&gt; by weight of the oral composition.</claim-text><claim-text>17. An oral composition as defined in claim 12, the dental etching agent having a concentration in a range of about 25%&gt; to about 45% by weight of the oral composition. 18. An oral composition as defined in claim 12, the oral composition having a pH of less than about 2.</claim-text><claim-text>19. An oral composition as defined in claim 12, the oral composition having a pH of less than about 1.</claim-text><claim-text>20. An oral composition as defined in claim 1, the sucralose having a concentration in a range of about 0.01%) to about 15% by weight of the oral composition.</claim-text><claim-text>21. An oral composition as defined in claim 1, the sucralose having a concentration in a range of about 0.05% to about 10%&gt; by weight of the oral composition. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="33"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>22. An oral composition as defined in claim 1, the sucralose having a concentration in a range of about 0.1% to about 5% by weight of the oral composition.</claim-text><claim-text>23. A hemostatic composition for use in providing hemostasis in oral tissues, comprising: water; at least one hemostatic agent in a range of about 1%&gt; to about 40%&gt; by weight of the hemostatic composition; and sucralose in a range of about 0.01%&gt; to about 15%&gt; by weight of the hemostatic composition, the hemostatic composition having a pH of less than about 3.</claim-text><claim-text>24. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 23, the hemostatic agent comprising at least one iron (III) compound.</claim-text><claim-text>25. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 24, the iron (III) compound comprising at least one of ferric sulfate, ferric subsulfate, or ferric chloride.</claim-text><claim-text>26. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 23, the hemostatic agent comprising at least one salt of aluminum, zinc, manganese or bismuth.</claim-text><claim-text>27. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 23, the hemostatic agent comprising at least one of zinc chloride, aluminum chloride, aluminum sulfate, aluminum chlorohydrate, aluminum acetate, alum, permanganate, or tannin.</claim-text><claim-text>28. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 23, the hemostatic agent having a concentration in a range of about 5%&gt; to about 30%&gt; by weight of the hemostatic composition. 29. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 23, the sucralose having a concentration in a range of about 0.05%&gt; to about 10%&gt; by weight of the hemostatic composition.</claim-text><claim-text>30. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 23, the sucralose having a concentration in a range of about 0.1 %&gt; to about 5%&gt; by weight of the hemostatic composition. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="34"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>31. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 23, the hemostatic composition having a pH of less than about 2.</claim-text><claim-text>32. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 23, further comprising at least one thickening agent. 33. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 32, the thickening agent comprising at least one particulate filler.</claim-text><claim-text>34. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 32, the thickening agent comprising at least one of fumed silica, colloidal silica, precipitated silica, ground silica, fumed aluminum oxide, or titanium dioxide. 35. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 32, the thickening agent comprising at least one polymeric thickening agent.</claim-text><claim-text>36. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 23, further comprising at least one polyol.</claim-text><claim-text>37. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 36, the polyol having a molecular weight of at least about 600.</claim-text><claim-text>38. A hemostatic composition as defined in claim 36, the polyol comprising at least of polyethylene glycol or polypropylene glycol.</claim-text><claim-text>39. A dental etching composition for use in etching teeth, comprising: water; at least one dental etching agent in amount so as to yield a composition having a pH of less than about 2; and sucralose in a range of about 0.01% to about 15%&gt; by weight of the dental etching composition.</claim-text><claim-text>40. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 39, the dental etching agent comprising at least one mineral acid.</claim-text><claim-text>41. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 40, the mineral acid comprising at least one of phosphoric acid, nitric acid, hydrochloric acid, or sulfuric acid.</claim-text><claim-text>42. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 39, the dental etching agent comprising at least one organic acid. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="35"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>43. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 42, the organic acid comprising at least one of glycolic acid, malic acid, maleic acid, acetic acid, citric acid, or EDTA.</claim-text><claim-text>44. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 39, the dental etching agent having a concentration in a range of about 10% to about 60% by weight of the dental etching composition.</claim-text><claim-text>45. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 39, the dental etching agent having a concentration in a range of about 20% to about 50% by weight of the dental etching composition. 46. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 39, the sucralose having a concentration in a range of about 0.05% to about 10% by weight of the dental etching composition.</claim-text><claim-text>47. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 39, the sucralose having a concentration in a range of about 0.1%&gt; to about 5%&gt; by weight of the dental etching composition.</claim-text><claim-text>48. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 39, the dental etching composition having a pH of less than about 1.</claim-text><claim-text>49. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 39, further comprising at least one thickening agent. 50. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 49, the thickening agent comprising at least one component selected from the group consisting of particulate fillers, fumed silica, colloidal silica, precipitated silica, ground silica, fumed aluminum oxide, or titanium dioxide.</claim-text><claim-text>51. A dental etching composition as defined in claim 49, the thickening agent comprising at least one polymeric thickening agent. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>