<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1153898-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1153898" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="24275771" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20011114"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1153898-A1" status="new" fvid="23279670"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1153898</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20011114</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01303849-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01303849</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010427</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-56951900-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>56951900</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000512</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  24/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  24/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  24/18        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/42        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/46        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/473       20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  24/06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  24/18</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  28/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/46</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/473</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zum Zementieren von unterirdischen Formationen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method of cementing subterranean zones</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour la cimentation de zones souterraines</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-3053673-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3053673</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3821985-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3821985</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4047567-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4047567</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4125160-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4125160</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4871395-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4871395</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4990191-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4990191</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5806594-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5806594</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5897699-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5897699</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/><source name="APP"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5900053-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5900053</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERV INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERVICES, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Halliburton Energy Services, Inc.</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 1431</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73536</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BRENNEIS DARREL C</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHATTERJI JITEN</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CROMWELL ROGER S</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GRAY DENNIS W</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KING BOBBY J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BRENNEIS, DARREL C.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHATTERJI, JITEN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CROMWELL, ROGER S.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GRAY, DENNIS W.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KING, BOBBY J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BRENNEIS, DARREL C.</last-name><address><street>Route 2, Box 195</street><city>Marlow, Oklahoma 73055</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CHATTERJI, JITEN</last-name><address><street>2213 Scott Lane</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73533</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CROMWELL, ROGER S.</last-name><address><street>128 East Nevada</street><city>Walters, Oklahoma 73572</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GRAY, DENNIS W.</last-name><address><street>Route 3, Box 63</street><city>Comanche, Oklahoma 73529</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KING, BOBBY J.</last-name><address><street>Route1, Box 16V</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73533</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Wain, Christopher Paul</last-name><address><street>A.A. Thornton &amp;amp; Co. 235 High Holborn</street><city>London WC1V 7LE</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Subterranean zones penetrated by a well bore are cemented using a foamed cement
composition comprised of hydraulic cement, a non-dispersing set retarder
comprised of a mixture of lignosulfonate, sugar acid and sulfonated lignin, sufficient water to
form a slurry, sufficient gas to foam the slurry and a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to an improved method of cementing in subterranean
zones with set retarded foamed cement compositions.</p><p num="0002">Foamed hydraulic cement compositions are often utilized in cementing subterranean
zones penetrated by well bores. For example, foamed cement compositions are used in
primary well cementing operations whereby strings of pipe such as casing and liners are
cemented in well bores. In performing primary cementing, a cement composition is pumped
into the annular space between the walls of a well bore and the exterior surfaces of a pipe
string disposed therein. The cement composition is permitted to set in the annular space
thereby forming an annular sheath of hardened substantially impermeable cement therein.
The cement sheath physically supports and positions the pipe string in the well bore and
bonds the exterior surfaces of the pipe string to the walls of the well bore whereby the
undesirable migration of fluids between zones or formations penetrated by the well bore is
prevented.</p><p num="0003">The cement compositions utilized for cementing in subterranean zones or formations
penetrated by well bores must often be lightweight to prevent excessive hydrostatic pressure
from unintentionally fracturing the zones or formations. In addition to being lightweight, a
foamed cement composition contains compressed gas which improves the ability of the
cement composition to maintain pressure and prevent the flow of formation fluid into and
through the cement composition during the transition time, i.e., the time during which the 
cement composition changes from a true fluid to a hard set mass. Foamed cement
compositions are also advantageous because they have low fluid loss properties.</p><p num="0004">When cement compositions are utilized for cementing in deep hot subterranean zones,
a set retarder must be included in the cement composition to increase the pumping time of the
composition and prevent premature thickening or setting before placement in the zones to be
cemented. Examples of set retarders which have heretofore been utilized in non-foamed
cement compositions include, but are not limited to, lignosulfonates, sulfomethylated
lignosulfonates, hydroxycarboxy acids, mixtures of sulfomethylated lignosulfonates and
hydroxycarboxy acids, acrylic acid/2-acrylamido-2-methyl propane sulfonic acid copolymers
and the like. While the foregoing set retarders function well in non-foamed cement
compositions, they do not function well in foamed cement compositions because they have
dispersing properties. That is, when used in a foamed cement composition, a set retarder
having dispersing properties causes the cement slurry to be thin which in turn causes the
foam to be unstable and either break or significantly decrease the viscosity of the foamed
cement slurry which in turn prevents the desired foamed cement composition low density
from being achieved. While carboxymethylhydroxyethylcellulose (CMHEC) has heretofore
been used in foamed cement compositions as a set retarder, the high concentrations of
CMHEC required for high temperatures causes the foamed compositions to have undesirable
high surface viscosities.</p><p num="0005">Thus, there are needs for improved methods and set retarded foamed cement
compositions for cementing subterranean zones penetrated by well bores.</p><p num="0006">The present invention provides an improved method of cementing in subterranean
zones penetrated by well bores, which method meets the needs described above and
overcomes or mitigates the deficiencies of the prior art. </p><p num="0007">In one aspect, the invention provides a method of cementing in a subterranean zone
penetrated by a well bore, which method comprises placing a foamed cement composition
into said subterranean zone, and allowing the composition to set into a solid mass, said
composition comprising hydraulic cement, a non-dispersing set retarder comprised of a
mixture of lignosulfonate, sugar acid and sulfonated lignin, sufficient water to form a slurry,
sufficient gas to foam said slurry, and a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant mixture.</p><p num="0008">The improved method and foamed cement compositions of the present invention is
particularly suitable for performing a variety of completion and remedial procedures in
subterranean zones or formations penetrated by well bores. The foamed cement compositions
have improved properties in that they include a non-dispersing set retarder which does not
cause the foamed cement compositions to break or decrease in viscosity whereby the density
of the foamed cement compositions increases. Since it is often very important that the
density of a foamed cement composition be as low as possible, an increase 
in density can cause adverse cementing results, e.g., fracturing of the formation or zone being
cemented.</p><p num="0009">The foamed cement compositions useful in accordance with this invention are
basically comprised of a hydraulic cement, a non-dispersing set retarder comprised of a
mixture of a lignosulfonate, one or more sugar acids and a sulfonated lignin, sufficient water
to form a slurry, sufficient gas to foam the slurry and a foaming and foam stabilizing
surfactant mixture present in an amount sufficient to facilitate the formation of the foam and
stabilize the foamed cement composition.</p><p num="0010">U.S. Patent Application Serial No. 09/569,422, entitled Set Retarders For Foamed
Cements filed of even date herewith which describes and claims similar non-dispersing set
retarders and foamed cement compositions is incorporated herein in its entirety by reference.</p><p num="0011">A variety of hydraulic cements can be utilized in accordance with the present
invention including those comprised of calcium, aluminum, silicon, oxygen and/or sulfur
which set and harden by reaction with water. Such hydraulic cements include Portland
cements, pozzolana cements, gypsum cements, high alumina content cements, silica cements
and high alkalinity cements. Portland cements or their equivalents are generally preferred for
use in accordance with the present invention when performing cementing operations in
subterranean zones penetrated by well bores. Portland cements of the types defined and
described in <u style="single">API Specification For Materials And Testing For Well Cements</u>, API
Specification 10, 5<sup>th</sup> Edition, dated July 1, 1990 of the American Petroleum Institute are
particularly suitable. Preferred API Portland cements include classes A, B, C, G and H, with
API classes G and H being more preferred, and class G being the most preferred.</p><p num="0012">The non-dispersing set retarder utilized in accordance with this invention is a mixture
of a lignosulfonate, one or more sugar acids and a sulfonated lignin. The lignosulfonate is a 
metallic sulfonate salt made from the lignin of sulfite pulp-mill liquors. The specific
lignosulfonate which is preferred for use in accordance with this invention is a hardwood
lignosulfonate having a sulfur content of about 6% by weight and an average molecular
weight of about 9,700 daltons. The one or more sugar acids in the mixture are preferably
derived from xylose. The sulfonated lignin in the mixture is preferably a sulfonated kraft
lignin, i.e., a lignin produced in the kraft process. The sulfonated kraft lignin preferably has
an organic sulfur content of about 3.8% by weight and an average molecular weight of about
60,000 daltons. The non-dispersing set retarder is preferably comprised of a mixture of about
59 parts by weight lignosulfonate, about 11 parts by weight sugar acid and about 30 parts by
weight sulfonated lignin.</p><p num="0013">As will be understood by those skilled in the art, the amount of the non-dispersing set
retarder included in the foamed cement compositions of this invention can vary depending
upon the temperature and the particular pumping time required. Generally, the non-dispersing
set retarder is present in a foamed cement composition of this invention in an
amount in the range of from about 0.05% to about 2.75% by weight of hydraulic cement in
the composition.</p><p num="0014">The water utilized to form the foamed cement compositions of this invention can be
fresh water or salt water. The term "salt water" is used herein to mean unsaturated salt
solutions and saturated salt solutions including brines and seawater. The water is included in
the foamed cement compositions in an amount sufficient to slurry the hydraulic cement.
Generally, the water is present in the foamed cement compositions in an amount in the range
of from about 30% to about 60% by weight of hydraulic cement therein. </p><p num="0015">The gas utilized for foaming the cement slurry can be air or nitrogen, with nitrogen
being preferred. The gas is present in an amount sufficient to foam the slurry, generally in an
amount in the range of from about 5% to about 60% by volume of the slurry.</p><p num="0016">A variety of foaming and foam stabilizing surfactants can be utilized in accordance
with the present invention. A preferred mixture of such surfactants is described in U.S.
Patent No. 5,897,699 issued to Chatterji et al. on April 27, 1999 which is incorporated herein
by reference. The patent discloses an aqueous solution of a mixture of an alpha-olefinic
sulfonate and a cocoylamidopropyl betaine.</p><p num="0017">A particularly preferred foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant mixture for use in
accordance with the present invention is comprised of an ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate of
the formula H(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>a</sub>(OC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>4</sub>)<sub>b</sub>OSO<sub>3</sub>NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> wherein a is an integer in the range of from about 6
to about 10 and b is an integer in the range of from about 3 to about 10, an alkyl or alkene
amidopropylbetaine having the formula R-CONHCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>N<sup>+</sup>(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup> wherein R
is a radical selected from the group of decyl, cocoyl, lauryl, cetyl and oleyl and an alkyl or
alkene amidopropyldimethylamineoxide having the formula R-CONHCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>N<sup>+</sup>(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>O<sup>-</sup>
wherein R is a radical selected from the group of decyl,
cocoyl, lauryl, cetyl and oleyl.</p><p num="0018">The ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate is generally present in the above described
mixture in an amount in the range of from about 60 to 64 parts by weight. The alkyl or
alkene amidopropylbetaine is generally present in the mixture in an amount in the range of
from about 30 to about 33 parts by weight and the alkyl or alkene
amidopropyldimethylamineoxide is generally present in the additive in an amount in the
range of from about 3 to about 10 parts by weight. In order to make the surfactant mixture 
more easily combinable with the cement slurry, water can be combined with the mixture in an
amount sufficient to dissolve the surfactants.</p><p num="0019">The most preferred foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant mixture of the type
described above for use in accordance with this invention is comprised of an ethoxylated
alcohol ether sulfate wherein a in the formula set forth above is an integer in the range of
from 6 to 10 and the ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate is present in the surfactant mixture in
an amount of about 63.3 parts by weight; the alkyl or alkene amidopropyl-betaine is
cocoylamidopropylbetaine and is present in the mixture in an amount of about 31.7 parts by
weight and the alkyl or alkene amidopropyldimethylamineoxide is
cocoylamidopropyldimethylamineoxide and is present in an amount of about 5 parts by
weight.</p><p num="0020">The foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant mixture is generally included in the
foamed cement composition of this invention in an amount in the range of from about 1% to
about 5% by volume of water in the cement slurry, preferably in an amount of from about 1%
to about 2.5%.</p><p num="0021">A particularly preferred foamed cement composition for use in accordance with this
invention is comprised of Portland cement, a non-dispersing set retarder comprised of a
mixture of about 59 parts by weight hardwood lignosulfonate, about 11 parts by weight
xylose sugar acid and about 30 parts by weight sulfonated kraft lignin, sufficient water to
form a slurry, sufficient nitrogen to foam the slurry and a foaming and foam stabilizing
surfactant mixture present in an amount sufficient to facilitate the formation of the foam and
stabilize the foamed cement composition.</p><p num="0022">The non-dispersing set retarder is preferably included in the above described foamed
cement composition in an amount in the range of from about 0.1% to about 2.5% by weight 
of hydraulic cement therein. The water used is preferably included in the composition in an
amount in the range of from about 45% to about 55% by weight of hydraulic cement therein,
and the nitrogen is preferably present in the composition in an amount in the range of from
about 10% to about 20% by volume of the composition. The foaming and foam stabilizing
surfactant mixture is preferably comprised of an ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate present in
an amount of about 63.3 parts by weight of the mixture, cocylamidopropylbetaine present in
an amount of about 31.7 parts by weight of the mixture and cocoylamidopropyldimethylamineoxide
present in an amount of about 5 parts by weight of the mixture. The
foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant mixture is preferably present in the foamed cement
composition in an amount in the range of from about 1% to about 2.5% by volume of water
therein.</p><p num="0023">A preferred method of the present invention for cementing in a subterranean zone
penetrated by a well bore is comprised of placing a foamed cement composition into the
subterranean zone, and allowing the foamed cement composition to set into a solid mass, said
composition being comprised of Portland cement, a non-dispersing set retarder comprised of
a mixture of 59 parts by weight hardwood lignosulfonate, 11 parts by weight xylose sugar
acid and 30 parts by weight sulfonated kraft lignin present in an amount in the range of from
about 0.1% to about 2.5% by weight of hydraulic cement in the composition, sufficient water
to foam a slurry, sufficient nitrogen to foam the slurry and a foaming and foam stabilizing
surfactant mixture comprised of an ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate present in an amount of
about 63.3 parts by weight of the mixture, cocoylamidopropylbetaine present in an amount of
about 31.7 parts by weight of the mixture and cocylamidopropyldimethylamineoxide present
in an amount of about 5 parts by weight of the mixture, the foaming and foam stabilizing
surfactant mixture being present in the composition in an amount in the range of from about
1% to about 2.5% by volume of water therein.</p><p num="0024">In order to further illustrate the methods and foamed cement compositions of this
invention, the following examples are given.</p><heading><b>Example 1</b></heading><heading><u style="single">The Apparatus Utilized</u></heading><p num="0025">The preparation of a foamed cement slurry at atmospheric pressure in the laboratory
requires a 2-step mixing procedure. The cement slurry without the foaming and foam 
stabilizing surfactant mixture is first mixed in a standard Waring blender. A specific weight
of the cement slurry along with the foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant mixture is then
placed into a one-litre multi-bladed sealable mixing container that has a known volume. The
weight of the cement slurry placed into the sealable mixing container is the weight that will
result in the final foamed cement slurry density when the cement slurry is foamed sufficiently
to completely fill the sealable mixing container. The cement slurry is then subjected to the
maximum shear energy (rpm) that can be developed by the mixer until the foamed cement
slurry produced completely fills the mixing container. For the cement slurry to be considered
for a foamed cement application, the cement slurry must foam enough to completely fill the
mixing container in 15 seconds or less. When this condition is met, the foamed cement slurry
can then be cured and tested for compressive strength and stability indications at atmospheric
pressure and temperatures less than approximately 82°C (180°F).</p><p num="0026">The preparation of a foamed cement slurry for curing at temperatures above
approximately 82°C (180°F) requires the use of special equipment. That is, an instrument
known as a Multiple Analysis Cement Slurry Analyzer (MACS Analyzer) must be used. The
MACS Analyzer has a sealable chamber of a known volume wherein the slurry is sheared and
mixed with nitrogen at high energy. In addition, the sealable chamber can be pressurized
with nitrogen and heated. The cement slurry without the foaming and foam stabilizing
surfactant mixture is prepared in a standard 2-litre Waring blender having a single mixing
blade. A weighed amount of the slurry is placed in the chamber of the MACS Analyzer that
will result in the final foamed slurry density when the slurry is foamed sufficiently to
completely fill the chamber. The chamber is then sealed and the paddle inside the MACS
Analyzer chamber is rotated at approximately 1,000 rpm for 5 minutes with 6.89 x 10<sup>6</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup>
(1,000 psi) nitrogen pressure applied to the cement slurry which causes the cement slurry to
be foamed. The resulting foamed slurry is subjected to a temperature schedule to simulate
well conditions while the nitrogen pressure is maintained on the foamed slurry. After
reaching a temperature equal to the bottom hole circulating temperature (BHCT), stirring is
continued for 1 hour. The slurry is then transferred through a manifold system to curing cells
that have been preheated and charged with nitrogen at the same pressure to which the slurry
is subjected in the mixing chamber. After the foamed cement slurry is transferred to the
curing cells, the cells are heated to the curing temperature which is normally the bottom hole 
static temperature (BHST). Upon curing for a selected period of time, the nitrogen pressure
is slowly released from the curing cells and the set foamed cement is removed from the cells
and tested for stability and/or compressive strength. The stability of the cured foamed cement
slurry specimens was determined by observing the density variation of the specimens from
the tops to the bottoms of the specimens.</p><heading><u style="single">Test Procedure and Results</u></heading><p num="0027">A mixture of Portland Class H cement and finely ground crystalline silica in an
amount of 35% by weight of the cement was mixed with water to form a cement slurry
containing water in an amount of 54.23% by weight of the Portland cement in the slurry. A
surfactant mixture comprised of ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate, cocoylamidopropylbetaine
and cocoylamidopropylamineoxide was combined with the cement slurry in an amount of 1%
by volume of the water in the slurry. The slurry was divided into test samples and various
amounts of the non-dispersing set retarder of this invention were added to the test samples.
The test samples were then foamed to densities of 1.9 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> (15.9 pounds per gallon)
and tested for thickening times in accordance with the API Specification 10 mentioned above
at various temperatures. The results of these tests are given in Table I below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><b>Foamed Cement Composition Thickening Times</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"><b>Test Sample No.</b></entry><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2"><b>Temperature,</b></entry><entry align="center" namest="4"><b>Amount of Non-Dispersing Retarding Agent <!--footnotes removed-->Used, % by Weight of Cement</b></entry><entry align="center" namest="5"><b>Thickening Time, hr:min</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>°C</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>(°F)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="center">66</entry><entry align="center">(150)</entry><entry align="center">0.1</entry><entry align="center">3:12</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="center">93</entry><entry align="center">(200)</entry><entry align="center">0.2</entry><entry align="center">3:31</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="center">93</entry><entry align="center">(200)</entry><entry align="center">0.3</entry><entry align="center">5:48</entry> </row><row><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="center">121</entry><entry align="center">(250)</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry> <entry align="center">2:53</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="center">121</entry><entry align="center">(250)</entry><entry align="center">1.125</entry><entry align="center">3:34</entry></row><row><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="center">121</entry><entry align="center">(250)</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry><entry align="center">4:07</entry></row><row><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="center">121</entry><entry align="center">(250)</entry><entry align="center">1.25</entry><entry align="center">7:40</entry></row><row><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="center">135</entry><entry align="center">(275)</entry><entry align="center">1.5</entry><entry align="center">2:00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="center">135</entry><entry align="center">(275)</entry><entry align="center">1.75</entry><entry align="center">2:32</entry></row><row><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="center">135</entry><entry align="center">(275)</entry><entry align="center">2.0</entry><entry align="center">2:49</entry></row><row><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="center">135</entry><entry align="center">(275)</entry><entry align="center">2.25</entry><entry align="center">4:00</entry></row><row><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="center">135</entry><entry align="center">(275)</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">6:48<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0028">From Table I, it can be seen that the non-dispersing set retarder of this invention
functioned very well.</p><heading><b>Example 2</b></heading><p num="0029">A number of non-foamed cement slurry test samples produced in Example 1 were
cured at various temperatures and tested for 12 hour and 24 hour compressive strengths as
well as for crushed strength using an Ultrasonic Cement Analyzer. The results of these tests
are set forth in Table II.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="9"><tbody><row><entry nameend="9" namest="1"><b>Compressive Strength Tests</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"><b>Test Sample No.</b></entry><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2"><b>Temperature</b></entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4"><b>Compressive Strength After 12 Hrs,</b></entry><entry nameend="7" align="center" namest="6"><b>Compressive Strength After 24 Hrs,</b></entry><entry nameend="9" align="center" namest="8"><b>Crushed Strength,</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>°C</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>(°F)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>N/m<sup>2</sup> x 10<sup>-7</sup></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>(psi)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>N/m<sup>2</sup> x 10<sup>-7</sup></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>(psi)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>N/m<sup>2</sup> x 10<sup>-7</sup></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>(psi)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">107</entry><entry align="center">(225)</entry><entry align="center">0.83</entry><entry align="center">(1209)</entry><entry align="center">1.19</entry><entry align="center">(1727)</entry><entry align="center">2.12</entry><entry align="center">(3070)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">117</entry><entry align="center">(243)</entry><entry align="center">1.03</entry><entry align="center">(1500)</entry><entry align="center">1.43</entry><entry align="center">(2074)</entry><entry align="center">2.54</entry><entry align="center">(3680)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">159</entry><entry align="center">(318)</entry><entry align="center">1.93</entry><entry align="center">(2800)</entry><entry align="center">2.44</entry><entry align="center">(3546)</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">(7250)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">166</entry><entry align="center">(330)</entry><entry align="center">1.91</entry><entry align="center">(2777)</entry><entry align="center">2.06</entry><entry align="center">(2990)</entry><entry align="center">5.26</entry><entry align="center">(7630)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0030">From Table II, it can be seen that the non-foamed cement slurries tested had good
compressive strengths.</p><heading><b>Example 3</b></heading><p num="0031">To a first test sample of the non-foamed cement/crystalline silica slurry described in
Example 1, the non-dispersing set retarder of this invention was added in an amount of 1% by
weight of Portland cement in the slurry. To a second test sample of the non-foamed
cement/crystalline silica slurry of Example 1, a dispersing sulfomethylated lignin set retarder
was added in an amount of 0.3% by weight of Portland cement in the slurry. The two test
samples were foamed at ambient conditions to densities of 1.3 x 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> (11.2 pounds per
gallon) and allowed to set at 60°C (140°F) for 24 hours. The densities of the set foamed
cement samples were then determined. The results of these test are shown in Table III below. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1"><b>Foamed Cement Slurry Properties with Dispersing And Non-Dispersing Set Retarders</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"><b>Test Cement Composition Sample</b></entry><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2"><b>Cement Slurry Density,</b></entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4"><b>Foamed Cement Slurry Density,</b></entry><entry nameend="7" align="center" namest="6"><b>Density of Set Foamed Cement Slurry,</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>kg/m<sup>3</sup> x 10<sup>-3</sup></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>(lb/gal)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>kg/m<sup>3</sup> x 10<sup>-3</sup></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>(lb/gal)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>kg/m<sup>3</sup> x 10<sup>-3</sup></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>(lb/gal)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center">First</entry><entry align="center">1.9</entry><entry align="center">(15.9)</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">(11.2)</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">(11.2)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Second</entry><entry align="center">1.9</entry><entry align="center">(15.9)</entry><entry align="center">1.3</entry><entry align="center">(11.2)</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">(15.0)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0032">From Table III, it can be seen that the cement composition containing the non-dispersing
set retarder of this invention maintain its low density during setting while the set
foamed cement composition containing the dispersing set retarder did not.</p><heading><b>Example 4</b></heading><p num="0033">A cement slurry was prepared comprised of Portland Class H cement, finely ground
crystalline silica in an amount of 30% by weight of the Portland cement, amorphous silica in
an amount of 15% by weight of the Portland cement, hydroxypropylguar gum with a M.S. of
0.6 in an amount of 0.4% by weight of the Portland cement, water in an amount of 53% by
weight of the Portland cement, and a foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant mixture
comprised of ethoxylated alcohol ether sulfate, cocoylamidopropylbetaine and
cocoylamidopropylamineoxide in an amount of 2% by volume of water in the slurry.</p><p num="0034">To a first test sample of the cement slurry, the non-dispersing set retarder of the
present invention was added in an amount of 1.2% by weight of the Portland cement. To a
second test portion of the cement slurry, a dispersing set retarder comprised of an aqueous
solution of tartaric acid was added in an amount of 3.2% by weight of the Portland cement
along with an aqueous solution of a dispersing set retarder comprised of a copolymer of
acrylic acid and 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid in an amount of 1% by weight
of the Portland cement. The first and second test cement slurry samples were foamed under
temperatures and pressures according to the following schedule: the foamed cement slurry
samples were heated from 27°C (80°F) to 121°C (250°F) in 1 hour, held at 121°C (250°F) for
1 hour, transferred and cured at 159°C (318°F) for 24 hours, all at 6.89 x 10<sup>6</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup> (1,000
psi). After setting, the set foamed cement compositions were tested for top, middle and
bottom densities. The results of these tests are set forth in Table IV below. <tables><table><tgroup cols="8"><tbody><row><entry nameend="8" namest="1"><b>Foamed Cement Slurry Properties With Dispersing And Non-Dispersing Properties</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"><b>Test Cement Composition Sample</b></entry><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2"><b>Cement Slurry Density,</b></entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4"><b>Foamed Cement Slurry Density</b></entry><entry nameend="8" align="center" namest="6"><b>Density of Set Foamed Cement Slurry,</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>kg/m<sup>3</sup> x 10<sup>-3</sup></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>(lb/gal)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>kg/m<sup>3</sup> x 10<sup>-3</sup></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>(lb/gal)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>kg/m<sup>3</sup> x 10<sup>-3</sup></b></entry><entry align="left"><b>(lb/gal)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"><b>Top</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Middle</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Bottom</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center">First</entry><entry align="center">1.93</entry><entry align="center">(16.14)</entry><entry align="center">1.45</entry><entry align="center">(12.1)</entry><entry align="center">1.44 (11.98)</entry><entry align="center">1.49 (12.45)</entry><entry align="center">1.53 (12.79)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Second</entry><entry align="center">1.92</entry><entry align="center">(15.99)</entry><entry align="center">1.53</entry><entry align="center">(12.8)</entry><entry align="center">1.34 (11.18)</entry><entry align="center">1.52 (12.66)</entry><entry align="center">1.57 (13.08)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0035">From Table IV, it can be seen that the first sample of the foamed cement composition
containing the non-dispersing set retarder of this invention was considerably more stable than
the second sample of the foamed cement composition containing prior art dispersing set
retarders.</p><p num="0036">Thus, the present invention is well adapted to carry out the objects and attain the ends
and advantages mentioned as well as those inherent therein.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method of cementing in a subterranean zone penetrated by a well bore, which
method comprises placing a foamed cement composition into said subterranean zone, and
allowing the composition to set into a solid mass, said composition comprising hydraulic
cement, a non-dispersing set retarder comprised of a mixture of lignosulfonate, sugar acid and
sulfonated lignin, sufficient water to form a slurry, sufficient gas to foam said slurry, and a
foaming and foam stabilizing surfactant mixture.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1, wherein said lignosulfonate in said non-dispersing set
retarder is hardwood lignosulfonate having a sulfur content of substantially 6% by weight and
an average molecular weight of substantially 9,700 daltons.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1 or 2, wherein said sugar acid in said non-dispersing set
retarder is xylose sugar acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1, 2 or 3, wherein said sulfonated lignin in said non-dispersing
set retarder is sulfonated kraft lignin having an organic sulfur content of
substantially 3.8% by weight and an average molecular weight of substantially 60,000
daltons.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1 to 4, wherein said non-dispersing set retarder is
comprised of a mixture of 59 parts by weight lignosulfonate, 11 parts by weight sugar acid
and 30 parts by weight sulfonated lignin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1 to 5, wherein said non-dispersing set retarder is
present in said composition in an amount in the range of from 0.05% to 2.75% by weight of
hydraulic cement in said composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1 to 6, wherein said hydraulic cement in said
composition is Portland cement, slag cement, pozzolana cement, gypsum cement, high
alumina content cement or a high alkalinity cement.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1 to 7, wherein said water in said composition is
fresh water, an unsaturated salt solution or a saturated salt solution, and wherein said water is
preferably present in said composition in an amount of from 30% to 60% by weight of
hydraulic cement in said composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1 to 8, wherein said gas in said composition is
air or nitrogen, and wherein said gas is preferably present in said composition in an amount
of from 5% to 60% by volume of said composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A method according to any of claims 1 to 9, wherein said foaming and foam
stabilizing surfactant mixture in said composition is comprised of an ethoxylated alcohol
ether sulfate present in an amount of about 63.3 parts by weight, cocoylamidopropylbetaine
present in an amount of about 31.7 parts by weight and cocoylamidopropyl-dimethylamine-oxide
present in an amount of about 5 parts by weight, and wherein said foaming and foam
stabilizing surfactant mixture is present in said composition in an amount of from 1% to 5%
by volume of water therein.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>