<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1338756-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1338756" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22099092" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030827"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1338756-A1" status="new" fvid="23812613"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1338756</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030827</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03250797-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03250797</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030207</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-7107602-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>7107602</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020208</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  24/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  24/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/42        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/46        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   8/487       20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  24/16P2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  28/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/46</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   8/487</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Flüssigkeitsverlust-Additive für Bohrzementierungszusammensetzungen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Fluid loss control additives for wellcements</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Additifs de contrôle de perte de fluides pour ciments utilisés lors de forage</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-4587283-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4587283</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5025040-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5025040</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5116421-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5116421</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6465587-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6465587</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERV INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HALLIBURTON ENERGY SERVICES, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Halliburton Energy Services, Inc.</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 1431</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73536</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>REDDY B RAGHAVA</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>RILEY WENDELL D</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>REDDY, B. RAGHAVA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>RILEY, WENDELL D.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>REDDY, B. RAGHAVA</last-name><address><street>2013 Waverly</street><city>Duncan, Oklahoma 73533</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>RILEY, WENDELL D.</last-name><address><street>HC 64, Box 144</street> <city>Markow, Oklahoma 73055</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor> </inventors> <agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Wain, Christopher Paul</last-name> <address><street>A.A. Thornton &amp;amp; Co. 235 High Holborn</street><city>London WC1V 7LE</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A high temperature viscosifying and fluid loss control additive for use in well
cements, comprises a mixture of a polymer of at least one monomer which is calcium
tolerant, anionic and disperses basic cement slurries, at least one monomer which
hydrolyzes in basic cement slurries to generate anionic carboxylate groups that bind with
calcium and viscosify the slurries and at least one monomer which generates non-ionic
pendant groups on the polymer upon hydrolyzing in basic cement slurries to prevent
polymer precipitation; and a homopolymer of a monomer which hydrolyzes in basic cement
slurries to generate anionic carboxylate groups that bind with calcium, viscosify the slurries
and prevent settling in the slurries.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to subterranean well cementing operations and, more
particularly, to viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additives for use in well cements
subjected to temperatures up to 500°F (260°C), well cement compositions containing the
additives and methods of using the compositions.</p><p num="0002">Hydraulic cement compositions are commonly utilized in subterranean well
completion and remedial operations. For example, hydraulic cement compositions are used
in primary cementing operations whereby strings of pipe such as casings and liners are
cemented in well bores. In performing primary cementing, a hydraulic cement composition
is pumped into the annular space between the walls of a well bore and the exterior surfaces of
a pipe string disposed therein. The cement composition is permitted to set in the annular
space thereby forming an annular sheath of hardened substantially impermeable cement
therein which supports and positions the pipe string in the well bore and bonds the exterior
surfaces of the pipe string to the walls of the well bore. Hydraulic cement compositions are
also utilized in remedial cementing operations such as plugging highly permeable zones or
fractures in well bores, plugging cracks or holes in pipe strings and the like.</p><p num="0003">Cement composition viscosifying additives are often used in well cement
compositions to prevent settling of solids in the cement compositions after they are placed in
a subterranean zone to be cemented. While such cement composition viscosifying additives
have been utilized successfully at subterranean temperatures up to about 350°F (176°C), at
higher temperatures the heretofore utilized viscosifying additives have not been able to
prevent thermal thinning which results in the settling of solids in cement compositions. The 
settling of the solids in a cement composition results in defective cementing and failure of the
set cement to provide zonal isolation.</p><p num="0004">Fluid loss control agents are also used in well cement compositions to reduce fluid
loss from the cement compositions to permeable formations or zones into or through which
the cement compositions are pumped. In primary cementing, the loss of fluid, i.e. water, to
permeable subterranean formations or zones can result in premature gelation of the cement
composition whereby bridging of the annular space between the permeable formation or zone
and the pipe string being cemented therein prevents the cement composition from being
placed over the entire length of the annulus.</p><p num="0005">Thus, there are needs for an improved viscosifying additive for well cements which
can be utilized in cements subjected to temperatures up to 500°F and which also provides
fluid loss control to the cements at such temperatures, improved well cement compositions
containing the additive and methods of using the cement compositions.</p><p num="0006">In one aspect, the present invention provides a viscosifying and fluid loss control
additive for use in well cement slurries subject to temperatures up to 500°F, which additive
comprises a mixture of a polymer comprised of at least one monomer which is calcium
tolerant, anionic and disperses basic cement slurries, at least one monomer which hydrolyzes
in basic cement slurries to generate anionic carboxylate groups that bind with calcium and
viscosify the slurries, and at least one monomer which generates non-ionic pendant groups on
the polymer upon hydrolyzing in basic cement slurries to prevent polymer precipitation; and
a homopolymer of a monomer which hydrolyzes in basic cement slurries to generate anionic
carboxylate groups that bind with calcium, viscosify the slurries and prevent settling in the
slurries. </p><p num="0007">The invention also provides a well cement composition for use at temperatures up to
about 500°F, comprising a hydraulic cement; water present in an amount sufficient to form a
slurry; and a viscosifying and fluid loss control additive of the invention.</p><p num="0008">The invention further includes a method of cementing a subterranean zone penetrated
by a well bore, which method comprises the steps of:
<sl><li>(a) placing a cement composition in said subterranean zone; and</li><li>(b) allowing said cement composition to set therein, wherein the cement composition
is a composition of the invention.</li></sl></p><p num="0009">The viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additive can be added in particulate solid
form directly to the hydraulic cement or mix water utilized or it can be combined with water
whereby a storable aqueous solution is formed which can be conveniently combined with the
cement composition mix water.</p><p num="0010">The viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additive of this invention is basically
comprised of a mixture of a polymer and a homopolymer. The polymer is characterized in
that it is obtained by polymerizing: (1) at least one monomer which is calcium tolerant,
anionic and disperses basic cement slurries selected from 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane
sulfonic acid and its salts; vinyl sulfonate, allyl sulfonate or 3-allyloxy-2-hydroxy-1-propanesulfonic
acid and its salts; (2) at least one monomer which is capable of hydrolyzing
in basic cement slurries to generate anionic carboxylate groups that bind with calcium,
viscosify the slurries and prevent settling in the slurries selected from acrylonitrile,
acrylamide, N,N-dialkylacrylamide wherein the alkyl group is selected from C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>6</sub> alkyl
groups, N-vinylpyrrolidone, 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid and its salts or
alkylacrylates such as methylmethacrylate and methylacrylate; and (3) at least one monomer 
which generates non-ionic pendant groups on the polymer upon hydrolysis in basic cement
slurries to prevent polymer precipitation selected from N-alkyl-N-vinylalkanamides such as
N-methyl-N-vinylacetamide, allyl glycidyl ether or vinylacetate. The molecular weight of
the polymer is advantageously in the range of from about 300,000 to about 1.5 million,
preferably about 500,000.</p><p num="0011">The ratio of the monomers in the polymer is selected such that when present in
cement slurries, the polymer does not viscosify the slurries excessively under ambient
conditions, but upon undergoing hydrolysis reactions in the cement slurries during placement,
the polymer will continuously generate sufficient carboxylate groups at down hole
temperatures to react with the calcium ions present in the slurries in cross-linking reactions
and viscosify the slurries to counteract the thermal thinning of the slurries. Thus, the higher
the down hole temperature, the greater the thermal thinning of cement slurries and the greater
the rate of slurry viscosification due to carboxylate generating hydrolysis reactions.</p><p num="0012">The polymer, due to its adsorption on cement grains as well as due to its fluid
viscosification properties, also provides fluid loss controlling properties. When the fluid loss
control of slurries containing the polymer is not adequate, additional fluid loss controlling
polymers can be added.</p><p num="0013">The preferred monomer ratio in the polymer depends on how the polymer affects the
viscosities of cement slurries under ambient conditions as well as under down hole
conditions. High viscosities under ambient conditions result in excessive pump pressures
during the placement of the slurries. On the other hand, excessive dispersion of cement
slurries at ambient temperature causes particle settling even before the slurries are placed in
the well. The preferred ratio of the dispersing monomer or monomers from group 1 set forth 
above may vary from 30 to 60 percent by weight of the polymer; the anionic carboxylate
generating monomer or monomer(s) of group 2 above may range from 20 to 60 percent by
weight of the polymer; and the monomer or monomers from group 3 above may range from 0
to 40 percent by weight of the polymer. Most preferably, the monomer or monomers from
group 1 are in the 40-50 percent range by weight of the polymer; the monomer or monomers
of group 2 are present in the 30-40 percent range; and the group 3 monomer or monomers are
in the 10-20 percent range by weight of the polymer.</p><p num="0014">It has been found that different homopolymers containing carboxylate generating
monomers at different temperatures can be used in combination with the above described
polymer. For example, it has been found that the polymer of the present invention can be
used in a synergistic mixture with other homopolymers obtained by polymerizing one or
more of the monomers listed in group 2 above. Thus for example, the above described
polymer can advantageously be used in admixture with polyvinylpyrrolidone or
polyacrylamide for preventing particle settling in cement slurries. The polymer is generally
present in the mixture in an amount in the range of from about 50% to about 95% by weight
of the mixture and the homopolymer or homopolymers used are present therein in an amount
in the range of from about 5% to about 50% by weight of the mixture.</p><p num="0015">Viscosifying and fluid loss controlling polymers useful in accordance with this
invention are available commercially. For example, polymers having the trade names
"HOSTAMER V 4707™", "HOSTAMER 4706™" and "HOSTADRILL 2825™" are
commercially available from the Clariant Corporation of Charlotte, North Carolina, and
contain 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid, acrylamide and N-vinyl-N-alkylalknamide
in proprietary ratios and are described in U.S. Patent No. 4,587,283 to which 
reference should be made for further details. A polymer containing multiple group 2
monomers with different hydrolysis rates is available under the trade designation "HE 300™"
from Drilling Specialties Company of Bartlesville, Oklahoma. The "HE 300™" polymer
contains 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid, N-vinylpyrrolidone and acrylamide in
a proprietary ratio. A homopolymer of vinylpyrrolidone having a molecular weight in the
range of from about 900,000 to about 1.5 million is commercially available under the trade
designation of "PVP K-90™" from ISP Technologies Incorporated of Wayne, New Jersey.</p><p num="0016">The viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additive of this invention can be combined
in a solid particulate form with the hydraulic cement or mix water utilized to form a well
cement composition. When the additive is utilized in offshore well cementing operations, the
additive is preferably in liquid form. That is, the solid particulate polymer described above
with at least one homopolymer described above can be combined with water in an amount
sufficient to form an aqueous solution of the additive. The water used can be fresh water or
salt water. The polymer and homopolymer mixture can be used effectively in combination
with a separate fluid loss controlling additive as well as other well cement composition
additives.</p><p num="0017">Thus, a preferred viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additive of this invention for
use in well cement compositions subjected to temperatures up to 500°F is comprised of a
mixture of a polymer comprised of at least one monomer which is calcium tolerant, anionic
and disperses basic cement slurries, at least one monomer which hydrolyzes in basic cement
slurries to generate anionic carboxylate groups that bind with calcium and viscosify the
slurries and at least one monomer which generates non-ionic pendant groups on the polymer
upon hydrolyzing in basic cement slurries to prevent polymer precipitation and a 
homopolymer of a monomer which hydrolyzes in basic cement slurries to generate anionic
carboxylate groups that bind with calcium, viscosify the slurries and prevent settling in the
slurries.</p><p num="0018">The improved well cement compositions of the present invention are basically
comprised of a hydraulic cement, sufficient water to form a slurry and a viscosifying and
fluid loss controlling additive of the present invention as described above.</p><p num="0019">A variety of hydraulic cements can be utilized in accordance with the present
invention including those comprised of calcium, aluminum, silicon, oxygen and/or sulfur
which set and harden by reaction with water. Such hydraulic cements include, but are not
limited to, Portland cements, pozzolana cements, gypsum cements, aluminous cements, silica
cements and alkaline cements. Portland cements are generally preferred for use in
accordance with the present invention. Portland cements of the types defined and described
in <u style="single">API Specification For Materials And Testing For Well Cements</u>, API Specification 10, 5<sup>th</sup>
Edition, dated July 1, 1990 of the American Petroleum Institute are particularly preferred.
API Portland cements include Classes A, B, C, G and H. API Classes G and H are preferred
with Class G being the most preferred.</p><p num="0020">The water utilized in the cement compositions of this invention can be fresh water,
unsaturated salt solutions including brines and seawater and saturated salt solutions.
Generally, the water can be from any source provided it does not contain an excess of
compounds that adversely affect other components in the cement compositions. The water is
present in the cement compositions of this invention in an amount sufficient to form a
pumpable slurry. More particularly, the water is present in the cement compositions in an 
amount in the range of from about 38% to about 70% by weight of hydraulic cement therein,
more preferably in an amount of about 60%.</p><p num="0021">The viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additive of this invention is included in the
cement compositions of this invention in an amount in the range of from about 0.2% to about
7% by weight of hydraulic cement therein, more preferably in an amount in the range of from
about 0.5% to about 3% and most preferably in an amount of 2%.</p><p num="0022">As mentioned above, the cement compositions containing the viscosifying and fluid
loss controlling additive of this invention maintain viscosities at levels sufficient to prevent
significant settling of particulate solids in the cement compositions at temperatures up to as
high as 500°F. In addition, the additive provides fluid loss control to the cement
compositions which often eliminates the need for one or more separate fluid loss control
additives in the cement compositions.</p><p num="0023">As is well understood by those skilled in the art, various other cement composition
additives can be utilized in the cement compositions of this invention including, but not
limited to, additional fluid loss controlling agents, set retarding agents, set accelerating
agents, fillers, weighting materials and the like.</p><p num="0024">A preferred well cement composition of this invention for use at temperatures up to
about 500°F is comprised of: a hydraulic cement; water present in an amount sufficient to
form a slurry; and a viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additive comprised of a mixture of
a polymer formed of at least one monomer which is calcium tolerant, anionic and disperses
basic cement slurries, at least one monomer which hydrolyzes in basic cement slurries to
generate anionic carboxylate groups that bind with calcium and viscosify the slurries and at
least one monomer which generates non-ionic pendant groups on the polymer upon 
hydrolyzing in basic cement slurries to prevent polymer precipitation and a homopolymer of
a monomer which hydrolyzes in basic cement slurries to generate anionic carboxylate groups
that bind with calcium, viscosify the slurries and prevent settling in the slurries.</p><p num="0025">A more preferred well cement composition of this invention for use at temperatures
up to about 500°F is comprised of: a hydraulic cement; water present in an amount sufficient
to form a slurry; and a viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additive having a molecular
weight of about 500,000 comprised of a mixture of a polymer formed of 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane
sulfonic acid, acrylamide and N-alkyl-N-vinyl-acetamide monomers, the 2-acrylamido-2-methyl
propane sulfonic acid monomer being present in the polymer in an
amount in the range of from about 40% to about 50% by weight of the polymer, the
acrylamide monomer being present in the polymer in an amount in the range of from about
30% to about 40% by weight of the polymer and the N-alkyl-N-vinyl-acetamide being
present in an amount in the range of from about 10% to about 20% by weight of the polymer
and a homopolymer of acrylamide having a molecular weight of about 1 million.</p><p num="0026">The methods of the present invention for cementing a subterranean zone penetrated by
a well bore are basically comprised of the steps of providing a cement composition comprised
of a hydraulic cement, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry and a
viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additive comprised of a mixture of a terpolymer and a
homopolymer as described above, placing the cement composition in the subterranean zone
to be cemented and allowing the cement composition to set into an impermeable solid mass
therein.</p><p num="0027">A preferred method of this invention for cementing a subterranean zone penetrated by
a well bore is comprised of the steps of: (a) providing a cement composition comprising a 
hydraulic cement, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry and a viscosifying
and fluid loss controlling additive comprised of a mixture of a polymer formed of at least one
monomer which is calcium tolerant, anionic and disperses basic cement slurries, at least one
monomer which hydrolyzes in basic cement slurries to generate anionic carboxylate groups
that bind with calcium and viscosify the slurries and at least one monomer which generates
non-ionic pendant groups on the polymer upon hydrolyzing in basic cement slurries to
prevent polymer precipitation and a homopolymer of a monomer which hydrolyzes in basic
cement slurries to generate anionic carboxylate groups that bind with calcium, viscosify the
slurries and prevent settling in the slurries; (b) placing the cement composition in the
subterranean zone; and (c) allowing the cement composition to set therein.</p><p num="0028">A more preferred method of this invention for cementing a subterranean zone
penetrated by a well bore is comprised of the steps of: (a) providing a cement composition
comprising a hydraulic cement, water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry and a
viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additive having a molecular weight of about 500,000
comprised of a mixture of a polymer formed of 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid,
acrylamide and N-alkyl-N-vinyl-acetamide monomers, the 2-acrylamido-2-methyl propane
sulfonic acid monomer being present in the polymer in an amount in the range of from about
40% to about 50% by weight of the polymer, the acrylamide monomer being present in the
polymer in an amount in the range of from about 30% to about 40% by weight of the polymer
and the N-alkyl-N-vinyl-acetamide being present in an amount in the range of from about
10% to about 20% by weight of the polymer and a homopolymer of acrylamide having a
molecular weight of about 1 million; (b) placing the cement composition in the subterranean
zone; and (c) allowing the cement composition to set therein. </p><p num="0029">In order to further illustrate the viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additive, well
cement compositions and methods of the present invention, the following Example is given.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLE</u></heading><p num="0030">Tests were conducted on well cement compositions containing the high temperature
viscosifying and fluid loss controlling additive of this invention.</p><p num="0031">Cement Slurry No. 1 contained Portland Class A cement as the basic ingredient. The
other ingredients present in Slurry No. 1 are shown in Table I. Cement Slurries Nos. 2
through 23 contained Portland Class H cement, silica flour in an amount of 35% by weight of
cement and the other ingredients shown in Tables I and II. The basic cement slurries also
contained viscosity increasing and settling preventing polymers as shown in Tables I and II.</p><p num="0032">Cement Slurries Nos. 24 through 33 contained Portland Class H cement, 40% silica
flour by weight of cement and 5% fumed silica by weight of cement. The other additives in
Cement Slurries Nos. 24 through 33 are listed in Table III. The cement retarders used in the
tests are commercially available from Halliburton Energy Services of Duncan, Oklahoma
under the trade names "FDP 601™" (lignosulfonate retarder), "SCR-100™" (a copolymer of
2-acrylamide-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid and acrylic acid), "SCR-500™" (a copolymer of
2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid and itaconic acid), "HR-15™" (a mixture of
lignosulfonate and tartaric acid), and "HR-5™" (sodium salt of lignosulfonate). The fluid
loss control agents used are also commercially available as Halliburton products, namely
"Halad 413™" (causticized lignite grafted with 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid,
N,N-dimethylformamide and acrylonitrile) and "Halad 344™" (a copolymer of N,N-dimethylformamide
and 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid). The transition time
increasing additive, "GasStop HT™" (tannin grafted with acrylamide and 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane 
sulfonic acid) is also available from Halliburton as is the settling preventing
additive "SA-541™" (causticized hydroxypropyl guar surface treated with sodium borate).</p><p num="0033">Slurries Nos. 1 through 10 were tested at temperatures in the range of from 150°F to
250°F. Slurries Nos. 11 through 23 were tested at temperatures in the range of from 300°F to
400°F and Slurries Nos. 24 through 33 were tested at a temperature of 434°F.</p><p num="0034">The viscosity, variation in density, set time, fluid loss and rheology tests were
conducted utilizing the following procedures. All the tests were carried out on an instrument
available from Halliburton Energy Services, Inc. under the trade name "MINI-MACS™."
The "MINI-MACS™" instrument is capable of measuring the consistency (Be or Bearden
units), the viscosity, and the static gel strength of a cement slurry. A variable speed stepper
motor drive and precision force transducer is used for stirring the slurry and measuring the
consistence and static gel strength values. The motor speed is controlled to rotate a paddle
inside the slurry container at 150 rpm for a standard API thickening time test and the initial
placement conditioning for a static gel strength test. When in the static gel strength testing
mode, the paddle is rotated at 0.2 degrees per minute.</p><p num="0035">The MINI-MACS™" instrument is rated for use at pressures up to 20,000 psi and
temperatures up to 500°F. A heating rate of approximately 10°F/min is attainable. The test
chamber is a two-part assembly that contains flow channels between the inside and outside
portions that are used for cooling. This results in extremely fast cooling of the instrument
after a testing is completed, even for high temperature tests. The API thickening time test
provides the user with information on how long a slurry will remain pumpable during a
cementing job. The instrument is one of the alternate apparatus for well simulation
thickening time tests described in API RP10B, Twenty-Second Edition, December 1997, 
Appendix D. The instrument rotates the paddle inside the slurry cup instead of rotating the
slurry cup as the traditional consistometer does. The static gel strength test is used to
determine the gellation properties of a slurry when in a static mode. The test is normally
started by stirring the slurry to simulate placement into a well bore and then the stirring
stopped and placed in the static gel strength mode. During this time, the paddle is rotated at
0.2 degrees per minute (as near to static conditions as practical to obtain an indication of
gellation)."</p><p num="0036">The tests were done in the thickening time test mode. If the slurry viscosity dropped
to zero Bc long before the thickening time, the slurry was assumed to be vulnerable to
settling. If a viscosity value of less than at least 5-10 Bc was maintained from the time the
test temperature is reached until the set time, then the slurry was not expected to have settling
problems. Frequently, it was noted that during the heating cycle, especially with gums
surface-treated for delayed hydration, the slurry viscosity suddenly increased to values which
are considered too high for pumping and dropped to near zero values after a few minut4s at
high temperatures. In order for the slurry to be placed with reasonable pump pressures which
do not exceed fracture gradients of the formation, slurries which maintain uniform viscosity
through the entire length of slurry placement are desired. During the course of the
experiment using "MINI-MACS™", Off/On cycles were programmed into the instrument
computer program. During Off/On experiments, the stirring was stopped and started again in
5 minutes, and the cycle was repeated. When the stirring was started again, if the immediate
viscosity was higher than that when the stirring was stopped, it was taken as an indication
settling or severe gellation. If the immediate viscosity was the same as when the stirring was
stopped, it was taken as a good sign indicating that the slurry was viscous and still flowable. </p><p num="0037">For selected slurries, the densities of different portions of set cement obtained from
"MINI-MACS™" testing were measured to estimate the amount of settling. The fluid loss
was measured either using a stirring high-temperature dynamic fluid loss cell for
temperatures exceeding 180°F, or using the procedure described in API Specification 10, 5<sup>th</sup>
Edition dated July 1, 1990 of the American Petroleum Institute. The rheology of the cement
slurries was measured at room temperature using a Fann viscometer Model 35 manufactured
by Fann Instruments of Houston, Texas.</p><p num="0038">A typical procedure is as follows for Slurry No. 30. A dry blend of Class H cement
(600 grams), tannin grafted with acrylamide and 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid
(4.8 grams), a copolymer of 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid and itaconic acid
(12 grams), tartaric acid (12 grams), silica flour (240 grams), fumed silica (30 grams),
polyvinylpyrrolidone (3 grams) and a terpolymer of 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic
acid/acrylamide/N-vinyl-N-methylacetamide (3 grams) was mixed with tap water (372
grams) in a Waring blender under high shear according to API procedure. The slurry was
transferred to the cell in the "MINI-MACS™" instrument and the heating cycle was set such
that the test temperature (434°F) was reached in 54 min. The stirring speed was 150 rpm.
The final pressure at this temperature was 15,000 psi. After the test temperature was reached,
the slurry viscosity was stabilized at 6 Bc. The slurry was allowed to set inside the cell at the
test temperature. The device was cooled, the cement column was removed and chunks of the
cement were removed with a drill. The densities of cement chunks from top, middle and
bottom of the column were measured and were found to be 15.45, 15.33 and 15.32,
respectively. <img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="115" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/></p><p num="0039">The results in Table I show that in the 150-200°F temperature range, the terpolymer
containing acrylamide is sufficient to prevent settling as seen in the good viscosity values of
the slurry throughout the test period at the test temperatures. <img id="img-00170001" orientation="unknown" wi="116" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00170001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/></p><p num="0040">The results in Table II for the temperature range 250-400°F show that the polymers
tested prevent settling of the particles as reflected in only small density variation in the set
cement. In the temperature range, the homopolymer of vinylpyrrolidone was inadequate
when used by itself as seen by the zero viscosity value reached during the test. This is
believed to be due to thermal thinning at intermediate temperatures prior to reaching the test
temperature. When the homopolymer is used in combination with the terpolymer containing
the easily hydrolyzable acrylamide, the slurry viscosities remained at levels at which settling
does not occur. The results also show that by using a proper amount of the terpolymer in
combination with additives which are not overly dispersing, the particulate settling can be
effectively prevented. <img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="114" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/></p><p num="0041">The results in Table III show that the proper combination of polymers which generate
carboxylate groups by hydrolysis continuously over the entire temperature range will provide
the slurry viscosification necessary to prevent particle settling at the test temperature.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A viscosifying and fluid loss control additive for use in well cement slurries subject to
temperatures up to 500°F, which additive comprises a mixture of a polymer comprised of at
least one monomer which is calcium tolerant, anionic and disperses basic cement slurries, at
least one monomer which hydrolyzes in basic cement slurries to generate anionic carboxylate
groups that bind with calcium and viscosify the slurries, and at least one monomer which
generates non-ionic pendant groups on the polymer upon hydrolyzing in basic cement slurries
to prevent polymer precipitation; and a homopolymer of a monomer which hydrolyzes in
basic cement slurries to generate anionic carboxylate groups that bind with calcium, viscosify
the slurries and prevent settling in the slurries.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>An additive according to claim 1, wherein said calcium tolerant monomer is selected
from 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid and its salts; vinyl sulfonate, allylsulfonate
and 3-allyloxy-2-hydroxy-1-propane sulfonic acid and its salts.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>An additive according to claim 1 or 2, wherein said monomer which hydrolyzes in
basic cement slurries is selected from acrylonitrile, acrylamide, N,N-dialkylacrylamide
wherein the alkyl group is C1 to C6, N-vinylpyrrolidone, 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane
sulfonic acid and its salts, alkylacrylate wherein the alkyl group is C1 to C6, and
alkylmethylacrylate wherein the alkyl group is C1 to C6.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>An additive according to claim 1, 2 or 3, wherein said monomer which generates non-ionic
pendant groups on the polymer is selected from N-alkyl-N-vinyl-acetamide wherein the
alkyl group is C1 to C6 allyl glycidyl ether and vinylacetate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An additive according to claim 1, 2, 3 or 4, wherein said calcium tolerant monomer is
present in said polymer in an amount of from 30% to 60% by weight of said polymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>An additive according to any of claims 1 to 5, wherein said monomer which
hydrolyzes in basic cement slurries is present in said polymer in an amount of from 20% to
60% by weight of said polymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>An additive according to any of claims 1 to 6, wherein said monomer which generates
non-ionic pendant groups on the polymer is present in said polymer in an amount up to 40%
by weight of said polymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>An additive according to any of claims1 to 7, wherein said polymer is present in said
mixture in an amount of from 50% to 95% by weight of said mixture and said homopolymer
is present therein in an amount of from 5% to 50% by weight of said mixture.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>An additive according to any of claims 1 to 8, wherein the molecular weight of said
polymer is from 300,000 to about 1.5 million and the molecular weight of said homopolymer
is from 900,000 to 1.5 million.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A well cement composition for use at temperatures up to about 500°F, comprising: a
hydraulic cement; water present in an amount sufficient to form a slurry; and a viscosifying
and fluid loss control additive as claimed in any of claims 1 to 9.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 10, wherein said hydraulic cement is a Portland
cement, pozzolana cement, gypsum cement, aluminous cement or silica cement.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 10 or 11, wherein said water is fresh water, or an
unsaturated or saturated salt solution.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A composition according to claim 12, wherein said water is present in said
composition in an amount of from 38% to 70% by weight of said hydraulic cement therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A cement composition according to claim 10, 11, 12 or 13, wherein said viscosifying
and fluid loss controlling additive is present in said cement composition in an amount of from
0.2% to 7%, preferably about 2%, by weight of hydraulic cement therein.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A cement composition according to claim 10, wherein the viscosifying and fluid loss
control additive comprises a polymer having a molecular weight of about 500,000 comprised
of 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropane sulfonic acid, acrylamide and N-alkyl-N-vinyl-acetamide
monomers, said 2-acrylamido-2-methyl propane sulfonic acid monomer being present in said
polymer in an amount of from 40% to 50% by weight of said polymer, said acrylamide
monomer being present in said polymer in an amount of from 30% to 40% by weight of said
polymer and said N-alkyl-N-vinyl-acetamide being present in an amount of from 10% to 20%
by weight of said polymer, and a homopolymer of acrylamide having a molecular weight of 1
million.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A method of cementing a subterranean zone penetrated by a well bore, which method
comprises the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) placing a cement composition in said subterranean zone; and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) allowing said cement composition to set therein, wherein the cement composition
is as claimed in any of claims 10 to 15.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>