<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1004427-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1004427" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26574268" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000531"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1004427-A1" status="new" fvid="22838366"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1004427</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20000531</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99309352-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99309352</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991123</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-33270898-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>33270898</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981124</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-33270998-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>33270998</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981124</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  67/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  67/24        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  73/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  73/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29C  67/24</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29C  67/24D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  73/10T</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L29C279:08</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zum Formen eines Polymers</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method for molding of polymer</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour le moulage d'un polymère</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0118240-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0118240</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0658586-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0658586</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0692357-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0692357</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0767191-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0767191</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-10287554-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>10287554</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-10292044-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>10292044</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-8302009-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>8302009</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4992220-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4992220</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5142062-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5142062</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5160467-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5160467</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997018249-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997018249</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999005346-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999005346</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 199715 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A26, AN 1997-161583 XP002130373 &amp; JP 09 031197 A (MITSUBISHI CHEM CORP), 4 February 1997 (1997-02-04)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 1997, no. 03, 31 March 1997 (1997-03-31) &amp; JP 08 302009 A (NIPPON SHOKUBAI CO LTD), 19 November 1996 (1996-11-19)</text><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 1999, no. 01, 29 January 1999 (1999-01-29) &amp; JP 10 287554 A (SANKYO CO LTD), 27 October 1998 (1998-10-27)</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 1999, no. 02, 26 February 1999 (1999-02-26) &amp; JP 10 292044 A (MITSUI CHEM INC), 4 November 1998 (1998-11-04)</text><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NIPPON CATALYTIC CHEM IND</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NIPPON SHOKUBAI CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Nippon Shokubai Co., Ltd.</last-name><address><street>1-1, Koraibashi 4-chome, Chuo-ku</street><city>Osaka-shi, Osaka 541-0043</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MIKOUYAMA MASAHARU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YASUDA SHINZO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MUKOUYAMA, MASAHARU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YASUDA, SHINZO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Mikouyama, Masaharu</last-name><address><street>318-3, Takaoka, Inamachi</street><city>Tsukuba-gun, Ibaraki 300-2301</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>YASUDA, SHINZO</last-name><address><street>1084-78, A-101 Tagucho</street><city>Ushiku-shi, Ibaraki 300-1236</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Rees, David Christopher</last-name><address><street>Kilburn &amp;amp; Strode 20 Red Lion Street</street><city>London WC1R 4PJ</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A method capable of molding by a simple procedure such
a polymer as a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer or a protein
which glass transition temperature can not be determined is
provided. The method for the molding of a polymer
contemplated by this invention comprises heating and melting
a polymer which glass transition temperature can not be
determined in the presence of a solvent having a low boiling
point and a high dielectric constant ratio and then molding
the resultant molten product.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention relates to a method for the molding of
a polymer. More particularly, this invention relates to a
method for molding such a polymer as which glass transition
temperature (Tg) can not be determined.</p><p num="0002">This invention relates further to a method for the
production of a polysuccinimide based polymer and/or
copolymer having the high molecular weight thereof increased.
More particularly, this invention relates to a method for
conveniently producing a polysuccinimide based polymer
and/or copolymer having a higher molecular weight than a
polysuccinimide based polymer and/or copolymer as a raw
material.</p><p num="0003">In general, a polymer can be subjected to molding and
processing in a glass state (molten state) by heating using
glass transition. Such polymers as proteins and
polysuccinimide based polymers and copolymers (which will
be collectively referred to simply as "polysuccinimide based
(co)polymers" in this specification), however, have the
problem of being incapable of yielding to the thermal molding
and processing via the glass transition temperature because
they apparently exhibit very closely approximating
decomposition temperatures and glass transition
temperatures and, when heated to be molded, they are fated
to be thoroughly decomposed before they are melted.</p><p num="0004">In these polymers, the polysuccinimide based
(co)polymers promise as prospective precursors of
biodegradable materials because the main aspartic acid chain 
formed by the ring-opening of an imide ring possesses
biodegradability. The polyaspartic acid which is obtained
by the hydrolysis of polysuccinimide, for example, is useful
as a chelating agent, a scale preventing agent, a detergent
builder, a dispersant, and etc.</p><p num="0005">To the polysuccinimide based (co)polymers, however, a
molding method which is used for a thermoplastic resin can
not be applied because they show no glass transition
temperature below their decomposition temperatures and have
no melting point below their thermal decomposition
temperatures as described above. Thus, they impose a very
rigid limit on the method to be adopted for the molding thereof.
As means for molding a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer,
a method which introduces a specific co-monomer component
such as an aliphatic aminocarboxylic acid for the sake of
molding a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer (JP-A-09-165,446),
a method which modifies a polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer in order to improve moldability thereof by
reacting by addition a monoamine compound to the
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer and heating the resultant
addition product till dissolution (JP-A-10-139,880), and a
method which comprises compatibilizing a polysuccinimide
based (co)polymer compatibly with another polymer component
to obtain a moldable composition (JP-A-10-168,326) have been
disclosed, for example. Besides the molding methods
mentioned above, as a means generally adopted for molding
a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer in an unmodified form,
a method which effects the molding of a polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer as dissolved in such an organic solvent as
N,N-dimethyl formamide (DMF) (JP-A-09-3,214) has been known.</p><p num="0006">In the methods mentioned above, the methods for molding
polysuccinimide based (co)polymers which are disclosed in 
JP-A-09-165,446, JP-A-10-139,880, and JP-A-10-168,326
entail operational complications by necessitating steps for
modification of a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer, i.e.,
a step of introducing a specific co-monomer component in the
main chain, a step of adding a monoamine, and a step of
compatibilizing the (co)polymer with another polymer
component, respectively, and prove unfavorable commercially
in consideration of quantity production. Further, the
method which relies on such an organic solvent as DMF to attain
necessary dissolution has the problem that since the organic
solvent which is usable for the dissolution of a
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer has a high boiling point
and exhibits high affinity as well for the polysuccinimide
based (co)polymer, the removal of the organic solvent from
the molded product which has been desired earnestly in due
consideration of the conservation of safety is attained only
with difficulty.</p><p num="0007">In such circumstances, the desirability for developing
a method which can easily obtain a molded article of a
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer containing no organic
solvents has been finding enthusiastic recognition.</p><p num="0008">The polysuccinimide based (co)polymers which are at
present available in the market fit only limited applications
because they have relatively low molecular weights falling
in the approximate range of 6000 to 7000 at most. Even when
they happen to find applications, the products thereof do
not exhibit very high qualities.</p><p num="0009">Various methods, therefore, have been attempted with
a view to accomplishing production of polysuccinimide based
(co)polymers having higher molecular weights. For example,
a method which comprises polycondensating aspartic acid in
the presence of a specific amount of an acid catalyst such 
as phosphoric acid and sulfuric acid (JP-A-08-239,468), a
method which comprises subjecting such an amino acid as
aspartic acid or glutamic acid to graft polymerization to
a polyfunctional polymer such as polyaspartic acid (salt)
in the presence of a catalyst such as phosphoric acid in an
aliphatic sulfur-containing organic solvent such as
sulfolane or methylsulfonic acid to obtain a polysuccinimide
based (co)polymer (JP-A-09-235,372), a method which
comprises polycondensing aspartic acid, maleamic acid, or
the reaction product of maleic acid with ammonia in the
presence of a phosphorous compound thereby obtaining a
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer of a high molecular weight
(JP-A-09-278,883), a method which comprises adding a
catalyst and a polymerization accelerator in respectively
specified amounts to a polymerization system and
polymerizing the resultant mixture in a substantially solid
state while stirred to obtain a polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer of a high molecular weight (JP-A-09-302,088),
and a method which comprises polycondensing a polycondensing
system such as aspartic acid, maleamic acid, or the reaction
product of maleic acid with ammonia with a compound having
two or more oxazoline structures in its molecular unit
thereof added as a chain extender, to obtain a
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer (JP-A-10-147,644) have
been known. In addition to these methods, JP-A-08-302,009
discloses a method for the treatment of a polysuccinimide,
characterized by subjecting polysuccinimide to the heat
treatment in an aqueous medium of a pH level of not more than
6, preferably in water, at a temperature of not lower than
50 °C and lower than 150 °C.</p><p num="0010">The reactions of polymerization (or polycondensation)
effected according to the methods disclosed in JP-A-08-239,468, 
JP-A-09-235,372, JP-A-09-278,883, JP-A-09-302,088,
and JP-A-10-147,644, however, do not necessarily deserve to
be called a satisfactory process for commercial production
due to the complication of the process and the high cost of
the catalyst to be used. In addition to the defects mentioned
above, the methods taught by the patent publications
mentioned above require the heating to be performed in an
organic solvent and, as a result, suffer persistence of the
organic solvent in the produced polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer, which organic solvent, depending on the purpose
of use, is preferably removed completely from the product
because it does not bring about any good to the safety. Since
the organic solvent has a high boiling point and exhibits
high affinity for a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as well,
however, it is extremely difficult to attain required removal
thereof. Thus, the methods disclosed in the above patent
publicaitons have the problem of inevitably limiting the
applicaitons to be found therefor.</p><p num="0011">Among the methods mentioned above, the method which is
disclosed in JP-A-08-302,009 can be favorably used in terms
of the safety of the product because it uses an aqueous medium
such as water which has a pH level of not more than 6 in place
of an organic solvent. According to the method disclosed in
JP-A-08-302,009, the polysodium aspartates which are
produced in Example 5 and Control 2 and in Example 6 and
Control 4, the pairs each using the same starting raw
materials, have weight average molecular weights (Mw) of
10,000 in Example 5 and 14,000 in Control 2 and 2,500 in
Example 6 and 5,000 in Control 4. From the results obtained
by these experiments which used the same raw materials, the
products obtained by the method disclosed in JP-A-08-302,009
show decreases in weight average molecular weights in some 
cases. Thus, this method has the problem of possibly failing
to attain an increase in molecular weight as aimed at.</p><p num="0012">While the development of a method capable of producing
a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer of a high molecular
weight inexpensively by a simple process has been craved for,
it remains yet to be realized.</p><p num="0013">An object of this invention, therefore, is to provide
a method which is capable of molding by a simple procedure
such polymers as polysuccinimide based (co)polymers and
proteins whose glass transition temperatures can not be
determined.</p><p num="0014">Another object of this invention is to provide a method
which is capable of molding by a simple procedure without
requiring the use of an organic solvent such polymers as
polysuccinimide based (co)polymers and proteins whose glass
transition temperatures can not be determined.</p><p num="0015">Yet another object of this invention is to provide a
convenient method for obtaining a polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer of a high molecular weight by increasing the
molecular weight of a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as
a raw material.</p><p num="0016">The present inventors, after pursuing a diligent study
with a view to fulfilling the objects mentioned above, have
found that when a polymer which glass transition temperature
can not be determined such as a polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer which is not melted at normal temperature under
normal pressure is heated in the presence of a solvent of
a low boiling point and a high dielectric constant ratio such
as water, it assumes a fluidized (partially molten) state
without being substantially decomposed at a reaction 
temperature falling in such a wide range as of 90° to 300 °C
(the substance in this state will be occasionally referred
to simply as "fluidized substance" in this specification)
and that when the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer in this
fluidized state is heated, it becomes melted without being
substantially decomposed and consequently a polymer in the
melted state can be manufactured easily as a molded product
aimed at.</p><p num="0017">In addition to the above knowledge, the present
inventors, after continuing the diligent study with a view
further to accomplishing the objects mentioned above, have
found that when the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer in the
fluidized state mentioned above is heated in the presence
of a chain extender and a solvent of a low boiling point and
a high dielectric constant ratio, the molecular weight of
the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as the raw material
can be easily increased. This invention has been perfected
based on this knowledge.</p><p num="0018">To be specific, the objects of this invention can be
attained by a method for the molding of a polymer which glass
transition temperature (Tg) can not be determined, which
method comprises heating and melting the polymer in the
presence of a solvent having a low boiling point and a high
dielectric constant ratio and then molding the molten
product.</p><p num="0019">The yet another object of this invention can be further
attained by a method for the production of a high molecular
polysuccinimide based polymer and/or copolymer, which method
comprises heating a polysuccinimide based polymer and/or
copolymer in the presence of a chain extender and a solvent
of a low boiling point and a high dielectric constant ratio
thereby increasing the molecular weight of said 
polysuccinimide based polymer and/or copolymer.</p><p num="0020">According to this invention, a polymer which glass
transition temperature can not be determined such as a
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer and a protein can be
rendered moldable in an expected shape by such a simple
procedure without requiring any use of an organic solvent
as by heating and melting the polymer in the presence of a
solvent having a low melting point and a high dielectric
constant ratio. Besides the merit mentioned above, the
polymer can be rendered moldable in an expected shape by such
a simple procedure without requiring any use of an organic
solvent and without entailing any decomposition, namely
without any decrease of the molecular weight, of the polymer
as by heating and melting the polymer in the presence of a
solvent having a low melting point and a high dielectric
constant ratio, and a chain extender and/or an acid catalyst.</p><p num="0021">Further, according to this invention, by heating a
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer in the presence of a chain
extender and a solvent having a low boiling temperature and
a high dielectric constant ratio, the molecular weight of
the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as the raw material
can be easily increased without requiring use of an organic
solvent. In addition to the merit mentioned above, the
increase of the molecular weight of the polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer can be attained more significantly by heating
the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer in the presence of a
chain extender, a solvent having a low boiling point and a
high dielectric constant ratio, and an acid catalyst.</p><p num="0022">The above and other objects, features, and advantages
of the present invention will become clear from the following
description of the preferred embodiments. </p><p num="0023">According to the first aspect, this invention is to
provide a method for the molding of a polymer which glass
transition temperature (Tg) can not be determined
(hereinafter occasionally referred to simply as "a polymer"),
which comprises heating and melting the polymer in the
presence of a solvent having a low boiling point and a high
dielectric constant ratio, and molding the resultant molten
product.</p><p num="0024">The raw material to be used in this invention is referred
to as a polymer whose glass transition temperature can not
be determined, i.e., a polymer whose glass transition
temperature is very close to the decomposition temperature
or whose glass transition temperature of itself is not
present. As concrete examples of the polymer which answers
the description, proteins such as casein, collagen, gelatin,
gluten, keratin, soybean protein, cellulose and silk fibroin,
and polysuccinimide based polymers and copolymers may be
cited. In these polymers, cellulose and polysuccinimide
based polymers and copolymers, in particular,
polysuccinimide based polymers and copolymers may be
advantageously used in consideration of such factors as wide
range of applications, excellent properties represented by
biodegradability.</p> <p num="0025">The polysuccinimide based (co)polymer which can be
advantageously used as the raw material in this invention
does not need to be particularly discriminated but is only
required to have as a repeating unit the succinimide ring
represented by the following formula: <img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="39" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="34"/>
The polysuccinimide based (co)polymer to be used in this
invention may embrace all the compounds that are generally
designated as polysuccinimide based (co)polymers. As
concrete examples thereof, polysuccinimides, succinimide
copolymers having a repeating unit other than the succinimide
ring, and polysuccinimide derivatives obtained by modifying
these polymers or copolymers as by suitably opening the
succinimide rings thereof may be cited. A repeating unit
other than the succinimide ring which may contained in the
polysuccinimide based copolymer does not need to be
particularly discriminated but is only required to have at
least two functional groups capable of reacting with an amino
group or carboxyl group or salts thereof. As concrete
examples of the repeating unit other than the succinimide
ring which may contained in the polysuccinimide based
copolymer, amino acid, hydroxycarboxylic acid,
hydroxycarboxylic acid amide, ammonium salt of
hydroxycarboxylic acid, aminocarboxylic acid,
aminocarboxylic acid amide, ammonium salt of aminocarboxylic
acid, dicarboxylic acid, ammonium salt of dicarboxylic acid,
and dicarboxylic acid amide may be cited. Among other
repeating units mentioned above, amino acid,
hydroxycarboxylic acid, and aminocarboxylic acid can be used
particularly advantageously. These repeating units may be
incorporated in the polysuccinimide based copolymer either
singly or in the form of a combination of two or more members
arranged in a blocked form or random form. When the 
polysuccinimide based copolymer is used, though the content
of the repeating unit other than the succinimide ring does
not need to be particularly limited, it may be generally not
more than 50%, preferably not more than 45%. Among other
polysuccinimide based (co)polymers cited above, the
polysuccinimide may be used particularly advantageously in
this invention. To be used as the raw material in this
invention, the polysuccinimide based (co)polymers may be
used singly or in a mixed form of two or more species of
polysuccinimide based polymers and/or polysuccinimide based
copolymers, or optionally in a form further containing other
components.</p><p num="0026">This invention does not particularly discriminate the
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer to be used as the raw
material on account of the magnitude of the molecular weight
thereof. It allows the use of any polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer without reference to the molecular weight
thereof. Specifically, the lower limit of the molecular
weight of the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer may be set
generally at 300, preferably at 500, and more preferably at
1,000. Then, the upper limit of the molecular weight of the
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer may be set generally at
1,000,000, preferably at 500,000, and more preferably at
100,000. Polysuccinimide based (co)polymers which have
molecular weights particularly in the approximate range of
6,000 to 7,000 can be easily produced or may be commercially
available and, therefore, can be used in their unmodified
form in the present invention. The molecular weights which
are mentioned in the present specification represent the
numerical values which are determined by the same method as
described in the working examples to be described herein
below. </p><p num="0027">This invention does not particularly limit the method
to be used for the preparation of the polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer. The production can be attained, for example,
by such a well-known method as of heating L-aspartic acid
in the presence or absence of phosphoric acid (JP-B-48-20,638
and P. Neri et al., J. Med. Chem., 16, 893 (1973)). This
method can similarly use ammonium (poly)aspartate, ammonium
maleate, or maleic acid amide as the starting raw material,
as well as aspartic acid.</p><p num="0028">The method for molding according to this invention has
an essential requirement of comprising a step of heating and
melting a polymer which glass transition temperature can not
be determined in the presence of a solvent having a low boiling
temperature and a high dielectric constant ratio and a step
of molding the resultant molten product. In this case, the
polymer such as a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as the
raw material herein may be fluidized to form a fluidized
substance by being heated in the presence of a solvent having
a low boiling temperature and a high dielectric constant
ratio as described above. The terms "fluidized" and
"fluidized substance" as used in the present specification
mean that the polymer as the raw material is partly dissolved
into the solvent having a low boiling temperature and a high
dielectric constant ratio and partly melted in itself and
consequently caused to form a homogeneous viscous substance
(resembling starch syrup) as a whole. They also refer to the
state which the produced substance assumes as mentioned
above.</p><p num="0029">The solvent having a low boiling temperature and a high
dielectric constant ratio and used in the present invention
does not need to be particularly limited but is only required
to satisfy the definition mentioned above. The lower limit 
of the boiling temperature of the solvent to be
advantageously used in this invention may be set preferably
at 50 °C, more preferably at 60 °C, and most preferably at
70 °C. Then, the upper limit of the boiling temperature may
be set preferably at 150 °C, more preferably at 145 °C, and
most preferably at 120 °C. The dielectric constant ratio
which the solvent advantageously used in this invention
exhibits at 20 °C may be preferably not less than 20, more
preferably not less than 25, and most preferably not less
than 30. If the boiling temperature of the solvent is less
than 50 °C, the shortage would be at a disadvantage in
preventing the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as the raw
material from being thoroughly fluidized in the solvent.
Conversely, if the boiling temperature of the solvent exceeds
150 C, the excess would be likewise at a disadvantage in
rendering difficult the removal of the solvent remaining
after the reaction. If the dielectric constant ratio of the
solvent at 20°C is less than 20, the shortage would be at a
disadvantage in degrading the affinity of the
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as the raw material for
the solvent and consequently markedly lowering the
homogeneity during the reaction.</p> <p num="0030">As concrete examples of the solvent having a low boiling
temperature and a high dielectric constant ratio which can
be used in this invention, water, 2,6-difluoropyridine,
formic acid, nitromethane, acetonitrile, acrylonitrile,
2-fluoropyridine, methanol, ethanol, isopropyl alcohol, and
acetone may be cited. Among other solvents mentioned above,
water and formic acid may be used advantageously herein and,
in consideration of the obviation of the necessity for a
special device for drying, water may be used especially
preferably. In this invention, the solvents mentioned above 
may be used either singly or in a mixed or dispersed form
of two or more members.</p> <p num="0031">Alternatively, according to this invention, a solvent
which is obtained by mixing or dispersing another solvent
having a boiling temperature and/or a dielectric constant
ratio deviating from the preferred ranges contemplated by
this invention with or in any of the solvents cited above
in such a ratio as to adjust the boiling temperature and the
dielectric constant ratio within the preferred ranges may
be used as the solvent of a low boiling temperature and a
high dielectric constant ratio according to this invention.
In the case of a solvent which has a boiling temperature in
the range of 50° to 150 °C and yet has a dielectric constant
ratio of less than 20, for example, the solvent conforming
to this invention may be prepared by mixing or dispersing
this solvent with or in the aforementioned solvent having
a low boiling temperature (50° to 150 °C) and a high dielectric
constant ratio (not less than 20) at such a ratio as to adjust
the dielectric constant ratio to a level of not less than
20. As concrete examples of the another solvent which have
a boiling temperature and/or a dielectric constant ratio
deviating from the preferred ranges according to this
invention, hexane, toluene, and ethyl acetate may be cited.</p> <p num="0032">The amount of the solvent of a low boiling temperature
and a high dielectric constant ratio to be used in this
invention does not need to be particularly restricted but
is only required to fluidize the polymer as the raw material.
Specifically, the lower limit of the amount of the solvent
of a low boiling temperature and a high dielectric constant
ratio to be used may be set generally at 0.1, preferably at
0.2, and more preferably at 0.3 by weight ratio based on the
amount of the polymer taken as 1. The upper limit of the 
amount of the solvent of a low boiling temperature and a high
dielectric constant ratio to be used may be set at 100,
preferably at 50, more preferably at 20, and most preferably
at 10 by weight ratio based on the amount of the polymer taken
as 1. In this case, if the amount of the solvent of a low
boiling temperature and a high dielectric constant ratio to
be used is less than 0.1, the shortage would be at a
disadvantage in preventing the polymer as the raw material
from being thoroughly fluidized and the system from acquiring
homogeneity. In contrast, if the amount of the solvent of
a low boiling temperature and a high dielectric constant
ratio to be used exceeds 100, the excess would be likewise
at a disadvantage in preventing the polymer as the raw
material from acquiring sufficient increase in the molecular
weight and not doing any good economically. Particularly
when the solvent of a low boiling temperature and a high
dielectric constant ratio happens to be water, the lower
limit of the amount of water to be used may be set preferably
at 0.1, more preferably at 0.2, and most preferably at 0.3,
by weight ratio based on the amount of the polymer taken as
1. Then, the upper limit of the amount of water to be used
may be set preferably at 10, more preferably at 2, and most
preferably at 1.5 by weight ratio based on the amount of the
high molecular weight taken as 1.</p><p num="0033">The molding method according to the present invention
is characterized by heating the polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer in the presence of a solvent having a low boiling
temperature and a high dielectric constant ratio thereby
imparting thereto a fluidized state which facilitates
molding. The heating temperature to be used in this case may
be variable with the kind of polymer to be used as the raw
material and the kind of the solvent of a low boiling 
temperature and a high dielectric constant ratio. It does
not need to be particularly restricted but is only required
to permit forming of the fluidized substance of the polymer
as the raw material. The lower limit of the heating
temperature may be set generally at 50 °C, preferably at 60
°C, more preferably at 70 °C, and most preferably at 80 °C.
Then, the upper limit of the heating temperature may be set
generally at 300 °C, preferably at 250 °C, more preferably
at 210 °C, and most preferably at 200 °C. In this case, if
the heating temperature is less than 50 °C, the shortage would
be at a disadvantage in bringing about no thorough
fluidization of the polymer as the raw material but suffering
a part thereof to be dispersed in its original form of powder,
not allowing the reaction to proceed easily, and preventing
the product aimed at from acquiring homogeneity. In contrast,
if the heating temperature exceeds 300 °C, the excess would
be likewise at a disadvantage in doing no good economically
as evinced by inducing decomposition of the polymer as the
raw material and degradation of the thermal efficiency. The
shortest reaction time (required for heating and
fluidization) may be set generally at one minute and
preferably at five minutes and the longest reaction time may
be set generally at 72 hours and preferably at 48 hours. When
the polymer is a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer and the
solvent of a low boiling temperature and a high dielectric
constant ratio is water, the lower limit of the heating
temperature may be set generally at 100 °C, preferably at 110
°C, and more preferably at 130 °C and the upper limit of the
heating temperature may be set generally at 250 °C, preferably
at 210 °C, and more preferably at 180 °C. The shortest heating
time may be set generally at one minute and preferably at
five minutes and the longest heating time may be set generally 
at 72 hours and preferably at 48 hours.</p><p num="0034">In the method of this invention, the other reaction
conditions may be varied with the kind of the polymer to be
used as the raw material and the kind of the solvent of a
low boiling temperature and a high dielectric constant ratio
and may be properly selected to suit the occasion. While the
reaction may be performed under pressure of any status such
as, for example, an increased pressure, a normal pressure,
or a reduced pressure, the temperature and the pressure may
be desirably maintained at respectively constant levels
throughout the course of the reaction in consideration of
the stability of the product in quality. More desirably, the
refluxing temperature of the solvent is set at the level which
exists at the reaction temperature under the reaction
pressure of the reaction system.</p><p num="0035">In this invention, for the purpose of preventing the
molecular weight of the polymer as the raw material,
particularly the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer, from
decreasing, the heating and melting process of the polymer
may be preferably performed in the presence of a chain
extender and/or an acid catalyst. The term "a chain
extender" as used in the present specification means an
organic compound which has a functional group capable of
reacting with an amino group and/or carboxyl group and is
capable of reacting with the polymer such as, for example,
a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer to form a repeating unit.</p><p num="0036">The chain extender which can be optionally used in this
invention is not particularly limited but is only required
to have at least two functional groups capable of reacting
with the amino group or carboxyl group or salts thereof. Any
of the well-known chain extenders may be used on the condition
that it satisfy the requirement just mentioned. As concrete 
examples of the chain extender which is usable herein,
dicyclohexyl carbodiimide, amino acid, hydroxycarboxylic
acid, hydroxycarboxylic acid amide, ammonium salt of
hydroxycarboxylic acid, aminocarboxylic acid,
aminocarboxylic acid amide, ammonium salt of aminocarboxylic
acid, dicarboxylic acid, ammonium salt of dicarboxylic acid,
dicarboxylic acid amide, monoammonium aspartate, diammonium
aspartate, aspartic acid monoamide, aspartic acid diamide,
monoammonium maleate, diammonium maleate, maleic acid
monoamide, maleic acid diamide, monoammonium fumarate,
diammonium fumarate, fumaric acid monoamide, fumaric acid
diamide, polysuccinimide, and polyaspartic acid may be cited.
Among other chain extenders cited above, polysuccinimide and
aspartic acid may be used particularly advantageously.</p><p num="0037">The acid catalyst which can be optionally used in this
invention is not particularly limited but may be selected
among conventional acid catalysts. As concrete examples of
the acid catalyst which is usable herein, sulfuric acid,
phosphoric acid, boric acid, paratoluenesulfonic acid,
phosphorous acid, and phosphorous esters may be cited. Among
other acid catalysts mentioned above, phosphoric acid and
boric acid may be particularly advantageously used.</p><p num="0038">When the polymer used as the raw material in this
invention is heated and melted in the presence of a chain
extender, the amount of the chain extender to be used can
be properly decided, depending on the kinds and amounts of
the raw material, solvent, and acid catalyst to be used. When
the polymer is a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer, for
example, the lower limit of the amount of the chain extender
may be set preferably at 0.1% by weight, more preferably at
0.5% by weight, based on the amount of the polysuccinimide
based (co)polymer, and the upper limit thereof may be set 
preferably at 100% by weight, more preferably at 50% by weight,
based on the amount of the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer.</p><p num="0039">When the polymer used as the raw material in this
invention is heated and melted in the presence of an acid
catalyst, the amount of the acid catalyst to be used may be
likewise decided properly, depending on the kinds and amounts
of the raw material, solvent, and chain extender. When the
polymer is a polysuccinimide based (co)polymer, for example,
the lower limit of the amount of the acid catalyst to be used
may be set preferably at 0.05% by weight, more preferably
at 0.1% by weight, based on the amount of the polysuccinimide
based (co)polymer, and the upper limit thereof may be set
preferably at 100% by weight, more preferably at 50% by weight,
based on the amount of the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer.
The times at which the chain extender or the acid catalyst
are added to the polymer as the raw material do not need to
be limited particularly. The chain extender and the acid
catalyst may be collectively added together with the polymer
or they may be added collectively or sequentially to the
polymer.</p><p num="0040">This invention allows the polymer to be heated and
melted together with other molding auxiliaries. As concrete
examples of the other molding auxiliaries which are usable
herein, inorganic fillers such as zeolite, talc, glass beads,
magnesium carbonate, calcium carbonate, silica, alumina, and
clay; organic fillers such as polyethylene succinate,
polybutylene succinate, polyhydroxybutyric acid, polylactic
acid, and polyglutamic acid; and organic acid metal salts
such as magnesium stearate may be cited. When the other
molding auxiliaries are present, the amounts thereof to be
used may be properly decided, depending on the kinds and
amounts of the raw material, solvent, chain extender, and 
acid catalyst to be used. When the polymer is a
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer, for example, the lower
limit of the amount of such other forming auxiliaries to be
added may be set preferably at 1% by weight, more preferably
at 3% by weight, and most preferably at 5% by weight, based
on the amount of the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer, and
the upper limit thereof may be set preferably at 90% by weight,
more preferably at 80% by weight, and most preferably at 50%
by weight, based on the amount of the polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer. The time at which the other molding auxiliaries
are added to the polymer as the raw material does not need
to be particularly limited. The other molding auxiliaries
may be collectively added in advance together with the
polymer or they may be added collectively or sequentially
to the polymer.</p><p num="0041">Since the polymer which has been heated and melted by
the method of this invention as described above can be in
a fluidized state, it can be easily molded in an expected
shape by any of the known methods such as, for example,
extrusion molding, cast molding, vacuum molding, and sheet
forming. The molded product consequently obtained merits
high safety. Further, since the polymer as the raw material,
particularly the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer,
undergoes no decomposition or suffers from no decrease of
molecular weight during the course of heating and melting
process, the molded product can effectively maintain the
expected properties. The shape of the molded product
obtained by the method of this invention is not particularly
limited but may be properly selected, depending on the
purpose of use.</p><p num="0042">According to the second aspect, the present invention
is to provide a method for the production of a high molecular 
polysuccinimide based polymer and/or polysuccinimide based
copolymer, which method comprises heating a polysuccinimide
based polymer and/or copolymer in the presence of a chain
extender and a solvent having a low boiling temperature and
a high dielectric constant ratio.</p><p num="0043">In the aspect mentioned above, the terms
"polysuccinimide based (co)polymer", "chain extender", and
"solvent of a low boiling temperature and a high dielectric
constant ratio" have the same definitions as in the first
aspect mentioned previously.</p><p num="0044">The method of production according to the second aspect
mentioned above is characterized by heating a
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer in the presence of a
solvent having a low boiling temperature and a high high
dielectric constant ratio thereby fluidizing the (co)polymer
and then enabling the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer in
such a fluidized state to acquire an increase in the molecular
weight thereof by means of the chain extender. The heating
temperature to be used at this time may be varied with the
kinds of polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as the raw
material, chain extender, and solvent of a low boiling
temperature and a high dielectric constant ratio to be used.
It has no particular limit but is only required to allow the
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as the raw material to form
the fluidized substance. The lower limit of the heating
temperature may be set generally at 50 °C, preferably at 60
°C, and more preferably at 70 °C, and the upper limit of the
heating temperature may be set generally at 300 °C, preferably
at 250 °C, and more preferably at 210 °C. In this case, if
the heating temperature is less than 50 °C, the
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as the raw material would
not be thoroughly fluidized and a part thereof would be 
dispersed in its originally powdered form and the chain
extender would not act sufficiently on the polysuccinimide
based (co)polymer and thus the molecular weight would not
be increased to a full extent. In contrast, if the heating
temperature exceeds 300 °C, the polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer as the raw material would be decomposed and thus
the increase of the molecular weight of the polysuccinimide
based (co)polymer would not be attained fully satisfactorily.
The heating time likewise may be varied with the kinds of
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as the raw material, chain
extender, and solvent of a low boiling temperature and a high
dielectric constant ratio to be used and the conditions such
as heating temperature. The lower limit of the heating time
may be set generally at one minute and preferably at five
minutes, and the upper limit of the heating time may be set
generally at 72 hours and preferably at 48 hours.</p><p num="0045">Further, in the method of this invention, the other
reaction conditions may be varied with the kinds of
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer as the raw material and
solvent of a low boiling temperature and a high dielectric
constant ratio to be used and, therefore, can be suitably
selected. The reaction may be performed under pressure of
any status such as, for example, an increased pressure, a
normal pressure, or a reduced pressure. The temperature and
the pressure may be preferably maintained at respectively
constant levels throughout the course of the reaction in
consideration of the stabilization of the product in quality.
More preferably, the refluxing temperature of the solvent
may be set at the level which exists at the reaction
temperature under the reaction pressure of the reaction
system.</p><p num="0046">For the purpose of promoting the increase of the 
molecular weight of the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer
as the raw material in this invention, the heating of the
polysuccinimide based (co)polymer is preferred to be carried
out additionally in the presence of an acid catalyst.</p><p num="0047">The acid catalyst to be used herein is not particularly
limited but may be selected among the well-known acid
catalysts. As concrete examples thereof, sulfuric acid,
phosphoric acid, boric acid, paratoluenesulfonic acid,
phosphorous acid, and phosphorous esters may be cited. Among
other acid catalysts enumerated above, phosphoric acid and
boric acid may be used particularly advantageously. The
amount of such an acid catalyst to be used may be properly
decided, depending on the kinds and amounts of the solvent
and chain extender to be used and the reaction conditions.
The lower limit of the amount of the acid catalyst to be used
may be set preferably at 0.05% by weight and more preferably
at 0.1% by weight, based on the amount of the polysuccinimide
based (co)polymer, and the upper limit of the amount of the
acid catalyst to be used may be set preferably at 50% by weight
and more preferably at 40% by weight, based on the amount
of the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer. The time at which
the acid catalyst is added to the polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer as the raw material does not need to be
particularly limited. The acid catalyst may be collectively
added together with the polymer or it may be added
collectively or sequentially to the polymer.</p><p num="0048">By this method, the increase of the molecular weight
of the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer can be accomplished
by a simple procedure without requiring any use of an organic
solvent.</p><p num="0049">The polysuccinimide based (co)polymer of an increased
molecular weight which has been produced as described above 
can be used for various applications such as, for example,
an absorbent resin (material), a detergent, a builder for
a detergent , a scale preventing agent, a chelating agent,
a moisture retaining agent, a dispersant, and a fertilizer
additive or as raw materials therefor. More specifically,
an absorbent resin (material) may be produced by any of the
known methods such as disclosed in JP-A-11-5,840, JP-A-11-5,838,
JP-A-11-1,559, JP-A-11-1,557, JP-A-10-292,044,
and JP-A-10-511,423, using the polysuccinimide based
(co)polymer which is produced by the method of production
of this invention.</p><p num="0050">Further, since the polysuccinimide based (co)polymer
of an increased molecular weight according to this invention,
on being hydrolyzed by addition of an alkali, can be converted
into biodegradable polyaspartic acid, it is at an advantage
in promising easy disposal of waste and allowing effective
use as a biodegradable resin material.</p><p num="0051">Now, this invention will be described more specifically
below with reference to working examples.</p><p num="0052">A molecular weight was determined by means of gel
permeation chromatography (GPC) under the following
conditions. The calibration curves were produced by using
a polyethylene glycol standard made by Scientific Polymer
Product Corp. As the molecular weights of samples, peak top
molecular weights were adopted because all the samples were
found to have relatively simple dispersions (Mw/Mn within
2) invariably.</p><heading>&lt;Method for determination of molecular weight&gt;</heading><p num="0053"><dl compact="compact" tsize="12"><dt>Detector:</dt><dd>RI</dd><dt>Column:</dt><dd>Shodex Ohpak KF-G

Shodex Ohpak SB-805HQ

Shodex Ohpak KB-803
 
Shodex Ohpak KB-803

Shodex Ohpak KB-802.5</dd><dt>Carrier:</dt><dd>NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>·2H<sub>2</sub>O 15.6 g

NaCl 11.7 g

Water 1000.0 g

pH 7.0</dd><dt>Flow volume:</dt><dd>1.0 ml/min</dd><dt>Temperature:</dt><dd>40 °C</dd></dl></p><heading>Preparation Example 1</heading><p num="0054">In an eggplant type flask, 245 g of maleic anhydride
and 500 g of water were placed and left dissolving. To the
resultant solution, 170 g of an aqueous 25% ammonia solution
was slowly added dropwise so as to avoid bumping. When the
resultant solution was homogenized, it was heated in a rotary
evaporator with the temperature of an oil bath kept at 100
°C and vacuum-concentrated till separation of crystals. The
monoammonium maleate consequently obtained was transferred
into a stainless steel pad and heated therein with a hot air
drier at a temperature of 180 °C for three hours. The hot
compound was cooled to obtain a polysuccinimide having a
molecular weight of 6720.</p><heading>Preparation Example 2</heading><p num="0055">1 kg of L-aspartic acid was placed in a stainless steel
pad, and 1 kg of water was additionally introduced thereto.
Then, the resultant mixture was heated therein with a hot
air drier at a temperature of 205 °C for 18 hours. The hot
compound was cooled to obtain a polysuccinimide. The
molecular weight of the resultant polysuccinimide was
determined to find to be 8960.</p><heading>Preparation Example 3</heading><p num="0056">In an eggplant type flask, 122.5 g of maleic anhydride
and 250 g of water were placed and left dissolving. To the 
resultant solution, 85g of an aqueous 25% ammonia solution
was slowly added dropwise. When the resultant solution was
homogenized, it was heated in a rotary evaporator with the
temperature of an oil bath kept at 100 °C and vacuum-concentrated
till separation of crystals. The monoammonium
maleate consequently obtained was transferred into a
stainless steel pad and heated therein with a hot air drier
at a temperature of 185 °C for 2.5 hours. The hot compound
was cooled to obtain a polysuccinimide having a molecular
weight of 3950.</p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0057">When 10 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 1 and 6 g of water were placed in an
eggplant type flask and heated on a hot water bath at 130
°C, the system assumed a homogeneously dissolved state in
about six minutes to afford a homogeneous fluidized substance
of polysuccinimide. This fluidized substance of
polysuccinimide was then poured onto a stainless steel pad
covered with a sheet of tetrafluoroethylene resin and
thoroughly deprived of water by hot air drying at 65 °C for
five hours to afford a sheet-like molded product of about
3 mm in thickness.</p><p num="0058">The sheet-like molded product of polysuccinimide thus
obtained was weighed to find 6 g, indicating no change in
the weight of the polysuccinimide as the raw material. It
is, therefore, observed that the treatment in this experiment
induced no decomposition of the polysuccinimide.</p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0059">When 10 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 1 and 20 g of water were placed in an
eggplant type flask and heated on a hot water bath at 130
°C, the system assumed a homogeneously dissolved state in 
about 12 minutes to afford a homogeneous fluidized substance
of polysuccinimide.. Then, this fluidized substance of
polysuccinimide was swept with a current of air to expel a
small amount (about 10 g) of water and adjust the viscosity
thereof properly (about 5 Pa·sec). A sheet-like molded
product having a thickness of about 3 mm was obtained by
following the procedure of Example 1 while using the
fluidized substance of polysuccinimide of properly adjusted
viscosity instead.</p><p num="0060">The sheet-like molded product of polysuccinimide thus
obtained was weighed to find 10 g, indicating no change in
the weight of the polysuccinimide as the raw material. It
is, therefore, inferred that the treatment in this experiment
induced no decomposition of the polysuccinimide.</p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="0061">When 10 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 1 and 10 g of water were placed in an
eggplant type flask and heated on a hot water bath at 130
°C, the system assumed a homogeneously dissolved state in
about 10 minutes to afford a homogeneous fluidized substance
of polysuccinimide. Then, this fluidized substance of
polysuccinimide was swept with a current of argon gas to expel
a small amount (about 5 g) of water and adjust the viscosity
thereof properly (about 10 Pa·sec). A sheet-like molded
product having a thickness of about 3 mm was obtained by
following the procedure of Example 1 while using the
fluidized substance of polysuccinimide of properly adjusted
viscosity instead.</p><p num="0062">The sheet-like molded product of polysuccinimide thus
obtained was weighed to find 10 g, indicating no change in
the weight of the polysuccinimide as the raw material. It
is, therefore, observed that the treatment in this experiment 
induced no decomposition of the polysuccinimide.</p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0063">when 10 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 1 and 5 g of water were placed in an
eggplant type flask and heated on a hot water bath at 130
°C, the system assumed a homogeneously dissolved state in
about 4 minutes to afford a homogeneous fluidized substance
of polysuccinimide. Then, this fluidized substance of
polysuccinimide was swept with a current of nitrogen gas to
expel a small amount (about 2 g) of water and adjust the
viscosity thereof properly (about 50 Pa·sec). A sheet-like
molded product having a thickness of about 3 mm was obtained
by following the procedure of Example 1 while using the
polysuccinimide fluid of properly adjusted viscosity
instead.</p><p num="0064">The sheet-like molded product of polysuccinimide thus
obtained was weighed to find 10 g, indicating no change in
the weight of the polysuccinimide as the raw material. It
is, therefore, observed that the treatment in this experiment
induced no decomposition of the polysuccinimide.</p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="0065">When 50 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 1 and 50 g of water were placed in an
eggplant type flask, the polysuccinimide was fluidized in
five minutes. This fluidized substance of polysuccinimide
was pored into a stainless steel pad and dried with a hot
air drier at a temperature of 160 °C for three hours.</p><p num="0066">When the molecular weight of the polysuccinimide of an
increased molecular weight obtained as described above was
determined by the method mentioned above, it was found to
be 7,148.</p><heading>Example 6</heading><p num="0067">when 50 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 1, 50 g of water, and 5 g of maleic acid
monoamide as a chain extender were placed in an eggplant type
flask, the polysuccinimide was fluidized in five minutes.
This fluidized substance of polysuccinimide was pored into
a stainless steel pad and dried with a hot air drier at a
temperature of 160 °C for three hours.</p><p num="0068">When the molecular weight of the polysuccinimide of an
increased molecular weight obtained as described above was
determined by the method mentioned above, it was found to
be 7,332.</p><heading>Example 7</heading><p num="0069">When 30 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 1, 30 g of water, and 3 g of phosphoric
acid as an acid catalyst were placed in an eggplant type flask,
the polysuccinimide was fluidized in five minutes. This
fluidized substance of polysuccinimide was pored into a
stainless steel pad and dried with a hot air drier at a
temperature of 160 °C for three hours.</p><p num="0070">When the molecular weight of the polysuccinimide of an
increased molecular weight obtained as described above was
determined by the method mentioned above, it was found to
be 7,405.</p><heading>Example 8</heading><p num="0071">When 0 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 1, 30 g of water, 10 g of maleic acid
monoamide as a chain extender, and 3 g of phosphoric acid
as an acid catalyst were placed in an eggplant type flask,
the polysuccinimide was fluidized in five minutes. This
fluidized substance of polysuccinimide was pored into a
stainless steel pad and dried with a hot air drier at a
temperature of 160 °C for three hours. </p><p num="0072">When the molecular weight of the polysuccinimide of an
increased molecular weight obtained as described above was
determined by the method mentioned above, it was found to
be 8,509.</p><heading>Example 9</heading><p num="0073">A slurry was prepared by thoroughly mixing 30 g of the
polysuccinimide powder obtained in Preparation Example 3
with 20 g of water. Then, the resultant slurry was placed
in Laboplastomill™ (produced by TOYO SEIKI SEISAKU-SHO,
LTD.) of 30 ml in an inner volume and reacted at 260 °C for
4 hours while stirred (rotation number of rotor : 50 rpm).
The molecular weight of the resultant product was determined
by the method mentioned above, it was found to be 4,290.</p><heading>Example 10</heading><p num="0074">A slurry was prepared by thoroughly mixing 20 g of the
polysuccinimide powder obtained in Preparation Example 3
with 15 g of water, 5 g of L-aspartic acid as a chain extender
and 5 g of an aqueous 85% phosphoric acid solution as an acid
catalyst. Then, the resultant slurry was placed in
Laboplastomill™ (produced by TOYO SEIKI SEISAKU-SHO, LTD.)
of 30 ml in an inner volume and reacted at 230 °C for 0.5 hour
while stirred (rotation number of rotor : 50 rpm). The
molecular weight of the resultant product was determined by
the method mentioned above, it was found to be 4,620.</p><heading>Control 1</heading><p num="0075">5 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 2 was placed in a beaker and heated with
a hot air drier at a temperature of 205 °C for 2 hours. The
hot compound was cooled to obtain a powdery polysuccinimide
having a molecular weight of 9,700.</p><heading>Example 11</heading><p num="0076">5 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in 
Preparation Example 2 and 2.5 g of water were placed in a
beaker and heated with a hot air drier at a temperature of
205 °C for 2 hours. The hot compound was cooled to obtain
a bulky polysuccinimide having a molecular weight of 10,010.</p><heading>Example 12</heading><p num="0077">5 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 2 and 5 g of water were placed in a beaker
and heated with a hot air drier at a temperature of 205 °C
for 2 hours. The hot compound was cooled to obtain a bulky
polysuccinimide having a molecular weight of 11,140.</p><heading>Example 13</heading><p num="0078">5 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 2 and 10 g of water were placed in a beaker
and heated with a hot air drier at a temperature of 205 °C
for 2 hours. The hot compound was cooled to obtain a bulky
polysuccinimide having a molecular weight of 11,800.</p><heading>Example 14</heading><p num="0079">5 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 2, 5 g of the polysuccinimide as a chain
extender obtained in Example 13 and 10 g of water were placed
in a beaker and heated with a hot air drier at a temperature
of 205 °C for 2 hours. The hot compound was cooled to obtain
a bulky polysuccinimide having a molecular weight of 25,994.</p><heading>Example 15</heading><p num="0080">when 10 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 2 and 10 g of a mixed solvent of 5 g of
water and 5 g of ethanol were placed in an eggplant type flask
and heated on a hot oil bath at 130 °C, the system assumed
a homogeneously dissolved state in about 6 minutes to afford
a homogeneous fluidized substance of polysuccinimide. Then,
this fluidized substance of polysuccinimide was swept with
a current of air to expel a small amount (about 5 g) of water 
and adjust the viscosity thereof properly (about 10 Pa·sec).
A sheet-like molded product having a thickness of about 3
mm was obtained by following the procedure of Example 1 while
using the polysuccinimide fluid of properly adjusted
viscosity instead.</p><p num="0081">When the molecular weight of the polysuccinimide thus
obtained was determined by the method mentioned above, it
was found to be 9,120.</p><heading>Example 16</heading><p num="0082">When 10 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 2 and 10 g of a mixed solvent of 5 g of
water and 5 g of ethyl acetate were placed in an eggplant
type flask and heated on a hot oil bath at 130 °C, the system
assumed a homogeneously dissolved state in about 6 minutes
to afford a homogeneous fluidized substance of
polysuccinimide. Then, this fluidized substance of
polysuccinimide was swept with a current of air to expel a
small amount (about 5 g) of water and adjust the viscosity
thereof properly (about 10 Pa·sec). A sheet-like molded
product having a thickness of about 3 mm was obtained by
following the procedure of Example 1 while using the
polysuccinimide fluid of properly adjusted viscosity
instead.</p><p num="0083">When the molecular weight of the polysuccinimide thus
obtained was determined by the method mentioned above, it
was found to be 9,410.</p><heading>Example 17</heading><p num="0084">When 10 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 2 and 10 g of a mixed solvent of 5 g of
water and 5 g of toluene were placed in an eggplant type flask
and heated on a hot water bath at 130 °C, the system assumed
a homogeneously dissolved state in about 6 minutes to afford 
a homogeneous fluidized substance of polysuccinimide. Then,
this fluidized substance of polysuccinimide was swept with
a current of air to expel a small amount (about 5 g) of water
and adjust the viscosity thereof properly (about 10 Pa·sec).
A sheet-like molded product having a thickness of about 3
mm was obtained by following the procedure of Example 1 while
using the polysuccinimide fluid of properly adjusted
viscosity instead.</p><p num="0085">When the molecular weight of the polysuccinimide thus
obtained was determined by the method mentioned above, it
was found to be 8,980.</p><heading>Example 18</heading><p num="0086">15 g of the polysuccinimide powder obtained in
Preparation Example 2, 5 g of water and 5 g of polyethylene
succinate as a molding auxiliary were placed in
Laboplastomill™ (produced by TOYO SEIKI SEISAKU-SHO, LTD.)
of 30 ml in an inner volume and reacted at 230 °C for 0.5 hour
while stirred (rotation number of rotor : 50 rpm), to obtain
a bulky product. Since the bulky product thus obtained was
insoluble in the solvent, the molecular weight thereof could
not be determined, but it was weighed to find 20 g, indicating
no change in the weight of the polysuccinimide and the molding
auxiliary as the raw materials. It is, therefore, observed
that the treatment in this experiment induced no
decomposition of the polysuccinimide.</p><p num="0087">The results of Examples 5 to 18 and Control 1 were
summarized in Table 1 below. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Example</entry><entry align="center">Molecular weight of polysuccinimide as raw material</entry><entry align="center">Chain extender</entry><entry align="center">Acid catalyst</entry><entry align="center">Molecular weight of produced polysuccinimide</entry></row><row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">6720</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">7148</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">6720</entry><entry align="center">Maleic acid monoamide</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">7332</entry></row><row><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">6720</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">Phosphoric acid</entry><entry align="center">7405</entry></row><row><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">6720</entry><entry align="center">Maleic acid monoxide</entry><entry align="center">Phosphoric acid</entry><entry align="center">8509</entry></row><row><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="center">3950</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">4290</entry></row><row><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">3950</entry><entry align="center">L-aspartic acid</entry><entry align="center">Phosphoric acid</entry><entry align="center">4620</entry></row><row><entry align="center">11</entry><entry align="center">8960</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">10010</entry></row><row><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">8960</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">11140</entry></row><row><entry align="center">13</entry><entry align="center">8960</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">11800</entry></row><row><entry align="center">14</entry><entry align="center">8960</entry><entry align="center">Polysuccin imide</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">25994</entry></row><row><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">8960</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">9120</entry></row><row><entry align="center">16</entry><entry align="center">8960</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">9410</entry></row><row><entry align="center">17</entry><entry align="center">8960</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">8980</entry></row><row><entry align="center">18</entry><entry align="center">8960</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Control 1</entry><entry align="center">8960</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">9700</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0088">The results of Table 1 indicate that when
polysuccinimide was heated in the presence of both a chain
extender and an acid catalyst, the increase of molecular
weight of the polysuccinimide as the raw material could be
significantly attained as compared with the case of using
only either of the additives or the case of omitting the use.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for the molding of a polymer which glass
transition temperature (Tg) can not be determined, which
method comprises heating and melting said polymer in the
presence of a solvent having a low boiling point and a high
dielectric constant ratio and then molding the resultant
molten product.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1, wherein said polymer
is a polysuccinimide based polymer and/or copolymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method according to claim 1 or 2, wherein said
solvent has a boiling temperature in the range of 50° to 150
°C and a dielectric constant ratio at 20 °C of not less than
20.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A method according to claim 3, wherein said solvent
is water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 4, wherein
the heating and melting process is carried out in the presence
of a chain extender.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 1 to 5, wherein
the heating and melting process is carried out in the presence
of an acid catalyst.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method for the production of a polysuccinimide based
polymer and/or polysuccinimide based copolymer of an
increased molecular weight, which method comprises heating
said polysuccinimide based polymer and/or polysuccinimide
based copolymer in the presence of a chain extender and a
solvent having a low boiling temperature and a high high
dielectric constant ratio.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A method according to claim 7, wherein said solvent
has a boiling temperature in the range of 50° to 150 °C and
a dielectric constant ratio at 20 °C of not less than 20.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method according to claim 8, wherein said solvent
is water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A method according to any one of claims 7 to 9, wherein
the heating is carried out additionally in the presence of
an acid catalyst.</claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="173" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="268" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="175" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="266" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90020001" orientation="portrait" wi="175" status="new" file="90020001.tif" he="265" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90030001" orientation="portrait" wi="178" status="new" file="90030001.tif" he="267" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>