<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1072268-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1072268" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="5176887" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010131"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1072268-A1" status="new" fvid="23052450"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1072268</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010131</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-98955312-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>98955312</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981124</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="CN-97122790-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>CN</country><doc-number>97122790</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19971124</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="CN-9800277-W" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>CN</country><doc-number>9800277</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>19981124</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   9/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K   9/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/715       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  31/715       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K  31/7004</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K  31/70B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K  31/70J</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K  31/715</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K   9/00M8</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">PHARMAZEUTISCHE ZUSAMMENSETZUNG ZUR STIMULIERUNG DES WACHSTUMS VON GRAM-POSITIVEN BAZILLEN UND ZUR ERHÖHUNG DER AZIDITÄT DER VAGINA UND IHRE VERWENDUNG</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">PHARMACEUTICAL FORMULATION FOR STIMULATING THE GROWTH OF GRAM-POSITIVE BACILLI AND INCREASING THE ACIDITY IN VAGINA AND THE USE THEREOF</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">FORMULATION PHARMACEUTIQUE DE STIMULATION DE LA CROISSANCE DE BACILLES GRAM POSITIF ET D'AUGMENTATION DE L'ACIDITE DU VAGIN ET SON UTILISATION</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0242459-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0242459</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3860707-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3860707</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5518733-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5518733</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1989005645-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1989005645</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1993014773-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1993014773</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>GUIRAUD M R:  "LE TRAITEMENT DES VULVO-VAGINITES" BORDEAUX MEDICAL, BORDEAUX MEDICAL, BORDEAUX, FR, vol. 11, no. 16, June 1978 (1978-06), pages 1393-1400, XP008016948 ISSN: 0021-7867</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>KAPLAN B ET AL:  "Single-dose systemic oral fluconazole for the treatment of vaginal candidiasis." INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF GYNECOLOGY &amp; OBSTETRICS, vol. 57, no. 3, 1997, pages 281-286, XP002243935 ISSN: 0020-7292</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>See also references of WO     9926635A1</text><sources><source name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ZENG ZHONGMING</name><address><country>CN</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ZENG, ZHONGMING</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Zeng, Zhongming</last-name><address><street>Nanshan Hospital, Nanshan District, Nantou</street><city>Shenzhen City, Guangdong Province 518052</city><country>CN</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ZENG ZHONGMING</name><address><country>CN</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ZENG, ZHONGMING</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ZENG, ZHONGMING</last-name><address><street>Nanshan Hospital, Nanshan District, Nantou</street><city>Shenzhen City, Guangdong Province 518052</city><country>CN</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Daniels, Jeffrey Nicholas</last-name><address><street>Page White &amp;amp; Farrer 54 Doughty Street</street><city>London WC1N 2LS</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><pct-or-regional-filing-data ucid="CN-9800277-W" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>CN</country><doc-number>9800277</doc-number><kind>W</kind></document-id></pct-or-regional-filing-data><pct-or-regional-publishing-data ucid="WO-1999026635-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999026635</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>19990603</date></document-id></pct-or-regional-publishing-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention relates to a pharmaceutical formulation for stimulating the growth of gram-positive bacilli and
increasing the acidity in the vagina which comprises sucrose and/or maltose, to the use of sucrose and/or maltose in preparing the
pharmaceutical formulation for stimulating the growth of gram-positive bacilli and increasing the acidity in the vagina, in
particular to a method for stimulating the growth of gram-positive bacilli and increasing the acidity in the vagina, treating the
reduction of gram-positive bacilli and the lowness of acidity in vagina as well as the vaginitis and the disturbance of vaginal
bacterioflora accompanying the reduction of gram-positive bacilli, especially bacterial vaginal disease, which applies sucrose
and/or maltose.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to pharmaceutical compositions containing saccharides as
active ingredients for promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli and increasing
the acidity in the vagina, to the use of particular saccharides in the preparation of
compositions for promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli and increasing the
acidity in the vagina, and especially to a method of promoting the growth of Gram-positive
bacilli and increasing the acidity in the vagina, treating decreased levels of
Gram-positive bacilli and decreased levels of acidity in the vagina, treating
vaginitis and disturbances of the vaginal bacterial flora accompanying the reduction
of Gram-positive bacilli, especially bacterial vaginosis.</p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0002">High acidity in female vagina is one important anti-infective mechanism of the
vagina and is of great significance for vaginal health. Lactobacilli and other Gram-positive
bacilli that can produce and resist acids serve an important role in
maintaining the normal acidity in the vagina by keeping the vaginal pH value in the
range from 4.0 to 4.6. They are the physiological bacterial flora of vagina, whereas
Gram-negative bacilli, Gram-negative cocci, and Gram-positive cocci are relatively
less abundant in the healthy vagina.</p><p num="0003">When the Gram-positive bacilli are reduced or disappear in vagina, vaginal pH
value rises and disturbance of vaginal bacterial flora results from abnormal
increases of Gram-negative bacilli, Gram-positive cocci and Gram-negative cocci,
which can cause harm to the human body and lead to a range of diseases. The most
typical condition resulting from altered vaginal flora is bacterial vaginosis (BV).
BV is characterized by the reduction or even disappearance of Lactobacillus and
other Gram-positive bacilli in the vagina, accompanied by decreased acidity (pH
value&gt;4.6) in the vagina, and abnormal increases of such bacteria as Gram-negative
bacilli including Gardnerella, Bacteroides and motile-curved bacilli; Gram-negative
cocci such as Veillonella; and Gram-positive cocci such as Streptococcus. Such
changes in the bacterial flora can cause vaginal secretions to exhibit an unpleasant
odor, and may be associated with pruritus of vulva, and symptoms. In addition, BV 
may also be related to IUGR [1], PTL, PROM [2], abortion, and obstetric infections
such as chorio-amnionitis, puerperal endometritis, vaginal wall phlegmon after
hysterectomy, female upper genital tract infection (salpingitis), and urinary
infection, etc. [3]. A high rate of morbidity is associated with vaginal bacterial flora
disturbance. According to one report, about 45% or more vaginitis cases result
from disturbance of vaginal bacterial flora [3], and 4-15% of American female
students in universities suffer from bacterial vaginosis [4], which has led to serious
compromise to health and quality of life.</p><p num="0004">There are few options for treatment of reduced Gram-positive bacilli colonization,
decreased vaginal acidity, and related disturbances of vaginal bacterial flora,
vaginitis, and bacterial vaginosis. Therapeutic options currently include:
<sl><li>1) Antibacterial drugs which are used to suppress the growth of Gram-negative
bacilli and other abnormal bacteria. These most commonly include clindamycin
and metronidazole [5-6]. These drugs suppress the bacteria that are abnormally
increased in the vagina but may also affect the Gram-positive bacilli. After
administration of these drugs, the Gram-positive bacilli (lactobacilli) can not be
restored very well, and it is very difficult to lower the pH value in the vagina to
normal level.</li><li>2) Lactic acid-containing pharmaceutical compositions. Vaginal secretions from
patients suffering from bacterial vaginosis have elevated pH values. Swedish
researchers used lactic acid gel for the improvement and recovery of the low-acidity
conditions in vagina, and reported that this treatment can restore the Gram-positive
bacilli (lactobacilli) in the vaginas of some of the patients [7]. But the
study also showed that the lactic acid pharmaceutical preparation is less effective
than the antibacterial drugs [8].</li><li>3) Lactobacillus preparations. Most of the Gram-positive bacilli in vagina are
lactobacillus. If there is disturbance of vaginal bacterial flora, the lactobacilli will
be reduced or disappear, and Gram-negative bacilli, Gram-negative, and Gram-positive
cocci, will increase. The Gram-positive bacilli in the vagina of some
patients can be restored by directly adding lactobacilli in the vagina [9]. However,
stable colonization is generally not achieved. Moreover, it is difficult to maintain
viability of the lactobacillus preparations during storage, with viable counts in such
preparations decreasing during storage, compromising their useful shelf life [10].</li></sl></p><p num="0005">The international Patent Application WO94/02148 discloses a pharmaceutical
compositions for treating vulvitis and vulvovaginitis, and indicates that such
compositions can promote restoration of vaginal epithelium tissues while
alleviating the symptoms. Its preferred compositions comprises 7 to 8 active
substances. Some preferred compositions may contain 3.0-15.0% (by
weight/volume) lactose or glucose. As mentioned in page 5 lines 8-10 of the 
published specification, the lactose or glucose contained in these compositions is
used as carbon source. But this application does not mention that saccharides can
be used solely as the effective component for treating vulvitis and vulvovaginitis,
and nor does it disclose explicitly or implicitly that the disclosed compositions can
stimulate the growth of Gram-positive bacilli in vagina. Furthermore, it does not
indicate that any other kinds of sugar can be used as active components of a
composition for treating related vaginal diseases. Besides, as mentioned in page 5
lines 17-18 of the specification, this application emphasizes that it is important for
the pH value of the compositions be between 2 and 3.5.</p><p num="0006">The U.S. Patent 3,860,707 teaches a method for treating trichomonal vaginitis and
monilial vaginitis. This method comprises administering lactulose into the vagina.
This patent also indicates that lactulose can be administered after being mixed with
some carriers such as glucose, lactose and galactose, wherein lactulose is required
to have a concentration as high as 50%, and the mixture also contains 5% lactose,
8% galactose as carriers, as mentioned in column 1 lines 51-55 and column 5 lines
1-5 of the patent specification. The quantity of lactulose is 4-10 grams administered
with each dose which is taken once or twice daily, as shown in Column 4 Lines 63-66
of the specification. But this patent does not describe the treatment effectiveness
on bacterial vaginosis or other vaginal diseases different from monilial vaginitis,
nor does it suggest that the lactulose of low or medium concentration (2.5-17%)
and small dosage (daily total amount 0.24-2.1 grams) would be able to stimulate
the growth of Gram-positive bacillus and increase the acidity of the vagina.
Furthermore, it fails to indicate whether any saccharide other than lactulose has
treatment effects.</p><p num="0007">European Patent Application EP-A-0257007 discloses a pharmaceutical
composition containing lactic acid and buffering substances and substrate to
support growth of lactobacillus, which can be used to improve micro-environment
in vagina and suppress the growth of harmful bacteria in the vagina, so as to
facilitate the growth of lactobacilli. This patent application discloses that glycogen
or lactose can be used as the said substrate. But as mentioned in Column 6 Line
10-14 of the specification, the main ingredient of this composition is lactic acid.
The lactic acid and the glycogen and/or lactose are incorporated in a ratio by weight
of from 20:1 down to 500:1, and the content of glycogen and/or lactose is only 0.1-0.166%(W/V).
It also stresses that the pH value of the pharmaceutical composition
should be adjusted to 3.5 to 4.0, which is very important. The in vitro experimental
results disclosed in this application show that this composition can effectively and
selectively kill pathogenic bacteria, and lactobacilli can survive in this composition
for a longer time than the pathogenic microorganisms. But no test in vitro or vivo
shows that this composition can stimulate the growth of lactobacilli or produce
acids. Nor does this application mention the treatment effect of glycogen or lactose
or any other saccharides when they are used separately as active ingredients. </p><p num="0008">GB2112285A discloses a lotion composition for cleaning the vagina. It is a
buffering liquid comprising acetic acid or lactic acid plus sodium acetate with a pH
value of 5.71 to 6.2 as shown in the examples. It also contains nutrients to support
the growth of lactobacillus [1-2 % (W/V) glucose and unsaturated fatty acid]. It
also generally mentions inclusion of mono- and/or disaccharides. The main
therapeutic mechanism of this composition is that the buffering lotion comprising
acetic acid or lactic acid plus sodium acetate can selectively suppress pathogens
and not suppress lactobacilli. As shown in claims 2 and 3 and the in vitro test data
of this application, this lotion can effectively suppress many kinds of pathogens,
and lactobacilli survive in this composition for a longer time. No data from test in
vitro or vivo indicates that this lotion has an activity of promoting the growth of
lactobacilli and producing acid, nor does it indicate the treatment effect of glucose
or any other sugar when used separately as active ingredients. This application
teaches that lactobacilli regulate pH value in vagina to about 5.8, as shown in Page
1 Lines 20-23 of the specification, which is strongly contradicted by most
knowledgeable investigators.</p><p num="0009">The above-mentioned pharmaceutical compositions disclosed in patent applications
EP-A-0257007 and GB2112285A which contain lactic acid, acetic acid and other
selective inhibitors as main active ingredients have strong suppressive action on
pathogens but no explicit suppressive action on lactobacilli, although they may
indirectly facilitate the growth of vaginal lactobacilli. These compositions
themselves, however, cannot directly promote significant growth of lactobacilli,
and only regulate vaginal acidity for a short time. Therefore, it remains very
difficult to restore the physiological conditions dominated by the Gram-positive
bacillus-flora and to restore the vaginal acidity to its normal value.</p><p num="0010">The object of the present invention is to provide a composition for promoting the
growth of Gram-positive bacilli and the production of acids, and thus increase the
acidity in the vagina. Another object of the present invention is to provide a
method by using such composition for reversing the reduction of Gram-positive
bacilli, lack of vaginal acidity and treating related vaginal diseases.</p><p num="0011">In order to seek a composition which is effective in promoting the growth of Gram-positive
bacilli, producing acid, and enhancing the acidity in the vagina, the
inventor has conducted an extensive study, performed tests by using various
pharmaceutical compositions known in the prior art, and has not found any
compositions promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli among the existing
compositions. After repeated tests and intensive study, the inventor has found very
surprisingly that sucrose and maltose both have a strong effect in promoting the
growth of Gram-positive bacilli and producing acids if they are presented in a
concentration and at a pH value in specific ranges. Combined in vitro culturing
experiments show that the two saccharides can stimulate the growth of Gram-positive 
bacilli, increasing their numbers significantly. To our surprise, although pH
values above 4.6 in vagina are considered un-physiologic, and most of state-of-the-art
technologies stress that the pharmaceutical compositions used in vagina must
have a pH value equal to 4.0 or below, the inventor has discovered that, if they have
pH value between 4.1 and 7.2, and especially above pH 5.0, sucrose and maltose
can stimulate the growth of Gram-positive bacilli of women vagina and the
production of acid, and are able to decrease the pH value in vagina to less than 4.6.
However, if they have pH values of 4.0 or less, they do not exert significant
growth-promoting effects on Gram-positive bacilli nor upon acid production and
the pH of the vagina can rarely be reduced to below 4.6. Based on the above
discoveries and further study, the inventor has completed the present invention.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0012">The present invention provides a water-based pharmaceutical composition for
promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli and increasing the acidity in the
vagina comprising, based on the volume of the composition, 2.5% to 17% (W/V) of
sucrose and/or maltose and optionally one or more saccharides selected from the
group consisted of glucose, fructose, galactose, mannose, lactose, lactulose,
mycose, cellobiose, melibiose, melitose, malto-oligosaccharide, iso-malto-oligosaccharide
and oligo-fructose, dextrin, starch and glycogen, at pH-value of
4.1-7.2 adjusted with pharmaceutically acceptable acid or alkali, optionally a
pharmaceutically acceptable viscous base, and optionally an effective amount of
anti-fungal and/or an anti-bacterial agents.</p><p num="0013">The invention also provides a use of sucrose and/or maltose as active ingredient in
the preparation of pharmaceutical compositions for promoting the growth of Gram-positive
bacilli and increasing the acidity in the vagina.</p><p num="0014">The invention also relates to a method for promoting the growth of Gram-positive
bacilli and increasing the acidity in the vagina, comprising administering to the
subject in need of such treatment an therapeutically effective amount of the
pharmaceutical composition according to the present invention.</p><p num="0015">The above-mentioned pharmaceutical composition, use and method of treatment
according to the invention are useful for the reversal of the reduced numbers of
vaginal Gram-positive bacilli, decreased vaginal acidity, as well as for treating
vaginitis and the disturbance of vaginal bacterial flora accompanied with the
reduction in numbers of Gram-positive bacilli, especially bacterial vaginosis.</p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0016">As mentioned above, this invention relates to water-based pharmaceutical
compositions with pH values between 4.1 and 7.2 intended to promote the growth
of Gram-positive bacilli and enhance vaginal acidity, and which contains 2.5-17%
(W/V) of one or more of such saccharides as defined above.</p><p num="0017">The compositions according to the present invention may contain one or a mixture
of two or several of such saccharides as defined above. Any hexose used in the
invention is of D-type. Starch used in the invention may be amylose or
amylopectin. The preferred saccharides are those having low price and abundant
sources.</p><p num="0018">According to this invention, the pharmaceutical composition contains a total
content of 2.5-17% (W/V) of saccharides, especially 2.5-16% (W/V), preferably 8-14%
(W/V), more preferably 10-13% (W/V), and most preferably 10-12% (W/V).
However, the content of the disaccharides other than sucrose and maltose mixed
with sucrose and/or maltose must not exceed [(17- content of sucrose and/or
maltose)%(W/V)]. The maximum content of hexoses mixed with sucrose and/or
maltose should be less than [0.42 X (17 - disaccharides content) % (W/V)].</p><p num="0019">The weight/volume content (W/V) mentioned in the context of this application
refers to the grams of the specified component in 100 milliliters of the composition.</p><p num="0020">The compositions formulated according to the preferred contents of saccharides axe
useful for reating the patients with any vaginal illness states, especially with severe
illness (with pH value of vaginal secretion greater than 5.0, and when the vaginal
Gram smear proves that there are few or no Gram-positive bacilli). The
compositions with a content of saccharides below 8% (W/V) are applicable to the
patients suffering from mild diseases (with a vaginal pH value of greater than 4.6,
and the vaginal Gram smear proves that there are Gram-positive bacilli, but in
which the Gram positive bacilli are fewer in number than the Gram-negative
bacilli, Gram-negative cocci, or Gram-positive cocci).</p><p num="0021">The pH value of the pharmaceutical compositions of this invention is between 4.1
and 7.2, with the optimum pH value between 4.5 and 6.5. The pH value of these
compositions can be adjusted by adding any pharmaceutically acceptable acid or
alkali, of which the preferred choices are acetic acid, lactic acid, or sodium
hydroxide. The nature and concentration of such acid or alkali can be readily
determined by a person skilled in the art.</p><p num="0022">According to this invention, the composition may contain an viscous base. One
example of such base is Xanthan Gum with concentration of 1.0-2.2% (W/V), and
preferably of 1.4-2.0% (W/V). Xanthan Gum is able to keep the sugar in uniform
contact with vaginal mucosa and retain the product within the vaginal vault for a
long time due to its high adherence and stability against changes of temperature and 
pH values, thus permit the compositions to promote the growth of Gram-positive
bacilli and increasing the production of acid in vagina.</p><p num="0023">The composition can also be formulated into gel form or ointment with other
suitable viscous carrier bases, auxiliaries well known to a person skilled in the art.</p><p num="0024">According to this invention, the composition also may not contain viscous base, it
may be administered by means of intravaginal tampon saturated with the liquid
composition. The intravaginal tampon may be composed of cotton ball, gauze ball,
ribbon gauze, etc. In this embodiment, the composition according to the present
invention can also stimulate the growth of Gram-positive bacilli and increase the
acidity in the vagina. The preferred use of the composition of this invention does
requires that the composition of the invention stay in the vagina for some time
before it can stimulate the growth of Gram-positive bacilli and produce vaginal
acidity in the vagina. Therefore as a lotion without a viscous base, the composition
can not exhibit its therapeutic effect very well.</p><p num="0025">The saccharide(s) is/are the essential basic active components of the composition of
the invention, and can fulfill the object of this invention when used with suitable
pharmaceutically acceptable carriers. But these saccharides can produce a better
treatment effect if it is combined with minor amount of amino-acid, vitamin or
other similar substances, or yeast extract rich in amino-acids and vitamins. The
vaginal secretion naturally contains sufficient amino-acids and vitamins. Such
amino-acids or vitamins are not available in conventional in vitro experiments and
should be added when in vitro experiments are carried out for the composition of
the invention.</p><p num="0026">The composition of the invention may also contain one or more anti-fungal agents
in an effective amount, and may be used for the control of possible increased fungal
growth. The anti-fungal agents may include but are not limited to ketoconazole,
terconazole, itraconazole and fluconazole.</p><p num="0027">The composition of the invention may also contain one or more anti-bacterial
agents that can suppress or kill Gram-negative bacteria but exert no effect or only
exert slight effect on Gram-positive bacilli. In this embodiment, the composition of
the invention may has an increased efficacy for treating vaginal infection or
inflammation. Such anti-bacterial agents may include, but are not limited to
polymyxin, metronidazole or aztreonam.</p><p num="0028">The composition of the invention can be prepared according to the processes
known to those skilled in the art.</p><p num="0029">If the saccharides used include little or no starch, such saccharide should be mixed
with viscous auxiliary substances homogeneously, and then distilled water is added 
into the mixture, which are then stirred to dissolve the saccharide and swell the
viscous auxiliary substances until a homogeneous viscous gel is formed. If starch is
included, it is sufficient to heat directly the mixture of saccharides and water to
form a paste. In the latter case, viscous auxiliary substances may be added or
not For adjusting the pH to a predetermined value, lactic acid or sodium hydroxide
solution is added prior to sterilization treatment Alternatively, sterilization
treatment is performed first, followed by adjustment of pH. For sterilization,
intermittent sterilization may be used, with the detailed steps described as follows:
sterilizing at 80°C for 30 minutes, keeping at 36°C for 8-12 hours, sterilizing at
80°C for 30 minutes, keeping at 36°C for 8-12 hours and finally sterilizing at 80°C
for 30 minutes. Alternatively, a high-pressure sterilization may be performed for
15-20 minutes at 116°C. A solution of saccharides may also be sterilized by
filtering the solution. Then the sterilized saccharide solution may be added to an
viscous base in the form of gel that has been sterilized at high pressure.</p><p num="0030">The composition of the invention also may be made into a solution by dissolving
the saccharides in water. The solution can be administered to a patient by means of
an intravaginal tampon soaked in it.</p><p num="0031">The composition of this invention uses sugar substances as active ingredients, and
has good stability during storage, but preferably it is stored under refrigeration or in
cool place. The near neutral pH value of the composition is also helpful in
stabilizing the sugar components.</p><p num="0032">The present invention also relates to the use of one or more of such saccharides as
defined above as active ingredients in the preparation of a medicament for
promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli and increasing the acidity in the
vagina. This invention uses D-type hexose, either amylose or amylopectin.</p><p num="0033">The medicament prepared according to the use of the invention can be used for
promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli and increasing the acidity in the
vagina, and reversing decreased numbers of Gram-positive bacilli, diminished
vaginal acidity (pH value above 4.6) as well as treating vaginitis and the
disturbance of vaginal bacterial flora accompanied with the reduction of Gram-positive
bacilli, especially bacterial vaginosis.</p><p num="0034">The experiments in vitro and in vivo have proven that the composition of the
invention can strongly stimulate the growth of Gram-positive bacilli and increase
the acidity in the vagina, and can be used for the reversal of the reduction of Gram-positive
bacilli, diminished vaginal acidity and treatment of vaginitis and the
disturbance of vaginal bacterial flora accompanied with reduction of Gram-positive
bacilli, especially bacterial vaginosis.</p><p num="0035">Therefore, this invention also relates to a method for promoting the growth of 
Gram-positive bacilli and increasing vaginal acidity, reversing the reduction of
Gram-positive bacilli, increasing vaginal acidity and treatment of vaginitis and the
disturbance of vaginal bacterial flora that accompanied with reduction of Gram-positive
bacilli, especially bacterial vaginosis, wherein the subject in need of such
treatment is given a medically-effective amount of the pharmaceutical composition
according to the invention.</p><p num="0036">The administration method of the composition is to administer the composition
locally inside the vagina. The composition of the invention containing a tissue
viscous base or other carriers may be applied directly to the lumen of the vagina. If
the composition of the invention is in the form of a solution, an intravaginal tampon
is soaked in the solution, then the tampon is placed inside the vagina.</p><p num="0037">For the composition and method of treatment according to the invention, the
medicament is administered according to the following dosage. For the
composition of this invention containing 8-14% (W/V) of saccharides as active
ingredients, such composition is applied inside the vagina 1-3 times daily in doses
of 3-5ml, with the total sugar amount controlled to 0.24-2.1 grams daily dosage,
generally applied before sleep at night or after arising in the morning, with an
additional dose applied at noon for a few patients. For the patients suffering from
severely abnormal vaginal bacterial flora and with the pH value of the vaginal
secretion greater than 5.0, and if the vaginal Gram smear shows few or no Gram-positive
bacilli, more extensive treatment is required with the sugar amount above
0.8 grams daily. For the patients having less severe disease with the pH value of
vaginal secretion between 5.0 and 4.6, or if the vaginal Gram smear reveals Gram-positive
bacilli, but in lesser abundance than that of any of Gram-negative bacilli,
Gram-negative cocci, or Gram-positive cocci, a smaller dosage is used and the total
sugar amount is limited to 0.8 grams or less.</p><p num="0038">During treatment with this composition, clinical symptoms may be observed daily
and the vaginal pH value checked for change. Moreover, the vaginal Gram smear
may be performed in order to check the change of bacterial flora and adjust the
treatment accordingly if necessary. Generally, the composition of this invention can
produce remarkable therapeutic effects 1-3 days after beginning of use, with
symptoms improved significantly even disappearing, and pH values in the vagina
reduced to normal levels and the Gram-positive bacilli in the vagina restored to
dominance in the vaginal bacterial flora, at which lime therapy with the
composition should be stopped or the dosage be reduced, or the treatment
continued at a low maintenance dosage.</p><p num="0039">For the method of this invention, the patients are provided with the composition
containing only the saccharides of this invention as active ingredients, or the
composition containing the saccharides, anti-fungal agent and/or anti-bacterial
agent. Alternatively, the composition containing the saccharides of this invention as 
its active ingredients is administered in conjunction with suitable anti-fungal agent
or anti-bacterial agent. For the latter case, the composition of this invention can be
administered simultaneously with the anti-fungal and/or anti-bacterial agent or
before/after the administration of the anti-fungal and/or anti-bacterial agent.</p><p num="0040">After the administration of this composition, the clinical symptoms of patients can
be alleviated quickly, the numbers of Gram-positive bacilli are increased in the
vagina, vaginal acidity is raised with the pH value reduced to 4.0-4.6, while the
Gram-negative bacilli, Gram-negative cocci and other harmful abnormal bacteria
are reduced substantially or even disappear. The composition of this invention is
easy to prepare and to use with reliable effects.</p><heading>Experimental Example 1</heading><p num="0041">Experiment in vitro with the composition of this invention: The effect of the
composition in promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli and the production
of acids.</p><heading>Method:</heading><p num="0042"><sl><li>(1) The preparation of the composition: Sucrose was used to prepare the following
composition according to the method mentioned above: sucrose 10.0%(W/V), yeast
extract 1.0%(W/V), Xanthan gum 1.6%(W/V), pH 5.0; then filled the composition
into the tubes after sterilization, with each tube containing 5 ml, and pre-reduced
for use.</li><li>(2) Specimen suspension: Vaginal secretion was taken from one of the patients
suffering from typical bacterial vaginosis with a cotton swab, then the swab was
washed in 2ml sterilized Trypcase-soy Broth immediately, and thus the specimen
suspension was ready. The vaginal Gram smear showed few Gram-positive bacilli
but an abundance of Gram-negative bacilli, negative cocci and positive cocci.</li><li>(3) The above-mentioned specimen suspension was inoculated immediately into the
tubes containing the above-mentioned composition, 10 microliter for each tube,
mixed homogeneously. The tubes were placed in an incubator for cultivation, at
37°C, anaerobically. Then, culture samples were taken from the tubes at 10 hours
and 24 hours later respectively. The Gram smears of the samples were observed and
the pH values of the samples were measured.</li></sl></p><heading>Results:</heading><p num="0043">As shown in. Table 1, although the Gram smear of the specimen showed few Gram-positive
bacilli, the Gram positive bacilli grew remarkably in the composition of
this invention after specimen suspension inoculated and cultivated. Meanwhile the
pH value of the composition decreased. <img id="img-00110001"  orientation="unknown"  wi="157"  img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="101"/></p><heading>Conclusion:</heading><p num="0044">The composition of this invention has the effect of promoting the growth of Gram-positive
bacilli and the production of the acids.</p><heading>Experiment Example 2</heading><p num="0045">Experiment in vitro with the compositions of this invention: the comparison of the
effects of compositions containing sucrose or maltose, and those continaining other
saccharides in promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli and the production of
acids</p><heading>Method:</heading><p num="0046"><sl><li>(1)The preparation of the compositions: Different saccharides were used
respectively to prepare the following compositions according to the methods
mentioned above: glucose, fructose, galactose, mannose, maltose, sucrose,
lactose, lactulose, mycose, cellobiose, melibiose, melitose, maltooligosaccharide,
isomaltooligosaccharide and fructooligosaccharide, dextrin,
starch, and glycogen:
<sl><li>A. 5% glucose, 1.0% yeast extract 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>B. 5% fructose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>C. 5% galactose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>D. 5% mannose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>E. 10.0% maltose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2; </li><li>F. 10.0% sucrose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>G. 10.0% lactose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>H. 10.0% lactulose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>I. 10.0% cellobiose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>J. 10.0% mycose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>K. 10.0% melibiose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>L. 10.0% melitose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>M. 10.0% maltooligosaccharide, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH
adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>N. 10.0% isomaltooligosaccharide, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH
adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>O. 10.0% fructooligosaccharide, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH
adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>P. 10.0% dextrin, 1.0% yeast extract, 0.5% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>Q. 10.0% starch, 1.0% yeast extract, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>R. 10.0% glycogen, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2.</li></sl></li><li>(2)The preparation of the test tubes: The compositions prepared above were filled
into test tubes, with each tube containing 5 ml, sterilized, and kept until use for
experiment.</li><li>(3)Specimen suspension: Vaginal secretion was taken from one of the patients
suffering from typical bacterial vaginosis with a cotton swab, then the swab was
washed in 2ml sterilized Trypcase-soy Broth immediately, and thus the
specimen suspension was ready. The vaginal Gram smear showed few Gram-positive
bacilli but an abundance of Gram-negative bacilli, negative cocci and
positive cocci.</li><li>(4)The specimen suspension was inoculated immediately into the tubes containing
the above-mentioned compositions, 10 microliter for each tube, mixed
homogeneously. Then the tubes were placed in a candle jar and cultivated at
37°C. After 24 hours and 48 hours' culture, culture samples were taken
respectively from each of the tubes, then the Gram smears of the samples were
observed and the pH values of culture samples were tested.</li></sl></p><heading>Results:</heading><p num="0047"><sl><li>(1)As shown in Table 2, although there was few Gram positive bacilli in the
vaginal secretion specimen, the Gram positive bacilli grew remarkably in the
compositions containing different sugars of this invention after the compositions
were inoculated with specimen suspension and cultivated for 24 hours or 48
hours. Meanwhile the pH values in most of the composition tubes decreased to
different levels. These results indicate that sucrose, maltose, or any other kind of
saccharides compatible to them according to this invention exerts respectively
effect in promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli.</li><li>(2)As shown in Table 2, the fact that the pH values in 10% maltose tube and in 
10% sucrose tube were lower than that of the other tubes after 24 or 48 hours
culture indicates that maltose and sucrose are metabolized rapidly by bacteria.
And maltose and sucrose exert better effect in promoting the growth of Gram-positive
bacilli and the production of acids than that of the other kinds of
oligosaccharides.</li></sl><img id="img-00130001" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="178"/><img id="img-00140001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00140001.tif" inline="no" he="217"/><img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="70"/></p><heading>Conclusion:</heading><p num="0048">The sugar components contained in the compositions of this invention can be
sucrose, maltose or the both or mixtures of sucrose and/or maltose and other
saccharides as defined above.</p><heading>Experiment Example 3</heading><p num="0049">Experiment in vitro with the compositions of this invention: The effects of the
compositions of this invention in promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli
and the production of acids.</p><heading>Methods:</heading><p num="0050"><sl><li>(1)The preparation of the compositions: Maltose and sucrose were used
respectively to prepare the following composition according to the methods
mentioned above:
<sl><li>A. 2.5% maltose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>B. 2.5% sucrose, 1.0 yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li></sl></li><li>(2)The preparation of the test tubes: Compositions as prepared above were filled
into the test tubes, with each tube containing 5 ml, sterilized, and kept until use
for experiment.</li><li>(3)Specimen suspension: Vaginal secretion was taken from one of the patients
suffering from typical bacterial vaginosis with a cotton swab, then the swab was
washed in 2ml sterilized Trypcase-soy Broth immediately, and thus the
specimen suspension was ready. The vaginal Gram smear showed few Gram-positive
bacilli but an abundance of Gram-negative bacilli, negative cocci and
positive cocci.</li><li>(4)The above-mentioned specimen suspension was inoculated immediately into the
tubes containing the above-mentioned compositions, 10 microliter for each tube, 
mixed homogeneously. Then the tubes were placed in a candle jar and cultivated
at 37°C. After 24 hours and 48 hours' culture, culture samples were taken
respectively from each of the tubes, then the Gram smears of the samples were
observed and the pH values of culture samples were tested.</li></sl></p><heading>Results:</heading><p num="0051">As shown in Table 3, although there was few Gram positive bacilli in the vaginal
secretion specimen, the Gram positive bacilli grew in the compositions containing
different sugars of this invention alter the compositions were inoculated with
specimen suspension and cultivated for 24 hours or 48 hours. It indicates that 2.5%
of sucrose and 2.5% of maltose have the effects in promoting the growth of Gram
positive bacilli.
<img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="150" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="56"/></p><heading>Conclusion:</heading><p num="0052">The compositions of this invention containing 2.5% sucrose or maltose exert
certain effects in promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli.</p><heading>Experiment Example 4</heading><p num="0053">Experiment in vitro with the compositions of this invention: effects of the
compositions of this invention in promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli
and the production of acids.</p><heading>Method:</heading><p num="0054"><sl><li>(1)The preparation of the compositions: Maltose and sucrose were used
respectively to prepare the following composition in the methods mentioned
above:
<sl><li>A. 17.0% maltose, 1.0% yeast extract; 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li><li>B. 17.0% sucrose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.2;</li></sl></li><li>(2)The preparation of the test tubes: Compositions prepared above were filled into
the test tubes, with each tube containing 5 ml, sterilized, and kept until use for
experiment. </li><li>(3)Specimen suspension: Vaginal secretion was taken from one of the patients
suffering from typical bacterial vaginosis with a cotton swab, then the swab was
washed in 2ml sterilized Trypcase-soy Broth immediately, and thus the
specimen suspension was ready. The vaginal Gram smear showed few Gram-positive
bacilli but an abundance of Gram-negative bacilli, negative cocci and
positive cocci.</li><li>(4)The above-mentioned specimen suspension was inoculated immediately into the
tubes containing the above-prepared compositions, 10 microliter for each tube,
mixed homogeneously. Then the tubes were placed in a candle jar and cultivated
at 37°C. After 24 hours and 48 hours' culture, culture samples were taken
respectively from each of the tubes, ten the Gram smears of the samples were
observed and the pH values of culture samples were tested.</li> </sl></p><heading>Results:</heading><p num="0055">As shown in Table 4, although there was few Gram positive bacilli in the vaginal
secretion specimen, numerous Gram positive bacilli grew in the compositions of
this invention after the compositions were inoculated with specimen suspension and
cultivated for 24 hours or 48 hours. Meanwhile the pH values of the composition
tubes decreased remarkably. These results indicate that compositions containing
17% of sugars of this invention exert remarkable effect in promoting the growth of
Gram positive bacilli.
<img id="img-00170001" orientation="unknown" wi="156" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00170001.tif" inline="no" he="69"/></p><heading>Conclusion:</heading> <p num="0056">The compositions of this invention containing 17% sucrose or maltose exert effects
in promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli.</p> <heading>Experiment Example 5</heading> <p num="0057">Experiment in vitro with the compositions of this invention: The influence of 
different pH values on the effects of the compositions of this invention on the
growth of Gram-positive bacilli and the production of acids.</p><heading>Method:</heading><p num="0058"><sl><li>(1)The preparation of the compositions: Maltose was used to prepare the following
compositions according to the method mentioned above:
<sl><li>A. 10.0% maltose, 1.0% yeast extract 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 4.4;</li><li>B. 10.0% maltose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 4.8;</li><li>C. 10.0% maltose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 5.1;</li><li>D. 10.0% maltose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 5.4;</li><li>E. 10.0% maltose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 5.8;</li><li>F. 10.0% maltose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.4;</li><li>G. 10.0% maltose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 6.8;</li><li>H. 10.0% maltose, 1.0% yeast extract, 1.6% xanthan gum, pH adjusted to 7.2;</li></sl></li><li>(2)The preparation of the test tubes: Compositions prepared above were filled into
the test tubes, with each tube containing 5 ml, sterilized, and kept until use for
experiments.</li><li>(3)Specimen suspension: Vaginal secretion was taken from one of the patients
suffering from typical bacterial vaginosis with a cotton swab, then the swab was
washed in 2ml sterilized Trypcase-soy Broth immediately, and thus the specimen
suspension was ready. The vaginal Gram smear showed few Gram-positive
bacilli but an abundance of Gram-negative bacilli, negative cocci and positive
cocci.</li><li>(4)The above-mentioned specimen suspension was inoculated immediately into the
tubes containing the above-mentioned compositions, 10 microliter for each tube,
mixed homogeneously. Then the tubes were placed in a candle jar and cultivated
at 37°C. After 24 hours and 48 hours' culture, culture samples were taken
respectively from each of the tubes, then the Gram smears of the samples were
observed and the pH values of culture samples were tested.</li></sl></p><heading>Results:</heading><p num="0059">As shown in Table 5,
<sl><li>(1)When the pH value of the composition of this invention was 4.4, a few of Gram-positive
bacilli grew in the composition alter 48 hours' culture.</li><li>(2)When the pH values of the compositions of this invention were 5.4-7.2, the
Gram-positive bacilli grew very well. Gram positive bacilli grew and the pH
values decreased after 24 hours' culture and the bacilli were numerous and the
pH values decreases to about 4.1 - 4.4 after 48 hours' culture.</li></sl><img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="157" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="185"/></p><heading>Conclusion:</heading><p num="0060">In this in vitro experiment, the compositions of this invention with pH values of
5.4-7.2 exerted stronger effects in promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli.</p><heading>Experiment Example 6:</heading><heading>Case Report</heading><p num="0061">Ms. Jiang, female, aged 30. Her vaginal secretions had exhibited unpleasant fish-odor
accompanying pruritus of vulvae for 2 years. Examined and diagnosed as
"bacterial vaginosis" by the present inventor. The patient was treated with a 
composition containing 12%(W/V) of lactose and having pH value of 5.0. The drug
was intravaginally administered, 3 ml for each time, once a day. After the
treatment continued successively for three days, the pH value of the vaginal
secretions of this patient decreased from 5.4 to 4.6. But the Gram smears showed
that the majority of the bacteria were still Gram-negative bacilli, and there were
also a lot of positive cocci and positive bacilli. Thus, the drug for treatment was
changed to a composition of this invention containing 12%(W/V) of maltose, with
the pH value 5.0. 10 hours after the administration of 3ml of the latter composition,
the pH value of the vaginal secretions of the patient decreased to 3.8. Then the dose
was reduced to 2 ml of the composition for each time, once a day. The pH values of
the vaginal swabs were maintained at normal levels (pH&lt;4.6). Afterwards, the
illness of this patient relapsed after the menstruation several times, and the
abnormal bacterial flora and the decreased vaginal acidity of this patient after the
menstruation restored to normal states by the intravaginal administration of the
composition of this invention containing 12%(W/V) of maltose.</p><heading>Experiment Example 7</heading><p num="0062">Experiment in vivo with the composition of the present invention: The influences
of the composition of this invention on the vaginal bacterial flora of rhesus
macaques.</p><heading>Experimental Method:</heading><p num="0063"><sl><li>(1)Animals: Took the vaginal swabs often female macaques, tested the pH values
and carried out Gram smears examination. The results showed that in eight
rhesus macaques, the pH values of the vaginal swabs were greater than 4.6 and
Gram smears revealed few Gram positive bacilli, a lot of Gram-negative bacilli
and negative cocci, alike the bacterial flora of bacterial vaginosis in human
beings. In the two left rhesus macaques, the pH values of the vaginal swabs
were lower than 4.6 and the bacteria revealed on Gram smears were Gram
positive bacilli, alike the bacterial flora of the normal vaginal bacterial flora of
human beings.</li><li>(2)In the 8 rhesus macaques, the vaginal bacterial flora were the type of bacterial
vaginosis of human beings. 3 of them were excluded from the experiment
because of menstruation. The other 5 rhesus macaques were included in the
experiment.</li><li>(3)Composition: A composition of this invention was used, which contained
12%(W/V) of sucrose, 1%(W/V) of yeast extract, 1.6%(W/V) of xanthan gum
and its' pH value was 5.1.</li><li>(4)Administration: 1 ml of the above-mentioned composition of this invention was
administrated intravaginally , twice a day. When most of the vaginal bacteria
was changed to Gram positive bacilli, the dose was reduced or the treatment 
stopped. In this experiment, 1 macaque received the composition only once, 2
macaques twice, and the other 2 macaques three times.</li><li>(5)Result examination: Took the vaginal swabs before each dosage was
administered to detect the pH values and to perform Gram smears examination.
Thus the change of the vaginal bacterial flora of the macaques was monitored.</li></sl></p><heading>Result:</heading><p num="0064">After the treatment with the composition of the present invention, the vaginal pH
values were reduced to 3.8 ― 4.1 and the vaginal bacterial floras were changed to be
dominated with Gram-positive bacilli in all the five macaques. This result indicates
that the composition of this invention has very strong effects in vivo in promoting
the growth of Gram-positive bacilli and the production of acids.</p><heading>ADVANTAGES OF THIS INVENTION COMPARED TO THE PRIOR ART:</heading><heading>Advantages Compared to Anti-bacterial Treatments:</heading><p num="0065">Anti-bacterial drugs, based on the views of etiology, control the abnormal bacteria
that grow excessively and cause pathological reaction by killing or suppressing
such bacteria. This method has the following shortcomings: (1) After repeated
treatments with anti-bacterial drugs, the bacteria may gain drug-resistances which
may lead to the failure of antibacterial therapy. (2) Anti-bacterial treatment may
result in the superinfection by drug-resistant bacteria. (3) Anti-bacterial drugs may
be allergic to human body and may have other kinds of adverse effects to skin or
vaginal mucous membrane. Compositions containing lactic acid or acetic acid or
other selective bacterial inhibitors as its active ingredients, for example, the
compositions described in the patent applications Nos. GB2112285A and EP-A-0257007,
exert strong prohibition effects on the pathogens and have no remarkable
prohibition effects on lactobacilli. Thus they may exert indirectly the favorable
effects on the growth of lactobacilli in the vagina. The compositions themselves,
however, cannot directly and remarkably promote the growth of lactobacilli in the
vagina. The effects of these compositions in increasing the acidity in the vagina last
only for a short period of time, and it is very hard for the physiological Gram-positive
bacilli to restore and dominate over the vaginal bacterial flora.</p><p num="0066">The compositions of this invention can stimulate the growth of Gram-positive
bacilli and increase acidity in the vagina, and thus suppress Gram-negative bacilli,
Gram negative cocci, and Gram-positive cocci thereby. Seen from above analysis,
the technologies and compositions of this invention actually enhance the natural
physiological anti-disease mechanisms in the vagina and fundamentally avoid and
overcome the disadvantages of the disturbance of vaginal bacterial flora by anti-bacterial
treatment, therefore have remarkable advantages. </p><heading>Advantages Compared to Lactobacilli Preparations:</heading><p num="0067">Firstly, the effects of lactobacilli preparations in the treatment of severe disturbance
of the vaginal bacterial flora, such as typical bacterial vaginosis, are often variable.
Secondly, the lactobacilli preparations are more difficult to produce and store in
addition to its high production cost. The compositions of this invention have a
lower cost of production and longer effective period, and are significantly superior
over the lactobacilli preparations. Moreover, the compositions of this invention
improve the condition of the local micro-habitat in the vagina thus promote the
growth of the endogenous Gram positive bacilli in the vagina. It should be better
than the direct supplement of the exogenous lactobacilli strains.</p><heading>Composition Examples</heading><heading>Example 1:</heading><p num="0068">2.5g of sucrose and 2.0g xanthan gum were mixed homogeneously. Then to the
resultant mixture, some distilled water is added while stirring in order to dissolve
the sugar component and swell the xanthan gum to homogeneous viscous gum. By
adding a suitable amount of lactic acid, the pH of the solution was adjusted to 5.0.
Distilled water was added until the total volume of the solution is equal to 100ml.
The resulting solution is sterilized by means of intermittent sterilization.</p><heading>Example 2:</heading><p num="0069">100ml of the composition in the following formulation was prepared substantially
according to the method as described in Example 1, except that the pH value is
adjusted with 0.5 N sodium hydroxide.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="21"><dt>Sucrose</dt><dd>17.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Yeast extract powder</dt><dd>1.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Xanthan gum</dt><dd>1.5% (W/V)</dd><dt>Distilled water</dt><dd>q.s.</dd><dt>PH</dt><dd>7.2</dd></dl></p><heading>Example 3:</heading><p num="0070">100ml of the composition in the following formulation was prepared substantially
according to the method as described in Example 1.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="21"><dt>Sucrose</dt><dd>12.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Yeast extract powder</dt><dd>1.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Xanthan gum</dt><dd>1.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Distilled water</dt><dd>q.s. </dd><dt>pH</dt><dd>4.1</dd></dl></p><heading>Example 4:</heading><p num="0071">100ml of the composition in the following formulation was prepared substantially
according to the method as described in Example 1.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="21"><dt>Sucrose</dt><dd>4.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Maltose</dt><dd>5.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Fructose</dt><dd>2.0 (W/V)</dd><dt>Histidine</dt><dd>100ppm</dd><dt>Methionine</dt><dd>50.0ppm</dd><dt>Riboflavin</dt><dd>0.2ppm</dd><dt>Thiamine</dt><dd>0.2ppm</dd><dt>Nicotinic acid</dt><dd>0.2ppm</dd><dt>Calcium pantothenate</dt><dd>0.2ppm</dd><dt>Xanthan gum</dt><dd>1.5% (W/V)</dd><dt>Distilled water</dt><dd>q.s.</dd><dt>PH</dt><dd>6.4</dd></dl></p><heading>Example 5:</heading><p num="0072">100ml of the composition in the following formulation was prepared substantially
according to the method as described in Example 1.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="16"><dt>Maltose</dt><dd>2.5% (W/V)</dd><dt>Xanthan gum</dt><dd>1.6% (W/V)</dd><dt>Distilled water</dt><dd>q.s.</dd><dt>PH</dt><dd>6.8</dd></dl></p><heading>Example 6:</heading><p num="0073">100ml of the composition in the following formulation was prepared substantially
according to the method as described in Example 1.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="16"><dt>Maltose</dt><dd>17.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Xanthan gum</dt><dd>1.6% (W/V)</dd><dt>Yeast extract</dt><dd>1.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Distilled water</dt><dd>q.s.</dd><dt>PH</dt><dd>5.4</dd></dl></p><heading>Example 7:</heading><p num="0074">100ml of the composition in the following formulation was prepared substantially
according to the method as described in Example 1.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="16"><dt>Maltose</dt><dd>13.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Yeast extract</dt><dd>1.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Xanthan gum</dt><dd>1.6% (W/V)</dd><dt>Distilled water</dt><dd>q.s.</dd><dt>pH</dt><dd>6.4</dd></dl></p><heading>Example 8:</heading><p num="0075">100ml of the composition in the following formulation was prepared substantially
according to the method as described in Example 1.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="16"><dt>Maltose</dt><dd>10.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Glucose</dt><dd>2.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Yeast extract</dt><dd>1.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Xanthan gum</dt><dd>1.6% (W/V)</dd><dt>Distilled water</dt><dd>q.s.</dd><dt>PH</dt><dd>4.8</dd></dl></p><heading>Example 9:</heading><p num="0076">100ml of the composition in the following formulation was prepared substantially
according to the method as described in Example 1.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="16"><dt>Sucrose</dt><dd>12.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Glucose</dt><dd>1.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Yeast extract</dt><dd>0.5% (W/V)</dd><dt>Xanthan gum</dt><dd>1.7% (W/V)</dd><dt>Distilled water</dt><dd>q.s.</dd><dt>PH</dt><dd>5.6</dd></dl></p><heading>Example 10:</heading><p num="0077">100ml of the composition in the following formulation was prepared substantially
according to the method as described in Example 1.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="21"><dt>Sucrose</dt><dd>10.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Glucose</dt><dd>1.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Histidine</dt><dd>100ppm</dd><dt>Methionine</dt><dd>50.0ppm</dd><dt>Riboflavin</dt><dd>0.2ppm</dd><dt>Thiamine</dt><dd>0.2ppm</dd><dt>Nicotinic acid</dt><dd>0.2ppm</dd><dt>Calcium pantothenate</dt><dd>0.2ppm</dd><dt>Xanthan gum</dt><dd>1.8% (W/V)</dd><dt>Distilled water</dt><dd>q.s.</dd><dt>pH</dt><dd>6.5</dd></dl></p><heading>Example 11:</heading><p num="0078">100ml of the composition in the following formulation was prepared substantially
according to the method as described in Example 1.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="16"><dt>Maltose</dt><dd>10.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Ketoconazole</dt><dd>2.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Yeast extract</dt><dd>1.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Xanthan gum</dt><dd>1.5% (W/V)</dd><dt>Distilled water</dt><dd>q.s.</dd><dt>PH</dt><dd>6.0</dd></dl></p><heading>Example 12:</heading><p num="0079">100ml of the composition in the following formulation was prepared substantially
according to the method as described in Example 1.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="16"><dt>Maltose</dt><dd>9.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Polymyxin E</dt><dd>0.5% (W/V)</dd><dt>Yeast extract</dt><dd>1.0% (W/V)</dd><dt>Xanthan gum</dt><dd>2.2% (W/V)</dd><dt>Distilled water</dt><dd>q.s.</dd><dt>pH</dt><dd>6.3</dd></dl></p><p num="0080">The compositions of this invention are simple in components and can be easily
manufactured at low cost. </p><heading>Reference:</heading><p num="0081"><sl><li>1) German-M et al Genital flora in pregnancy and its association with
intrauterine growth retardation J Clin Microbiol 1994 Sep 32(9) 216 2 8.</li><li>2) McDonald-HM, et al Vaginal infection and preterm labour Br-J-Obstet-Gynaecol
1991 May 98(5) 4 27-35.</li><li>3) Eschenbach.DA, Clin.Infect.Dis. 1993.16(Suppl.4):S282-7.</li><li>4) Thomason JL Bacterial vaginosis current review with indications for
asymptomatic therapy. Am J Obstet Gynecol .1991 16 5 12 10</li><li>5) Stein-GE, et al: Placebo-controlled trial of intravaginal clindamycin 2% cream
for the treatment of bacterial .
vaginosis Ann-Pharmacother. 1993 Nov 27 (11) 13 43-5.</li><li>6) Hillier-SL, et al: Efficacy of intravaginal 0.75% metronidazole gel for the
treatment of bacterial vaginosis. Obstet-Gynecol. 1993 Jun; 81(6): 963-7.</li><li>7) Hoster-E, et al: Treatment of bacterial vaginosis in pregnancy with a lactate gel.
Scand-J-Infect-Dis. 1990; 22(5):625-6.</li><li>8) Boeke-AJ, et al: Effect of lactic acid suppositories compared with oral
metronidazole and placebo in bacterial vaginosis: a randomised clinical trial.
Genitourin-Med. 1993 Oct; 69(5): 388-92.</li><li>9) Hallen-A, et al: Treatment of bacterial vaginosis with lactobacilli. Sex-Transm-Dis.
1992 May-Jun; 19(3):146-8.</li><li>10) Hughes-VL, et al: Microbiologic characteristics of lactobacillus products used
for colonization of the vagina. Obstet-Gynecol. 1990 Feb; 75(2): 244-8.</li></sl></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A water-based pharmaceutical composition for promoting the growth of Gram-positive
bacilli and increasing the acidity in the vagina comprising, based on the
volume of the composition, 2.5% to 17% (W/V) of sucrose and/or maltose and
optionally one or more saccharides selected from the group consisted of glucose,
fructose, galactose, mannose, lactose, lactulose, mycose, cellobiose, melibiose,
melitose, malto-oligosaccharide, iso-malto-oligosaccharide and oligo-fructose,
dextrin, starch and glycogen, at pH-value of 4.1-7.2 adjusted with pharmaceutically
acceptable acid or alkali, optionally a pharmaceutically acceptable viscous base,
and optionally an effective amount of anti-fungal and/or an anti-bacterial agents.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 1, wherein the total amount of saccharides
is equal to 8-14% (W/V).</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 2, wherein the total amount of saccharides
is equal to 10-12% (W/V).</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 1, wherein if other disaccharides are mixed
with sucrose and/or maltose in the composition, the content of such disaccharides is
not greater than [( 17- content of sucrose and/or maltose) % (W/V)].</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 1, wherein the hexose content is less than
[0.42X(17- total content of disaccharides)%(W/V)] if the hexose is mixed with
sucrose and/or maltose in the composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 1, wherein its pH value is from 4.5 to 6.5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 1, wherein it contains 1.0-2.2% (W/V) of
xanthan gum.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 1, wherein it contains no vicous base and is
a solution in which an intravaginal tampon can be soaked.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 1, wherein it also contains an effective
amount of anti-fungal agent</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 9, wherein the anti-fungal agent is selected
from: ketoconazole, terconazole, itraconazole and fluconazole.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 1, wherein it also contains an effective
amount of agent that selectively inhibits Gram-negative bacilli.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The composition according to Claim 11, wherein the anti-bacterial agent is
metronidazole, polymyxin, or aztreonam.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>Use of sucrose or maltose as active ingredients in the preparation of a
composition for promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacillus and increasing the
vaginal acidity.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The use according to Claim 13, where said composition is useful for the
treatment of the reduction of Gram-positive bacilli in vagina and the decrease in
vaginal acidity.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The use according to Claim 13, wherein said composition is useful for the
treatment of vaginitis and the disturbance of vaginal bacterial flora accompanied
with the reduction of Gram-positive bacilli.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The use according to of Claim 13, wherein said composition is useful for the
treatment of bacterial vaginosis.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A method of promoting the growth of Gram-positive bacilli in vagina and
increasing the vaginal acidity comprising administering to a subject in need of such
treatment an therapeutically effective amount of composition according to any one
of claims 1 to 12.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A method of treating the reduction of Gram-positive bacilli in the vagina and
decreased vaginal acidity comprising administering to a subject in need of such
treatment an therapeutically effective amount of composition according to any one
of claims 1 to 12.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A method of treating the vaginitis and the disturbance of vaginal bacterial flora
comprising administering to a subject in need of such treatment an therapeutically
effective amount of composition according to any one of claims 1 to 12.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>A method of treating bacterial vaginosis comprising administering to a subject
in need of such treatment an therapeutically effective amount of composition
according to any one of claims 1 to 12.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>