<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1538221-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1538221" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34610060" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050608"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1538221-A1" status="new" fvid="24363226"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1538221</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050608</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04028280-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04028280</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20041130</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-03027753-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03027753</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031202</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="EP-04028280-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04028280</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20041130</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07H  21/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07H  21/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07H  21/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N  15/09        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N  15/09        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12P  19/00        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12P  19/34        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/68        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/68        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07H  21/00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Molekulare Stäbchen enthaltende Oligonukleotide</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Oligonucleotides containing molecular rods</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Oligonucléotides contenant des bâtons moléculaires</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-20030143616-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20030143616</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5770715-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5770715</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5932711-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5932711</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2003059881-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2003059881</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>SCHWAB ET AL.:  "Molecular Rods. 1. Simple Axial Rods" CHEM REV, vol. 99, no. 7, 1999, pages 1863-1933, XP002278076</text><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HOFFMANN LA ROCHE</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ROCHE DIAGNOSTICS GMBH</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>F.HOFFMANN-LA ROCHE AG</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ROCHE DIAGNOSTICS GMBH</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>F.HOFFMANN-LA ROCHE AG</last-name><address><street>Grenzacherstrasse 124</street><city>4070 Basel</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Roche Diagnostics GmbH</last-name><address><street>Sandhofer Strasse 116</street><city>68305 Mannheim</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HAUBER ALEXANDER</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HEINDL DIETER DR</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>JUNIUS MARTINA DR</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>REISER ASTRID</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TABITI KARIM DR</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HAUBER, ALEXANDER</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HEINDL, DIETER, DR.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>JUNIUS, MARTINA, DR.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>REISER, ASTRID</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TABITI, KARIM, DR.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HAUBER, ALEXANDER</last-name><address><street>Schwalbenweg 2</street><city>82407 Wielenbach</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HEINDL, DIETER, DR.</last-name><address><street>Sternstrasse 4</street><city>82396 Paehl</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>JUNIUS, MARTINA, DR.</last-name><address><street>Hallberger Allee 11</street><city>82327 Tutzing</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>REISER, ASTRID</last-name><address><street>Schleier-Weg 20</street><city>82387 Antdorf</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TABITI, KARIM, DR.</last-name><address><street>Gartenstrasse 26 C</street><city>82343 Poecking</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IS</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The invention is directed to an oligonucleotide comprising a molecular rod,
wherein preferentially the molecular rod covalently connects the 3' end of a first
nucleotide residue with the 5' end of a second nucleotide residue. Such
oligonucleotides are highly advantageous for Real time PCR melting curve analysis.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b><u style="single">Field of invention</u></b></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to the field of chemically modified oligonucleotides.
More precisely, the present invention relates to the field of providing chemically
modified oligonucleotides which can be used as hybridization probes either in real
time PCR or nucleic acid array technology.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Prior art background</u> </b></heading><p num="0002">Amplification of DNA by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) is a technique
fundamental to molecular biology. Nucleic acid analysis by PCR requires sample
preparation, amplification, and product analysis. Although these steps are usually
performed sequentially, amplification and analysis can occur simultaneously. DNA
dyes or fluorescent probes can be added to the PCR mixture before amplification
and used to analyze PCR products during amplification. Sample analysis occurs
concurrently with amplification in the same tube within the same instrument. This
combined approach decreases sample handling, saves time, and greatly reduces the
risk of product contamination for subsequent reactions, as there is no need to
remove the samples from their closed containers for further analysis. The concept
of combining amplification with product analysis has become known as "real time"
PCR. See, for example, U.S. Patent No. 6,174,670.</p><heading><b>Real Time PCR detection formats</b></heading> <p num="0003">In kinetic real time PCR, the formation of PCR products is monitored in each cycle
of the PCR. The amplification is usually measured in thermocyclers which have
additional devices for measuring fluorescence signals during the amplification
reaction.</p> <p num="0004">DNA binding dye formate: Since the amount of double stranded amplification
product usually exceeds the amount of nucleic acid originally present in the sample
to be analyzed, double-stranded DNA specific dyes may be used, which upon
excitation with an appropriate wavelength show enhanced fluorescence only if they 
are bound to double-stranded DNA. Preferably, only those dyes may be used which
like SybrGreenI I, for example, do not affect the efficiency of the PCR reaction.</p> <p num="0005">All other fomates known in the art require the design of a fluorescent labeled
Hybridization Probe which only emits fluorescence upon binding to its target
nucleic acid.</p><p num="0006">TaqMan probes: A single-stranded Hybridization Probe is labeled with two
components. When the first component is excited with light of a suitable
wavelength, the absorbed energy is transferred to the second component, the so-called
quencher, according to the principle of fluorescence resonance energy
transfer. During the annealing step of the PCR reaction, the hybridization probe
binds to the target DNA and is degraded by the 5'-3' exonuclease activity of the Taq
Polymerase during the subsequent elongation phase. As a result the excited
fluorescent component and the quencher are spatially separated from one another
and thus a fluorescence emission of the first component can be measured. TaqMan
probe assays are disclosed in detail in US 5,210,015, US 5,538,848, and US
5,487,972. TaqMan hybridization probes and reagent mixtures are disclosed in US
5,804,375.</p><p num="0007">Molecular Beacons: These hybridization probes are also labeled with a first
component and with a quencher, the labels preferably being located at both ends of
the probe. As a result of the secondary structure of the probe, both components are
in spatial vicinity in solution. After hybridization to the target nucleic acids both
components are separated from one another such that after excitation with light of
a suitable wavelength the fluorescence emission of the first component can be
measured (US 5,118,801). Molecular beacons can be used for melting curve analysis
in order to identify specific alleles or polymorphisms (see below).</p><p num="0008">FRET hybridization probes: The FRET Hybridization Probe test format is especially
useful for all kinds of homogenous hybridization assays (Matthews, J.A., and
Kricka, L.J. , Analytical Biochemistry 169 (1988) 1-25. It is characterized by two
single-stranded hybridization probes which are used simultaneously and are
complementary to adjacent sites of the same strand of the amplified target nucleic
acid. Both probes are labeled with different fluorescent components. When excited
with light of a suitable wavelength, a first component transfers the absorbed energy
to the second component according to the principle of fluorescence resonance 
energy transfer such that a fluorescence emission of the second component can be
measured when both hybridization probes bind to adjacent positions of the target
molecule to be detected.</p><p num="0009">When annealed to the target sequence, the hybridization probes must sit very close
to each other, in a head to tail arrangement. Usually, the gap between the labeled 3'
end of the first probe and the labeled 5' end or the second probe is as small as
possible, i.e. 1-5 bases. This allows for a close vicinity of the FRET donor compound
and the FRET acceptor compound, which is typically 10-100 Angstroem.</p><p num="0010">Alternatively to monitoring the increase in fluorescence of the FRET acceptor
component, it is also possible to monitor fluorescence decrease of the FRET donor
component as a quantitative measurement of hybridization event.</p><p num="0011">In particular, the FRET Hybridization Probe format may be used in real time PCR,
in order to detect the amplified target DNA. Among all detection formats known in
the art of real time PCR, the FRET-Hybridization Probe format has been proven to
be highly sensitive, exact and reliable (WO 97/46707; WO 97/46712; WO
97/46714). Yet, the design of appropriate FRET Hybridization Probe sequences may
sometimes be limited by the special characteristics of the target nucleic acid
sequence to be detected.</p><p num="0012">As an alternative to the usage of two FRET hybridization probes, it is also possible
to use a fluorescent-labeled primer and only one labeled oligonucleotide probe
(Bernard, P. S., et al., Analytical Biochemistry 255 (1998) 101-107). In this regard, it
may be chosen arbitrarily, whether the primer is labeled with the FRET donor or
the FRET acceptor compound.</p><p num="0013">There exist many different pairs of fluorescent dyes known in the art which
according to the invention are principally capable of acting together as a FRET
donor/FRET acceptor pair. Yet, prior to the present invention, no functional
example has been disclosed, characterized in that 4 different FRET pairs have
succesfully been used in a multiplex detection assay. Among other reasons, this may
be due to lack of approriate instrumentation and, moreover, due to fact that the
functionality of the FRET process of a specific FRET pair is interfered by other
fluorecent compounds which are present in the same reaction mixture. </p><p num="0014">Besides PCR and real time PCR, FRET hybridization probes and molecular beacons
are used for melting curve analysis. In such an assay, the target nucleic acid is
amplified first in a typical PCR reaction with suitable amplification primers. The
hybridization probes may already be present during the amplification reaction or
added subsequently. After completion of the PCR-reaction, the temperature of the
sample is constitutively increased, and fluorescence is detected as long as the
hybridization probe was bound to the target DNA. At melting temperature, the
hybridization probes are released from their target, and the fluorescent signal is
decreasing immediately down to the background level. This decrease is monitored
with an appropriate fluorescence versus temperature-time plot such that a first
derivative value can be determined, at which the maximum of fluorescence decrease
is observed.</p><p num="0015">However, in some cases and depending on the design of FRET hybridization probes
or hybridization probes such as molecular beacons, the first derivatives of such
temperature-time plots do not have the expected bell-shaped curves but comprise
shoulders which cannot be explained by primary sequence analysis. The physicochemical
processes underlying the time course of melting DNA hybrids at present
can not be predicted accurately by any mathematical model. Thus, in practice, a
person skilled in needs to design and test several similar hybridization probes or
pairs of FRET hybridization probes in order to identify and select a suitable pair
which may generate melting curves having a more or less ideally bell shaped curve.</p><p num="0016">One possibility to overcome this problem is the introduction of artificial
mismatches as it has been disclosed in WO 97/46711. However, introduction of
mismatches only in some cases results in non ideally shaped melting curves,
especially in case of multiplex analysis using several hybridization probes or several
pairs of FRET hybridization probes in the same reaction vessel.</p><p num="0017">Thus there is a need in the art to provide oligonucleotides and especially FRET
hybridization probes with an improved melting curve behavior.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Brief description of the invention</u></b></heading><p num="0018">This problem is solved by providing oligonucleotides according to the invention. </p><p num="0019">More precisely, the present invention is directed to oligonucleotides comprising an
axial molecular rod.</p><p num="0020">In a first embodiment, the molecular rod connects a first part and a second part of
an oligonucleotide chain, characterized in that the molecular rod covalently
connects the 3' end of a first nucleotide residue, said residue being the 3' terminal
residue of said first part of said chain with the 5' end of a second nucleotide residue,
said second nucleotide residue being the 5' terminal of said second part of said
chain.</p><p num="0021">In a second embodiment, the molecular rod is covalently connected to the 5'
position of the 5' terminal residue or to the 3' position of the 3' terminal residue.
Preferably, the molecvular rod is connected to the 5' or 3' ebd of the
oligonucleotide via a Phosphate moiety.</p><p num="0022">In another aspect, the present invention is directed to a composition comprising an
oligonucleotide as disclosed above.</p><p num="0023">In a third aspect, the present invention is directed to a kit comprising an
oligonucleotide as disclosed above.</p><p num="0024">In a further aspect, the present invention is directed to a Phosphor-Amidite
comprising a molecular rod.</p><p num="0025">An oligonucleotide containing a molecular rod according to the invention may for
example be used as a primer for a primer extension reaction or a primer for a
nucleic acid amplification reaction.</p><p num="0026">Alternatively, an oligonucleotide containing a molecular rod according to the
invention may be used as a hybridization probe. In a specific embodiment, using a
hybridization probe according to the invention, temperature dependence of
hybridization is monitored, for example by means of performing a melting curve
analysis.</p><p num="0027">An oligonucleotide comprising a molecular rod according to the invention may also
become immobilized on a solid support. Preferentially, it is the molecular rod
which connects the chain of nucleotide residues to the solid support. </p><heading><b><u style="single">Detailed description of invention</u></b></heading><p num="0028">The present invention is directed to oligonucleotides comprising an axial molecular
rod. A detailed review on molecular rods is given by Schwab et al., In Chem. Rev. 99
(1999) 1863-1933, the content of which is hereby incorporated in the discolure of
the present invention in its entirety by reference.</p><p num="0029">In the context of the present invention, axial molecular rods can be defined as
linkers connecting two molecules (e.g. two parts of an oligonucleotide) in such a
way that the relative positions of each of the carbon atoms that contribute to the
rod structure fixed to each other. In other words: a molecular rod is a rigid
structure which in itself cannot become bended. As a consequence, the distance
between the atoms of the two molecules which are covalently bound to the rod
structure is fixed and cannot become altered.</p><p num="0030">Within the scope of the present invention, any kind of molecular rod which is
compatible with oligonucleotide synthesis protocols may be used. Preferentially,
rods used for the synthesis of oligonucleotides according to the invention are small
simple chemical structures which are composed of only a few carbon atoms. Also
preferred are those types of molecular rods which can be synthesized very cheap
and easily by conventional methods of organic chemistry starting from basic
compounds which are preferably commercially available.</p><p num="0031">In a preferred embodiment, the rod is a singly linked axial molecular rod. Per
definition, singly linked axial molecular rods are linked by a single covalent bond to
each of the two molecules connected by the rod. For example, the molecular rod is
simply composed of two carbon atoms linked by an ethylene. Other examples for
singly linked molecular rods not limiting the scope of the invention are
bicyclopentane, bicyclclooctane, cubane, benzene, naphtalene, anthracene, pyrene,
pyridine, or porphyrine. Molecules and especially oligonucleotides linked by a
connecting singly axial molecular rod can be rotated relatively against each other,
although the distance between the atoms of the two molecules which are covalently
bound to the rod structure is fixed.</p><p num="0032">In a highly preferred embodiment the singly linked axial molecular rod comprises
or consists of either an ethylene moiety or, alternatively, a phenylene moiety. </p><p num="0033">In another highly preferred embodiment, the singly linked axial molecular rod
comprises or consists of a molecular structure as follows:
<img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="75" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="26"/></p><p num="0034">In an alternative embodiment, the rod is a doubly linked axial molecular rod. Per
definition, doubly linked axial molecular rods are linked by two covalent bonds to
each of the two molecules connected by the rod. Examples for doubly linked axial
molecular rods are Ethenene, Cyclobutane, Cyclohexane, and Cyclohexadiene.
Molecules and especially oligonucleotides linked by a connecting doubly axial
molecular rod can not be rotated relatively against each other, in addition to the
fact that the distance between the atoms of the two molecules which are covalently
bound to the rod structure is fixed.</p><p num="0035">It is also within the scope of the present invention if the axial molecular rod of an
oligonucleotide is composed out of several modules such as poly-ethylene, e.c.
Therefore, depending on the number of modules which are used, the length of the
axial molecular rod may be adjusted as required accordingly.</p><p num="0036">Synthesis of oligonucleotides comprising molecular rods may be performed
according to conventional oligonucleotide synthesis chemistry.</p><p num="0037">In one embodiment, the molecular rod is covalently bound to the 3'-OH position
of the 3' terminal residue or to the 3' position of the 3' terminal residue. For this
embodiment, an axial molecular rod may be introduced at the 3' end of a
chemically synthesized oligonucleotide using an appropriate CPG (Controlled Pore
Glass) comprising a trifunctional spacer. This can either be done by applying a CPG
already carrying a molecular rod analogous to the compounds and methods
disclosed in US 5,290,925.</p><p num="0038">In another embodiment, the molecular rod is covalently bound to the 5'- position
of the 5' terminal residue. For this other embodiment, an axial molecular rod may
be linked to a nascent oligonucleotide chain by using an appropriate phosphor-amidite. 
Optionally, an amino group at the free end of the rod can be introduced
which may serve as a basis for subsequent conventional post labeling strategies.</p><p num="0039">The phosphor-amidite chemistry method is well known by any person skilled in the
art. A 3'-phosporous group of one nucleoside reacts with the 5'-hydroxyl moiety of
another. The reaction proceeds from 3'- to 5'-, between each phosphor-amidite
with a 5'-dimethoxytrityl protected monomer delivered in solution and the
growing, 3' reactive oligonucleotide bound to an inert substrate. In comparison to
other methods, the inherent coupling yields are typically on the order of 98±0.5%,
resulting in adducts that are easily purified. An important factor ensuring a high
yield synthesis is the capping step - the acetylation of uncoupled bases at the 5'-hydroxyl
moiety. The crude reaction mixture collected at the conclusion of each
synthesis consists of the desired adduct, along with small quantities of side
products. These deletion sequences range in size from one base to n-1 bases - where
n is the number of bases in the desired product. Deletion sequences, which formed
due to failed couplings, must be chemically capped prior to subsequent base
additions. Otherwise these failed sequences would compete with the full length
adduct for phosphor-amidites. Also, the separation of the (n-1)-mer from the
desired product is much more challenging than the separation of other truncated
sequences of shorter length.</p><p num="0040">Nascent oligonucleotides have the 5'-hydroxyl positions protected by
dimethoxytrityl (DMT) groups., which have to be removed after each synthesis
cycle in order to generate a reactive 5' OH group of the nascent oligonucleotide
chain. For product oligonucleotides, the DMT group can be removed during
synthesis (TRITYL OFF) or left on (TRITYL ON) if reverse phase HPLC is the
purification method of choice. A free 3'-hydroxyl moiety is created when the
synthesized oligonucleotide is cleaved from the support, so no further deprotection
is required.</p><p num="0041">The inventors of the present invention surprisingly discovered that hybridization
probes comprising an internal molecular rod possess an altered and more
predictable behavior in melting curve analysis experiments. Therefore, in one
important embodiment of the present invention, the molecular rod connects a first
part and a second part of an oligonucleotide chain, characterized in that the
molecular rod covalently connects the 3' end of a first nucleotide residue, said 
residue being the 3' terminal residue of said first part of said chain with the 5' end
of a second nucleotide residue, said second nucleotide residue being the 5' terminal
of said second part of said chain.</p><p num="0042">There exists an easy possibility for generating oligonucleotides comprising an
internal axial molecular rod. An appropriate phosphor-amidite comprising an axial
molecular rod may be introduced carrying an appropriately protected hydroxyl
group, which during the next synthesis cycle may become deprotected such that it
can react with another deoxynuclotide-phosphor-amidite.</p><p num="0043">An example for the synthesis of a Phenylene phosphor-amidite is given in Fig. 1 and
example 1. Other molecular rod phosphor-amidites can be synthesized
correspondingly, starting from rod scaffolds comprising, for example, two hydroxyl
groups as reactive groups.</p><p num="0044">In another embodiment, several rod-carrrying phosphor-amidites may be coupled
to the nascent oligonucleotide chain one after another in order to generate an
oligonuceotide comprising an internal rod of appropriate length.</p><p num="0045">In another aspect, the present invention is directed to compositions comprising at
least one oligonucleotide with axial molecular rods as disclosed above.</p><p num="0046">In still another aspect, the present invention is directed to a kit comprising an
oligonucleotide as disclosed above.</p><p num="0047">In general, oligonucleotides comprising axial molecular rods according to the
invention may be used for a variety of applications, for example as a primer for a
primer extension reaction, as a primer for a nucleic acid amplification reaction, or
as a hybridization probe.</p><p num="0048">In one embodiment, axial molecular rods may serve as linkers of labeled
oligonucleotides between the oligonucleotide chain and the labeling entity. As a
consequence, the rigid structure of the rod results in prevention of a partial vicinity
between the labeling entity and the oligonucleotide chain. In case the label is a
fluorescent entity, such an avoidance is highly advantageous, since undesired
quenching effect due to an uncontrollable interaction between G residues and the
fluorescent entity are avoided. </p><p num="0049">In another important embodiment, oligonucleotides containing internal axial
molecular rods according to the invention are used as hybridization probes. The
axial molecular rods may be an integral part of any kind of hybridization probes
such as TaqMan probes, Molecular Beacons or may be in integral part of one or
both members of a pair of FRET hybridization probes. Those hybridization probes
according to the invention may be used for hybridization on blots, microtiter
plates, microarrays, and, in particular for real time PCR.</p><p num="0050">In a specific embodiment, using a hybridization probe or a pair of FRET
hybridization probes according to the invention, temperature dependence of
hybridization is monitored, for example by means of performing a melting curve
analysis.</p><p num="0051">Real time PCR melting curve analysis is usually performed after completion of the
PCR-reaction. After an initial denaturation and cooling step, the temperature of the
amplicon is constitutively increased, and fluorescence is detectable as long as the
hybridization probe is bound to the target DNA. In case of the FRET hybridization
probe formate, both probes need to stay hybridized to the target nucleic acid in
order to generate a fluorescent signal. At melting temperature, the hybridization
probes (in case of the FRET fomat: at least one member of said pair of hybridization
probes) are released from their target, and the fluorescent signal is decreasing
immediately down to the background level.</p><p num="0052">This decrease is monitored with an appropriate fluorescence versus temperature-time
plot such that a first derivative value can be determined, at which the
maximum of fluorescence decrease is observed. As it will be demonstrated by the
examples below, oligonucleotides containing internal axial molecular rods
according to the invention will be highly advantageous for this particular
embodiment.</p><p num="0053">Due to the rigid nature of the axial molecular rod, the melting characterics of an
oligonucleotide can be altered substantially and thus adjusted to the required
conditions.</p><p num="0054">First, introduction of an internal molecular rod may result in a moderate shift in
the melting temperature™ of the oligonucleotide which is usually a moderate
temperature decrease. Such a decrease may be advantageous especially for multiplex 
melting curve approaches, where multiple Tms have to be analyzed and
discriminated from each other.</p><p num="0055">Second, introduction an internal molecular rod usually results in an increase in the
difference of melting temperatures detectable when compared hybridization events
with and without base pairing mismatches. Therefore, oligonucleotides according
to the invention significantly improve allelic discrimination and analysis of single
nucleotide polymorphism analysis in real time PCR as well as in embodiments
using solid supports.</p><p num="0056">Third, introduction an internal molecular rod in all cases investigated so far results
in sharp, slender and optimally bell shaped melting peaks when first derivative
temperature versus time plots are produced. This could be explained by the rigid
nature of the axial molecular rods, which results in a situation where the respective
hybridization probe is either still completely hybridized to the target DNA, or
completely free in its single stranded form in the reaction solution. In other words:
partially hybridization intermediates resulting in non bell shaped melting curves
with shoulders are avoided.</p><p num="0057">Fourth, usage of probes containing internal axial molecular rods results in many
cases in an improvement of assay specificity.</p><p num="0058">In a final aspect, oligonucleotides comprising an axial molecular rod according to
the invention may also become immobilized on a solid support, for example a
nucleic acid microarray. Preferentially, it is the molecular rod which connects the
chain of nucleotide residues to the solid support. Such an application is highly
advantageous, because the rigid structure of the rods leads to a limited, defined and
controllable spatial separation between the oligonucleotide itself and the solid
support. As a consequence, a putative sterical hindrance of hybridization to the
immobilized oligonucleotides caused by the vicinity to the solid support is avoided.</p><p num="0059">Since for nucleic acid array applications it is particularily important to achieve an
optimized match/mismatch discrimination, introduction an internal molecular rod
according to the invention is highly advantageous., because it results in an increase
in the difference of melting temperatures detectable whe hybridization events with
and without base pairing mismatches are compared. </p><p num="0060">The appropriate mode of coupling of the molecular rod onto the solid support
depends on the type of solid support which actually shall be used. For example,
amino groups of the rod may react with epoxy-groups on the surface such as glass
or plastic. Alternatively, alkoxy-silanated rods may be coupled to glass surfaces. For
surfaces carrying reactive C-OH groups, linkage may be obtained using
conventional phosphoramidate cheimstry.</p><p num="0061">In order to control the density of oligonucleotides immobilized by in situ synthesis
onto solid support, the solid support is in a first step reacted with a mixed solution
of axial molecular rods exendable by oligonucleotides synthesis and non extendable
axial molecular rods. Density can then be adjusted by amending the concentration
of non extendable rod compounds.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Brief description of the Figures</u></b></heading><p num="0062"><sl><li><b>Figure 1: Synthesis of a Phosphor-Amidite comprising a molecular rod</b>

The figure depicts the synthesis strategy for the generation of a Phsosphor-Amidite
comprising a molecular rod, which according to the invention may be
incorporated internally into an oligonucleotidy by conventional oligonucleotide
synthesis chemistry. Details are explained in example 1.</li><li><b>Figure 2: Prothrombin mutation analysis</b>

1 ng of prothrombin homozygous wild type, heterozygous and homozygous
mutant plasmid DNA was amplified. The Hybridization Probe, which spanned the
mutation site (mutation probe), had 100% homology to the homozygous wildtype
plasmid DNA.</li><li><b>Figure 3: Prothrombin mutation analysis with an artifical mismatch</b>

1 ng of prothrombin homozygous wildtype, heterozygous and homozygous mutant
plasmid DNA was amplified. The Hybridization Probe, which spanned the
mutation site (mutation probe), carried an artificial mismatch.</li><li><b>Figure 4: Prothrombin mutation analysis with inserted Phenylene linker</b>
 
1 ng of prothrombin homozygous wildtype, heterozygous and homozygous
mutant plasmid DNA was amplified. The Hybridization Probe, which spanned the
mutation site (mutation probe), carried an inserted Phenylene linker.</li><li><b>Figure 5: Prothrombin mutation analysis: TM shift of the melting peaks using
modified mutation probes</b>

1 ng of prothrombin homozygous mutant plasmid DNA was amplified. Three
different mutation probes were tested: one with 100% homology to the
homozygous wildtype plasmid DNA, one with an artificial mismatch and one with
an inserted Phenylene linker.</li><li><b>Figure 6: EBV detection with perfect matching Hybridization Probes</b>

10<sup>4</sup> copies of EBV plasmid DNA were amplified. The LC Red 640 labeled
Hybridization Probe, which determined the T<sub>M</sub>, showed 100% homology to the
EBV plasmid DNA.</li><li><b>Figure 7: EBV detection with Hybridization Probes carrying an inserted Phenylene
linker</b>

10<sup>4</sup> copies of EBV plasmid DNA were amplified. The LC Red 640 labeled
Hybridization Probe, which determined the T<sub>M</sub>, carried an inserted Phenylene
linker.</li></sl></p><p num="0063">The following examples, references, sequence listing and figures are provided to aid
the understanding of the present invention, the true scope of which is set forth in
the appended claims. It is understood that modifications can be made in the
procedures set forth without departing from the spirit of the invention. </p><heading><b><u style="single">Examples</u></b></heading><heading><b><u style="single">Example 1</u></b></heading><heading><b>Synthesis of an oligonucleotide comprising a molecular Rod</b></heading><p num="0064">As an example for the synthesis of an oligonucleotide according to the invention,
an oligonucleotide according to the invention carrying an internal rod was
synthesized according to the strategy depicted in fig. 1 as follows:</p><heading><b>A) 4-(p,p'- Dimethoxytrityl-methyloxy) benzyl alcohol</b></heading><p num="0065">Within 1 h a solution of 51.5 g Dimethoxytritylchlorid in 300 ml dry pyridine was
dropped at room temperature to a solution of 20 g of 1,4 bis hydroxymethylbenzol
in 100 ml dry pyridine. After stirring overnight the solvent was evaporated using a
rotary evaporator. The residue was dissolved in 800ml acetic acid ethyl ester and
was washed with once with 400 ml and than with two times 200 ml water. The
organic phase was separated and dried with sodium sulfate. After filtration the
solvent was removed by using a rotary evaporator.</p><p num="0066">Purification was performed by column chromatography on silica gel. Therefore 10
grams of the crude product were dissolved in a Toluol/ Acetic Acid Ethyl ester/Methanol
4:1:1 mixture containing 0.1% Triethylamin. The solution was applied on
a 40 cm/ d= 6.9 cm column filled with silica gel 60 (0.063-0.200 mm). The product
was eluated with a Toluol/ Acetic Acid Ethyl ester/ Methanol 4:1:1 mixture
containing 0.1% Triethylamin.</p><p num="0067">TLC: Toluol/ Acetic Acid Ethyl ester/ Methanol 4:1:1 mixture containing 0.1%
Triethylamin Rf: 0.56</p><heading><b>B) Diisopropyl-phosphoramidous acid 4-[bis-(4-methoxy-phenyl)-phenyl-methoxy]-benzyl
ester 2-cyano-ethyl ester</b></heading><p num="0068">At room temperature under argon 0.78 gram diisopropylammonium tetrazolid
were added to a solution of 2 grams of 1-(O-Dimethoxytrityl-hydroxymethyl) 4-hydroxymethyl-benzol
in dry 15 ml Methylenchloride. A solution of 1.37 g of 2-cyanoethyl-tetra
isopropyl-phosphordiamidit in 10 ml dry Methylenchloride was
added drop wise within 30 min. After stirring at room temperature for 2h the 
suspension was filtrated. From the filtrate the solvent was removed by using a
rotary evaporator. The residue was dissolved in 50 ml acetic acid ethyl ester and
washed two times with 10 ml 5% aqueous sodium hydrogencarbonat solution. The
organic phase was separated and dried with sodium sulfate. After filtration the
solvent was removed by using a rotary evaporator.</p><p num="0069">Purification was performed by column chromatography on silica gel. Therefore the
crude product was dissolved in an Acetic Acid Ethylester/ Hexane 1:1 mixture
containing 0.1% Triethylamin. The solution was applied on a l=32 cm/ d= 4.5 cm
column filled with silica gel 60 (0.063-0.200 mm). The product was eluated with an
Acetic Acid Ethyl ester/ Hexane 1:1 mixture containing 0.1% Triethylamin:
<sl><li>TLC: Acetic Acid Ethyl ester/ Hexane 1:1 mixture containing 0.1% Triethylamin
Rf: 0.80</li><li>NMR <sup>1</sup>H( 300 MHz): 1.21 t [12H], 2.76 t[2H], 3.7 m[2H], 3.78 s[6H], 3.88 m[2H],
4.16 s[2H], 4.75 m[2H], 6.91 d[4]7.23-7.67 m,s [13] NMR <sup>31</sup>P( 300 MHz): 149.19</li></sl></p><p num="0070">The resulting Phosphoramidate was incorporated into oligonucleotides by
conventional oligonucleotide synthesis using Phosphor-Amidate chemistry. A
molecular rod in the oligonucleotide as synthesized above will be termed
"Phenylene linker" in the examples which follow.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 2</u></b></heading><heading><b>Real Time Mutation Analysis of Prothrombin plasmid DNA</b></heading><p num="0071">To demonstrate the validity of the invention, genotyping of the prothrombin
(G20210A) point mutation by using Hybridization Probes was chosen as test
system.</p><p num="0072">Partial fragments of wildtype and mutant prothrombin sequence were cloned into
separate pCR™ 2.1 plasmid vectors (Invitrogen). Concentration of plasmid DNA
was estimated by spectrophotometry . Prothrombin plasmid DNA dilutions and
mixtures of wildtype and mutant plasmid to get heterozygous DNA were prepared
by using a diluent consisting of MS2 RNA (10ng/µl) in 10mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.3. </p><p num="0073">PCR was conducted on a LightCycler instrument (Roche Molecular Biochemicals).
A typical PCR assay consisted of 2 µl DNA, 1 x Detection Mix, 1 x Reaction buffer,
4 mM magnesium chloride and 1.6 units of Taq Polymerase (all from Roche
Diagnostics, Mannheim, Germany) adjusted with water to a 20 µl volume in one
reaction capillary.</p><p num="0074">For mutation analysis, the reaction buffer and the unmodified Taq Polymerase
from the LightCycler - DNA Master Hybridisation Probes Kit (Roche Molecular
Biochemical, Cat. No. 2 015 102) were used.</p><p num="0075">The 10 x Detection Mixes for prothrombin consisted of 5 µM of each primer
(forward and reverse), 2 µM of mutation probe (Fluorescein-labeled), 4 µM of
anchor probe (LC Red 640-labeled), 0.05% Brij-35 in 10mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.3
buffer.</p><p num="0076">The following primer and Hybridization Probe sequences were used:
<sl><li>Prothrombin forward primer:
<img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="9"/></li><li>Prothrombin reverse primer:
<img id="img-00160002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00160002.tif"  inline="no" he="11"/></li><li>Prothrombin probe 1:
<img id="img-00160003" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif"  img-content="dn"  file="00160003.tif"  inline="no" he="17"/></li><li>Prothrombin probe 2:
<img id="img-00160004" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00160004.tif" inline="no" he="11"/></li><li>Prothrombin probe 3:
<img id="img-00160005" orientation="unknown" wi="123" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00160005.tif" inline="no" he="9"/></li><li>Prothrombin probe 4:
<img id="img-00160006" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00160006.tif" inline="no" he="6"/>
x = Phenylene linker</li></sl></p><p num="0077">Regular PCR cycling conditions consisted of an initial 95°C incubation for 30
seconds followed by 45 cycles of 95°C for 0 seconds, 55°C for 10 seconds and 72°C
for 5 seconds and was concluded with 40°C for 30 seconds.</p><p num="0078">Melting Temperatures for each reaction were determined by the LightCycler
Analysis software using the polynomial calculation method with background
substraction.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 3</u></b></heading><heading><b>Genotyping of the prothrombin (G20210A) point mutation is not possible with
the perfect matching mutation probe</b></heading><p num="0079">Real time PCR of 1 ng wildtype, heterozygous and mutant prothrombin DNA was
performed in a setup according to example 1. Results are shown in Fig. 2. As can be
seen, after performing a melting curve analysis with a perfect matching mutation
probe it is not possible to determine the prothrombin genotype exactly, since the
homozygous wildtype and the heterozygous genotype could not be differentiated
exactly.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 4</u></b></heading><heading><b>Using a mutation probe with an artifical mismatch genotyping of the prothrombin
(G20210A) point mutation is possible, but not perfect.</b></heading><p num="0080">Real time PCR of 1 ng wildtype, heterozygous and mutant prothrombin DNA was
performed in a setup according to example 1. Results are shown in Fig. 3. As can be
seen, correct determination of the prothrombin genotype is principally possible
using the mutation probe with an artifical mismatch, but the wildtype melting peak
is still very broad and shows a distinct shoulder. Additionally, the minimum
between the two melting peaks of the heterozygous samples has a high signal level,
so there is no big difference between the minimum between the peaks and the
maximum of the wildtype melting peak. </p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 5</u></b></heading><heading><b>Perfect genotyping of the prothrombin (G20210A) point mutation can be
performed using the mutation probe with an inserted Phenylene linker</b></heading><p num="0081">Real time PCR of 1 ng wildtype, heterozygous and mutant prothrombin DNA was
performed in a setup according to example 1. Results are shown in Fig. 4. As can be
seen, the prothrombin genotype can be determinated perfectly using the mutation
probe with an inserted Phenylene linker. All melting peaks are very sharp and
without any shoulders.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 6</u></b></heading><heading><b>Shift of the melting temperature of the prothrombin mutation melting peak using
different mutation probes</b></heading><p num="0082">Real time PCR of 1 ng mutant prothrombin DNA was performed in a setup
according to example 1. Results are shown in Fig. 5. As can be seen, the melting
temperature of the prothrombin mutation melting peak shifts dependent on the
used mutation probe. The table below shows the different melting temperatures.
<img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="123" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="39"/></p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 7</u></b></heading><heading><b>Real Time PCR of EBV plasmid DNA</b></heading><p num="0083">To demonstrate the validity of the invention, Epstein-Barr virus, frequently referred
to EBV, a member of the herpes virus family and one of the most common human
viruses, was chosen as second test system.</p><p num="0084">A partial fragment of EBVwas cloned into the pT3T7 plasmid vector (Roche
Molecular Biochemicals). Copy numbers of plasmid DNA were estimated by
spectrophotometry with the assumption that 1 mole is equivalent to 6 x 1023
copies. EBV plasmid DNA dilutions were prepared by using a diluent consisting of
MS2 RNA ( 10ng/µl) in 10mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.3. </p><p num="0085">PCR was conducted on a LightCycler instrument (Roche Molecular Biochemicals).
A typical PCR assay consisted of 5 µl DNA, 1 x Detection Mix, 1 x Reaction buffer,
3.5 mM magnesium chloride and 1.6 units of modified Taq Polymerase (all from
Roche Diagnostics, Mannheim, Germany) adjusted with water to a 20 µl volume in
one reaction capillary.</p><p num="0086">For PCR, the reaction buffer and the modified Taq Polymerase from the
LightCycler - Fast Start DNA Master Hybridization Probes Kit (Roche Molecular
Biochemical, Cat. No. 3 003 248) were used.</p><p num="0087">The 10 x Detection Mixes for EBV consisted of 5 µM of each primer (forward and
reverse), 2 µM of each hybridization probe (Fluorescein and LC Red 640 labeled),
0.05% Brij-35 in 10mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.3 buffer.</p><p num="0088">The following primer and hybridization probes sequences were used:
<sl><li>EBV forward primer:
<img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="11"/></li><li>EBV reverse primer:
<img id="img-00190002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00190002.tif" inline="no" he="9"/></li><li>EBV probe 1:
<img id="img-00190003" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00190003.tif" inline="no" he="9"/></li><li>EBV probe 2:
<img id="img-00190004" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00190004.tif" inline="no" he="9"/></li><li>EBV probe 3:
<img id="img-00190005" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="dn" file="00190005.tif" inline="no" he="6"/>
x = Phenylene linker</li></sl></p><p num="0089">Regular PCR cycling conditions consisted of an initial 95°C incubation for 10
minutes followed by 45 cycles of 95°C for 10 seconds, 55°C for 15 seconds and 72°C
for 15 seconds and was concluded with 40°C for 30 seconds. </p><p num="0090">Melting Temperatures for each reaction were determined by the LightCycler
Analysis software using the polynomial calculation method with background
substraction.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 8</u></b></heading><heading><b>With perfect matching Hybridization Probes a double melting peak is generated</b></heading><p num="0091">Real time PCR of 10<sup>4</sup> copies EBV was performed in a setup according to example 6.
Results are shown in Fig. 6. As can be seen, performing a melting curve analysis
with perfect matching hybridization probes a double peak and not the expected
single melting peak was generated.</p><heading><b><u style="single">Example 9</u></b></heading><heading><b>Using the Hybridization Probe with an inserted Phenylene linker a single melting
peak is generated</b></heading><p num="0092">Real time PCR of 10<sup>4</sup> copies EBV was performed in a setup according to example 6.
Results are shown in Fig. 6. As can be seen, if the Hybridization Probe, which
determined the T<sub>M</sub>, carried an inserted Phenylene linker, the exspected single
melting peak was generated after performing a melting curve analysis. </p><heading><b><u style="single">List of References</u></b></heading><p num="0093"><sl><li>Bernard, P. S., et al., Analytical Biochemistry 255 (1998) 101-107</li><li>Matthews, J.A., and Kricka, L.J. , Analytical Biochemistry 169 (1988) 1-25</li><li>Schwab et al., In Chem. Rev. 99 (1999) 1863-1933</li><li>US 5,118,801</li><li>US 5,141,837</li><li>US 5,210,015</li><li>US 5,290,925</li><li>US 5,487,972</li><li>US 5,538,848</li><li>US 5,804,375</li><li>US 6,174,670</li><li>WO 97/46707</li><li>WO 97/46711</li><li>WO 97/46712</li><li>WO 97/46714</li></sl><img id="img-00220001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00220001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/><img id="img-00230001" orientation="unknown" wi="155" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00230001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/><img id="img-00240001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tx" file="00240001.tif" inline="no" he="204"/></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for synthesizing an oligonucleotide comprising an axial molecular
rod, said molecular rod being a rigid structure which in itself cannot become
bended, comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>providing a controlled pore glass particle</claim-text><claim-text>synthesizing said oligonucleotide by means of phosphor-amidite chemistry.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>Method acccording to claim 1, wherein said axial molecular rod is
incorporated into said oligonucleotide by means of providing a phosphor-amidite
comprising an axial molecular rod.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>Method according to claim 1, wherein said axial molecular rod is provided
by means of providing a controlled pore glass particle comprising an axial
molecular rod.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>Oligonucleotide comprising an axial molecular rod, said molecular rod being
a rigid structure which in itself cannot become bended, wherein said rod is
covalently connected via a phosphate moiety to the 5' position of the 5'
terminal residue or to the 3' position of the 3' terminal residue.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>Composition comprising an oligonucleotide according to claim 4.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>Kit comprising an oligonucleotide according to claim 4.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>Use of an oligonucleotide comprising an axial molecular rod, said molecular
rod being a rigid structure which in itself cannot become bended,
characterized in that said rod is covalently connected to the 5' terminal
residue, as a primer for a primer extension reaction or a primer for a nucleic
acid amplification reaction.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>Use of an oligonucleotide comprising an axial molecular rod, said molecular
rod being a rigid structure which in itself cannot become bended as a
hybridization probe, wherein temperature dependence of hybridization is
monitored in real time.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>An oligonucleotide according to claim 4, wherein said oligonucleotide is
immobilized on a solid support.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An oligonulceotide according to claim 9, wherein said molecular rod connects
said solid support and the chain of nucleotide residues.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>