<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1403341-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1403341" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="31977877" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040331"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1403341-A1" status="new" fvid="24006414"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1403341</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040331</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03077891-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03077891</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030915</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-25682202-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>25682202</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020927</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/42        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/42        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/50        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/52        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41J   2/42</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B41M   5/52</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C2B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="IDT">B41J2/42</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="IDT">B41M5/00J</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Tintenstrahldruckverfahren und Tintenstrahltintenzusammensetzung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Inkjet printing method and inkjet ink composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Méthode d'impression à jet d'encre et composition d'encre pour impression à jet d'encre</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0974626-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0974626</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1219688-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1219688</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1226970-A2"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1226970</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6447110-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6447110</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>EASTMAN KODAK CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>EASTMAN KODAK COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>EASTMAN KODAK COMPANY</last-name><address><street>343 State Street</street><city>Rochester, New York 14650</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHEN HUIJUAN D</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>FRAZIER RICKY G</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WANG XIAORU</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHEN, HUIJUAN D.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>FRAZIER, RICKY G.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WANG, XIAORU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Chen, Huijuan D., c/o Eastman Kodak Company</last-name><address><street>Patent Legal Staff, 343 State Street</street><city>Rochester, New York 14650-2201</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Frazier, Ricky G., c/o Eastman Kodak Company</last-name><address><street>Patent Legal Staff, 343 State Street</street><city>Rochester, New York 14650-2201</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Wang, Xiaoru, c/o Eastman Kodak Company</last-name><address><street>Patent Legal Staff, 343 State Street</street><city>Rochester, New York 14650-2201</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Weber, Etienne Nicolas</last-name><address><street>Kodak Industrie, Département Brevets, CRT, Zone Industrielle</street><city>71102 Chalon sur Saône Cedex</city><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An ink jet printing method, comprising the steps of A) providing 
an ink jet printer that is responsive to digital data signals; B) loading the printer 
with an ink jet recording element; C) loading the printer with an ink jet ink 
composition comprising an aqueous ink jet ink composition comprising: a 
pigment, a polymer latex containing at least one halogenated vinyl monomer, at 
least one surfactant, and a humectant; and D) printing on the ink jet recording 
element accompanied by a heating step using the ink jet ink composition in 
response to the digital data signals. </p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to an ink jet printing method using an 
aqueous ink jet ink composition comprising pigment and a polymer latex. The 
polymer latex is prepared from at least one halogenated vinyl monomer 
composition. </p><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0002">Ink jet printing is a non-impact method for producing images by 
the deposition of ink droplets on a substrate (paper, transparent film, fabric, etc.) 
in response to digital signals. Ink jet printers have found broad applications 
across markets ranging from industrial labeling to short run printing to desktop 
document and pictorial imaging and large format printing for outdoor applications 
such as banners, signages, displays, posters, billboard and buswraps. </p><p num="0003">This technique of printing is well suited for printing on a variety of 
surfaces (receivers) including porous and non-porous surfaces. Porous inkjet 
receivers have the advantage of large fluid intake and this provides fast printing 
speed. However, in some applications, such as banners, signages, displays, 
posters, billboard and buswraps, these porous receivers suffer from durability 
issues such as lightfastness, waterfastness, abrasion resistance and weather 
resistance. In order to overcome these problems, the prints are usually post 
treated by methods such as lamination, which adds to the cost considerably. 
Historically, in order to overcome these problems, solvent based inks or UV 
curable inks were developed to be printed on non-absorbing substrates such as 
vinyl to achieve the desired durability. US patent 4,106,027 describes such a 
solvent based ink that is suitable for printing images on non-absorbing receivers 
with improved adhesion and durability. EP 0 882 104 B1 describes a UV curable 
inkjet ink composition for better durability of the print on non-absorbing 
substrate. A significant environmental, health and safety concern with both of 
these types of ink is the evaporation of solvent or UV monomer during printing.  </p><p num="0004">US Patent 6,087,416 describes the use of an aqueous based 
pigment ink for printing on non-absorbing vinyl substrate. That ink contains a 
grafted copolymer binder that is soluble in the aqueous vehicle but insoluble in 
water. However, the problem with the ink is that, due to the soluble nature of the 
binder in the ink vehicle, the ink viscosity is high and the printing reliability is 
poor. In addition, the printed images are not durable to solvent. </p><p num="0005">US Patent 4,762,875 described a printing inks containing pigment 
and polymer additives for plastics and metal surfaces, however, there is a problem 
with this invention that the solid content for this ink is high, therefore the 
viscosity of the ink is too high for inkjet ink applications; in addition, the 
additives used in this invention is hydrophilic in nature therefore the resulted 
coatings has poor water resistance. </p><p num="0006">Therefore, there is a need for an aqueous based ink jet ink that 
provides good waterfastness, lightfastness, abrasion resistance, good adhesion to 
non-absorbing substrates including untreated vinyl, and that can be printed 
reliably through a piezo or thermal printhead. </p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0007">This and other objects are achieved in accordance with the present 
invention which comprises an ink jet printing method, comprising the steps of: 
<sl><li>A) providing an ink jet printer that is responsive to digital data signals; </li><li>B) loading said printer with an ink jet recording element; </li><li>C) loading said printer with an ink jet ink composition comprising an 
aqueous ink jet ink composition comprising: 
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>a pigment; </li><li>a polymer latex containing at least one halogenated vinyl monomer; </li><li>at least one surfactant; and </li><li>a humectant; and </li></ul></li><li>D) printing on said ink jet recording element accompanied by a heating 
step using said ink jet ink composition in response to said digital data signals. </li></sl></p><p num="0008">It was found that the colloid stability, stain resistance and 
abrasion resistance of an ink jet image was improved using the composition 
described herein. </p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0009">The method of the present invention is suited for printing on a 
variety of substrates, especially on non-absorbing substrates. The non-absorbing 
substrates that may be used in the present invention include any substrate that is 
essentially non-porous. They are usually not specially treated for additional liquid 
absorption. Therefore, these materials have very low or no liquid absorbing 
capacity. Examples of such non-absorbing substrates are metals such as 
aluminum, copper, stainless steel and alloy etc.; plastics such as vinyl, 
polycarbonate, polytetrafluoroethylene (PTFE), polyethylene, polypropylene, 
polystyrene, cellulose; and other substrates such as ceramics, glass. </p><p num="0010">In order to achieve good image durability when printing aqueous 
based inks onto a non-absorbing substrate, the polymeric binder in the ink 
composition needs to be essentially hydrophobic, capable of providing good 
adhesion strength to the non-absorbing substrate, and also not be easily re-dispersible 
in water after drying . In addition, in order to provide good ink storage 
stability and prevent potential nozzle clogging, the hydrophobic polymer binder 
also needs to be sufficiently stable as a dispersion and compatible with other ink 
components, such as surfactant, colorants and humectants. Therefore, the polymer 
binders need to be dispersible in aqueous ink environment but not soluble to 
achieve low ink viscosity and print durability to both water and solvents. 
Furthermore, the ink should have sufficiently low surface tension to have good 
wettability to the non-absorbing substrate. </p><p num="0011">The pigment used in the present invention can be either self-dispersible 
such as those described in US patent 5,630,868, encapsulated as those 
described in the pending US patent application Serial No. 09/822,723, filed March 
30, 2001, or can be stabilized by a dispersant. The process of preparing inks from 
pigments commonly involves two steps: (a) a dispersing or milling step to break  
 
up the pigment to the primary particle, and (b) dilution step in which the dispersed 
pigment concentrate is diluted with a carrier and other addenda to a working 
strength ink. In the milling step, the pigment is usually suspended in a carrier 
(typically the same carrier as that in the finished ink) along with rigid, inert 
milling media. Mechanical energy is supplied to this pigment dispersion, and the 
collisions between the milling media and the pigment cause the pigment to 
deaggregate into its primary particles. A dispersant or stabilizer, or both, is 
commonly added to the pigment dispersion to facilitate the deaggregation of the 
raw pigment, to maintain colloidal particle stability, and to retard particle 
reagglomeration and settling. </p><p num="0012">There are many different types of materials which may be used as 
milling media, such as glasses, ceramics, metals, and plastics. In a preferred 
embodiment, the grinding media can comprise particles, preferably substantially 
spherical in shape, e.g., beads, consisting essentially of a polymeric resin. In 
general, polymeric resins suitable for use as milling media are chemically and 
physically inert, substantially free of metals, solvent and monomers, and of 
sufficient hardness and firability to enable them to avoid being chipped or crushed 
during milling. Suitable polymeric resins include crosslinked polystyrenes, such 
as polystyrene crosslinked with divinylbenzene, styrene copolymers, polyacrylates 
such as poly(methyl methylacrylate), olycarbonates, polyacetals, such as Derlin™, 
vinyl chloride polymers and copolymers, polyurethanes, polyamides, 
poly(tetrafluoroethylenes), e.g., Teflon™, and other fluoropolymers, high density 
polyethylenes, polypropylenes, cellulose ethers and esters such as cellulose 
acetate, poly(hydroxyethylmethacrylate), poly(hydroxyethylacrylate), silicone 
containing polymers such as polysiloxanes and the like. The polymer can be 
biodegradable. Exemplary biodegradable polymers include poly(lactides), 
poly(glycolids) copolymers of lactides and glycolide, polyanhydrides, poly(imino 
carbonates), poly(N-acylhydroxyproline) esters, poly(N-palmitoyl hydroxyprolino) 
esters, ethylene-vinyl acetate copolymers, poly(orthoesters), poly(caprolactones), 
and poly(phosphazenes). The polymeric resin can have a density from 0.9 to 3.0 
g/cm3. Higher density resins are preferred inasmuch as it is believed that these  
 
provide more efficient particle size reduction. Most preferred are crosslinked or 
uncrosslinked polymeric media based on styrene. </p><p num="0013">Milling can take place in any suitable grinding mill. Suitable mills 
include an air jet mill, a roller mill, a ball mill, an attritor mill and a bead mill. A 
high speed mill is preferred. By high speed mill we mean milling devices capable 
of accelerating milling media to velocities greater than about 5 meters per second. 
Sufficient milling media velocity is achieved, for example, in Cowles-type saw 
tooth impeller having a diameter of 40 mm when operated at 9,000 rpm. The 
preferred proportions of the milling media, the pigment, the liquid dispersion 
medium and dispersant can vary within wide limits and depends, for example, up 
on the particular material selected and the size and density of the milling media 
etc. After milling is complete, the dispersion of active material is separated from 
the grinding media by simple sieving or filtration. With either of the above modes 
the preferred amounts and ratios of the ingredients of the mill grind will vary 
widely depending upon the specific materials and the intended applications. The 
contents of the milling mixture comprise the mill grind and the milling media. 
The mill grind comprises pigment, dispersant and a liquid carrier such as water. 
For aqueous ink jet inks, the pigment is usually present in the mill grind at 1 to 50 
weight %, excluding the milling media. The weight ratio of pigment to dispersant 
is 20:1 to 1:2. The high speed mill is a high agitation device, such as those 
manufactured by Morehouse-Cowles, Hockmeyer et al. </p><p num="0014">The dispersant is another ingredient in the mill grind. It can be 
either a small molecule or a polymer. Preferred dispersants used in the present 
invention include sodium dodecyl sulfate, acrylic and styrene-acrylic copolymers, 
such as those disclosed in U. S. Pat. Nos. 5,085,698 and 5,172,133, and sulfonated 
polyesters and styrenics, such as those disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 4,597,794. Other 
patents referred to above in connection with pigment availability also disclose a 
wide variety of dispersants. The dispersant used in the examples is potassium N-methyl-N-oleoyl 
taurate (K-OMT). </p><p num="0015">The milling time can vary widely and depends upon the pigment, 
mechanical means and residence conditions selected, the initial and desired final  
 
particle size, etc. For aqueous mill grinds using the preferred pigments, 
dispersants, and milling media described above, milling times will typically range 
from 1 to 100 hours. The milled pigment concentrate is preferably separated from 
the milling media by filtration. </p><p num="0016">The pigment particles useful in the invention may have any particle 
sizes which can be jetted through a print head. Preferably, the pigment particles 
have a mean particle size of less than about 0.5 micron, more preferably less than 
about 0.2 micron. </p><p num="0017">A wide variety of organic and inorganic pigments, alone or in 
combination, may be selected for use in the present invention. Colorant particles 
which may be used in the invention include pigments as disclosed, for example in 
U.S. Patents 5,026,427; 5,086,698; 5,141,556; 5,160,370; and 5,169,436. The 
exact choice of pigments will depend upon the specific application and 
performance requirements such as color reproduction and image stability. 
Pigments suitable for use in the present invention include, for example, azo 
pigments, monoazo pigments, disazo pigments, azo pigment lakes, β-Naphthol 
pigments, Naphthol AS pigments, benzimidazolone pigments, disazo 
condensation pigments, metal complex pigments, isoindolinone and isoindoline 
pigments, polycyclic pigments, phthalocyanine pigments, quinacridone pigments, 
perylene and perinone pigments, thioindigo pigments, anthrapyrimidone pigments, 
flavanthrone pigments, anthanthrone pigments, dioxazine pigments, 
triarylcarbonium pigments, quinophthalone pigments, diketopyrrolo pyrrole 
pigments, titanium oxide, iron oxide, and carbon black. Typical examples of 
pigments which may be used include Color Index (C. I.) Pigment Yellow 1, 2, 3, 
5, 6, 10, 12, 13, 14, 16, 17, 62, 65, 73, 74, 75, 81, 83, 87, 90, 93, 94, 95, 97, 98, 
99, 100, 101, 104, 106, 108, 109, 110, 111, 113, 114, 116, 117, 120, 121, 123, 
124, 126, 127, 128, 129, 130, 133, 136, 138, 139, 147, 148, 150, 151, 152, 153, 
154, 155, 165, 166, 167, 168, 169, 170, 171, 172, 173, 174, 175, 176, 177, 179, 
180, 181, 182, 183, 184, 185, 187, 188, 190, 191, 192, 193, 194; C. I. Pigment 
Orange 1, 2, 5, 6, 13, 15, 16, 17, 17:1, 19, 22, 24, 31, 34, 36, 38, 40, 43, 44, 46, 
48, 49, 51, 59, 60, 61, 62, 64, 65, 66, 67, 68, 69; C. I. Pigment Red 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,  
 
7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 21, 22, 23, 31, 32, 38, 48:1, 48:2, 48:3, 
48:4, 49:1, 49:2, 49:3, 50:1, 51, 52:1, 52:2, 53:1, 57:1, 60:1, 63:1, 66, 67, 68, 81, 
95, 112, 114, 119, 122, 136, 144, 146, 147, 148, 149, 150, 151, 164, 166, 168, 
169, 170, 171, 172, 175, 176, 177, 178, 179, 181, 184, 185, 187, 188, 190, 192, 
194,200,202,204,206,207,210,211,212,213,214,216,220,222,237,238, 
239,240,242,243,245,247,248,251,252,253,254,255,256,258,261,264; 
C.I. Pigment Violet 1, 2, 3, 5:1, 13, 19, 23, 25, 27, 29, 31, 32, 37, 39, 42, 44, 50; 
C.I. Pigment Blue 1, 2, 9, 10, 14, 15:1, 15:2, 15:3, 15:4, 15:6, 15, 16, 18, 19, 24:1, 
25, 56, 60, 61, 62, 63, 64, 66; C.I. Pigment Green 1, 2, 4, 7, 8, 10, 36, 45; C.I. 
Pigment Black 1, 7, 20, 31, 32, and C.I. Pigment Brown 1, 5, 22, 23, 25, 38, 41, 
42. In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the pigment is C.I. Pigment Blue 
15:3, C.I. Pigment Red 122, C.I. Pigment Yellow 155, C.I. Pigment Yellow 74, 
C.I. Pigment Black 7 or bis(phthalocyanylalumino)tetraphenyldisiloxane as 
described in U.S. Pat. No. 4,311,775. </p><p num="0018">In the case of organic pigments, the ink may contain up to 
approximately 20% pigment by weight, but will generally be in the range of 
approximately 0.1 to 10%, preferably approximately 0.1 to 5%, by weight of the 
total ink composition for most ink jet printing applications. If an inorganic 
pigment is selected, the ink will tend to contain higher weight percentages of 
pigment than with comparable inks employing organic pigments. </p><p num="0019">Instead of pigment, a dye can also be used in the current invention. 
Preferably, the dye is a water insoluble dye. To make the ink, the water insoluble 
dye can be dispersed or encapsulated into water dispersible particles as disclosed 
in U. S. Serial No. 10/020,694, filed December 14, 2001. A broad range of water-insoluble 
dyes may be used in the invention such as an oil dye, a disperse dye, or a 
solvent dye, such as Ciba-Geigy Orasol Red G, Ciba-Geigy Orasol Blue GN, 
Ciba-Geigy Orasol Pink, and Ciba-Geigy Orasol Yellow. Preferred water-insoluble 
dyes can be xanthene dyes, methine dyes, polymethine dyes, 
anthroquinone dyes, merocyanine dyes, azamethine dyes, azine dyes, 
quinophthalone dyes, thiazine dyes, oxazine dyes, phthalocyanine dyes, mono or 
poly azo dyes, and metal complex dyes. More preferably, the water insoluble dyes  
 
can be an azo dye such as a water insoluble analog of the pyrazoleazoindole dye 
disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 6,468,338, and the arylazoisothiazole dye disclosed in 
U. S. Patent 4,698,651, or a metal-complex dye, such as the water-insoluble 
analogues of the dyes described in U.S. Patents 5,997,622 and 6,001,161, i.e., a 
transition metal complex of an 8-heterocyclylazo-5-hydroxyquinoline. The 
solubility of the water insoluble dye used in the present invention should be less 
than 1 g/L in water, and more preferably less than 0.5 g/L in water. </p><p num="0020">The water insoluble dye can be present in any effective amount in 
the ink of the present invention, usually up to about 20% by weight of an ink jet 
ink composition, and preferably from about 0.05 to 15 wt. %. </p><p num="0021">The polymer latex used in this invention can be homopolymer or 
copolymer or cross-linked polymer prepared with at least one halogenated vinyl 
monomer, and optionally other ethylenically-unsaturated monomers such that the 
latex can be stabilized in a water-based medium. The polymer latex contains an 
ethylenically-unsaturated monomer capable of addition polymerization. The 
ethylenically-unsaturated monomers which can be used in the invention include, 
for example, the following monomers and their mixtures: acrylic acid, methacrylic 
acid, ethacrylic acid, methyl acrylate, ethyl acrylate, ethyl methacrylate, benzyl 
acrylate, benzyl methacrylate, propyl acrylate, propyl methacrylate, iso-propyl 
acrylate, iso-propyl methacrylate, butyl acrylate, butyl methacrylate, hexyl 
acrylate, hexyl methacrylate, octadecyl methacrylate, octadecyl acrylate, lauryl 
methacrylate, lauryl acrylate, hydroxyethyl acrylate, hydroxyethyl methacrylate, 
hydroxyhexyl acrylate, hydroxyhexyl methacrylate, hydroxyoctadecyl acrylate, 
hydroxyoctadecyl methacrylate, hydroxylauryl methacrylate, hydroxylauryl 
acrylate, phenethylacrylate, phenethyl methacrylate, 6-phenylhexyl acrylate, 6-phenylhexyl 
methacrylate, phenyllauryl acrylate, phenyllaurylmethacrylate, 3-nitrophenyl-6-hexyl 
methacrylate, 3-nitrophenyl-18-octadecyl acrylate, 
ethyleneglycol dicyclopentyl ether acrylate, vinyl ethyl ketone, vinyl propyl 
ketone, vinyl hexyl ketone, vinyl octyl ketone, vinyl butyl ketone, cyclohexyl 
acrylate,3-methacryloxypropyl-dimethylmethoxysilane, 3-methacryloxypropylmethyldimethoxysilane, 
3-methacryloxypropyl-pentamethyldisiloxane,  
 
3-methacryloxypropyltris-(trimethylsiloxy)silane, 3-acryloxypropyldimethylmethoxysilane, 
acryloxypropylmethyldimethoxysilane, trifluoromethyl 
styrene, trifluoromethyl acrylate, trifluoromethyl methacrylate, tetrafluoropropyl 
acrylate, tetrafluoropropyl methacrylate, heptafluorobutyl methacrylate, isobutyl 
acrylate, isobutyl methacrylate, 2-ethylhexyl acrylate, 2-ethylhexyl methacrylate, 
isooctyl acrylate, isooctyl methacrylate, N,N-dihexyl acrylamide, N,N-dioctyl 
acrylamide, N,N-dimethylaminoethyl acrylate, N,N-dimethylaminoethyl 
methacrylate, N,N-diethylaminoethyl acrylate, N,N-diethylaminoethyl 
methacrylate, piperidino-N-ethyl acrylate, vinyl propionate, vinyl acetate, vinyl 
butyrate, vinyl butyl ether, and vinyl propyl ether ethylene, styrene, vinyl 
carbazole, vinyl naphthalene, vinyl anthracene, vinyl pyrene, methyl methacrylate, 
methyl acrylate, alpha-methylstyrene, dimethylstyrene, methylstyrene, 
vinylbiphenyl, glycidyl acrylate, glycidyl methacrylate, glycidyl propylene, 2-methyl-2-vinyl 
oxirane, vinyl pyridine, aminoethyl methacrylate, 
aminoethylphenyl acrylate, maleimide, N-phenyl maleimide, N-hexyl maleimide, 
N-vinyl-phthalimide, and N-vinyl maleimide poly(ethylene glycol) methyl ether 
acrylate, polyvinyl alcohol, vinyl pyrrolidone, vinyl 4-methylpyrrolidone, vinyl 4-phenylpyrrolidone, 
vinyl imidazole, vinyl 4-methylimidazole, vinyl 4-phenylimidazole, 
acrylamide, methacrylamide, N,N-dimethyl acrylamide, N-methyl 
acrylamide, N-methyl methacrylamide, aryloxy dimethyl acrylamide, N-methyl 
acrylamide, N-methyl methacrylamide, aryloxy piperidine, and N,N-dimethyl 
acrylamide acrylic acid, methacrylic acid, chloromethacrylic acid, maleic 
acid, allylamine, N,N-diethylallylamine, vinyl sulfonamide, sodium acrylate, 
sodium methacrylate, ammonium acrylate, ammonium methacrylate, 
acrylamidopropanetriethylammonium chloride, methacrylamidopropanetriethylammonium 
chloride, vinyl-pyridine hydrochloride, sodium vinyl 
phosphonate and sodium 1-methylvinylphosphonate, sodium vinyl sulfonate, 
sodium 1-methylvinyl-sulfonate, sodium styrenesulfonate, sodium 
acrylamidopropanesulfonate, sodium methacrylamidopropanesulfonate, and 
sodium vinyl morpholine sulfonate, allyl methacrylate, allyl acrylate, butenyl 
acrylate, undecenyl acrylate, undecenyl methacrylate, vinyl acrylate, and vinyl  
 
methacrylate; dienes such as butadiene and isoprene; esters of saturated glycols or 
diols with unsaturated monocarboxylic acids such as, ethylene glycol diacrylate, 
ethylene glycol dimethacrylate, triethylene glycol dimethacrylate, 1,4-butanediol 
dimethacrylate, 1,3-butanediol dimethacrylate, pentaerythritol tetraacrylate, 
trimethylol propane trimethacrylate and polyfunctuional aromatic compounds such 
as divinylbenzene. </p> <p num="0022">The halogenated vinyl monomer used in the present invention can 
be vinyl chloride, vinylidene chloride, vinyl fluoride, vinylidene fluoride, vinyl 
bromide and vinylidene bromide, chloromethacrylic acid and the like. </p><p num="0023">Surfactants that can be used in the present invention to synthesize 
the polymers include, for example, a sulfate, a sulfonate, a cationic compound, a 
reactive surfactant, an amphoteric compound, and a polymeric protective colloid. 
Specific examples are described in "McCutcheon's Emulsifiers and Detergents: 
1995, North American Editor" and will be known to those skilled in the art. </p><p num="0024">Depending on the types of initiators used, the reaction temperature 
can vary from about 30°C to about 90°C. Preferably the reaction temperature is at 
least 40°C, and most preferably at least 50°C. To ensure that no free monomer is 
present, usually the reaction is continued for a time after the monomer addition. 
Also, more initiator may need to be added as a scavenger during the final stage of 
the reaction to increase the reaction conversion. </p><p num="0025">Addition polymerization initiators useful in the practice of the 
invention include, for example, azo and diazo compounds, such as 
2,2'-azobisisobutyronitrile, 2,2'-azobis(2,4-dimethyl valeronitrile), 
2,2'-azobis(2,3-dimethyl butyronitrile), 2,2'-azobis(2-methyl butyronitrile), 
2,2'-azobis(2,3,3-trimethyl butyronitrile), 2,2'-azobis(2-isopropyl butyronitrile), 
1,1'-azobis(cyclohexane-1-carbonitrile), 2, 2'-azobis(4-methoxyl-2,4-dimethyl 
valeronitrile), 2-(carbamoylazo)isobutyronitrile, 4,4'-azobis(4-cyanovaleric acid), 
and dimethyl -2,2'azobis isobutyrate, or peroxide compounds, such as butyl 
peroxide, propyl peroxide, butyryl peroxide, benzoyl isobutyryl peroxide, and 
benzoyl peroxide, or water soluble initiators, for example, sodium persulfate, and 
potassium persulfate, or any redox initiators. Preferred initiators are the oil  
 
soluble initiators. Examples of particularly suitable initiators are azo, peroxide, 
persulfate, and redox initiators. The initiators may be used in an amount varying 
from about 0.2 to 4 weight percent or higher by weight of the total monomers. A 
chain transfer agent such as butyl mercaptan, may also be used to control the 
properties of the polymer formed. </p><p num="0026">The polymers can be made via emulsion polymerization, dispersion 
polymerization, suspension polymerization, grand milling, or solution/bulk 
polymerization and then post-emulsification. Detailed information about the 
process and the stabilizers can be found in <i>"Emulsion Polymerization and 
Emulsion Polymers "</i> (P. A. Lovell, M. S. El-Aasser, John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd., 
England, 1997). </p> <p num="0027">The polymer latex employed in the invention in general has a Tg of 
-50 to 150 °C, preferably 5 to 100 °C, most preferably 10 to 80 °C. </p> <p num="0028">The polymer latex employed in the invention in general have an 
average particle size of less than 2 µm, preferably less than 0.5 µm, more 
preferably less than 0.25 µm. </p> <p num="0029">The polymer latex used in the invention is present in the ink jet ink 
generally from 0.1% to 20% by weight, preferably from 0.5% to 10% by weight. </p><p num="0030">All monomer units in the polymer latex used in the invention may 
be hydrophobic. Alternatively, the polymer latex may contain at least one 
hydrophilic monomer unit. The content of hydrophilic monomer unit is less than 
50 mole % of the total monomer units in the polymer latex, preferably less than 20 
mole % of the total monomer units in the polymer latex, most preferably less than 
5 mole % of the total monomer units in the polymer latex. </p><p num="0031">The hydrophilic monomer unit in the polymer latex may be selected 
from the group consisting of acrylic acid, methacrylic acid, chloromethacrylic 
acid, maleic acid, allylamine, N,N-diethylallylamine, vinyl sulfonamide, sodium 
acrylate, sodium methacrylate, ammonium acrylate, ammonium methacrylate, 
acrylamidopropane-triethylammonium chloride, methacrylamidopropanetriethylammonium 
chloride, vinyl-pyridine hydrochloride, sodium vinyl 
phosphonate and sodium 1-methylvinylphosphonate, sodium vinyl sulfonate,  
 
sodium 1-methylvinyl-sulfonate and sodium styrenesulfonate. The hydrophilic 
monomers can also be non-ionic, such as ethyoxytriethylene glycol methacrylate, 
methoxypolyethylene oxide methacrylate, methoxypropylene oxide acrylate, 
polyethyleneoxide methacrylate, polyethylenoxide acrylate, N-vinyl pyrrolidone 
and the like. </p><p num="0032">The aqueous carrier medium for the ink composition is water or a 
mixture of water and at least one water miscible co-solvent. Selection of a 
suitable mixture depends on requirements of the specific application, such as 
desired surface tension and viscosity, the selected pigment, drying time of the 
pigmented ink jet ink, and the type of paper onto which the ink will be printed. 
Representative examples of water-miscible co-solvents that may be selected 
include (1) alcohols, such as methyl alcohol, ethyl alcohol, n-propyl alcohol, 
isopropyl alcohol, n-butyl alcohol, sec-butyl alcohol, t-butyl alcohol, iso-butyl 
alcohol, furfuryl alcohol, and tetrahydrofurfuryl alcohol; (2) ketones or 
ketoalcohols such as acetone, methyl ethyl ketone and diacetone alcohol; (3) 
ethers, such as tetrahydrofuran and dioxane; (4) esters, such as ethyl acetate, ethyl 
lactate, ethylene carbonate and propylene carbonate; (5) polyhydric alcohols, such 
as ethylene glycol, diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol, tetraethylene glycol, 
propylene glycol, polyethylene glycol, glycerol, 2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol 1,2,6-hexanetriol 
and thioglycol; (6) lower alkyl mono- or di-ethers derived from 
alkylene glycols, such as ethylene glycol mono-methyl (or -ethyl) ether, diethylene 
glycol mono-methyl (or -ethyl) ether, diethylene glycol mono-butyl (or -ethyl) 
ether, propylene glycol mono-methyl (or -ethyl) ether, poly(ethylene glycol) butyl 
ether, triethylene glycol mono-methyl (or -ethyl) ether and diethylene glycol dimethyl 
(or -ethyl) ether; (7) nitrogen containing cyclic compounds, such as 
pyrrolidone, N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone, and 1,3-dimethyl-2-imidazolidinone; and (8) 
sulfur-containing compounds such as dimethyl sulfoxide, 2,2'-thiodiethanol, and 
tetramethylene sulfone. </p><p num="0033">The amount of aqueous carrier medium is in the range of 
approximately 70 to 99 weight %, preferably approximately 90 to 98 weight %, 
based on the total weight of the ink. A mixture of water and a polyhydric alcohol,  
 
such as diethylene glycol, is useful as the aqueous carrier medium. In a preferred 
embodiment, the inks contain from about 5 to about 60 weight % of water 
miscible organic solvent based on the total weight of the aqueous carrier medium. </p><p num="0034">Jet velocity, separation length of the droplets, drop size and stream 
stability are greatly affected by the surface tension and the viscosity of the ink. 
Pigmented ink jet inks suitable for use with ink jet printing systems should have a 
surface tension in the range of about 20 dynes/cm to about 60 dynes/cm and, more 
preferably, in the range 30 dynes/cm to about 50 dynes/cm. Control of surface 
tensions in aqueous inks is accomplished by additions of small amounts of 
surfactants. The level of surfactants to be used can be determined through simple 
trial and error experiments, usually about 0.1% to about 6%, preferably, 0.5% to 
about 4% by weight of the total ink composition. Anionic, cationic and nonionic 
surfactants may be selected from those disclosed in U. S. Patents 5,324,349; 
4,156,616 and 5,279,654 as well as many other surfactants known in the ink jet 
ink art. Commercial surfactants include the Surfynols® from Air Products; the 
Zonyls® from DuPont and the Fluorads® from 3M. Preferred surfactants can be 
silicon surfactants or fluorinated surfactants. Preferred silicon surfactants are 
available from BYK-Chemie as BYK surfactants, and from Crompton Corp, as 
Silwet® surfactants. Commercially available fluorinated surfactants can be the 
Zonyls® from DuPont and the Fluorads® from 3M, they can be used alone or in 
combination with other surfactants. </p><p num="0035">A humectant is added to the composition employed in the process 
of the invention to help prevent the ink from drying out or crusting in the orifices 
of the ink jet printhead. Polyhydric alcohols useful in the composition employed 
in the invention for this purpose include, for example, ethylene glycol, diethylene 
glycol, triethylene glycol, propylene glycol, tetraethylene glycol, polyethylene 
glycol, glycerol, 2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol, 1,2,6-hexanetriol and thioglycol. The 
humectant may be employed in a concentration of from about 10 to about 50 % by 
weight of the entire ink composition. In a preferred embodiment, diethylene 
glycol or a mixture of glycerol and diethylene glycol is employed a concentration 
of between 10 and 20 % by weight of the entire ink composition.  </p><p num="0036">The ink has physical properties compatible with a wide range of 
ejecting conditions, i.e., driving voltages and pulse widths for thermal ink jet 
printing devices, driving frequencies of the piezo element for either a drop-on-demand 
device or a continuous device, and the shape and size of the nozzle. </p><p num="0037">A penetrant (0-10% by weight) may also be added to the ink 
composition employed in the process of the invention to help the ink penetrate the 
receiving substrate, especially when the substrate is a highly sized paper. A 
preferred penetrant for the inks employed in the present invention is n-propanol at 
a final concentration of 1-6 % by weight. </p><p num="0038">A biocide (0.01-1.0% by weight) may also be added to prevent 
unwanted microbial growth which may occur in the ink over time. A preferred 
biocide for the inks employed in the present invention is Proxel® GXL (Zeneca 
Colours Co.) at a concentration of 0.05-0.5 % by weight. Additional additives 
which may optionally be present in ink jet inks include thickeners, conductivity 
enhancing agents, anti-kogation agents, pH buffering agents, drying agents, and 
defoamers. </p><p num="0039">Ink jet inks made using water-dispersible polymers employed in 
this invention are employed in ink jet printing wherein liquid ink drops are 
applied in a controlled fashion to an ink receiving substrate, by ejecting ink 
droplets from plurality of nozzles, or orifices, in a print head of ink jet printers. </p><p num="0040">Commercially available ink jet printers use several different 
methods to control the deposition of the ink droplets. Such methods are generally 
of two types: continuous stream and drop-on-demand. </p><p num="0041">In drop-on-demand systems, a droplet of ink is ejected from an 
orifice directly to a position on the ink receiving layer by pressure created by, for 
example, a piezoelectric device, an acoustic device, or a thermal process 
controlled in accordance digital data signals. An ink droplet is not generated and 
ejected through the orifices of the print head unless it is needed. Ink jet printing 
methods, and related printers, are commercially available and need not be 
described in detail.  </p><p num="0042">To accelerate the printing speed and increase durability, an extra 
heating step can be added during the process of printing the ink composition of 
this invention. This heating step can be employed either during printing or after 
printing. In a preferred embodiment, heating is employed both during and after 
printing. Heating will help fluids to spread on a non-absorbing substrate as well 
as to accelerate its evaporation. Heating can also help ink components to 
penetrate into the non-absorbing substrate by swelling mechanism. The heating 
step during printing can be achieved using a heating means so that the non-absorbing 
substrate is heated to elevated temperature during the process of 
printing. The substrate is preferably heated to between 30 °C and 90 °C, more 
preferably between 40 to 70 °C. During the heating step after printing, the printed 
substrate is heated to elevated temperature using a heating means where substrate 
is heated to a temperature range between 50 °C and 150 °C, more preferably 
between 80 to 120 °C. Various methods may be used for the means of heating, for 
example, using light irradiation, a hot air source or an electrical heater. For the 
heating step during printing, an electrical heater or an infrared lamp is preferred. 
For the heating step after printing, light irradiation such as an infrared lamp is 
preferred. Optionally, an infrared absorbing material can be employed in the ink 
of the present invention to assist the heating by an infrared lamp. </p><p num="0043">The following examples illustrate the utility of the present 
invention. </p><heading><b>EXAMPLES</b></heading><heading><b>Preparation of Pigment Dispersion</b></heading><p num="0044">The magenta pigment dispersion contains: 300 g of Polymeric 
beads, mean diameter of 50 µm (milling media); 30 g of quinacridone magenta 
pigment Pigment Red 122 (Sun Chemicals); 9 g of Oleoyl methyl taurine, (OMT) 
Potassium salt and 208 g of Deionized water, and 0.2 g of Proxel GXL ® (biocide 
from Zeneca). The above components were milled in a 2 liter double walled 
vessel obtained from BYK-Gardner using a high energy media mill manufactured 
by Morehouse-Cowles Hochmeyer. The mill was run for approximately 8 hours at  
 
room temperature. The dispersion was separated from the milling media by 
filtering the millgrind through a 4-8 µm KIMAX® Buchner Funnel obtained from 
VWR Scientific Products. At the end of milling, additional water is added to the 
dispersion so that the pigment is about 10.0% by weight of the total final 
dispersion and the biocide is about 230ppm by weight of the total final dispersion. 
The particle size is about 30 nm as measured by MICROTRAC II Ultrafine 
particle analyzer (UPA) manufactured by Leeds &amp; Northrup. </p><heading><b>Preparation of Polymer Latex Particle Dispersions</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of Comparative Polymer Dispersion 1 (PC- 1: Acrylate)</u></heading><p num="0045">400 g of deionized water and 0.6 g Olin 10G® surfactant were 
charged to a 1-liter, three-neck round-bottom flask equipped with a mechanical 
stirrer and nitrogen inlet. The solution was purged with nitrogen for 30 min and 
heated to 80°C in a constant temperature bath. 172.8 g of methyl acrylate and 7.2 
g of 2-acrylamido-2-methyl-1-propanesufonic acid (sodium salt) were added and 
stirred for three minutes. 16.4 g of 10% sodium persulfate solution and 5.5 g of 
10% sodium metabisulfite solution were added to initiate the polymerization. 
Polymerization was continued for one hour and heated one more hour at 80°C. 
The temperature was reduced to 65-70 °C and 1ml each of t-butyl hydroperoxide 
(10%) and sodium formaldehyde bisulfite (10%) were post-added. The latex was 
cooled and filtered. The dispersion contains 30% solid by weight. </p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of Comparative Polymer Dispersion 2 (PC-2:Watersoluble)</u></heading><p num="0046">Water soluble polymer Jonrez IJ-4655@ is obtained from Westvaco 
as a styrene acrylic polymer solution at 25% Solids. This polymer dispersion is 
designated as Comparative Polymer Dispersion 2 (PC-2). </p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of Polymer Latex 1 of the Invention (P-1)</u></heading><p num="0047">160 g deionized water were charged to a 500 mL 1-neck round 
bottom flask equipped with mechanical stirrer. The flask was first flushed with 
nitrogen for 20 minutes, then immersed in a constant temperature bath at 40 °C.  
 
Afterwards, 0.25 g of potassium persulfate, 0.35 g sodium metabisufite, 2.0 g 
Triton 770 (30% active), 4.0 g of ethyl acrylate, 36.0 g vinylidene chloride were 
added to the flask. The polymerization reaction was continued for additional 12 
hours. The latex was cooled and filtered. The final polymer latex dispersion 
contained 13.52% solid by weight and the average particle size is 0.056 micron. 
This polymer dispersion is designated as Polymer Latex 1 (P-1). </p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of Latex Polymer 2 of the Invention (P-2)</u></heading><p num="0048">160 g deionized water were charged to a 500 mL 1-neck round 
bottom flask equipped with mechanical stirrer. The flask was first flushed with 
nitrogen for 20 minutes, then immersed in a constant temperature bath at 40 °C. 
Afterwards, 0.25 g of potassium persulfate, 0.35 g sodium metabisufite, 2.0 g 
Triton 770 (30% active), 2.0 g of ethyl acetate, 18.0 g vinylidene chloride, 19.2 g 
of methyl methacrylate, and 1.6 g of sodium 2-sulfo-1,1-dimethylethyl acrylamide 
(50%) were added to the flask. The polymerization reaction was continued for 
additional 12 hours. The latex was cooled and filtered. The final polymer latex 
dispersion contained 15.5% solid by weight and the average particle size is 0.062 
micron. This polymer dispersion is designated as Polymer Latex 1 (P-2). </p><heading><b>Ink Formulation</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Ink 1 of the Invention (I-1: Ink Containing Polymer Latex 1)</u></heading><p num="0049">To prepare the Ink-1, 4.36 g of the Magenta Pigment Dispersion 
(10% active), 0.2 g Silwet® L-7608 (Crompton Corp.), 2.0 g diethylene glycol 
and 1.0 g di(propyleneglycol) methyl ether (Dowanol® DPM), 0.6 g 2-pyrrolidone, 
and 2.90 g of Polymer Latex 1 (13.52 % active) were added together 
with distilled water so that the final weight of the ink was 20.0 g. The final ink 
contained 2.18% Pigment Red 122, 1.0% Silwet® L-7608, 10.0% diethylene 
glycol, 5% di(propyleneglycol) methyl ether, 3% pyrrolidone and 2.0% polymer 
latex 1. The solution was filtered through a 3 µm polytetrafluoroethylene filter.  </p><heading><u style="single">Ink 2 of the Invention (I-2)</u></heading><p num="0050">Ink-2 of the present invention was prepared similar to Ink-1 except 
that the amount of Polymer Latex 1 (13.52% active) was increased from 2.90 g to 
6.51 g such that the final ink contained 4.4% polymer latex 1 by weight of the total 
ink. </p><heading><u style="single">Ink 3 of the Invention (I-3)</u></heading><p num="0051">Ink-3 of the present invention was prepared similar to Ink-1 except 
that 2.53 g of Polymer Latex 2 (15.5% active) was used instead of Polymer Latex 
1 such that the final ink contained 2.0% of Polymer Latex 2 by weight of the total 
ink. </p><heading><u style="single">Ink 4 of the Invention (I-4)</u></heading><p num="0052">Ink-4 of the present invention was prepared similar to Ink-3 except 
that amount of Polymer Latex 2 (15.5% active) was increased from 2.53 g to 5.68 
such that the final ink contained 4.4% of Polymer Latex 2 by weight of the total 
ink. </p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Ink 1 (C-1)</u></heading><p num="0053">The comparative ink 1 was prepared similar to Ink-1 of the 
Invention except that 1.30 g of Comparative Polymer Dispersion PC-1 (30% 
active) was used instead of Polymer Latex 1. The final Ink contained 2.0% of 
Comparative Polymer Dispersion PC-1. </p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Ink 2 (C-2)</u></heading><p num="0054">The comparative ink 2 was prepared similar to Comparative Ink 1 
except that the amount of Comparative Polymer Dispersion PC-1 (30% active) 
was increased from 1.30 g to 2.90 g such that the final Ink contained 4.4% of 
Comparative Polymer Dispersion PC-1.  </p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Ink 3 (C-3)</u></heading><p num="0055">The Comparative Ink 3 was prepared similar to Comparative Ink 1 
of the Invention except that 1.57 g of Comparative Polymer Dispersion PC-2 (25% 
active) was used instead of Comparative Polymer Dispersion 1. The final ink 
contained 2.0% of Comparative Polymer Dispersion PC-2. </p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Ink 4 (C-4)</u></heading><p num="0056">The Comparative Ink 4 was prepared similar to Comparative Ink 3 
of the Invention except that the amount of Comparative Polymer Dispersion PC-2 
(25% active) was increased from 1.57 g to 3.52 g such that the final ink contained 
4.4% of Comparative Polymer Dispersion PC-2. </p><heading><u style="single">Comparative Ink 5 (C-5)</u></heading><p num="0057">The Comparative Ink 5 of the invention was prepared similar to Ink 
1 of the invention except that 4.36 g of distilled water was used instead of Polymer 
Latex 1 so that the final ink did not contain any polymer latex. </p><heading><b>Ink Firability Test</b></heading><p num="0058">The Inks of the present invention were filled into Epson 880 empty 
cartridges and printing was done with an Epson 880 Ink jet printer, using the 
above inks. All inks of the invention fired well through the Epson 880 printer, no 
nozzles were clogged. The inks were left in printer for over 48 hours and the 
above printing test was repeated. All the nozzles were firing with minimum 
cleaning cycles without any problems for the inks of the present invention. </p><heading><b>Ink Printing Reliability &amp; Printing Test</b></heading><p num="0059">The inks of the present invention were filled into an ink bag and 
tested using an Inkjet ink fixture apparatus having a Brother piezo printhead with a 
heatable printing drum. Ink drop volume was measured vs time to test the printing 
reliability. A 1" by 10" non-absorbing vinyl substrate, a multi-purpose inkjet cast 
vinyl (MPI 1005 #226 from Avery Graphics), was mounted on the printing drum.  
 
The drum was kept at 50 °C during printing. A 0.7"x4" Dmax density patch print 
target was printed. After printing, the samples were further heated at 90 °C for 1 
minute using an infrared lamp. A successful test result occurred when 67 pL ink 
droplets of the ink composition were continuously fired through the printhead at a 
rate of 7,500 drops/second for at least an hour without nozzle failure or ink droplet 
misdirection. </p><p num="0060">To compare the effectiveness of printing, a controlled printing test 
was done when the printing drum was not heated, the resulted image can be wiped 
off with paper towel very easily and the prints show much lower density compared 
with samples printed on the heated drum. Another controlled printing test was 
done when the sample was not heated after printing. The resulted prints can wiped 
off easily immediately after printing, and the imaged area took up to several weeks 
to be dried to touch at room temperature. </p><heading><b>Durability Test</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Sample Preparation</u></heading><p num="0061">A non-absorbing vinyl substrate, a multi-purpose inkjet cast vinyl 
(MPI 1005 #226 from Avery Graphics) was cut into 14 by 25 cm in size and 
placed on a heated coating block with temperature at about 40 °C. The above inks 
were filled into an airbrush (Paasche Sirbrush Set H-3 available from Paasche 
Airbrush Company, Harwood Heights, IL) connected to compressed house air. 
The pressure of the airbrush was adjusted to about 20 lb. such that smooth ink 
flow was obtained. The inks were sprayed onto the heated vinyl substrates 
described above. Uniform coatings of the inks were obtained. The selected 
samples were then heated at 90 °C for 1 minute using an infrared lamp. </p><heading><u style="single">Dry Rub Resistance Test</u></heading><p num="0062">The dry rub resistance test was carried out by rubbing the samples 
with a dry Q-tip for 4 passes under a consistent pressure in the inked area. The 
color loss in the treated sample area and the color transfer to Q-tip were examined  
 
visually and a rating of the dry rub resistance was given as follows on a scale of 0 
to 5. 
<sl><li>0: Best, No color loss, and/or color transfer; </li><li>1: hardly visible amount of color loss and/or color transfer; </li><li>2: visible amount of color loss and/or color transfer; </li><li>3: some color loss and color transfer; </li><li>4: large amount of color loss and color transfer; </li><li>5: Worst, almost complete color loss and color transfer. </li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Wet Rub Resistance Test</u>:</heading><p num="0063">A wet rub resistance test was carried out by placing an 
approximately 2.54 cm diameter water droplet on the ink-coated sample surface 
for 5 minutes, after which the excess water was wiped off with a paper towel. The 
above treated area was then rubbed with a dry paper towel for 4 passes under a 
consistent pressure a 3.5 cm diameter area. The color loss in the treated sample 
area and the color transfer to the paper towel were examined visually and a rating 
of the wet rub resistance was given similar as above on a scale of 0 to 5, 0 being 
the best and 5 being the worst. Both of the dry and wet rub resistance test results 
are shown in Table 1.  <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Ink </entry><entry align="center">Polymer </entry><entry align="center">Polymer/Pigment Ratio </entry><entry align="center">Dry Rub Rating </entry><entry align="center">Wet Rub Rating </entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-1</entry><entry align="center">PC-1</entry><entry align="center">1/1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-3</entry><entry align="center">PC-2</entry><entry align="center">1/1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">3 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-1</entry><entry align="center">P-1</entry><entry align="center">1/1</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">1 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-3</entry><entry align="center">P-2</entry><entry align="center">1/1</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">1 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-2</entry><entry align="center">PC-1</entry><entry align="center">2/1</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">1 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-4</entry><entry align="center">PC-2</entry><entry align="center">2/1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-2</entry><entry align="center">P-1</entry><entry align="center">2/1</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-4</entry><entry align="center">P-2</entry><entry align="center">2/1</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">1 </entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-5</entry><entry align="center">N/A</entry><entry align="center">N/A</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">5 </entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0064">From the above table, it is evident that the presence of polymer 
latex in the ink significantly improves the image durability under both dry and wet 
conditions compared to the inks without polymer latex. The inks of the present 
invention show further advantages in image durability compared to the 
comparative inks. </p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An ink jet printing method, comprising the steps of 
<claim-text><claim-text>A) providing an ink jet printer that is responsive to digital data signals; </claim-text><claim-text>B) loading said printer with an ink jet recording element </claim-text><claim-text>C) loading said printer with an ink jet ink composition comprising an 
aqueous ink jet ink composition comprising: 
<claim-text><claim-text>a pigment; </claim-text><claim-text>a polymer latex containing at least one halogenated vinyl monomer; </claim-text><claim-text>at least one surfactant; and </claim-text><claim-text>a humectant; and </claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>D) printing on said ink jet recording element accompanied by a heating 
step using said ink jet ink composition in response to said digital data signals. </claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 wherein said heating step is applied 
during the process of printing using a heating means wherein said ink recording 
element is heated to an elevated temperature. </claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method of claim 2 wherein said temperature is between 
30°C and 90°C. </claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 wherein said heating step is applied after 
the process of printing using a heating means wherein said ink recording element 
is heated to an elevated temperature. </claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method of claim 4 wherein said temperature is between 
50°C and 150°C. </claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 wherein said heating step is first applied 
during the process of printing using a first heating means wherein said ink 
recording element is heated to a first elevated temperature, said ink recording 
 
element is further heated to a second elevated temperature after the process of 
printing using a second heating means. </claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method of claim 6 wherein said first elevated temperature is 
between 30°C to 90°C and said second elevated temperature is between 50°C to 
150°C. </claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 wherein said ink jet recording element 
comprises a non-absorbing substrate. </claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 wherein the weight ratio of said pigment 
to said polymer is 1:20 to 20:1. </claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method of claim 1 wherein said pigment has a particle size 
of less than 0.5 micron. </claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>