<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1090954-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1090954" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="23628294" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010411"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1090954-A1" status="new" fvid="23094126"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1090954</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010411</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00121514-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00121514</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000929</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-41127899-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>41127899</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991004</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B  33/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C01B  33/44        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   9/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   9/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K  21/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K  21/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C01B  33/44</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   9/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K  21/14</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Organoton/Polymer-Zusammensetzungen mit flammhemmenden Eigenschaften</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Organoclay/polymer compositions with flame retardant properties</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new"  lang="FR">Compositions argile organique/polymère avec des propriétés ignifuges</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="WO-1997030950-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997030950</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>RHEOX INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>RHEOX, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>RHEOX, INC.</last-name><address><street>Wyckoffs Mill Road</street><city>Hightstown, New Jersey 08520</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KAIZERMAN JACOB</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ROSS MARK</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KAIZERMAN, JACOB</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ROSS, MARK</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KAIZERMAN, JACOB</last-name><address><street>703 Ocean Avenue 24</street><city>Bradley Beach 07720</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ROSS, MARK</last-name><address><street>Parkview Court</street><city>Newtown, PA 18940</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Groening, Hans Wilhelm, Dipl.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>BOEHMERT &amp;amp; BOEHMERT Franz-Joseph-Strasse 38</street><city>80801 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention is directed to polymer compositions with flame
retardant properties that are made from a polymer blended using a defined
process with a smectite clay that has been reacted with a specified mixture of
organic materials.</p><p>The inventive compositions have the property that when the organically
modified clay is added to the polymer, a composite results which has flame-retardant
properties and is based on the finding that degree of dispersion of a
smectite organoclay in a polymer matrix will give the compositions flame-retardant
properties. Further, it has been found that it is very important to proper
functioning of the flame retardant polymer compositions that they have the
organoclay dispersed in the polymer such that it is not completely exfoliated.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single"><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></u></heading><heading><u style="single">Field of the Invention</u>:</heading><p num="0001">The present invention is directed to polymer compositions with flame
retardant properties that are made from a polymer blended using a defined
process with a smectite clay that has been reacted with a specified mixture of
organic materials.</p><p num="0002">The inventive compositions have the property that when the organically
modified clay is added to the polymer, a composite results which has flame-retardant
properties.</p><p num="0003">This invention covers improved polymer compositions with increased char
yield and fire retardancy. The use of organoclay is a new, environmentally-benign
approach to improve the fire retardance of these polymers. Such
polymers will find use, for example, as architectural and construction materials
such as interior panels, home sidings, and roofing pads and shingles, automotive
parts particularly for car interiors, and in ship and military uses where fire
retardancy is required. </p><heading><u style="single">Background of the Invention</u>:</heading><p num="0004">It has long been a goal when using plastic materials to render them
resistant to burning. Building codes and other government rules issued by
regulatory bodies often require that plastic materials used as structural members
or other useful articles pass a series of precise tests to insure that they will not
accelerate a fire. In the past, many flame retardant polymer formulations have
been developed. These include several classes of materials such as
halogenated additives, char chemical producers, and chemical water generators.
Each of these prior art materials has its particular strengths and weaknesses as
a fire retardant.</p><p num="0005">The use of synthetic polymers has grown dramatically over the last three
decades, as have the research efforts of scientists on controlling polymer
flammability. Research and development to that end has focused primarily on fire
retardant additives. One way to improve fire resistance has relied on the
introduction of aromatic rings into the polymer structure; an increase in the
aromaticity yields higher char residues that normally correlate with higher oxygen
index and lower flammability. The high cost of these specialized materials and
the specialized processing techniques required have limited their use and makes
the search for an effective additive even more focused.</p><p num="0006">The effectiveness of fire retardant fillers has also been limited because
the large amounts required for effective performance make processing difficult
and the additives often negatively affect some properties of the final polymer
compositions. High loadings of fillers can cause problems in the plastic such as
loss of strength and flexibility, and discoloration. The relatively high loading of fire 
retardants needed in some plastics to achieve sufficient reduction in flame
spread can also be very expensive.</p><p num="0007">Particularly disadvantaged prior art materials used as fire retardants are
additives containing halogens. Problems associated with these materials include
high costs, high use levels, and potential environmental problems. Brominated
aromatic compounds, for example, have been widely used as fire retardants for
polyolefins and other thermoplastics. In addition to the poor economics of using
these materials, other concerns include suspected negative environmental
impact and their well-established tendency to generate corrosive by-products
during processing or when exposed to fire.</p><p num="0008">These concerns have established the need for fire retardant systems for
polymers with reduced halogen content. It is thus the object of the instant
invention to provide a flame retardant blend comprising reduced levels of
halogenated compounds.</p><heading><u style="single">Description of the Prior Art</u></heading><p num="0009">In the past organoclays have been blended with polymers as fire
retardants in circumstances where an additional fire retardant additive was used.
Several general articles on polymer-clay blends have included in their discussion
a section about fire retardancy. - see for example Miller, B.; <u style="single">Plastics</u><u style="single">World</u>,
No.10, October 1997, pp. 36-38.</p><p num="0010">An early patent by Berk Ltd., U.S. Patent No. 3,516,959, describes an
organophilic clay used with at least one additional flame retardant. A variety of
thermoplastic polymer composites is described. No attempt is made to show the 
effect of an organoclay by itself on flame retardancy nor how the degree of
dispersion would influence this.</p><p num="0011">Several specific patents discuss clay-polymer composites in the context of
fire retardance. U.S. Patent No. 4,472,538 discloses clay treated with a
chlorosilane to initiate polymerization with an adsorbed monomer to give a
composite with excellent flame retardance. The use of silane initiator gives a
polymer chemically bound to the clay surface. A second object of the patent is to
create a uniformly dispersed polymer-clay composite. No flame testing was done
to indicate the degree of flame retardance nor are there comparisons of differing
levels of dispersion.</p><p num="0012">U.S. Patent No. 5,854,327 by Bridgestone/Firestone discloses a roofing
membrane that is made flame retardant by a complex mixture of ingredients. The
clay component is treated to make it reactive with the EPDM rubber matrix but
no specific flame-retardant properties are associated with the clay.</p><p num="0013">A General Electric patent, European Patent No. 899,301 A1, describes a
non-halogenated flame retardant resin-molding polyester composition that
contains organoclay, polysiloxane, and compounds of boron and phosphorus.</p><p num="0014">A number of authors have made statements in the literature that to
achieve the best properties from a smectite clay-polymer composite, it is
necessary to achieve the best dispersion possible. This can be described as
completely exfoliating the smectite clay into individual platelets separated by the
polymer matrix. It has been surmised that it is optimum that the platelets should
be in insufficient contact to be chemically associated with each other. It is the
fully dispersed state that is frequently held up as the ideal for all developments in
the smectite clay/organoclay composite areas. </p><p num="0015">Several papers and patents explicitly mention the critical need for platelet
interlayer distances to be greater than 70Å to have complete
exfoliation/delamination. These papers include: Giannelis, E.P.; <u style="single">Polymer Layered
Silicate Nanocomposites</u>, Advanced Materials 8, No. 1, pp. 29-35 (1996); and
Kishnamoorti, R.; Vaia, R.A.; Giannelis, E.P.; <u style="single">Structure and Dynamics of
Polymer Layered Silicated Nancomposites</u>, Chemistry of Materials 8, No. 8, pp.
1728, (1996).</p><p num="0016">Several prior art patents go into significant detail on the differences
between incompletely exfoliated states and the benefits of fully delaminated clay-polymer
composites. A Toyota patent, U.S. Patent No. 4,739,007, asserts that
the best improvements in mechanical properties are observed in composites with
platelet spacings greater than or equal to 100Å. It is clear from the prior literature
that fully exfoliated clay-polymer systems have been the goal of researchers
working in the field.</p><p num="0017">It is noted that several papers on flame-retardant polymer compositions
not using organoclays show evidence that less than full exfoliation has benefits.
For example, Nyden, M.R. and Gilman, J.W.; <u style="single">Molecular Dynamics Simulations of
the Thermal Degradation of Nano-Confined Polypropylene</u>, Computational and
Theoretical Polymer Science, Vol. 7, No. 3/4, pp. 191-8 (1997), shows
polypropylene confined by graphite. A minimum in the burning mass loss rate
was calculated for polypropylene confined between the graphite sheets at 30Å.
The author did not show any experimental evidence to support the theoretical
conclusions.</p><p num="0018">A United States patent based on a Japanese invention describes
polymeric compositions using calcium carbonate and other materials including 
kaolin clays other than smectites as fire retardant additives to polymers - see
U.S. Patent No. 5,025,057. United States Patent No. 5,091,462, also based on a
Japanese invention, shows the addition of an inorganic filler to crystalline
polypropylene to improve the heat resistance of the polypropylene in the form of
a four or five ingredient resin composition. The inorganic filler can be a
polyamide partially modified with hectorite.</p><p num="0019">Organically modified clays, also called organoclays, have been used for
many years as rheological additives for solvent based systems. They are usually
produced by making a water dispersion of a phyllosilicate clay, usually a
bentonite or hectorite clay, and adding to it a quaternary ammonium salt of a
long chain fatty acid to produce an organically modified clay by cation exchange
reaction and adsorption. The reaction causes the organoclay to coagulate from
the water dispersion which allows for its isolation by filtration and washing.</p><p num="0020">For example, Rheox, Inc. has issued patents describing organoclay
compositions useful as rheological additives which comprise the reaction product
of smectite clay, quaternary ammonium compounds and in addition in some
embodiments certain organic anions, wherein a quaternary-organic anion
complex is reacted with the smectite clay. These patents include representative
U.S. Patent Nos. 4,412,018, 4,434,075, and 4,517,112 (descriptions herein
incorporated by reference) and are described to include a large variety of organic
cationic compounds, in combination with one or more organic anion compounds.
These patents do not describe the use of these organoclays to provide
thermoset or thermoplastic polymers with fire retardant properties.</p><p num="0021">A recently allowed United States patent application by the assignee
hereof (U.S. Patent Application No. 09/064,216, filed April 22, 1998) describes a 
hybrid organoclay system that gives improved dispersion in a polyester resin
over conventional organoclays or simple intercalates when forming a
nanocomposite. See also pending U.S. Patent Application No. 09/317,963 filed
by assignee hereto entitled Smectite Clay/Organic Chemical/Polymer
Compositions Useful as Nanocomposites.</p><heading><u style="single"><b>OBJECT AND SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></u></heading><heading><u style="single">Object of the Invention</u>:</heading><p num="0022">It is an object of the invention to provide a modified clay/polymer
composition using a thermoset or thermoplastic polymer and a smectite clay
modified with organic chemicals, i.e. an organoclay. The organoclay used is
dispersed into thermoset or thermoplastic polymers to form a composition with
fire retardancy.</p><p num="0023">It is a specific object of the invention that the organoclay can be made
inexpensively and the polymer composition in some circumstances needs no
other material except the organoclay to possess acceptable fire retarding
properties.</p><heading><u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u>:</heading><p num="0024">The present invention is of a composition comprising a polymer system
and a smectite clay modified with an organic chemical composition. The modified
clay is an organic chemical/clay mixture prepared by the reaction of a smectite
clay and one or more quaternary ammonium compounds, and/or optionally one
or more organic materials. The organoclay is then blended into a polymer matrix
to give the invention composition. The behavior of the resultant 
plastic/organoclay product is qualitatively different in fire retardant properties
from that exhibited by the plastic, polymer, or resin by itself.</p><p num="0025">This invention provides a practical way to disperse organoclays based on
smectite clays into polymers without resorting to expensive processes or special
resin materials to insure compatibility with the polymer matrix. The resulting
compositions have fire retardant properties.</p><p num="0026">In one important embodiment, we have determined that a substantial gain
of fire retardancy occurs if a clay-polymer composite is produced in a way that
causes the organoclay to substantially but not completely delaminate in the
polymer. Testing in a thermoplastic polyolefin elastomer (TPO) has shown a
strong, correlation between degree of delamination (exfoliation) of the
organoclay and flame testing. By delaminate it is meant dispersed or exfoliated.</p><p num="0027">In one aspect, the present invention provides a polymer composition that
comprises: (a) one or more smectite clays, modified with (1) one or more
quaternary ammonium compounds at between about 50 to 150% of its cation
exchange capacity, and also in some embodiments with (2) one or more defined
organic materials to form an organoclay composition and
<sl><li>(b) one or more polymer resins;</li></sl>
   whereby the organoclay composition is mixed or blended into the polymer
resin in a manner so that the organoclay is not completely delaminated.</p><p num="0028">Further advantages and features of the invention, as well as the scope,
nature and utilization of the invention, will become apparent to those of ordinary
skill in the art from the description of the preferred embodiment of the invention
set forth below. </p><heading><u style="single">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u></heading> <p num="0029">The clay and polymer compositions of this invention may be made using a
variety of materials and by a variety of methods disclosed hereafter, or which will
appear obvious when the disclosure of this patent occurs. Applicants do not
intend to limit the materials or methods of manufacture or use of such additives
by the following descriptions.</p><p num="0030">This invention is in one main embodiment, synthetic polymer
compositions, particularly thermoset or thermoplastic compostions, which have
flame-retardant properties.</p><p num="0031">The synthetic thermoset or thermoplastic polymers with which this
invention is concerned (hereinafter referred to, for convenience, simply as
"thermoset or thermoplastic polymers") are those which are combustible and, in
addition to being combustible, which melt or drip when heated beyond their
softening point.</p><p num="0032">While the flammability of these polymers can be substantially reduced by
the incorporation therein of one or more flame retardants, they represent (with
the use of present additives) a considerable fire hazard. When heated beyond
their softening point, they will melt and hot material will drip or flow onto
surrounding areas and increase the risk of ignition of surrounding materials. This
can be true even when the polymer itself does not burn. Examples of
thermoplastic polymers are polystyrene, polyethylene, and polyamides, such as
nylon. Examples of thermoset polymers are urea-formaldehyde polymers,
epoxies, and melamine-formaldehyde polymers. </p><p num="0033">The tendency of thermoplastic polymers to melt and drip when heated to
temperatures above their softening points can be substantially reduced by
incorporating into them a small proportion (that is, less than 10% based on the
weight of the polymer) of the organically modified clay of this invention.</p> <p num="0034">Synthetic polymers suitable for this invention include a wide variety of
resins and plastic materials, both polar or non-polar. Such materials can include
polyolefins such as polyethylenes, polypropylenes, polybutylenes,
polymethylpentane, polyisoprenes, and copolymers thereof; copolymers of
olefins and other monomers such as ethylene-vinyl acetate, ethylene acid
copolymers, ethylene-vinyl alcohol, ethylene-ethyl acrylate, and ethylene-methyl
acrylate. Ionomers are also useful and comprise metal salts of polyolefins
copolymerized with acrylic acid.</p> <p num="0035">Additional polymers are polyamides (nylons), polyphenylene ether, and
polyamide-imide copolymers. Various polyesters are useful such as polyarylates,
polybutylene terephthalate, and polyethylene terephthalate. Engineering resins
such as polycarbonate, polyetherimide, polyetheretherketone, polyphenylene
sulfide, and thermoplastic polyimides are suitable candidates. Polystyrene and
copolymers such as ABS, SAN, ASA, and styrene-butadiene are appropriate.
Also included are the sulfone based resins such as polysulfone,
polyethersulfone, and polyarylsulfone. Elastomers are also candidates for the
present invention and comprise a wide variety of useful materials including
olefinic TPE's, polyurethane TPE's, and styrenic TPE's. Chlorinated polymers
such as PVC, and polyvinylidene dichloride can also be used. In addition,
miscible or immiscible blends of the above polymers are useful for this invention. </p> <p num="0036">The present invention accordingly comprises a polymer composition
comprising a thermoset or thermoplastic polymer, and incorporated therein, an
organoclay defined hereafter.</p><p num="0037">One important aspect of the invention is a clay and polymer composition
comprising:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>A reaction product obtained by the intercalation and reaction of (a) one
or more smectite clays; (b) one or more quaternary ammonium
compounds and<u style="single">/or</u> (c) one or more organic materials; which is then
dispersed in a manner not to be completely exfoliated into;</li><li>(d) one or more polymers.</li></ul></p><p num="0038">Clays useful for element a) are smectite clays. Such clays are swellable
layered clays which contain individual platelets. Useful swellable layered
materials include phyllosilicates such as smectite clay minerals, e.g.,
montmorillonite, particularly sodium montmorillonite; bentonite; hectorite;
saponite; stevensite; beidellite; and the like.</p><p num="0039">The clays used are typically smectite clays, particularly bentonite and
hectorite, Smectite clays possess some structural characteristics similar to the
better-known minerals talc and mica. Their crystal structures consist of two-dimensional
layers formed by fusing two silica tetrahedral sheets to an edge-shared
dioctahedral or trioctahedral sheet of either alumina (for example
bentonite) or magnesia (for example hectorite) - each of the different smectite
clays having somewhat different structures. Stacking of these layers in nature in
depths of hundreds or more is caused by ionic and weak Van der Waals forces.
The area between the platelets is occupied by cations which balance the charge 
deficiency that is generated by isomorphous substitution (often called
disharmonies) within the platelet lattices.</p><p num="0040">As used herein the term "interlayer spacing" refers to the distance
between the internal faces of adjacent smectite clay platelet layers, either in the
dry state or as incorporated into a polymer. The interlayer spacing is measured
by standard X-Ray Diffraction techniques.</p><p num="0041">Central to the instant invention is the degree of dispersion of the
organoclay in the polymer. When the organoclay is dispersed in the polymer
such that only a few polymer chains are between the clay platelets, the system is
referred to as being substantially intercalated. When measured by X-Ray
Diffraction such a material will display an interlayer spacing of approximately 15
to 60Å, depending on the polymer. The extreme of dispersion is exfoliation, and
is defined as a state in which the clay particles are substantially or completely
separated by the polymer matrix. Interlayer platelet spacings in an exfoliated
system are typically greater than 70Å, and such systems are easily characterized
by X-Ray Diffraction by the near or total absence of any reflection peaks from the
organoclay. As defined above, the required state of dispersion for the
organoclays of this invention consists of intercalation, or a mixture of
intercalation and exfoliation, but <u style="single">not</u> complete exfoliation.</p><p num="0042">The clays which may be used in the present invention are preferably
smectite-type clays having a cationic exchange capacity of at least 50
milliequivalents per 100 grams of clay, 100% active clay basis, as determined by
the well-known ammonium acetate or methylene blue methods. Preferred
smectite materials are bentonite and hectorite clays having a negative charge on 
the layers ranging from about 0.15 to about 0.9 charges per formula unit and a
commensurate number of exchangeable metal cations in the interlayer spaces.</p><p num="0043">Smectite-type clays are well known in the art and are commercially
available from a variety of sources. Prior to use in the invention, the clays may
preferably be converted to the sodium form if they are not already in this form.
This may be conveniently carried out by preparing an aqueous clay slurry and
passing the slurry through a bed of cation exchange resin in the sodium form.
Alternatively, the clay can be mixed with water and a soluble sodium compound,
such as sodium carbonate, sodium hydroxide, etc., and the mixture sheared,
such as with a pugmill or extruder.</p><p num="0044">Representative smectite clays useful in accordance with the present
invention are the following:</p><heading><u style="single">Montmorillonite</u></heading><p num="0045"><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">[(Al<sub>4-x</sub>Mg<sub>x</sub>)Si<sub>8</sub>O<sub>20</sub>(OH)<sub>4-f</sub>F<sub>f</sub>]<sub>x</sub>R<sup>+</sup></st32:che>
where 0.55 &lt; x &lt; 1.10, f &lt; 4 and R is selected from the group consisting of Na,
Li, NH<sub>4</sub>, and mixtures thereof;</p><heading><u style="single">Bentonite</u></heading><p num="0046"><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">[(Al<sub>4-x</sub>Mg<sub>x</sub>)(Si<sub>8-y</sub>Al<sub>y</sub>)O<sub>20</sub>(OH)<sub>4-f</sub>F<sub>f</sub>]<sub>(x+y)</sub>R<sup>+</sup></st32:che>
where 0 &lt; x &lt; 1.10, 0 &lt; y &lt; 1.10, 0.55 &lt; (x + y) &lt; 1.10, f &lt; 4 and R is selected
from the group consisting of Na, Li, NH<sub>4</sub>, and mixtures thereof;</p><heading><u style="single">Hectorite</u></heading><p num="0047"><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">[(Mg<sub>6-x</sub>Li<sub>x</sub>)Si<sub>8</sub>0<sub>20</sub>(OH)<sub>4-f</sub>F<sub>f</sub>]<sub>x</sub>R<sup>+</sup></st32:che> 
where 0.57 &lt; x &lt; 1.15, f &lt; 4 and R is selected from the group consisting of Na,
Li, NH<sub>4</sub>, and mixtures thereof;</p><heading><u style="single">Saponite</u></heading><p num="0048"><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">[(Mg<sub>6-y</sub>Al<sub>y</sub>)Si<sub>8-x-y</sub>Al<sub>x+y</sub>0<sub>20</sub>(OH)<sub>4-f</sub>F<sub>f</sub>]<sub>x</sub>R<sup>+</sup></st32:che>
where 0.58 &lt; x &lt; 1.18, 0 &lt; y &lt; 0.66, f &lt;4 and R is selected from the group
consisting of Na, Li, NH<sub>4</sub>, and mixtures thereof; and</p><heading><u style="single">Stevensite</u></heading><p num="0049"><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">[Mg<sub>6-x</sub>Si<sub>8</sub>0<sub>20</sub>(OH)<sub>4-f</sub>F<sub>f</sub>]<sub>2x</sub>R<sup>+</sup></st32:che>
where 0.28 &lt; x &lt; 0.57, f = 4 and R is selected from the group consisting of Na,
Li, NH<sub>4</sub>, mixtures thereof.</p><heading><u style="single">Beidellite</u></heading><p num="0050"><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">[(Al<sub>4+y</sub>)(Si<sub>8-x-y</sub>Al<sub>x+y</sub>)O<sub>20</sub>(OH)<sub>4-f</sub>F<sub>f</sub>]<sub>x</sub>R<sup>+</sup></st32:che>
where 0.55 &lt; x &lt; 1.10, 0 &lt; y &lt; 0.44, f &lt; 4 and R is selected from the group
consisting of Na, Li, NH<sub>4</sub>, and mixtures thereof;</p><p num="0051">The preferred clays used in the present invention are bentonite and
hectorite. Bentonite and its properties are described at length in the chapter
entitled "Bentonite," in Carr, D., ed., <u style="single">Industrial Minerals and Rocks,</u> 6th Edition,
published by the Society For Mining, Metallurgy and Exploration, Colorado,
1994. A particularly preferred clay is hectorite.</p><p num="0052">It will be understood that both sheared and non-sheared forms of the
above-listed smectite clays may be employed. In addition, the smectite clay 
employed can be either crude (containing gangue or non-clay material) or
beneficiated (gangue removed). The ability to use crude clay in the smectite-type
clay of this invention represents a substantial cost savings, since the clay
beneficiation process and conversion to the sodium form do not have to be
carried out.</p><p num="0053">Compound(s) (b) of the invention is one or more quaternary ammonium
compounds. Particularly useful are quaternary ammonium compounds which
include those having the formula:
<img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="48" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="45"/>
wherein R<sub>1</sub> comprises a group selected from (i) linear or branched aliphatic,
aralkyl, or aromatic hydrocarbon groups having from 8 to 30 carbon atoms or (ii)
alkyl or alkyl-ester groups having 8 to 30 carbon atoms; R<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>3</sub>, and R<sub>4</sub> are
independently selected from the group consisting of (a) linear or branched
aliphatic hydrocarbon, fluorocarbon, or other halocarbon groups having from 1 to
about 30 carbon atoms; (b) aralkyl or aromatic groups having from 6 to about 30
carbon atoms, (c) alkoxylated groups containing from 1 to about 80 moles of
alkylene oxide; (d) amide groups, (e) oxazolidine groups, (f) allyl, vinyl, or other
alkenyl or alkynyl groups possessing reactive unsaturation and having from 2 to
about 30 carbon atoms, and (g) hydrogen: and X' comprises an anion selected
from the group consisting of chloride, methyl sulfate, acetate, iodide, and
bromide, preferably chloride. For purposes of this invention, quaternary 
phosphonium and sulfonium based salts are defined as within the definition of
quaternary ammonium compound.</p><p num="0054">The raw materials used to make the quaternary amonium compounds can
be derived from natural oils such as tallow, soya, coconut and palm oil. Useful
aliphatic groups in the above formula may be derived from other naturally
occurring oils including various vegetable oils, such as corn oil, coconut oil,
soybean oil, cottonseed oil, castor oil and the like, as well as various animal oils
or fats. The aliphatic groups may likewise be petrochemically derived from, for
example, alpha olefins. Representative examples of useful branched, saturated
radicals included 12-methylstearyl and 12-ethylstearyl.</p><p num="0055">Examples of useful aromatic groups include benzyl and benzylic-type
materials derived from benzyl halides, benzhydryl halides, trityl halides, halophenylalkanes
wherein the alkyl chain has from 1 to 30 carbon atoms, such as 1-halo-1-phenyloctadecane;
substituted benzyl moieties, such as those derived
from <i>ortho</i>-, <i>meta</i>-, and <i>para</i>-chlorobenzyl halides, <i>para</i>-methoxybenzyl halides,
<i>ortho</i>-, <i>meta</i>-, and <i>para</i>-nitrilobenzyl halides, and <i>ortho</i>-, <i>meta</i>-, and <i>para</i>-alkylbenzyl
halides wherein the alkyl chain contains from 1 to 30 carbon atoms;
and fused ring benzyl-type moieties, such as those derived from 2-halomethylnaphthalene,
9-halomethylanthracene, and 9-halomethylphenanthrene,
wherein the halo group comprises chloro, bromo, or
any other such group which serves as a leaving group in the nucleophilic attack
of the benzyl type moiety by a nitrogen atom to generate a substituted amine.</p><p num="0056">Examples of other aromatic groups include aromatic-type substituents
such as phenyl and substituted phenyl; N-alkyl and N,N-dialkyl anilines, where
the alkyl groups contain between 1 and 30 carbon atoms; ortho-, meta-, and 
para-nitrophenyl, ortho-, meta-, and para-alkyl phenyl, wherein the alkyl group
contains between 1 and 30 carbon atoms; 2-,3-, and 4-halophenyl wherein the
halo group is defined as chloro, bromo, or iodo; and 2-, 3-, and 4-carboxyphenyl
and esters thereof, where the alcohol of the ester is derived from an alkyl
alcohol, wherein the alkyl group contains between 1 and 30 carbon atoms, aryl
such as phenol, or aralkyl such as benzyl alcohols; and fused ring aryl moieties
such as naphthalene, anthracene, and phenanthrene.</p><p num="0057">Preferred quaternary ammonium compounds for purposes of the invention
comprises a quaternary ammonium salt that contains at least one, preferably two
or three, hydrocarbon chains having from about 8 to about 30 carbon atoms and
either no hydrophilic carbon chains or having hydrophilic radicals having a total
of about 9 moles of ethylene oxide or less.</p><p num="0058">Some examples of preferred quaternary ammonium compounds to make
the compositions of this invention are: dimethyl bis[hydrogenated tallow]
ammonium chloride (2M2HT), methyl benzyl bis[hydrogenated tallow] ammonium
chloride (MB2HT), and methyl tris[hydrogenated tallow alkyl] chloride (M3HT).</p><p num="0059">Materials suitable for optional element (c) of this invention include
materials listed as anionic components in US 4,412,018, 4,434,075, and
4,577,112. These include materials that are capable of reacting with component
(b) of this invention and for intercalation with component (a) as an alkyl
quarternary ammonium-organic anion complex. The molecular weight (gram
molecular weight) of the organic anion is preferably 3,000 or less, and most
preferably 1,000 or less and contains at least one anionic moiety per molecule as
disclosed herein. The organic anion is preferably derived from an organic acid 
having a pK<sub>A</sub> less than about 11.0. As indicated, the source acid must contain at
least one ionizable hydrogen having the preferred pK<sub>A</sub> in order to allow the
formation of the alkyl quarternary ammonium-organic anion complex.</p><p num="0060">Exemplary types of suitable acidic functional organic compounds useful in
this invention include:
<sl><li>(1) Carboxylic acids including:
<sl><li>a) benzene carboxylic acids such as benzoic acid; ortho-, iso- and
terephthalic acid; 1,2,3-benzenetricarboxylic acid; 1,2,4-benzenetricarboxylic
acid; 1,3,5-benzenetricarboxylic acid; 1,2,4,5-benzenetetracarboxylic
acid; 1,2,3,4,5,6-benzenehexacarboxylic
acid (mellitic acid);</li><li>b) alkyl carboxylic acids having the formula CH<sub>3</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub>-COOH,
wherein n is a number from 0 to 20; such compounds include
acetic acid; pentanoic acid; hexanoic acid; heptanoic acid; octanoic
acid; nonanoic acid; decanoic acid; undecanoic acid; lauric acid;
tridecanoic acid; tetradecanoic acid; pentadecanoic acid;
hexadecanoicanoic acid; heptadecanoic acid; octadecanoic acid
(stearic acid); nonadecanoic acid; eicosonic acid.</li><li>c) Alkyl dicarboxylic acids having the formula HOOC-(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub>-COOH
wherein n is 0 to 8 such as oxalic acid; malonic acid; succinic acid;
glutaric acid; adipic acid; pimelic acid; suberic acid; azelaic acid;
sebacic acid;</li><li>d) Hydroxyalkyl carboxylic acids such as citric acid; tartaric acids;
malic acid; mandelic acid; and 12-hydroxystearic acid; </li><li>e) unsaturated alkyl carboxylic acids such as maleic acid; fumaric
acid; and cinnamic acid;</li><li>f) Fused ring aromatic carboxylic acids such as naphthalenic acid
and anthracenecarboxylic acid;</li><li>g) Cycloaliphatic acids such as cyclohexanecarboxylic acid;
cyclopentanecarboxylic acid; furancarboxylic acids.</li></sl></li><li>(2) Organic sulfuric acids including:
<sl><li>a) sulfonic acids including:
<sl><li>1) benzenesulfonic acids such as benzenesulfonic acid;
phenolsulfonic acid; dodecylbenzenesulfonic acid;
benzenedisulfonic acid; benzenetrisulfonic acids; <i>para</i>-toluenesulfonic
acid; and</li><li>2) alkyl sulfonic acids such as methanesulfonic acid;
ethanesulfonic acid; butanesulfonic acid; butanedisulfonic
acid; sulfosuccinate alkyl esters such as dioctyl
succinylsulfonic acid; and alkyl polyethoxy-succinyl sulfonic
acid; and</li></sl></li><li>b) alkyl sulfates such as the lauryl half ester of sulfuric acid and the
octadecyl half ester of sulfuric acid.</li></sl></li><li>3) Organophosphorus acids including phosphonic acids, phosphinic acids,
thiophosphinic acids, phosphites, and phosphates as described in US Patent
No. 4,412,018 </li><li>4) Phenols such as phenol; hydroquinone; t-butylcatechol; p-methoxyphenol;
and naphthols.</li><li>5) Thioacids as described in US Patent No. 4,412,018.</li><li>6) Amino acids such as the naturally occurring amino acids and derivatives
thereof such as 6-aminohexanoic acid; 12-aminododecanoic acid; N-phenylglycine;
and 3-aminocrotonic acid.</li></sl></p><p num="0061">Other materials useful for element c) can be selected from a wide
variety of non-anionic materials as described in U.S. Patent Application
No. 09/064216, descriptions herein incorporated by reference. These
materials are either water soluble, liquid, or can be made into a liquid at
reaction temperature so that the aforementioned clay materials absorbs
them. These materials can be any of a wide range of materials and can
have a wide range of molecular weights. Materials of this type suitable for
element (c) of this invention include polyurethanes; polyamides;
polyesters; polycarbonates; polyepoxides and polyolefins. Such materials
also include polyethers (polymers and copolymers) based on ethylene
oxide, butylene oxide, propylene oxide, phenols and bisphenols;
polyesters (polymers and copolymers) based on aliphatic and aromatic
diols and polyurethanes based on aliphatic and aromatic diisocyanates,
polyamides (polymers and copolymers) based on aliphatic and aromatic
diamines, and polycarbonates (polymers and copolymers) based on
aliphatic or aromatic diols; polycarboimides (polymers and copolymers)
based on tetrabasic acids and diamines, vinyl polymers and copolymers
based on vinyl monomers, styrene and derivatives of styrene; acrylic
polymers and copolymers based on acrylic monomers; copolymers based 
on styrene, vinyl and acrylic monomers; polyolefin polymers and
copolymers based on ethylene, propylene and other alphaolefin
monomers; polymers and copolymers based on dienes, isobutylenes and
the like; and copolymers based on dienes, styrene, acryl and vinyl
monomers. Other organic materials can include monomeric materials that
have the functionality of the materials described above. The definition of
element c) does not include quaternary ammonium compounds.</p><p num="0062">Specific preferred examples of useful non-anionic organic materials
include THIXATROL VF-10 and THIXATROL VF-20 which are liquid
polyester amide copolymers made by RHEOX. Examples of other specific
materials are polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP) or its hydrolysis product,
polyvinyl alcohol (PVA), polymethacrylamide, poly(N,N-dimethylacrylamide),
poly(N-isopropylacrylamide), poly(N-acetamidacrylamide),
poly(N-acetimidomethacrylamide), polyvinyloxazolidone, and
polyvinylmethyl oxazolidone, polyoxypropylene, polyoxyethylene and
copolymers thereof.</p><p num="0063">The materials (b) and (c) can be reacted together, or in any order, with the
smectite clay and the resultant product blended with the polymer to produce the
inventive composition.</p><p num="0064">The amount of quaternary compound and optional organic compound
used can vary over wide ranges. This amount is defined as the millequivalent
ratio which is the number of milliequivalents (m.e.) of the organic cation in the
organoclay per 100 grams of clay, 100% active clay basis.</p><p num="0065">Normally, where only a quaternary is employed, at least 90 to 100 m.e. of
organic cation, more typically 100 to 140 m.e. of quaternary salt based on 100 g 
of 100% active clay are preferred although lower and higher ratios are also
useful.</p><p num="0066">It is typical that component (c), if present, is used at an amount of 5 to 100
milliequivalents, and more preferably 10 to 50 m.e., per 100g of clay, 100%
active basis.</p><p num="0067">The organoclays useful in the composites of this invention may be
prepared in a number of ways. One is to first disperse the smectite clay in water.
The clay is preferably dispersed in water at a concentration of from about 1 to
80%, most preferably from about 2 to 8% by weight. Optionally, the slurry may
be centrifuged to remove non-clay impurities that constitute about 10% to 50% of
the starting clay composition. If the optional organic material is to be part of the
composition, it is added to the clay/water dispersion and mixed. This mixture can
then be heated and is ion exchanged with a quaternary ammonium compound to
form the final organoclay as a coagulate, which is washed with water and
isolated by filtration. If only the optional organic material is used, it can be added
to the purified clay/water slurry an adsorbed onto the clay. The clay is then
isolated by drying.</p><p num="0068">A second general method to prepare this invention uses dry clay that is
intimately mixed with the organic material in a heated device, such as an
extruder. The mixture can also have some water present to facilitate
intercalation. After the addition is complete, the quaternary ammonium
compound and/or organic material is added and the final product is isolated. This
composition can be washed with water and dried. </p><p num="0069">Both of the methods mentioned above where both components (b) and (c)
are used can be modified by either: 1) reversing the order of addition, i.e.,
reacting the clay with the quaternary ammonium ion followed by the organic
material; or 2) adding the quaternary ammonium compound and organic material
to the clay simultaneously.</p><p num="0070">The reaction is preferably followed by drying and grinding the organoclay
product. Incorporation of the organoclay into the plastic resin can be
accomplished by mixing or blending the organoclay by any means that can
create sufficient shear. The shear can be provided by any appropriate method
such as mechanical, thermal shock, pressure changes, or ultrasonics as known
in the art. Particularly useful are methods where a flowable polymer is mixed with
the organoclay by mechanical means such as extruders, roll mills, stirrers,
Banbury® type mixers, Brabender® type mixers, and continuous mixers. Other
methods for making this invention can be postulated by those knowledgeable in
the art.</p><p num="0071">Polymer compositions that are made by these methods using the
compositions of this invention will exhibit improved fire retardancy when sufficient
energy is imparted to the blend to create dispersed but not completely
delaminated mixtures. This can be achieved by manipulation of various
processing variables, for example: a) adjusting process temperature to raise or
lower melt viscosity, b) adjusting time of processing or residence time, and c)
changing machinery components such as extruder screw segments to provide a
different shear processing profile.</p><p num="0072">A preferred method of determining a useful composition, as shown in the
examples, is that it exhibits a discernable d<sub>001</sub> peak for the smectite clay by XRD. </p><p num="0073">The preferred amounts and types of clays, quaternary ammonium
compounds, organic materials, and polymers used to make the compositions of
this invention will vary depending upon the type of matrix polymer that each
composition is to be mixed into, with the goal to achieve incomplete delamination
of the clay platelets in the matrix polymer.</p><p num="0074">In an important aspect of this invention, the milliequivalent ratio of clay to
organic compound(s) is important. A preferred clay/organic chemical composition
for purposes of the instant invention is comprised of:
<sl><li>1. The reaction product of:
<sl><li>(a) a smectite-type clay having a cation exchange capacity of
preferably at least 50 milliequivalents per 100 grams of clay; and</li><li>(b) one or more quaternary ammonium compounds in an amount of
from about 50% to about 150% of the cation exchange capacity of
the smectite-type clay and/or</li><li>(c) one or more organic materials in an amount of 1% to 50% of the
weight of the smectite-type clay; and</li></sl></li><li>2. One or more polymer resins or copolymers where the amount of organoclay
from the reaction of (a), (b) and (c) above is from 0.1% to 40% of the weight
of the polymer resin.</li></sl></p><p num="0075">The smectite-type clay can be sheared in slurry form prior to reaction with
the organic materials, or treated in solid form with a pugmill or similar apparatus. </p><p num="0076">The following examples further illustrate the invention hereof, but is not
intended to limit its scope. All parts and percentages are defined without
prejudice.</p><heading><u style="single">Example I</u></heading><p num="0077">In a baffled three liter reactor with efficient stirrung was placed 1500 g of a
prehydrated aqueous hectorite clay slurry (total solids 3.15%). The slurry was
heated to 70°C with stirring. A mixture of dimethyl bis(hydrogenated tallow)
ammonium chloride, 35.01 g, and sodium lauryl sulfate, 4.09 g in a small amount
of isopropanol was added. The reaction was mixed at temperature for 45
minutes and filtered on a large Buchner funnel. The product was washed by
redispersing in 1L water and heated with stirring to 70°C, then refiltered. The
resulting product was dried at 60°C to give a moisture content below 0.5%, and
ground to less than 325 mesh.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><p num="0078">The organoclay from Example 1 was incorporated at 5.5% loading into a
compounded TPO Elastomer formulation based on Adflex KS353P, a product of
Montell, Inc. A variety of conditions was used. The resulting films were analyzed
by X-Ray Diffraction and gave the following results: <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1"><b>Example 2 Results</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Height Ratio<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">Area Ratio<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">Flame Test<!--footnotes removed--> (in/min)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Unprocessed</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">&gt;8</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">6.5</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry><entry align="center">3.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">31.3</entry><entry align="center">5.8</entry><entry align="center">5.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">53.8</entry><entry align="center">9.5</entry><entry align="center">&gt;8</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">82.1</entry><entry align="center">12.1</entry><entry align="center">&gt;8<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Discussion of Results:</u></heading><p num="0079">Table I above shows the peak heights and areas of the d<sub>001</sub> reflection of
the organoclay and the results of horizontal flame testing for each of the
materials prepared. Peak information is expressed as the ratio to the crystalline
polymer peak at 4.9Å.</p><p num="0080">The data clearly show the correlation between the dispersion of the
organoclay and the fire retardant properties of the polymer. Samples prepared
under conditions 3 and 4 were subjected to significantly more shear in
processing than the first two, and the delamination of the organoclay is apparent
by the dramatic increase in polymer/organoclay peak heights and ratios as
observed in the XRD spectrum. The samples which had a high degree of
delamination performed very poorly in fire testing, while those which were less
dispersed showed excellent improvement over the natural polymer resin.</p><p num="0081">The invention thus being described, it will be obvious that the same
may be varied in many ways. Such variations are not to be regarded as a 
departure from the spirit and scope of the invention and all such
modifications are intended to be included within the scope of the claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A polymer composition with enhanced fire retardation qualities
comprised of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(I) one or more organoclays which are the ion-exchanged reaction
product of:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) a smectite clay; and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) one or more quaternary ammonium compounds in an
amount of from about 50% to about 150% of the cation
exchange capacity of the smectite clay; and/or</claim-text><claim-text>(c) one or more organic materials in an amount of 1% to 50% of
the weight of the smectite clay and</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>(II) one or more polymers;
wherein the composition is prepared in a manner so that the
organoclay is not completely delaminated into the polymer.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the amount of reaction and
intercalation product of I(a), (b) and (c) is from 0.1% to 40% of the weight
of the one or more polymers.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein one or more of the quaternary
ammonium compounds has the formula:
   wherein R1 comprises a group selected from (i) linear or branched
aliphatic, aralkyl, or aromatic hydrocarbon groups having from 8 to 30
carbon atoms or (ii) alkyl or alkyl-ester groups having 8 to 30 carbon
atoms; R2, R3, and R4 are independently selected from the group
consisting of (a) linear or branched aliphatic hydrocarbon, fluorocarbon, or
other halocarbon groups having from 1 to about 30 carbon atoms; (b)
aralkyl or aromatic groups having from 6 to about 30 carbon atoms, (c)
alkoxylated groups containing from 1 to about 80 moles of alkylene oxide;
(d) amide groups, (e) oxazolidine groups, (f) allyl, vinyl, or other alkenyl or
alkynyl groups possessing reactive unsaturation and having from 2 to
about 30 carbon atoms, and (g) hydrogen; and X' comprises an anion
selected from the group consisting of chloride, methyl sulfate, acetate,
iodide, and bromide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein one or more of the organic materials is
selected from the groups consisting of carboxylic acids and organic sulfuric
acids.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein one or more of the organic materials is
selected from the groups consisting of polyurethanes, polyamides, polyestes,
polycarbonates, polyglycols, polyepoxides and polyolefins.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the one or more polymers are selected
from the group consisting of synthetic thermoset or thermoplastic polymers</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1 wherein the composition is useful as an
architectural or construction material.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 6 wherein the architectural material is
roofing membrane or shingles.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the smectite clay is selected from
the group consisting of bentonite, hectorite, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the quaternary ammonium
compound is selected from the group consisting of 2M2HT, MB2HT,
M3HT and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The composition of Claim 1 wherein the composition has a visible XRD
d001 peak.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>