<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1586606-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1586606" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34928954" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20051019"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1586606-A1" status="new" fvid="24482227"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1586606</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20051019</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04101527-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04101527</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040414</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-04101527-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04101527</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040414</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 297/00        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 297/04        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  53/00        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  53/00        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  53/02        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  95/00        20060101A I20080531RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  95/00        20060101C I20080531RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09J 153/00        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09J 153/02        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F 297/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F 297/04K</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  95/00+B5</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  95/00+B5B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09J 153/02+B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09J 153/02+B5B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Asphalt Binder auf Basis polymermodifiziertes Bitumen, daraus hergestellte heissgemischte Asphalte und Belagsysteme</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">An asphalt binder based on polymer modified bitumen, hot mix asphalts made thereof, and pavements made therefrom</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Liant asphalte en basse de bitumen modifie avec polymères, melanges bitumineaux prepares a chaud et pavements</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-20310484-U1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>20310484</doc-number><kind>U1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-2318121-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2318121</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5773496-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5773496</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6150439-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6150439</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="YD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>MCKAY K W ET AL:  "THE INFLUENCE OF STYRENE-BUTADIENE DIBLOCK COPOLYMER ON STYRENE-BUTADIENE-STYRENE TRIBLOCK COPOLYMER VISCOELASTIC PROPERTIES AND PRODUCT PERFORMANCE" JOURNAL OF APPLIED POLYMER SCIENCE, JOHN WILEY AND SONS INC. NEW YORK, US, vol. 56, no. 8, 23 May 1995 (1995-05-23), pages 947-958, XP000535273 ISSN: 0021-8995</text><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KRATON POLYMERS RES BV</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KRATON POLYMERS RESEARCH B.V.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KRATON Polymers Research B.V.</last-name><address><street>Badhuisweg 3</street><city>1031 CM Amsterdam</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KORENSTRA JAN</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VAN DIJK CORNELIS MARTINUS</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VONK WILLEM C</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KORENSTRA, JAN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VAN DIJK, CORNELIS MARTINUS</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VONK, WILLEM C.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KORENSTRA, JAN</last-name><address><street>KRATON Polymers Research B.V. Badhuisweg 3</street><city>1031 CM Amsterdam</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VAN DIJK, CORNELIS MARTINUS</last-name><address><street>KRATON Polymers Research B.V. Badhuisweg 3</street><city>1031 CM Amsterdam</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VONK, WILLEM C.</last-name><address><street>KRATON Polymers Research B.V. Badhuisweg 3</street><city>1031 CM Amsterdam</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kortekaas, Marcellinus C. J. A.</last-name><address><street>KRATON Polymers Research B.V. P.O. Box 37666</street><city>1030 BH Amsterdam</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An asphalt binder comprising 85 to 98.5 parts by weight of a bitumen and 15-1.5
parts by weight of a polymer composition, wherein the polymer composition
comprises:
<sl><li>(i) from 5 to 70% by weight of a linear styrenic block copolymer (SBC1)
comprising at least two polymer blocks each substantially made of an aromatic vinyl
compound and at least one polymer block substantially made of a conjugated diene
compound and having an apparent molecular weight greater than 250,000 and/or a
radial styrenic block copolymer (SBC2) having three or more polymer arms
attached to the residue of a cross-linking agent or multifunctional compound,
comprising at least two polymer blocks each substantially made of an aromatic vinyl
compound and at least one polymer block substantially made of a conjugated diene
compound and wherein the polymer arms have an average apparent molecular
weight greater than 125,000 and</li><li>(ii) from 95 to 30% by weight of an elastomer (EI) having an apparent
molecular weight in the range of 120,000 to 250,000, preferably a styrenic diblock
copolymer having one polymer block substantially made of an aromatic vinyl
compound and at least one polymer block substantially made of a conjugated diene
compound.</li></sl></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>Background Art</b></heading><p num="0001">According to the Transportation Research Board the most common type of
flexible pavement surfacing in the U.S. is hot mix asphalt (HMA). Hot mix
asphalt is known by many different names such as hot mix, asphalt, or
blacktop. HMA consists of two basic ingredients: aggregate and asphalt
binder (bitumen).</p><p num="0002">Asphalt binders nowadays often comprise a mixture of bitumen and
polymer. Of these polymers, the thermoplastic rubbers forming a
continuous network are the most commonly used polymers, and have led to
various papers on the subject matter. In <b>GROS, William A., et al</b> The
Influence of Styrene-Butadiene Diblock Copolymer on
Styrene-Butadiene-Styrene Triblock Copolymer Viscoelastic Properties and
Product Performance. J. <i>appl. polym. sci. ,</i> 1995, vol. 56, p. 947-958. , for
instance, the effects of SB diblock copolymer on the complex shear
modulus and elasticity of a polymer-modified asphalt is described, with a
predicted lack of network participation for the SB diblock, accounting for
lower strength and greater temperature susceptibility of diblock-containing
systems. This article hence suggests a departure from diblock containing 
asphalt binders.</p><p num="0003">In <b>US 4196115</b> (PHILIPS) 01.04.1980 blends are described of different
conjugated diene/monovinyl aromatic copolymers in bituminous based
roofing and waterproofing membranes. Thus a radial conjugated
diene/monovinyl aromatic copolymer having a weight average molecular
weight (Mw) above 200,000 and a conjugated diene/monovinyl aromatic
ratio of 50/50 to 85/15 is used together with a conjugated diene/monovinyl
aromatic copolymer having an Mw below 200,000 and being radial or linear,
with same conjugated diene/monovinyl aromatic weight ratios as earlier
given, in an asphalt-containing composition to yield desirable high as well
as low temperature properties. It is suggested that the high Mw copolymer
contributes to the high temperature stability, e.g., low or no flow between
25°-100°C and that the low Mw copolymer contributes to low temperature
flexibility, e.g., no cracking at -25°C.</p><p num="0004">There are numerous examples of asphalt binders to be found in the patent
literature. <b>US 5863971</b> (SHELL) 26.01.1999 provides a process for
preparing a bitumen composition which comprises mixing at an elevated
temperature an oxidised bitumen having a penetration index of at least 0
with a thermoplastic rubber which is present in an amount of less than 5%
wt., based on total bitumen composition. It further provides bitumen
compositions obtainable by such process; and the use of such bitumen
compositions in asphalt mixtures for road applications </p><p num="0005"><b>US 5773496</b> (KOCH) 30.06.1998 and <b>US 5795929</b> (KOCH) 18.08.1998
relate to an asphalt composition prepared from bitumen (asphalt), linear
and non-linear copolymers of styrene and butadiene, further comprising
respectively cross-linking agents, and emulsifiers ('929) or elemental
sulphur ('496). The asphalt polymer compositions are useful for industrial
applications, such as hot-mix and emulsified asphalts used with aggregates
for road paving, and repair.</p><p num="0006"><b>US 6150439</b> (JAPAN ELASTOMER CO) 21.11.2000 claims a block
copolymer composition for modifying asphalt, which comprises a mixture of:
(A) a block copolymer comprising: at least two polymer blocks each mainly
comprising a monoalkenyl aromatic compound; and at least one polymer
block mainly comprising a conjugated diene compound; and (B) a block
copolymer comprising: at least one polymer block mainly comprising a
monoalkenyl aromatic compound; and at least one copolymer block mainly
comprising a conjugated diene compound, and having a molecular weight
equivalent to 1/3 to 2/3 of the molecular weight of block copolymer (A),
wherein (a) the total bonding alkenyl aromatic compound content in the
mixture of block copolymers (A) and (B) is from 10 to 50% by weight,
wherein (b) the vinyl bond content in the conjugated diene polymer blocks
is not greater than 70% by weight, and wherein the block copolymer
composition has: (c) a content of (A) component of from 98 to 20% by
weight and a content of (B) component of from 2 to 80% by weight; (d) a 
melt index value of from 0.3 to 15.0 g/10 min; (e) a bulk density of from 0.1
to 0.7; (f) a particle size distribution such that the content of constituents
remaining on a 5-mesh sieve is not greater than 30% by weight and the
content of constituents passing through a 20-mesh sieve is not greater than
30% by weight; and (g) a total pore volume of from 100 to 2,000 mm<sup>3</sup>/g.</p><p num="0007">Further patent applications by the same applicant and/or inventor include <b>JP
10212416</b> (NIPPON ELASTOMER KK) 11.08.1998 , which has as its
problem to be solved: To obtain an asphalt composition manifesting high
softening point, excellent in mechanical strengths, processability and
storing stability and suitable for road paving by compounding a specific
amount of a composition of a block copolymer of an alkenyl aromatic
compound having a specific structure and a conjugated diene. The
proposed solution comprises the use of a composition consisting of (A)
3-15 parts of the block copolymer composition having 0.3-15.0 of melt flow
index and 80-130 °C of softening point, (B) 85-97 parts of asphalt, wherein
component (A) consists of 98-20wt.% of a block copolymer (A1 )
comprising a polymer block (R1 ) mainly consisting of at least two
monoalkenyl aromatic compounds and a copolymer block (R2 ) mainly
consisting of the conjugated diene polymer (X), and 2-80% of a block
copolymer (A2 ) comprising R1 and R2 having peak molecular weight
corresponding to 1/3-2/3 of (A1), the difference between total amount of
alkenyl aromatic compounds (Z) and R1 content is 2-30%, the contents of Z 
and R1 are 10-50% respectively, the amount of vinyl bond in the X is
0-50%.</p><p num="0008">In <b>JP 1254768</b> (NIPPON ELASTOMER KK) 11.10.1989 , <b>JP 6041439</b> (
NIPPON ELASTOMER KK) 15.02.1994 and <b>JP 9012898</b> (NIPPON
ELASTOMER KK) 14.01.1997 a similar asphalt composition is described
comprising a block copolymer having a random copolymer block of the
alkenyl aromatic compound and the conjugated diene polymer; or a mixture
of a triblock copolymer and a diblock copolymer, respectively such block
copolymers with a random copolymer block of the alkenyl aromatic
compound and the conjugated diene polymer.</p><p num="0009">In <b>JP 3143961</b> (ASAHI) 19.06.1991 an asphalt composition is described
with excellent heat resistance and processability, and with an improved
balance of properties such as softenting point, rate of penetration,
elongation, cohesive force and grasp of aggregate by using a composition
comprising 30-95%wt of a styrenic block copolymer composition having a
vinyl aromatic hydrocarbon content (S) of 10-35w%, a contents of vinyl
bonds in the butadiene block (V) of 15-55% and satisfying the relation of
35≤S+V≤75, and 5-70%wt of a block copolymer having a polyisoprene
block.</p><p num="0010">In <b>GB 2294935</b> (SHELL) 15.05.1996 and asphalt composition is described
containing highly coupled radial block copolymers of a conjugated diolefin
and a vinyl aromatic hydrocarbon. </p><p num="0011">In <b>JP 8165436</b> (J S R SHELL ELASTOMER KK ) 25.06.1996 and <b>JP
8225711</b> (J S R SHELL ELASTOMER KK ) 03.09.1996 asphalt
compositions are described comprising a specific block copolymer
expressed by general formulae: (A<sub>1</sub> -B<sub>1</sub> )n X; (A<sub>1</sub> -B<sub>1</sub> -A<sub>5</sub> )<sub>n</sub> X; A<sub>2</sub> -B<sub>2;</sub> A<sub>2</sub> -B<sub>2</sub> -A<sub>6</sub> (A<sub>3</sub>
-B<sub>3</sub> )<sub>n</sub> Y; (A<sub>3</sub> -B<sub>3</sub> -A<sub>7</sub> )<sub>n</sub> Y; and A<sub>4</sub> -B<sub>4</sub> -A<sub>8</sub> -B<sub>5</sub> , wherein A<sub>1</sub> to A<sub>8</sub> are each a polymer
block consisting essentially of an aromatic vinyl compound; B<sub>1</sub> to B<sub>5</sub> each
represents a polymer block consisting essentially of a conjugated diene; X
is the residue of a coupling agent; Y is a residue of a multifunctional
monomer; and n is an integer of 1 to 6.</p><p num="0012">Finally, in <b>US 6136899</b> (GOODYEAR ) 24.10.2000 it has been determined
that a specific type of emulsion SBR can be used to modify asphalt cement
to greatly enhance the resistance to shoving, rutting and low temperature
cracking of asphalt concretes made therewith. The SBR used for asphalt
cement modification is a blend of (i) a high molecular weight
styrene-butadiene rubber having a weight average molecular weight of at
least about 300,000 and (ii) a low molecular weight styrene-butadiene
rubber having a weight average molecular weight of less than about
280,000; wherein the ratio of the high molecular weight styrene-butadiene
rubber to the low molecular weight styrene-butadiene rubber is within the
range of about 80:20 to about 25:75; and wherein the bound styrene
content of the high molecular weight styrene-butadiene rubber differs from
the bound styrene content of the low molecular weight styrene-butadiene 
rubber by at least 5 percentage points. It should be realized, however, that
SBR does not form continuous networks.</p><p num="0013">HMA's are made by heating and blending the aggregate and asphalt binder,
e.g., in a batch plant or a drum mix plant. During mixing, the hot asphalt
binder must be readily able to coat the dried and heated mineral aggregate,
given the shearing conditions employed, in a relatively short period of time
(typically 30 to 90 seconds). Whilst the mixing temperature must be
sufficiently high to allow rapid distribution of the asphalt binder on the
aggregate, the use of the lowest temperature possible is advocated to avoid
excessive oxidation of the bitumen. There are therefore upper and lower
limits to mixing temperature. The material so produced is generally stored
in silos before being discharged into trucks. So called "gap graded" HMA's
commonly suffer from drainage or drain-down, a process in which the
excess asphalt binder comes off the aggregates during storage or
transport.</p><p num="0014">Until about 20 years ago asphalt mixes were dense and often had a
continuous grading of aggregate to reduce the voids volume. Asphalt binder
content was optimised to get the right balance of properties. This generally
avoided the issue of drain-down or drainage of the asphalt binder. Also,
adding filler helped avoiding the issue of drainage.</p><p num="0015">More recently, however, mixes have been developed that consist of a rather
different aggregate grading. Some contain more voids deliberately for 
reasons of water drainage in service and noise reduction, while others are
dense but gap-graded (no continuity in the aggregate grading). Examples of
such gap-graded mixes are porous asphalt, based on so-called
"open-graded" aggregate; stone mastic asphalt or stone matrix asphalt
(SMA) based on so-called "gap-graded" material, and also (ultra) thin
overlays are based on this concept. The gap-graded aggregate mixture
provides a stable stone-to-stone skeleton, and through aggregate interlock
and particle friction give the structure its stability. These HMA's are more
prone to drain-down for reasons described below.</p><p num="0016">The present inventors set out to solve the problem of drain-down, without
adversely affecting the processability of the HMA, while improving its
performance in service</p><p num="0017">The maximum binder content of these open and gap graded mixes at which
no drainage will take place is typically lower than what is desirable in use.
For instance in porous asphalt the maximum would be at 3 to 3.5% by
weight of asphalt binder. However, with their open structure this would
result in excessive hardening of the binder and hence early brittle failure. It
is desirable to increase the thickness of the binder films by increasing the
asphalt binder content, which then leads to binder drainage during storage
and transport. SMAs are mixes that are basically similar to porous asphalt,
but instead of having excessive air voids, the voids are filled with mortar of
asphalt binder, filler, sand and small aggregate. In these mixes too, storage 
and transport will lead to binder drainage if no counter measures are taken.</p><p num="0018">There are several ways to reduce or inhibit drainage. One way is to add
fibres. Fibres can provide an excellent resistance to binder drainage, but do
not contribute much to the overall performance of the mix.</p><p num="0019">Finally, the addition of polymers to the bitumen may reduce the drainage
due to their increase in viscosity of the binder so-produced. However, there
is obviously a limit to the amount of polymer, as it will not only reduce
drainage, but will also make it more difficult to mix, lay and compact the
mix.</p><p num="0020">The present inventors therefore set out to find an asphalt binder that does
not suffer from drain-down, whilst maintaining processability at all stages of
blending, mixing, laying and compaction using standard available
equipment.</p><heading><b>Disclosure of Invention"</b></heading><p num="0021">Accordingly, an asphalt binder comprising 85 to 98.5 parts by weight of a
bitumen and 15-1.5 parts by weight of a polymer composition, wherein the
polymer composition comprises:
<sl><li>(i) from 5 to 70% by weight of a linear styrenic block copolymer (SBC1)
comprising at least two polymer blocks each substantially made of an
aromatic vinyl compound and at least one polymer block substantially made
of a conjugated diene compound and having an apparent molecular weight 
greater than 250,000 and/or a radial styrenic block copolymer (SBC2)
having three or more polymer arms attached to the residue of a
cross-linking agent or multifunctional compound, comprising at least two
polymer blocks each substantially made of an aromatic vinyl compound and
at least one polymer block substantially made of a conjugated diene
compound and wherein the polymer arms have an average apparent
molecular weight greater than 125,000 and</li><li>(ii) from 95 to 30% by weight of an elastomer (EI) having an
apparent molecular weight in the range of 120,000 to 250,000, preferably a
styrenic diblock copolymer having one polymer block substantially made of
an aromatic vinyl compound and at least one polymer block substantially
made of a conjugated diene compound.</li></sl></p><p num="0022">In addition, a hot mix asphalt is provided comprising 2 to 8 parts by weight
of the asphalt binder of the present invention and 98 to 92 parts by weight
aggregate material, preferably of gap-graded aggregate such as open
gap-graded or dense gap-aggregate material.</p><p num="0023">Furthermore, a pavement is claimed, produced from the open or gap-graded
mixes, by compacting the hot mix asphalt mentioned above.</p><heading><b>Mode(s) for Carrying Out the Invention</b></heading><p num="0024">The modification of bitumen by the addition of various polymers and
elastomers is known. Such elastomers include polybutadiene, polyisoprene, 
conjugated diene copolymers, natural rubber, butyl rubber, chloroprene,
random styrene-butadiene rubber, and styrene-butadiene diblock
copolymers. In addition bitumen's have been modified with a special class
of elastomers, so-called thermoplastic elastomers, which derive their
strength and elasticity from a physical cross-linking of the molecules into
three-dimensional networks. Of the four main groups of thermoplastic
elastomers, polyurethane, polyether-polyester copolymers, olefinic
copolymers and styrenic block copolymer, the latter have proved to be the
thermoplastic elastomer with the greatest potential when blended with
bitumen.</p><p num="0025">The present invention realizes sufficient processability of the asphalt binder
at the mixing stage, with little or no drainage of the asphalt binder at the
storage or transport stage and with sufficient workability at the compacting
stage.</p><p num="0026">Whilst achieving the aforementioned properties will greatly improve the
future of open or porous asphalt for road construction, ideally these
achievements should be obtained without adversely effecting or preferably
even improving the properties of the final pavement. Thus, the softening
point of the asphalt binder has been found to be important too. The present
invention solves these problems by using a polymer composition
comprising a high molecular weight styrenic block copolymer combined with
a low molecular weight elastomer. </p><p num="0027">Preferably, the styrenic block copolymer has a molecular weight in the
range of 250,000 to 800,000 if said copolymer is a linear polymer, or in the
range of 500,000 to 1,500,000 if said copolymer is a branched or
star-shaped polymer.</p><p num="0028">Most preferably the styrenic block copolymer constituents are selected from
the group consisting of
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">A-B-A-(B)<sub>p</sub> or (A-B)<sub>2</sub> X (II)</st32:che>
wherein A represents the polymer block substantially made of an aromatic
vinyl compound, typically a polystyrene block; B a polymer block
substantially made of a conjugated diene, typically a polybutadiene block, n
is an integer greater than or equal to 1, p is 0 or 1, and X is the residue of a
coupling agent or multifunctional monomer.</p><p num="0029">These preferred styrenic block copolymer constituents are selected from a
larger group of styrenic block copolymers, that all may be used in the
compositions of the present invention, consisting of those of the formulae
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">(B)<sub>p</sub> -(A-B)<sub>2</sub> X; or (B)<sub>p</sub> -A(B-A)<sub>n</sub> -(B)<sub>p</sub>, (linear SBC1)</st32:che><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">((B)<sub>p</sub> (A-B)<sub>n</sub>)<sub>m</sub> X (radial SBC2)</st32:che>
wherein A, B, p and X have the meaning set out above, n is an integer
greater than or equal to 1, and m is an integer greater than 2.</p><p num="0030">The expression "substantially" as used herein means that sufficient vinyl
aromatic compound is used, for instance at least 50% by weight, to provide 
a hard block A having a glass transition temperature of greater than 25°C,
whereas in terms of the block B the expression "substantially" means that
sufficient conjugated diene is used, for instance at least 70% by weight, to
provide an elastomer block having a glass transition temperature below
25°C.</p><p num="0031">The content of the vinyl aromatic compound in the styrenic block copolymer
is from 10 to 50% by weight, preferably from 15 to 40% by weight.</p><p num="0032">The vinyl aromatic compound may be selected from compounds having 8 to
18 carbon atoms per molecule. For instance, some representative
examples thereof include: styrene; 1-vinylnaphthalene; 3-methylstyrene;
3,5-diethylstyrene; 4-propylstyrene; 2,4,6-trimethylstyrene;
4-dodecylstyrene; 3-methyl,5-n-hexylstyrene; 4-phenylstyrene;
2-ethyl,4-benzylstyrene; 2,3,4,5-tetraethylstyrene;
3-ethyl-1-vinylnaphthalene; alpha-methylstyrene, and the like. Preferred
examples comprise 3-methylstyrene, styrene and mixtures thereof, styrene
being most preferred. Compounds that may be copolymerized and form
part of the A block(s) may be selected from the conjugated dienes
hereafter, and other anionically polymerizable, ethylenically unsaturated
compounds, such as vinylcyclohexane, methylmethacrylate and the like.
Most preferably each polymer block A is a polystyrene block.</p><p num="0033">Block B is preferably made from butadiene, isoprene or mixtures thereof.
Conjugated dienes that can be used, preferably having from 4 to 12 carbon 
atoms per molecule, further include 2,3-dimethyl-1,3-butadiene, piperylene,
3-butyl-1,3-octadiene, phenyl-1,3-butadiene, and the like. Said block(s) may
also comprise other monomers, such as the vinyl aromatic compounds
mentioned herein above. Most preferably block B is a polybutadiene block.</p><p num="0034">As is known, butadiene (and other conjugated dienes) may polymerize in
1,4-addition manner and/or 1,2-addition manner. The latter results in
pending vinyl groups. It is known in the art to use styrenic block copolymers
having relatively high vinyl content, e.g. up to 70% and higher (based on
the conjugated diene), e.g. by polymerizing the conjugated diene monomer
in the presence of a polar cosolvent and/or at a relatively cool
polymerization temperature. In producing the polymer block (B) under
ordinary conditions a vinyl content of less than 25% is obtained. Both high
vinyl and ordinary styrenic block copolymers may be used.</p><p num="0035">Styrenic block copolymer and elastomer may be used in relative amounts of
15 to 70% by weight (SBC1 and/or SBC2) and 85 to 30% by weight (EI),
respectively, but preferably in relative amounts 20 to 50% by weight (SBC1
and/or SBC2) and 80 to 50% by weight (EI). Most preferably, the relative
amounts are selected within the aforementioned range on the basis of
some scouting experiments, to compensate for the effect of the molecular
weights of these components and the effect of the bitumen.</p><p num="0036">Depending on their method of preparation these SBC's are known to
comprise diblock copolymers of formula A-B in various amounts. Indeed, in 
coupling reactions, the diblock copolymers of formula A-B have the same
molecular weight of the arms in the coupled polymer.</p><p num="0037">The co-produced diblock copolymer of formula A-B may be the low
molecular weight elastomer (EI) component of the polymer composition,
provided it has a molecular weight in the range of from 10,000 to 250.000
and is present in an amount in the range of 85 to 30% by weight basis the
polymer composition. This is the preferred embodiment. On the other hand,
elastomer (EI) may be a separate elastomer, selected from the elastomers
mentioned herein before. Elastomer (EI) may also be a diblock copolymer
produced independent of the preparation of the styrenic block copolymer
(A).</p><p num="0038">The polymer composition that has been found to be most suitable for the
present application is a high mol weight styrene-butadiene-styrene coupled
block copolymer with a large amount of di-block, with the following
characteristics:

styrene content in the range of 25-40%, preferably about 30% by weight:

diblock molecular weight 180,000-215,000, preferably about 200,000:
<sl><li>diblock content 75-85%, preferably 80% by weight (which corresponds with
a coupling efficiency of 15-25, preferably 20%);</li><li>having a linear structure (manufactured with a difunctional coupling agent),
having an apparent MW (SBS) of
30,000-40,000//300,000-350,000//30,000-40,000, preferably 36000 - 
328000 - 36000.</li></sl></p><p num="0039">This polymer composition is believed to be novel and is therefore claimed
herein as well, as is its use in other applications.</p><p num="0040">With the term "apparent molecular weight", as used throughout the present
specification, is meant the molecular weight, as measured by means of Gel
Permeation Chromatography (GPC), relative to commercially available
poly(styrene) calibration standards (according to ASTM D6474-99).</p><p num="0041">The asphalt component may be naturally occurring bitumen or derived from
a mineral oil. Also petroleum derivatives obtained by a cracking process,
pitch and coal tar can be used as the asphalt components, as well as the
blends of various asphalt materials. Examples of suitable components
include distillation or "straight-run" bitumens, precipitation bitumens, e.g.,
propane bitumens, blown bitumens and mixtures thereof. Other suitable
bitumens include mixtures of one or more of these bitumens with extenders
such as petroleum extracts, e.g. aromatic extracts, distillates or residues, or
with oils. Some representative examples of bitumens that may be used in
the present invention have a PEN value of below about 300 as measured
by ASTM Method D5.</p><p num="0042">For Hot Mix Asphalt compositions the preferred ranges are 3 to 8 parts on
97 to 92 parts of aggregate, more preferably from 4 to 8 parts on 96 to 92
parts of aggregate (parts by weight). </p><p num="0043">The aggregate materials basically comprise inert granular materials such as
rocks, stones, crushed stones, gravel, sand and filler. Aggregate material is
used in different sizes from rather small to relatively course, e.g., less than
0.075 mm ⊘, and up to 40 mm ⊘, and is available in all sizes between the
given boundaries. The aggregate composition is then chosen so that it
fulfils mechanical/structural requirements, which can either be a continuous
grading or gap-grading.</p><p num="0044">Aggregates can either be natural or manufactured. Natural gravel and sand
are usually dug or dredged from a pit, river, lake, or seabed. Crushed
aggregate is produced by crushing quarry rock, boulders, cobbles, or
large-size gravel. Recycled concrete is a viable source of aggregate, as is
the use of industrial by-products such as slag (by-product of metallurgical
processing). Aggregate processing consists of crushing, screening, and
washing the aggregate to obtain proper cleanliness and gradation. If
necessary, a benefaction process such as jigging or heavy media
separation can be used to upgrade the quality. Once processed, the
aggregates are handled and stored in a way that minimizes segregation
and degradation and prevents contamination. Aggregates strongly influence
the properties of a HMA composition, mixture proportions, and economy.
Consequently, selection of aggregates is an important process. Although
some variation in aggregate properties is expected, characteristics that are
considered when selecting aggregate include:
 
   grading; durability; particle shape and surface texture; abrasion and
skid resistance; unit weights and voids; and absorption and surface
moisture.</p><p num="0045">Grading refers to the determination of the particle-size distribution for
aggregate. Grading limits and maximum aggregate size are specified
because grading and size affect the amount of aggregate used as well as
workability and durability of hot mix asphalt.</p><p num="0046">The selection of aggregate size can be such that the voids left by the
coarsest particles are filled by smaller particles. The voids between the
smaller particles are yet again filled by even smaller particles and so on. In
this case the grading is called continuous. The selection can also be such
that a certain particle size is left out. In this case the aggregate material is
referred to as a gap-graded mix.</p><p num="0047">In the below table, examples are given of some standard aggregate
materials. In the left hand column the diameter of the sieve size is given.
Thus, using a sieve having 11.2 mm size holes only some 0-6 parts by
weight of aggregate material is retained. In case of a sieve having 63 mu
size holes, nearly all aggregate material is retained. What is obvious from
these examples is that the distribution in continuous graded aggregate is
roughly equal, whereas such is not the case in open gap-graded and dense
gap-graded aggregates. <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>sieve size □</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>continuous graded</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Open gap-graded</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Dense gap-graded</b></entry></row><row><entry align="right">C11,2mm</entry><entry align="center">0-6</entry><entry align="center">0-5</entry><entry align="center">0-8</entry></row><row><entry align="right">C8 mm</entry><entry align="center">5-25</entry><entry align="center">60-85</entry><entry align="center">40-55</entry></row><row><entry align="right">C5,6 mm</entry><entry align="center">25-50</entry><entry align="center">80-85</entry><entry align="center">60-75</entry></row><row><entry align="right">2 mm</entry><entry align="center">52-58</entry><entry align="center">85</entry><entry align="center">72.2-82.5</entry></row><row><entry align="right">63 mu</entry><entry align="center">92.5-94</entry><entry align="center">95.5</entry><entry align="center">90-94</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0048">Other components that may be used include fillers and reinforcing agents
such as ground tires, silica, talc, calcium carbonate, mineral matter powder,
and fibres (glass, cellulose, acryl, and rock); curing agents such as sulphur
and sulphur compounds; pigments; softening agents such as paraffinic,
naphthenic or aromatic oils; tackiness imparting resins; foaming agents;
and stiffeners such as waxes and low molecular weight polyolefins.</p><p num="0049">In addition to the binder composition and the new polymer composition, the
present invention also concerns pavements and overlays based on the
asphalt binder described above.</p><p num="0050">In addition to gap graded asphalt, the new polymer composition and the
binder may be used in crack filler applications, where the polymer offers the
elasticity and softness desired for crack filler; in self adhered membranes,
and in high efficiency crosslinked product for paving. They may also be 
used in shingles and roofing felts, carpet backing and sound deadening, as
well as in coatings based on polymer modified bitumen.</p><p num="0051">The new polymer composition may also find other end-uses. For instance it
may be used in blends with thermoplastic polymers to improve the impact
resistance of the polymer systems. Thermoplastics in particular are
polystyrene and polyphenylene oxide, and
poly(styrene-methylmethacrylate), and high impact polystyrene. Inclusion of
the new polymer composition will improve toughness of these polymer
systems. Also, the polymer composition can be used in sheet moulding
compounds together with unsaturated polyester, styrene monomer, fillers,
glass fibre, and peroxide crosslinker. The advantage of using the new
polymer composition is to provide good shrink control of the sheet moulding
compounds. The polymer composition and blends thereof may also find use
in adhesive, sealant and coating compositions, in oil gels (e.g., as cable
filling component) and in footwear.</p><p num="0052">The present invention will hereinafter be illustrated more specifically by the
following examples, however without restricting the scope to these specific
embodiments.</p><heading><u style="single">Test methods</u></heading><p num="0053">Standard tests were carried out for softening point Ring &amp;Ball (according to
ASTM D36), Penetration at 25°C (ASTM D5), elastic recovery (DIN 52013), 
and fracture toughness (analogous to ASTM E399).</p><p num="0054">In addition the dynamic viscosity at 150°C was determined, which is the
temperature at which HMA is typically hauled. At blending conditions (which
are at temperatures even above 150°C, involving high shear) the dynamic
viscosity should be low, whereas during transport it should be high.</p><p num="0055">The dynamic viscosity was also determined at 120°C as a function of shear
rate. This test models the temperature and shear conditions during
compacting. An ideal HMA should have a low dynamic viscosity at high
temperatures and high shear conditions, a high dynamic viscosity at 150°C
at low shear conditions, coupled with a drop in dynamic viscosity at high
shear conditions at 120°C.</p><p num="0056">Shear-rate dependency has been measured using a Haake Rotoviscometer
with beaker and coaxial cylinder and shear rates from 20 to 500s<sup>-1</sup>.</p><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of the block copolymer compositions SBS-1. SBS-2 and SBS-3</u></heading><p num="0057">Cyclohexane, styrene, and butadiene were purified by activated
aluminumoxide and stored at 4 °C under a nitrogen atmosphere. EPON™
826 (a diglycidyl ether) was used as coupling agent. An autoclave,
equipped with a helical stirrer was charged with cyclohexane and the
content was heated to 50 to 60 °C. As initiator sec-BuLi was dosed
immediately followed by styrene monomer, which was allowed to
polymerize to completion. The reaction temperature was increased to 
70 °C, at which temperature butadiene was dosed and reacted. The
resulting diblock was coupled with an excess EPON™ 826. This excess
was optionally scavenged with sec-BuLi and followed by addition of ethanol
as terminator. The reaction mixture was cooled to 40 °C, transported to a
blending vessel and a stabilization package was added (comprising
IRGANOX™ 565 and tris(nonylphenol)phosphite 0.08/0.35 phr as a
cyclohexane solution) and stirred at RT. Dry rubber was obtained by steam
coagulation finishing, followed by drying in an oven.</p><p num="0058">The polymers were analyzed by GPC. The results of the GPC analysis are
in Table 2.</p><p num="0059">The polymer modified binders were based on a PX-100 bitumen (a PEN 100
bitumen consisting of 75% propane bitumen and 25% Brightstock Furfural
Extract) by blending the polymer composition or components at a
modification level of 5% by weight polymer composition or total weight of
the components with the bitumen at 160 - 180°C</p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0060">Polymer modified binders were made with 100% triblock or diblock styrenic
block copolymer (Comparatives A and B), with a combination of a triblock
and diblock styrenic block copolymer at weight ratios 85/15, 70/30 and
50/50 (Experiments 1-3), as well as with the synthesised SBS-1, SBS-2 and
SBS-3 (Experiments 4-6) mentioned above. Results from Table 3 show that 
Comparative A does not exhibit the desired drop in viscosity as a result of
shear (shear thinning). Comparative B does exhibit a drop in viscosity, but
at a dynamic viscosity level at 150°C that prohibits successful mixing. Table
4 lists the results of Experiments 1-3, Table 5 lists the results of Experiments 4-6. These experiments reveal the desired viscosity
behaviour.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Polymer</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>SB diblock</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>SBS triblock</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>SBS-1</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>SBS-2</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>SBS-3</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total Mw (di)</entry><entry align="center">139,700</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">189,500</entry><entry align="center">177,800</entry><entry align="center">169,400</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total Mw (tri)</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">294,100</entry><entry align="center">379,000</entry><entry align="center">355,600</entry><entry align="center">338,800</entry></row><row><entry align="left">CE (%)</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">0</entry><entry align="center">23.3</entry><entry align="center">27.8</entry><entry align="center">37</entry> </row><row><entry align="left">PSC (%)</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry> <entry align="center">30</entry> <entry align="center">30</entry> </row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0061">CE = coupling efficiency; PSC = Polystyrene content.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="left"  namest="1"><b>Properties</b></entry><entry nameend="3"  align="left"  namest="2"><b>Comp A</b></entry><entry nameend="5" align="left" namest="4"><b>Comp B</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="1"/><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2"><b>(SB)</b></entry><entry nameend="5" align="center" namest="4"><b>(SBS)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Softening point R&amp;B (°C)</entry><entry align="left">53.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">105.5 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Penetration at 25°C (dmm)</entry><entry align="left">66</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">59</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elastic recovery 20 cm, 13°C (%)</entry><entry align="left">45.7</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">93.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ductility 13°C, cm</entry><entry align="left">43.9</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dynamic visc. 150°C, 26s <sup>-1</sup> (mPas)</entry><entry align="left">439</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">1282</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dynamic visc. 150°C, 395s<sup>-1</sup> (mPas)</entry><entry align="left">460</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">1040</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dynamic visc. 120°C,</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2540</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">4415</entry></row><row><entry align="left">26s<sup>-1</sup> (mPas)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2454</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">3306</entry></row><row><entry align="left">52</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2429</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2960</entry></row><row><entry align="left">79</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2418</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2757</entry></row><row><entry align="left">105</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2368</entry></row><row><entry align="left">132</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Properties</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Exp 1</b></entry><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>Exp 2</b></entry><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>Exp 3</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>(85/15)</b></entry><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>(70/30)</b></entry><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>(50/50)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Softening point</entry><entry align="left">58.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">67.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">92 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">R&amp;B (°C)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Penetration at 25°C (dmm)</entry><entry align="left">64</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">62</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">61</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elastic recovery 20 cm, 13°C (%)</entry><entry align="left">70.3</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">76.8</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">83.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ductility 13°C, cm</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dynamic visc. 150°C, 26s<sup>-1</sup> (mPas)</entry><entry align="left">510</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">586</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">763</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dynamic visc. 150°C, 395s<sup>-1</sup> (mPas)</entry><entry align="left">537</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">613</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">765</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="3">Dynamic visc. 120°C, 26s<sup>-1</sup> (mPas)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2804</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">3168</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">3550</entry></row><row><entry align="right" namest="2"/><entry align="left" namest="3">2450</entry><entry align="right" namest="4"/><entry align="left" namest="5">2639</entry><entry align="right" namest="6"/><entry align="left" namest="7">2875</entry></row><row><entry align="right" namest="2"/><entry align="left" namest="3">2368</entry><entry align="right" namest="4"/><entry align="left" namest="5">2461</entry><entry align="right" namest="6"/><entry align="left" namest="7">2615</entry></row><row><entry align="right" namest="2"/><entry align="left" namest="3">2283</entry><entry align="right" namest="4"/><entry align="left" namest="5">2314</entry><entry align="right" namest="6"/><entry align="left" namest="7">2467</entry></row><row><entry align="left">52</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2291</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2237</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2381</entry></row><row><entry align="left">79</entry></row><row><entry align="left">105</entry></row><row><entry align="left">132</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0062">All polymer modified bitumen exhibit attractive properties for road (and
other) applications. Moreover, a quite noticeable drop in dynamic viscosity
is observed, in particular for Experiments 2 and 3. The dynamic viscosity at
150°C for the binder of Experiment 3 is relatively high. Experiment 2 is
clearly the best performer.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Properties</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Exp 4</b></entry><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>Exp 5</b></entry><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>Exp 6</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>SBS-1</b></entry><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>SBS-2</b></entry><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>SBS-3</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Softening point R&amp;B (°C)</entry><entry align="left">94.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">91.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">88.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Penetration at 25°C (dmm)</entry><entry align="left">71</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">67</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">67</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Elastic recovery 20 cm, 13°C (%)</entry><entry align="left">76.2</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">73.2</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">79.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ductility 13°C, cm</entry><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">&gt;100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dynamic visc. 150°C, 26s<sup>-1</sup> (mPas)</entry><entry align="left">1083</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">854</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">790</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dynamic visc. 150°C, 395s<sup>-1</sup> (mPas)</entry><entry align="left">719</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">771</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">848</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dynamic visc.</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">3858</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">3640</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">3757 </entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="2">120°C, 26s<sup>-1</sup> (mPas)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2990</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">3001</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">3008</entry></row><row><entry align="right" namest="2"/><entry align="left" namest="3">2708</entry><entry align="right" namest="4"/><entry align="left" namest="5">2778</entry><entry align="right" namest="6"/><entry align="left" namest="7">2773</entry></row><row><entry align="right" namest="2"/><entry align="left" namest="3">2563</entry><entry align="right" namest="4"/><entry align="left" namest="5">2673</entry><entry align="right" namest="6"/><entry align="left" namest="7">2654</entry></row><row><entry align="left">52</entry></row><row><entry align="left">79</entry></row><row><entry align="left">105</entry></row><row><entry align="left">132</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0063">Exp 4 exhibits the greatest drop in viscosity, whilst having the largest
viscosity at 150°C, 26s<sup>-1</sup>.</p><heading>Example 2 (drainage test)</heading><p num="0064">Four polymer modified bitumen were prepared by blending 4.5% KRATON®
D1116 (a radial SBC polymer having about 4 arms attached to the residue
of the coupling agent.), or 6.5% KRATON D1116, or 4.5% SBS-1,
respectively 6% SBS-1 with the PX-100 bitumen. Blending was carried out
under standard conditions with a high shear mixer. PMB1 and PMB2 are
comparative binders (PMB1 = 4.5% D1116; PMB2 = 6% D1116), PMB3
and PMB4 are binders in accordance with the present invention (PMB3 =
4.5% SBS-1 and PMB4 = 6% AW03/95).</p><p num="0065">Stone Mastic Asphalt mixes were by mixing at 165°C 6.8% by weight one of
the above four polymer modified bitumen (at a pre-mixing temperature of 
175°C) with a pre-heated gap graded aggregate (175°C) comprising 10.3%
by weight filler; 12.8% by weight crushed sand; 13.0% aggregate 4-8 mm
⊘; 13.1 % by weight aggregate 8-11 mm ⊘, and 50.8% by weight aggregate
11-16 mm ⊘.</p><p num="0066">The SMA mixes were subjected to the Schellenberg binder drainage test
(according to the draft Comité Européen de Normalisation standard no.
12697-18), which measures the drainage during 1 hour at mixing
temperature plus 25°C. The results are set out in Table 6.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Binder composition</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>PMB1</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>PMB2</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>PMB3</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>PMB4</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Softening point Ring &amp;Ball (°C)</entry><entry align="right">74</entry><entry align="right">82.5</entry><entry align="right">64</entry><entry align="right">97</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity (mPas)</entry><entry align="right">2327</entry><entry align="right">-</entry><entry align="right">1944</entry><entry align="right">2419</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right">637</entry><entry align="right">986</entry><entry align="right">623</entry><entry align="right">915</entry></row><row><entry align="left"> @</entry><entry align="right">233</entry><entry align="right">391</entry><entry align="right">231</entry><entry align="right">405</entry></row><row><entry align="left">120°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left"> @</entry></row><row><entry align="left">150°C</entry></row><row><entry align="left"> @</entry></row><row><entry align="left">180°C </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Av. Drainage (%)</entry><entry align="right">2.0</entry><entry align="right">1.5</entry><entry align="right">0.6</entry><entry align="right">0.7</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0067">The binders with both 4.5 and 6% of SBS-1 had substantially reduced
drainage.</p><heading><b>Technical Field</b></heading><p num="0068">The present invention concerns asphalt binders based on Polymer Modified
Bitumen (PMBs), as well as Hot Mix Asphalt (HMA) based on asphalt
binders and mineral aggregate, in particular gap-graded aggregate, as well
as pavements made from said HMAs. Also claimed is the novel polymer
composition for use in HMA application, and in other asphalt applications,
including repair, coating and roofing applications. The new polymer
composition may have other applications, e.g. as mentioned in this
specification, as well.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An asphalt binder comprising 85 to 98.5 parts by weight of a bitumen and
15-1.5 parts by weight of a polymer composition, wherein the polymer
composition comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) from 5 to 70% by weight of a linear styrenic block copolymer (SBC1)
comprising at least two polymer blocks each substantially made of an
aromatic vinyl compound and at least one polymer block substantially made
of a conjugated diene compound and having an apparent molecular weight
greater than 250,000 and/or a radial styrenic block copolymer (SBC2) having
three or more polymer arms attached to the residue of a cross-linking agent
or multifunctional compound, comprising at least two polymer blocks each
substantially made of an aromatic vinyl compound and at least one polymer
block substantially made of a conjugated diene compound and wherein the
polymer arms have an average apparent molecular weight greater than
125,000 and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) from 95 to 30% by weight of an elastomer (EI) having an apparent molecular
weight in the range of 120,000 to 250,000, preferably a styrenic diblock
copolymer having one polymer block substantially made of an aromatic vinyl
compound and at least one polymer block substantially made of a conjugated
diene compound .</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>An asphalt binder as claimed in claim 1, wherein the styrenic block
copolymer has a molecular weight in the range of 250,000 to 800,000 if said
copolymer is a linear polymer, or in the range of 500,000 to 1,500,000 if said
copolymer is a branched or star-shaped polymer</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>An asphalt binder as claimed in claim 2, wherein the styrenic block
copolymer is selected from the group consisting of those of the formulae
(B)p -(A-B)2 X; or (B)p -A(B-A)n -(B)p, (linear SBC1)((B)p (A-B)n)m X (radial SBC2)
wherein A represents the polymer block substantially made of an aromatic vinyl
compound, typically a polystyrene block; B a polymer block substantially
made of a conjugated diene, typically a polybutadiene block, n is an integer
greater than or equal to 1, m is an integer greater than 2, p is 0 or 1, and X is
the residue of a coupling agent or multifunctional monomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>An asphalt binder as claimed in any one of claims 1 to 3, wherein the
styrenic block copolymer and elastomer may be used in relative amounts of
15 to 70% by weight (SBC1 and/or SBC2) and 85 to 30% by weight (EI).</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An asphalt binder as claimed in any one of claims 1 to 3, wherein the
styrenic block copolymer and elastomer may be used in relative amounts of
20 to 50% by weight (SBC1 and/or SBC2) and 80 to 50% by weight (EI).</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>An asphalt binder as claimed in any one of claims 1 to 3, wherein component
(i) and (ii) are components of a polymer composition wherein the elastomer
(EI) is a diblock copolymer of formula A-B that is co-produced in the
synthesis of the styrenic block copolymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>An asphalt binder as claimed in claim 6, wherein the styrenic block
copolymer polymer composition comprises a styrene-butadiene-styrene
coupled block copolymer with a large amount of diblock copolymer, with the
following characteristics:
styrene content in the range of 25-40%, preferably about 30% by weight:
diblock molecular weight 180,000-215,000, preferably about 200,000:
<claim-text><claim-text>diblock content 75-85%, preferably 80% by weight (which corresponds with a
coupling efficiency of 15-25, preferably 20%);</claim-text><claim-text>having a linear structure (manufactured with a difunctional coupling agent),</claim-text><claim-text>having an apparent MW (SBS) of
30,000-40,000//300,000-350,000//30,000-40,000, preferably 36000 - 328000
- 36000.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A hot mix asphalt comprising 2 to 8 parts by weight of the asphalt binder of
anyone of claims 1 to 7, and 98 to 92 parts by weight aggregate material.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The hot mix asphalt of claim 8, wherein the aggregate material is gap-graded
aggregate material, such as open gap-graded or dense gap-aggregate
material.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>Pavement comprising the compacted hot mix asphalt of claim 8 or 9.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>Polymer composition comprising a styrene-butadiene-styrene coupled
block copolymer with a large amount of diblock copolymer, with the following
characteristics:
styrene content in the range of 25-40%, preferably about 30% by weight:
diblock molecular weight 180,000-215,000, preferably about 200,000:
<claim-text><claim-text>diblock content 75-85%, preferably 80% by weight (which corresponds with a
coupling efficiency of 15-25, preferably 20%);</claim-text><claim-text>having a linear structure (manufactured with a difunctional coupling agent),</claim-text><claim-text>having an apparent MW (SBS) of
30,000-40,000//300,000-350,000//30,000-40,000, preferably 36000 - 328000
- 36000.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="151" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="230" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="158" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="231" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>