<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1217042-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1217042" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="24986745" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020626"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1217042-A1" status="new" fvid="23501933"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1217042</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020626</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01310286-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01310286</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011210</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-74291100-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>74291100</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001220</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B   7/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B   7/34        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B   7/44        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B   7/48        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B   7/74        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B   7/84        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B   7/88        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B  11/14        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29B  11/14        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  47/38        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29C  47/40        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29K  19/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B29K 105/16        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/20        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/36        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/54        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   9/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   9/06        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/07        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29B   7/44</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29B   7/48</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29B   7/74H</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29B   7/74P5</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B29C  47/40</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08J   3/20E+L83/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08J   3/22L83</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L29C283:00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L29C305:30</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L29C305:39P</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Kontinuierliche Herstellung von Flüssigsilikonkautschuk</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Continuous preparation of a liquid silicone rubber composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Préparation de caoutchouc de silicone liquide en continu</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1110691-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1110691</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4649005-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4649005</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5198171-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5198171</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEN ELECTRIC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1 River Road</street><city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BOUDREAU BRUCE E</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GROCELA-ROCHA TERESA</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>JERAM EDWARD MATTHEW</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>LIERMANN AUGUST O</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ROCHA GERARDO GALICIA</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WILLIAMS DAVID A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BOUDREAU, BRUCE E.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GROCELA-ROCHA, TERESA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>JERAM, EDWARD MATTHEW</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LIERMANN, AUGUST O.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ROCHA, GERARDO GALICIA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WILLIAMS, DAVID A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BOUDREAU, BRUCE E.</last-name><address><street>12 Robin Lane</street><city>Waterford, New York 12188</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GROCELA-ROCHA, TERESA</last-name><address><street>14 Canvasback Ridge</street><city>Waterford, New York 12188</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>JERAM, EDWARD MATTHEW</last-name><address><street>11 Conifer Drive</street><city>Burnt Hills, New York 12027</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>LIERMANN, AUGUST O.</last-name><address><street>214 McClellan Street</street><city>Schenectady, New York 12309</city> <country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ROCHA, GERARDO GALICIA</last-name> <address><street>14 Canvasback Ridge</street> <city>Waterford, New York 12188</city> <country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WILLIAMS, DAVID A.</last-name><address><street>26 Castleberry Drive</street><city>Ganesvoort, New York 12831</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Szary, Anne Catherine, Dr.</last-name><address><street>GE London Patent Operation, Essex House, 12-13 Essex Street</street><city>London WC2R 3AA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A continuous process provides a devolatilized liquid injection moldable
silicone composition. In the process, a filler, treating agent (16) and silicone
polymer are introduced into an extruder (22) having a length to diameter
ratio of at least greater than 50. The filler, treating agent (16) and silicone
elastomer are continuously compounded in the extruder (22) into a
devolatilized liquid injection moldable silicone composition. A system (40) for
preparing a liquid silicone rubber composition comprises a mixer (18) to
prepare a concentrate (20) of filler and silicone polymer, a long extruder (22)
having an L/D ratio of greater than 50, connected to the mixer (18) to receive
the concentrate (20) from the mixer (18) and to compound and devolatilize the
concentrate (20), a treating agent (16) and silicone polymer into a liquid
silicone rubber composition containing volatiles and a cooler to receive the
liquid silicone rubber composition to cool, homogenize and further
devolatilized the composition.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The invention relates to a process of preparing a liquid silicon rubber (LSR)
composition.</p><p num="0002">An LSR composition also referred to as a LIM composition, is a multicomponent
combination of a vinyl-containing polydiorgansiloxane fluid, a
hydrogen-containing polydiorganosiloxane fluid, an effective amount of a
platinum catalyst and a reinforcing filler, such as a fumed silica and
additional additives. Typically, two component mixtures are mixed and
charged into a preheated mold where they are rapidly cured to produce a
rubber part. A first component mixture includes a vinyl-containing
polydiorgansiloxane fluid, a silica filler and an effective amount of a platinum
catalyst and a second component mixture includes a hydrogen containing
polydiorganosiloxane fluid in combination with other ingredients, including a
vinyl containing polyorganosiloxane fluid and a silica filler.</p><p num="0003">Typically, the LSR composition is produced by kneading a
polydiorganosiloxane, inorganic filler and additives by means of a kneading
machine such as a Banbury mixer, a turbulizer, a change can mixer or a low
intensity double arm dough mixer. In this process, polydiorganosiloxane,
inorganic filler, treating agents and additives are batch mixed until desired
properties are obtained. The batch mixing process can take 12 to 30 hours per
batch. After mixing, the LSR composition is stripped of volatiles and cooled.
This final step requires additional time to complete preparation of the LSR
composition.</p><p num="0004">A batch process requires long residence times and large amounts of energy.
Non-homogeneous shear and extensional stresses across a commercial sized 
batch can result in non-uniform size distribution of filler that results in
variations in properties. Different physical properties may result form batch to
batch. Batches processed at different times may be characterized by different
physical properties. The batch process is labor, energy and capital intensive
and produces materials of only marginal consistency.</p><p num="0005">There is a need for a continuous process that consistently produces a
devolatilized LSR composition from polymer, filler and additives.</p><heading>BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0006">The invention provides a continuous process that prepares a devolatilized
LSR composition. The process comprises introducing a filler, treating agent
and silicone polymer into an extruder having a length to diameter ratio of at
least greater than 50. The filler, treating agent and silicone polymer are
continuously compounded and devolatilized in the extruder into a
devolatilized LSR composition.</p><p num="0007">In an embodiment, the invention provides a system for preparing a liquid
silicone rubber composition. The system comprises a mixer to prepare a
densified concentrate of filler and silicone polymer, a long extruder having an
L/D ratio of greater than 50, connected to the mixer to receive the densified
concentrate from the mixer and to compound and devolatilize the densified
concentrate, a treating agent and silicone polymer into a liquid silicone rubber
composition containing volatiles and a cooler to receive the liquid silicone
rubber composition to cool, homogenize and further devolatilized the
composition.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0008"><sl><li>FIG. 1 is a schematic representation of a continuous LSR composition process; </li><li>FIG. 2 is a schematic representation of an overall process for preparing an LSR
composition;</li></sl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0009">The invention reduces filler treatment reaction time and provides an
economical system for producing silicone compositions including LSR
compositions. Two parts of an LSR composition can be made simultaneously.
Inventories can be reduced and equipment clean-out required between runs
of a batch process can be eliminated.</p><p num="0010">In one step of the process, filler surface treatment is effected by mixing and
reacting filler, polydimethylsiloxane polymer and treating agents. The
mixture can then be stripped of volatiles and cooled. According to the
invention, filler treatment is reduced from hours to a few minutes, e.g., 2-6.
The filler is continuously in-situ treated to produce a base, which can be
filtered and then catalyzed.</p><p num="0011">In one embodiment, the process comprises four steps; 1) filler densification, 2)
In-situ treatment, volatiles stripping and filtering, 3) cooling, homogenization
and de-airing and 4) catalization. Prior to densification, the filler can be premixed
with silicone polymer to facilitate feeding into a reactor. A co-rotating
twin screw extruder can be used as the reactor to mix the densified filler with
treating agents (HMDZ, water, vinyl silazane) and additional polymer.</p><p num="0012">The subsequent reaction is effected at higher temperatures and pressures than
in a batch process. The in-situ treatment can require a minimum residence
time in the extruder, a temperature in the range of 160-210°C and pressure
between about 70 and about 300 psi. </p><p num="0013">Stripping of volatiles can be effected toward the end of the extruder while the
material is hot thereby eliminating secondary operations. Residual amounts
of nitrogen containing by-products measured as parts per million HMDZ can
be at about the 100 ppm level. Filtration can be done at the discharge of the
extruder while the material is hot, eliminating secondary operations. Cooling
and de-airing can be effected in a separate counter-rotating mixer, which can
provide back-mixing and a high residence time to homogenize the material
into a base.</p><p num="0014">Finally, the base can be divided in two components and separately mixed in
static mixers with catalyst and other additives to produce two separate "A"
and "B" components. The two components can be made simultaneously to
reduce inventories.</p><p num="0015">These and other features will become apparent from the drawings and
following detailed discussion, which by way of example without limitation
describe preferred embodiments of the present invention.</p><p num="0016">In FIG. 1, a filler such as fumed silica is continuously in situ treated and
compounded with a silicone polymer such as a vinyl-terminated
polydimethylsiloxane. In a first step, fumed silica 12, an initial amount of
silicone polymer 14 and a treating agent 16 are charged into a continuous
mixer 18 such as a Bepex Turbolizer to form a densified polymer/filler mass.</p><p num="0017">The filler that can be used in this invention is any inorganic filler with silanol
surface groups that can be compounded with silicone polymers. Examples of
inorganic fillers include a reinforcing silica such as fumed silica or
precipitated silica. A single filler or a combination of fillers can be used to
reinforce the silicone polymer. </p><p num="0018">The silicone polymer used in the compositions of the present invention is
typically a vinyl-terminated polydimethylsiloxane having a viscosity varying
from 100 to 2,000,000 cps at 25°C. The polymer can be represented by
recurring units of Formula I:
<img id="img-00050001" orientation="unknown" wi="119" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050001.tif" inline="no" he="55"/>
wherein, R<sup>1</sup> independently at each occurrence represents C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl, or C<sub>2-4</sub>
alkylene; R<sup>2</sup> independently at each occurrence represents C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub>
haloalkyl or C<sub>2-4</sub> alkylene; R<sup>3</sup> independently at each occurrence represents H,
C<sub>1-10</sub> alkyl, C<sub>2-4</sub> alkylene, C<sub>4-6</sub> cycloalkyl, OH or C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> haloalkyl; and n
represents an integer so that the viscosity of the silicone polymer varies from
100 to 2,000,000 cps at 25°C, preferably from 4,000 to about 10,000 cps at 25°C.
Broadly, n can be about 80 to about 3500, desirably, n is a value of about 100
to less than 1000.</p><p num="0019">A further preferred composition comprises a silicone polymer wherein, R<sup>1</sup>
independently at each occurrence represents, CH<sub>3</sub> or CH=CH<sub>2</sub>; R<sup>2</sup>
independently at each occurrence represents, CH<sub>3</sub>, CH=CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CF<sub>3</sub>;
R<sup>3</sup> independently at each occurrence represents CH<sub>3</sub>, CH=CH<sub>2</sub>, OH or
CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CF<sub>3</sub>; and n represents an integer from about 200 to about 900. </p><p num="0020">Another embodiment provides a composition wherein the vinyl content of the
silicone polymer ranges from about 0.05% to about 0.5 % by weight of the
silicone polymer.</p><p num="0021">The amount of filler in the densification step can be from about 20 to about
150 parts by weight, desirably from about 30 to about 100 parts by weight and
preferably from about 40 to about 70 parts by weight, per 100 parts by weight
of the high viscosity silicone polymer. During the compounding step,
addition of further silicone polymer reduces the proportion of silica in the
final silicone composition to about 10 to about 100 parts by weight, desirably
from about 15 to about 90 parts by weight and preferably from about 25 to
about 70 parts by weight, per 100 parts by weight of the total high viscosity
silicone polymer.</p><p num="0022">The treating agent is a silanol or methoxy stopped silicone polymer that reacts
with the filler surface hydroxyl or silanol groups to prevent a condensation
reaction among filler particles or between filler and gum molecules that
otherwise leads to stiffening and loss of elastomeric properties. The treating
agent reduces filler silanol groups and reduces the time required for aging of
the silicone, to prevent crepe hardening and/or to regulate plasticity. The
treating agent can be an organosilane, an organosilazane, a low-viscosity
polyorganosiloxance or a silicone resin, which has a silanol group and/or an
alkoxy group having 1 to 6 carbon atoms. Examples include
diphenylsilanediol, dimethylsilanediol, methyltriethoxysilane and
phenyltrimethoxysilane. The low-viscosity polysiloxane may contain one or
more kinds of organic groups selected from a methyl group, a phenyl group,
a vinyl group and a 3,3,3-trifluoropropyl group. Preferred silanol-reactant
treating agents include silanol-stopped polydimethylsiloxane,
octamethylcyclotetrasiloxane (D4) and hexamethyldisilazane (HMDZ). The 
viscosity of the polysiloxane measured at 25°C is in the range of from about 1
to about 300 cP, preferably from about 5 to about 100 cP.</p><p num="0023">The treating agent can be added in the compounding step in a weight
proportion of about 0.1 to about 100 parts fluid to 100 parts of filler, desirably
about 0.5 to about 75 parts fluid to 100 parts of filler and preferably about 1.0
to about 50 parts fluid to 100 parts of filler. The treating agent can react to
reduce available groups of the filler to a concentration of between about 8 to
about 2 hydroxyl groups/ (nanometer)<sup>2</sup> of filler, preferably between about 7 to
about 3 hydroxyl groups/ (nanometer)<sup>2</sup> of filler. In an embodiment, the
treating agent can be a combination of HMDZ and water. This combination
can comprise a weight ratio of HMDZ/water of between about 0.1 to 10,
desirably between 0.2 to 5 and preferably between 0.3 to 3.</p><p num="0024">In the extruder 22, a densified filler and polymer concentrate 20 and
additional silicone polymer 24, treating agent and water are fed at barrels 1 to
2, further additional fluid 26 is added downstream at about barrel 16 and
volatiles are stripped in two vacuum vents 28, 30 at barrels 18 to 19 and at 21
to 22. Water 32 is injected between vent sections to facilitate stripping.
According to the invention, the L/D ratio of the entire extruder is at least
greater than 50 to achieve proper filler treatment and stripping of volatiles.
Desirably, the L/D ratio is greater than 60 and preferably greater than 70.
The exemplary extruder 22 of FIG. 1 has an L/D ratio of 78.</p><p num="0025">During the extruder step, addition of further silicone polymer reduces the
proportion of silica in the final silicone composition to about 5 to about 100
parts by weight, desirably from about 10 to about 40 parts by weight and
preferably from about 15 to about 30 parts by weight, per 100 parts by weight
of the total high viscosity silicone polymer. </p><p num="0026">Reaction between silanol groups on the filler and the treating agent takes
place under pressure and at elevated temperature in the extruder
compounding step. The screws of the treatment section (barrels 3 to 18), can
be configured to provided a pressure of about 16 and about 400 psi.</p><p num="0027">Desirably, the pressure is about 40 to about 300 psi and preferably about 100
and about 200 psi. Temperature in a feed section of the extruder (L/D&lt;9) is
maintained at less than about 150°C, preferably less than about 120°C.
Temperature is controlled in the treatment section (L/D = 9 to discharge)
between about 100 and 250 °C, desirably between 120 and 240 °C and
preferably between 130 and about 230 °C.</p><p num="0028">Compounding in extruder 22 produces a base silicone composition 32 that can
be used to produce LSR silicone composition components.</p><p num="0029">FIG. 2 illustrates an overall process and system for preparing an LSR
composition. In FIG. 2, the system 40 includes long extruder 42 having an
L/D ratio of at least greater than 50. In the process, filler is fed from feeder 44
to densifier 46, e.g., a Bepex turbolizer or a Drais mixer, where it is mixed
with initial silicone polymer 48 to form a concentrate of a filler and polymer
concentrate 50. The densified filler and polymer concentrate 50 is crammed
by means of screw feed 52, e.g., a Werner and Pfleiderer ESBV crammer
feeder, into the long extruder 42</p><p num="0030">Additional silicone polymer 54 is combined in mixer 56 with additives such as
HMDZ treating agent 58, water 60 and silazane 62 and is then charged 64 into
the long extruder 42 for compounding with densified filler and polymer
concentrate 50. Further additional silicone polymer 66 can be mixed with
vinyl polymer 68 and charged 70 to the long extruder 42 downstream from
the charge of concentrate 50. </p><p num="0031">The compounded and reacted components are devolatilized at vents 72 and
74 with water 76 charged between the vents. Devolatilization is important for
at least two reasons. First, devolatilization removes unreacted treating agents
to "quench" further reaction with filler silanol groups. Otherwise, further
reaction can diminish filler reinforcement properties in the heat-vulcanizable
silicone composition. Second, devolatilization removes surplus liquids that
adversely affect rheological properties of the silicone composition.</p><p num="0032">The compounded, reacted and devolatilized LSR composition is filtered 78
and pumped 80 to a cooler 82. The LSR composition is cooled and back
mixed in cooler 82 to de-air and to further homogenize the composition. The
cooler 82 can be under vacuum to produce further devolatilization. Cooler 82
can be a counter-rotating twin screw mixer such as a LIST ORP. The volatiles
84 from the cooler are combined with volatiles 86 from the extruder 42 and
are exhausted by vacuum 88 to volatiles recovery 90.</p><p num="0033">Cooled LSR composition 92 is divided into two streams, A and B. Stream A is
pumped 94 with platinum catalyst and other additives A 96 to static mixer 98
to produce component mixture A 100 and stream B is pumped 102 with
hydrides and other additives B 104 to produce component mixture B 106.
Component mixture A 100 and component mixture B 106 can be charged to a
mold (not shown) where they can be rapidly cured to produce a rubber part.</p><p num="0034">These and other features will become apparent from the following detailed
discussion, which by way of example without limitation describes preferred
embodiments of the present invention. </p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0035">Filler was mixed with vinyl-terminated polydimethylsiloxane (viscosity about
40,000 cps at 25°C, n about 800) in a Bepex Turbolizer to provide a densified
filler concentrate. The densified concentrate was fed into a 53 mm, Krupp
Werner &amp; Pfleiderer co-rotating twin screw extruder with a 78 L/D ratio. In
the extruder, the filler was mixed with HMDZ, water, vinyl silazane and
additional vinyl-terminated polydimethylsiloxane at barrels 1 and 2.
Downstream (barrel 6), the filler was mixed with more vinyl-terminated
polydimethylsiloxane and the mixture was compounded under elevated
temperature in a section of the extruder that was sealed to maintain pressure.
Table 1 shows conditions for two runs of the extruding step.</p><p num="0036">Hot compounded base material was discharged from the extruder to a LIST
ORP jacketed mixer for cooling. The base was subjected to back mixing in the
mixer to even-out inconsistencies to provide a homogenous product. The
mixer was under a vacuum, which served to further strip and de-air the base.</p><p num="0037">The base is divided into two parts (A and B), which are fed via metering
pumps into static mixers. Platinum catalyst and other additives are
introduced into part A base just prior to feed to the mixer. Hydrides and
other additives are introduced into part B base before mixing.</p><p num="0038">Properties of two final formulations each containing catalyst and hydride are
shown in Table 2. The two rows of results shown in Table 2 correspond to the
two runs of Table 1. <img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="82" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/><img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="82" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/></p><p num="0039">These Examples show that a devolatilized LSR composition with excellent
properties can be continuously produced from polymer, filler and additives
according to the invention.</p><p num="0040">While preferred embodiments of the invention have been described, the
present invention is capable of variation and modification and therefore
should not be limited to the precise details of the Examples. The invention
includes changes and alterations that fall within the purview of the following
claims.</p><p num="0041">For the sake of good order, various features of the invention are set out in the
following clauses:-
<sl><li>1. A process of preparing a liquid silicone rubber composition,
comprising:
<sl><li>introducing a filler, treating agent (16) and silicone polymer into an extruder
(22) having a length to diameter ratio of at least greater than 50; and</li><li>continuously compounding and devolatilizing said filler, treating agent (16)
and silicone polymer into said liquid silicone rubber composition in said
extruder (22).</li></sl></li><li>2. The process of clause 1, wherein said extruder (22) is a co-rotating,
intermeshing double screw extruder (22).</li><li>3. The process of clause 1, comprising densifying filler with an initial
amount of silicone polymer prior to introduction of said filler into said
extruder (22).</li><li>4. The process of clause 1, further comprising discharging said liquid
rubber composition from said extruder (22) to a cooler.</li><li>5. The process of clause 4, wherein said cooler comprises a counter
rotating double screw extruder (22).</li><li>6. The process of clause 4, wherein said liquid silicone rubber
composition is cooled, homogenized and further devolatilized in said cooler. </li><li>7. The process of clause 6, wherein said liquid silicone rubber is in
residence in said cooler for a period greater than residence in said extruder
(22).</li><li>8. The process of clause 1, further comprising dividing said liquid silicone
rubber composition into a first stream and a second stream.</li><li>9. The process of clause 8, wherein a platinum catalyst is added to said
first stream to produce a component mixture A (100) and a crosslinker is
added to said second stream to produce a component mixture B (108).</li><li>10. The process of clause 9, wherein said component mixture A (100) and
said component mixture B (108) are injected into a mold where they are cured
to produce a rubber part.</li><li>11. The process of clause 1, wherein said filler is a raw, untreated silica
(12).</li><li>12. The process of clause 1, wherein said filler is a pretreated filler with
treating agent (16).</li><li>13. The process of clause 12, wherein said treating agent (16) is a silanol-reacting
treating agent (16).</li><li>14. The process of clause 1, wherein said filler contains silanol groups and
said treating agent (16) comprises silanol-stopped polydimethylsiloxane,
octamethylcyclotetrasiloxane (D4) or hexamethyldisilazane (HMDZ).</li><li>15. The process of clause 14, further comprising maintaining an elevated
pressure in a section of said extruder (22) while compounding said filler,
treating agent (16) and silicone fluid (14) to enhance reaction.</li><li>16. The process of clause 15, comprising maintaining a pressure between
about 16 and about 400 psi.</li><li>17. The process of clause 15, comprising maintaining a pressure between
about 40 to about 300 psi. </li><li>18 The process of clause 15, comprising maintaining a pressure between
about 100 and about 200 psi.</li><li>19. The process of clause 1, comprising controlling temperature in said
extruder (22) in a feed section (L/D&lt;9) to less than 150°C and then from said
feed section to discharge between about 120 and about 240 °C.</li><li>20. The process of clause 1, comprising controlling temperature in said
extruder (22) in a feed section (L/D&lt;9) to less than 120°C and then from said
feed section to discharge between about 130 and about 230 °C.</li><li>21. The process of clause 1, wherein said length to diameter ratio is at least
greater than 60.</li><li>22. The process of clause 1, wherein said length to diameter ratio is at least
greater than 70.</li><li>23. The process of clause 1, wherein said silicone polymer comprises a
vinyl-terminated polydimethylsiloxane represented by recurring units of
Formula I:
<img id="img-00150001" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00150001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/>
wherein, R<sup>1</sup> independently at each occurrence represents C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl, or C<sub>2-4</sub>
alkylene; R<sup>2</sup> independently at each occurrence represents C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub>
haloalkyl or C<sub>2-4</sub> alkylene; R<sup>3</sup> independently at each occurrence represents H,
C<sub>1-10</sub> alkyl, C<sub>2-4</sub> alkylene, C<sub>4-6</sub> cycloalkyl, OH or C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> haloalkyl; and n is a
value of about 100 to less than 1000.</li><li>24. The process of clause 23, wherein R<sup>1</sup> independently at each occurrence
represents, CH<sub>3</sub> or CH=CH<sub>2</sub>; R<sup>2</sup> independently at each occurrence represents, 
CH<sub>3</sub>, CH=CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CF<sub>3</sub>; and R<sup>3</sup> independently at each occurrence
represents CH<sub>3</sub>, CH=CH<sub>2</sub>, OH or CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CF<sub>3</sub>.</li><li>25. A process of preparing a silicone composition, comprising:
<sl><li>introducing a filler, treating agent (16) and silicone polymer into an extruder
(22) having a length to diameter ratio of at least greater than 50;</li><li>continuously compounding and devolatilizing said filler, treating agent (16)
and silicone polymer into said silicone composition in said extruder (22); and
discharging said silicone composition from said extruder (22) to a cooler.</li></sl></li><li>26. The process of clause 25, wherein said cooler comprises a counter
rotating double screw extruder (22).</li><li>27. The process of clause 25, wherein said silicone composition is cooled,
homogenized and further devolatilized in said cooler.</li><li>28. The process of clause 27, wherein said silicone composition is in
residence in said cooler for a period greater than residence in said extruder
(22).</li><li>29. The process of clause 25, wherein said silicone polymer comprises a
vinyl-terminated polydimethylsiloxane represented by recurring units of
Formula I:
<img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="79" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="42"/>
wherein, R<sup>1</sup> independently at each occurrence represents C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl, or C<sub>2-4</sub>
alkylene; R<sup>2</sup> independently at each occurrence represents C<sub>1-4</sub> alkyl, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub>
haloalkyl or C<sub>2-4</sub> alkylene; R<sup>3</sup> independently at each occurrence represents H,
C<sub>1-10</sub> alkyl, C<sub>2-4</sub> alkylene, C<sub>4-6</sub> cycloalkyl, OH or C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> haloalkyl; and n 
represents an integer such that viscosity of the silicone polymer is between
about 100 to about 2,000,000 cps at 25°C.</li><li>30. The process of clause 29, wherein R<sup>1</sup> independently at each occurrence
represents, CH<sub>3</sub> or CH=CH<sub>2</sub>; R<sup>2</sup> independently at each occurrence represents,
CH<sub>3</sub>, CH=CH<sub>2</sub> or CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CF<sub>3</sub>; R<sup>3</sup> independently at each occurrence
represents CH<sub>3</sub>, CH=CH<sub>2</sub>, OH or CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CF<sub>3</sub>; and n represents an integer
from about 4,000 to about 10,000.</li><li>31. A system (40) for preparing a liquid silicone rubber composition,
comprising:
<sl><li>a mixer (18) to prepare a concentrate (20) of filler and silicone polymer;</li><li>a long extruder (22) having an L/D ratio of greater than 50, connected to said
mixer (18) to receive said concentrate (20) from said mixer (18) and to
compound and devolatilize said concentrate (20), a treating agent (16) and</li><li>silicone polymer into a liquid silicone rubber composition containing
volatiles; and</li><li>a cooler to receive said liquid silicone rubber composition to cool,
homogenize and further devolatilized said composition.</li></sl></li><li>32. The system (40) of clause 31, wherein said extruder (22) is a co-rotating,
intermeshing double screw extruder (22).</li><li>33. The system (40) of clause 31, wherein said cooler comprises a counter
rotating double screw extruder (22).</li><li>34. The system (40) of clause 31, further comprising a mold to receive at
least a part of said composition for molding into a rubber part.</li><li>35. The system (40) of clause 31, wherein said long extruder (22) has an
L/D ratio of greater than about 60.</li><li>36. The system (40) of clause 31, wherein said long extruder (22) has an
L/D ratio of greater than about 70.</li></sl></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process of preparing a liquid silicone rubber composition,
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>introducing a filler, treating agent (16) and silicone polymer into an extruder
(22) having a length to diameter ratio of at least greater than 50; and</claim-text><claim-text>continuously compounding and devolatilizing said filler, treating agent (16)
and silicone polymer into said liquid silicone rubber composition in said
extruder (22).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, wherein said extruder (22) is a co-rotating,
intermeshing double screw extruder (22).</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, comprising densifying filler with an initial
amount of silicone polymer prior to introduction of said filler into said
extruder (22).</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, further comprising discharging said liquid
rubber composition from said extruder (22) to a cooler.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The process of claim 4, wherein said cooler comprises a counter
rotating double screw extruder (22).</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The process of claim 4, wherein said liquid silicone rubber composition
is cooled, homogenized and further devolatilized in said cooler.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The process of claim 6, wherein said liquid silicone rubber is in
residence in said cooler for a period greater than residence in said extruder
(22).</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, further comprising dividing said liquid silicone
rubber composition into a first stream and a second stream.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The process of claim 8, wherein a platinum catalyst is added to said
first stream to produce a component mixture A (100) and a crosslinker is
added to said second stream to produce a component mixture B (108).</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, wherein said filler is a raw, untreated silica (12)
or is a pretreated filler with treating agent (16).</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, wherein said filler contains silanol groups and
said treating agent (16) comprises silanol-stopped polydimethylsiloxane,
octamethylcyclotetrasiloxane (D4) or hexamethyldisilazane (HMDZ).</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The process of claim 11, further comprising maintaining an elevated
pressure in a section of said extruder (22) while compounding said filler,
treating agent (16) and silicone fluid (14) to enhance reaction.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, comprising controlling temperature in said
extruder (22) in a feed section (L/D&lt;9) to less than 150°C and then from said
feed section to discharge between about 120 and about 240 °C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, wherein said length to diameter ratio is at least
greater than 60.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, wherein said length to diameter ratio is at least
greater than 70.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The process of claim 1, wherein said silicone polymer comprises a
vinyl-terminated polydimethylsiloxane represented by recurring units of
Formula I:

wherein, R1 independently at each occurrence represents C1-4 alkyl, or C2-4
alkylene; R2 independently at each occurrence represents C1-4 alkyl, C1-C4
haloalkyl or C2-4 alkylene; R3 independently at each occurrence represents H,
C1-10 alkyl, C2-4 alkylene, C4-6 cycloalkyl, OH or C1-C4 haloalkyl; and n is a
value of about 100 to less than 1000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The process of claim 16, wherein R1 independently at each occurrence
represents, CH3 or CH=CH2; R2 independently at each occurrence represents,
CH3, CH=CH2 or CH2CH2CF3; and R3 independently at each occurrence
represents CH3, CH=CH2, OH or CH2CH2CF3.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>