<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1077253-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1077253" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="26847093" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010221"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1077253-A1" status="new" fvid="23043102"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1077253</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010221</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00307155-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00307155</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000821</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-14985099-P" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>14985099</doc-number><kind>P</kind><date>19990819</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="US-57398900-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>57398900</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000517</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  35/12        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  35/12        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   5/02        20060101A I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   5/02        20060101C I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   5/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   5/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   5/08        20060101A I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   5/08        20060101C I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C12N   5/06B20</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C12N   5/06B26</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61K35:12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M12N501:390</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M12N506:26</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verwendung von Fettgewebe-abgeleiteten Stromalen Zellen zur Differenzierung in Chondrozyten und ihre Verwendung zur Reparatur von Knorpelgewebe</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Use of adipose tissue-derived stromal cells for chondrocyte differentiation and cartilage repair</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Utilisation de cellules de stroma adipeuses pour leur différentiation en chondrocytes et leur utilisation pour la réparation de cartilage</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-5446143-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5446143</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1995033821-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1995033821</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999028444-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999028444</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>AHRENS M ET AL:  "Expression of human bone morphogenetic proteins-2 or -4 in murine mesenchymal progenitor C3H10T1/2 cells induces differentiation into distinct mesenchymal cell lineages" DNA AND CELL BIOLOGY,US,NEW YORK, NY, vol. 12, no. 10, 1 December 1993 (1993-12-01), pages 871-880, XP002087786 ISSN: 1044-5498</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>BOND A ET AL:  "Human subcutaneous preadipocytes differentiate into osteoblasts." FASEB JOURNAL, vol. 13, no. 4 PART 1, 12 March 1999 (1999-03-12), page A600 XP000971053 Annual Meeting of the Professional Research Scientists for Experimental Biology 99;Washington, D.C., USA; April 17-21, 1999 ISSN: 0892-6638</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>GIMBLE J M ET AL:  "Adipose tissue: Derived stromal cells are multipotent." JOURNAL OF BONE AND MINERAL RESEARCH, vol. 15, no. Suppl. 1, September 2000 (2000-09), page S508 XP000972512 Twenty-Second Annual Meeting of the American Society for Bone and Mineral Research;Toronto, Ontario, Canada; September 22-26, 2000 ISSN: 0884-0431</text><sources><source category="T" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>POLIARD A ET AL:  "Controlled conversion of an immortalized mesodermal progenitor cell towards osteogenic, chondrogenic, or adipogenic pathways" JOURNAL OF CELL BIOLOGY,US,ROCKEFELLER UNIVERSITY PRESS, NEW YORK, US, vol. 130, no. 6, September 1995 (1995-09), pages 1461-1472, XP002099457 ISSN: 0021-9525</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>TAVASSOLI M:  "IN-VIVO DEVELOPMENT OF ADIPOSE TISSUE FOLLOWING IMPLANTATION OF LIPID DEPLETED CULTURED ADIPOCYTE" EXPERIMENTAL CELL RESEARCH, vol. 137, no. 1, 1982, pages 55-62, XP000972508 ISSN: 0014-4827</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ZEN BIO INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ZEN BIO, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Zen Bio, Inc.</last-name><address><street>Suite 102, 3200 Chapel Hill-Nelson Boulevard, P.O. Box 12503</street><city>Research Triangle Park, NC 27709</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GIMBLE JEFFREY</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HALVORSEN YUAN-DI CHANG</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WILKISON WILLIAM O</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GIMBLE, JEFFREY</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HALVORSEN, YUAN-DI CHANG</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WILKISON, WILLIAM O.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GIMBLE, JEFFREY</last-name><address><street>910 Constitution Drive, No.711</street><city>Durham, North Carolina 27705</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HALVORSEN, YUAN-DI CHANG</last-name><address><street>5128 Salem Ridge Road</street><city>Holly Springs, North Carolina 27540</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WILKISON, WILLIAM O.</last-name><address><street>9706 Gallop Lane</street><city>Bahama, North Carolin 27503</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MacDougall, Donald Carmichael</last-name><address><street>Cruikshank &amp;amp; Fairweather 19 Royal Exchange Square</street><city>Glasgow G1 3AE, Scotland</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country> <country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country> <country>PT</country> <country>SE</country> </ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Methods and compositions for directing adipose-derived stromal cells cultivated
<i>in vitro</i> to differentiate into cells of the chondrocyte lineage are disclosed. The invention
further provides a variety of chondroinductive agents which can be used singly or in
combination with other nutrient components to induce chondrogenesis in adipose-derived
stromal cells either in cultivating monolayers or in a biocompatible lattice or
matrix in a three-dimensional configuration. Use of the differentiated chondrocytes
for the therapeutic treatment of a number of human conditions and diseases including
repair of cartilage <i>in vivo</i> is disclosed.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>FIELD OF INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to methods and compositions for directing adipose-derived
stromal cells cultivated <i>in vitro</i> to differentiate into cells of the chondrocyte
lineage and particularly to such directed lineage induction prior to, or at the time of, their
implantation into a recipient or host for the therapeutic treatment of pathologic conditions
in humans and other species.</p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0002">Mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) are the formative pluripotent blast or
embryonic-like cells found in bone marrow, blood, dermis, and periosteum that are
capable of differentiating into specific types of mesenchymal or connective tissues
including <i>adipose,</i> osseous, cartilaginous, elastic, muscular, and fibrous connective
tissues. The specific differentiation pathway which these cells enter depends upon
various influences from mechanical influences and/or endogenous bioactive factors, such
as growth factors, cytokines, and/or local microenvironmental conditions established by
host tissues.</p><p num="0003">In prenatal organisms, the differentiation of MSCs into specialized connective
tissue cells is well established; for example embryonic chick, mouse or human limb bud
mesenchymal cells differentiate into cartilage, bone and other connective tissues (Caplan
A I (1981) In: 39th Annual Symposium of the Society for Developmental Biology, ed by
S. Subtelney and U Abbott, pp 3768. New York, Alan R Liss Inc; Elmer <i>et al.</i>(1981)
Teratology, <i>24</i>:215-223; Hauschka S.D. (1974) <i>Developmental Biology</i> (1974) <i>37</i>:345-368;
Solursh <i>et al</i>. (1981) <i>Developmental Biology</i>, 83:9-19; Swalla <i>et. al.</i> (1986) <i>Developmental Biology, 116</i>:31-38. In addition, a clonal rat fetus calvarial cell line has
also been shown to differentiate into muscle, fat, cartilage, and bone (Goshima <i>et
al</i>. (1991) <i>Clin Orthop Rel Res.</i> 269:274-283. The existence of MSCs in post-natal
organisms has not been widely studied with the objective of showing the differentiation
of post-embryonic cells into several mesodermal phenotypes. The few studies which
have been done involve the formation of bone and cartilage by bone marrow cells
following their encasement in diffusion chambers and <i>in vivo</i> transplantation (Ashton <i>et
al</i>.(1980) <i>Clin Orthop Rel Res, 151</i>:294-307; Bruder <i>et al.</i> (1990) <i>Bone Mineral, 11</i>:141-151,
1990). Recently, cells from chick periosteum have been isolated, expanded in
culture, and, under high density conditions <i>in vitro</i>, shown to differentiate into cartilage
and bone (Nakahara <i>et al.</i> (1991) <i>Exp Cell Res, 195</i>:492-503). Rat bone marrow-derived
mesenchymal cells have been shown to have the capacity to differentiate into osteoblasts
and chondrocytes when implanted <i>in</i> vivo (Dennis <i>et al.</i> (1991) <i>Cell Transpl,</i> 1:2332;
Goshima <i>et al</i>. (1991) <i>Clin Orthop Rel Res. 269</i>:274-283). Work by Johnstone <i>et al.</i> U.S,
Pat. No. 5,908,784 has shown the ability of mesenchymal cells derived from skin to
differentiate into cells biochemically and phenotypically similar to chondrocytes.</p><p num="0004">The adult bone marrow microenvironment is a potential source for these
hypothetical mesodermal stem cells. Cells isolated from adult marrow are referred to by
a variety of names, including stromal cells, stromal stem cells, mesenchymal stem cells
(MSCs), mesenchymal fibroblasts, reticular-endothelial cells, and Westen-Bainton cells
(Gimble <i>et al</i>. (Nov. 1996) <i>Bone</i> 19(5): 421-8). <i>In vitro</i> studies have determined that
these cells can differentiate along multiple mesodermal or mesenchymal lineage
pathways. These include, but are not limited to, adipocytes (Gimble, <i>et al.</i> (1992) <i>J. Cell
Biochem.</i> 50:73-82, chondrocytes; Caplan, <i>et al.</i> (1998) <i>J Bone Joint Surg. Am.</i>
80(12):1745-57; hematopoietic supporting cells, Gimble, <i>et al.</i> (1992) J. <i>Cell Biochem.</i>
50:73-82; myocytes, Prockop, <i>et al.</i> (1999) <i>J. Cell Biochem.</i>72(4):570-85; myocytes,
Charbord, <i>et al.</i>(1999) <i>Exp. Hematol,</i> 27(12):1782-95; and osteoblasts, Beresford <i>et al.</i>
(1993) <i>J. Cell Physiol. 154</i>:317-328). The bone marrow has been proposed as a source of
stromal stem cells for the regeneration of bone, cartilage, muscle, adipose tissue, and
other mesenchymal derived organs. The major limitations to the use of these cells are the 
difficulty and risk attendant upon bone marrow biopsy procedures and the low yield of
stem cells from this source.</p><p num="0005">Adipose tissue offers a potential alternative to the bone marrow as a source of
multipotential stromal stem cells. Adipose tissue is readily accessible and abundant in
many individuals. Obesity is a condition of epidemic proportions in the United States,
where over 50% of adults exceed the recommended BMI based on their height.
Adipocytes can be harvested by liposuction on an outpatient basis. This is a relatively
non-invasive procedure with cosmetic effects that are acceptable to the vast majority of
patients. It is well documented that adipocytes are a replenishable cell population. Even
after surgical removal by liposuction or other procedures, it is common to see a
recurrence of adipocytes in an individual over time, This suggests that adipose tissue
contains stromal stem cells which are capable of self-renewal.</p><p num="0006">Pathologic evidence suggests that adipose-derived stromal cells are capable of
differentiation along multiple mesenchymal lineages. The most common soft tissue
tumor, liposarcomas, develop from adipocyte-like cells. Soft tissue tumors of mixed
origin are relatively common. These may include elements of adipose tissue, muscle
(smooth or skeletal), cartilage, and/or bone. Just as bone forming cells within the bone
marrow can differentiate into adipocytes or fat cells, the extramedullary adipocytes are
capable of forming osteoblasts (Halvorsen WO 99/28444).</p><p num="0007">Cartilage is a hyperhydrated structure with water comprising 70% to 80% of its
weight. The remaining 20% to 30% comprises type II collagen and proteoglycan. The
collagen usually accounts for 70% of the dry weight of cartilage (in "Pathology" (1988)
Eds. Rubin &amp; Farber, J. B. Lippincott Company, PA pp. 1369-1371). Proteoglycans are
composed of a central protein core from which long chains of polysaccharides extend.
These polysaccharides, called glycosaminoglycans, include: chondroitin-4-sulfate,
chondroitin-6-sulfate, and keratan sulfate. Cartilage has a characteristic structural
organization consisting of chondrogenic cells dispersed within an endogenously produced
and secreted extracellular matrix. The cavities in the matrix which contain the
chondrocytes are called cartilage lacunae. Unlike bone, cartilage is neither innervated
nor penetrated by either the vascular or lymphatic systems (Clemente (1984) in "Gray's
Anatomy, 30.sup.th Edit," Lea &amp; Febiger). </p><p num="0008">Three types of cartilage are present in mammals and include: hyaline cartilage;
fibrocartilage and elastic cartilage (Rubin and Farber, supra). Hyaline cartilage consists
of a gristly mass having a firm, elastic consistency, is translucent and is pearly blue in
color. Hyaline cartilage is predominantly found on the articulating surfaces of
articulating joints. It is found also in epiphyseal plates, costal cartilage, tracheal
cartilage, bronchial cartilage and nasal cartilage. Fibrocartilage is essentially the same as
hyaline cartilage except that it contains fibrils of type 1 collagen that add tensile strength
to the cartilage. The collagenous fibers are arranged in bundles, with the cartilage cells
located between the bundles. Fibrocartilage is found commonly in the annulus fibrosis of
the invertebral disc, tendinous and ligamentous insertions, menisci, the symphysis pubis,
and insertions of joint capsules. Elastic cartilage also is similar to hyaline cartilage
except that it contains fibers of elastin. It is more opaque than hyaline cartilage and is
more flexible and pliant These characteristics are defined in part by the elastic fibers
embedded in the cartilage matrix. Typically, elastic cartilage is present in the pinna of the
ears, the epiglottis, and the larynx.</p><p num="0009">The surfaces of articulating bones in mammalian joints are covered with articular
cartilage. The articular cartilage prevents direct contact of the opposing bone surfaces
and permits the near frictionless movement of the articulating bones relative to one
another (Clemente, supra). Two types of articular cartilage defects are commonly
observed in mammals and include full-thickness and partial-thickness defects. The two-types
of defects differ not only in the extent of physical damage but also in the nature of
repair response each type of lesion elicits.</p><p num="0010">Full-thickness articular cartilage defects include damage to the articular cartilage,
the underlying subchondral bone tissue, and the calcified layer of cartilage located
between the articular cartilage and the subchondral bone. Full-thickness defects typically
arise during severe trauma of the joint or during the late stages of degenerative joint
diseases, for example, during osteoarthritis. Since the subchondral bone tissue is both
innervated and vascularized, damage to this tissue is often painful. The repair reaction
induced by damage to the subchondral bone usually results in the formation of
fibrocartilage at the site of the full-thickness defect. Fibrocartilage, however, lacks the 
biomechanical properties of articular cartilage and fails to persist in the joint on a long
term basis.</p><p num="0011">Partial-thickness articular cartilage defects arc restricted to the cartilage tissue
itself. These defects usually include fissures or clefts in the articulating surface of the
cartilage. Partial-thickness defects are caused by mechanical arrangements of the joint
which in turn induce wearing of the cartilage tissue within the joint. In the absence of
innervation and vasculature, partial-thickness defects do not elicit repair responses and
therefore tend not to heal. Although painless, partial-thickness defects often degenerate
into full-thickness defects.</p><p num="0012">In accordance with the present invention it has been observed by the inventors
that when human adipose tissue-derived stromal cells are associated in a three-dimensional
format they can be induced to commit and differentiate along the
chondrogenic pathway when contacted <i>in vitro</i> with certain chondroinductive agents or
factors. The three dimensional format is critical to the <i>in vitro</i> chondrogenesis of the
invention and the cells are - preferably condensed together, for example, as a packed or
pelleted cell mass or in an alginate matrix. This invention presents examples of methods
and composition for Lhe isolation, differentiation, and characterization of adult human
extramcdullary adipose tissue stromal cells along the chondrocyte lineage and outlines
their use for the treatment of a number of human conditions and diseases. This <i>in vitro</i>
process is believed to recapitulate that which occurs <i>in vivo</i> and can be used to facilitate
repair of cartilage <i>in vivo</i> in mammals.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF INVENTION</heading><p num="0013">The present invention provides methods and composition for consistent and
quantitative induction of stromal cells derived from subcutaneous, mammary, gonadal, or
omental adipose tissues into fully functional chondrocytes. The methods comprise
incubation of isolated adipose tissue-derived stromal cells, plated at densities of 500 to
20,000 cells/cm<sup>2</sup> in a chemically defined culture medium having or supplemented
with (1) a chondroinductive agent that can activate any cellular transduction pathway
leading to the mature chondrocyte phenotype; (2) an antibiotic; (3) a nutrient supplement 
such as fetal bovine serum or horse serum; (4) ascorbate or related vitamin C analogue;
and (5) a glucocorticoid or another chemical agent capable of activating the cellular
glucocorticoid receptor.</p><p num="0014">The present invention also provides a method for differentiating adipose
tissue derived stromal cells into chondrocytice cells by pelleting stromal cells
in medium such as DMEM or alpha-MEM or RPMI 1640 and supplementing
the medium with (1) a chondroinductive agent that can activate any cellular transduction
pathway leading to the mature chondrocyte phenotype; (2) an antibiotic; (3) a nutrient
supplement such as fetal bovine serum or horse serum; (4) ascorbate or related vitamin C
analogue; and (5) a glucocorticoid or another chemical agent capable of activating the
cellular glucocorticoid receptor.</p><p num="0015">The present invention also provides a method for differentiating adipose tissue
derived stromal cells into chondrocytic cells by suspending the cells in a calcium alginate
or other biocompatible lattice or matrix capable of supporting chondrogenesis in a three
dimensional configuration.</p><p num="0016">The present invention provides methods for determining the ability of these
culture conditions and agents to direct the differentiation and function of the adipose
tissue-derived stromal cells, for the transduction of viral vectors carrying regulatory
genes into the stromal cells, for the transfection of plasmid vectors carrying regulatory
genes into the stromal cells, for the tracking and detection of functional proteins encoded
by these genes, and for developing biomechanical carriers for the re-introduction of these
cells into a living organism.</p><p num="0017">This invention further provides methods for the introduction of these
chondrocytes into cartilage defect areas for repair.</p><p num="0018">The methods and composition have use in drug discovery for compounds and
proteins with relevance to the differentiated cell-related disease states and traumatic
injuries including but not limited to: anterior crucia ligament tears, full-thickness articular
cartilage defects, partial-thickness articular cartilage defects. </p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0019">Figure 1 shows the immunodetection of collagen type II in human adipose stromal
cells from monolayer cultures. Phase contrast microscopy is used in the upper panel;
Immunofluorescence is used in the lower panel.</p><p num="0020">Figure 2 shows immunodetection of collagen type II in human adipose stromal
cells from pellet cultures. Phase contrast microscopy is used in the upper panel; Immunofluorescence
is used in the lower panel.</p><p num="0021">Figure 3 shows immunodetection of collagen type IT in human adipose stromal
cells from alginate cultures. Phase contrast microscopy is used in the upper panel;
Immunofluorescence is used in the lower panel.</p><p num="0022">Figure 4 shows Collagen type VI expression when cells were cultured in an
alginate matrix at 2 weeks without TGF-beta (control) and with TGF-beta.</p><p num="0023">Figure 5 shows a Western blot of results when cells were grown as monolayers
or in an alginate suspension for the expression of different proteins including: collagen
type VI, link, aggrecan, collagen type I, and actin.</p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF INVENTION</heading><p num="0024">The present invention provides methods and a composition for the differentiation
and culture of adipose tissue-derived stromal cells into chondrocytes. The cells produced
by the methods of invention are useful in providing a source of fully differentiated and
functional cells for research, transplantation, and development of tissue engineering
products for the treatment of human disease and traumatic injury repair. Thus, in one 
aspect, the invention provides a method for differentiating adipose tissue-derived stromal
cells into chondrocytes comprising culturing stromal cells in a composition which
comprises a medium capable of supporting the growth and differentiation of stromal cells
into functional chondrocytes. This invention further provides methods for the
introduction of these chondrocytes into cartilage defect areas for repair.</p><p num="0025">"Adipose stromal cells" refers to stromal cells that originate from adipose tissue.
By "adipose" is meant any fat tissue. The adipose tissue may be brown or white adipose
tissue, derived from subcutaneous, omental/visceral, mammary, gonadal, or other adipose
tissue site. Preferably, the adipose is subcutaneous white adipose tissue. Such cells may
comprise a primary cell culture or an immortalized cell line. The adipose tissue may be
from any organism having fat tissue. Preferably, the adipose tissue is mammalian, most
preferably the adipose tissue is human. A convenient source of adipose tissue is from
liposuction surgery, however, the source of adipose tissue or the method of isolation of
adipose tissue is not critical to the invention. If stromal cells are desired for autologous
transplantation into a subject, the adipose tissue will be isolated from that subject.</p><p num="0026">"Chondrocytes (cartilage cells)" refers to cells that are capable of expressing
characteristic biochemical markers of chondrocytes, including but not limited to collagen
type II, chondroitin sulfate, keratin sulfate and characteristic morphologic markers of
smooth muscle, including but not limited to the rounded morphology observed in culture,
and able to secrete collagen type II, including but not limited to the generation of tissue
or matrices with hemodynamic properties of cartilage <i>in vitro.</i></p><p num="0027">Any medium capable of supporting stromal cells in tissue culture may be used,
Media formulations that will support the growth of fibroblasts include, but are not limited
to, Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium (DMEM), alpha modified Minimal Essential
Medium (αMEM), and Roswell Park Memorial Institute Media 1640 (RPMI Media
1640) and the like. Typically, 0 to 20% Fetal Bovine Serum (FBS) or 1-20% horse serum
will be added to the above media in order to support the growth of stromal cells and/or
chondrocytes. However, a defined medium could be used if the necessary growth factors,
cytokines, and hormones in FBS for stromal cells and chondrocytes are identified and
provided at appropriate concentrations in the growth medium. Media useful in the
methods of the invention may contain one or more compounds of interest, including, but 
not limited to antibiotics mitogenic or differentiative compounds for stromal cells. The
cells will be grown at temperatures between 31°C to 37°C in a humidified incubator. The
carbon dioxide content will be maintained between 2% to 10% and the oxygen content
between 1% and 22%, Cells will remain in this environment for periods of up to 4 weeks.</p><p num="0028">Antibiotics which can supplemented into the medium include, but are not limited
to penicillin and streptomycin. The concentration of penicillin in the chemically defined
culture medium is about 10 to about 200 units per ml. The concentration of streptomycin
in the chemically defined culture medium is about 10 to about 200 ug/ml.</p><p num="0029">Glucocorticoids that can be used in the invention include but are not limited to
hydrocortisone and dexamethasone. The concentration of dexamethasone in the medium
is about 1 to about 100 nM. The concentration of hydrocortisone in the medium is about
1 to about 100 nM.</p><p num="0030">As used herein the terms "chondroinductive agent" or "chondroinductive factor"
refers to any natural or synthetic, organic or inorganic chemical or biochemical
compound or combination or mixture of compounds, or any mechanical or other physical
device, container, influence or force that can be applied to human adipose tissue-derived
stromal cells so as to effect their <i>in vitro</i> chondrogenic induction or the production of
chondrocytes. The chondroinductive agent is preferably selected, individually or in
combination, from the group consisting of (i) a glucocorticoid such as dexamethasone;
(ii) a member of the transforming growth factor-β superfamily such as a bone
morphogenic protein (preferably BMP-2 or BMP-4), TGF- β1, TGF-β2, TGF-β3,
insulin-like growth factor (IGF), platelet derived growth factor (PDGF), epidermal
growth factor (EGF), acidic fibroblast growth factor (aFBF), basic fibroblast growth
factor (bFBF), hepatocytic growth factor (HGF), keratocyte growth factor (KGF),
osteogenic proteins (OP-1, OP-2, and OP-3), inhibin A or chondrogenic stimulating
activity factor (CSA); (iii) a component of the collagenous extracellular matrix such as
collagen I (particularly in the fonn of a gel); and (iv) a vitamin A analogue such as
retinoic acid and; (v) ascorbate or other related vitamin C analogue.</p><p num="0031">The concentration of transforming growth factor-beta is about 1 to about 100
ng/ml. The concentration of retinoic acid is about 0.1 to about 1 µg/ml. </p><p num="0032">Examples of compounds that are stromal cell mitogens include but are not limited
to transforming growth factor β; fibroblast growth factor, bone morphogenetic protein
and stromal cell differentiating factors include but are not limited to dexamethasone,
hydrocortisone, transforming growth factor β, fibroblast growth factor, and bone
morphogenetic protein and the like.</p><p num="0033">Preferably, the adipose tissue derived stromal cells are isolated from the adipose
tissue of the subject into which the final differentiated cells are to be introduced.
However, the stromal cells may also be isolated from any organism of the same or
different species as the subject. Any organism with adipose tissue can be a potential
candidate. Preferably, the organism is mammalian, most preferably the organism is
human.</p><p num="0034">The present invention also provides a method for differentiating adipose derived
slromal cells into chondrocytic cells by suspending the cells in a calcium alginate or
another biocompatible lattice or matrix capable of supporting chondrogenesis in a three
dimensional configuration. Examples of lattice materials include (1) calcium alginate, a
polysaccharide of cross linked L-glucuronic and D-mannuronic acid, at concentrations of
between 1% to 4%; (2) fibrin; (3) collagen type II; or (4) agarose gel. The lattices or
matrixes containing the cells are transferred to culture dishes containing: (1) a
chondroinductive agent that can activate any cellular transduction pathway leading to the
mature chondrocyte phenotype; (2) an antibiotic; (3) a nutrient supplement such as fetal
bovine serum or horse serum; (4) ascorbate or related vitamin C analogue; and (5) a
glucocorticoid or another chemical agent capable of activating the cellular glucocorticoid
receptor.</p><p num="0035">The adipose tissue derived stromal cells may be stably or transiently transfected
or transduced with a nucleic acid of interest using a plasmid, viral or alternative vector
strategy. Nucleic acids of interest include, but are not limited to, those encoding gene
products which enhance the production of extracellular matrix components found in
cartilage; examples include transforming growth factor β, bone morphogentic protein,
activin and insulin-like growth factor.</p><p num="0036">The transduction of viral vectors carrying regulatory genes into the stromal cells
can be performed with viral vectors (adenovinis, retrovirus, adeno-associated virus, or 
other vector) purified by cesium chloride banding or other method at a multiplicity of
infection (viral units:cell) of between 10:1 to 2000:1. Cells will be exposed to the virus
in serum free or serum-containing medium in the absence or presence of a cationic
detergent such as polyethyleneimine or Lipofectamine™ for a period of 1 hour to 24
hours (Byk T. <i>et al.</i> (1998) <i>Human Gene Therapy 9</i>:2493-2502; Sommer B. <i>et al.</i> (1999)
<i>Calcif</i>. <i>Tissue Int. 64</i>:45-49).</p><p num="0037">The transfection of plasmid vectors carrying regulatory genes into the stromal
cells can be introduced into the cells in monolayer cultures by use of calcium phosphate
DNA precipitation or cationic detergent methods (Lipofectamine™, DOTAP) or in three
dimensional cultures by incorporation of the plasmid DNA vectors directly into the
biocompatible polymer (Bonadio J. et al<i>.</i> (1999) <i>Nat. Med</i>. <i>5</i>:753-759).</p><p num="0038">For the tracking and detection of functional proteins encoded by these genes, the
viral or plasmid DNA vectors will contain a readily detectable marker gene, such as the
green fluorescent protein or beta-galactosidase enzyme, both of which can be tracked by
histochemical means.</p><p num="0039">For the development of biomechanical carriers for the re-introduction of the
stromal cells into a living organism, the carriers include but are not limited to calcium
alginate, agarose, types I, II, IV or other collagen isoform, fibrin, poly-lactic/polyglycolic
acid, hyaluronate derivatives or other materials (Perka C. <i>et al.</i> (2000) <i>J. Biomed.
Mater. Res.</i> 49:305-311; Sechriest VF. <i>et al.</i> (2000) <i>J</i>. <i>Biomed. Mater. Res. 49</i>:534-541;
Chu CR <i>et al.</i> (1995) <i>J. Biomed. Mater. Res. 29</i>:1147-1154; Hendrickson DA <i>et al.</i>
(1994) <i>Orthop.Res.12</i>:485-497).</p><p num="0040">Another object of the invention is to provide for the identification and study of
compounds that enhance the differentiation of adipose tissue derived stromal cells into
chondrocytes. Compounds which enhance differentiation may be of value in the
treatment of partial or full cartilage defects, osteoarthritis, traumatized cartilage, cosmetic
surgery of inborn defects including cleft palate or deviated septum. Methods include but
are not limited to the development of three-dimensional <i>in vitro</i> cultures maintaining
adipose tissue-derived stromal cells as chondrocytes that can be subsequently exposed to
novel compounds of interest. </p><p num="0041">Any compound may be tested for its ability to affect the differentiation of adipose
tissue derived stromal cells into chondrocytes. Appropriate vehicles compatible with the
compound to be tested are known to those skilled in the art and may be found in the
current edition of Remington's Pharmaceutical Sciences (1995, Mack Publishing Co.,
Easton, PA) the contents of which are incorporated herein by reference.</p><p num="0042">The features and advantages of the present invention will be more clearly
understood by reference to the following examples, which are not to be construed as
limiting the invention.</p><heading>EXPERIMENTAL</heading><heading>Differentiation of Adipose Tissue-Derived Stromal Cells into Chondrocytes</heading><heading>EXAMPLE 1: <i>In vitro</i> Chondrogenesis using Dexamethasone</heading><p num="0043">Stromal cells are isolated from human subcutaneous adipose tissue according to
methods described in <i>"Methods and Composition of the Differentiation of Human
Preadipocytes into Adipocytes"</i> Serial Number 09/240,029 Filed January 29, 1999.
These cells are plated at a density of 500 to 20,000 cells per cm<sup>2</sup>, The present invention
contemplates that the creation of a precartilage condensation <i>in vitro</i> promotes
chondrogenesis in mesenchymal progenitor cells derived from human adipose tissue.
This is accomplished by methods including, but not limited to:
<sl><li>(1) The pellet culture system, which was developed for use with isolated growth
plate cells (Kato <i>et al.</i> (1988) <i>PNAS 85</i>:9552-9556 ; Ballock &amp; Reddi, <i>J</i>. <i>Cell
Biol.</i> (1994) <i>126(5)</i>:1311-1318) and has been used to maintain expression of
the cartilage phenotype of chondrocytes placed in culture (Solursh (1991) <i>J.
Cell Biochem 45</i>:258-260).</li><li>(2) The alginate suspension method, where cells are maintained in a calcium
alginate suspension to prevent cell-cell contact and maintain a characteristic
rounded morphology promoting the maintenance or acquisition of the
chondrocyte phenotype.</li></sl></p><p num="0044">Human adipose tissue-derived cells are isolated as described above. For pellet
cultures, aliquots of 200,000 cells were centrifuged at 500g for 10 minutes in sterile 15
ml conical polypropylene tubes in DMEM with 10% fetal bovine serum, 50 ng/ml
ascorbate-2-phosphate, 100 nM dexamethasone (DEX) and then incubated at 37° C in a
5% CO<sub>2</sub> incubator for up to 3 weeks. For alginate cultures, cells were suspended at a
density of 1 million cells per ml in 1.2% calcium alginate and maintained in DMEM
with 10% fetal bovine serum, 50 ng/ml ascorbate-2-phosphate, 100 nM dexamethasone
(DEX) and then incubated at 37° C in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> incubator for up to 3 weeks. After 2 or 4
weeks, the cells were isolated, fixed and analyzed for chondrocyte lineage markers by
immunohistochemistry with appropriate antibody reagents or by staining with toluidine
blue to detect the presence of sulfated proteoglycans in the extracellular matrix.</p><p num="0045">Results obtained with an antibody detecting a representative chondrocyte marker
protein, collagen II, are shown in Figures 1-3. The cells maintained in pellet culture
(Figure 2) or calcium alginate (Figure 3) stained positive by immunofluorescence for the
intracellular presence of the collagen II protein, These results are to be contrasted with
identical analysis of adipose tissue-derived cells maintained for 3 weeks in monolayer
culture as shown in Figure 1; here, no staining whatsoever is observed.
Immunohistochemical results with an antibody reagent detecting the chondrocyte marker
protein, collagen VI, are shown in Figure 4. Adipose tissue-derived stromal cells were
maintained in 1.2% calcium alginate and maintained in DMEM with 10% fetal bovine
serum, 50 ng/ml ascorbate-2-phosphate, 100 nM dexamethasone (DEX) in the absence or
presence of transforming growth factor β (10 ng/ml) and then incubated at 37° C in a 5%
CO<sub>2</sub> incubator for up to 2 weeks. Immunohistochemistry revealed a dense deposition of
the collagen VI protein surrounding those cells maintained in the presence, but not the
absence, of transforming growth factor β.</p><p num="0046">Polymerase chain reaction results detecting representative gene markers
associated with chondrogenesis are shown in Figure 5. Adipose tissue-derived stromal
cells were maintained in 1.2% calcium alginate (Alg) or in monolayer (Mono) cultures
and maintained in DMEM with 10% fetal bovine serum, 50 ng/ml ascorbate-2-phosphate,
100 nM. dexamethasone (DEX) in the absence (TGFβ-) or presence (TGFβ 
+) of transforming growth factor β (10 ng/ml) for a period of 4 weeks. Total RNA was
isolated from the individual cultures and used in polymerase chain reactions with primers
specific for collagens types I or VI, the proteoglycan link (Link) protein, aggrecan, or
actin. The collagen markers and actin were detected under all growth conditions.
However, the link mRNAs were most abundant under alginate suspension conditions and
aggrecan was only present under alginate conditions in the presence of TGFβ.</p><p num="0047">These results demonstrate that, through a combination of creating an <i>in vitro</i> cell
condensation and adding the appropriate permissive factors, we are able to produce the
expression of chondrocyte markers consistent with chondrogenesis in cells from
subcutaneous adipose tissue.</p><heading>Example 2: Preparation of Synthetic Cartilage Patch</heading><p num="0048">Following proliferation, the chondrogenic cells still having chondrogenic
potential may be cultured in an anchorage-independent manner, i.e., in a well having a
cell contacting, cell adhesive surface, in order to stimulate the secretion of cartilage-specific
extracellular matrix components.</p><p num="0049">Heretofore, it has been observed that chondrogenic cells proliferatively expanded
in an anchorage-dependent manner usually dedifferentiate and lose their ability to secrete
cartilage-specific type II collagen and sulfated proteoglycan . (Mayne <i>et al,</i> (1984) <i>Exp.
Cell. Res</i>. 151(1): 171-82; Mayne <i>et al.</i> (1976) <i>PNAS 73</i>(5); 1674-8; Okayama <i>et al.</i>
(1976) <i>PNAS 73</i>(9):3224-8; Pacifici <i>et al.</i> (1981) <i>J. Biol Chem.</i> 256(2): 1029-37; Pacifici
<i>et al</i>. (1980) <i>Cancer Res.</i> 40(7); 2461-4; Pacifici <i>et al.</i> (1977) Cell 4: 891-9; von der
Mark <i>et al.</i> (1977) <i>Nature</i> 267(5611):531-2; West <i>et al.</i> (1979) <i>Cell</i> 17(3):491-501;
Oegama <i>et al.</i> (1981) <i>J</i>. <i>Biol. Chem</i>. 256(2):1015-22; Benya <i>et al. (1982) Cell</i> 30(1):215-24).</p><p num="0050">It has been discovered that undifferentiated chondrogenic cells, when seeded
into, and cultured in a well having a cell contacting surface that discourages adhesion of
cells to the cell contacting surface, the cells redifferentiate and start to secrete cartilage-specific 
collagen and sulfated proteoglycans thereby to form a patch of synthetic cartilage
<i>in vitro</i> (US Patent Nos. 5,902,741 and 5,723,331).</p><p num="0051">In addition, it has been found that culturing the cells in a pre-shaped well, enables
one to manufacture synthetic cartilage patches of pre-determined thickness and volume,
It is appreciated, however, that the volume of the resulting patch of cartilage is dependent
not only upon the volume of the well but also upon the number of chondrogenic cells
seeded into the well. Cartilage of optimal pre-determined volume may be prepared by
routine experimentation by altering either, or both of the aforementioned parameters.</p><heading>A. Preparation of Pre-shaped Well.</heading><p num="0052">Several approaches are available for preparing pre-shaped wells with cell
contacting, cell adhesive surfaces.</p><p num="0053">The cell contacting surface of the well may be coated with a molecule that
discourages adhesion of chondrogenic cells to the cell contacting surface. Preferred
coating reagents include silicon based reagents i.e, dichlorodimethylsilane or
polytetrafluoroethylene based reagents, i.e., Teflon.RTM.. Procedures for coating
materials with silicon based reagents, specifically dichlorodimethylsilane, are well known
in the art. See for example, Sambrook et <i>al.</i> (1989) "Molecular Cloning A Laboratory
Manual", Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, the disclosure of which is incorporated
by reference herein. It is appreciated that other biocompatible reagents that prevent the
attachment of cells to the surface of the well may be useful in the practice of the instant
invention.</p><p num="0054">Alternatively, the well may be cast from a pliable or moldable biocompatible
material that does not pennit attachment of cells per se. Preferred materials that prevent
such cell attachment include, but are not limited to, agarose, glass, untreated cell culture
plastic and polytetrafluoroethylene, i.e., Teflon.RTM. Untreated cell culture plastics, i.e.,
plastics that have not been treated with or made from materials that have an electrostatic
charge are commercially available, and may be purchased, for example, from Falcon
Labware, Becton-Dickinson, Lincoln Park, N.J. The aforementioned materials, however,
are not meant to be limiting. It is appreciated that any other pliable or moldable 
biocompatible material that inherently discourages the attachment of chondrogenic cells
may be useful in the practice of the instant invention.</p><p num="0055">The size and shape of the well may be determined by the size and shape of the
articular cartilage defect to be repaired. For example, it is contemplated that the well may
have a cross-sectional surface area of 25 cm.sup.2. This is the average cross-sectional
surface area of an adult, human femoral chondyle. Accordingly, it is anticipated that a
single piece of synthetic cartilage may be prepared in accordance with the invention in
order to resurface the entire femoral chondyle. The depth of the well is preferably greater
than about 0.3 cm and preferably about 0.6 cm in depth. The thickness of natural
articular cartilage in an adult articulating joint is usually about 0.3 cm. Accordingly, the
depth of the well should be large enough to permit a cartilage patch of about 0.3 cm to
form. However, the well should also be deep enough to contain growth medium
overlaying the cartilage patch.</p><p num="0056">It is contemplated also that a large piece of cartilage prepared in accordance with
the invention may be "trimmed" to a pre-selected size and shape by a surgeon performing
surgical repair of the damaged cartilage. Trimming may be performed with the use of a
sharp cutting implement, i.e., a scalpel, a pair of scissors or an arthroscopic device <i>fitted</i>
with a cutting edge, using procedures well known in the art.</p><p num="0057">The pre-shaped well preferably is cast in a block of agarose gel under aseptic
conditions. Agarose is an economical, biocompatible, pliable and moldable material that
can be used to cast pre-shaped wells, quickly and easily. As mentioned above, the
dimensions of the well may dependent upon the size of the resulting cartilage plug that is
desired.</p><p num="0058">A pre-shaped well may be prepared by pouring a hot solution of molten LT
agarose (BioRad, Richmond, CA) into a tissue culture dish containing a cylinder. The
cylinder having dimensions that mirror the shape of the well to be formed. The size and
shape of the well may be chosen by the artisan and may be dependent upon the shape of
the articular cartilage defect to be repaired. Once the agarose has cooled and solidified
around the cylinder, the cylinder is carefully removed with forceps. The surface of the
tissue culture dish that is exposed by the removal of the cylinder is covered with molten
agarose. This seals the bottom of the well and provides a cell adhesive surface at the base 
of the well, When the newly added molten LT agarose cools and solidifies, the resulting
pre-shaped well is suitable for culturing, and stimulating the redifferentiation of
proliferated chondrogenic cells. It is appreciated, however, that alternative methods may
be used to prepare a pre-shaped well useful in the practice of the invention.</p><heading>B. Growth of Cartilage Patch.</heading><p num="0059">Proliferated chondrogenic cells in suspension may be seeded into and cultured in
the pre-shaped well. The cells may be diluted by the addition of cell culture medium to a
cell density of about 1 x 10<sup>5</sup> to 1 x 10<sup>9</sup> chondrogenic cells per ml. A preferred cell culture
medium comprises DMEM supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum.</p><p num="0060">Within about four hours of seeding the chondrogenic cells into the well, the cells
may coalesce to form a cohesive plug of cells, After about 4-10 days, the cells will start
to secrete cartilage-specific sulfated proteoglycans and type II collagen. After prolonged
periods of time in culture the collagen expressed by the chondrogenic cells in the well
will be predominantly type II collagen. It is contemplated however, that the cohesive
plug of cells formed within four hours may be removed from the well and surgically
implanted into the cartilage defect. It is anticipated that the undifferentiated
chondrogenic cells subsequently may redifferentiate in situ thereby to form synthetic
cartilage within the joint.</p><p num="0061">It is contemplated that chondrocytic differentiation or stimulatory factors may be
added to the chondrogenic cells in the pre-shaped well to enhance or stimulate the
production of articular cartilage specific proteoglycans and/or collagen (Luyten &amp; Reddi
(1992) in "Biological Regulation of the Chondrocytes", CRC Press, Boca Raton, Ann
Arbor, London, and Tokyo, p.p. 227-236). Preferred growth factors include, but are not
limited to transforming growth factor-β (TGF-β), insulin-like growth factor (IGF),
platelet derived growth factor (PDGF), epidermal growth factor (EGF), acidic fibroblast
growth factor (aFBF), basic fibroblast growth factor (bFBF), hepatocytic growth factor,
(HGF) keratinocyte growth factor (KGF), the bone morphogenic factors (BMPs) i.e.,
BMP-1, BMP-2, BMP-3, BMP-4, BMP-5 and BMP-6 and the osteogenic proteins (OPs),
i.e. OP-1, OP-2 and OP-3. Preferred concentrations of TGF-β, IGF, PDGF, EGF, aFBF, 
bFBF, HGF, and KGF, range from about 1 to 100 ng/ml. Preferred concentrations of the
BMP's and OP's range from about 1 to about 500 ng/ml.</p><p num="0062">However, these particular growth factors are not limiting. Any polypeptide
growth factor capable of stimulating or inducing the production of cartilage specific
proteoglycans and collagen may be useful in the practice of the instant invention.</p><p num="0063">Tn addition, it is contemplated that ascorbate may be added to the chondrogenic
cells in the pre-shaped well to enhance or stimulate the production of cartilage specific
proteoglycans and collagen. Preferred concentrations of ascorbate range from about 1 to
about 1000 µg/ml.</p><heading>Example 3: Surgical Repair of Articular cartilage Defect</heading><p num="0064">Cartilage defects in mammals are readily identifiable visually during arthroscopic
examination or during open surgery of the joint. Cartilage defects may also be identified
inferentially by using computer aided tomography (CAT scanning), X-ray examination,
magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), analysis of synovial fluid or serum markers or by
any other procedures known in the art. Treatment of the defects can be effected during
an arthroscopic or open surgical procedure using the methods and compositions disclosed
herein.</p><p num="0065">Accordingly, once the defect has been identified, the defect may be treated by the
following steps of (1) surgically implanting at the pre-determined site, a piece of
synthetic articular cartilage prepared by the methodologies described herein, and (2)
permitting the synthetic articular cartilage to integrate into pre-determined site.</p><p num="0066">The synthetic cartilage patch optimally has a size and shape such that when the
patch is implanted into the defect, the edges of the implanted tissue contact directly the
edges of the defect In addition, the synthetic cartilage patch may be fixed in placed
during the surgical procedure. This can be effected by surgically fixing the patch into the
defect with biodegradable sutures, i.e,, (Ethicon, Johnson &amp; Johnson) and/or by applying
a bioadhesive to the region interfacing the patch and the defect. Preferred bioadhesives
include, but are not limited to: fibrin-thrombin glues similar to those disclosed in Fr. Pat.
No. 2 448 900; Fr. Pat. No. 2 448 901 and EP.S.N. 88401961.3 and synthetic 
bioadhesives similar to those disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 5,197,973. It is contemplated,
however, that alternative types of sutures and biocompatible glues may be useful in the
practice of the invention</p><p num="0067">In some instances, damaged articular cartilage may be surgically excised prior the
to implantation of the patch of synthetic cartilage. Additionally, the adhesion of the
synthetic cartilage patch to the articular cartilage defect may be enhanced by treating the
defect with transglutaminase (Ichinose <i>et al.</i> (1990) <i>J. Biol. Chem.</i> 265(3):13411-13414;
Najjar <i>et al.</i> (1984) in "Transglutaminases", Boston, Martinuse-Nijhoff). Initially, the
cartilage defect is dried, for example by using cottonoid, and filled with a solution of
transglutaminase. The solution is subsequently removed, for example, by aspiration,
leaving a film containing transglutaminase upon the cartilage. The synthetic cartilage
patch is implanted subsequently into the defect by the methods described above.</p><p num="0068">In addition the synthetic cartilage may be useful in the repair of human articular
cartilage defects. Accordingly, chondrogenic cells may be differentiated from human
adipose tissue-derived stromal cells, i.e, human subcutaneous adipose tissue.</p><p num="0069">Surgical procedures for effecting the repair of articular cartilage defects are well
known in the art. See for example: Luyten &amp; Reddi (1992) in "Biological Regulation of
the Chondrocytes", CRC Press, Boca Raton, Ann Arbor, London, &amp; Tokyo, p.p. 227-236,
the disclosure of which is incorporated by reference herein.</p><p num="0070">The above demonstrates a culture system in which human adipose tissue-derived
stromal cells differentiate into hypertrophic chondrocytes. Since all components are
defined, the system can be used for studies of the effects of growth factors <i>etc.</i> on the
progression of chondrogenesis. <i>In vitro</i> systems have been used by us and others to show
that these cell populations have osteogenic and adipocytic potential. We demonstrate
here that this population has chondrogenic potential. This has clinical applicability for
cartilage repair.</p><p num="0071">The invention also provides a process for inducing chondrogenesis in human
adipose tissue-derived stromal cells by contacting such cells with a chondroinductive
agent <i>in vitro</i> where the stromal cells arc associated in a three dimensional format. </p><p num="0072">The invention also provides a process for using <i>in vitro</i> differentiated
chondrocytes from adipose-derived stromal cells in the repair of cartilage tissue in
mammals, including humans.</p><p num="0073">In the above methods, the stromal cells are preferably isolated, culture expanded
human adipose tissue-derived stromal cells in a chemically defined environment and are
condensed into close proximity, such as in the form of a three dimensional cell mass, e.g.
packed cells or a centrifugal cell pellet. Further, the contacting preferably comprises
culturing a pellet of human adipose tissue-derived stromal cells in a chemically defined
medium which comprises DMEM with 10% serum, 50 ng/ml ascorbabe-2-phosphate, 10<sup>-7</sup>
M dexamethasone. The differentiated cells are then introduced into the surgery site to
repair cartilage. Since all components of the system are defined, the system can be used
as a product for cartilage repair in mammals, including man and horses.</p></description><claims load-source="ep"  status="new"  lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A medium for differentiating adipose tissue derived stromal cells into
chondrocyte cells, comprising: a chemically defined culture medium having or
supplemented with (i) a chondroinductive agent capable of activating any cellular
transduction pathway leading to the mature chondrocyte phenotype (ii) an antibiotic (iii)
a nutrient supplement such as 1-20% fetal bovine serum or 1-20% horse serum or any
other biological or synthetic equivalent combination of proteins (iv) ascorbate or related
vitamin C analogue and (v) a glucocorticoid or other chemical agent capable of activating
the cellular glucocorticoid receptor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The medium of claim 1, wherein the chondroinductive agent or stromal
cell mitogen is selected individually or in combination from the group consisting of: a
glucocorticoid; a member of the transforming growth factor-beta superfamily; a
collagenous extracellular matrix molecule; and a vitamin A analog.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The medium of claim 1, wherein said antibiotic is penicillin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The medium of claim 1, wherein said antibiotic is streptomycin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The medium of claim 3, wherein the concentration of penicillin is about
10 to about 200 units per ml.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The medium of claim 4, wherein the concentration of streptomycin is
about 10 to about 200µg per ml.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The medium of claim 2, wherein the glucocoritcoid is hydrocortisone.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The medium of claim 2, wherein said glucocorticoid is dexamethasone.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The medium of claim 8, wherein the concentration of dexamethasone is
about 1 to about 100 nM.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The medium of claim 7, wherein the concentration of hydrocortisone is
about 1 to about 100 nM.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The medium of claim 2, wherein said transforming growth factor-beta is
selected from the group consisting of: bone morphogenic protein-2, bone morphogenic
protein-4, TGF-β1, TGF-β2, TGF-β3, IGF, PDGF, EGF, aFBF, bFBF, HGF, KGF,
inhibin A, and chondrogenic stimulating factor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The medium of claim 11, wherein the concentration of transforming
growth factor-beta is about 1 to about 100 ng per ml.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The method according to claim 11, further comprising TGFβ-1 at
concentrations from about 1 ng/ml to about 10 ng/ml.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The medium of claim 2, wherein the collagenous extracellular matrix
molecule is collagen I.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The medium of claim 2, wherein the vitamin A analog is retinoic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The medium of claim 15, wherein the concentration of retinoic acid is
about 0.1ng per ml to about 1µg per ml.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A method for differentiating adipose tissue derived stromal cells into
chondrocytic cells, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) pelleting said stromal cells by centrifuging between 50,000 to 5
million cells at 500 X g for 2 to 20 minutes in sterile tubes containing a medium such as
Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium (DMEM) or alpha modified Minimal Essential
Medium (αMEM) or Roswell Park Memorial Institute media 1640 (RPMI Media 1640;</claim-text><claim-text>b) plating isolated stromal cells at a density of 500 to 20,000
cells/cm2 in a differentiating medium;</claim-text><claim-text>c) supplementing said medium with:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) a chondroinductive agent capable of activating any cellular
signal transduction pathway leading to the mature chondrocyte phenotype</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) an antibiotic</claim-text><claim-text>(iii) a nutrient supplemented with 1 to 20% fetal bovine serum
or 1 to 20% horse serum or any other biological or synthetic equivalent combination of
proteins</claim-text><claim-text>(iv) ascorbate or related vitamin C analog</claim-text><claim-text>(v) a glucocorticoid or other chemical agent capable of
activating the cellular glucocorticoid receptor; and</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>d) incubating said cells at about 31°C to 37° C for about 3-4 weeks in
with 5% CO2 and between 1% and 20% oxygen.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A method for differentiating adipose tissue derived stromal cells into
chondrocytic cells, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) suspending stromal cells at a concentration of 0.5 to 10 million
cells per ml in calcium alginate or any other biocompatible lattice or matrix of supporting
chondrogenesis in a three-dimensional configuration;</claim-text><claim-text>b) transferring cells to 35 mm culture dishes and plating cells at a
density of 500 to 20,000 cells/cm2 in a differentiating medium comprising a chemically
defined culture medium having or supplemented with:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) a chondroinductive agent capable of activating any cellular
transduction pathway leading to the mature chondrocyte phenotype;</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) an antibiotic;</claim-text><claim-text>(iii) a nutrient supplemented with 1 to 20% fetal bovine serum
or 1 to 20% horse serum or any other biological or synthetic equivalent combination of
proteins;</claim-text><claim-text>(iv) ascorbate or related vitamin C analog;</claim-text><claim-text>(v) a glucocorticoid or other chemical agent capable of
activating the cellular glucocorticoid receptor; and</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>c) incubating said cells at about 31 to 37°C for about 3-4 weeks in an
incubator with 5% CO2 and between 1% and 20% oxygen.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure num="1"><img id="img-00250001"  orientation="unknown" wi="174" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00250001.tif" inline="no" he="180"/></figure><figure num="2"><img id="img-00260001" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00260001.tif" inline="no" he="168"/></figure><figure num="3"><img id="img-00270001" orientation="unknown" wi="172" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00270001.tif" inline="no" he="166"/></figure><figure num="4"><img id="img-00280001" orientation="unknown" wi="184" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00280001.tif" inline="no" he="140"/></figure><figure num="5"><img id="img-00290001" orientation="unknown" wi="92" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00290001.tif" inline="no" he="142"/></figure></drawings><search-report-data status="new"><doc-page id="img--90000001" orientation="portrait" wi="177" status="new" file="90000001.tif" he="268" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90010001" orientation="portrait" wi="179" status="new" file="90010001.tif" he="268" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90020001" orientation="portrait" wi="174" status="new" file="90020001.tif" he="264" type="tif"/><doc-page id="img--90030001" orientation="portrait" wi="177" status="new" file="90030001.tif" he="266" type="tif"/></search-report-data><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>