<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2005000922-A1" country="WO" doc-number="2005000922" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="33518089" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20050106"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2005000922-A1" status="new" fvid="78934052"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2005000922</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050106</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-2004020099-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>2004020099</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20040623</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-60240503-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>60240503</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030623</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>C08F 220/04</main-classification><further-classification>C08F 216/12</further-classification><further-classification>C08F 216/08</further-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  24/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  24/16        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  24/26        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  24/16P2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  24/26K10</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">CEMENT DISPERSANT AND METHODS OF MAKING AND USING THE SAME</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">DISPERSANT DE CIMENT ET PROCEDES DE FABRICATION ET D'UTILISATION DE CE DISPERSANT</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-20030052303-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20030052303</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4652621-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4652621</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4870120-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4870120</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>See also references of EP     1636280A1</text><sources><source name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BAIR KEITH A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEO SPECIALTY CHEMICALS INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SAVOLY ARPAD</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VEAL BENNIE</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BAIR, KEITH, A.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GEO SPECIALTY CHEMICALS, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SAVOLY, ARPAD</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VEAL, BENNIE</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BAIR KEITH A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook> </inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>SAVOLY ARPAD</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook> </inventor> <inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VEAL BENNIE</name> <address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BAIR, KEITH, A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SAVOLY, ARPAD</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VEAL, BENNIE</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb"  source="national office"  status="new"  lang="EN"><p>The present invention relates to cement dispersant that is a copolymerization product of a first monomer (A) comprising a carboxylic acid, a second monomer (B) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol sulfate, and, optionally, a third monomer (C) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol. The cement dispersant according to the invention provides improved slump life properties and water reduction properties in cement admixtures.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>L'invention concerne un dispersant de ciment qui est un produit de copolymérisation d'un premier monomère (A) comprenant un acide carboxylique, d'un second monomère (B) comprenant un sulfate d'alcool allylique alcoxylé, et éventuellement d'un troisième monomère (C) comprenant un alcool allylique alcoxylé. Ce dispersant pour ciment présente de propriétés améliorées de maintien de l'ouvrabilité et un effet amélioré de réduction de l'eau dans le ciment.</p></abstract><description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="2"/>--><p num="p0001"> CEMENT DISPERSANT AND METHODS OF MAKING AND USING THE SAME</p><p num="p0002">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION [0001] This is a continuation-in-part of Application Serial No. 10/602,405, filed June 23, 2003.</p><p num="p0003">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION [0002] 1. Field of Invention</p><p num="p0004">[0003] The present invention relates to a cement dispersant and methods of making and using the same. [0004] 2. Description of Related Art</p><p num="p0005">[0005] Cement dispersants are often added to cementitious compositions such as Portland cement, concrete other hydraulic cement compositions (hereinafter collectively "cement") to improve the workability or slump properties of the cement, to reduce the amount of water necessary to obtain good workability, which improves the strength of the resulting cured cement. Dispersants, which are also sometimes referred to as fluidity modifiers or slump modifiers, also help control the hardening and curing time of the cement.</p><p num="p0006">[0006] Cement dispersants have conventionally been based on polymers and copolymers of naphthalene, aminosulfonic acids and polycarboxylic acids. Although cement dispersants of this type do improve the workability of cement when used properly, slump loss still remains a persistent problem in the field. Unexpected delays in delivering cement to construction sites and/or changes in ambient temperatures can negatively impact the quality of the cement and decrease the slump. There exists a need for a cement dispersant that provides improves slump life properties and water reduction properties.</p><p num="p0007">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION [0007] The present invention provides a dispersant for use in cementitious compositions that provides improved slump life properties and water reduction 
<!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>-->
properties. The dispersant according to the invention comprises a copolymerization product of a first monomer (A) comprising a carboxylic acid such as, for example, acrylic acid, a second monomer (B) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol sulfate such as, for example, an allyloxypolyethyleneglycol ammonium sulfate, and, optionally, a third monomer (C) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol. [0008] The present invention also provides: (1) a method of improving the slump properties of cement comprising dispersing into an admixture comprising cement and water a dispersant comprising a copolymerization product of a first monomer (A) comprising a carboxylic acid, a second monomer (B) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol sulfate, and, optionally, a third monomer (C) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol; (2) a method of forming a cement dispersant comprising copolymerizing a first monomer (A) comprising a carboxylic acid, a second monomer (B) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol sulfate, and, optionally, a third monomer (C) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol to form a copolymerization product; and (3) a cement admixture comprising water, cement and a copolymerization product of a first monomer (A) comprising a carboxylic acid, a second monomer (B) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol sulfate, and, optionally, a third monomer (C) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol. [0009] The foregoing and other features of the invention are hereinafter more fully described and particularly pointed out in the claims, the following description setting forth in detail certain illustrative embodiments of the invention, these being indicative, however, of but a few of the various ways in which the principles of the present invention may be employed.</p><p num="p0008">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION [0010] The cement dispersant according to the present invention comprises a copolymerization product of a first monomer (A) comprising a carboxylic acid, a second monomer (B) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol sulfate, and, optionally, a third monomer (C) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol. The polymerization of the monomers into a copolymerization product is 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
preferably accomplished using conventional solution, precipitation or emulsion polymerization techniques. Conventional polymerization initiators such as azo compounds, persulfates, peroxides, UV light, and the like may be used. Chain transfer agents such as alcohols (preferably isopropanol), amines, hypophosphites or mercapto compounds may be used to regulate or control the molecular weight of the copolymerization product. The backbone of the copolymerization product preferably comprises a random combination of the repeat unit remaining after polymerization of the monomers. The resulting copolymerization product may be isolated by common isolation techniques including precipitation isolation and the like. If polymerization is carried out in water, the copolymerization product may simply be used in its aqueous solution.</p><p num="p0009">[0011] The first monomer (A) used to form the copolymerization product according to the invention preferably comprises a carboxylic acid, amido carboxylic acid, C1-C6 alkyl ester of carboxylic acid, C1-C6 alkyl ester of amido carboxylic acid, hydroxylated C1-C6 alkyl ester of carboxylic acid, or a hydroxylated C1-C6 alkyl ester of amido carboxylic acid. Particularly preferred carboxylic acids for use as first monomer (A) include acrylic acid, methacrylic acid, acrylamide, maleic acid, maleic anhydride, fumaric acid, itaconic acid, 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropanesulfonic acid, and water-soluble salts thereof.</p><p num="p0010">[0012] The second monomer (B) used to form the copolymerization product according to the invention preferably comprises an alkoxylated allyl alcohol sulfate according to Formula (I) below: -[-(CHz-CH)-]- I CH<sub>2</sub> O</p><p num="p0011">R1 I so<sub>3</sub>M Formula (I) 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
[0013] Where "R1" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-O)n, (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)-O)n, or a mixture of both and "n" is an integer from about 1 to about 100; and "M" is sodium, potassium, calcium, ammonium or an organic amine such as triethylamine, morpholine, and the like. As noted in Formula (I) above, the second monomer (B) has a terminal sulfate group covalently bonded through an oxygen atom [- C-O-S-O<sub>3</sub>-], and thus is not a sulfonate, which has a terminal sulfate group covalently bonded directly to a carbon atom [-C-S-O<sub>3</sub>-]. Monomer (B) can be prepared by ethoxylation, propoxylation or a combination of the ethoxylation and propoxylation of an allyl alcohol followed by an addition of sulfamic acid, which produces the monomer unit having a covalently bonded sulfate terminated end group bonded through an oxygen atom. [0014] The optional third monomer (C) used to form the copolymerization product according to the invention preferably comprises an alkoxylated allyl alcohol according to Formula (II) below: R2 I -[-CH<sub>2</sub>-C-]-</p><p num="p0012">R3 I o R4 I R5 Formula (II)</p><p num="p0013">[0015] Where "R2" is H or a lower (C1 -C4) straight or branched alkyl chain; "R3" is CH<sub>2</sub> or C=O; "R4" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-O)m, (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)-O)m, or a mixture of both and "m" is an integer from about 1 to about 150; and "R5" is H or a C1-C18 straight or branched alkyl chain. Third monomer (C) is referred to as polyethylene gylcol allyl ether (PEGAE) when "R2" and "R5" are H; "R3" is CH<sub>2</sub>; and "R4" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-O). Third monomer (C) is referred to as polypropylene glycol allyl ether (PPGAE) when "R2" and "R5" are H; "R3" is CH<sub>2</sub>; and "R4" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)-O). Third monomer (C) is referred to as polyethyleneglycol/propylene glycol ally ether (PEGPGAE) when "R2" and 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
"R5" are H; "R3" is CH<sub>2</sub>; and "R4" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-0-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)-O). Third monomer (C) is referred to as hydroxyethyleneglycolmethylmethacrylate (HEME) when "R2" is CH<sub>3</sub>; "R3" is C=O; "R4" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-0); and "R5" is H. Third monomer (C) is referred to as methoxyethyleneglycolmethylmethacrylate (MHEM) when "R2" is CH<sub>3</sub>; "R3" is C=O; "R4" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-O); and "R5" is CH<sub>3</sub>. It will be appreciated that "R5" can be sulfonated.</p><p num="p0014">[0016] Preferably, the molar ratio of first monomer (A) to second monomer (B) to third monomer (C) in the copolymerization product is in a range of from about 1 to about 10 for first monomer (A), from about 1 to about 4 for second monomer (B), and from about 0 or 1 to about 10 for third monomer (C). In other words, the molar ratio of first monomer (A) to second monomer (B) to third monomer (C) in the copolymerization product is from about 1-10:1-4:0 or 1-10. More preferably, the molar ratio of first monomer (A) to second monomer (B) to third monomer (C) in the copolymerization product is in a range of from about 2.5 to about 6 for first monomer (A), from about 1 to about 2 for second monomer (B), and from about 0 or 1 to about 3 for third monomer (C) (or about 2.5-6:1-2:0 or 1-3).</p><p num="p0015">[0017] The dispersant according to the invention can be added to freshly mixed cement to disperse and to adjust the rheological properties of the admixture. As noted above, throughout the instant specification and in the appended claims, the term "cement" refers to all cementitious materials including, for example, Portland cement, concrete and other hydraulic cementitious compositions. The addition of the dispersant to freshly mixed cement compositions improves, for example, the slump life of the admixture and also reduces the amount of water needed to obtain desired slump properties. Typically, the dispersant is added into an aqueous cement mixture in an amount in a range of about 0.1 percent by weight to about 1.0 percent by weight, and more preferably in an amount in a range of from about 0.2 percent by weight to about 0.32 percent by weight. [0018] It will be appreciated that although the dispersant according to the invention is primarily intended for use in cement compositions, it can also be 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
used in other compositions where dispersants are used. Examples include powdered inorganic and organic substances, for example clays, porcelain slips, silicate meals, chalk, carbon black, powdered rock, pigments, talc, synthetic material powders and hydraulic binding agents. Also, the dispersant can be used in the oilfield industry for oil well cementing. Additionally, the polymers can be used in the gypsum industry as dispersants or water reducing agents. Further, these polymers can be used to disperse SBR and NBR emulsion rubbers during polymerization and processing of the rubber. The dispersants according to the invention also find utility in other applications such as, for example, in metal pre-treatment and cooling and boiler water treatment applications.</p><p num="p0016">EXAMPLES [0019] The following examples are intended only to illustrate the invention and should not be construed as imposing limitations upon the claims. Unless specified otherwise, all reagents and equipment used in the following examples can be obtained from Sigma Aldrich, Inc. (St. Louis, MO) and/or Fisher Scientific International, Inc. (Hanover Park, IL). The allyloxypolyethyleneglycol ammonium sulfate monomers used in the examples are available from Bimax, Inc. (Cockeysville, MD), and the allyloxypolyethyleneglycol/propylene glycol ammonium sulfate monomers used in the examples are available both from Bimax, Inc. and from Rhodia, Inc., (Cranbury, NJ). The abbreviations shown in Table 1 below are used throughout the Examples: 
<!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>-->
 Table 1</p><p num="p0017"><img id="imgf000008_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="154" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000008_0001.tif" inline="no" he="169"/></p><p num="p0018">[0020] EXAMPLE 1 [0021] Sample 1 [0022] A suitable flask was equipped with a condenser, an addition funnel, a mechanical stirrer, a thermometer and a nitrogen sparger. The flask was charged with 46.3 g (.075 mole @ 95%) of APES-10 and 90 g of deionized water. 16.2 g (0.225 mole @ 99%) of AA was charged to a 20 cc syringe and 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>-->
placed on a syringe pump. 9.12 g of a 16.6% solution of sodium persulfate ("initiator solution") was charged to a separate syringe and placed on a separate syringe pump. The aqueous APES-10 solution was sparged with nitrogen and heated to 85°C. The AA and the initiator solution were pumped into to the aqueous APES-10 solution simultaneously over three hours. The resulting aqueous copolymer solution was heated for one more hour at 85°C then cooled to room temperature. Caustic (50%) was then added to adjust the pH to 6.4. The resulting copolymerization product, acrylic acid/allyloxypolyethylene glycol sulfate ammonium salt ("AA/APES-10"), was in the form of a clear, light yellow solution. After diluting the solution to 25% solids by weight, a Brookfield viscosity of 31.7 cps was recorded. The physical properties for the AA/APES-10 copolymerization product were recorded in Table 2 below. [0023] Samples 2-13</p><p num="p0019">[0024] The same procedure and equipment used to produce Sample 1 was used to prepare the copolymerization products identified as Samples 2-13 in Table 2 below. The molar ratios of the monomers used to form the copolymerization products are also set forth in Table 2 below. [0025] Sample 14</p><p num="p0020">[0026] The same equipment used to produce Sample 1 was used to prepare an acrylic acid/allyloxypolyethyleneglycol sulfate ammonium salt/allyloxypolyethyleneglycol (AA APES-10/PEGAE-10 terpolymer) copolymerization product. Specifically, 21.92 g (0.035 mole @ 95%) of APES-10 and 17.45 g (0.035 mole) of PEGAE-10 and 78.44 g of deionized water were charged to the flask. 15.14 g (0.21 mole) of AA was charged to a 20 cc syringe and placed on a syringe pump. 5.86 g of a 20% solution of sodium persulfate ("initiator solution") was charged to a separate syringe and placed on a separate syringe pump. The aqueous APES-10/PEGAE-10 solution was sparged with nitrogen and heated to 85°C. The AA and the initiator solution were pumped into to the aqueous APES-10/PEGAE-10 solution simultaneously over three hours. The resulting aqueous terpolymer solution was heated for one more hour at 85°C then cooled to room 
<!-- EPO <DP n="10"/>-->
temperature. Caustic (50%) was then added to adjust the pH to 5.3. The resulting copolymerization product, acrylic acid/allyloxypolyethylene glycol sulfate ammonium salt/allyloxypolyethyleneglycol glycol ("AA/APES- 10/PEGAE-10"), was in the form of a clear, light yellow solution. After diluting the solution to 25% solids by weight, a Brookfield viscosity of 31.5 cps was recorded. The physical properties for the AA/APES-10/PEGAE-10 copolymerization product were recorded in Table 2 below. [0027] Samples 15-26</p><p num="p0021">[0028] The same procedure and equipment used to produce Sample 14 was used to prepare the copolymerization products identified as Samples 15- 26 in Table 2 below. The molar ratios of the monomers used to form the copolymerization products are also set forth in Table 2 below. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="11"/>--></p><p num="p0022">Table 2</p><p num="p0023"><img id="imgf000011_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000011_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="209"/><!-- EPO <DP n="12"/>-->
[0029] Several of the samples produced in Example 1 were subjected to 13-C NMR testing. The spectra were characterized by a broad polyacrylic acid type backbone. Strong resonances at 61 , 70 and 72 ppm correspond to the polyethylene glycol moiety and a broad carbonyl region (179-184 ppm). A very low level (&lt;3%) of unreacted allylic monomer was detected in some of the samples. [0030] EXAMPLE 2</p><p num="p0024">[0031] Each of the samples of dispersants produced in Example 1 was tested for slump efficacy using the Cement Mini-slump testing procedure known as the "Standard Test Method for Slump of Hydraulic Cement Concrete" ASTM C143 -97, Vol. 04.02, which is hereby incorporated by reference in its entirety. Additional information regarding the Cement Mini- slump test is found in D.L. Kantro's, Influence of Water-Reducing Admixtures on Properties of Cement Paste - A Miniature Slump Test, Cement, Concrete and Aggregates, 2, (1980) pp. 95-102, the entire contents of which is hereby incorporated by reference. Specifically, 100 grams (g) of Type 1 Portland cement was added to a disposable beaker. 35 g water was added to the beaker and the cement and water was mixed for 30 seconds with a metal spatula to produce a slurry. 0.32 weight percent of each of the samples produced in Example 1 was dosed via a disposable syringe into the cement slurry. The slurry was mixed for an additional 30 seconds. The cement slurry was poured into a mini-slump cone, which was sitting on a glass plate. The mini-slump cone was then filled to the top with the cement slurry and then the mini-slump cone was lifted quickly and evenly from the glass plate, allowing the cement slurry to flow onto the glass plate. The diameter of the cement slurry patty thus formed was measured. The measurement was the initial slump diameter. The material was returned to the disposable beaker, then re-mixed and measured every 30 minutes to monitor slump retention. The results of Mini-slump Testing using Samples 1-26 produced in Example 1 is shown in Table 3 below, where the term "Thick" means that the cement slurry thickened to such an extent that no meaningful slump data could be obtained. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="13"/>-->
 Table 3</p><p num="p0025"><img id="imgf000013_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000013_0001.tif" inline="no" he="130"/></p><p num="p0026">[0032] EXAMPLE 3</p><p num="p0027">[0033] Each of the samples of dispersants produced in Example 1 was tested for slump efficacy using the same procedure as in Example 2, except that 0.20 weight percent of each of the samples produced in Example 1 was dosed via a disposable syringe into the cement slurry. The results of Mini- slump Testing using Samples 1-26 produced in Example 1 is shown in Table 4 below. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="14"/>-->
 Table 4</p><p num="p0028"><img id="imgf000014_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000014_0001.tif" inline="no" he="125"/></p><p num="p0029">[0034] COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE 4</p><p num="p0030">[0035] To illustrate the relative efficacy of the dispersants produced in accordance with the invention with conventional dispersants, the Mini-slump Test was repeated using three different amounts of a conventional calcium naphthalene sulfonate condensate dispersant available from GEO Specialty Chemicals as DILOFLO<sup>®</sup> CA. The results of the comparative Mini-Slump Testing are shown in Table 5 below.</p><p num="p0031">Table 5</p><p num="p0032"><img id="imgf000014_0002" orientation="portrait" wi="136" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000014_0002.tif" inline="no" he="27"/><!-- EPO <DP n="15"/>-->
[0036] Comparative Example 4 demonstrates that nearly two times as much of a conventional cement dispersant must be used in order to achieve the same slump properties as can be obtained with cement dispersants according to the present invention.</p><p num="p0033">[0037] Additional advantages and modifications will readily occur to those skilled in the art. Therefore, the invention in its broader aspects is not limited to the specific details and illustrative examples shown and described herein. Accordingly, various modifications may be made without departing from the spirit or scope of the general inventive concept as defined by the appended claims and their equivalents. 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="16"/>--><claim-text/><claim-text>What is claimed is:</claim-text><claim-text>1. A composition for use as a cement dispersant comprising a copolymerization product of: a first monomer (A) comprising a carboxylic acid; a second monomer (B) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol sulfate according to Formula (I): -[-(CH<sub>2</sub>-CH)-]- I CH<sub>2</sub> I o R1</claim-text><claim-text>SO<sub>3</sub>M Formula (I) where "R1" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-O)n or (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)-0)n or a mixture of both and "n" is an integer greater than 1 ; and "M" is sodium, potassium, calcium, ammonium or an organic amine; and a third monomer (C) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol according to Formula (II): R2 I -[-CHs-C-]- I R3 O R4 I R5 Formula (II) where "R2" is H or a C1-C4 straight or branched alkyl chain; "R3" is CH<sub>2</sub> or C=O; "R4" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-O)m or (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)- 
<!-- EPO <DP n="17"/>-->
 O)m or a mixture of both and "m" is an integer greater than 1 ; and "R5" is H or a C1-C18 straight or branched alkyl chain.</claim-text><claim-text>2. The composition according to claim 1 wherein the first monomer (A) is one or more selected from the group consisting of amido carboxylic acids, C1-C6 alkyl esters of carboxylic acids, C1-C6 alkyl ester of amido carboxylic acids, hydroxylated C1-C6 alkyl esters of carboxylic acids, and hydroxylated C1-C6 alkyl esters of amido carboxylic acids.</claim-text><claim-text>3. The composition according to claim 1 wherein the first monomer (A) is one or more selected from the group consisting of acrylic acid, methacrylic acid, acrylamide, maleic acid, maleic anhydride, fumaric acid, itaconic acid, 2-acrylamido-2-methylpropanesulfonic acid, and water-soluble salts thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>4. The composition according to claim 1 wherein the second monomer (B) comprises an allyl alcohol that has been ethoxylated, propoxylated, or both, followed by the addition of sulfamic acid to form an end terminal sulfate group that is covalently bonded through an oxygen atom.</claim-text><claim-text>5. The composition according to claim 1 wherein the second monomer (B) is an ammonium allylpolyethoxy sulphate alkoxylated with an average of about 100 moles or more of ethylene oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>6. The composition according to claim 1 wherein the second monomer (B) is an ammonium allylpolyethoxy sulphate alkoxylated with an average of up to about 50 moles of ethylene oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>7. The composition according to claim 1 wherein the third monomer (C) is one or more selected from the group consisting of polyethylene glycol allyl ether (PEGAE), polypropylene glycol allyl ether (PPGAE), polyethylene glycol/polypropylene glycol allyl ether (PEGPGAE), 
<!-- EPO <DP n="18"/>-->
hydroxyethyene glycol methylmethacrylate (HEME), and methoxyethyene glycol methylmethacrylate (MEME).</claim-text><claim-text>8. The composition according to claim 1 wherein the molar ratio of first monomer (A) to second monomer (B) to third monomer (C) in the copolymerization product is in a range of from about 1 to about 10 for first monomer (A), from about 1 to about 4 for second monomer (B), and from about 1 to about 10 for third monomer (C).</claim-text><claim-text>9. The composition according to claim 1 wherein the molar ratio of first monomer (A) to second monomer (B) to third monomer (C) in the copolymerization product is in a range of from about 2.5 to about 6 for first monomer (A), from about 1 to about 2 for second monomer (B), and from about 1 to about 3 for third monomer (C).</claim-text><claim-text>10. A method of improving the slump properties of a cement admixture, the method comprising adding a dispersant composition to an admixture comprising cement and water, wherein the dispersant composition comprises a copolymerization product of: a first monomer (A) comprising a carboxylic acid; a second monomer (B) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol sulfate according to Formula (I): -[-(CH<sub>2</sub>-CH)-]-</claim-text><claim-text>CH<sub>2</sub> I o I R1</claim-text><claim-text>S0<sub>3</sub>M Formula (I) where "R1" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-O)n or (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)-0)n or a mixture of both and "n" is an integer greater than 1 ; and "M" is sodium, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="19"/>-->
 potassium, calcium, ammonium or an organic amine; and, optionally, a third monomer (C) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol according to Formula (II): R2</claim-text><claim-text>-[-CHz-C-]- I R3 O I R4</claim-text><claim-text>R5 Formula (II) where "R2" is H or a C1-C4 straight or branched alkyl chain; "R3" is CH<sub>2</sub> or C=O; "R4" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-0)m or (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)- O)m or a mixture of both and "m" is an integer greater than 1 ; and "R5" is H or a C1-C18 straight or branched alkyl chain.</claim-text><claim-text>11. The method according to claim 10 wherein the first monomer (A) is one or more selected from the group consisting of amido carboxylic acids, C1-C6 alkyl esters of carboxylic acids, C1-C6 alkyl ester of amido carboxylic acids, hydroxylated C1-C6 alkyl esters of carboxylic acids, and hydroxylated C1-C6 alkyl esters of amido carboxylic acids.</claim-text><claim-text>12. The method according to claim 10 wherein the first monomer (A) is one or more selected from the group consisting of acrylic acid, methacrylic acid, acrylamide, maleic acid, maleic anhydride, fumaric acid, itaconic acid, 2- acrylamido-2-methylpropanesulfonic acid, and water-soluble salts thereof.</claim-text><claim-text>13. The method according to claim 10 wherein the second monomer (B) comprises an allyl alcohol that has been ethoxylated, propoxylated, or 
<!-- EPO <DP n="20"/>-->
both, followed by the addition of sulfamic acid to form an end terminal sulfate group that is covalently bonded through an oxygen atom.</claim-text><claim-text>14. The method according to claim 10 wherein the second monomer (B) is an ammonium allylpolyethoxy sulphate alkoxylated with an average of about 100 moles or more of ethylene oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>15. The method according to claim 10 wherein the second monomer</claim-text><claim-text>(B) is an ammonium allylpolyethoxy sulphate alkoxylated with an average of up to about 50 moles of ethylene oxide.</claim-text><claim-text>16. The method according to claim 10 wherein the third monomer</claim-text><claim-text>(C) is one or more selected from the group consisting of polyethylene glycol allyl ether (PEGAE), polypropylene glycol allyl ether (PPGAE), polyethylene glycol/polypropylene glycol allyl ether (PEGPGAE), hydroxyethyene glycol methylmethacrylate (HEME), and methoxyethyene glycol methylmethacrylate (MEME).</claim-text><claim-text>17. The method according to claim 10 wherein the molar ratio of first monomer (A) to second monomer (B) to third monomer (C) in the copolymerization product is in a range of from about 1 to about 10 for first monomer (A), from about 1 to about 4 for second monomer (B), and from about 0 to about 10 for third monomer (C).</claim-text><claim-text>18. The method according to claim 10 wherein the molar ratio of first monomer (A) to second monomer (B) to third monomer (C) in the copolymerization product is in a range of from about 2.5 to about 6 for first monomer (A), from about 1 to about 2 for second monomer (B), and from about 0 to about 3 for third monomer (C).</claim-text><claim-text>19. A cement admixture comprising: a cementitious material; 
<!-- EPO <DP n="21"/>-->
water; and a dispersant composition comprising a copolymerization product of: a first monomer (A) comprising a carboxylic acid; a second monomer (B) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol sulfate according to Formula (I): -[-(CH<sub>2</sub>-CH)-]-</claim-text><claim-text>CH<sub>2</sub> I O</claim-text><claim-text>R1 I SO<sub>3</sub>M Formula (I) where "R1" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-0)n or (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)-0)n or a mixture of both and "n" is an integer greater than 1 ; and "M" is sodium, potassium, calcium, ammonium or an organic amine; and, optionally, a third monomer (C) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol according to Formula (II): R2</claim-text><claim-text>-[-CH<sub>2</sub>-C-]-</claim-text><claim-text>R3</claim-text><claim-text>O I R4</claim-text><claim-text>R5 Formula (II) where "R2" is H or a C1-C4 straight or branched alkyl chain; "R3" is CH<sub>2</sub> or C=O; "R4" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-O)m or (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)-O)m or a mixture of both and "m" is an 
<!-- EPO <DP n="22"/>-->
 integer greater than 1 ; and "R5" is H or a C1-C18 straight or branched alkyl chain.</claim-text><claim-text>20. A method of forming a composition according to claim 1 comprising: providing a first monomer (A) comprising a carboxylic acid; providing a second monomer (B) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol sulfate according to Formula (I): -[-(CH<sub>2</sub>-CH)-]-</claim-text><claim-text>CH<sub>2</sub> I o R1</claim-text><claim-text>SO<sub>3</sub>M Formula (I) where "R1" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-O)n or (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)-O)n or a mixture of both and "n" is an integer greater than 1 ; and "M" is sodium, potassium, calcium, ammonium or an organic amine; providing a third monomer (C) comprising an alkoxylated allyl alcohol according to Formula (II): R2</claim-text><claim-text>-[-CH<sub>2</sub>-C-]-</claim-text><claim-text>R3 I O I R4 I R5 Formula (II) where "R2" is H or a C1-C4 straight or branched alkyl chain; "R3" is CH<sub>2</sub> or C=O; "R4" is (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-0)m or (CH<sub>2</sub>-CH(CH<sub>3</sub>)- 
<!-- EPO <DP n="23"/>-->
 0)m or a mixture of both and "m" is an integer greater than 1 ; and "R5" is H or a C1-C18 straight or branched alkyl chain; and copolymerizing the first monomer (A) and the second monomer (B) and the third monomer (C) to form a copolymerization product. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>