<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1574543-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1574543" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34808512" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050914"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1574543-A1" status="new" fvid="24460308"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1574543</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050914</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-05001397-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>05001397</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20050125</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-77169304-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>77169304</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040204</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/20        20060101C I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/22        20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   3/24        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101C N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/14        20060101A N20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  27/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  27/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  27/16        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08J   3/22L27+L27/12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  27/12+B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  27/16+B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08K5:14</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L205:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L27:12</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L27:16</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Peroxide-vernetzte Zusammensetzungen aus Fluoroelastomeren</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Peroxide cured fluorocarbon elastomer compositions</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Compositions d'élastomères fluorocarbonés réticulés par peroxyde.</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0168020-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0168020</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0439734-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0439734</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0543342-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0543342</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0574913-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0574913</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-61057641-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>61057641</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>FREUDENBERG CARL</name><address><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CARL FREUDENBERG</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Carl Freudenberg</last-name><address><street>Höhnerweg 2-4</street><city>69469 Weinheim</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PARK EDWARD HOSUNG</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WALKER FRANCIS JOSEPH</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PARK, EDWARD HOSUNG</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WALKER, FRANCIS JOSEPH</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PARK, EDWARD HOSUNG</last-name><address><street>586 Hobart Court</street><city>Saline, MI 48176</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WALKER, FRANCIS JOSEPH</last-name><address><street>223 Burt Street</street><city>Tecumseh, MI 49286</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IS</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LT</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A process involves adding a peroxide masterbatch to a molten blend of a
fluorocarbon elastomer and a thermoplastic material. The peroxide
masterbatch contains greater than or equal to 5% weight percent organic
peroxide, further contains a fluorocarbon elastomer, and typically also contains
a crosslinker containing at least two sites of olefinic unsaturation. The
fluorocarbon elastomer in the molten blend and in the peroxide masterbatch
may be the same or different. After the peroxide masterbatch is added to the
molten blend, the combination is mixed at a temperature and for a time
sufficient to effect cure of the fluorocarbon elastomers. By using a
masterbatch, a faster and more uniform dispersion of peroxide curative is
possible due to pre-dispersion of peroxide in the elastomer phase, which leads
to shaped articles having improved mechanical properties.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>INTRODUCTION</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to dynamic vulcanization of
fluorocarbon elastomers in thermoplastics. More particularly, it relates to the
use of organic peroxides as curing agents for the elastomers.</p><p num="0002">Cured elastomers or rubbers have a variety of physical
properties useful for applications in molded articles. Among the properties are
a high degree of flexibility, elasticity, and resistance to compression set. As
such they find use in a variety of applications, such as seals and gaskets.
Uncured elastomers or rubbers are in the form of a resin or gum. To obtain a
molded article with suitable elastomeric properties, the uncured resins are
crosslinked or cured with a variety of crosslinking agents.</p><p num="0003">For conventional elastomers, cure is generally carried out
in a mold under conditions of temperature and pressure suitable for forming a
cured or partially cured article. In the interest of increased turnaround time and
to save on manufacturing costs, molded articles are generally released from the
mold before the crosslinking reactions that provide cure have been completed.
Under these situations, the molded article goes through a process of "post
cure", where the elastomeric properties of the molded article develop further.</p><p num="0004">Dynamically vulcanized rubbers are prepared by carrying
out the crosslinking reaction while the elastomer is stirred or mixed together
with a thermoplastic material. The thermoplastic material forms a continuous
phase and the cured rubber particles are dispersed in the thermoplastic as a
discrete phase. The compositions are dynamically vulcanized for a period of
time to allow elastomeric properties to develop. Typically, the cured or partially
cured dynamic vulcanizate is then transferred into a mold to prepare molded
articles for use such as seals and gaskets. Due to the same phenomenon of 
post cure, crosslinking reactions may continue to occur in the mold after the
dynamic vulcanization process.</p><p num="0005">The reactions occurring during the post cure process
generate heat. The heat generated can lead to volatilization of various
components of the composition during the post cure phase. This volatilization
can result, for example, in a porous cured article, or an article having a rough
surface. Physical properties such as tensile strength may be adversely
affected.</p><p num="0006">In one aspect, the problem of post curing can be minimized
by using fast reacting crosslinkers such as organic peroxides, preferably in
combination with organic crosslinking molecules having two or more sites of
olefinic unsaturation. Because the peroxide initiated cure is rapid, the cure
tends to be nearly completed by the time the molding is finished, or in the case
of dynamic vulcanization, by the time the dynamic blending is finished. In this
way, peroxide initiated curing provides faster turnaround time and molded
articles with desirable physical properties.</p><p num="0007">Because it is added to a hot molten mixture of an
elastomer and thermoplastic, the peroxide may splash or bump upon addition.
This can lead to formation of molded parts with pores or a rough surface, much
in the same way that reactions during post cure cause them, as described
above.</p><p num="0008">It would therefore be desirable to provide methods for
curing fluorocarbon elastomers in a dynamic vulcanization process, using fast
curing peroxide initiating curing systems, but avoiding the disadvantages noted
above.</p><heading>SUMMARY</heading><p num="0009">In one embodiment, a high temperature peroxide is added
to a molten blend of fluorocarbon elastomer and thermoplastic material to make
a thermoplastic vulcanizate (TPV) by a process of dynamic vulcanization. The 
peroxide is subject to a lower level of volatilization and degradation due to its
high temperature stability, which leads to improved physical properties of
shaped articles made from the TPV's.</p><p num="0010">In another embodiment, advantages are provided by a
process that involves adding a peroxide masterbatch to a molten blend of a
fluorocarbon elastomer and a thermoplastic material. The molten blend
contains a first portion of a fluorocarbon elastomer, while the peroxide
masterbatch contains a second portion of a fluorocarbon elastomer. The
fluorocarbon elastomer in the molten blend and in the peroxide masterbatch
may be the same or different. After the peroxide masterbatch is added to the
molten blend, the combination is mixed at a temperature and for a time
sufficient to effect cure of the fluorocarbon elastomers. The peroxide
masterbatch contains greater than or equal to 5% weight percent organic
peroxide, further contains a fluorocarbon elastomer, and typically also contains
a crosslinker containing at least two sites of olefinic unsaturation.</p><p num="0011">A method of preparing a moldable polymer composition
thus comprises melt blending a curable fluorocarbon elastomer and a
thermoplastic material, and adding a curing composition comprising the
peroxide masterbatch to the melt blend. Thereafter, the curing composition, the
elastomer, and the thermoplastic material are heated while continuing to mix for
a time and at a temperature sufficient to cure the fluorocarbon elastomer.</p><p num="0012">The method may be used to prepare melt processable
molded articles. The molded articles comprise a peroxide dynamic vulcanizate
of a fluorocarbon elastomer and a thermoplastic material. In some
embodiments, the thermoplastic is a fluorine containing thermoplastic. Molded
articles made by the processes have elastomeric properties suitable for use in
seals and gaskets. The properties are generally more advantageous than the
properties of peroxide cured articles made without the masterbatch method.
For example, the tensile modulus of the molded article is above 10 MPa in 
some embodiments, while in others embodiments, the tensile modulus is above
12 MPa or greater than 15 MPa.</p><heading>DESCRIPTION</heading><p num="0013">The following description of the preferred embodiment(s) is
merely exemplary in nature and is in no way intended to limit the invention, its
application, or uses.</p><p num="0014">The headings (such as "Introduction" and "Summary,")
used herein are intended only for general organization of topics within the
disclosure of the invention, and are not intended to limit the disclosure of the
invention or any aspect thereof. In particular, subject matter disclosed in the
"Introduction" may include aspects of technology within the scope of the
invention, and may not constitute a recitation of prior art. Subject matter
disclosed in the "Summary" is not an exhaustive or complete disclosure of the
entire scope of the invention or any embodiments thereof.</p><p num="0015">The citation of references herein does not constitute an
admission that those references are prior art or have any relevance to the
patentability of the invention disclosed herein. All references cited in the
Description section of this specification are hereby incorporated by reference in
their entirety.</p><p num="0016">The description and specific examples, while indicating
embodiments of the invention, are intended for purposes of illustration only and
are not intended to limit the scope of the invention. Moreover, recitation of
multiple embodiments having stated features is not intended to exclude other
embodiments having additional features, or other embodiments incorporating
different combinations of the stated features. Specific Examples are provided
for illustrative purposes of how to make, use and practice the compositions and
methods of this invention and, unless explicitly stated otherwise, are not
intended to be a representation that given embodiments of this invention have,
or have not, been made or tested. </p><p num="0017">As used herein, the words "preferred" and "preferably" refer
to embodiments of the invention that afford certain benefits, under certain
circumstances. However, other embodiments may also be preferred, under the
same or other circumstances. Furthermore, the recitation of one or more
preferred embodiments does not imply that other embodiments are not useful,
and is not intended to exclude other embodiments from the scope of the
invention.</p><p num="0018">As used herein, the word "include," and its variants, is
intended to be non-limiting, such that recitation of items in a list is not to the
exclusion of other like items that may also be useful in the materials,
compositions, devices, and methods of this invention.</p><p num="0019">The terms "elastomeric material", "elastomer", and the like
refer to chemical compositions that possess, or can be modified (i.e. cured or
crosslinked) to possess elastomeric properties. According to context, the terms
refer to an uncured or partially cured material, in which elastomeric properties
are not fully developed, or to a cured rubber-like material, with fully developed
elastomeric properties. At some points in the specification, the terms are used
with adjectives such as "cured", "partially cured", or "uncured" for clarity.</p><p num="0020">The terms "curing agent", "curative", "curative agent", and
the like are used interchangeably to designate the chemical compound or
composition that reacts with the (uncured) elastomer to form a cured elastomer
and to develop the elastomeric properties of the cured product. According to
context it is used to refer to a formal curing initiator (e.g. a radical initiator such
as a peroxide) as well as a crosslinking agent that may be used in conjunction
with the initiator (e.g. triallylisocyanurate). At some points, the term "curing
system" or the like is used to refer to a combination of initiator and crosslinker
and optional additional components used in the curing. It is to be understood
that often the curing system is provided by an elastomer supplier (and may be
incorporated into the elastomer), and may be used according to the
manufacturer's instructions. </p><p num="0021">In one embodiment, a method of preparing a molded
polymer composition comprises forming a mixture of a curable fluorocarbon
elastomer and a thermoplastic material at a temperature above the melt flow
temperature or melting point of the thermoplastic, adding a curing composition
to the mixture, and heating while continuing to mix the curing composition, the
elastomer, and thermoplastic material. The curing composition contains an
initiator having a half-life of 0.1 hours or more at a temperature of 180°C or
higher, and further contains a crosslinking agent. Preferably, the crosslinker
contains at least two sites of olefinic unsaturation. In various embodiments, the
initiator is an organic peroxide. In a preferred embodiment, the thermoplastic
material comprises a fluorine containing thermoplastic polymer.</p><p num="0022">The fluorocarbon elastomer used in the melt blend with the
thermoplastic material comprises a fluorine-containing polymer that may be
cured upon action of a peroxide initiated crosslinker to provide a cured
fluorocarbon rubber having elastomeric properties. Many different types of
fluorocarbon elastomers are commercially available. In one embodiment, the
fluorocarbon elastomers comprise copolymers of vinylidene fluoride. In another
embodiment, perfluororubbers may be used that are based on polymers and
copolymers of monomers containing no carbon hydrogen bonds. Another class
of fluorocarbon elastomer is given by copolymers of tetrafluoroethylene and
olefins such as propylene. In general, it is preferred that the fluorocarbon also
have small amounts of a cure site monomer, discussed below, to enhance the
curing with the peroxide initiated crosslinker.</p><p num="0023">In another embodiment, the invention provides a process
for making a melt processable fluorocarbon rubber composition comprising
adding a peroxide masterbatch to a molten blend of a first portion of
fluorocarbon elastomer and a thermoplastic material, wherein the masterbatch
comprises greater than or equal to 5% weight percent organic peroxide and
further comprises a second portion of a fluorocarbon elastomer; and mixing the
peroxide masterbatch, the first portion of fluorocarbon elastomer, and the 
thermoplastic material while heating for a time and at a temperature sufficient to
effect cure of the fluorocarbon elastomers. In one embodiment, the process
comprises injecting a composition comprising the first portion of fluorocarbon
elastomer and the thermoplastic material into a twin-screw extruder with a first
feeder; and adding the masterbatch into the extruder with a second feeder
downstream from the first.</p><p num="0024">The process may be carried out by adding a peroxide
masterbatch to a molten blend of a first portion of fluorocarbon elastomer and a
thermoplastic material. The peroxide masterbatch, the first portion of
fluorocarbon elastomer and the thermoplastic material are then heated with
mixing for a time and at a temperature effective to cure the fluorocarbon
elastomer. The process thus involves dynamic vulcanization of a fluorocarbon
elastomer in a thermoplastic material, preferably a fluorine containing
thermoplastic material, with peroxide curing.</p><p num="0025">The first portion of fluorocarbon elastomer and the
thermoplastic material may be added into the barrel of a twin-screw extruder
with a first feeder while the peroxide masterbatch is injected into the extruder
with a second feeder downstream of the first. Continuous or semi-continuous
processes for making the multiple polymer composition may be carried out in
such twin extruders.</p><p num="0026">In one aspect, the addition of peroxide curative in the form
of a masterbatch with an elastomer matrix phase leads to better uniformity and
faster dispersion of peroxide curative in the peroxide curable main elastomer
phase of the TPV. It also provides effective use of curative by minimizing the
volatility of peroxide curative during the dynamic vulcanization compounding
process of the TPV, especially at high temperature.</p><p num="0027">In another embodiment, the invention provides a molded
article comprising a peroxide cured dynamic vulcanizate of a fluorocarbon
elastomer and a fluorine containing thermoplastic, having a tensile modulus
above 10 MPa, preferably above 12 MPa, and more preferably above 15 MPa. 
It is believed the dynamically vulcanized TPV compounding process with a
peroxide curative-containing masterbatch provides better mechanical properties
by achieving more homogeneously cured elastomer phase in the thermoplastic
matrix phase, and by minimizing the volatility of the peroxide curative especially
at high temperature.</p><p num="0028">Various types of fluoroelastomers may be used. One
classification of fluoroelastomers is given in ASTM-D 1418, "Standard practice
for rubber and rubber latices-nomenclature". The designation FKM is given for
fluoro-rubbers that utilize vinylidene fluoride as a co-monomer. Several
varieties of FKM fluoroelastomers are commercially available. A first variety
may be chemically described as a copolymer of hexafluoropropylene and
vinylidene fluoride. These FKM elastomers tend to have an advantageous
combination of overall properties. Some commercial embodiments are
available with about 66% by weight fluorine. Another type of FKM elastomer
may be chemically described as a terpolymer of tetrafluoroethylene,
hexafluoropropylene, and vinylidene fluoride. Such elastomers tend to have
high heat resistance and good resistance to aromatic solvents. They are
commercially available with, for example 68-69.5% by weight fluorine. Another
FKM elastomer is chemically described as a terpolymer of tetrafluoroethylene, a
fluorinated vinyl ether, and vinylidene fluoride. Such elastomers tend to have
improved low temperature performance. In various embodiments, they are
available with 62-68% by weight fluorine. A fourth type of FKM elastomer is
described as a terpolymer of tetrafluoroethylene, propylene, and vinylidene
fluoride. Such FKM elastomers tend to have improved base resistance. Some
commercial embodiments contain about 67% weight fluorine. A fifth type of
FKM elastomer may be described as a pentapolymer of tetrafluoroethylene,
hexafluoropropylene, ethylene, a fluorinated vinyl ether and vinylidene fluoride.
Such elastomers typically have improved base resistance and have improved
low temperature performance. </p><p num="0029">Another category of fluorocarbon elastomers is designated
as FFKM. These elastomers may be designated as perfluoroelastomers
because the polymers are completely fluorinated and contain no carbon
hydrogen bond. As a group, the FFKM fluoroelastomers tend to have superior
fluid resistance. They were originally introduced by DuPont under the Kalrez®
trade name. Additional suppliers include Daikin and Ausimont.</p><p num="0030">A third category of fluorocarbon elastomer is designated as
FTPM. Typical of this category are the copolymers of propylene and
tetrafluoroethylene. The category is characterized by a high resistance to basic
materials such as amines.</p><p num="0031">Fluorocarbon elastomers include commercially available
copolymers of one or more fluorine containing monomers, chiefly vinylidene
fluoride (VDF), hexafluoropropylene (HFP), tetrafluoroethylene (TFE), and
perfluorovinyl ethers (PFVE). Preferred PFVE include those with a C<sub>1-8</sub>
perfluoroalkyl group, preferably perfluoroalkyl groups with 1 to 6 carbons, and
particularly perfluoromethyl vinyl ether and perfluoropropyl vinyl ether. In
addition, the copolymers may also contain repeating units derived from olefins
such as ethylene (Et) and propylene (Pr). The copolymers may also contain
relatively minor amounts of cure site monomers (CSM), discussed further
below. Preferred copolymer fluorocarbon elastomers include VDF/HFP,
VDF/HFP/CSM, VDF/HFP/TFE, VDF/HFP/TFE/CSM, VDF/PFVE/TFE/CSM,
TFE/Pr, TFE/Pr/VDF, TFE/Et/PFVE/VDF/CSM, TFE/Et/PFVE/CSM and
TFE/PFVE/CSM. The elastomer designation gives the monomers from which
the elastomer gums are synthesized. In some embodiments, the elastomer
gums have viscosities that give a Mooney viscosity in the range generally of 15-160
(ML1 + 10, large rotor at 121 °C), which can be selected for a combination
of flow and physical properties. Elastomer suppliers include Dyneon (3M),
Asahi Glass Fluoropolymers, Solvay/Ausimont, Dupont, and Daikin.</p><p num="0032">In various embodiments, the fluoroelastomers of the
composition of the invention also comprise at least one halogenated cure site 
or a reactive double bond resulting from the presence of a copolymerized unit
of a non-conjugated diene. In various embodiments, the fluorocarbon
elastomers contain up to 5 mole % and preferably up to 3 mole % of repeating
units derived from the so-called cure site monomers.</p><p num="0033">The cure site monomers are preferably selected from the
group consisting of brominated, chlorinated, and iodinated olefins; brominated,
chlorinated, and iodinated unsaturated ethers; and non-conjugated dienes.
Halogenated cure sites may be copolymerized cure site monomers or halogen
atoms that are present at terminal positions of the fluoroelastomer polymer
chain. The cure site monomers, reactive double bonds or halogenated end
groups are capable of reacting to form crosslinks.</p><p num="0034">The brominated cure site monomers may contain other
halogens, preferably fluorine. Examples are bromotrifluoroethylene, 4-bromo-3,3,4,4-tetrafluorobutene-1
and others such as

vinyl bromide,

1-bromo-2,2-difluoroethylene, perfluoroallyl bromide,

4-bromo-1,1,2-trifluorobutene, 4-bromo-1,1,3,3,4,4,-hexafluorobutene,

4-bromo-3-chloro-1,1,3,4,4-pentafluorobutene,

6-bromo-5,5,6,6-tetrafluorohexene, 4-bromoperfluorobutene-1 and

3,3-difluoroallyl bromide.

Brominated unsaturated ether cure site monomers useful in the invention
include ethers such as 2-bromo-perfluoroethyl perfluorovinyl ether and
fluorinated compounds of the class CF<sub>2</sub> Br-R<sub>f</sub> --O-CF=CF<sub>2</sub> (R<sub>f</sub> is
perfluoroalkylene), such as CF<sub>2</sub> BrCF<sub>2</sub> O-CF=CF<sub>2</sub>, and fluorovinyl ethers of
the class ROCF=CFBr or ROCBr=CF<sub>2</sub>, where R is a lower alkyl group or
fluoroalkyl group, such as CH<sub>3</sub>OCF=CFBr or CF<sub>3</sub> CH<sub>2</sub> OCF=CFBr.</p><p num="0035">Iodinated olefins may also be used as cure site monomers.
Suitable iodinated monomers include iodinated olefins of the formula:
CHR=CH--Z-CH<sub>2</sub>CHR--I, wherein R is --H or -CH<sub>3</sub> ; Z is a C<sub>1</sub> -C<sub>18</sub>
(per)fluoroalkylene radical, linear or branched, optionally containing one or 
more ether oxygen atoms, or a (per)fluoropolyoxyalkylene radical as disclosed
in U.S. Pat. No. 5,674,959. Other examples of useful iodinated cure site
monomers are unsaturated ethers of the formula: I(CH<sub>2</sub> CF<sub>2</sub> CF<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub>OCF=CF<sub>2</sub>
and ICH<sub>2</sub> CF<sub>2</sub> O[CF(CF<sub>3</sub>)CF<sub>2</sub> O]<sub>n</sub> CF=CF<sub>2</sub>, and the like, wherein n=1-3, such as
disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 5,717,036. In addition, suitable iodinated cure site
monomers including iodoethylene, 4-iodo-3,3,4,4-tetrafluorobutene-1; 3-chloro-4-iodo-3,4,4-trifluorobutene;
2-iodo-1,1,2,2-tetrafluoro-1-(vinyloxy)ethane; 2-iodo-1-(perfluorovinyloxy)-1,1,2,2-tetrafluoroethylene;
1,1,2,3,3 3-hexafluoro-2-iodo-1-(perfluorovinyloxy)propane;
2-iodoethyl vinyl ether; 3,3,4,5,5,5-hexafluoro-4-iodopentene;
and iodotrifluoroethylene are disclosed in U.S. Pat.
No. 4,694,045.</p><p num="0036">Examples of non-conjugated diene cure site monomers
include 1,4-pentadiene, 1,5-hexadiene, 1,7-octadiene and others, such as
those disclosed in Canadian Patent 2,067,891. A suitable triene is 8-methyl-4-ethylidene-1,7-octadiene.</p><p num="0037">Of the cure site monomers listed above, preferred
compounds include 4-bromo-3,3,4,4-tetrafluorobutene-1; 4-iodo-3,3,4,4-tetrafluorobutene-1;
and bromotrifluoroethylene.</p><p num="0038">Additionally, or alternatively, iodine, bromine or mixtures
thereof may be present at the fluoroelastomer chain ends as a result of the use
of chain transfer or molecular weight regulating agents during preparation of the
fluoroelastomers. Such agents include iodine-containing compounds that result
in bound iodine at one or both ends of the polymer molecules. Methylene
iodide; 1,4-diiodoperfluoro-n-butane; and 1,6-diiodo-3,3,4,4,tetrafluorohexane
are representative of such agents. Other iodinated chain transfer agents
include 1,3-diiodoperfluoropropane; 1,4-diiodoperfluorobutane; 1,6-diiodoperfluorohexane;
1,3-diiodo-2-chloroperfluoropropane; 1,2-di(iododifluoromethyl)perfluorocyclobutane;
monoiodoperfluoroethane;
monoiodoperfluorobutane; and 2-iodo-1-hydroperfluoroethane. Particularly
preferred are diiodinated chain transfer agents. Examples of brominated chain 
transfer agents include 1-bromo-2-iodoperfluoroethane; 1-bromo-3-iodoperfluoropropane;
1-iodo-2-bromo-1,1-difluoroethane and others such as
disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 5,151,492.</p><p num="0039">Additionally, or alternatively, iodine, bromine or mixtures
thereof may be present at the fluoroelastomer chain ends as a result of the use
of chain transfer or molecular weight regulating agents during preparation of the
fluoroelastomers. Such agents include iodine-containing compounds that result
in bound iodine at one or both ends of the polymer molecules. Methylene
iodide; 1,4-diiodoperfluoro-n-butane; and 1,6-diiodo-3,3,4,4,tetrafluorohexane
are representative of such agents. Other iodinated chain transfer agents
include 1,3-diiodoperfluoropropane; 1,4-diiodoperfluorobutane; 1,6-diiodoperfluorohexane;
1,3-diiodo-2-chloroperfluoropropane; 1,2-di(iododifluoromethyl)perfluorocyclobutane;
monoiodoperfluoroethane;
monoiodoperfluorobutane; and 2-iodo-1-hydroperfluoroethane. Particularly
preferred are diiodinated chain transfer agents. Examples of brominated chain
transfer agents include 1-bromo-2-iodoperfluoroethane; 1-bromo-3-iodoperfluoropropane;
1-iodo-2-bromo-1,1-difluoroethane and others such as
disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 5,151,492.</p><p num="0040">Other cure monomers may be used that introduce low
levels, preferably less than or equal about 5 mole %, more preferably less than
or equal about 3 mole %, of functional groups such as epoxy, carboxylic acid,
carboxylic acid halide, carboxylic ester, carboxylate salts, sulfonic acid groups,
sulfonic acid alkyl esters, and sulfonic acid salts. such monomers and cure are
described for example in Kamiya et al., U.S. Patent No. 5, 354, 811.</p><p num="0041">Fluorocarbon elastomers based on cure site monomers are
commercially available. Non-limiting examples include Viton GF, GLT-305,
GLT-505, GBL-200, and GBL-900 grades from DuPont. Others include the G-900
and LT series from Daikin, the FX series and the RE series from NOK, and
Tecnoflon P457 and P757 from Solvay. </p><p num="0042">In some embodiments, the thermoplastic material
comprises at least one fluorine containing thermoplastic polymer, or
fluoroplastic. Thermoplastic fluorine-containing polymers may be selected from
a wide range of polymers and commercial products. The polymers are melt
processable - they soften and flow when heated, and can be readily processed
in thermoplastic techniques such as injection molding, extrusion, compression
molding, and blow molding. The materials are readily recyclable by melting and
re-processing.</p><p num="0043">The thermoplastic polymers may be fully fluorinated or
partially fluorinated. Fully fluorinated thermoplastic polymers include
copolymers of tetrafluoroethylene and perfluoroalkyl vinyl ethers. The
perfluoroalkyl group is preferably of 1 to 6 carbon atoms. Examples of
copolymers are PFA (copolymer of TFE and perfluoropropyl vinyl ether) and
MFA (copolymer of TFE and perfluoromethyl vinyl ether). Other examples of
fully fluorinated thermoplastic polymers include copolymers of TFE with
perfluoro olefins of 3 to 8 carbon atoms. Non-limiting examples include FEP
(copolymer of TFE and hexafluoropropylene).</p><p num="0044">Partially fluorinated thermoplastic polymers include E-TFE
(copolymer of ethylene and TFE), E-CTFE (copolymer of ethylene and
chlorotrifluoroethylene), and PVDF (polyvinylidene fluoride). A number of
thermoplastic copolymers of vinylidene fluoride are also suitable thermoplastic
polymers for use in the invention. These include, without limitation, copolymers
with perfluoroolefins such as hexafluoropropylene, and copolymers with
chlorotrifluoroethylene. Thermoplastic terpolymers may also be used. These
include thermoplastic terpolymers of TFE, HFP, and vinylidene fluoride.
Commercial embodiments are available which contain 59 to 76% by weight
fluorine. An example is Dyneon THV, which exhibits a melting point of from
about 120°C to about 200°C, depending on the composition. In one
embodiment, partially fluorinated fluoroplastics are preferred that are
characterized by a melting point of from about 105°C to about 160°C. Use of 
these rather low melting fluoroplastics permits the use of peroxide curing
agents at a low temperature where undesirable volatilization of the peroxides is
minimized.</p><p num="0045">Non-fluorine containing thermoplastic polymers may also
be used. In one aspect, a thermoplastic material is one the melt viscosity of
which can be measured, such as by ASTM D-1238 or D-2116, at a temperature
above its melting point</p><p num="0046">The thermoplastic material of the invention may be
selected to provide enhanced properties of the rubber/thermoplastic
combination at elevated temperatures, preferably above 100°C and more
preferably at about 150°C and higher. Such thermoplastics include those that
maintain physical properties, such as at least one of tensile strength, modulus,
and elongation at break to an acceptable degree at the elevated temperature.
In a preferred embodiment, the thermoplastics possess physical properties at
the elevated temperatures that are superior (i.e. higher tensile strength, higher
modulus, and/or higher elongation at break) to those of the cured fluorocarbon
elastomer (rubber) at a comparable temperature.</p><p num="0047">The thermoplastic polymeric material used in the invention
may be a thermoplastic elastomer. Thermoplastic elastomers have some
physical properties of rubber, such as softness, flexibility and resilience, but
may be processed like thermoplastics. A transition from a melt to a solid
rubber-like composition occurs fairly rapidly upon cooling. This is in contrast to
conventional elastomers, which harden slowly upon heating. Thermoplastic
elastomers may be processed on conventional plastic equipment such as
injection molders and extruders. Scrap may generally be readily recycled.</p><p num="0048">Thermoplastic elastomers have a multi-phase structure,
wherein the phases are generally intimately mixed. In many cases, the phases
are held together by graft or block copolymerization. At least one phase is
made of a material that is hard at room temperature but fluid upon heating.
Another phase is a softer material that is rubber like at room temperature. </p><p num="0049">Some thermoplastic elastomers have an A-B-A block
copolymer structure, where A represents hard segments and B is a soft
segment. Because most polymeric material tend to be incompatible with one
another, the hard and soft segments of thermoplastic elastomers tend to
associate with one another to form hard and soft phases. For example, the
hard segments tend to form spherical regions or domains dispersed in a
continuous elastomer phase. At room temperature, the domains are hard and
act as physical crosslinks tying together elastomeric chains in a 3-D network.
The domains tend to lose strength when the material is heated or dissolved in a
solvent.</p><p num="0050">Other thermoplastic elastomers have a repeating structure
represented by (A-B)<sub>n</sub>, where A represents the hard segments and B the soft
segments as described above.</p><p num="0051">Many thermoplastic elastomers are known. Non-limiting
examples of A-B-A type thermoplastic elastomers include
polystyrene/polysiloxane/polystyrene, polystyrene/polyethylene-co-butylene/polystyrene,
polystyrene/polybutadiene polystyrene, polystyrene/polyisoprene/polystyrene,
poly-α-methyl styrene/polybutadiene/poly-α-methyl
styrene, poly-α-methyl styrene/polyisoprene/poly-α-methyl
styrene, and polyethylene/polyethylene-co-butylene/polyethylene.</p><p num="0052">Non-limiting examples of thermoplastic elastomers having
a (A-B)<sub>n</sub> repeating structure include polyamide/polyether, polysulfone/polydimethylsiloxane,
polyurethane/polyester, polyurethane/polyether,
polyester/polyether, polycarbonate/ polydimethylsiloxane, and
polycarbonate/polyether. Among the most common commercially available
thermoplastic elastomers are those that contain polystyrene as the hard
segment. Triblock elastomers are available with polystyrene as the hard
segment and either polybutadiene, polyisoprene, or polyethylene-co-butylene
as the soft segment. Similarly, styrene butadiene repeating co-polymers are 
commercially available, as well as polystyrene/polyisoprene repeating
polymers.</p><p num="0053">A thermoplastic elastomer may have alternating blocks of
polyamide and polyether. Such materials are commercially available, for
example from Atofina under the Pebax® trade name. The polyamide blocks
may be derived from a copolymer of a diacid component and a diamine
component, or may be prepared by homopolymerization of a cyclic lactam. The
polyether block is generally derived from homo- or copolymers of cyclic ethers
such as ethylene oxide, propylene oxide, and tetrahydrofuran.</p><p num="0054">The thermoplastic polymeric material may also be selected
from among solid, generally high molecular weight, plastic materials. Preferably,
the materials are crystalline or semi-crystalline polymers, and more preferably
have a crystallinity of at least 25 percent as measured by differential scanning
calorimetry. Amorphous polymers with a suitably high glass transition
temperature are also acceptable as the thermoplastic polymeric material. The
thermoplastic also preferably has a melt temperature or glass transition
temperature in the range from about 80°C to about 350°C, but the melt
temperature should generally be lower than the decomposition temperature of
the thermoplastic vulcanizate.</p><p num="0055">Non-limiting examples of thermoplastic polymers include
polyolefins, polyesters, nylons, polycarbonates, styrene-acrylonitrile
copolymers, polyethylene terephthalate, polybutylene terephthalate,
polyamides, polystyrene, polystyrene derivatives, polyphenylene oxide,
polyoxymethylene, and fluorine-containing thermoplastics.</p><p num="0056">Polyolefins are formed by polymerizing α-olefins such as,
but not limited to, ethylene, propylene, 1-butene, 1-hexene, 1-octene, 2-methyl-1-propene,
3-methyl-1-pentene, 4-methyl-1-pentene, 5-methyl-1-hexene, and
mixtures thereof. Copolymers of ethylene and propylene or ethylene or
propylene with another α-olefin such as 1-butene, 1-hexene, 1-octene, 2-methyl-1-propene,
3-methyl-1-pentene, 4-methyl-1-pentene, 5-methyl-1-hexene 
or mixtures thereof are also contemplated. These homopolymers and
copolymers, and blends of them, may be incorporated as the thermoplastic
polymeric material of the invention.</p><p num="0057">Polyester thermoplastics contain repeating ester linking
units in the polymer backbone. In one embodiment, they contain repeating
units derived from low molecular weight diols and low molecular weight
aromatic diacids. Non-limiting examples include the commercially available
grades of polyethylene terephthalate and polybutylene terephthalate.
Alternatively, the polyesters may be based on aliphatic diols and aliphatic
diacids. Exemplary here the copolymers of ethylene glycol or butanediol with
adipic acid. In another embodiment, the thermoplastic polyesters are
polylactones, prepared by polymerizing a monomer containing both hydroxyl
and carboxyl functionality. Polycaprolactone is a non-limiting example of this
class of thermoplastic polyester.</p><p num="0058">Polyamide thermoplastics contain repeating amide linkages
in the polymer backbone. In one embodiment, the polyamides contain
repeating units derived from diamine and diacid monomers such as the well
known nylon 66, a polymer of hexamethylene diamine and adipic acid. Other
nylons have structures resulting from varying the size of the diamine and diacid
components. Non-limiting examples include nylon 610, nylon 612, nylon 46,
and nylon 6/66 copolymer. In another embodiment, the polyamides have a
structure resulting from polymerizing a monomer with both amine and carboxyl
functionality. Non-limiting examples include nylon 6 (polycaprolactam), nylon
11, and nylon 12.</p><p num="0059">Other polyamides made from diamine and diacid
components include the high temperature aromatic polyamides containing
repeating units derived from diamines and aromatic diacids such as terephthalic
acid. Commercially available examples of these include PA6T (a copolymer of
hexanediamine and terephthalic acid), and PA9T (a copolymer of
nonanediamine and terephthalic acid), sold by Kuraray under the Genestar 
tradename. For some applications, the melting point of some aromatic
polyamides may be higher than optimum for thermoplastic processing. In such
cases, the melting point may be lowered by preparing appropriate copolymers.
In a non-limiting example, in the case of PA6T, which has a melting
temperature of about 370°C, it is possible to in effect lower the melting point to
below a moldable temperature of 320°C by including an effective amount of a
non-aromatic diacid such as adipic acid when making the polymer.</p><p num="0060">In another preferred embodiment, an aromatic polyamide is
used based on a copolymer of an aromatic diacid such as terephthalic acid and
a diamine containing greater than 6 carbon atoms, preferably containing 9
carbon atoms or more. The upper limit of the length of the carbon chain of the
diamine is limited from a practical standpoint by the availability of suitable
monomers for the polymer synthesis. As a rule, suitable diamines include
those having from 7 to 20 carbon atoms, preferably in the range of 9 to 15
carbons, and more preferably in the range from 9 to 12 carbons. Preferred
embodiments include C9, C10, and C11 diamine based aromatic polyamides.
It is believed that such aromatic polyamides exhibit an increase level of solvent
resistance based on the oleophilic nature of the carbon chain having greater
than 6 carbons. If desired to reduce the melting point below a preferred
molding temperature (typically 320°C or lower), the aromatic polyamide based
on diamines of greater than 6 carbons may contain an effective amount of a
non-aromatic diacid, as discussed above with the aromatic polyamide based on
a 6 carbon diamine. Such effective amount of diacid should be enough to lower
the melting point into a desired molding temperature range, without
unacceptably affecting the desired solvent resistance properties.</p><p num="0061">Other non-limiting examples of high temperature
thermoplastics include polyphenylene sulfide, liquid crystal polymers, and high
temperature polyimides. Liquid crystal polymers are based chemically on linear
polymers containing repeating linear aromatic rings. Because of the aromatic
structure, the materials form domains in the nematic melt state with a 
characteristic spacing detectable by x-ray diffraction methods. Examples of
materials include copolymers of hydroxybenzoic acid, or copolymers of ethylene
glycol and linear aromatic diesters such as terephthalic acid or naphthalene
dicarboxylic acid.</p><p num="0062">High temperature thermoplastic polyimides include the
polymeric reaction products of aromatic dianhydrides and aromatic diamines.
They are commercially available from a number of sources. Exemplary is a
copolymer of 1,4-benzenediamine and 1,2,4,5-benzenetetracarboxylic acid
dianhydride.</p><p num="0063">The curing composition contains a radical initiator. The
initiator is believed to function by first extracting a hydrogen or halogen atom
from the fluorocarbon elastomer to create a free radical that can be crosslinked.
Crosslinkers may also be included in the curing composition. The crosslinkers
also contain at least two sites of olefinic unsaturation, which react with the free
radical on the fluorocarbon elastomer molecule generated by the reaction of the
initiator.</p><p num="0064">In various embodiments, the initiators have peroxide
functionality. As examples of initiators, a wide range of organic peroxides is
known and commercially available. The initiators, including the organic
peroxides, are activated over a wide range of temperatures. The activation
temperature may be described in a parameter known as half-life. Typically
values for half-lives of, for example, 0.1 hours, 1 hour, and 10 hours are given
in degrees centigrade. For example a T<sub>1/2</sub> at 0.1 hours of 143°C indicates that
at that temperature, half of the initiator will decompose within 0.1 hours.
Organic peroxides with a T<sub>1/2</sub> at 0.1 hours from 118°C to 228°C are
commercially available. Such peroxides have a half-life of at least 0.1 hours at
the indicated temperatures. The T<sub>1/2</sub> values indicate the kinetics of the initial
reaction in crosslinking the fluorocarbon elastomers, that is decomposition of
the peroxide to form a radical containing intermediate. </p><p num="0065">In some embodiments, it is preferred to match the T<sub>1/2</sub> of
the initiator such as an organic peroxide to the temperature of the molten
material into which the curing composition is to be added. In various
embodiments, the initiator has a thermal stability such that the half-life is at
least 0.1 hours at temperatures of 180°C or higher. In other embodiments,
suitable initiators have a half-life of 0.1 hours at 190°C or higher, or at
temperatures of 200°C or higher. Non-limiting examples of peroxides and their
T<sub>1/2</sub> for a half-life of 0.1 hours include Trigonox 145-E85 (T<sub>1/2</sub> = 182°C),
Trigonox M55 (T<sub>1/2</sub> = 183°C), Trigonox K-90 (T<sub>1/2</sub> = 195°C), Trigonox A-W70
(T<sub>1/2</sub> = 207°C), and Trigonox TAHP-W85 (T<sub>1/2</sub> = 228°C). A non-limiting example
of a non-peroxide initiator is Perkadox-30 (T<sub>1/2</sub> = 284°C). The Trigonox and
Perkadox materials are commercial or developmental products of AkzoNobel.</p><p num="0066">Non-limiting examples of commercially available organic
peroxides for initiating the cure of fluorocarbon elastomers include butyl 4,4-di-(tert-butylperoxy)valerate;
tert-butyl peroxybenzoate; di-tert-amyl peroxide;
dicumyl peroxide; di-(tert-butylperoxyisopropyl)benzene; 2,5-dimethyl-2,5-di(tert-butylperoxy)hexane;
tert-butyl cumyl peroxide; 2,5,-dimethyl-2,5-di(tert-butylperoxy)hexyne-3;
di-tert-butyl peroxide; 3,6,9-triethyl-3,6,9-trimethyl-1,4,7-triperoxonane;
1,1,3,3-tetramethylbutyl hydroperoxide; diisopropylbenzene
monohydroperoxide; cumyl hydroperoxide; tert-butyl hydroperoxide; tert-amyl
hydroperoxide; tert-butyl peroxyisobutyrate; tert-amyl peroxyacetate; tert-butylperoxy
stearyl carbonate; di(1-hydroxycyclohexyl) peroxide; ethyl 3,3-di(tert-butylperoxy)butyrate;
and tert-butyl 3-isopropenylcumyl peroxide.</p><p num="0067">Non-limiting examples of crosslinking co-agents include
triallyl cyanurate; triallyl isocyanurate; tri(methallyl)-isocyanurate;
tris(diallylamine)-s-triazine, triallyl phosphite; N,N-diallyl acrylamide; hexaallyl
phosphoramide; N,N,N',N'-tetraallyl terephthalamide; N,N,N',N'-tetraallyl
malonamide; trivinyl isocyanurate; 2,4,6-trivinyl methyltrisiloxane; and tri(5-norbornene-2-methylene)
cyanurate. The crosslinking co-agents preferably
contain at least two sites of olefinic unsaturation. These sites of unsaturation 
react with the free radical generated on the fluorocarbon elastomer molecule
and crosslink the elastomer. A commonly used crosslinking agent is
triallylisocyanurate (TAIC).</p><p num="0068">In various embodiments, the cured fluorocarbon elastomer
compositions of the invention are prepared by a process of dynamic
vulcanization. Dynamic vulcanization is a vulcanization or a curing process for
a rubber (here a fluorocarbon elastomer) contained in a thermoplastic
composition, wherein the curable rubber is vulcanized under conditions of
sufficiently high shear at a temperature above the melting point of the
thermoplastic component. In this way, the rubber is simultaneously crosslinked
and dispersed within the thermoplastic matrix. Dynamic vulcanization may be
carried out by applying mechanical energy to mix the elastomeric and
thermoplastic components at elevated temperature in the presence of a
curative in conventional mixing equipment, such as roll mills, Moriyama mixers,
Banbury mixers, Brabender mixers, continuous mixers, mixing extruders such
as single and twin-screw extruders, and the like. An advantageous
characteristic of dynamically cured compositions is that, not withstanding that
the elastomeric component is fully cured, the composition can be processed
and reprocessed by conventional plastic processing techniques such as
extrusion, injection molding, and compression molding. Scrap or flashing can
also be salvaged and reprocessed with thermoplastic techniques.</p><p num="0069">The vulcanized elastomeric material that results from the
process of dynamic vulcanization is generally present as small particles within a
continuous thermoplastic polymer matrix. A co-continuous morphology is also
possible depending on the amount of elastomeric material relative to
thermoplastic material, the cure system, the mechanism of cure and the
amount and degree of mixing.</p><p num="0070">After dynamic vulcanization, a homogeneous mixture is
obtained wherein the cured fluoroelastomer is in the form of dispersed particles
having an average particle smaller than about 50 micrometers, preferably of an 
average particle size smaller than about 25 micrometers. Typically, the
particles have an average size of 10 micrometers or less, more preferably 5
micrometers or less. In some embodiments, the particles have an average size
of 1 micrometer or less. In other embodiments, even when the average particle
size is higher, there will be a significant number of cured elastomer particles
with a diameter of less than 1 micron dispersed in the thermoplastic matrix.</p><p num="0071">Masterbatches of peroxide are prepared by combining the
peroxide cure initiator, a fluorocarbon elastomer, and optionally a crosslinking
agent. The masterbatch may contain from about 5 to about 50% by weight of
the peroxide. The masterbatches may be conveniently prepared by combining
the ingredients in conventional mixers such as Banbury mixers, and the like.
They may also be compounded on screw mixers such as twin-screw extruders.
The masterbatches containing fluorocarbon elastomer and peroxide may be
added to molten mixtures during the dynamic vulcanization processing batch
mixtures or in continuous mixers such as twin-screw extruders.</p><p num="0072">The fluorocarbon elastomer of the peroxide masterbatch
may be chosen to be compatible with mixing in the fluorocarbon elastomer
during the dynamic vulcanization process. In typical dynamic vulcanization
processes, a fluorocarbon elastomer is mixed together in a molten
thermoplastic material. The temperature is typically 10-20°C higher than the
melting point of the thermoplastic. Adding the peroxide curing agent, optionally
along with a crosslinking agent containing multiple sites of olefinic unsaturation,
in the form of a masterbatch allows for faster incorporation of the peroxide
curing agent into the elastomer phase of the dynamic vulcanizate. It is also
believed that the fluorocarbon elastomer component of the masterbatch
protects the peroxide from bumping and volatilization upon addition to the
molten mixture.</p><p num="0073">In one embodiment, the fluorocarbon elastomer of the
peroxide masterbatch and that of the molten mixture are selected to be the
same. In this way, the masterbatch containing the peroxide is immediately 
compatible with the fluorocarbon elastomer of the dynamic vulcanizate. By
using the masterbatch method, a portion of the fluorocarbon elastomer to be
cured in the dynamic vulcanization process is added along with the peroxide.
Recipes for the dynamic vulcanizations, along with the charges of fluorocarbon
elastomer during the different steps of the dynamic vulcanization process, can
be designed and calculated depending on the concentration of the fluorocarbon
elastomer in the masterbatch.</p><p num="0074">The masterbatch can contain a wide range of peroxide
concentrations, but it is usually preferred to make masterbatches having from
about 5% up to about 50% by weight peroxide. In some embodiments, it will be
desirable to add peroxide in the master batch process in as little fluorocarbon
elastomer as possible, so as to achieve desired properties in the fully cured
dynamic vulcanizate. In other embodiments, it may be desirable to add more of
the fluorocarbon elastomer into the dynamic vulcanization process after the
initial melt blending of the fluorocarbon elastomer and the thermoplastic. In
these cases, masterbatches having peroxide concentrations toward the lower
end of the preferred range may be used.</p><p num="0075">The masterbatch is blended under conditions such that the
blending temperature does not exceed a temperature at which the peroxide
would act to cure the fluorocarbon elastomer. Typically, the masterbatch may
be blended at temperatures up to 100°C, in order to provide a mixture of low
enough viscosity for efficient blending. A preferred temperature range for
blending of the masterbatch is 80-100°C. For reactive elastomers, it may be
desirable to blend at 80°C or less.</p><p num="0076">The cured dynamic vulcanizates of the invention may be
made in batch, semi-batch, or continuous processes. For example, melt
processable fluoroelastomer compositions may be made by blending a
thermoplastic material and a fluorocarbon elastomer to form a first mixture, at a
temperature above a temperature at which the thermoplastic will flow
sufficiently, to form a dispersion of the fluorocarbon elastomer in thermoplastic. 
Such temperature may be referred to as a melt flow temperature. Next, a
second mixture (masterbatch) is provided that contains a fluorocarbon
elastomer and preferably greater than about 5% by weight of an organic
peroxide. The masterbatch is provided at a temperature below that at which
the peroxide would activate to initiate crosslinking of the fluorocarbon
elastomer. The first mixture and the second mixtures are then combined and
blended together while heating at a temperature and for a time sufficient to
effect cure of the fluorocarbon elastomer in the first and second mixtures.</p><p num="0077">The process may also be carried out continuously, for
example in extrusion mixers such as a twin-screw extruder. In one
embodiment, a solid blend of an uncured fluorocarbon elastomer and a
thermoplastic material is delivered to a first feeder of a first twin-screw extrusion
apparatus. The solid blend is injected into the barrel of the extruder, with the
barrel heated above a temperature at which the thermoplastic will melt and
flow, to produce a dispersion of the fluorocarbon elastomer in the thermoplastic.
For example, the barrel may be heated above the crystalline melting
temperature of the thermoplastic material. In preferred embodiments, the
temperature is 10°, 20° or 30°C higher than the melting temperature of the
thermoplastic. For example, the barrel may be heated above 180°C, above
210°C, or above 240°C. The solid blend is then mixed in the twin-screw
extruder to form a homogeneous melt blend. A peroxide masterbatch
containing greater or equal to 5% by weight of an organic peroxide is then
delivered to a second feeder and injected into the barrel of the twin-screw
extruder at a point downstream of the first feeder. The peroxide masterbatch
and the homogeneous melt blend in the barrel are then further mixed while
continuing to heat for a time and at a temperature sufficient to effect cure of the
fluorocarbon elastomers. The cured dynamic vulcanizate may then be extruded
from the twin-screw extrusion apparatus.</p><p num="0078">In an alternate embodiment, the peroxide masterbatch may
be delivered to the second feeder with a twin-screw extrusion apparatus that 
blends the organic peroxide, fluorocarbon elastomer, and optional crosslinking
agent at a temperature less than that which would activate the peroxide to cure
the elastomer. In this way, it is possible to continuously feed a fluorocarbon
elastomer and thermoplastic material at a first feeder port, and a curing agent
and fluorocarbon elastomer at a second port downstream from the first.</p><p num="0079">After extrusion from the mixing apparatus, the dynamically
vulcanized strand may be cooled in a water bath and chopped into pellets for
later use.</p><p num="0080">The use of the peroxide masterbatch method of making
dynamic vulcanizates leads to the formation of molded articles having an
advantageous combination of physical properties, when compared to the
physical properties of articles made by adding the peroxide and crosslinking
co-agent as individual components instead of as part of a masterbatch. The
masterbatch method also allows the use of high melting thermoplastics and
fluoroplastics to make dynamic vulcanizates, while still retaining acceptable
elastomeric properties. At 150°C, it is possible to make articles having a tensile
strength above 10 MPa, or even above 15 MPa or above 20 MPa. Even at
250°C, articles can be made have a tensile strength above 10 MPa, preferably
above 12 MPa, and more preferably above 15 MPa. Articles made at these
temperatures without the masterbatch method tend to exhibit lower or less
advantageous values of tensile strength and other properties.</p><p num="0081">The invention has been described above with respect to
preferred embodiments, further non-limiting examples of the compositions and
methods of the invention are given in the examples that follow.</p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><heading>Example 1 - Preparation of Peroxide Masterbatches</heading><p num="0082">The procedure to make masterbatches containing curable
fluorocarbon elastomer is as follows: 1) Melt the fluorocarbon elastomer, (for 
example Technoflon P757, a peroxide curable fluorocarbon elastomer
containing a cure site, commercially available from Solvay) in a batch mixer
such as a Brabender with an internal mixer attachment at a temperature of from
80-100°C. 2) Add a curative package consisting of Luperco 101 XL and TAIC.
Luperco 101 XL contains as an active ingredient 2,5,-dimethyl-2,5-di(tert-butylperoxy)hexyne-3.
TAIC is triallylisocyanurate. Continue mixing until a
homogeneous mixture is obtained. 3) Discharge the mixture from the internal
mixer, cool and pulverize into a powder or small pellets. The compositions may
then be used as masterbatch material during dynamic compounding of
fluorocarbon elastomers with thermoplastic material.</p><p num="0083">Masterbatches are made at three different concentrations
of peroxide and TAIC, given in Examples 1 a, 1b, and 1 c.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Ingredients</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 1a phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 1b phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 1 c phr</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Tecnoflon P757</b></entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Luperco 101 XL</b></entry><entry align="center">15.0</entry><entry align="center">30.0</entry><entry align="center">45.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>TAIC, 75% Dispersion</b></entry><entry align="center">20.00</entry><entry align="center">40.00</entry><entry align="center">60.00</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Examples 2-4 - Continuous and batch processes</heading><p num="0084">Examples 2-4 illustrate recipes for making moldable
compositions of the invention. They can be made by either batch or continuous
processes.</p><p num="0085">In a batch process, the peroxide curable elastomer
(Tecnoflon P757) and the thermoplastic (here a fluoroplastic, Kynar Flex 2500-04)
are mixed and melted in a Brabender or Banbury type batch mixer at 150°C
for 5 minutes. The zinc oxide is then stirred in. A chopped masterbatch
material (1-3 mm size, Example 1) is added to the mixer and stirred for an 
additional 3-5 minutes at 150°C to form a fully cured thermoplastic vulcanizate.
Alternatively, the mixing may be carried out for a shorter time such as 30
seconds to prepare a partially cured vulcanizate. The composition is then
discharged from the batch mixer and granulated to make small size pellets for
use in subsequent fabrication processes, such as injection molding,
compression molding, blow molding, single layer extrusion, multi-layer
extrusion, insert molding, and the like.</p><p num="0086">A continuous process is carried out in a twin-screw
extruder. Tecnoflon P757 and Kynar Flex 2500-04 pellets are mixed and
added to a hopper. The pellets are fed into the barrel, which is heated to
150°C. The screw speed is 100-200 rpm. At a downstream hopper, pellets of
a peroxide masterbatch are fed into the barrel. The downstream port is located
about one third of the total barrel length from the end of the extruder exit. The
masterbatch is melted and blended with the molten elastomer and
(fluoro)plastic mixture for a time determined by the screw speed and the length
of the barrel. For example, the residence time is about 4-5 minutes at 100 rpm
and about 2-2.5 minutes at 200 rpm. The cured material is extruded through 1-3
mm diameter strand die and is quenched by cooling in a water bath before
passing through a strand pelletizer. The pellets may be processed by a wide
variety of thermoplastic techniques into molded articles. The material may also
be formed into plaques for the measurement of physical properties. </p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0087"><tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Ingredients</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 2a phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 2b phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 2c phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 2d phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 2e phr</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Tecnoflon P757</b></entry><entry align="center">80.0</entry><entry align="center">80.0</entry><entry align="center">80.0</entry><entry align="center">80.0</entry><entry align="center">80.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Kynar Flex 2500-04</b></entry><entry align="center">25.0</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry><entry align="center">150.0</entry><entry align="center">200.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>ZnO</b></entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>MT N-990 carbon black</b></entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Masterbatch - Ex 1a</b></entry><entry align="center">20.00</entry><entry align="center">20.00</entry><entry align="center">20.00</entry><entry align="center">20.00</entry><entry align="center">20.00</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="0088"><tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Ingredient</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 3a phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 3b phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 3c phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 3d phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 3e phr</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Technoflon P757</b></entry><entry align="center">90.0</entry><entry align="center">90.0</entry><entry align="center">90.0</entry><entry align="center">90.0</entry><entry align="center">90.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Kynar Flex 2500-04</b></entry><entry align="center">25.0</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry><entry align="center">150.0</entry><entry align="center">200.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>ZnO</b></entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry> <entry align="center">5.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>MT N-990 Carbon Black</b></entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry> <entry align="center">10.00</entry> <entry align="center">10.00</entry> <entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Masterbatch - Ex 1b</b></entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0089"><tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Ingredient</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 4a phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 4b phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 4c phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 4d phr</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Ex 4e phr</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Technoflon P757</b></entry><entry align="center">93.3</entry><entry align="center">93.3</entry><entry align="center">93.3</entry><entry align="center">93.3</entry><entry align="center">93.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Kynar Flex 2500-04</b></entry><entry align="center">25.0</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">100.0</entry><entry align="center">150.0</entry><entry align="center">200.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>ZnO</b></entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry><entry align="center">5.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>MT N-990 Carbon Black</b></entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry><entry align="center">10.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Masterbatch -Ex 1c</b></entry><entry align="center">6.70</entry><entry align="center">6.70</entry><entry align="center">6.70</entry><entry align="center">6.70</entry><entry align="center">6.70</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0090">Molded articles prepared from the cured compositions of
Examples 2-4 are prepared by conventional plastic processing techniques.
Cross sections of the molded articles may be examined with microscope or
scanning electron microscopes. The dynamic vulcanizates made with the
masterbatches in Examples 2-4 have a smooth surface and a non-porous
structure compared to molded articles prepared in the same way, but without
using the masterbatch process.</p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="0091">Physical properties are measured of compositions of
Example 2, The masterbatch of peroxide is added to the molten blend of
elastomer and thermoplastic at 250°C. The batch process is used. <tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Composition of example</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>% thermoplasti c</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Shore A hardness</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>tensile strength, MPa</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>modulus at 50%, MPa</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>elongation at break, %</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>2a</b></entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">80</entry><entry align="center">5.25</entry><entry align="center">2.49</entry><entry align="center">157</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>2b</b></entry><entry align="center">33</entry><entry align="center">86</entry><entry align="center">6.95</entry><entry align="center">3.39</entry><entry align="center">223</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>2c</b></entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">93</entry><entry align="center">10.68</entry><entry align="center">4.97</entry><entry align="center">339</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>2d</b></entry><entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="center">96</entry><entry align="center">13.24</entry><entry align="center">6.25</entry><entry align="center">371</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>2e</b></entry><entry align="center">67</entry><entry align="center">97</entry><entry align="center">14.25</entry><entry align="center">6.93</entry><entry align="center">383</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 6</heading><p num="0092">Physical properties are measured as for Example 5, except
that the compositions are obtained by adding a peroxide masterbatch to a
molten blend of elastomer and thermoplastic at 150°C. The batch process is
used.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Composition of example, masterbatch added at 150°C</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>% thermoplastic</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Shore A hardness</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>tensile strength, MPa</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>modulus at 50%, MPa</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>elongation at break, %</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>2a</b></entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>2b</b></entry><entry align="center">33</entry><entry align="center">81</entry><entry align="center">11.17</entry><entry align="center">4.41</entry><entry align="center">192</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>2c</b></entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">15.93</entry><entry align="center">5.93</entry><entry align="center">282</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>2d</b></entry><entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="center">91</entry><entry align="center">18.62</entry><entry align="center">8.48</entry><entry align="center">346</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>2e</b></entry><entry align="center">67</entry><entry align="center">95</entry><entry align="center">22.6</entry><entry align="center">8.06</entry><entry align="center">442</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Example 7 - comparative</heading><p num="0093">Moldable compositions are prepared according to the
recipes given in Example 2 (batch process), except that the peroxide and TAIC
are added to the molten blend of elastomer and thermoplastic as individual
components, and not as part of a masterbatch containing a fluorocarbon
elastomer portion. The temperature of the molten blend is 250°C.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Example</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>% thermoplasti c</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Shore A hardness</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>tensile strength, MPa</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>modulus at 50%, MPa</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>elongation at break, %</b></entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>7a</b></entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">74</entry><entry align="center">2.11</entry><entry align="center">1.69</entry><entry align="center">385</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>7b</b></entry><entry align="center">33</entry><entry align="center">78</entry><entry align="center">2.4</entry><entry align="center">2.32</entry><entry align="center">286</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>7c</b></entry><entry align="center">50</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="center">3.62</entry><entry align="center">3.58</entry><entry align="center">182</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>7d</b></entry><entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="center">95</entry><entry align="center">5.14</entry><entry align="center">5.03</entry><entry align="center">92</entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>7e</b></entry><entry align="center">67</entry><entry align="center">95</entry><entry align="center">6.66</entry><entry align="center">6.34</entry><entry align="center">167</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method of preparing a moldable polymer composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) forming a mixture of thermoplastic material and a curable
fluorocarbon elastomer at a temperature above the melting point
of the thermoplastic;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) adding a curing composition to the mixture, wherein the curing
composition comprises an initiator having a half-life of 0.1 hours
or more at a temperature of about 180°C or higher and
crosslinking agent; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) heating while continuing to mix the mixture and the curing
composition.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 1, wherein the initiator has a half-life of 0.1
hours or more at a temperature of about 190°C or higher.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 2, wherein the initiator has a half-life of 0.1
hours or more at a temperature of about 200°C or higher.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 1, wherein the thermoplastic material
comprises a fluorine-containing thermoplastic polymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 1, wherein the curable fluorocarbon
elastomer comprises a copolymer of VDF, HFP, and a cure site
monomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 5, wherein the curable fluorocarbon
elastomer comprises a copolymer of VDF, HFP, TFE, and a cure site
monomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 1, wherein the fluorocarbon elastomer
comprises a copolymer of VDF, fluorinated vinyl ether, TFE, and a cure
site monomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 1, wherein the fluorocarbon elastomer
comprises a copolymer of VDF, propylene, TFE, and a cure site
monomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 1, wherein the fluorocarbon elastomer
comprises a copolymer of VDF, TFE, HFP, ethylene, fluorinated vinyl
ether, and a cure site monomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 1, wherein the fluorocarbon elastomer
comprises a perfluoro rubber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 1, wherein the fluorocarbon elastomer
comprises a copolymer of TFE and propylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 1, comprising heating the mixture above
about 180°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 12, comprising heating the mixture above
about 190°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 13, comprising heating the mixture above
about 200°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A process for making a melt processable fluorocarbon rubber
composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) adding a peroxide masterbatch to a molten blend of a first portion
of fluorocarbon elastomer and a thermoplastic material, wherein
the masterbatch comprises greater than or equal to about 5%
weight percent organic peroxide and further comprises a second
portion of a fluorocarbon elastomer; and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) mixing the peroxide masterbatch, the first portion of fluorocarbon
elastomer, and the thermoplastic material while heating for a time
and at a temperature sufficient to effect cure of the fluorocarbon
elastomers.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 15, using a twin-screw extruder having a
first feeder and a second feeder downstream from the first feeder,
wherein said adding comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) injecting a composition comprising the first portion of fluorocarbon
elastomer and the thermoplastic material into the first feeder of the
extruder; and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) adding the masterbatch into the with a second feeder of the extruder.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 15, wherein the fluorocarbon elastomer of
the first portion and the second portion are the same.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 15, wherein the fluorocarbon elastomer
comprises a copolymer of vinylidene fluoride and cure site monomers
containing iodine.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 15, wherein the peroxide masterbatch
comprises greater than about 10% by weight percent peroxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 15, wherein the peroxide masterbatch
comprises greater than about 20% by weight percent peroxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 19, wherein the thermoplastic material
comprises a fluoroplastic.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 21, wherein the fluoroplastic comprises a
vinylidene fluoride homopolymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 21, wherein the fluoroplastic comprises a
vinylidene fluoride copolymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>A molded article comprising a peroxide cured dynamic vulcanizate of a
fluorocarbon elastomer and a fluorine containing thermoplastic, having a
tensile modulus above about 10 MPa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="25"><claim-text>A molded article according to Claim 24, having a tensile modulus above
about 12 MPa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="26"><claim-text>A molded article according to Claim 25, having a tensile modulus above
about 15 MPa.</claim-text></claim><claim num="27"><claim-text>A molded article according to Claim 24, comprising a discrete phase of
cured fluorocarbon elastomer and a continuous phase of a fluoroplastic
material.</claim-text></claim><claim num="28"><claim-text>A molded article according to Claim 26, wherein the fluorocarbon
elastomer comprises a copolymer of VDF and HFP.</claim-text></claim><claim num="29"><claim-text>A molded article according to Claim 28, wherein the fluorocarbon
elastomer comprises a copolymer of VDF, HFP, and TFE.</claim-text></claim><claim num="30"><claim-text>A molded article according to Claim 26, wherein the fluorocarbon
elastomer comprises a copolymer of VDF, fluorinated vinyl ether, and
TFE.</claim-text></claim><claim num="31"><claim-text>A molded article according to Claim 26, wherein the fluorocarbon
elastomer comprises a copolymer of VDF, TFE, and propylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="32"><claim-text>A molded article according to Claim 26, wherein the fluorocarbon
elastomer comprises a copolymer of VDF, HFP, TFE, fluorinated vinyl
ether, and ethylene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="33"><claim-text>A molded article according to Claim 26, wherein the fluorocarbon
elastomer comprises a perfluoro rubber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="34"><claim-text>A process for making melt processable fluoroelastomer composition
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) blending a thermoplastic polymeric material and a first
fluorocarbon elastomer to form a first mixture at a temperature
above a melt flow temperature of the thermoplastic;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) combining the first mixture with a second mixture comprising a
second fluorocarbon elastomer and greater than or equal to about
5% by weight of an organic peroxide at a temperature below that
at which the peroxide would activate to initiate crosslinking of the
second fluorocarbon elastomer; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) blending the first and second mixtures together while heating at a
temperature and for a time sufficient to cure the fluorocarbon
elastomer in the first and second mixtures.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="35"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 34, wherein the second mixture further
comprises a crosslinker containing at least two sites of olefinic
unsaturation.</claim-text></claim><claim num="36"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 35, wherein the crosslinker comprises
triallylisocyanurate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="37"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 35, wherein the first mixture further
comprises a crosslinker containing at least two sites of olefinic
unsaturation.</claim-text></claim><claim num="38"><claim-text>A method according to Claim 37, wherein the crosslinker comprises
triallylisocyanurate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="39"><claim-text>A continuous process for preparing a peroxide cured dynamic
vulcanizate of a fluorocarbon elastomer in a thermoplastic, using a twin-screw
extrusion apparatus having a barrel, a first feeder, and a second
feeder that is downstream of the first feeder, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) delivering a solid blend of an uncured fluorocarbon elastomer and
thermoplastic to the first feeder;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) injecting the solid blend into the barrel of the extruder, wherein the
barrel is heated above a melt flow temperature of the
thermoplastic;</claim-text><claim-text>(c) mixing the solid blend in the extruder to form a homogeneous melt
blend;</claim-text><claim-text>(d) injecting a peroxide masterbatch to the second feeder, wherein
the peroxide masterbatch comprises an uncured fluorocarbon
elastomer and greater or equal to about 5% by weight of an
organic peroxide;</claim-text><claim-text>(e) mixing the peroxide masterbatch and the homogenous melt blend
in the barrel while continuing to heat at a temperature and for a
time sufficient to effect cure of the fluorocarbon elastomers, and;</claim-text><claim-text>(f) extruding the mixture from the twin-screw extruder.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="40"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 39, wherein the peroxide masterbatch is
delivered to the second feeder with a twin screw apparatus that blends
the organic peroxide and fluorocarbon elastomer at a temperature less
than that which would activate the peroxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="41"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 39, wherein the fluorocarbon elastomers
comprise a copolymer of vinylidene fluoride and a cure site monomer,
and the thermoplastic comprises a fluoroplastic.</claim-text></claim><claim num="42"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 41, wherein the fluoroplastic comprises a
vinylidene fluoride polymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="43"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 39, comprising heating the barrel above
about 180°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="44"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 43, comprising heating the barrel above
about 210°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="45"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 44, comprising heating the barrel above
about 240°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="46"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 39, wherein the peroxide masterbatch
further comprises a crosslinker containing two or more sites of olefinic
unsaturation.</claim-text></claim><claim num="47"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 46, wherein the crosslinker comprises
triallylisocyanurate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="48"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 39, wherein the solid blend of uncured
fluorocarbon elastomer and thermoplastic further comprises a crosslinker
containing two or more sites of olefinic unsaturation.</claim-text></claim><claim num="49"><claim-text>A process according to Claim 48, wherein the crosslinker comprises
triallylisocyanurate.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>