<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1510552-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1510552" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="34104703" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050302"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1510552-A1" status="new" fvid="24287288"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1510552</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050302</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04255148-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04255148</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040826</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-65039103-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>65039103</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030828</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  63/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  63/199       20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/32        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/52        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/00        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/02        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  69/00        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  69/00        20060101C I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  67/02+B4K</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  69/00+B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  69/00+B4K</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L205:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L67:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L69:00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Polycarbonat-Polyester Formmasse</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Polycarbonate polyester molding composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition de moulage à base de polycarbonate et de polyester</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="US-20020128357-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>20020128357</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4188314-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4188314</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4786692-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4786692</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GEN ELECTRIC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</last-name><address><street>1 River Road</street><city>Schenectady, NY 12345</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DE WIT GERRIT</name><address><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VOLLENBERG PETER H TH</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DE WIT, GERRIT</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VOLLENBERG, PETER H. TH.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>DE WIT, GERRIT</last-name><address><street>Binnenweg 23</street><city>Ossendrecht</city><country>NL</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VOLLENBERG, PETER H. TH.</last-name><address><street>401 Marlene Drive</street><city>Evansville Indiana 47712</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Szary, Anne Catherine, Dr.</last-name><address><street>London Patent Operation General Electric International, Inc. 15 John Adam Street</street><city>London WC2N 6LU</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A clear blend of three resin components includes a first polycarbonate resin
component; a second resin component of a first polyester copolymer resin derived
from a cycloaliphatic diol and a cycloaliphatic dicarboxylic acid, and a third resin
component of a second polyester polymer resin derived from the condensation of a
cyclohexane diol with a terephthalic acid and an additional condensation reaction
component selected from aliphatic or aromatic diacids or diols suitable for enhancing
the clarity of said blend wherein the three component blend has a light transmission of
seventy percent or greater and an elongation at break after exposure to Fuel C of forty
percent or greater.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="117" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="70"/><img id="img-00000002" orientation="unknown" wi="125" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000002.tif" inline="no" he="71"/><img id="img-00000003" orientation="unknown" wi="131" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000003.tif" inline="no" he="72"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention relates to clear bends of polycarbonate and polyester resins.</p><p num="0002">U.S. Patent No. 5,942,585 to Scott et al relates to clear blends of polycarbonates and
polyesters where the polyester comprises a dicarboxylic acid component based on 1,4-cyclohexanedicarboxylic
acid units and a glycol component comprising 2,2,4,4-tetramethyl-1,3-cyclobutanediol
units. Miscible polycarbonate polyester blends are
described in a Free Volume approach to the Mechanical Behaviour of Miscible
Polycarbonate Blends, by A. J. Hill et al, J. PHYS.: Condens Matter, 8, 3811-3827
(1996) and in Dynamic Mechanical and Dielectric Relaxation Study of Aliphatic
Polyester Based Blends by Stack et al., J.M. Polym. Mater. Sci. Eng. (1993), 69, 4-5,
Eastman Chemical Company, Kingsport, TN 37662. U.S. Patent 4,879,355 to Light et
al relates to a clear polymer blend comprising a glycol copolyester having repeat units
from 1,4-cyclohexanedimethanol, terephthalic acid and an alkylene glycol; a
polycarbonate resin; and an aromatic polyester having repeat units from terephthalic
acid, isophthalic acid and Bisphenol A. U.S. patent 4,786,692 to Allen et al. relates to
a blend of an aromatic polycarbonate and a copolymer derived from a glycol portion
comprising 1,4-cyclohexanedimethanol and ethylene glycol. Some of these references
describe clear properties of the thermoplastic blends.</p><p num="0003">US Patent 5,399,661 to Borman et al relates to copolyester compositions which
comprise the reaction product of at least one straight chain, branched, or
cycloaliphatic C2-C1 0 alkane diol or a chemical equivalent and a mixture of at least
two cycloaliphatic diacids. The diacid mixture comprises predominantly a trans
isomer and at least one aromatic diacid. As set forth in column 5, lines 41 to 45, "The
reaction is generally run with an excess of the diol component and in the presence of a
suitable catalyst". US Patent 5,486,562 to Borman et al additionally describes an
impact strength modifier for compositions of the type set forth in the '661 patent.</p><p num="0004">U.S. patent 4,879,355 to Light et al. describes a clear polymer blend comprising (10
50-90 wt. % of a glycol copolyester having repeat units from 1,4-cyclohexanedimethanol, 
terephthalic acid and an alkylen glycol; (2) 45-5 wet. % of a
polycarbonate resin; and (3) 5-45 wt. % of an aromatic polyester having repeat units
from terephthalic acid, isophthalic acid and Bisphenol A.</p><p num="0005">U.S. patent 4,188,314 to Fox describes the addition of a polyester polymer derived
from a cyclohexanedimethanol and a mixture of iso- and terephthalic acid to an
aromatic carbonate polymer to enhance the solvent resistance as compared to a
polycarbonate article.</p><p num="0006">Other references include patent 4,879,355; 6,043,322; 6,037,424; 6,011,124;
6,005,059; 5,942,585; 5,194,523; and 5,017,659 and GB 1,559,230A.</p><p num="0007">Transparent blends of polycarbonate and polyesters may have attractive properties like
toughness and chemical resistance. Also, UV resistance may be improved over that of
polycarbonate by itself. Certain compositional blends of these resins may have high
optical transparency and good chemical resistance. It is desired to enlarge the
compositional design space in which the combination of these properties may be met.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0008">According to an embodiment, a clear thermoplastic blend includes three resin
components. A first resin component is a polycarbonate resin. A second resin blend
component is a first polyester copolymer resin derived from a cycloaliphatic diol or
equivalent thereof and a cycloaliphatic dicarboxylic acid or equivalent thereof. A
third resin component is a second polyester polymer resin derived from the
condensation of a cyclohexane diol or equivalents thereof with a terephthalic acid or
equivalents thereof and an additional condensation reaction component selected from
aliphatic or aromatic diacids or diols suitable for enhancing the clarity of said blend.
The three components are present in proportions to form a clear blend having a
transmission of seventy percent or greater and an elongation at break after exposure to
Fuel C of forty percent or greater. Desirable enhanced chemical resistance is provided
to the polycarbonate/polyester blend by the addition of the third component, which is 
the second polyester, as compared to a two component blend absent said second
polyester component.</p><p num="0009">According to an embodiment, the blend consisting essentially of the three resin
components with the first resin component comprising about 35 to about 66 weight
percent of a polycarbonate resin based on the total weight of the three blend
components. The second resin blend component, i.e. first polyester component, is
present in an amount of about 33 to about 65 weight percent based on the total weight.
The third resin blend component, i.e. second polyester component, is present in an
amount from about 2 to about 35 weight percent based on the total weight of the
blend.</p><p num="0010">According to an embodiment, the clear three component blend consists essentially of a
polycarbonate resin, a second component of a first polyester derived from
cyclohexanedimethanol or equivalents and a dimethyl cyclohexanedicarboxylic acid
or equivalents, and a third component of a second polyester which is derived from the
reaction of 1,4-cylohexanedimethanol or equivalents, with a mixture of terephthalic
acid or equivalents and isophthalic acid or equivalents wherein the isophthalic acid is
present in said mixture in an amount for enhancing the clarity of the three component
blend.</p><p num="0011">According to an embodiment, desirable enhanced chemical resistance is provided with
the addition of the second polyester as compared to a two component blend absent
said second polyester component.</p><p num="0012">According to an embodiment, a clear three component blend comprises a first
component polycarbonate resin, a second component of a first polyester derived from
cyclohexanedimethanol or equivalents and a dimethyl cyclohexanedicarboxylic acid
or equivalents, and a third component of a second polyester derived from the
condensation reaction of a mixture of 1,4-cylohexanedimethanol or equivalents and
ethylene glycol or equivalents with terephthalic acid or equivalents wherein the 
ethylene glycol is present in said mixture in an amount for enhancing the clarity of the
three component blend.</p><p num="0013">The polyester resins are typically obtained through the condensation or ester
interchange polymerization of the diol or diol equivalent component with the diacid or
diacid chemical equivalent component according to methods known in the prior art.
The polycarbonate resin components are prepared according to prior art techniques as
referred to herein.</p><heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0014">The Figures 1A, 1B and 1C, respectively, show ternary type diagrams for the resin
blends set forth.</p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0015">For sake of clarity, the following Table 1 sets forth the meaning of the abbreviations
used throughout the specification.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Abbreviations</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Abbreviation</i></entry><entry align="left"><i>Name</i></entry></row><row><entry align="left">PC</entry><entry align="left">polycarbonate 1,4-cyclohexanedicarboxylic acid, polymer with</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PCCD</entry><entry align="left">1,4-cyclohexanedimethanol (9CI Chemical Abstracts Index name); also poly(1,4-cyclohexylenedimethylene 1,4-cyclohexanedicarboxylate)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">CHDM</entry><entry align="left">1,4-cyclohexanedimethanol (trans/cis mixture)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">t-DMCD</entry><entry align="left">dimethyl trans-1,4-cyclohexanedicarboxylate</entry></row><row><entry align="left">TPA</entry><entry align="left">Terephthalic acid</entry></row><row><entry align="left">IPA</entry><entry align="left">Isophthalic acid</entry></row><row><entry align="left">EG</entry><entry align="left">Ethylene glycol</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PCT</entry><entry align="left">polycyclohexane dimethanol terephthalate (TPA + CHDM)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PCTA</entry><entry align="left">TPA + IPA + CHDM</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PCTG</entry><entry align="left">   TPA + CHDM + EG</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MV</entry><entry align="left">Melt Viscosity</entry></row><row><entry align="left">T<sub>m</sub></entry><entry align="left">Melting Point</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables> 
PCCD and PC are miscible and mixing results in transparent translucent blends,
having a single T<sub>g</sub> and excellent impact performance.</p><p num="0016">Surprisingly it was found that by using PCTA or PCTG as an additional polyester
polymer component to PCCD in the blend, the compositional design space can be
increased. PCTA is preferred for obtaining a large compositional design space in
which the favorable combination of high optical transparency and good chemical
resistance can be met. This is graphically shown in Figure 1, where the light colored
areas in the compositional areas indicate formulations that meet an optical
transparency of over 70% with a tensile elongation at break after exposure to Fuel C
of over 40%. The benefit of adding PCTA type polymers to PC/PCCD blends is that
the heat and chemical resistance are improved and the total raw material cost of the
formulation can be reduced.</p><p num="0017">In an embodiment, the transparent ternary blend includes PC, PCCD, and a 1)
cycloaliphatic polyester containing the condensation product of 1,4-cyclohexanedimentanol
and a mixture of terephthalic acid, divalent residues or
derivatives thereof and isophthalic acid, divalent residues, or derivatives or 2)
cycloaliphatic polyester containing the condensation product of 1,4-cyclohexanedimentanol,
ethylene glycol, and a terephthalic acid, divalent residues or
derivatives thereof. Preferably the third component of the above ternary blend is
PCTA which comprises the reaction product of CHDM, TPA and IPA. The third
component may be PCTG type as set forth in 2). In this case CHDM and DMCD
condensation reactants and equivalents thereof may include polyol components such
as divalent aliphatic, alicyclic or aromatic radical diols, or diol derivatives, or
mixtures of such diols and derivatives that do not adversely affect the favorable
desired properties. One such example is the addition ethylene glycol to the
condensation reaction of CHDM and TPA.</p><p num="0018">A process for the preparation of a transparent/translucent molding composition
comprises selecting a blend of PCCD, PC and PCTA or PCTG within the
compositional range of ingredients for imparting clear or transparent properties to the 
resulting blend and wherein said proportions of ingredients are selected so as to impart
high heat and chemical resistant properties.</p><p num="0019">The cycloaliphatic polyester resin has repeating units of the formula IA:
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="21"/>
wherein R<sup>1</sup> and A<sup>1</sup> are cycloaliphatic groups.</p><p num="0020">With reference to the previously set forth general formula, for R<sup>1</sup> is derived from 1,4
cyclohexane dimethanol or chemical equivalent; and A<sup>1</sup> is a cyclohexane ring derived
from cyclohexanedicarboxylate or a chemical equivalent thereof. The favored PCCD
has a cis/trans formula.</p><p num="0021">A preferred cycloaliphatic polyester is poly(cyclohexane-1,4-dimethylene
cyclohexane-1,4-dicarboxylate) also referred to as poly(1,4-cyclohexane-dimethanol-1,4-dicarboxylate)
(PCCD) which has recurring units of formula IB:
<img id="img-00060002" orientation="unknown" wi="135" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060002.tif" inline="no" he="19"/></p><p num="0022">In formula IB, R is H or alkyl, such as alkyl groups having from 1 to 6 carbon atoms.</p><p num="0023">The polyester polymerization reaction is generally run in the melt in the presence of a
suitable catalyst such as a tetrakis (2-ethyl hexyl) titanate, in a suitable amount,
typically about 50 to 200 ppm of titanium based upon the final product.</p><p num="0024">Preferred cycloaliphatic polyesters will have weight average molecular weights
(determined by gel permeation chromatography using polystyrene standards) of about
30,000 to about 150,000 atomic mass units (amu), with about 60,000 to about 100,000
amu being preferred, and about 65,000 to about 95,000 amu being more preferred.
Preferred cycloaliphatic polyesters will also have viscosities of about 500 to about 
25,000 poise, with about 1,000 to about 20,000 poise being preferred, and about 2,000
to about 6,000 poise being more preferred.</p><p num="0025">Also contemplated herein are the above polyesters with from about 1 to about 50
percent by weight, of units derived from polymeric aliphatic acids and/or polymeric
aliphatic polyols to form copolyesters. The aliphatic polyols include glycols, such as
poly(ethylene glycol) or poly(butylene glycol). Such polyesters can be made
following the teachings of, for example, U.S. Patent Nos. 2,465,319 and 3,047,539.</p><p num="0026">In the preferred formula IB:
<img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="134" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="20"/></p><p num="0027">R is an alkyl from 1 to 6 carbon atoms or residual endgroups derived from either
monomer, and n is greater than about 70. The polyester is derived from the
transesterification reaction of a starting DMCD and a starting CHDM. The trans-cis
ratio of repeating units derived from DMCD is preferably greater than about 8 to 1,
and the trans-cis ratio of repeating units derived from CHDM is preferable greater
than about 1 to 1. The polyester resin typically a viscosity greater than 3500 poise and
a melting temperature greater than 216 C degrees Centigrade, and an acid number less
than about 10, preferably less than about 6 meq/kg.</p><p num="0028">The linear PCCD polyester is prepared by the condensation reaction of CHDM and
DMCD in the presence of a catalyst wherein the starting DMCD has a <i>trans-cis</i> ratio
greater than the equilibrium <i>trans-cis</i> ratio. The resulting prepared PCCD polyester
has a <i>trans-cis</i> ratio of repeating polymer units derived from the respective starting
DMCD which has a <i>trans-cis</i> ratio substantially equal to the respective starting trans-cis
ratio for enhancing the crystallinity of the resulting PCCD.</p><p num="0029">The starting DMCD typically has a trans-cis ratio greater than about 6 to 1, preferably
greater than 9 to 1, and even more preferably greater than 19 to 1. In the resulting
PCCD, it is preferable that less than about 10 percent the starting trans DMCD, and 
more preferable that less than about 5 percent of the starting trans DMCD be
converted to the cis isomer during the reaction of CHDM and DMCD to produce
PCCD. The <i>trans:cis</i> ratio of the CHDM is preferable greater than 1 to 1, and more
preferably greater than about 2 to 1.</p><p num="0030">The resulting linear PCCD polymer is characterized by the absence of branching.
During the reaction process, branching may be induced by the addition of polyglycol
and such branching agents as trimellitic acid or anhydride, trimesic acid,
trimethyiolethane, trimethylolpropane, or a trimer acid. The use of such branching
agents is not desirable according to the present invention.</p><p num="0031">The preferred enhanced melt viscosity of the final prepared PCCD is greater than
3500 poise with temperatures of melting, <i>T</i><sub>m</sub><i>,</i> being greater than about 220°C. The acid
number which is determined by the number of acid end groups on the polymer chain
is preferably less than about 6 meq/kg as determined from the titration method.
Preferred melting temperature is preferably greater than about 216°C and more
preferably from about 216 to about 230°C. Preferably the amount of catalyst present
is less than about 200 ppm. Typically, catalyst may be present in a range from about
20 to about 300 ppm. The most preferred materials are blends where the polyester has
both cycloaliphatic diacid and cycloaliphatic diol components specifically
polycyclohexane dimethanol cyclohexyl dicarboxylate (PCCD). The preferred
polycarbonate comprises units of BPA, SBI bis phenol, aryl substituted bisphenols,
cycloaliphatic bisphenols and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0032">The PCTA cycloaliphatic polyester resin comprises a polyester having repeating units
of the formula IIA, -O-R<sup>2</sup>-O-(CO)-A<sup>2</sup>-(CO)- and IIB, -O-R<sup>2</sup>-O-(CO)-A<sup>3</sup>-(CO)-. The
polyester is a condensation product having units of formula IIA and IIB where R<sup>2</sup> in
both formulae are a cyclohexyl group which is the residue from a cyclohexyl diol or
chemical equivalent thereof. Formula IIA has phenyl units A<sup>2</sup> derived from the
dicarboxylic acid isophthalic acid or derivatives thereof and formula IIB has phenyl</p><p num="0033">A<sup>3</sup> units derived from the dicarboxylic acid terephthalic acid or derivatives thereof. </p><p num="0034">According to an embodiment, the PCTA type cycloaliphatic polyesters are
condensation products of aliphatic diacids, or chemical equivalents and aliphatic diols,
or chemical equivalents. The present PCTA cycloaliphatic polyesters are formed from
a mixture of isophthalic acid or derivatives thereof and terephthalic acid or derivatives
thereof. The hexacarbocyclic dicarboxylic acids which are condensed with the
cyclohexanedimethanol are mixtures of terephthalic and isophthalic acids. According
to an embodiment, the mixture may contain, in weight percent, from about 5% to
about 90% isophthalic acid and from about 95% to about 10% by terephthalic acid,
preferably from about 10% to about 80% isophthalic acid and from about 90% to
about 20% terephthalic acid, and more preferably from about 10% to about 25%
isophthalic acid and from about 90% to about 75% terephthalic acid. According to a
preferred embodiment, the three component blend comprises from about 35 to 45 wt%
PC; from about 33 to 43 wt% PCCD; from about 20 to 35 wt% PCTA.</p><p num="0035">According to an embodiment, the PCTG type cycloaliphatic polyesters are
condensation products of aliphatic diacids, or chemical equivalents and aliphatic diols,
or chemical equivalents. The diol component comprises CHDM and an additional
diol component such as PCTG for enhancing the clarity of the blend. Typical diol
components for condensation reactions include aliphatic diols, such as alkylene diols
containing from 2 to about 10 carbon atoms. The hexacarbocyclic dicarboxylic acids
which are condensed with the cyclohexanedimethanol and the alkylene diol, such as
ethylenen diol, is terephthalic acids.</p><p num="0036">Polycarbonate resins useful in preparing the blends of the present invention are
generally aromatic polycarbonate resins.</p><p num="0037">Typically these are prepared by reacting a dihydric phenol with a carbonate precursor,
such as phosgene, a haloformate or a carbonate ester. Generally speaking, such
carbonate polymers may be typified as possessing recurring structural units of the
formula IIIA: -O-Ar-O-(CO)-, wherein Ar is a divalent aromatic radical of derived
from dihydric phenol employed in the polymer producing reaction. </p><p num="0038">Preferably, the carbonate polymers used to provide the resinous mixtures of the
invention have an intrinsic viscosity (as measured in methylene chloride at 25° C.)
ranging from about 0.30 to about 1.00 dl/g.</p><p num="0039">The dihydric phenol which may be employed to provide such aromatic carbonate
polymers are mononuclear or polynuclear aromatic compounds, containing as
functional groups two hydroxy radicals, each of which is attached directly to a carbon
atom of an aromatic nucleus. Typical dihydric phenols are: 2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)
propane; hydroquinone; resorcinol; 2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl) pentane; 2,4'-(dihydroxydiphenyl)
methane; bis(2 hydroxyphenyl) methane; bis(4 -hydroxyphenyl)
methane; bis(4-hydroxy-5-nitrophenyl) methane; 1,1-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl) ethane;
3,3-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl) pentane; 2,2-dihydroxydiphenyl; 2,6-dihydroxynaphthalene;
bis(4-hydroxydiphenyl)sulfone; bis(3,5-diethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)sulfone; 2,2-bis(3,5-dimethyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propane;
2,4'-dihydroxydiphenyl sulfone; 5'-chloro-2,4'-dihydroxydiphenyl
sulfone; bis-(4hydroxyphenyl)diphenyl sulfone; 4,4'-dihydroxydiphenyl
ether; 4,4'-dihydroxy-3,3'-dichlorodiphenyl ether; and 4,4-dihydroxy-2,5-dihydroxydiphenyl
ether.</p><p num="0040">Other dihydric phenols which are also suitable for use in the preparation of the above
polycarbonates are disclosed in U.S. Pat Nos. 2,999,835; 3,038,365; 3,334,154; and
4,131,575.</p><p num="0041">These aromatic polycarbonates can be manufactured by known processes, such as, for
example and as mentioned above, by reacting a dihydric phenol with a carbonate
precursor, such as phosgene, in accordance with methods set forth in the above-cited
literature and in U.S. Pat. No. 4,123,436, or by transesterification processes such as
are disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 3,153,008, as well as other processes known to those
skilled in the art.</p><p num="0042">It is also possible to employ two or more different dihydric phenols or a copolymer of
a dihydric phenol with a glycol or with a hydroxy- or acid-terminated polyester or
with a dibasic acid in the event a carbonate copolymer or interpolymer rather than a 
homopolymer is desired for use in the preparation of the polycarbonate mixtures of
the invention. Branched polycarbonates are also useful, such as are described in U.S.</p><p num="0043">Pat. No. 4,001,184. Also, there can be utilized blends of linear polycarbonate and a
branched polycarbonate. Moreover, blends of any of the above materials may be
employed in the practice of this invention to provide the aromatic polycarbonate.</p><p num="0044">The preferred aromatic carbonate for use in the practice in the present invention is a
homopolymer, e.g., a homopolymer derived from 2,2-bis(4-hydroxyphenyl)propane
(bisphenol-A), commercially available under the trade designation LEXAN Registered
TM from General Electric Company.</p><p num="0045">Additionally, additives such as antioxidants, thermal stabilizers, mold release agents,
antistatic agents, whitening agents, colorants, plasticizers, minerals such as talc, clay,
mica, barite, wollastonite and other stabilizers including but not limited to UV
stabilizers, such as benzotriazole, supplemental reinforcing fillers such as flaked or
milled glass, and the like, flame retardants, pigments, additional resins or
combinations thereof may be added to the compositions of the present invention. The
different additives that can be incorporated in the compositions are commonly used
and known to one skilled in the art. Illustrative descriptions of such additives may be
found in R. Gachter and H. Muller, Plastics Additives Handbook, 4th edition, 1993.</p><p num="0046">Examples of thermal stabilizers include triphenyl phosphite, tris-(2,6-dimethylphenyl)phosphite,
tris-(2,4-di-t-butyl-phenyl) phosphite, tris-(mixed mono-
and di-nonylphenyl)phosphite, dimethylbenzene phosphonate and trimethyl
phosphate. Examples of antioxidants include octadecyl-3-(3,5-di-tert-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propionate,
and pentaerythrityl-tetrakis[3-(3,5-di-tert-butyl-4-hydroxyphenyl)propionate].
Examples of light stabilizers include 2-(2-hydroxy-5-methylphenyl)benzotriazole,
2-(2-hydroxy-5-tert-octylphenyl)-benzotriazole and 2-hydroxy-4-n-octoxy
benzophenone. Examples of plasticizers include dioctyl-4,5-epoxy-hexahydrophthalate,
tris-(octoxycarbonylethyl)isocyanurate, tristearin and
epoxidized soybean oil. Examples of the antistatic agents include glycerol
monostearate, sodium stearyl sulfonate, and sodium dodecylbenzenesulfonate. </p><p num="0047">A preferred class of stabilizers including quenchers are those which provide a
transparent/translucent and colorless product. Typically, such stabilizers are used at a
level of 0.001-10 weight percent and preferably at a level of from 0.005-2 weight
percent. The favored stabilizers include an effective amount of an acidic phosphate
salt; an acid, alkyl, aryl or mixed phosphite having at least one acidic hydrogen; a
Group IB or Group IIB metal phosphate salt; a phosphorus oxo acid, a metal acid
pyrophosphate or a mixture thereof. The suitability of a particular compound for use
as a stabilizer and the determination of how much is to be used as a stabilizer may be
readily determined by preparing a mixture of the polyester resin component and the
polycarbonate and determining the effect on melt viscosity, gas generation or color
stability or the formation of interpolymer. The acidic phosphate salts include sodium
dihydrogen phosphate, mono zinc phosphate, potassium hydrogen phosphate, calcium
dihydrogen phosphate and the like. The phosphites may be of the formula V:
<img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="38" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="20"/>
where R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup> and R<sup>3</sup> are independently selected from the group consisting of
hydrogen, alkyl and aryl with the proviso that at least one of R<sup>1</sup>, R<sup>2</sup> and R<sup>3</sup> is
hydrogen.</p><p num="0048">The phosphate salts of a Group IB or Group IIB metal include zinc phosphate and the
like. The phosphorus oxo acids include phosphorous acid, phosphoric acid,
polyphosphoric acid or hypophosphorous acid.</p><p num="0049">The polyacid pyrophosphates may be of the formula VI:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">MzxHyPnO3n+1</st32:che>
wherein M is a metal, x is a number ranging from 1 to 12 and y is a number ranging
from 1 to 12, n is a number from 2 to 10, z is a number from 1 to 5 and the sum of
(xz) + y is equal to n + 2. The preferred M is an alkaline or alkaline earth metal. </p><p num="0050">The most preferred quenchers are oxo acids of phosphorus or acidic organo
phosphorus compounds. Inorganic acidic phosphorus compounds may also be used as
quenchers, however they may result in haze or loss of clarity. Most preferred
quenchers are phosphoric acid, phosphorous acid or their partial esters.</p><p num="0051">Examples of mold releasing agents include pentaerythritol tetrastearate, stearyl
stearate, beeswax, montan wax, and paraffin wax. Examples of other resins include
but are not limited to polypropylene, polystyrene, polymethyl methacrylate, and
polyphenylene oxide. Combinations of any of the foregoing additives may be used.
Such additives may be mixed at a suitable time during the mixing of the components
for forming the composition.</p><p num="0052">The production of the compositions may utilize any of the blending operations known
for the blending of thermoplastics, for example blending in a kneading machine such
as a Banbury mixer or an extruder. The sequence of addition is not critical but all
components should be thoroughly blended.</p><p num="0053">To prepare the resin composition, the components may be mixed by any known
methods. Typically, there are two distinct mixing steps: a premixing step and a melt
mixing step. In the premixing step, the dry ingredients are mixed together. The
premixing step is typically performed using a tumbler mixer or ribbon blender.
However, if desired, the premix may be manufactured using a high shear mixer such
as a Henschel mixer or similar high intensity device. The premixing step is typically
followed by a melt mixing step in which the premix is melted and mixed again as a
melt. Alternatively, the premixing step may be omitted, and raw materials may be
added directly into the feed section of a melt mixing device, preferably via multiple
feeding systems. In the melt mixing step, the ingredients are typically melt kneaded in
a single screw or twin screw extruder, a Banbury mixer, a two roll mill, or similar
device.</p><p num="0054">The glass transition temperature of the preferred blend is from about 60°C to about
150°C, more preferably from 120°C to about 150°C. </p><p num="0055">The optical properties and impact resistance of the composition make it suitable for
use in building and construction industries, especially for use in a variety of glazing
applications, for example, roofs, greenhouses, sun rooms, swimming pool enclosures,
and the like.</p><p num="0056">The composition may be shaped into a final article by various techniques known in the
art such as injection molding, extrusion, gas assist blow molding, or vacuum forming.</p><p num="0057">A desirable form is an extruded sheet, including solid sheets, multi-wall sheets, and
profiled sheets. There is no particular limitation on the composition of additional
layers used to form coextruded sheets. There is no particular limitation on the
structure or geometry of the multi-wall sheets. The additional layers may comprise,
for example, fluorescing agents to facilitate manufacturing and/or ultraviolet light
absorbers to improve weatherability. The extruded solid sheets typically have a
weight from about 0.5 to about 15 kilograms per square meter, and typically have a
thickness from about 0.5 mm to about 15 mm, preferably from about 1 mm to about
12 mm. The extruded multi-wall sheets typically have a weight from about 0.5 to
about 8 kilograms, and typically have a thickness of about 2 to about 50 mm,
preferable from about 4 to about 40 mm.</p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0058">The following examples employed the materials listed in Table 1 according to the
formulations listed in Tables 2 - 4. All amounts are weight percents based on the
total weight of the composition unless otherwise indicated. All ingredients were
mixed in a ribbon blender and extruded on a Werner-Pleiderer twin screw extruder at
260°C to form pellets. The pellets were then fed into an injection moulding machine
to mould discs-test bars. From the tables and FIG. 1, the three component blend of
PC, PCCD, PCTA gives a large compositional space having the desired properties.
As shown in FIG. 1, when the third component is PCT, there is no clear blend shown
on the three component diagram that has the desired properties. As shown in FIG. 1,
when the diol component CHDM additional includes the diol EG, the compositional
space having the desired properties is reduced. </p><heading><u style="single">TABLE 2 TEST PROCEDURES</u></heading><p num="0059">Optical properties (transmission and haze are measured according ASTM D1003.</p><p num="0060">Yellowness index is determined according ASTM D1925 where 3.2 mm thick plaques
are measured on a Gardner XL-835 Colorimeter.</p><p num="0061">Impact values are measured on 4 mm thick bars according ISO 180/1A.</p><p num="0062">From the granulate, the melt volume rate (MVR) was measured according ISO 1133
(265°C/2.16kg, unless otherwise stated) in units of cm <sup>3</sup>/10 min.</p><p num="0063">Vicat B120 temperatures are measured on 4 mm thick bars according ISO 306.</p><p num="0064">Tensile Properties: The testing procedure follows the ISO 527 standard. The test is
carried out on a Zwick 1474 (+HASY). This machine is equipped with an automatic
handling system. Tensile bars of type MPTS (ISO 3167) with the following
dimensions were used: width of 10 mm and thickness of 4 mm.</p><p num="0065">Chemical Resistance: Chemical resistance against 4 different chemicals: 1) Fuel C,
composition: 42.5% Toluene, 42.5% Iso-octane, 15.0% MeOH; 2)Alcohol; 3) Acetic
acid (0.75vol% in water); and 4) Caustic soda (1.0wt% in water). The test is carried
out according to ISO 4599. The following test conditions are used: Duration of the
test: 15 min; Test temperature: 23°C; Applied constant strain: 0.5%; The method of
contact: complete soak. After the test the tensile bars were inspected visually on
change in appearance according to the following classification: 1) No visual change;
2) Dull surface; 3) Little cracks or crazes; 4) Large cracks; 5) Break of testing bar.
After the visual inspection the tensile test procedure according to the ISO 527
standard was performed to determine the physical properties. Notched Izod: This test
procedure is based on the ASTM D256 method. In this case, using Izod Method E, the
unnotched impact strength is obtained by testing an unnotched specimen. The results
of the test is reported in terms of energy absorbed per unit of specimen width, and
expressed in foot times pounds per inch (Ft.Lbs./In.). Typically the final test result is
calculated as the average of test results of five test bars. </p><p num="0066">Dynatup impact test: This test procedure is based on the ASTM D3763 method. This
procedure provides information on how a material behaves under multiaxial
deformation conditions. The deformation applied is a high speed puncture. An
example of a supplier of this type of testing equipment is Dynatup. Reported as the
test result is the so-called total energy absorbed (TE), which is expressed in foot
pounds (Ft.Lbs.). The final test result is calculated as the average of the test results of
typically ten test plaques.</p><p num="0067">Melt viscosity: This test procedure is based on the ASTM D1238 method. The
equipment used is an extrusion plastometer equipped with an automatic timer. A
typical example of this equipment would be the Tinius Olson MP 987. Before testing,
the samples are dried for one hour at 150°C. The testing conditions are a melt
temperature of 266°C, a total load of 5,000 gram, an orifice diameter of 0.0825 inch,
and a dwell time of 5 minutes. The test result is expressed in the unit Poise.</p><p num="0068">Flexural Modulus: This test procedure is based on the ASTM D790 method. Typical
test bars have the following dimensions: 1/8 inch times 1/2 inch times 2-1/2 inch. The
final test result is calculated as the average of test results of five test bars. The test
involves a three point loading system utilizing center loading on a simply supported
beam.</p><p num="0069">Instron and Zwick are typical examples of manufacturers of instruments designed to
perform this type of test. The flexural modulus is the ratio, within the elastic limit, of
stress to corresponding strain and is expressed in pounds per square inch (psi).</p><p num="0070">Tensile Strength: This test procedure is based on the ASTM D638 method. Test bars
in the form of the standard dumbbell shape are used in this test method. The final test
result is calculated as the average of the test results of five test bars. The tensile
strength is calculated by dividing the maximum load observed in the test by the
original minimum cross-sectional area of the test specimen. The result is expressed in
pounds per square inch (psi). Instron and Zwick are typical examples of manufacturers
of instruments designed to perform this type of test. </p><p num="0071">Tensile Elongation: The ability of a material to resist breaking under tensile stress is
based upon ASTM D638. Samples are generally injection molded. The tensile testing
machine pulls the sample from both ends and measures the force required to pull the
specimen apart and how much the sample stretches before breaking. The ultimate
elongation of a plastic is the percentage increase in length that occurs before it breaks
under tension. <img id="img-00180001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00180001.tif" inline="no" he="195"/><img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="78" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="204"/><img id="img-00200001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00200001.tif" inline="no" he="202"/><img id="img-00210001" orientation="unknown" wi="75" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00210001.tif" inline="no" he="204"/><tables><table><tgroup cols="11"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Formulations [%]</entry><entry align="center"/><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">-43</entry><entry align="center">-44</entry><entry align="center">-45</entry><entry align="center">-46</entry><entry align="center">-47</entry><entry align="center">-48</entry><entry align="center">-49</entry><entry align="center">-50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PC</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">59.67%</entry><entry align="left">49.73%</entry><entry align="left">69.62%</entry><entry align="left">59.67%</entry><entry align="left">49,73%</entry><entry align="left">69.62%</entry><entry align="left">59.67%</entry><entry align="left">49.73%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PCCD</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">X28731X2874</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PCTA</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Eastar A150</entry><entry align="right" namest="4"/><entry align="right" namest="5"/><entry align="right" namest="6"/><entry align="right" namest="7"/><entry align="right" namest="8"/><entry align="left" namest="9">29.84%</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">39.78%</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">49.73%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PCT</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Ektar 13787</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PCTG</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Eastar 5445</entry><entry align="right" namest="4"/><entry align="right" namest="5"/><entry align="left" namest="6">29.84%</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">39.78%</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">49.73%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PETG</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Eastar 6763</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">39.78%</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">49.73%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MZP</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PEPQ</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Ph 168</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">020%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Irg 1076</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">020%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry><entry align="left">020%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry><entry align="left">0.20%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">H3PO3</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">0.15%</entry><entry align="left">0.15%</entry><entry align="left">0.15%</entry><entry align="left">0.15%</entry><entry align="left">0.15%</entry><entry align="left">0.15%</entry><entry align="left">015%</entry><entry align="left">0.15%</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Polyester / Polyester+PC</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">Total</entry><entry align="left">100.00%</entry><entry align="left">100.00%</entry><entry align="left">100.00%</entry><entry align="left">100.00%</entry><entry align="left">100.00%</entry><entry align="left">100.00%</entry><entry align="left">100.00%</entry><entry align="left">100.00%</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Test Results:</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Initial Color</entry><entry align="left">Standaard</entry><entry align="left">L</entry><entry align="left">57.85</entry><entry align="left">58.62</entry><entry align="left">42.36</entry><entry align="left">42.36</entry><entry align="left">41.38</entry><entry align="left">42.04</entry><entry align="left">42.15</entry><entry align="left">41.81</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Transmission</entry><entry align="left">(Engel 1)</entry><entry align="left">A</entry><entry align="left">-1.76</entry><entry align="left">-1.76</entry> <entry align="left">0.26</entry><entry align="left">0.23</entry><entry align="left">0.24</entry><entry align="left">0.24</entry><entry align="left">0.26</entry> <entry align="left">0.27</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">(if opaque)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">B</entry><entry align="left">-0.03</entry><entry align="left">-0.03</entry><entry align="left">-026</entry><entry align="left">-0,37</entry><entry align="left">0.15</entry><entry align="left">0.1</entry><entry align="left">-0.06</entry><entry align="left">0.18</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Initial Color</entry><entry align="left">Standaard</entry><entry align="left">L</entry><entry align="left">82.57</entry><entry align="left">83.34</entry><entry align="left">96.87</entry><entry align="left">97</entry><entry align="left">94.22</entry><entry align="left">8913</entry><entry align="left">80.64</entry><entry align="left">80.89</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Reflection</entry><entry align="left">(Engel 1)</entry><entry align="left">A</entry><entry align="left">1.57</entry><entry align="left">1.46</entry><entry align="left">0.27</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.44</entry><entry align="left">0.36</entry><entry align="left">0.34</entry><entry align="left">0.36</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(if transparent)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">B</entry><entry align="left">4.48</entry><entry align="left">3.94</entry><entry align="left">0.86</entry><entry align="left">0.76</entry><entry align="left">2.54</entry><entry align="left">1 95</entry><entry align="left">1.56</entry><entry align="left">1.95</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Transmission in %</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">T</entry><entry align="left">60.6</entry><entry align="left">60</entry><entry align="left">88.9</entry><entry align="left">893</entry><entry align="left">83</entry><entry align="left">86.7</entry><entry align="left">88.4</entry><entry align="left">87.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">"haze"</entry><entry align="left">47.1</entry><entry align="left">65.9</entry><entry align="left">3.23</entry><entry align="left">2.41</entry><entry align="left">9.56</entry><entry align="left">5.88</entry><entry align="left">4.43</entry><entry align="left">4.54</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Initial Gloss</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">20 deg</entry><entry align="left">117.7</entry><entry align="left">96.4</entry><entry align="left">178.2</entry><entry align="left">179.3</entry><entry align="left">150.9</entry><entry align="left">170.8</entry><entry align="left">171</entry><entry align="left">163.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">60 deg</entry><entry align="left">114.3</entry><entry align="left">108.5</entry><entry align="left">148.1</entry><entry align="left">159.2</entry><entry align="left">143</entry><entry align="left">155.4</entry><entry align="left">162.4</entry><entry align="left">149.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MVR (ml/10')</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">250°C /5 kg</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">26.6</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">43.1</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">14.2</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">16.7</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">21.7</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">12.5</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">13.0</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">13.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">265°C /2.16 kg</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">265°C / 5 kg</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Vicat B120</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">°C</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">114.1</entry><entry align="left"  namest="5">101.2</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">121.8</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">114.8</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">107.9</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">123.3</entry><entry align="left"  namest="10">117.3</entry><entry align="left"  namest="11">111.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">HDT Ae 1.80</entry><entry align="left">°C</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">97.7</entry><entry align="left">84.5</entry><entry align="left">102.1</entry><entry align="left">95.7</entry><entry align="left">90.3</entry><entry align="left">105.2</entry><entry align="left">99</entry><entry align="left">929</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tensile</entry><entry nameend="3"  align="left" namest="2">modulus (Mpa)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">2390</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">2150</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">2071</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">2412</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">2254</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">2214</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">2218</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">2272</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">yield strength (Mpa)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">64.2</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">59.8</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">57.8</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">71.6</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">68.4</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">67.5</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">62.3</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">62.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">yield at break (Mpa)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">64.2</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">61.1</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">58.1</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">71.6</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">68.4</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">68.1</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">62.3</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">62.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">elong at break (%)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">91.7</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">133.5</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">134.5</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">97</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">113.4</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">117.4</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">124.2</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">122.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Notched Izod</entry><entry align="left">23°C</entry><entry align="left">gem</entry><entry align="left">8.4</entry><entry align="left">7.4</entry><entry align="left">10.5</entry><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="left">5.9</entry><entry align="left">11.2</entry><entry align="left">10.9</entry><entry align="left">10</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Impact</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">sd</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry><entry align="left">0.5</entry><entry align="left">03</entry><entry align="left">3.6</entry><entry align="left">3.7</entry><entry align="left">0.5</entry><entry align="left">0.2</entry><entry align="left">0.4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flexplate</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Maximum Force (N)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">8469</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">6497</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">9065</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">8842</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">8575</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">9292</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">9275</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">9184</entry></row><row><entry align="left">23°C</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Energy at Max. (J)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">78.6</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">57</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">88.9</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">84.2</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">80.3</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">107</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">98.7</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">104.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Energy at break (J)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">121.1</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">83.2</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">1272</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">125.2</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">127.6</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">128.4</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">131.3</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">138</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Deflection at Break (mm)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">221</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">17.9</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">22</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">22.1</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">22.8</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">22.2</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">22.7</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">23.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flexplate</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Maximum Force (N)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">-20°C</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Energy at Max (J)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Energy at break (J)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Defection at Break (mm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Failure mode</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fuel C</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Classification (1-5)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">5</entry><entry align="right" namest="5"/><entry align="left" namest="6">5</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">5</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">5</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">5</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">5</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">3*4 1*5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   Strain 0.5%</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">modulus (Mpa)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">1932</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">yield strength (Mpa)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">yield at break (Mpa)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">14.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">elong at break (%)</entry><entry align="left" namest="4">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="5">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="6">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="7">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="8">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="9">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="10">-----</entry><entry align="left" namest="11">0.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alcohol</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Classification (1.5)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   Strain 0.5%</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">modulus (Mpa)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">yield strength (Mpa)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">yield at break (Mpa)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">elong at break (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Acetic Acid</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Classification (1 - 5)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">0.75vol% in water</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">modulus (Mpa)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">yield strength (Mpa)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   Strain 0.5%</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">yield at break (Mpa)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">elong at break (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Caustic Soda</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">Classification (1 - 5)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1.0 wt% in water</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">modulus (Mpa)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">yield strength (Mpa)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   Strain 0.5%</entry><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">yield at break (Mpa)</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry nameend="3" align="left" namest="2">elong at break (%)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A clear thermoplastic blend comprising a first polycarbonate resin component;
a second resin blend component of a first polyester copolymer resin derived from a
cycloaliphatic diol or equivalent thereof and a cycloaliphatic dicarboxylic acid or
equivalent thereof, and a third resin component of a second polyester polymer resin
derived from the condensation of a cyclohexane diol or equivalents thereof with a
terephthalic acid or equivalents thereof and an additional condensation reaction
component selected from aliphatic or aromatic diacids or diols suitable for enhancing
the clarity of said blend wherein the three components are present in proportions for to
form a clear blend having a transmission of seventy percent or greater and an
elongation at break after exposure to Fuel C of forty percent or greater.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A clear thermoplastic blend according to claim 1 comprising a clear blend
portion having enhanced chemical resistance as compared to a two component blend
of only said first and second blend components.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A clear thermoplastic blend according to claim 1 or claim 2 comprising
consisting of the three resin components consisting essentially of a first resin
component of about 35 to about 65 weight percent of a polycarbonate resin based on
the total weight of the three blend components; a second resin blend component of
about 33 to about 65 weight percent of the three component blend and consisting of a
first polyester resin derived from a cycloaliphatic diol or equivalent thereof and a
cycloaliphatic dicarboxylic acid or equivalent thereof, and about 2 to about 35 weight
percent of the three component blend comprising a third resin component comprising
said second polyester resin component.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A clear thermoplastic blend according to claim 3 wherein said third
component consists essentially of the condensation reaction of a mixture 1,4-cylohexanedimethanol
or equivalents and a terephthalic acid or equivalent, and
isophthalic acid or equivalents wherein said isophthalic acid or equivalent is present in
said mixture in an amount for enhancing the clarity of the three component blend.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A clear thermoplastic blend according to claim 3 wherein said third
component consists essentially of the condensation reaction of a mixture of 1,4-cylohexanedimethanol
or equivalents and a ethylene glycol with terephthalic acid or
equivalents wherein said ethylene glycol is present in said mixture in an amount for
enhancing the clarity of the three component blend.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A clear thermoplastic blend according to claim 3 comprising wherein said
third resin component consists essentially of PCTA, and said three component blend
comprises from about 35 to 45 wt% PC; from about 33 to 43 wt% PCCD; from about
20 to 35 wt% PCTA.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A clear thermoplastic blend according to any preceding claim wherein said
polycarbonate resin is an aromatic polycarbonate resin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A clear thermoplastic blend according to any preceding claim comprising
additional ingredients selected from the group consisting of antioxidants, thermal
stabilizers, mold release agents, antistatic agents, whitening agents, colorants,
plasticizers, and reinforcing materials and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A clear thermoplastic blend according to claim 8 wherein said stabilizer
includes an effective amount of an acidic phosphate salt; an acid, alkyl, aryl or mixed
phosphite having at least one acidic hydrogen; a Group IB or Group IIB metal
phosphate salt; a phosphorus oxo acid, a metal acid pyrophosphate or a mixture
thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A clear thermoplastic blend according to any preceding claim wherein said
blend is formed into an article by molding or extrusion.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>