<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1354936-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1354936" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="28679007" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20031022"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1354936-A1" status="new" fvid="23860830"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1354936</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20031022</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03009044-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03009044</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030417</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002114307-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002114307</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020417</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002116172-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002116172</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020418</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002116181-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002116181</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020418</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002228216-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002228216</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020806</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/29        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/72        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/72        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/37        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/37        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   1/14B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   1/14D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   1/22</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   1/29</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   1/72</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/37C6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/37C9</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/37E</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Polymer enthaltendes Waschmittel</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Polymer compounded detergent composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition detergente comprenant de polymère</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0754712-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0754712</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0942015-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0942015</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998023712-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998023712</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999019444-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999019444</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NIPPON CATALYTIC CHEM IND</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NIPPON SHOKUBAI CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NIPPON SHOKUBAI CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>4-1-1 Koraibashi</street><city>Chuo-ku, Osaka-shi, Osaka</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>FUJII YOSHIKAZU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>SAEKI TAKUYA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TSUMORI TAKAHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YAMAGUCHI SHIGERU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>FUJII, YOSHIKAZU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SAEKI, TAKUYA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TSUMORI, TAKAHIRO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YAMAGUCHI, SHIGERU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>FUJII, YOSHIKAZU</last-name><address><street>Nippon Shokubai Co.Ltd., 5-8, Nishiotabi-cho</street><city>Suita-shi, Osaka</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Saeki, Takuya, Nippon Shokubai Co.Ltd.</last-name><address><street>2-2, Uchisaiwai-cho 1-chome, Chiyoda ku</street><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TSUMORI, TAKAHIRO</last-name><address><street>Nippon Shokubai Co.Ltd., 5-8, Nishiotabi-cho</street><city>Suita-shi, Osaka</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>YAMAGUCHI, SHIGERU</last-name><address><street>Nippon Shokubai Co.Ltd., 5-8, Nishiotabi-cho</street><city>Suita-shi, Osaka</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Grünecker, Kinkeldey, Stockmair &amp;amp; Schwanhäusser Anwaltssozietät</last-name><address><street>Maximilianstrasse 58</street><city>80538 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A detergent composition containing at least 0.1 % by weight of at least one
polymer selected from the group consisting of 1) a polycarboxylic acid-based polymer
containing a polyalkylene glycol chain in the structure thereof, 2) a sulfonic acid
group-terminated (meth)acrylic acid-based polymer, and 3) an acrylic acid (salt)-maleic
acid (salt)-based copolymer having a clay dispersibility under a condition of 50 ppm of
calcium carbonate of 0.3 or more; and at least 0.5 % by weight of a longer alkyl chain
mid-chain branched surfactant compound. The detergent composition can enhance
anti-gelling properties to calcium ions, improve the dispersibility to solid particles at low
temperatures or under high-hardness conditions, and improve detergency against stains
such as mud and carbon black.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a detergent composition comprising a specific
polymer and an alkyl mid-chain branched surfactant. For this reason, the detergent
composition according to the invention is useful in laundry and cleaning compositions,
especially granular and liquid detergent compositions. These detergent compositions
have high detergency against stains such as mud and carbon black, enhance anti-gelling
properties to calcium ions, etc., and enhance detergency at low temperatures or under
high-hardness conditions.</p><heading><b>DESCRIPTION OF THE RELATED ART</b></heading><p num="0002">In the past, for the purpose of enhancing the detergency, there have been
proposed various detergent compositions. In powder detergents, there are proposed
detergent compositions having an improved solubility, as described in, for example,
JP-A-2000-345198 and JP-A-2000-186298. However, these detergent compositions
were not satisfactory in the solubility of detergent at low temperatures or detergency
under high-hardness conditions. Further, JP-T-11-507956 and JP-T-2001-506679 (the
term "JP-T" as used herein means a published Japanese translation of a PCT patent
application") propose surfactant enhancing the solubility at low temperature and the
detergency under high-hardness conditions as well as detergent compositions containing
such a surfactant. However, according to the conventional polycarboxylic acid-based
polymers that are used in these detergent compositions, a satisfactory performance was
not obtained.</p><p num="0003">Similar to the powder detergents, in liquid detergents, according to detergent
compositions using the foregoing surfactant, sufficient detergency could not be achieved 
because it is difficult to incorporate the polycarboxylic acid-based polymer.</p><p num="0004">JP-T-2001-511473 discloses alkoxylated polycarboxylates. However, the
number of ethoxy side chains (m) is from 2 to 3, and sufficient dispersibility could not be
achieved.</p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0005">An object of the invention is to provide a detergent composition that can enhance
anti-gelling properties to calcium ions, improve dispersibility to solid particles at low
temperatures or under high-hardness conditions, and improve detergency against stains
such as mud and carbon black.</p><p num="0006">In order to achieve the above object, the present inventors made extensive and
intensive investigations about an enhancement of the detergency of the detergent
composition. As a result, it has been found that when a specific polymer having good
dispersibility of solid particles, good anti-gelling properties to calcium ions, etc., and
good clay dispersibility and a mid-chain branched surfactant are formulated, the
detergency against stains such as mud and carbon black are high and that the detergency
are not lowered even at low temperatures or under high-hardness conditions, leading to
accomplishment of the invention.</p><p num="0007">Specifically, the object of the invention is achieved the following detergent
composition.</p><p num="0008">A detergent composition comprises:
<sl><li>at least 0.1 % by weight of at least one polymer selected from the group
consisting of 1) a polycarboxylic acid-based polymer containing a polyalkylene glycol
chain in the structure thereof, 2) a sulfonic acid group-terminated (meth)acrylic
acid-based polymer, and 3) an acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based copolymer
having a clay dispersibility under a condition of 50 ppm of calcium carbonate of 0.3 or 
more, and</li><li>at least 0.5 % by weight of a longer alkyl chain mid-chain branched surfactant
compound represented by the following formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">R-X-Y</st32:che></li></sl>
wherein:
<sl><li>(a) R is a hydrophobic C9 to C22, as total carbons in the moiety, preferably from
C12 to C18, mid-chain branched alkyl moiety having: (1) a longest linear carbon chain
attached to the -X-Y moiety in the range of from 8 to 21 carbon atoms; (2) one or more
C<sub>1</sub> - C<sub>3</sub> alkyl moieties branching from this longest linear carbon chain; (3) at least one of
the branching alkyl moieties is attached directly to a carbon of the longest linear carbon
chain at a position within the range of position 2 carbon (counting from carbon #1 which
is attached to the -X-Y moiety) to position ω - 2 carbon (the terminal carbon minus 2
carbons); and (4) the surfactant composition has an average total number of carbon
atoms in the R-X moiety in the above formula within the range of greater than 14 to 18,
preferably from 15 to 17;</li><li>(b) Y is a hydrophilic moiety selected from sulfates, sulfonates, amine oxides,
and polyoxyalkylenes; and</li><li>(c) X is selected from -CH<sub>2</sub>- and -C(O) -.</li></sl></p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0009">The embodiments for carrying out the invention will be described in detail
below.</p><p num="0010">All percentages, ratios and proportions herein are by weight, unless otherwise
specified. All temperatures are in degrees Celsius (°C) unless otherwise specified. All
documents cited are in relevant part, incorporated herein by reference.</p><heading><u style="single">Polycarboxylic acid-based polymers</u></heading><p num="0011">Preferred examples of the polycarboxylic acid-based polymers containing a
polyalkylene glycol chain in the structure thereof are as follows.
<sl><li>(1) Water-soluble graft polymers comprising a polyalkylene glycol having a
monoethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid-based monomer graft polymerized
thereon:
<sl><li>Examples include water-soluble graft polymers in which a monoethylenically
unsaturated monomer component essentially containing a monoethylenically
unsaturated carboxylic acid-based monomer is graft polymerized on a polyether
compound or a polyalkylene oxide substantially in the absence of a solvent, as described
in JP-A-7-53645, JP-A-8-208769, JP-A-8-208770, and Japanese Patent Application No.
2002-061091.</li><li>The repeating number of the polyalkylene glycol is preferably from 3 to 100,
more preferably from 4 to 50, and particularly preferably from 5 to 30.</li><li>These water-soluble graft polymers have better dispersibility of mud and carbon
black and have good compatibility with liquid detergents, etc.</li></sl></li><li>(2) Water-soluble polymers comprising a polyalkylene glycol-containing ethylenically
unsaturated monomer (not containing an ester bond between the polyalkylene glycol
chain and the ethylenically unsaturated bond) having a monoethylenically unsaturated
carboxylic acid-based monomer copolymerized therewith:
<sl><li>Examples include copolymers of an unsaturated alcohol-based monomer and a
monoethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid-based monomer, as described in
JP-A-56-81320, JP-A-58-47099, JP-A-58-149911, JP-A-58-147413, JP-A-58-147412,
JP-A-62-68806, JP-A-62-86098, and Japanese Patent Application No. 2000-253003.
Examples of the unsaturated alcohol-based monomer include compounds comprising a
polyalkylene glycol monoallyl ether or an unsaturated alcohol (such as 
3-methyl-3-buten-1-ol) having one or more alkylene oxides added thereto.</li><li>The repeating number of the polyalkylene glycol is preferably from 1 to 200,
more preferably from 3 to 100, and particularly preferably from 5 to 50.</li><li>Since the chain backbone is not bound to the polyalkylene glycol via the ester
bond, the stability of the polymer is good, and the dispersibility of mud and carbon black
is better.</li></sl></li><li>(3) Water-soluble polymers comprising a polyalkylene glycol-containing ethylenically
unsaturated monomer (containing an ester bond between the polyalkylene glycol chain
and the ethylenically unsaturated bond) having a monoethylenically unsaturated
carboxylic acid-based monomer copolymerized therewith:
<sl><li>Examples include copolymers of a polyalkylene glycol ester of a
monoethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid-based monomer (such as polyalkylene
glycol monoacrylates or monomethacrylates) and a monoethylenically unsaturated
carboxylic acid-based monomer.</li><li>The repeating number of the polyalkylene glycol is preferably 5 or more, more
preferably 10 or more, and particularly preferably 15 or more.</li><li>The molecular weight of the polycarboxylic acid-based polymer containing a
polyalkylene glycol chain in the structure thereof is preferably from 1,000 to 200,000,
more preferably from 2,000 to 100,000, and particularly preferably from 3,000 to
80,000.</li><li>The weight ratio of the polyalkylene glycol chain of the polycarboxylic
acid-based polymer containing a polyalkylene glycol chain in the structure thereof to the
carboxylic acid-based monomer is preferably from 1:99 to 99:1, more preferably from
5:95 to 95:5, and particularly preferably from 10:90 to 90:10.</li></sl></li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">(Meth)acrylic acid-based polymers</u></heading><p num="0012">Preferred examples of the sulfonic acid group-terminated (meth)acrylic
acid-based polymer are as follows.
<sl><li>(1) Sulfonic acid group-terminated (meth)acrylic acid-based polymers comprising a
(meth)acrylic acid-based polymer having an anti-gelling capacity Q of less than 2.0:
<sl><li>Examples include polymers comprising from 50 to 100 mole % of (meth)acrylic
acid and from 0 to 50 mole % of a water-soluble monoethylenically unsaturated
monomer that is copolymerizable with (meth)acrylic acid, having a sulfonic acid group
at the terminals thereof and having an anti-gelling capacity Q, as defined by the
following equation, of less than 2.0, as described in JP-A-11-315115.</li></sl><st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Q = [(Degree of gelation) × 10<st32:sup pos="post">5</st32:sup>]/(Weight average molecular weight)</st32:df></li><li>(2) (Meth)acrylic acid-based polymers having an introduction amount of sulfur element,
S value of 35 or more:
<sl><li>Examples include (meth)acrylic acid-based polymers having an introduction
amount of sulfur element, S value, as defined by the following equation, of 35 or more,
as described in Japanese Patent Application No. 2001-307557.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">S = (S amount contained in the polymer)/(Total S amount) × 100</st32:df></li><li>The total S amount includes the S amount contained in the polymer and the S
amount of S-containing compounds derived from a residual initiator, etc.</li></sl>Preferably, the anti-gelling capacity Q, as defined by the following equation, is
less than 3.0.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Q = [(Degree of gelation) × 10<st32:sup pos="post">5</st32:sup>]/(Weight average molecular weight)</st32:df>Preferably, the iron ion concentration is from 0.01 ppm to 10 ppm.</li><li>(3) (Meth)acrylic acid-based polymers having an R value of from 1 to 15:
<sl><li>Examples include (meth)acrylic acid-based polymers having an R value, as
defined by the following equation, of from 1 to 15 in the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum, as 
described in Japanese Patent Application No. 2001-307757.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">R = (Integration ratio of signal at 2.3 to 4.3 ppm)/(Integration ratio at 0.8 to 4.3 ppm
containing PSA signal) × 100</st32:df></li><li>Preferably, the anti-gelling capacity Q, as defined by the following equation, is
less than 3.0.</li></sl><st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Q = [(Degree of gelation) × 10<st32:sup pos="post">5</st32:sup>]/(Weight average molecular weight)</st32:df>Preferably, the iron ion concentration is from 0.01 ppm to 10 ppm.</li><li>(4) Sulfonic acid group-terminated (meth)acrylic acid-based polymers produced by
using a sulfite and oxygen:
<sl><li>Examples include sulfonic acid group-terminated (meth)acrylic acid-based
polymers containing at least 0.1 % by weight of a polymer obtained by polymerization
using a sulfite and oxygen, as described in JP-A-56-55407.</li><li>As the sulfite, hydrogensulfites are preferable, and sodium hydrogensulfite is
more preferable.</li><li>As the supply method of oxygen, oxygen may be supplied singly, but preferably,
oxygen is supplied as air.</li><li>The polymerization may be carried out in a batch manner. In the case where the
production amount is large, the polymerization may be carried out in a continuous
manner.</li><li>The weight average molecular weight of the sulfonic acid group-terminated
(meth)acrylic acid-base polymer is preferably in the range of from 1,000 to 20,000, more
preferably from 2,000 to 15,000, and particularly preferably from 3,000 to 10,000.</li></sl></li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based copolymers</u></heading><p num="0013">The acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based copolymer used in the present
invention has a clay dispersibility under a condition of 50 ppm of calcium carbonate of 
0.3 or more, preferably 0.4 or more, more preferably 0.5 or more, and most preferably
0.6 or more.</p><p num="0014">The acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based copolymer further has a clay
dispersibility under a condition of 200 ppm of calcium carbonate of 0.2 or more,
preferably 0.3 or more, more preferably 0.4 or more, and most preferably 0.5 or more.</p><p num="0015">The acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based copolymer used in the present
invention also has a calcium ion-binding capacity of 250 mg/g or more, preferably 260
mg/g or more, more preferably 270 mg/g or more, and most preferably 280 mg/g or
more.</p><p num="0016">Preferred examples of the acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based copolymer
having a clay dispersibility under a condition of 50 ppm of calcium carbonate of 0.3 or
more are as follows.</p><p num="0017">The weight average molecular weight of the copolymer is from 2,500 to 30,000,
preferably from 3,000 to 20,000, more preferably from 3,500 to 15,000, particularly
preferably from 4,000 to 13,000, and most preferably from 4,500 to 12,000.</p><p num="0018">The composition (molar) ratio of acrylic acid to maleic acid of the copolymer is
from 99:1 to 40:60, preferably from 90:10 to 45:55, more preferably from 85:15 to 60:40,
particularly preferably from 80:20 to 65:35, and most preferably from 80:20 to 67:33.</p><p num="0019">In the combination of the weight average molecular weight and the composition
ratio of acrylic acid to maleic acid of the copolymer, the weight average molecular
weight is from 2,500 to 30,000, and the composition (molar) ratio is from 99:1 to 40:60;
preferably, the weight average molecular weight is from 3,000 to 20,000, and the
composition (molar) ratio is from 90:10 to 45:55; more preferably, the weight average
molecular weight is from 3,500 to 15,000, and the composition (molar) ratio is from
85:15 to 60:40; particularly preferably, the weight average molecular weight is from 
4,000 to 13,000, and the composition (molar) ratio is from 80:20 to 65:35; and most
preferably, the weight average molecular weight is from 4,500 to 12,000, and the
composition (molar) ratio is from 80:20 to 67:33.</p><p num="0020">Examples include acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based copolymers having
a magnesium ion-binding capacity of 210 mg Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>/g or more and a magnesium
hydroxide scale-inhibition capacity of 30 % or more, as described in JP-A-2000-143737.
Preferably, the clay-dispersibility in the presence of magnesium ions is 60 % or more;
and more preferably, the molecular weight distribution is 3.5 or less, and the amount of
low-molecular weight portions having a molecular weight of 1,000 or less is 9 % by
weight or less based on the total amount of the copolymer.</p><p num="0021">Incidentally, in the invention, the acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based
copolymer may be of a complete acid type, a partially neutralized salt, or a completely
neutralized salt. Preferred examples of the alkaline component used for the
neutralization include alkali metal hydroxides such as sodium hydroxide and potassium
hydroxide, alkaline earth metal hydroxides such as calcium hydroxide and magnesium
hydroxide, ammonia, and organic amines such as monoethanolamine, diethanolamine,
triethanolamine, and triethylamine; more preferably alkali metal hydroxides; and
particularly preferably sodium hydroxide. With respect to the neutralization method by
the alkaline component, partial neutralization or complete neutralization may be carried
out after completion of the polymerization; partial neutralization or complete
neutralization may be carried out during the polymerization; or previously partially
neutralized and/or completely neutralized monomers may be polymerized.</p><p num="0022">The polymerization may be carried out in a batch manner. In the case where the
production amount is large, the polymerization may be carried out in a continuous
manner. </p><p num="0023">Any of the polycarboxylic acid-based polymer containing a polyalkylene glycol
chain in the structure thereof, the sulfonic acid group-terminated (meth)acrylic
acid-based polymer, and the acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based copolymer
having a clay dispersibility under a condition of 50 ppm of calcium carbonate of 0.3 or
more is usually contained in an amount of 0.1 % by weight or more, preferably 0.5 % by
weight or more, more preferably 1.0 % by weight, and most preferably 3.0 % by weight
or more in the detergent composition.</p><heading><u style="single">Mid-chain branched surfactant</u></heading><p num="0024">In the formula, R-X-Y,
<sl><li>(a) R is a hydrophobic C9 to C22, as total carbons in the moiety, preferably from
C12 to C18, mid-chain branched alkyl moiety having: (1) a longest linear carbon chain
attached to the -X-Y moiety in the range of from 8 to 21 carbon atoms; (2) one or more
C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>3</sub> alkyl moieties branching from this longest linear carbon chain; (3) at least one of
the branching alkyl moieties is attached directly to a carbon of the longest linear carbon
chain at a position within the range of position 2 carbon (counting from carbon 1 which
is attached to the -X-Y moiety) to position ω - 2 carbon (the terminal carbon minus 2
carbons); and (4) the surfactant composition has an average total number of carbon
atoms in the R-X moiety in the above formula within the range of greater than 14 to 18,
preferably from 15 to 17;</li><li>(b) Y is a hydrophilic moiety selected from sulfates, sulfonates, amine oxides,
polyoxyalkylenes (preferably polyoxyethylene and polyoxypropylene), alkoxylated
sulfates, polyhydroxy moieties, phosphate esters, glycerol sulfonates, polygluconates,
polyphosphate esters, phosphonates, sulfosuccinates, sulfosuccaminates,
polyalkoxylated carboxylates, glucamides, taurinates, sarcosinates, glycinates,
isethionates, dialkanolamides, monoalkanolamides, monoalkalnolamide sulfates, 
diglycolamides, diglycolamide sulfates, glycerol esters, glycerol ester sulfates, glycerol
ethers, glycerol ether sulfates, polyglycerol ethers, polyglycerol ether sulfates, sorbitan
esters, polyalkoxylated sorbitan esters, ammonioalkanesulfonates, amidopropyl betains,
alkylated quats, alkylated/polyhydroxyalkylated quats, imidazolines, 2-yl-succinates,
sulfonated alkyl esters, and sulfonated fatty acids; and</li><li>(c) X is selected from -CH<sub>2</sub>- and -C(O)-.</li></sl></p><p num="0025">Preferred examples of the mid-chain branched surfactant are as follows.
<sl><li>(1) Mid-chain branched primary alkyl sulfate surfactants:
The detergent composition of the invention may contain one or two or more
mid-chain branched primary alkyl sulfate surfactants.The surfactant mixture of the invention contains a surfactant having a linear
primary alkyl sulfate chain backbone (i.e., the longest alkyl chain containing the sulfated
carbon atom). These alkyl chain backbones have from 12 to 19 carbon atoms. Further,
the molecule contains a branched primary alkyl moiety having at least 14, but not more
than 20, carbon atoms. In addition, the surfactant mixture has an average total number
of carbon atoms for the branched primary alkyl moiety within the range of from greater
than 14 to about 18. Thus, the mixture of the invention contains at least one branched
primary alkyl sulfate surfactant compound having a longest alkyl chain having from 12
or more carbon atoms or 19 or less carbon atoms, and the total number of carbon atoms
including branching must be at least 14, and further, the average total number of carbon
atoms for the branched primary alkyl chain is within the range of from greater than 14 to
about 18.The composition of the invention may contain a small amount of a linear,
non-branched primary alkyl sulfate. Further, this linear, non-branched primary alkyl
sulfate surfactant may be present as the result of the process used to manufacture the 
surfactant mixture having the requisite one or more mid-chain branched primary alkyl
sulfates according to the invention, or for the purpose of formulating the detergent
composition, a small amount of the linear, non-branched primary alkyl sulfate may be
admixed into the final product formulation.Further, the composition of the invention may contain a small amount of a
non-sulfated mid-chain branched alcohol. Such a material may be present as the result
of incomplete sulfation of the alcohol as used to prepare the alkyl sulfate surfactant, or
these alcohols may be separately added to the detergent composition of the invention
along with the mid-chain branched primary alkyl sulfate surfactant according to the
invention.The counter ion of the sulfate is hydrogen or a salt forming cation depending
upon the method of synthesis. Examples of the salt forming cation include lithium,
sodium, potassium, calcium, magnesium, quaternary alkylamines, and mixtures thereof.
Preferred cations are ammonium, sodium, potassium, mono-, di- and trialkanol
ammoniums, and mixtures thereof. Preferred alkanol ammonium salts of the invention
are mono-, di- and tri-quaternary ammonium compounds having an ethanolamine,
diethanolamine, or triethanolamine structure.Preferred counter ions of the sulfate are sodium, potassium, and the C2 alkanol
ammonium salts listed above, with sodium being most preferred.The preferred surfactant mixture of the invention has one or more branched
primary alkyl sulfates in an amount of at least 0.01 % by weight, more preferably at least
5 % by weight, and most preferably at least 20 % by weight of the mixture. The total
number of carbon atoms, including branching, is from 15 to 18. Further, in the case of
this surfactant mixture, the average total number of carbon atoms in the branched
primary alkyl moiety is within the range of from greater than 14 to about 18. Preferred mono-methyl branched primary alkyl sulfates are selected from the
group consisting of 3-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 4-methyl pentadecanol sulfate,
5-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 6-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 7-methyl pentadecanol
sulfate, 8-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 9-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 10-methyl
pentadecanol sulfate, 11-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 12-methyl pentadecanol sulfate,
13-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 3-methyl hexadecanol sulfate, 4-methyl hexadecanol
sulfate, 5-methyl hexadecanol sulfate, 6-methyl hexadecanol sulfate, 7-methyl hexadecanol
sulfate, 8-methyl hexadecanol sulfate, 9-methyl hexadecanol sulfate, 10-methyl
hexadecanol sulfate, 11-methyl hexadecanol sulfate, 12-methyl hexadecanol sulfate,
13-methyl hexadecanol sulfate, 14-methyl hexadecanol sulfate, and mixtures thereof.Preferred di-methyl branched primary alkyl sulfates are selected from the group
consisting of 2,3-methyl tetradecanol sulfate, 2,4-methyl tetradecanol sulfate,
2,5-methyl tetradecanol sulfate, 2,6-methyl tetradecanol sulfate, 2,7-methyl tetradecanol
sulfate, 2,8-methyl tetradecanol sulfate, 2,9-methyl tetradecanol sulfate, 2,10-methyl
tetradecanol sulfate, 2,11-methyl tetradecanol sulfate, 2,12-methyl tetradecanol sulfate,
2,3-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 2,4-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 2,5-methyl pentadecanol
sulfate, 2,6-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 2,7-methyl pentadecanol sulfate,
2,8-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 2,9-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 2,10-methyl pentadecanol
sulfate, 2,11-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, 2,12-methyl pentadecanol sulfate,
2,13-methyl pentadecanol sulfate, and mixtures thereof.The following branched primary alkyl sulfates having 16 carbon atoms and
having one branching unit are examples of preferred branched surfactants useful in the
composition of the invention.Examples include 5-methylpentadecyl sulfate, 6-methylpentadecyl sulfate,
7-methylpentadecyl sulfate, 8-methylpentadecyl sulfate, 9-methylpentadecyl sulfate, 
and 10-methylpentadecyl sulfate, wherein the counter ion is preferably sodium.The following branched primary alkyl sulfates having 17 carbon atoms and
having two branching units are examples of preferred branched surfactants according to
the invention.Examples include 2,5-dimethylpentadecyl sulfate, 2,6-dimethylpentadecyl
sulfate, 2,7-dimethylpentadecyl sulfate, 2,8-dimethylpentadecyl sulfate, 2,9-dimethylpentadecyl
sulfate, and 2,10-dimethylpentadecyl sulfate, wherein the counter ion is
preferably sodium.</li><li>(2) Mid-chain branched primary alkyl polyoxyalkylene surfactants:
The branched surfactant composition of the invention may contain one or two or
more mid-chain branched primary alkyl polyoxyalkylene surfactants.The surfactant mixture of the invention contains a linear primary
polyoxyalkylene chain backbone. These alkyl chain backbones have from 12 to 19
carbon atoms. Further, the molecule contains a branched primary alkyl moiety having at
least 14, but not more than 20, carbon atoms. In addition, the surfactant mixture has an
average total number of carbon atoms for the branched primary alkyl moiety within the
range of from greater than 14 to about 18. Thus, the mixture of the invention contains at
least one branched primary polyoxyalkylene surfactant compound having a longest alkyl
chain having from 12 or carbon atoms or 19 or less carbon atoms, and the total number
of carbon atoms including branching must be at least 14, and further the average total
number of carbon atoms for the branched primary alkyl chain is within the range of from
greater than 14 to about 18.For example, a C16 total carbon (in the alkyl chain) primary polyoxyalkylene
surfactant having 15 carbon atoms in the backbone must have a methyl branching unit,
whereby the total number of carbon atoms in the molecule is 16. The composition of the invention may contain a small amount of a linear,
non-branched primary polyoxyalkylene. Further, this linear, non-branched primary
polyoxyalkylene surfactant may be present as the result of the process used to
manufacture the surfactant mixture having the requisite one or more mid-chain branched
primary polyoxyalkylenes according to the invention, or for the purpose of formulating
the detergent composition, a small amount of the linear, non-branched primary
polyoxyalkylene may be admixed into the final product formulation.Further, the composition of the invention may contain a small amount of a
non-alkoxylated mid-chain branched alcohol. Such a material may be present as the
result of incomplete alkoxylation of the alcohol as used to prepare the polyoxyalkylene
surfactant, or these alcohols may be separately added to the detergent composition of the
invention along with the mid-chain branched primary polyoxyalkylene surfactant
according to the invention.The polyoxyalkylene (EO/PO) is an alkoxy moiety, selected from ethoxy,
propoxy, and mixed ethoxy/propoxy groups, and most preferably ethoxy, wherein the
repeating number (m) of the oxyalkylene is at least about 1, preferably within the range
of from about 3 to about 30, more preferably from about 5 to about 20, and most
preferably from about 5 to about 15. The EO/PO may be a distribution with an average
degree of alkoxylation (e.g., ethoxylation and/or propoxylation) corresponding to <u style="single">m</u>, or
a single specific chain with alkoxylation (e.g., ethoxylation and/or propoxylation) of
exactly the number of units corresponding to <u style="single">m</u>.The preferred surfactant mixture of the invention has one or more mid-chain
branched primary alkyl polyxoyalkylenes in an amount of at least 0.01 % by weight,
more preferably at least 5 % by weight, and most preferably at least 20 % by weight of
the mixture. The total number of carbon atoms, including branching, is from 15 to 18. 
Further, in the case of this surfactant mixture, the average total number of carbon atoms
in the branched primary alkyl moiety is within the range of from greater than 14 to about
18. Here, EO/PO is an alkoxy moiety, selected from ethoxy, propoxy, and mixed
ethoxy/propoxy groups, and most preferably ethoxy, wherein <u style="single">m</u> is at least about 1,
preferably within the range of from about 3 to about 30, more preferably from about 5 to
about 20, and most preferably from about 5 to about 15. More preferred are
compositions having at least 5 % by weight of the mixture comprising one or more
mid-chain branched primary polyoxyalkylenes.Preferably, the surfactant mixture contains at least 5 % by weight, and more
preferably at least about 20 % by weight of the mid-chain branched primary alkyl
polyoxyalkylene.The preferred detergent composition according to the invention contains from
about 0.01 to about 99 % by weight of a mixture of mid-chain branched primary alkyl
polyoxyalkylene surfactants.Further, in the case of this surfactant mixture, the average total number of carbon
atoms in the branched primary alkyl moiety is within the range of from greater than 14 to
about 18. Here, EO/PO is an alkoxy moiety, selected from ethoxy, propoxy, and mixed
ethoxy/propoxy groups, and most preferably ethoxy, wherein <u style="single">m</u> is at least about 1,
preferably within the range of from about 3 to about 30, more preferably from 5 to about
20, and most preferably from about 5 to about 15. Moreover, the surfactant composition
of the invention may be a mixture comprising one or more mid-chain branched primary
alkyl polyoxyalkylenes. In the foregoing, the total number of carbon atoms, including
branching, is from 14 to 20.In addition, in the case of this surfactant mixture, the average total number of
carbon atoms in the branched primary alkyl moieties is within the range of from greater 
than 14 to about 18. EO/PO is an alkoxy moiety, selected from ethoxy, propoxy, and
mixed ethoxy/propoxy groups, wherein <u style="single">m</u> is at least about 1, preferably within the range
of from about 3 to about 30, more preferably from 5 to about 20, and most preferably
from about 5 to about 15.Preferred mono-methyl branched primary alkyl ethoxylates are selected from the
group consisting of 3-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, 4-methyl pentadecanol
ethoxylate, 5-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, 6-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate,
7-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, 8-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, 9-methyl pentadecanol
ethoxylate, 10-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, 11-methyl pentadecanol
ethoxylate, 12-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, 13-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate,
3-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylate, 4-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylate, 5-methyl hexadecanol
ethoxylate, 6-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylate, 7-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylate,
8-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylate, 9-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylate, 10-methyl hexadecanol
ethoxylate, 11-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylate, 12-methyl hexadecanol
ethoxylate, 13-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylate, 14-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylate,, and
mixtures thereof, wherein the compounds are ethoxylated with an average degree of
ethoxylation of from about 5 to about 15.Preferred di-methyl branched primary alkyl ethoxylates are selected from the
group consisting of 2,3-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylate, 2,4-methyl tetradecanol
ethoxylate, 2,5-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylate, 2,6-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylate,
2,7-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylate, 2,8-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylate, 2,9-methyl
tetradecanol ethoxylate, 2,10-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylate, 2,11-methyl tetradecanol
ethoxylate, 2,12-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylate, 2,3-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate,
2,4-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, 2,5-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, 2,6-methyl
pentadecanol ethoxylate, 2,7-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, 2,8-methyl pentadecanol 
ethoxylate, 2,9-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, 2,10-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate,
2,11-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, 2,12-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate,
2,13-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylate, and mixtures thereof, wherein the compounds are
ethoxylated with an average degree of ethoxylation of from about 5 to about 15.</li><li>(3) Mid-chain branched primary alkyl alkoxylated sulfate surfactants:
The branched surfactant composition of the invention may contain one or more
(preferably a mixture of two or more) mid-chain branched primary alkyl alkoxylated
sulfates.The surfactant mixture of the invention contains molecules having a linear
primary alkoxylated sulfate chain backbone (i.e., the longest linear carbon chain
including the alkoxy-sulafted carbon atom). These alkyl chain backbones have from 12
to 19 carbon atoms, and further, the molecules contain a branched primary alkyl moiety
having at least a total of 14, but not more than 20, carbon atoms. In addition, the
surfactant mixture has an average total number of carbon atoms for the branched
primary alkyl moieties within the range of from greater than 14 to about 18. Thus, the
mixture of the invention comprises at least one alkoxylated sulfate compound having a
longest linear carbon chain of 12 or more carbon atoms or 19 or less carbon atoms, and
the total number of carbon atoms including branching must be at least 14, and further,
the average total number of carbon atoms for the branched primary alkyl chains is within
the range of from greater than 14 to about 18.For example, a C16 total carbon (in the alkyl chain) primary alkyl alkoxylated
sulfate surfactant having 15 carbon atoms in the backbone must have a methyl branching
unit, whereby the total number of carbon atoms in the primary alkyl moiety of the
molecule is 16.The composition of the invention may still further contain a small amount of a 
linear, non-branched primary alkoxylated sulfate. Further, this linear, non-branched
primary alkoxylated sulfate surfactant may be present as the result of the process used to
manufacture the surfactant mixture having the requisite mid-chain branched primary
alkoxylated sulfates according to the invention, or for the purpose of formulating the
detergent composition, a small amount of the linear, non-branched primary alkoxylated
sulfate may be admixed into the final product formulation.A small amount of a mid-chain branched alkyl sulfate may be present in the
detergent composition. This is typically the result of sulfation of a non-alkoxylated
alcohol remaining following incomplete alkoxylation of the mid-chain branched alcohol
used to prepare the alkoxylated sulfate useful herein. However, such mid-chain
branched alkyl sulfates may also be separately added.In addition, the alkoxylated sulfate-containing composition of the invention may
contain a small amount of a non-sulfated mid-chain branched alcohol (including
polyoxyalkylene alcohols). Such materials may be present as the result of incomplete
sulfation of the alcohol (alkoxylated or non-alkoxylated) used to prepare the alkoxylated
surface surfactant, or these alcohols may be separately added to the detergent
composition of the invention along with the mid-chain branched alkoxylated sulfate
surfactant according to the invention.The counter ion of the surfactant is described hereinbefore.The polyoxyalkylene (EO/PO) is an alkoxy moiety, selected from ethoxy,
propoxy, and mixed ethoxy/propoxy groups, wherein the repeating number (m) of the
polyoxyalkylene is at least 0.01, preferably within the range of from 0.1 to 30, more
preferably from 0.5 to 10, and most preferably from 1 to 5. The EO/PO may be a
distribution with an average degree of alkoxylation (e.g., ethoxylation and/or
propoxylation) corresponding to <u style="single">m</u>, or a single specific chain with alkoxylation (e.g., 
ethoxylation and/or propoxylation) of exactly the number of units corresponding to <u style="single">m</u>.The preferred surfactant mixture of the invention has one or more mid-chain
branched primary alkyl alkoxylated sulfate in an amount of at least 0.01 % by weight,
more preferably at least 5 % by weight, and most preferably at least 20 % by weight of
the mixture.The total number of carbon atoms, including branching, is from 15 to 18. Further,
in the case of this surfactant mixture, the average total number of carbon atoms in the
branched primary alkyl moiety is within the range of from greater than 14 to about 18.
Here, EO/PO is an alkoxy moiety, selected from ethoxy, propoxy, and mixed
ethoxy/propoxy groups, wherein <u style="single">m</u> is at least 0.01, preferably within the range of from
0.1 to 30, more preferably from 0.5 to 10, and most preferably from 1 to 5. More
preferred are compositions having at least 5 % by weight of the mixture comprising one
or more mid-chain branched primary alkoxylated sulfates.The preferred detergent composition according to the invention contains from
0.01 to 99 % by weight of a mixture of mid-chain branched primary alkyl alkoxylated
sulfate surfactants, the mixture containing at least 5 % by weight of one or more
mid-chain branched alkyl alkoxylated sulfates. The counter ion of the surfactant is one
or more cations.Further, in the case of this surfactant mixture, the average total number of carbon
atoms in the branched primary alkyl moieties is within the range of from greater than 14
to about 18. Here, EO/PO is an alkoxy moiety, selected from ethoxy, propoxy, and
mixed ethoxy/propoxy groups, wherein <u style="single">m</u> is at least 0.01, preferably within the range of
from 0.1 to 30, more preferably from 0.5 to 10, and most preferably from 1 to 5.Further, the surfactant composition of the invention may be a mixture of the
foregoing branched primary alkyl alkoxylated sulfates. The total number of carbon 
atoms, including branching, is from 14 to 20. Moreover, in the case of this surfactant
mixture, the average total number of carbon atoms in the branched primary alkyl
moieties is within the range of greater than 14 to 18. Here, EO/PO is an alkoxy moiety,
selected from ethoxy, propoxy, and mixed ethoxy/propoxy groups, wherein <u style="single">m</u> is at least
0.01, preferably within the range of from 0.1 to 30, more preferably from 0.5 to 10, and
most preferably from 1 to 5. Also preferred are surfactant compositions containing less
than 50 % by weight, preferably less than 40 % by weight, more preferably less than
25 % by weight, and most preferably less than 20 % by weight of the branched primary
alkyl alkoxylated sulfate.Preferred mono-methyl branched primary alkyl ethoxylated sulfates are selected
from the group consisting of 3-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 4-methyl pentadecanol
ethoxylated sulfate, 5-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 6-methyl
pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 7-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 8-methyl
pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 9-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 10-methyl
pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 11-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate,
12-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 13-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated
sulfate, 3-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 4-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated
sulfate, 5-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 6-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated
sulfate, 7-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 8-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated
sulfate, 9-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 10-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated
sulfate, 11-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 12-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated
sulfate, 13-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 14-methyl hexadecanol ethoxylated
sulfate, and mixtures thereof, wherein the compounds are ethoxylated with an average
degree of ethoxylation of from 0.1 to 10.Preferred di-methyl branched primary alkyl ethoxylated sulfates are selected 
from the group consisting of 2,3-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 2,4-methyl
tetradecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 2,5-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylated sulfate,
2,6-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 2,7-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylated sulfate,
2,8-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 2,9-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylated sulfate,
2,10-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 2,11-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylated
sulfate, 2,12-methyl tetradecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 2,3-methyl pentadecanol
ethoxylated sulfate, 2,4-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 2,5-methyl pentadecanol
ethoxylated sulfate, 2,6-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 2,7-methyl
pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 2,8-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate,
2,9-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 2,10-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated
sulfate, 2,11-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, 2,12-methyl pentadecanol
ethoxylated sulfate, 2,13-methyl pentadecanol ethoxylated sulfate, and mixtures thereof,</li></sl>
wherein the compounds are ethoxylated with an average degree of ethoxylation of from
0.1 to 10.</p><p num="0026">The detergent composition of the invention contains from 0.01 to 99.9 % by
weight of detergent auxiliary components. These detergent auxiliary components and
preferred other detergent auxiliary components that are optionally used will be described
below in detail.</p><p num="0027">The detergent composition of the invention include a wide range of daily
detergent product compositions inclusive of kinds to be shipped, such as powders,
liquids, granules, gels, pastes, tablets, small bags, bars, and double-partitioned
containers, sprays or foamed detergents and other homogenous or multi-phase daily
detergent product forms. These products can be manually used or coated, and/or can be
used in a constant or freely variable amount of use, or by automatic charge means, or can
be used in electric products such as washing machines. These products can have a wide 
range of pH of, e.g., from 2 to 12 or more, and several tens gram-equivalent, per 100 g of
the formulation, of NaOH may be added. These products can have a wide range of
preliminary alkalinity. Both types of high suds and low suds detergents are included.</p><heading><u style="single">Light-duty liquid detergents (LDL):</u></heading><p num="0028">These compositions include LDL compositions containing magnesium ions for
improving surface activity and/or organic diamines and/or various foam stabilizers
and/or suds boosters, such as amine oxides and/or skin feeling improvers of surfactant
and relaxing agents and/or enzyme types including protease, and/or sterilizers.</p><heading><u style="single">Heavy-duty liquid detergents (HDL):</u></heading><p num="0029">These compositions include all of so-called "structured" or multi-phase and
"non-structured" or isotropic liquid types, and generally include aqueous or
non-aqueous bleaching agents, and/or enzymes, or do not include bleaching agents
and/or enzymes.</p><heading><u style="single">Heavy-duty granular detergents (HDG):</u></heading><p num="0030">These compositions include both of a so-called "compact" or coagulated, or
non-spray dried type and a so-called "flocculated" or spray dried type. These
compositions include both of a phosphate addition type and a phosphate non-addition
type. Such detergents can include a type comprising a more general anionic surfactant
as a substrate, or may be a so-called "highly nonionic surfactant" type comprising a
generally nonionic surfactant held on an absorbent, for example, in or on the surface of a
zeolites or other porous inorganic salt.</p><heading><u style="single">Softeners (STW):</u></heading><p num="0031">These compositions include various types of granular or liquid products that are
softened by laundry, and can generally organic (such as quaternary) or inorganic (such as
clay) softeners. </p><heading><u style="single">Bar soaps (BS &amp; HW):</u></heading><p num="0032">These compositions include laundry bars and include both of a type comprising a
synthetic detergent and a soap as substrates and a type containing a softener. Such
compositions include compositions manufactured by general soap manufacture
techniques, such as pressure molding, or techniques that are no so general, such as
casting and absorption of surfactant into a porous support. Other hand wash detergents
are also included.</p><heading><u style="single">Fabric softeners (FS):</u></heading><p num="0033">These compositions include both of the conventional liquid and concentrated
liquid types and kinds to be added by dryers or supported by a substrate. Other fabric
softeners include those that are solid.</p><p num="0034">Special purpose cleaners (SPC) including the following products may be
considered. That is, there are house-hold dry detergent modes, pre-treatment products of
laundry bleaching agents, pre-treatment products for fabric protection, liquid higher
fabric detergent types, especially high suds products, liquid bleaching agents including
both of chlorine type and oxygen bleaching agent type, disinfectants, detergent aids,
pre-treatment types including, for example, bleaching additives and "stain-stick" or
special sudsing type cleaners, and anti-fading treatment by sunlight.</p><p num="0035">Cleaners containing a durable perfume become general more and more.
Laundry or detergent components</p><p num="0036">The detergent composition of the invention contains from 0.01 to 99 % by weight
of at least one member selected from the group consisting of (i) detergent enzymes, and
preferably enzymes selected from protease, amylase, lipase, cellulase, peroxidase, and
mixtures thereof, (ii) organic detergent builders, and preferably builders selected from
polycarboxylate compounds, ether hydroxy polycarboxylates, substituted ammonium 
salts of polyacetic acid, and mixtures thereof, (iii) enzyme bleaching agents, and
preferably bleaching agents selected from hydrogen peroxide, inorganic peroxo hydrates,
organic peroxo hydrates, organic peracids containing hydrophilic or hydrophobic mono-
or di-peracids, and mixtures thereof, (iv) bleach surfactant, and preferably bleach
surfactant selected from TAED, NOBS, and mixtures thereof, (v) transition metal
bleaching agent catalysts, and preferably manganese-containing bleaching agent
catalysts, (vi) oxygen transfer agents and precursor materials, (vii) polymeric soil
releasing agents, (viii) water-soluble ethoxylated amines having clay soil removal and
anti-redeposition characteristics, (ix) polymeric dispersing agents, (x) polymeric dye
transfer inhibitors, (xi) alkoxylated polycarboxylates, and (xii) mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0037">In general, the laundry or detergent auxiliary components are all components
necessary for converting a composition containing only the minimum essential
components into a composition useful for the laundry or detergent purpose.</p><p num="0038">In preferred embodiments, it can be easily recognized by those skilled in the art
that the laundry or detergent auxiliary components are indispensable for laundry or
detergent products, especially laundry or detergent products for direct use by consumers
in the house-hold environment.</p><p num="0039">The precise nature of these additional components, and levels of incorporation
thereof vary depending upon the physical form of the composition and the nature of the
cleaning operation for which it is to be used.</p><p num="0040">Preferably, in the case where the auxiliary components are used along with the
bleaching agent, they must have good stability to the bleaching agent. The specific
preferred detergent composition of the invention should be of a boron-free or phosphoric
acid-free pursuant to the regulations. The amount of the auxiliary components is from
0.01 to 99.9 % by weight, and typically from 70 to 95 % by weight of the composition. 
The amount of the whole of the composition to be used can be widely varied in the range
of, for example, from several ppm in the solution to the case of the so-called "direct
application" of the non-dilute detergent composition on the surface to be cleaned
depending on the intended object.</p><p num="0041">Examples of the general auxiliary components include builders, surfactants,
enzymes, polymers, bleaching agents, bleach surfactants, and catalyst components other
than those as already defined above as the essential components in the composition of
the invention. Examples of other auxiliary components include various active
components or special components such as dispersant polymers, color speckles, silver
protecting agents, anti-fogging agents and/or corrosion inhibitors, dyes, fillers,
sterilizers, alkaline agents, hydrotropic agents, antioxidants, enzyme stabilizers,
pro-perfumes, perfumes, plasticizers, carriers, processing aids, pigments, and solvents
for liquid formulations.</p><p num="0042">Extremely typically, the laundry or washing compositions of the invention, for
example, laundry detergents, laundry detergent additives, synthetic and soap-based
laundry bars, fabric softeners, and fabric processing liquids, often require some kinds of
auxiliary components. But, some simply formulated products such as bleaching
additives, require only, for example, enzyme bleaching agents and surfactants as
described herein.</p><heading><u style="single">Detergent surfactants:</u></heading><p num="0043">This composition may contain known detergent surfactants and is widely
described in the known literature references.</p><p num="0044">Accordingly, the detergent surfactants of the invention contain anionic, nonionic,
zwitter-ionic or amphiprotic (amphiphilic) surfactants that are known as detergents in
fabric laundering. </p><p num="0045">In all of the detergent surfactants, the chain length of the hydrophobic moiety is
typically in the general range of from C8 to C20, and especially in the case of laundering
with cold water, the chain length is often preferably in the range of from C8 to C18.</p><heading><u style="single">Detergent enzymes:</u></heading><p num="0046">The detergent composition of the invention preferably uses enzymes for various
purposes such as removal of protein-based, carbohydrate-based, or triglyceride-based
soils from substrates, transfer inhibition of refugee dyes in fabric laundering, and fabric
restoration.</p><p num="0047">The "detergent enzymes" as used herein mean all of enzymes having
advantageous effects in washing, soil removal, and others in laundering.</p><heading><u style="single">Builder:</u></heading><p num="0048">The composition of the invention controls the hardness of minerals in washing
water, especially Ca and/or Mg, makes it easy to remove and/or disperse granular soils
from the surface, and optionally imparts an alkaline agent and/or buffer action. In
granular or powder detergents, the builder may function as an absorbent for the
surfactant. Alternatively, some compositions can be formulated in a completely
water-soluble form, which may be either organic or inorganic, depending on the
intended utility.</p><p num="0049">Suitable silicate builders include water-soluble types and hydrated solid types,
and include other kinds such as those having a chain, layer or steric structure, amorphous
solid silicates, and those as prepared such that they are used as not particularly structured
liquid detergents.</p><p num="0050">Aluminosilicate builders, so-called zeolites, are particularly useful in granular
detergents, but can be incorporated into pastes or gels. The aluminosilicates may be
crystalline or amorphous, or may be natural or synthetic. </p><p num="0051">For the purpose of making it easy to control the hardness of minerals in the
washing water, especially Ca and/or Mg, or of making it easy to remove granular solids
from the surface, the composition of the invention may optionally contain detergent
builders in place of or in addition to the foregoing silicates and aluminosilicates. The
builders can be made to function in various mechanisms so as to form soluble or
insoluble complexes with mineral ions by ion exchange or by providing mineral ions
with the surface more adherent than the surface of the material to be cleaned. The
amount of the builder can be varied widely depending on the final utility and physical
form of the composition.</p><p num="0052">Here, suitable builder can be selected from the group consisting of phosphates
and polyphosphates, especially sodium salts, carbonates, bicarbonates, sodium
carbonate, organic mono-, di-, tri-, and tetracarboxylates, especially water-soluble
non-surfactant carboxylates in acid, sodium, potassium or alkanolammonium forms, and
aliphatic and aromatic type-containing oligomers or water-soluble low-molecular
polymer carboxylates. For example, for the purpose of pH buffer, these builders can be
complemented by all of fillers or carriers that are important in the techniques of
detergent compositions including borates or sulfates, especially sodium sulfate, and
other stabilized surfactants and/or builders.</p><p num="0053">In the invention, builder mixtures can be used. In general, the builder mixture
optionally comprises two or more usual builders, and is complemented by a chelating
agent, a pH buffer, or a filler.</p><p num="0054">Examples of phosphorus-containing builders include polyphosphates,
represented by tripolyphosphates, pyrophosphates, and glassy polymer metaphosphates,
of alkali metals and ammonium and alkanolammoniums, and phosphonates.</p><p num="0055">Suitable carbonate builders include carbonates of an alkaline earth metal or an 
alkali metal, inclusive of carbonate minerals such as sodium bicarbonate and sodium
carbonate, complex salts of sodium carbonate or potassium carbonate, and calcium
carbonate.</p><p num="0056">As described herein, the "organic detergent builders" suitable for the use along
with the alkylaryl sulfonate surfactant include polycarboxylate compounds including
water-soluble non-surfactant dicarboxylates and tricarboxylates. More generally, the
builder polycarboxylate has plural carboxylate groups, preferably at least three
carboxylates. The carboxylate builder can be incorporated in an acidic or partially
neutral, neutral or excessively basic form. In the case of the salt form, salts of alkali
metals such as sodium, potassium, and lithium, or alkanolammonium salts are preferred.

The polycarboxylate builder includes ether polycarboxylates.</p><p num="0057">Citric acid salts such as citric acid and soluble salts thereof are a polycarboxylate
builder important for, for example, heavy-duty liquid detergents because they are
available from resources that can be regenerated and are biodegradable. The citric acid
salts can also be used in granular compositions especially in combination of zeolites
and/or layered silicates. Oxydisuccinic acid salts are especially useful in such
compositions and combinations.</p><heading><u style="single">Oxygen bleaching agents:</u></heading><p num="0058">The preferred composition of the invention comprises an "oxygen bleaching
agent" as a part or whole of the laundry or detergent auxiliary components. As useful
oxygen bleaching agents of the invention, any known oxidizing agents can be used.
Though oxygen bleaching agents or mixtures thereof are preferred, other oxidizing agent
bleaching agents such as systems of generating hydrogen peroxide by oxygen or an
enzyme, or hypohalogenic acid salts, for example, chlorine bleaching agents such as
hyposulfites, can also be used. </p><p num="0059">Examples of peroxide-based general oxygen bleaching agents include hydrogen
peroxide, inorganic peroxohydrates, organic peroxohydrates, and organic peroxy acids
including hydrophilic or hydrophobic mono- or diperoxy acids. These components may
be peroxycarboxylic acids, perpoxyimide acids, amidoperoxycarboxylic acids, or salts
thereof including their calcium, magnesium or mixed cationic salts. Various kinds of
peracids can be used in a liberated form or as precursor materials called "bleach
surfactant" or "bleach promoters", which release peracids corresponding to hydrolysis
in the case of a combination with a supply source of hydrogen peroxide.</p><p num="0060">Inorganic peroxides, suproxides, organic hydroperoxides such as cumene
hydroperoxide and t-butyl hydroperoxide, and inorganic peroxo acids and salts thereof,
such as peroxosulfates, are also useful as the oxygen bleaching agent.</p><p num="0061">Mixed oxygen bleaching agent systems are generally effective as in mixtures of
oxygen bleaching agents with known bleach surfactant, organic catalysts, enzyme
catalysts, or mixtures thereof. Further, these mixtures can further contain brighteners,
light bleaching agents, and dye transfer inhibitors of types that are well known in this
field.</p><p num="0062">As described above, the preferred oxygen bleaching agent includes
hydroperoxides and peroxohydrates. These components are organic salts, or more
generally, inorganic salts that can readily release hydrogen peroxide. The
peroxohydrates are a general example of the "hydrogen peroxide source" and include
perborates, percarbonates, perphosphates, and persilicates. Preferred peroxohydrates
include all of sodium carbonate hydroperoxide and equivalent commercially available
"percarbonate" bleaching agents, and so-called sodium perborate hydrtates, and sodium
pyrrophosphate hydroperoxide can also be used. Urea hydroperoxides are also useful as
the peroxohydrate. </p><p num="0063">There are included inorganic peroxohydrates, organic peroxohydrates,
hydrophilic or hydrophobic mono- or diperacids, organic peracids including
peroxycarboxylic acids, peroxyimide acids, and amidoperoxycarboxylic acids, salts of
calcium, magnesium, or mixed cationic salts</p><heading><u style="single">Bleach surfactant:</u></heading><p num="0064">Examples of useful bleach surfactant include amides, imides, esters, and acid
anhydrides. Generally, there is present at least one substituted or unsubstituted acyl
moiety having a leaving group in the structure, R-C(O)-L. As a preferred method of use,
is a combination of the bleach surfactant with a hydrogen peroxide supply source such as
perborates and percarbonates. One or more peracid-forming moieties or leaving groups
can be present. Mixtures of bleach surfactants can be used.</p><p num="0065">The bleach surfactant can be used in an amount of up to 20 % by weight, and
preferably from 0.1 to 10 % by weight of the composition. For the form of highly
concentrated bleaching agent additive products or the form in which the bleach
surfactant is used in an automatic charge device, it can be used in an amount of 40 % by
weight or more.</p><heading><u style="single">Transition metal bleaching agent catalysts:</u></heading><p num="0066">Manganese compounds can be optionally used as the bleaching compound to
have a catalytic action. As useful cobalt bleaching catalysts, ones that are known may be
used.</p><heading><u style="single">Enzyme-based supply sources of hydrogen peroxide:</u></heading><p num="0067">Besides the above-enumerated bleach surfactant, other suitable hydrogen
peroxide generating mechanisms include combinations of C1 to C4 alkanol oxidases and
C1 to C4 alkanols, especially a combination of methanol oxidase (MOX) and ethanol.
Bleaching-related other enzymatic materials such as peroxidases, haloperoxidases, and 
oxidases, superoxide molecular displacement enzymes, catalases, and their reinforcing
agents, or more generally, inhibitors can be optionally used in the composition.</p><heading><u style="single">Oxygen transfer agents and precursors:</u></heading><p num="0068">All of known organic bleaching agent catalysts, oxygen transfer agents, or
precursors thereof are also useful herein. These materials include their compounds
themselves and/or precursors thereof, such as all of ketones suitable for manufacture of
dioxiranes, and and/or dixoirane precursors or all different atom-containing analogues
of dioxiranes. As preferred examples of such components, are especially included
hydrophilic or hydrophobic ketones that manufacture the dioxiranes on the spot, along
with monoperoxysulfate. Examples of such oxygen bleaching agents that are preferably
used along with the oxygen transfer agent or precursor include percarboxylic acids and
salts, percarbonic acids and slats, peroxy monosulfuric acid and salts, and mixtures
thereof.</p><heading><u style="single">Polymeric soil releasing agents:</u></heading><p num="0069">The composition of the invention can optionally comprise one or more soil
releasing agents. The polymeric soil releasing agent is characterized by having
hydrophilic segments to hydrophilize the surface of hydrophobic fibers such as polyester
and nylon and hydrophobic segments to deposit upon hydrophobic fibers and remain
adhered thereto through completion of the laundry cycle to function as an anchor for the
hydrophilic segments. This can enable stains occurring sequent to treatment with the
soil releasing agent to be more easily cleaned in later washing procedures.</p><p num="0070">In the case of the use, the soil releasing agent generally accounts for from about
0.01 to about 10 % by weight of the composition.</p><heading><u style="single">Clay soil removal/anti-redeposition agents:</u></heading><p num="0071">The composition of the invention can also optionally contain water-soluble 
ethoxylated amines having clay soil removal and anti-redeposition properties. Granular
detergent compositions containing these compounds typically contain from about
0.01 % to about 10.0 % by weight of the water-soluble ethoxylated amines, and liquid
detergent compositions typically contain about 0.01 % to about 5 % by weight of the
water-soluble ethoxylated amines.</p><p num="0072">Preferred soil release and anti-redeposition agents are ethoxylated
tetraethylenepentamine. Other preferred soil release removal/anti-redeposition agents
are ethoxylated amine polymers, zwitter-ionic polymers, and amine oxides. Other soil
release removal and/or anti-redeposition agents that are known in this field can also be
used in the composition of the invention. Another type of the preferred anti-redeposition
agent includes carboxy methyl cellulose (CMC)-based components.</p><heading><u style="single">Polymeric dispersing agents:</u></heading><p num="0073">Polymeric dispersing agents can be effectively used in an amount of from about
0.01 to about 10 % by weight of the composition of the invention especially in the
presence of zeolite and/or layered silicate builders. Suitable polymeric dispersing agents
include polymeric polycarboxylates and polyethylene glycols, although others known in
the art can also be used. It is believed that polymeric dispersing agents enhance overall
detergent builder performance, when used in combination with other builders (including
lower molecular weight polycarboxylates) by crystal growth inhibition, particulate soil
release, peptization, and anti-redeposition.</p><p num="0074">Polymeric polycarboxylate materials can be prepared by polymerizing or
copolymerizing suitable unsaturated monomers, preferably in their acid forms.
Unsaturated monomeric acids that can be polymerized to form suitable polymeric
polycarobyxlates include acrylic acid, maleic acid (or maleic anhydride), fumaric acid,
itaconic acid, aconitic acid, mesaconic acid, citraconic acid, and methylenemalonic acid. </p><p num="0075">Particularly suitable polymeric polycarboxylates can be derived from acrylic
acid. Such acrylic acid-based polymers that are useful herein are the water-soluble salts
of polymerized acrylic acid. The average molecular weight of such polymers in the acid
form preferably ranges from about 1,000 to 20,000, more preferably from about 2,000 to
15,000, and most preferably from about 3,000 to 10,000. Water-soluble salts of such
acrylic acid polymers can include, for example, the alkali metal, ammonium and
substituted ammonium salts.</p><p num="0076">Acrylic acid/maleic acid-based copolymers may also be used as a preferred
component of the dispersing/anti-redeposition agent. Such materials include the
water-soluble salts of copolymers of acrylic acid and maleic acid. The average
molecular weight of such copolymers in the acid form preferably ranges from about
2,000 to 100,000, more preferably from about 3,000 to 80,000, and most preferably from
about 4,000 to 70,000. The ratio of acrylate to maleate segments in such copolymers
generally ranges from about 9:1 to about 1:9, and more preferably from about 8:2 to 3:7.
Water-soluble salts of such acrylic acid/maleic acid copolymers can include, for
example, the alkali metal, ammonium and substituted ammonium salts.</p><p num="0077">Copolymers of acrylic acid and/or maleic acid and a polyalkylene glycol can also
be used as a preferred component of the dispersing/anti-redeposition agent. The
copolymers are preferably graft polymers of acrylic acid and/or maleic acid and a
polyalkylene glycol, copolymers of acrylic acid and/or maleic acid and an alkylene
oxide adduct of allyl alcohol or isoprenol, and copolymers of acrylic acid and/or maleic
acid and a polyalkylene glycol acrylate or methacrylate, and more preferably graft
polymers of acrylic acid and/or maleic acid and a polyalkylene glycol and copolymers of
acrylic acid and/or maleic acid and an alkylene oxide adduct of allyl alcohol or
isoprenol. </p><p num="0078">The average molecular weight of the copolymers preferably ranges from about
2,000 to 100,000, more preferably from about 3,000 to 80,000, and most preferably from
about 4,000 to 70,000.</p><p num="0079">Another polymeric component that can be incorporated is polyethylene glycol
(PEG). PEG can exhibit dispersing agent performance as well as act as a clay soil
removal/anti-redeposition agent. Typical molecular weight ranges for these purposes
range from about 500 to about 100,000, preferably from about 1,000 to about 50,000,
and more preferably from about 1,500 to about 10,000.</p><p num="0080">Polyasparatate and polyglutamate dispersing agents may also be used, especially
in conjunction with zeolites builders. Dispersing agents such as polyasparatate
preferably have a (weight average) molecular weight of about 10,000.</p><heading><u style="single">Brighteners:</u></heading><p num="0081">In the detergent composition of the invention (in the case where it is designed for
fabric washing or processing), any optical brighteners or other brightening or whitening
agents known in this field can be incorporated generally in an amount of from about 0.01
to about 1.2 % by weight.</p><heading><u style="single">Polymeric dye transfer inhibiting agents:</u></heading><p num="0082">The composition of the invention may also include one or more materials
effective for inhibiting the transfer of dyes from one fabric to another during the cleaning
process. Generally, such dye transfer inhibiting agents include polyvinylpyrrolidone
polymers, polyamide N-oxide polymers, copolymers of N-vinylpyrrolidone and
N-vinylimidazole, manganese phthalocyanine, peroxidases, and mixtures thereof. If
used, these agents generally comprise from about 0.01 to about 10 % by weight,
preferably from about 0.01 to about 5 % by weight, and more preferably from about 0.05
to about 2 % by weight of the composition. </p><p num="0083">The optical brightener selected for use in the invention exhibits especially
effective dye transfer inhibition performance benefits when used in combination with
the polymeric dye transfer inhibiting agent. The combination of such selected polymeric
materials with such selected optical brightener provides significantly better dye transfer
inhibition in aqueous wash solutions than does either of these two detergent composition
components when used alone.</p><heading><u style="single">Chelating agents:</u></heading><p num="0084">The detergent composition of the invention may also optionally contain one or
more chelating agents, especially chelating agents for transition metal coming from
others. The transition metals generally seen in washing solutions include water-soluble,
colloidal or granular iron and/or manganese and may sometimes associate as oxides or
hydroxides. Preferred chelating agents are chelating agents that effectively inhibit such
transition metals, especially inhibit such transition metals or their compounds to adhere
to fabrics, and/or inhibit non-preferred redox reaction occurred in the washing medium
and/or on the interface of the fabric or hard surface. The general chelating agents can be
selected from the group consisting of amino carboxylates, amino phosphates,
polyfunctionally-substituted aromatic chelating agents, and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0085">The composition of the invention may also contain water-soluble methyl glycine
diacetic acid salts as a chelating agent that can effectively be used together with
insoluble builders such as zeolites and layered silicates.</p><p num="0086">If utilized, the chelating agent generally accounts for from about 0.01 to about
15 % by weight of the composition. More preferably, if utilized, the chelating agent
accounts for from about 0.01 to about 3.0 % by weight.</p><heading><u style="single">Suds suppressors:</u></heading><p num="0087">In the case where washing is required in intended utilities, especially washing by 
washing machines, compounds for reducing or suppressing the formation of suds can be
incorporated into the composition of the invention. For other compositions, for example,
compositions as designed for hand washing, high sudsing may be desired, and such
components can be omitted. Suds suppression can be of particularly importance in the
so-called "high concentration cleaning process" and in front-loading European-style
washing machines (so-called drum type washing machines).</p><p num="0088">A very wide variety of materials may be used as suds suppressors. The
composition of the invention generally comprises from 0 % by weight to about 10 % by
weight of suds suppressors.</p><heading><u style="single">Fabric softeners:</u></heading><p num="0089">Various through-the-wash fabric softeners can optionally be used in an amount
of from about 0.5 to about 10 % by weight to provide fabric softener benefits
concurrently with fabric cleaning. Clay softeners can be used in combination with
amine and cationic softeners. Further, in the cleaning process of the invention, known
fabric softeners including those of biodegradation type can be used in modes including
the pre-treatment, main cleaning, post-laundry, and addition into washing machines and
dryers.</p><heading><u style="single">Perfumes:</u></heading><p num="0090">Perfumes and perfumery ingredients useful in the compositions and processes
comprise a wide variety of natural and synthetic chemical ingredients, including, but not
limited to, aldehydes, ketones, and esters. Also, included are various natural extracts
and essences that can comprise complex mixtures of ingredients such as orange oil,
lemon, oil, rose extract, lavender, musk, patchouli, balsamic essence, sandalwood oil,
pine oil, and cedar. Finished perfumes typically comprise from about 0.01 to about 2 %
by weight of the detergent composition, and individual perfumery ingredients can 
comprise from about 0.0001 to about 90 % by weight of a finished perfume composition.</p><heading><u style="single">Other ingredients:</u></heading><p num="0091">A wide variety of other ingredients useful in detergent compositions can be
included in the composition, including other ingredients, carriers, hydrotropes,
processing aids, dyes or pigments, solvents for liquid formulations, and soil fillers for
bar compositions. If high sudsing is desired, suds boosters such as C10 to C16
alkanolamides can be incorporated into the composition, typically in an amount of from
1 % by weight to 10 % by weight. C10 to C14 monoethanl and diethanol amides
illustrate a typical class of such suds boosters. Use of such suds boosters with high
sudsing adjuvant surfactants such as the amine oxides, betaines and sultanines noted
above is also advantageous. If desired, water-soluble magnesium and/or calcium salts
can be added typically in an amount of from 0.1 % by weight to 2 % by weight, to
provide additional suds.</p><p num="0092">Various detergent ingredients employed in the composition can optionally be
further stabilized by absorbing the ingredients onto a porous hydrophobic substrate, then
coating the substrate with a hydrophobic coating. Preferably, the detergent ingredient is
admixed with a surfactant before being absorbed into the porous substrate. In use, the
detergent ingredient is released from the substrate into the aqueous washing liquor,
where it performs its intended detergent function.</p><p num="0093">The liquid detergent composition can contain water and other solvents as
diluents. Low-molecular weight primary or secondary alcohols exemplified by
methanol, ethanol, propanol, and isopropanol are suitable. Monohydric alcohols are
preferred for stabilizing the surfactant, but polyols such as those having from 2 to about
6 carbon atoms and from 2 to about 6 hydroxyl groups (such as 1,3-propanediol,
ethylene glycol, glycerin, and propylene glycol) can also be used. The composition can 
contain such diluents in an amount of from 5 % by weight to 90 % by weight, and
preferably from 10 % by weight to 50 % by weight.</p><p num="0094">The detergent composition is preferably formulated such that, during use in
aqueous cleaning operations, the wash water has a pH of from about 6.5 to about 11,
preferably from 7.5 to 10.5, and more preferably from about 7.0 to about 9.5. Laundry
products are typically at a pH of from 9 to 11. Techniques for controlling the pH at
recommended usage levels include the use of buffers, alkalis, acids, etc.</p><heading><u style="single">Forms of the composition:</u></heading><p num="0095">The composition of the invention can take a variety of physical forms including
granular, gel, tablet, bar and liquid forms. These compositions include a so-called
concentrated granular detergent composition adapted to be added to a washing machine
by means of a dispensing device placed in the machine drum with the soiled fabric load.</p><p num="0096">Some preferred granular detergent compositions of the invention are of a general
high-density type in the current commercial market.</p><heading><u style="single">Surfactant agglomerate particles:</u></heading><p num="0097">One of preferred methods for incorporating the surfactants into daily products is
the manufacture of surfactant agglomerate particles. These particles can take the form
of flakes, prills, marumes, noodles, or ribbons, but preferably take the form of granules.
A preferred way to process the particles is by agglomerating powders (such as
aluminosilicates and carbonates) with highly active surfactant pastes to control the
particle size of the resulting agglomerates within specified limits.</p><p num="0098">In the following Examples, all amounts are quoted as % by weight of the
composition. The following Examples are illustrative of the invention, but are not meant
to limit or otherwise define its scope. All parts, percentages and ratios used herein are
expressed as percent weight unless otherwise specified. </p><p num="0099">In the following Examples, the abbreviations for various ingredients used for the
compositions have the following meanings.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">MLAS</entry><entry align="left">Mid-chain branched sodium alkylbenzene sulfonate</entry></row><row><entry align="left">LAS</entry><entry align="left">Sodium linear alkylbenzene sulfonate</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MBAS</entry><entry align="left">Mid-chain branched primary alkyl (average total carbons = x) sulfate</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MEA</entry><entry align="left">Monoethanolamine</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PG</entry><entry align="left">Propylene glycol</entry></row><row><entry align="left">EtOH</entry><entry align="left">Ethanol</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbonate</entry><entry align="left">Anhydrous sodium carbonate with a particle size of from 200 to 900 µm</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Citrate</entry><entry align="left">Trisodium citrate dihydrate with an activity of 86.4 % and a particle size distribution of from 425 to 850 µm</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PSA:</entry><entry align="left">Sodium polyacrylate not terminated with a sulfonic acid group (weight average molecular weight = 4,500), Q value: 3.92, S value: 0, R value: 0.0, iron ion concentration: 0.40 ppm</entry></row><row><entry align="left">AA/MA</entry><entry align="left">Copolymer of acrylic acid/maleic acid (weight average molecular weight = 70,000), acrylic acid/maleic acid composition ratio = 20/80 (by mole), clay-dispersibility: 0.1 or less (at both for 50 ppm and 200 ppm of calcium carbonate), calcium ion-binding capacity: 410 mg/g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PEG</entry><entry align="left">Polyethylene glycol (weight average molecular weight = 4,600)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zeolite A</entry><entry align="left">Hydrated sodium aluminosilicate of formula Na<sub>12</sub>(AlO<sub>2</sub>SiO<sub>2</sub>)<sub>12</sub>·27H<sub>2</sub>O</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sulfate</entry><entry align="left">Anhydrous sodium sulfate</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PB 1</entry><entry align="left">Sodium perborate monohydrate</entry></row><row><entry align="left">NOBS</entry><entry align="left">Nonanoyloxybenzene sulfonate in the form of the sodium salt</entry></row><row><entry align="left">BPP</entry><entry align="left">Butoxypropoxy propanol</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="left">Softanol 70H, manufactured by Nippon Shokubai Co., Ltd., </entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">polyoxyethylene alkyl ether</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="left">Stearyl trimethylammonium chloride</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0100">In the case where no specific description is given, the ingredients are in the
anhydrous form.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 1</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Water-soluble graft polymer (1) comprising a polyalkylene glycol having a
monoethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid-based monomer graft polymerized
thereon:</u></heading><p num="0101">In a 300-ml separable flask equipped with a stirrer, a condenser, a thermometer, a
nitrogen-introducing tube and a dropping funnel, were charged 200 g of a polyethylene
glycol comprising methanol having 10 moles of ethylene oxide added thereto
(hereinafter referred to as "PGM-10"), 29.6 g of maleic anhydride, and 1.1 g of pure
water, and about one hour after purging with nitrogen, the mixture was elevated to 120
°C while stirring. At the time when the temperature reached 120 °C, 50.7 g of an acrylic
acid solution of 100 % by weight and 5.1 g of t-butyl peroxybenzoate (hereinafter
referred to as "PBZ") were respectively added dropwise thereto over 150 minutes. After
completion of the dropwise addition of the solutions, the mixture was aged at the same
temperature (120 ± 3 °C) for 2 hours to complete the polymerization. The resulting
polymer had a weight average molecular weight of 8,300.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 2</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Water-soluble graft polymer (2) comprising a polyalkylene glycol having a monoethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid-based monomer graft polymerized
thereon:</u></heading><p num="0102">In a 300-ml separable flask equipped with a stirrer, a condenser, a thermometer, a
nitrogen-introducing tube and a dropping funnel, were charged 64 g of SOFT-70 (an 
ethylene oxide adduct of an alkyl alcohol, manufactured by Nippon Shokubai Co., Ltd.)
and 64 g of PM-10, and about one hour after purging with nitrogen, the mixture was
elevated to 130 °C while stirring. At the time when the temperature reached 130 °C,
54.9 g and 4.4 g of an acrylic acid solution of 100 % by weight were added dropwise
thereto over 180 minutes and 120 minutes, respectively. After completion of the
dropwise addition of the solution, the mixture was aged at the same temperature (130 ± 3
°C) for 90 minutes to complete the polymerization. The resulting polymer had a weight
average molecular weight of 11,000.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 3</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Water-soluble polymer (1) comprising a polyalkylene glycol-containing ethylenically
unsaturated monomer (not containing an ester bond between the polyalkylene glycol
chain and the ethylenically unsaturated bond) having a monoethylenically unsaturated
carboxylic acid-based monomer copolymerized therewith:</u></heading><p num="0103">In a 300-ml separable flask equipped with a stirrer, a condenser, a thermometer, a
nitrogen-introducing tube and a dropping funnel, was charged 120 g of pure water, and
after purging with nitrogen, the water was elevated to the reflux temperature while
stirring. At the time when the temperature reached a prescribed temperature, 23.4 g of a
sodium persulfate aqueous solution of 3 % by weight, 60 g of an aqueous solution of
50 % by weight of an unsaturated alcohol comprising 3-methyl-2-buten-1-ol having 10
moles of ethylene oxide added thereto (hereinafter referred to as "IPN-10"), and an
aqueous solution of a mixture of 6.1 g of an acrylic acid aqueous solution of 80 % by
weight and 39.9 g of a sodium acrylate aqueous solution of 37 % by weight were added
dropwise thereto, respectively. However, IPN-10 and the acrylic acid monomer were
added dropwise over 120 minutes, and the sodium persulfate aqueous solution was
added dropwise over 150 minutes. After completion of the dropwise addition of the 
sodium persulfate aqueous solution, the mixture was aged at the same temperature for 30
minutes to complete the polymerization. The resulting polymer had a weight average
molecular weight of 5,000.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 4</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Water-soluble polymer (2) comprising a polyalkylene glycol-containing ethylenically
unsaturated monomer (not containing an ester bond between the polyalkylene glycol
chain and the ethylenically unsaturated bond) having a monoethylenically unsaturated
carboxylic acid-based monomer copolymerized therewith:</u></heading><p num="0104">In a 300-ml separable flask equipped with a stirrer, a condenser, a thermometer, a
nitrogen-introducing tube and a dropping funnel, were charged 16.35 g of maleic
anhydride, 45.2 g of pure water, and 0.007 g of Mohr's salt, and after purging with
nitrogen, the mixture was elevated to the reflux temperature (about 103 °C) while
stirring. At the time when the temperature reached a prescribed temperature, a solution
of 50 g of IPN-10 in 20 g of pure water, 43.0 g of an acrylic acid aqueous solution of
80 % by weight, and a solution of 14.4 g of hydrogen peroxide of 35 % by weight in 22
g of pure water were respectively added dropwise thereto over 120 minutes. After
completion of the addition of the solutions, the mixture was aged at the reflux
temperature for one hour to complete the polymerization. The resulting polymer had a
weight average molecular weight of 12,000.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 5</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Water-soluble polymer (3) comprising a polyalkylene glycol-containing ethylenically
unsaturated monomer (not containing an ester bond between the polyalkylene glycol
chain and the ethylenically unsaturated bond) having a monoethylenically unsaturated
carboxylic acid-based monomer copolymerized therewith:</u></heading><p num="0105">In a 300-ml separable flask equipped with a stirrer, a condenser, a thermometer, a 
nitrogen-introducing tube and a dropping funnel, were charged 20.42 g of maleic
anhydride, 40 g of pure water, and 0.007 g of Mohr's salt, and after purging with
nitrogen, the mixture was elevated to the reflux temperature (about 103 °C) while
stirring. At the time when the temperature reached a prescribed temperature, a solution
of 70 g of allyl alcohol having 5 moles of ethylene oxide added thereto (hereinafter
referred to as "PEA-5") in 28 g of pure water, 28.1 g of an acrylic acid aqueous solution
of 80 % by weight, and a solution of 15 g of hydrogen peroxide of 35 % by weight in 18
g of pure water were respectively added dropwise thereto over 120 minutes. After
completion of the addition of the solutions, the mixture was aged at the reflux
temperature for one hour to complete the polymerization. The resulting polymer had a
weight average molecular weight of 14,000.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 6</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Water-soluble polymer (4) comprising a polyalkylene glycol-containing ethylenically
unsaturated monomer (containing an ester bond between the polyalkylene glycol chain
and the ethylenically unsaturated bond) having a monoethylenically unsaturated
carboxylic acid-based monomer copolymerized therewith:</u></heading><p num="0106">In a 500-ml separable flask equipped with a stirrer, a condenser, a thermometer, a
nitrogen-introducing tube and a dropping funnel, was charged 150 g of pure water, and
after purging with nitrogen, the aqueous solution was elevated to 70 °C while stirring.
At the time when the temperature reached a prescribed temperature, a solution of 22.95 g
of an aqueous solution of sodium persulfate of 20 % by weight, 80 g of an esterfication
production of methacrylic acid and PGM-10, 60 g of a methacrylic acid solution of
100 % by weight, and 55.23 g of an NaOH aqueous solution of 48 % by weight were
respectively added dropwise thereto over 120 minutes. After completion of the addition
of the solutions, the mixture was aged at the same temperature for 60 minutes to 
complete the polymerization. The resulting polymer had a weight average molecular
weight of 12,000.</p><heading><u style="single">Performance evaluation:</u></heading><p num="0107">Detergent formulations and formation amounts of polymer are as follows.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">(Formulation Example 1: Powder detergent model composed mainly of anions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">B</entry><entry align="center">C</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MLAS</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zeolite A</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PEG</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbonate</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble graft polymer (1)</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble polymer (2)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble polymer (4)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">(Formulation Example 2: Liquid detergent model composed mainly of nonions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">D</entry><entry align="center">E</entry><entry align="center">F</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MBAS</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="center">32</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MEA</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">EtOH</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PG</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble graft polymer (2)</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble polymer (1)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble polymer (3)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">(Formulation Example 3: Anhydrous liquid detergent model composed mainly of anions) Formulation</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">G</entry><entry align="center">H</entry><entry align="center">I</entry><entry align="center">J</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MBAS</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">14</entry><entry align="center">14</entry></row><row><entry align="left">LAS</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="center">32</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sulfate</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">BPP</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">20</entry></row><row><entry align="left">C<sub>12-14</sub> Alcohol EO<sub>5</sub> adduct</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbonate</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">NOBS</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PB1</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">15</entry><entry align="center">13</entry><entry align="center">15</entry></row><row><entry align="left" morerows="1">Water-soluble graft polymer (2) Water-soluble polymer (1)</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="right" namest="2"/><entry align="center" namest="3">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble polymer (3)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble polymer (4)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">3</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Clay dispersibility of detergent formulations:</u></heading><heading>Evaluation methods</heading><heading>(1) Clay dispersibility of detergent formulations (calcium carbonate: 50 ppm):</heading><p num="0108">Pure water is added to 67.56 g of glycine, 52.6 g of sodium chloride, and 2.4 g of
NaOH to make 600 g (buffer (1)). To 60 g of the buffer (1), is added 0.0817 g of calcium
chloride dihydrate, to which is then added pure water to make 1,000 g (buffer (2)). To 4
g of an aqueous solution of 1 % by weight of the detergent formulation is 36 g of the
buffer (2), and the mixture is stirred to prepare a dispersion. In a test tube (manufactured
by Maruemu Corporation, diameter: 18 mm, height: 180 mm), is charged 0.3 g of a clay
(JIS test powder I, class 11, available from The Association of Powder Process Industry
and Engineering, Japan), to which is then added 30 g of the dispersion, followed by
sealing the test tube. The test tube is shaken to uniformly disperse the clay. Thereafter,
the test tube is allowed to stand in a place where the sun is not directly caught for 20
hours. After 20 hours, 5 cc of a supernatant of the dispersion is taken and measured for
absorbance by a UV spectrometer (UV-1200 Model, manufactured by Shimadzu
Corporation, 1 cm-cell, wavelength: 380 nm). </p><heading>(2) Clay dispersibility of detergent formulations (calcium carbonate: 200 ppm):</heading><p num="0109">Pure water is added to 67.56 g of glycine, 52.6 g of sodium chloride, and 2.4 g of
NaOH to make 600 g (buffer (1)). To 60 g of the buffer (1), is added 0.3268 g of calcium
chloride dihydrate, to which is then added pure water to make 1,000 g (buffer (2)). To 4
g of an aqueous solution of 1 % by weight of the detergent formulation is 36 g of the
buffer (2), and the mixture is stirred to prepare a dispersion. In a test tube (manufactured
by Maruemu Corporation, diameter: 18 mm, height: 180 mm), is charged 0.3 g of a clay
(JIS test powder I, class 11, available from The Association of Powder Process Industry
and Engineering, Japan), to which is then added 30 g of the dispersion, followed by
sealing the test tube. The test tube is shaken to uniformly disperse the clay. Thereafter,
the test tube is allowed to stand in a place where the sun is not directly caught for 20
hours. After 20 hours, 5 cc of a supernatant of the dispersion is taken and measured for
absorbance by a UV spectrometer (UV-1200 Model, manufactured by Shimadzu
Corporation, 1 cm-cell, wavelength: 380 nm).</p><p num="0110">Each of the following mid-chain branched surfactant compositions was
incorporated with a polyalkylene glycol chain-containing polycarboxylic acid-based
polymer to prepare a detergent formulation, whose dispersibility to clay was then
measured.</p><p num="0111">The formulation amounts of the detergent formulation and the polymer are as
follows. <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">(Formulation Example 1': Powder detergent model composed mainly of anions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">B'</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Formulation Example 1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MLAS</entry> <entry align="center">41</entry><entry align="center">41</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">4</entry> <entry align="center">4</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium carbonate</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">44</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble polymer (2)</entry><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PSA</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Clay dispersibility</entry><entry align="center">0.43</entry><entry align="center">0.40</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">(Formulation Example 2': Liquid detergent model composed mainly of nonions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">D</entry><entry align="center">E</entry><entry align="center">F</entry><entry align="left">Comparative Formulation Example 2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MBAS</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="center">32</entry><entry align="center">32</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MEA</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">EtOH</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PG</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble graft polymer (2)</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble polymer (1)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water-soluble polymer (3)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Citrate</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Clay dispersibility</entry><entry align="center">0.58</entry><entry align="center">1.05</entry><entry align="center">1.00</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0112">With respect to the (meth)acrylic acid-based polymers according to the invention,
the weight average molecular weight, anti-gelling capacity, and terminal sulfonic acid
group were measured or quantitatively determined in the following manners.</p><heading>(1) Measurement of weight average molecular weight and number average molecular
weight:</heading><p num="0113">The weight average molecular weight (hereinafter abbreviated as "Mw") of the 
(meth)acrylic acid-based polymer was measured by GPC (gel permeation
chromatography). At this time, Model GF-7MHQ (a trade name, manufactured by
Showa Denko K.K.) was used as a column of GPC. As a mobile phase, was used an
aqueous solution prepared by adding ion-exchanged water (hereinafter referred to as
"pure water") to 34.5 g of disodium hydrogenphosphate dodecahydrate and 46.2 g of
sodium dihydrogenphosphate dihydrate to make 5,000 g in total and filtering the mixture
through a 0.45-µm membrane filter. Incidentally, any of the reagents as used herein are
of a special grade. Further, all of the reagents as used in the measurement of degree of
gelation and Examples as described blow are of a special grade. As a detector, was used
Model 481, manufactured by Waters Corporation (detection wavelength UV: 214 nm).
As a pump, was used Model L-7110 (manufactured by Hitachi, Ltd.). The flow rate of
the mobile phase was defined as 0.5 ml/min., and the temperature was set up at 35 °C. A
calibration curve was prepared by using a standard sample of sodium polyacrylate
manufactured by Sowa Kagaku K.K.</p><heading>(2) Measurement of degree of gelation:</heading><p num="0114">In the measurement of the degree of gelation, a boric acid buffer solution, a
calcium chloride aqueous solution, and a 1 % polymer aqueous solution were first
prepared. The boric acid buffer solution is one prepared by adding pure water to 7.42 g
of boric acid, 1.75 g of sodium chloride and 7.63 g of sodium borate decahydrate to
make 1,000 g in total. The calcium chloride aqueous solution is one prepared by adding
pure water to 0.735 g of calcium chloride dihydrate to make 2,500 g in total. The 1 %
polymer aqueous solution is one prepared by diluting the polymer according to the
invention with pure water to make 1 % in concentration.</p><p num="0115">Next, prescribed amounts of the foregoing solutions were charged in a 500-mL
tall beaker in a prescribed order. The prescribed amounts and the prescribed order are as 
follows. First, 250 ml of pure water was charged; secondly, 10 ml of the boric acid
buffer solution was charged; thirdly, 5 ml of the 1 % by weight polymer aqueous solution
was charged; and finally, 250 ml of the calcium chloride aqueous solution was charged.</p><p num="0116">The respective solutions thus charged in this order were mixed to make the
polymer according to the invention gel, thereby preparing a test solution. The tall beaker
having the test solution charged therein was lidded and allowed to stand for one hour in
a thermostatic chamber previously regulated at 90 °C. After one hour, the test solution
was immediately charged in a 5-cm quartz cell and measured for an absorbance <u style="single">a</u> at a
UV wavelength of 380 nm.</p><p num="0117">Separately, among the above four ingredients charged as the test solution, 250 ml
of the calcium chloride aqueous solution was replaced by 250 ml of pure water to
prepare a blank solution. This black solution was subjected to the same procedures as in
the test solution to measure an absorbance <u style="single">b</u> (blank value) at a UV wavelength of 3 80 nm.
The degree of gelation was calculated from the absorbance <u style="single">a</u> and the blank value <u style="single">b</u>
according to the following equation.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">(Degree of gelation) = a- b</st32:df></p><p num="0118">Using this degree of gelation, an anti-gelling capacity (Q value) was calculated
according to the following equation.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Q = (Degree of gelation) × 10<st32:sup pos="post">5</st32:sup>/Mw</st32:df></p><heading>(3) Measurement of S amount contained in the polymer and pre-S amount:</heading><p num="0119">The S amount of the (meth)acrylic acid-based polymer before and after the
treatment was quantitatively determined by inductively coupled plasma (ICP) emission
spectrometry. Here, the S amount of the (meth)acrylic acid-based polymer before
dialysis was defined as "pre-S amount), and the S amount of the (meth)acrylic
acid-based polymer after the dialysis was defined as "S amount contained in the 
polymer", respectively. The dialysis will be described below.</p><heading>Dialysis</heading><p num="0120"><sl><li>(1) A suitable amount of water was added to the (meth)acrylic acid-based
polymer (or its aqueous solution) to prepare a (meth)acrylic acid-based polymer aqueous
solution having a solids content of 30 % by weight, and 20 g of the (meth)acrylic
acid-based polymer aqueous solution was then charged in a dialysis membrane having a
length of 40 cm, followed by sealing. As the dialysis membrane, was used Spectra/Por
Membrane MWCO: 1000, molecular weight cut off: 1,000 (manufactured by Spectrum
Laboratories, Inc.). (Incidentally, any dialysis membranes having a molecular weight
cut off equal to this dialysis membrane may be employed in the invention.)</li><li>(2) The resulting dialysis membrane was dipped in 2,000 g of water charged in a
2-L beaker and stirred with a stirrer.</li><li>(3) Six hours later, the dialysis membrane was taken out from the beaker, the
outside of the dialysis membrane was well rinsed with water, and the contents of the
dialysis membrane were then taken out.</li><li>(4) The resulting contents were concentrated by an evaporator to prepare a
(meth)acrylic acid-based polymer sample after the dialysis treatment.
As the (meth)acrylic acid-based polymer sample before the dialysis treatment,
was used one prepared by concentrating the (meth)acrylic acid-based polymer obtained
by the polymerization as in (1) above by the evaporator in the same manner as in (4)
above.</li></sl></p><heading>(4) Quantitative determination of terminal sulfonic acid group and measurement of R
value:</heading><p num="0121">Kind:  Varian Gemini2000 (200 MHz)

Resonance frequency:  199.93 MHz
 
Probe:  5 mm Switchable probe

Observation nucleus:   Hydrogen nucleus

Measurement conditions:
<dl compact="compact" tsize="22"><dt>90 Degree pulse:</dt><dd>100 µsec. (irradiation with 45 degree pulse)</dd><dt>Waiting time:</dt><dd>1.254 sec.</dd><dt>Number of integration:</dt><dd>16 times</dd><dt>Temperature:</dt><dd>Room temperature</dd></dl></p><heading>Sample preparation:</heading><p num="0122">D<sub>2</sub>O was added to 0.1 g of the (meth)acrylic acid-based polymer from which the
solvent had been removed upon drying in vacuo to make 1.0 g and completely dissolved
to prepare a sample.</p><p num="0123">The quantitative determination of the terminal sulfonic acid group was
performed by first measuring the (meth)acrylic acid-based polymer obtained in an
aqueous solution state by <sup>1</sup>H-NMR (D<sub>2</sub>O solvent). As a result, a peak of methylene
hydrogen derived from the sulfonic acid group was detected in the vicinity of 2.4 ppm,
and a peak of methylene hydrogen derived from the sulfonic acid group was detected in
the vicinity of 3.0 ppm, respectively, the both peaks being not observed in the case of the
polymerization using the persulfate (NaPS) alone.</p><p num="0124">Then, an integration ratio of these peaks to peaks of methylene hydrogen in the
backbone of sodium polyacrylate and methylene hydrogen (in the vicinity of from about
1 to 2.2 ppm) was calculated, thereby undergoing the quantitative determination of the
terminal sulfonic acid group of the (meth)acrylic acid-based polymer.</p><heading>(5) Measurement of iron ion concentration:</heading><p num="0125">The iron ion concentration of the (meth)acrylic acid-based polymer was
quantitatively determined according to ICP emission spectrometry. </p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 7</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Sulfonic acid group-terminated (meth)acrylic acid-based polymer having an anti-gelling
capacity of less than 2.0:</u></heading><p num="0126">In a 5-liters volume SUS-made separable flask equipped with a reflux condenser
and a stirrer, 300 g of pure water was charged (initial charging) and elevated to the
boiling point while stirring. Subsequently, 720 g (i.e., 8 mole) of an 80 % acrylic acid
aqueous solution (hereinafter abbreviated as "80 % AA"), 106.7 g (2 g/mole, as reduced
into the amount of the monomer as charged) of a 15 % sodium persulfate aqueous
solution (hereinafter abbreviated as "15 % NaPS"), 182.9 g (8 g/mole, as reduced into
the amount of the monomer as charged) of a 35 % sodium bisulfite aqueous solution
(hereinafter abbreviated as "35 % SBS"), and 126.5 g of pure water were added
dropwise from separate dropping nozzles to the polymerization reaction system in the
boiling point-reflux state with stirring over 120 minutes.</p><p num="0127">After completion of the dropwise addition, the reaction solution was further kept
(aged) in the boiling point-reflux state over 30 minutes to complete the polymerization.
After completion of the polymerization, the reaction solution was allowed to cool and
then neutralized by gradually adding dropwise 600 g (i.e., 7.2 moles) of a 48 % sodium
hydroxide aqueous solution (hereinafter abbreviated as "48 % NaOH") thereto while
stirring. There was thus obtained an aqueous solution of sodium polyacrylate (1)
(hereafter referred to as "polymer (1)") having a solids content of 40 % and a final
degree of neutralization of 90 %.</p><p num="0128">The resulting polymer (1) had a weight average molecular weight (Mw) of 8,700,
an anti-gelling capacity (Q value) of 1.09, and an amount (measured value) of terminal
sulfonic acid group of SBS/AA= 1/13.8 (mole) [charging ratio: 1/13 (by mole)].</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 8</b></heading><heading><u style="single">(Meth)acrylic acid-based polymer having a sulfur introduction amount (S value) of 35 or
more:</u></heading><heading><u style="single">(Meth)acrylic acid-based polymer having an R value of from 1 to 15:</u></heading><p num="0129">In a 2.5-liters volume SUS-made separable flask equipped with a reflux
condenser and a stirrer, 156.5 g of pure water was charged (initial charging) and elevated
to 90 °C while stirring. Subsequently, 427.5 g (i.e., 4.75 mole) of 80 % AA, 63.5 g (i.e.,
0.25 moles) of a 37 % sodium acrylate aqueous solution (hereafter abbreviated as "37 %
SA"), 66.7 g (2.0 g/mole, as reduced into the amount of the monomer as charged) of
15 % NaPS, and 71.4 g (5.0 g/mole, as reduced into the amount of the monomer as
charged) of 35 % SBS were added dropwise from separate dropping nozzles to the
polymerization reaction system in a constant state at about 90 °C with stirring. The
dropwise addition time was 300 minutes for 80 % AA, 37 % SA and 35 % SBS and 310
minutes for 15 % NaPS, respectively.</p><p num="0130">After completion of the dropwise addition, the reaction solution was further kept
at 90 °C over 30 minutes to complete the polymerization. After completion of the
polymerization, the reaction solution was allowed to cool and then neutralized by
gradually adding dropwise 366.7 g (i.e., 4.40 moles) of 48 % NaOH thereto while
stirring. There was thus obtained an aqueous solution of sodium polyacrylate (2)
(hereafter referred to as "polymer (2)") having a solids content of 45 % and a final
degree of neutralization of 93 %.</p><p num="0131">The resulting polymer (2) had a weight average molecular weight of 5,800, a
number average molecular weight of 2,400, an S value of 49, an R value of 5.0, a Q
value of 2.02, and an iron ion concentration of 1.40 ppm.</p><heading><u style="single">Performance evaluation:</u></heading><p num="0132">Detergent formulations and formation amounts of polymer are as follows. <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">(Formulation Example 4: Powder detergent model composed mainly of anions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">B</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MLAS</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zeolite A</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PEG</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbonate</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer (1)</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer (2)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">(Formulation Example 5: Powder detergent model composed mainly of nonions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="center">D</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MBAS</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">31</entry><entry align="center">31</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zeolite A</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PEG</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbonate</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer (1)</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer (2)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Clay dispersibility of detergent formulations:</u></heading><p num="0133">The dispersion ability of each detergent formulation comprising the polymer
having the following mid-chain branched surfactant composition incorporated therein to
clay was measured in the same manner as described above.</p><p num="0134">Detergent formulations and formation amounts of polymer are as follows. <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">(Formulation Example 4': Powder detergent model composed mainly of anions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">A'</entry><entry align="center">B'</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Formulation Example 1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MLAS</entry><entry align="center">41</entry><entry align="center">41</entry><entry align="center">41</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium carbonate</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">44</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer (1)</entry><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer (2)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PSA</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Clay dispersibility (calcium carbonate: 50 ppm)</entry><entry align="center">0.43</entry><entry align="center">0.44</entry><entry align="center">0.40</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">(Formulation Example 5': Powder detergent model composed mainly of nonions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="center">D</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Formulation Example 2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MBAS</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">41</entry><entry align="center">41</entry><entry align="center">41</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbonate</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">44</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer (1)</entry><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer (2)</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PSA</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Clay dispersibility (calcium carbonate: 200 ppm)</entry><entry align="center">0.59</entry><entry align="center">0.60</entry><entry align="center">0.55</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0135">With respect to the acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based polymers
according to the invention, the weight average molecular weight, clay dispersibility, and
calcium ion-binding capacity were measured or quantitatively determined in the
following manners.</p><heading>(1) Measurement of weight average molecular weight and number average molecular
weight:</heading><p num="0136">The weight average molecular weight (hereinafter abbreviated as "Mw") of the
acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based polymer was measured by GPC (gel
permeation chromatography). At this time, Model GF-7MHQ (a trade name,
manufactured by Showa Denko K.K.) was used as a column of GPC. As a mobile phase,
was used an aqueous solution prepared by adding ion-exchanged water (hereinafter
referred to as "pure water") to 34.5 g of disodium hydrogenphosphate dodecahydrate
and 46.2 g of sodium dihydrogenphosphate dihydrate to make 5,000 g in total and
filtering the mixture through a 0.45-µm membrane filter. Incidentally, any of the
reagents as used herein are of a special grade. Further, all of the reagents as used in the
measurement of degree of gelation and Examples as described blow are of a special
grade. As a detector, was used Model 481, manufactured by Waters Corporation
(detection wavelength UV: 214 nm). As a pump, was used Model L-7110
(manufactured by Hitachi, Ltd.). The flow rate of the mobile phase was defined as 0.5
ml/min., and the temperature was set up at 35 °C. A calibration curve was prepared by
using a standard sample of sodium polyacrylate manufactured by Sowa Kagaku K.K.</p><heading>(2) Clay-dispersibility:</heading><heading>Clay-dispersibility in high-hardness water (calcium concentration: 200 ppm)</heading><p num="0137">First, ion-exchanged water was added to 67.56 g of glycine, 52.6 g of sodium
chloride, and 60 ml of 1N-NaOH to make 600 g, thereby preparing a glycine buffer
solution. To 60 g of the preparation liquid, was added 0.3268 g of calcium chloride
dihydrate, to which was then added ion-exchanged water to make 1,000 g, thereby
preparing a dispersion.</p><p num="0138">Next, an aqueous solution of the polymer (adjusted at a pH of 7) of 0.1 % as
reduced into solids content was prepared. In a test tube, was charged 0.3 g of 8 kinds of
a clay (JIS test powder I, class 11 (Kanto loam, fine granules, available from The 
Association of Powder Process Industry and Engineering, Japan), to which was then
added 3 g of the foregoing preparation liquid. As this time, the calcium concentration of
this test solution is 200 ppm as reduced into calcium carbonate.</p><p num="0139">The test tube was sealed by a paraffin film and lightly shaken such that the clay
was uniformly dispersed, and further shaken 20 times in the vertical direction. The
resulting test tube was allowed to stand in a place where the sun was not directly caught
for 20 hours. Thereafter, 5 ml of a supernatant of the dispersion was collected by means
of a transfer pipette. This solution was measured for transmittance (T %) in a 1-cm cell
at a wavelength of 380 nm by means of a spectrometer. A value obtained by subtracting
this T % from 100 was defined as a clay-dispersibility (cloudiness).</p><heading>Clay-dispersibility in low-hardness water (calcium concentration: 50 ppm)</heading><p num="0140">The clay-dispersibility in low-hardness water was determined in the same
manner as in the foregoing measurement of the clay-dispersibility in high-hardness
water, except that the addition amount of the calcium chloride dihydrate was changed to
0.0817 g (50 ppm as reduced into calcium carbonate).</p><heading>(3) Calcium ion-binding capacity:</heading><heading>Calcium ion-binding capacity</heading><p num="0141">First, a calcium ion standard aqueous solution (aqueous solution for calibration
curve) was prepared in the following manner. That is, using calcium chloride dihydrate,
50 cc of each of aqueous solutions having a Ca<sup>2+</sup> ion concentration of 0.01 moles/liter,
0.001 moles/liter and 0.0001 moles/liter was prepared, and the pH of each aqueous
solution was adjusted at from 9 to 11 with a 4.8 % sodium hydrochloride aqueous
solution, to which was then added 1 ml of an aqueous solution of 4 moles/liter of
potassium chloride.</p><p num="0142">Next, a sample aqueous solution for measurement was prepared. That is, the 
polymer (adjusted at a pH of 7) in an amount of 10 mg as reduced into solids content was
weighed in a 100-ml beaker, to which was then added 50 ml of the aqueous solution
having a calcium ion concentration of 0.001 moles/liter as adjusted with sodium chloride
dihydrate. The mixture was uniformly stirred by means of a stirrer, the pH of the
mixture was adjusted at from 9 to 11 with a 4.8 % sodium hydroxide aqueous solution,
and 1 ml of an aqueous solution of 4 moles/liter of potassium chloride was then added
thereto.</p><p num="0143">The measurement was carried out with calcium ion electrodes 93-20
(manufactured by Orion Corporation) by using an ion analyzer EA920 (manufactured by
Orion Corporation). The calcium ion amount captured by the sample was determined
from the calibration curve and the measured value of the sample (polymer), and the
binding amount per gram of the solids content of the polymer was expressed in terms of
milligram number as reduced into calcium carbonate. This value was defined as a
calcium ion-binding value.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 9</b></heading><heading>Acrylic acid/maleic acid composition ratio = 80/20 by mole:</heading><p num="0144">In a 2.5-liters volume SUS-made separable flask equipped with a thermometer, a
stirrer and a reflux condenser, was charged 282.8 g of ion-exchanged water (hereinafter
referred to as "pure water"), and the aqueous solution was elevated to the boiling point in
the reflux state while stirring. Next, 360.0 g of an 80 % by weight acrylic acid aqueous
solution (hereinafter referred to as "80 % AA"), 98.0 g of maleic anhydride (hereinafter
referred to as "MA"), 133.3 g of a 15 % by weight sodium persulfate aqueous solution
(hereinafter referred to as "15 % NaPS"), 85.7 g of a 35 % by weight hydrogen peroxide
aqueous solution (hereinafter referred to as "35 % H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>), and 350.0 g of a 48 % by
weight sodium hydroxide aqueous solution (hereinafter referred to as "48 % NaOH") 
were continuously added dropwise at uniform rates from separate dropping nozzles over
180 minutes from the initiation of the polymerization, 150 minutes from the initiation of
the polymerization, 190 minutes from the initiation of the polymerization, 120 minutes
from the initiation of the polymerization, and 180 minutes from the initiation of the
polymerization, respectively, while keeping the reflux state with stirring. After the
completion of the dropwise addition of all of the aqueous solutions, the boiling point
reflux state was kept over 20 minutes. Finally, 100.0 g of 48 % NaOH was added to the
reaction mixture to complete the polymerization.</p><p num="0145">There was thus obtained an acrylic acid/maleic acid copolymer 1 having a solids
content of 40.3 % (hereinafter referred to as "polymer 1"). The resulting polymer 1 had
a weight average molecular weight (Mw) of 5,800.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 10</b></heading><heading>Acrylic acid/maleic acid composition ratio = 50/50 by mole:</heading><p num="0146">In a 2.5-liters volume SUS-made separable flask equipped with a thermometer, a
stirrer and a reflux condenser, was charged 196.5 g of pure water, and the aqueous
solution was elevated to the boiling point in the reflux state while stirring. Next, 180.0 g
of 80 % AA, 196.0 g of MA, 106.7 g of 15 % NaPS, 68.6 g of 35 % H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, 300.0 g of
48 % NaOH, and 136.9 g of pure water were continuously added dropwise at uniform
rates from separate dropping nozzles over 180 minutes from the initiation of the
polymerization, 70 minutes from the initiation of the polymerization, 190 minutes from
the initiation of the polymerization, 150 minutes from the initiation of the
polymerization, 180 minutes from the initiation of the polymerization, and 180 minutes
from the initiation of the polymerization, respectively, while keeping the reflux state
with stirring. After the completion of the dropwise addition of all of the aqueous
solutions, the boiling point reflux state was kept over 20 minutes. Finally, 125.0 g of 
48 % NaOH was added to the reaction mixture to complete the polymerization.</p><p num="0147">There was thus obtained an acrylic acid/maleic acid copolymer 2 having a solids
content of 39.4 % (hereinafter referred to as "polymer 2"). The resulting polymer 2 had
a weight average molecular weight (Mw) of 3,200.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 11</b></heading><heading>Acrylic acid/maleic acid composition ratio = 70/30 by mole:</heading><p num="0148">In a 2.5-liters volume SUS-made separable flask equipped with a thermometer, a
stirrer and a reflux condenser, was charged 260.0 g of pure water, and the aqueous
solution was elevated to the boiling point in the reflux state while stirring. Next, 252.0 g
of 80 % AA, 117.6 g of MA, 106.7 g of 15 % NaPS, 68.6 g of 35 % H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, and 216.7 g of
48 % NaOH were continuously added dropwise at uniform rates from separate dropping
nozzles over 240 minutes from the initiation of the polymerization, 180 minutes from
the initiation of the polymerization, 250 minutes from the initiation of the
polymerization, 120 minutes from the initiation of the polymerization, and 240 minutes
from the initiation of the polymerization, respectively, while keeping the reflux state
with stirring. After the completion of the dropwise addition of all of the aqueous
solutions, the boiling point reflux state was kept over 50 minutes. Finally, 164.7 g of
48 % NaOH was added to the reaction mixture to complete the polymerization.</p><p num="0149">There was thus obtained an acrylic acid/maleic acid copolymer 3 having a solids
content of 39.9 % (hereinafter referred to as "polymer 3"). The resulting polymer 3 had
a weight average molecular weight (Mw) of 6,300.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 12</b></heading><heading>Acrylic acid/maleic acid composition ratio = 60/40 by mole:</heading><p num="0150">In a 2.5-liters volume SUS-made separable flask equipped with a thermometer, a
stirrer and a reflux condenser, was initially charged 295.0 g of pure water, and the 
aqueous solution was elevated to the boiling point in the reflux state while stirring. Next,
216.0 g of 80 % AA, 156.8 g of MA, 106.7 g of 15 % NaPS, 68.6 g of 35 % H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, and
256.7 g of 48 % NaOH were continuously added dropwise at uniform rates from
separate dropping nozzles over 180 minutes from the initiation of the polymerization,
100 minutes from the initiation of the polymerization, 190 minutes from the initiation of
the polymerization, 120 minutes from the initiation of the polymerization, and 240
minutes from the initiation of the polymerization, respectively, while keeping the reflux
state with stirring. After the completion of the dropwise addition of all of the aqueous
solutions, the boiling point reflux state was kept over 50 minutes. Finally, 140.0 g of
48 % NaOH was added to the reaction mixture to complete the polymerization.</p><p num="0151">There was thus obtained an acrylic acid/maleic acid copolymer 4 having a solids
content of 39.4 % (hereinafter referred to as "polymer 4"). The resulting polymer 4 had
a weight average molecular weight (Mw) of 4,900.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 13</b></heading><heading>Acrylic acid/maleic acid composition ratio = 52/48 by mole:</heading><p num="0152">In a 5-liters volume SUS-made separable flask equipped with a thermometer, a
stirrer and a reflux condenser, were charged 310.0 g of pure water and 450 g of maleic
anhydride, to which was then gradually added 708.3 g of 48 % by weight NaOH while
stirring. Thus, the initial degree of neutralization was 85 % by mole, and the initial
solids content was 50.9 % by weight. Thereafter, the aqueous solution was elevated to
the boiling point in the reflux state while stirring. Next, 450.0 g of 80 % AA, 100 g of
35 % H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, 200.0 g of 15 % NaPS, and 30 g of pure water were continuously added
dropwise at uniform rates from separate dropping nozzles over 120 minutes from the
initiation of the polymerization, 50 minutes from the initiation of the polymerization,
130 minutes from 50 minutes after the initiation of the polymerization, and 130 minutes 
from 50 minutes after the initiation of the polymerization, respectively, while keeping
the reflux state with stirring. After the completion of the dropwise addition of all of the
aqueous solutions, the boiling point reflux state was kept over 20 minutes. Finally, the
pH of the acrylic acid/maleic acid copolymer aqueous solution was adjusted at 8 with
48 % NaOH.</p><p num="0153">There was thus obtained an acrylic acid/maleic acid copolymer 5 (hereinafter
referred to as "polymer 5"). The resulting polymer 5 had a weight average molecular
weight (Mw) of 10,000 and a number average molecular weight of 2,900. That is, the
molecular weight distribution was 3.45.</p><heading><b>SYNTHESIS EXAMPLE 14</b></heading><heading>Acrylic acid/maleic acid composition ratio = 71/29 by mole:</heading><p num="0154">In a 5-liters volume SUS 316-made separable flask equipped with a thermometer,
a stirrer and a reflux condenser, were charged 281.3 g of pure water and 176.4 g of
maleic anhydride, to which was then gradually added 300 g of 48 % by weight NaOH
while stirring. Thus, the initial degree of neutralization was 100 % by mole, and the
initial solids content was 38.1 % by weight. Thereafter, the aqueous solution was
elevated to the boiling point in the reflux state while stirring. Next, 401.7 g of 80 % AA,
89.3 g of 35 % H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, 124.6 g of 15 % NaPS, and 177.5 g of pure water were
continuously added dropwise at uniform rates from separate dropping nozzles over 240
minutes from the initiation of the polymerization, 240 minutes from the initiation of the
polymerization, 245 minutes from the initiation of the polymerization, and 246 minutes
from 90 minutes after the initiation of the polymerization, respectively, while keeping
the reflux state with stirring. After the completion of the dropwise addition of all of the
aqueous solutions, the boiling point reflux state was kept over 30 minutes. Thereafter,
263 g of 48 % by weight NaOH was added to the reaction mixture, to which were then 
added 27.9 g of 35 % by weight sodium hydrogensulfite, 50.9 g of 48 % by weight
NaOH, and 128.6 g of water, to prepare an acrylic acid/maleic acid copolymer aqueous
solution.</p><p num="0155">There was thus obtained an acrylic acid/maleic acid copolymer 6 (hereinafter
referred to as "polymer 6"). The resulting polymer 6 had a weight average molecular
weight (Mw) of 11,000 and a number average molecular weight of 2,800. That is, the
molecular weight distribution was 3.93.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">AA/MA (mole/mole)</entry><entry align="center">80/20</entry><entry align="center">50/50</entry><entry align="center">70/30</entry><entry align="center">60/40</entry><entry align="center">52/48</entry><entry align="center">71/29</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mw</entry><entry align="center">5,800</entry><entry align="center">3,200</entry><entry align="center">6,300</entry><entry align="center">4,800</entry><entry align="center">10,000</entry><entry align="center">11,000</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Clay-dispersibility (calcium carbonate: 50 ppm)</entry><entry align="center">0.77</entry><entry align="center">0.71</entry><entry align="center">0.77</entry><entry align="center">0.67</entry><entry align="center">0.69</entry><entry align="center">0.75</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Clay-dispersibility (calcium carbonate: 200 ppm)</entry><entry align="center">0.47</entry><entry align="center">0.09</entry><entry align="center">0.51</entry><entry align="center">0.10</entry><entry align="center">0.07</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Calcium ion-binding capacity (mg/g)</entry><entry align="center">283</entry><entry align="center">355</entry><entry align="center">315</entry><entry align="center">336</entry><entry align="center">422</entry><entry align="center">348</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Performance evaluation:</u></heading><p num="0156">Detergent formulations and formation amounts of polymer are as follows.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry nameend="7" namest="1">(Formulation Example 6: Powder detergent model composed mainly of anions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">A</entry><entry align="center">B</entry><entry align="center">C</entry><entry align="center">D</entry><entry align="center">E</entry><entry align="center">H</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MLAS</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zeolite A</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PEG</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbonate</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry><entry align="center">29</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 1</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 2</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 3</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 4</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 6</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">(Formulation Example 7: Powder detergent model composed mainly of nonions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">F</entry><entry align="center">G</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MBAS</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">31</entry><entry align="center">31</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zeolite A</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">30</entry></row><row><entry align="left">PEG</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbonate</entry><entry align="center">25</entry><entry align="center">25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 1</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 3</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Clay dispersibility of detergent formulations:</u></heading><p num="0157">The dispersion force of each detergent formulation comprising the polymer
having the following mid-chain branched surfactant composition incorporated therein to
clay was measured in the same manner as described above.</p><p num="0158">Detergent formulations and formation amounts of polymer are as follows.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">(Formulation Example 6': Powder detergent model composed mainly of anions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">A'</entry><entry align="center">B'</entry><entry align="center">H'</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Formulation Example 1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MLAS</entry><entry align="center">41</entry><entry align="center">41</entry><entry align="center">41</entry><entry align="center">41</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Sodium carbonate</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">45</entry><entry align="center">44</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 1</entry><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 6</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">6</entry></row><row><entry align="left">AA/MA</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Clay dispersibility (calcium carbonate: 50 ppm)</entry><entry align="center">0.54</entry><entry align="center">0.50</entry><entry align="center">0.56</entry><entry align="center">0.41</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">(Formulation Example 7': Powder detergent model composed mainly of nonions)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Formulation</entry><entry align="center">F'</entry><entry align="center">G'</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Formulation Example 2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">MBAS</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SFT</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">44</entry></row><row><entry align="left">SMA</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Carbonate</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">44</entry><entry align="center">44</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 1</entry><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polymer 3</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">AA/MA</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Clay dispersibility (calcium carbonate: 200 ppm)</entry><entry align="center">0.46</entry><entry align="center">0.43</entry><entry align="center">0.35</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0159">The invention relates to detergent compositions comprising a specific polymer
and an alkyl mid-chain branched surfactant. These detergent compositions have high
detergency against stains such as mud and carbon black, enhance anti-gelling properties
to calcium ions, etc., and enhance detergency at low temperatures or under
high-hardness conditions.</p><p num="0160">It should further be apparent to those skilled in the art that various changes in
form and detail of the invention as shown and described above may be made. It is
intended that such changes be included within the spirit and scope of the claims
appended hereto.</p><p num="0161">This application is based on Japanese Patent Application Nos. 2002-114307 filed
April 17, 2002, 2002-116172 filed April 18, 2002, 2002-116181 filed April 18, 2002 and
2002-228216 filed August 6, 2002, the disclosures of which are incorporated herein by
reference in their entireties.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A detergent composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>at least 0.1 % by weight of at least one polymer selected from the group
consisting of 1) a polycarboxylic acid-based polymer containing a polyalkylene glycol
chain in the structure thereof, 2) a sulfonic acid group-terminated (meth)acrylic
acid-based polymer, and 3) an acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based copolymer
having a clay dispersibility under a condition of 50 ppm of calcium carbonate of 0.3 or
more, and</claim-text><claim-text>at least 0.5 % by weight of a longer alkyl chain mid-chain branched surfactant
compound represented by the following formula:
R-X-Y</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) R is a hydrophobic C9 to C22, as total carbons in the moiety, mid-chain
branched alkyl moiety having: (1) a longest linear carbon chain attached to the -X - Y
moiety in the range of from 8 to 21 carbon atoms; (2) one or more C1 - C3 alkyl moieties
branching from this longest linear carbon chain; (3) at least one of the branching alkyl
moieties is attached directly to a carbon of the longest linear carbon chain at a position
within the range of position 2 carbon (counting from carbon 1 which is attached to the
-X-Y moiety) to position ω - 2 carbon (the terminal carbon minus 2 carbons); and (4)
the surfactant composition has an average total number of carbon atoms in the R-X
moiety in the above formula within the range of greater than 14 to 18;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) Y is a hydrophilic moiety selected from sulfates, sulfonates, amine oxides,
and polyoxyalkylenes; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) X is selected from -CH2- and -C(O)-.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The detergent composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the polycarboxylic
acid-based polymer is a water-soluble graft polymer comprising a polyalkylene glycol
having a monoethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid-based monomer graft
polymerized thereon.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The detergent composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the polycarboxylic
acid-based polymer is a water-soluble graft polymer comprising a polyalkylene
glycol-containing ethylenically unsaturated monomer (not containing an ester bond
between the polyalkylene glycol chain and the ethylenically unsaturated bond) having a
monoethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid-based monomer copolymerized
therewith.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The detergent composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the polycarboxylic
acid-based polymer is a water-soluble graft polymer comprising a polyalkylene
glycol-containing ethylenically unsaturated monomer (containing an ester bond between
the polyalkylene glycol chain and the ethylenically unsaturated bond) having a
monoethylenically unsaturated carboxylic acid-based monomer copolymerized
therewith.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The detergent composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the (meth)acrylic
acid-based polymer is a polymer comprising from 50 to 100 mole % of (meth)acrylic
acid and from 0 to 50 mole % of a water-soluble monoethylenically unsaturated
monomer that is copolymerizable with (meth)acrylic acid, having a sulfonic acid group
at the terminals thereof and having an anti-gelling capacity Q, as defined by the
following equation, of less than 2.0:Q = [(Degree of gelation) × 105]/(Weight average molecular weight)</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The detergent composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the (meth)acrylic
acid-based polymer has an introduction amount of sulfur element, S value, as defined by
the following equation, of 35 or more:
S = (S amount contained in the polymer)/(Total S amount) × 100</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The detergent composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the (meth)acrylic
acid-based polymer has an R value, as defined by the following equation, of from 1 to 15
in the 1H-NMR spectrum:
R = (Integration ratio of signal at 2.3 to 4.3 ppm)/(Integration ratio at 0.8 to 4.3
ppm containing PSA signal) × 100</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The detergent composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the acrylic acid
(salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based copolymer is an acrylic acid (salt)-maleic acid
(salt)-based copolymer having a clay dispersibility under a condition of 200 ppm of
calcium carbonate of 0.2 or more.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The detergent composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the acrylic acid
(salt)-maleic acid (salt)-based copolymer has a calcium ion-binding capacity of 250
mg/g or more.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The detergent composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the detergent
composition is a liquid detergent composition and/or a gel detergent composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The detergent composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the detergent
composition is a powder detergent compsosition.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>