<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1264893-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1264893" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="8177673" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20021211"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1264893-A1" status="new" fvid="23640754"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1264893</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20021211</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01113962-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01113962</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010608</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-01113962-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01113962</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010608</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/00        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23K   1/00        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23L   1/03        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A23L   1/03        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  35/66        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  35/74        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   9/90        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N   9/90        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N  15/61        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N  15/61        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12P   7/64        20060101A I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12P   7/64        20060101C I20051110RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A23K   1/00C2B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A23L   1/03M</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C12P   7/64</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K23B10:10+BR</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K23B10:10+DE</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K23B10:10+PS</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61K35:11A</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Biosynthese von CLA durch Bifidobakterien</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep"  status="new" lang="EN">CLA biosynthesis by bifidobacteria</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Biosynthèse de CLA par bifidobactéries</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="WO-1999029886-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999029886</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TEAGASC DAIRY PRODUCTS RES CT</name><address><country>IE</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TEAGASC DAIRY PRODUCTS RESEARCH CENTRE</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Teagasc Dairy Products Research Centre</last-name><address><street>Moorepark, Fermoy</street><city>Cork</city><country>IE</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KAESLER, BRUNO, DR.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ROSS, PAUL R., DR.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>STANTON, CATHERINE, DR.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ZELDER, OSKAR, DR.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>The designation of the inventor has not yet been filed</last-name></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Dörper, Thomas Michael</last-name><address><street>BASF Aktiengesellschaft, ZDX - C6, Abteilung 'Patente, Marken und Lizenzen'</street><city>67056 Ludwigshafen</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Nineteen strains of <i>Lactobacillus</i>, 2 strains of <i>Lactococcus</i>, 1 strain of <i>Pediococcus, 4</i>
strains of <i>Propionibacterium</i> and 23 strains of <i>Bifidobacterium</i> were screened for their
ability to produce conjugated linoleic acid (CLA) from linoleic acid. Of these, 7 strains of
<i>Bifidobacterium</i>, as well as 2 strains of <i>Propionibacterium</i> produced the <i>cis-9, trans</i>-11 CLA
isomer from linoleic acid. In contrast, strains of <i>Lactobacillus, Lactococcus</i> and
<i>Pediococcus</i> lacked the ability to synthesise CLA. CLA (<i>cis</i>-9, <i>trans-</i>11 isomer) production
by the genus <i>Bifidobacterium</i> was shown to exhibit considerable interspecies variation, with <i>B</i>.
<i>breve</i> and <i>B</i>. <i>dentium</i> being the most efficient producers among the strains tested, yielding up
to 65 % conversion of linoleic acid to CLA at linoleic acid concentrations of 0.2-1.0 mg/ml
in MRS medium. The growth of <i>B. breve</i> strains was inhibited by increasing concentrations of
linoleic acid. Viability of <i>B. breve</i> 2257 was unaffected in the presence of up to 0.5 mg/ml
linoleic acid for 48 h but was dramatically reduced to 1.5% survival at 1 mg/ml linoleic acid.
However, viability of the <i>B</i>. <i>breve</i> strains NCFB2258, NCTC 11815, NCIMB 8815 and
NCIMB 8807 was reduced to &lt; 60 % at linoleic acid concentrations of 0.2 mg/ml. These data
suggest that certain strains of bifidobacteria may have applications to elevate CLA content of
food products and CLA status in humans.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>INTRODUCTION</b></heading><p num="0001">Conjugated linoleic acid (CLA) refers to a mixture of positional and geometric
isomers of linoleic acid, and has gained considerable attention in recent years
because of the many beneficial effects attributed to the <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 and
trans-10, cis-12 isomers, in particular. These include anticarcinogenic activity,
antiatherogenic activity, the ability to reduce the catabolic effects of immune
stimulation, the ability to enhance growth promotion and the ability to reduce
body fat (Martin and Banni, 1998 for review, and references therein). Of the
individual isomers of CLA, <i>cis-</i>9, trans-11-octadecadienoic acid has been
implicated as the most biologically active because it is the predominant isomer
incorporated into the phospholipids of cell membranes, liver phospholipids and
triglycerides (Kramer <i>et al.,</i> 1998). This isomer is also the predominant dietary
form of CLA, obtained from fats derived from ruminant animals, including milk,
dairy products and meat (Chin <i>et al.,</i> 1992, O'Shea <i>et al.,</i> 2000).</p><p num="0002">In addition to the ability of certain rumen-derived strains, including
<i>Butyrivibrio fibrisolvens</i> to form CLA from dietary linoleic acid (Kepler and
Tove, 1967), it has also been shown that certain cultures used in food
fermentations possess the ability to generate <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans</i>-11 CLA. Strains of
the intestinal flora in rats (Chin et al., 1994), two strains of <i>Propionibacterium
freudenreichii</i> spp.. <i>freudenreichii</i> and one strain of <i>P</i>. <i>freudenreichii</i> subsp.
<i>shermanii</i> (Jiang <i>et al.,</i> 1998), and six lactic cultures, including <i>L. acidophilus</i>
(Lin <i>et al.,</i> 1999) have been shown to possess this capability. In this study, we
assessed a collection of strains, many which are human intestinal isolates
(previously isolated from the human GIT) with probiotic potential, for ability to
form the <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA isomer, using linoleic acid as the substrate.</p><heading><b>MATERIALS AND METHODS</b></heading><heading><b>Maintenance of bacterial strains</b></heading><p num="0003">The 19 strains of <i>Lactobacillus</i>, 2 strains of <i>Lactococcus</i>, 1 strain of <i>Pediococcus,</i> 4 strains of <i>Propionibacterium</i> and 19 strains of <i>Bifidobacterium</i>
used in this study are listed in Table 1. The UCC strains used in the study were
previously isolated from the human gastrointestinal tract (GIT) and obtained
from University College Cork, Ireland under a restricted materials transfer
agreement.</p><p num="0004">The <i>Lactobacilli, Pediococci</i> and <i>Bifidobacterium</i> strains were cultured
in MRS (Difco Laboratories, Detroit, MI, USA) under anaerobic conditions
(anaerobic jars with 'Anaerocult A' gas packs; Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) and
1.5 % (w/v) agar (Oxoid Ltd. Basingstoke, Hampshire, UK) was included for
plating. <i>Pediococci, Lb.reuteri</i> NCIMB 702655, <i>Lb. reuteri</i> NCIMB 7025656
and <i>Lb. reuteri</i> DSM 20016 were routinely cultured at 30°C and the remaining
<i>Lactobacillus</i> strains were cultured at 37°C for 24 h. For <i>Bifidobacterium,</i> 0.05
% (w/v) L-cysteine hydrochloride (98 % pure, Sigma Chemical Co. St. Louis,
MO, USA) was added to the medium and cultures were grown for 48 h at 37°C
under anaerobic conditions. <i>Lactococcus</i> strains were cultured in MRS under
aerobic conditions at 30°C for 24 h. The <i>Propionibacterium</i> strains were
cultured in sodium lactate medium (SLM, Malik <i>et al.</i> 1968) at 20°C for 72 h
under anaerobic conditions. Total viable counts were determined by pour
plating of 10-fold serial dilutions in Maximum Recovery Diluent (Oxoid), using
MRS agar for lactobacilli and MRS agar with 0.05 % (w/v) cysteine for
bifidobacteria.</p><heading><b>Assay for microbial CLA production</b></heading><p num="0005">Prior to examination of the strains for CLA production, each was subcultured
twice in MRS broth (supplemented with cysteine, 0.05 % w/v for
<i>Bifidobacterium</i>) for 48 h, using a 1 % innoculum. All strains were then
cultured in MRS broth (supplemented with cysteine, 0.05 % w/v for
<i>Bifidobacterium</i>), spiked with different concentrations of free linoleic acid (LA:
<i>cis-</i>9, <i>cis</i>-12-octadecadienoic acid, 99 % pure, Sigma Chemical Co.). This was
added as a 30 mg/ml stock solution of linoleic acid in 2 % (v/v) Tween 80
(polyoxyethylene sorbitan mono-oleate; Merck-Schuchardt, Germany), which 
was previously sterile-filtered through a 0.45 µm Minisart filter (Sartrius AG,
Germany). The strains were inoculated to a density of 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/ml in free linoleic
acid-containing MRS media and incubated for their respective times and
temperatures (described above). Following incubation, 5 ml of the cultures were
centrifuged at 960 × g for 5 min at room temperature (Sanyo MISTRAL 2000R
Centrifuge).</p><p num="0006">The fatty acid composition of the resulting supernatant was analysed as
follows. Initially, C<sub>13:0</sub> (tridecanoic acid, 99 % pure, Sigma Chemical Co.) was
added to 4 ml of the resulting supernatant, as an internal standard at a
concentration of 0.25 x the initial linoleic acid concentration and lipid extraction
was performed as follows. Two milliliters of isopropanol (99 % purity, Alkem
Chemicals Ltd., Cork, Ireland) was added to the supernatant and the samples
were vortexed for 30 sec. A total of 4.5 ml hexane (99 % purity, LabScan
Ltd., Dublin, Ireland) was added to this and the mixture plased on a shaking
platform for 3 min before centrifugation at 960 × g for 5 min at room
temperature. The supernatant (the hexane layer containing the lipids) was
removed and the procedure was repeated twice. The hexane layers were pooled
and stored at -20 °C prior to preparation of fatty acid methyl esters (FAME)
for gas liquid chromatographic (GLC) analysis.</p><heading><b>Preparation of Fatty Acid Methyl Esters (FAME) and GLC Analysis</b></heading><p num="0007">The lipid extracts in hexane were analysed by GLC following acid-catalyzed
methylation as described previously (Stanton <i>et al</i>., 1997). Free fatty acids in
oils such as sunflower and soybean oils were calculated as the difference
between fatty acid concentrations obtained following acid and base catalyzed
methylation, performed using 2 N methanolic KOH (Sigma Chemical Co.) at
room temperature.</p><p num="0008">The GLC was performed with reference to the internal standard C<sub>13:0</sub>.
Separation of the FAME was performed on a Chrompack CP Sil 88 column
(Chrompack, Middleburg, The Netherlands, 100 m x 0.25 mm i.d., 0.20 µm
film thickness), using helium as carrier gas at a pressure of 37 psi. The injector 
temperature was held isothermally at 225°C for 10 min and the detector
temperature was 250°C. The column oven was held at an initial temperature of
140°C for 8 min and then programmed at an increase of 8.5°C/min to a final
temperature of 200°C, which was held for 41 min. Collected data were
recorded and analyzed on a Minichrom PC system (VG Data System,
Manchester, UK). The <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA isomer was identified by retention
time with reference to a CLA mix (Nu-Chek- Prep. Inc., Elysian, MN). The
percentage conversion to CLA and the remaining linoleic acid in the broth were
calculated by dividing the amount of CLA and linoleic acid present in the broth
after inoculation and incubation with the various cultures used with the amount
of linoleic acid present in the spiked broth before incubation.</p><heading><b>CLA production by <i>B. Breve</i> NCFB 2258 using triglyceride bound Linoleic
acid as substrate</b></heading><p num="0009"><i>B. breve</i> NCFB 2258 was further investigated for ability to utilise triglyceride
bound linoleic acid as substrate for CLA production. <i>B. breve</i> NCFB 2258 was
inoculated from a fully grown culture into MRS broth with added cysteine (0.05
%) and trilinolein (C<sub>18:2</sub>, <i>cis-</i>9, cis-12, 99 % pure, Sigma Chemical Co.),
soybean oil and sunflower oil (purchased from a local grocery store) containing
known linoleic acid concentrations. The triglyceride mixtures were sterile-filtered
through 0.45 µm Minisart filters and added as 5 mg/ml aqueous
solutions in 2.5 % (v/v) Tween 80. Substantial vortexing was required to
dissolve the fat particles. The volume of the triglyceride stock solutions added
was calculated to give a final concentration of 0.2 mg linoleic acid/ml of broth.
<i>B. breve</i> 2258 was inoculated into MRS broth in the presence of the triglyceride
substrates under anaerobic conditions at 37°C and incubated for 48 h.</p><heading><b>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</b></heading><heading><b>CLA production by bacterial strains</b></heading><p num="0010">Throughout the screening programme, the two <i>Propionibacterium</i> strains, <i>Propionibacterium freudenreichii</i> subsp. <i>freudenreichii Propioni</i> 6 (PFF-6) and
<i>Propionibacterium freudenreichii</i> spp. <i>shermanii</i> 9093 (PFS), previously
reported to synthesise CLA from linoleic acid (Jiang <i>et al.,</i> 1998) were used as
positive controls. The CLA biosynthetic assay was set up, with the positive
controls in SLM broth, using similar incubation conditions as described
previously (Jiang et al., 1998). GLC analysis confirmed that the two strains did
convert free linoleic acid to the <i>cis-</i>9, trans-11 CLA isomer following
incubation at 20 ºC for 72 h, using CRM (certified reference material) 164 and
CLA standards for fatty acid identification (data not shown). However, the
levels of CLA produced by the two strains of <i>Propionibacterium</i> were lower
than that reported previously by Jiang <i>et al.</i> (1998), producing ∼ 60 µg/ml of
CLA in comparison with 111.8 µg/ ml previously reported by Jiang <i>et al.</i>
(1998), using 0.5 mg/ml linoleic acid as substrate. In addition, we found that
the amount of linoleic acid remaining in the media following incubation with the
PFS strain was ∼ 50 µg/ml, compared with 289.5 µg/ml reported previously
(Jiang <i>et al.,</i> 1998). The variation in these data may be a result of differences in
the numbers of cells present during incubation, and possibly as a result of the
different procedures used for fatty acid extraction and methylation.</p><p num="0011">Three strains of <i>Propionibacterium</i> were then examined for their ability
to produce CLA. These were <i>Propionibacterium acidi propionici</i> NCFB 5633,
<i>Propionibacterium freudenreichii</i> spp. <i>shermanii</i> LMG 16424 and
<i>Propionibacterium freudenreichii</i> spp. <i>shermanii</i> JS (Laboratorium Visby,
Tonder, Denmark). The strains were incubated in the presence of 0.5 mg/ml
linoleic acid using the same growth conditions and media as described above.

The two <i>Propionibacterium shermanii</i> strains synthesized CLA in MRS media
while <i>Propionibacterium acidi propionici</i> did not produce any detectable CLA
product (Table 1). The amounts of CLA produced by the two
<i>Propionibacterium shermanii</i> strains (12-14 µg/ml) were low however,
compared with 60 mg/ml produced by PFS strain in this study.</p><heading><b>Screening of Lactobacilli, Lactococci, and Pediococci for CLA production</b></heading><p num="0012">A variety of different strains of lactobacilli, lactococci, and pediococci,
obtained from various sources (Table 2) were tested for ability to produce CLA
from linoleic acid. These strains included a number of probiotic strains
including <i>Lactobacillus salivarius</i> UCC 43310, <i>Lactobacillus salivarius</i> UCC
43348, <i>Lactobacillus paracasei</i> UCC 43338, <i>Lactobacillus paracasei</i> UCC
43364, <i>Lactobacillus paracasei</i> UCC 42319, five strains of <i>Lb. reuteri</i> and the
bacteriocin producing <i>Lactcoccus lactis</i> DPC 3147 strain (Ryan <i>et al</i>., 1996).
The strains were inoculated into MRS to a density of ∼10<sup>6</sup> cfu/ml and incubated
under respective conditions as described above, in the presence of linoleic acid
concentrations of 0.5 to 3.0 mg/ml.</p><p num="0013">The ability of the strains to grow in the different linoleic acid
concentrations varied considerably. Good growth of all five <i>Lb. reuterii</i> strains
occurred at linoleic acid concentrations up to 1 mg/ml, while at 3 mg/ml, the
growth of strains NCIMB 701359 and NCIMB 70256 was completely inhibited
(data not shown). At all linoleic acid concentrations investigated, none of the
<i>Lb. reuteri</i> strains investigated produced CLA in detectable quantities.
<i>Lactobacillus helveticus</i> NCDO 1244 exhibited no growth in 0.5 mg/ml linoleic
acid while <i>Lactobacillus leichmanii</i> NCDO 302 showed good growth in the
presence of high linoleic acid concetrations (3 mg/ml). However, none of the
strains produced CLA from linoleic acid (between 0.5 to 3 mg/ml) under the
conditions used.</p><heading><b>CLA production from linoleic acid among <i>Bifidobacterium</i> strains cultured
in MRS</b></heading><p num="0014">A variety of bifidobacteria obtained from a number of sources (Table 3) were
screened for CLA production. Since free linoleic acid was found to be
inhibitory to the growth of bifidobacteria strains, the minimum inhibitory
concentration of linoleic acid for the <i>B. breve</i> strains was initially determined.
This involved inoculation (1 % from grown cultures) of the <i>Bifidobacterium</i>
strains into MRS containing free linoleic acid concentrations ranging from 0.2
to 1.5 mg/ml and incubation under anaerobic conditions at 37°C for 48 h. The pH 
of the media remained unchanged following the addition of the linoleic acid
substrate in this concentration range at pH ∼ 6.1. Viable bifidobacteria were
enumerated at time zero and following 48 h incubation in the presence of the linoleic
acid substrate. Viability of <i>B</i>. <i>breve</i> 2257 was unaffecetd in the presence of linoleic
acid at concentrations up to 0.5 mg/ml. However, viability was dramatically
reduced at 1.0 mg/ml and only 1.5 % survival was observed. In contrast the
survival of strains <i>B. breve</i> 2258, 8807, 8815 and 11815 was reduced to &lt;60 % at
linoleic acid concentrations of 0.2 mg/ml and higher. The bifidobacteria strains
were then screened for CLA production from linoleic acid substrate at a
concentration of 0.5 mg/ml, using the incubation conditions described above. A
number of the <i>Bifidobacterium</i> strains investigated produced CLA following
incubation in MRS containing 0.5 mg/ml linoleic acid, and the results from this
screening program showed that there was considerable inter-species variation in
the ability of bifidobacteria to produce CLA (Table 3).</p><p num="0015">All 5 strains of <i>Bifidobacterium breve</i> species examined tested positive
for CLA production with four of these strains producing more than 60 µg/ml
CLA, while strain <i>B</i>. <i>breve</i> NCFB 2257 produced 15 µg/ml under these
conditions. In addition, <i>B</i>. <i>dentium</i> NCFB 2243 was an efficient CLA
producer, also yielding &gt;60 µg/mg CLA (Table 3), while <i>B.
pseudocatenulatum</i> NCIMB 8811 produced &gt;15 µg/ml under the experimental
conditions employed. Among the other bifidobacteria species investigated, 3
strains of <i>B .adolescentis</i>, 2 strains of <i>B. longum</i> and 1 strain each of <i>B.
angulatum</i>, <i>B</i>. <i>bifidum</i> and <i>B. lactis</i> were all negative for CLA production
(Table 3). The exact role of biohydrogenation in the metabolic environment of
the bacterial cell is unclear. In the study by Jiang <i>et al.</i> (1998), strains which
were able to produce CLA were those inhibited by the presence of free linoleic
acid, but a positive correlation between CLA production and tolerance to
linoleic acid was observe within the three CLA producing strains of
propionibacteria. This suggests that the conversion of linoleic acid to CLA is a
detoxification mechanism for the bacterial cell. This is supported by the fact
that the antimicrobial activity of fatty acids with double bonds of <i>cis</i> 
configuration is stronger than that of <i>trans</i> (Kabara, 1983).</p><p num="0016">The most efficient CLA producers were strains <i>B. breve</i> 8815 and 2258 at
linoleic acid concentration of 1.0 mg/ml. The strains <i>B. breve</i> 8815, 2258 and 2257
were present at less than 10<sup>4</sup> cells/ml at the highest linoleic acid concentration (1.5
mg/ml) and were not analysed for CLA conversion. <i>B. breve</i> NCFB 2258
converted ∼50 % of the added linoleic acid to CLA at 0.2 and 0.5 mg/ml linoleic
acid concentrations. The ability of <i>B. breve</i> NCFB 2258 strain to utilise
triglyceride bound linoleic acid as substrate for CLA production, using
trilinolein (C<sub>18:2</sub>, <i>cis-</i>9, cis-12), sunflower and soybean oils was also
investigated. The <i>B. breve</i> NCFB 2258 strain was found to be negative for
ability to utilise triglyceride bound linoleic acid as substrate at 0.2 mg/ml linoleic
acid for CLA production (data not shown), from trilinolein, sunflower and
soybean oils. These data are in agreement with a previous study which showed
that of 61 rumen isolates with ability to produce CLA, none utilised triglyceride
bound linoleic acid (Fujimoto <i>et al.,</i> 1993). In addition, trilinolein did not
inhibit the growth of <i>B. breve</i> 2258 to the same extent as similar concentrations
of free linoleic acid (data not shown). This indicates that linoleic acid in the free
fatty acid form is more toxic to bifidobacteria than triglyceride-bound linoleic
acid.</p><heading><b>Microbial biohydrogenation of unsaturated C 18 fatty acids</b></heading><p num="0017"><i>B. breve</i> 2258 and <i>P. freudenreichii shermanii</i> 9093 were screened for their ability to
produce CLA. The strains were incubated in duplicate in the presence of 0.5 mg/ml
linoleic acid (LA) and CLA (the pure <i>cis-</i>9, trans-11 isomer), respectively, using the same
growth conditions and media as described above. In order to compare the fatty acid
composition, control cultures without added LA and CLA were also incubated using the
same conditions. The propionibacteria strain used in this study was previously reported to
synthezise CLA from LA (Jiang <i>et al.,</i> 1998) and therefore used as a positive control.
However, in this study, that result was not reproducible since the strain was clearly
inhibited in the presence of LA and CLA and hence grew very poorly. No CLA production 
from that strain was therefore detected and the results from the GLC analysis are not
presented here.

After separation (by centrifugation) of <i>B</i>. <i>breve</i> 2258 cells from the supernatant following
incubation for 48 h, followed by lipid extraction and methylation, the fatty acid
composition of both the cells (pellets) and the supernatant were analysed using GLC .</p><heading><b>Change in supernatant fatty acid composition following incubation of
<i>B. breve</i> 2258 with 0.5 mg/ml LA</b></heading><p num="0018">GLC analysis confirmed that B. <i>breve</i> 2258 converted LA to CLA. Of the added 0.5
mg/ml, only 0.27 mg/ml (54 %) remained in the supernatant (Fig. 5), while the remainder
(46 %) was converted to other fatty acids, preferentially the <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA isomer
followed by <i>cis-</i>9-C 18:1 (oleic acid) and a peak of unidentified fatty acids, which most
likely is another CLA isomer, although confirmation of this requires further study. The
amount of <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA produced was 0.136 mg/ml, and the unidentified fatty
acids accounted for 0.03 mg/ml. The amount of these two fatty acids present in the
control supernatant was negligible (Fig. 5) There was also a substantial increase of <i>cis-</i>9-C
18:1 (oleic acid) (64.8 % compared with the control supernatant), which indicates that <i>B.
breve</i> 2258 harbours a CLA reductase enzyme that hydrogenates the <i>trans-</i>11 double
bond of <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA. Compared to the control culture there was 64,8 % more
stearic acid in the LA added supernatant. Smaller increases were observed also in the
concentrations of <i>trans-</i>11 C 18:1 (vaccenic acid) (30.3 %) and C 18:0 (stearic acid) (17.5
%) compared with the control supernatant, suggesting that other hydrogenating enzymes
may be involved.</p><heading><b>Change in membrane fatty acid composition following incubation of <i>B. breve</i> 2258
with 0.5 mg.ml LA</b></heading><p num="0019">The fatty acid composition of the membranes from the cultures (pellet) grown in MRS
medium with 0.5 mg/ml LA was also analysed and compared with the control cultures
(Fig. 9). Results are expressed as mg fatty acids from cells/ml fully grown culture (see
section 3.4.2) The fatty acid concentration in the pellets in mg/ml is lower than that of the
supernatant and therefore are not directly comparable. Results from the GLC analysis
show that CLA was incorporated in the cell membranes, whereas the control culture
contained negligible CLA. The <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 isomer was the most abundant CLA isomer
and accounted for 0.012 mg/ml, which represents 70 % of the total CLA isomers
(assuming that the unidentified fatty acid peak was other CLA isomers). The content of
the <i>cis-</i>9-C 18:1 (oleic acid) was increased (by 271 % compared with controls) in the
membranes of <i>B. breve</i> 2258 cells incubated in LA (0.5 mg/ml), indicating the presence of
a CLA reductase, which was capable of reducing the unsaturated <i>trans-</i>11 bond in CLA in
<i>B. breve</i> 2258. The <i>trans-</i>11 C 18:1 (vaccenic acid) content of the cell membranes wes
reduced (over 4-fold) in the LA treated cells compared with the control cells. As seen in
the supernatant, a small increase of 28 % in C 18:0 (stearic acid) was detected in the
membranes of the LA treated cells compared with the controls (Fig. 9).</p><heading><b>Change in supernatant fatty acid composition following incubation of <i>B. breve</i> 2258
with 0.5 mg/ml <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA</b></heading><p num="0020">In order to evaluate if <i>B. breve</i> 2258 possesses enzymes other than the putative linoleic
acid isomerase, involved in the biohydrogenation of linoleic acid, studies were undertaken
using <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA as the substrate. Strain <i>B. breve</i> 2258 was inoculated in MRS
containing 0.5 mg/ml of the pure <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans</i>-11 CLA isomer (Matreya Inc. PA, USA) and
incubated for 24 h at 37°C. Following incubation in the presence CLA (0.5 mg/ml), only
0.32 mg/ml (65 %) remained in the supernatant (Fig. 9) with the remaining 35 %
converted to other fatty acids. The most predominantly formed fatty acid formed
corresponded to the unidentified peak, observed following incubation with LA and eluted 
at 43 mins (Figs. 6 and 10). We propose this is another CLA isomer which was present at
0.12 mg/ml (71 % of the <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA peak). Oleic acid was also formed in the
supernatant by <i>B. breve</i> 2258 following incubation with <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA with an
increase of 85.5 % compared with the control supernatant. Smaller increases were also
observed in the concentration of <i>trans-</i>11-C 18:1 (vaccenic acid) (74.5 % compared to
control supernatant) and C 18:0 (stearic acid) (23.9 % compared to control supernatant).</p><heading><b>Change in membrane fatty acid compositio following incubation os <i>B. breve</i> 2258
with 0.5 mg/ml <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA</b></heading><p num="0021">The lipid composition of the membrane following incubation of <i>B. breve</i> 2258 in <i>cis-</i>9,
trans-11 CLA was also compared with control cells incubated in the absence of CLA.

The fatty acid composition of the membranes from cultures inoculated in MRS containing
0.5 mg/ml of the pure <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA isomer shows that the membrane composition
changed compared with the control. <i>Cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA was incorporated into the
membrane of the culture grown in the presence of CLA (0.03 mg/ml) compared with the
culture, grown in the absence of CLA, which contained no CLA (Fig. 12.). The same
unidentified fatty acid as observed in the supernatant was also present in the membrane
following incubation with <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA (0.012 mg/ml). Verification of the identity
of this fatty acid will be important, as clearly the bacterial cell has the capacity to convert
<i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA to this compound. the possibility is that it is another CLA isomer,
although this was not verified in this study, nor was its exact identity confirmed. This
could be accomplished using co-eluting fatty acid standards analyzed by GLC or by
GCMS. An increase of 54.8 % in the <i>cis-9-C</i> 18:1 oleic acid membrane content was
obtained following incubation of <i>B. breve</i> 2258 in CLA (0.5 mg/ml). This amount of oleic
acid in the membranes, formed relative to the control, was greater in the LA treated cells 
(2.7-fold increase) than the CLA treated cells. As observed in the cell membranes obtained
following incubation of <i>B</i>. <i>breve</i> 2258 in LA (0.5 mg/ml), the <i>trans-</i>11-C 18:1 vaccenic
acid content of membranes was lower in the cells incubated with <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA than
the control pellets (5.8-fold greater in the control). Only a very small increase was
obtained in the content of C 18:0 stearic acid in the membranes of CLA treated cells
compared with controls.</p><p num="0022">The GLC analysis confirmed that <i>B. breve</i> 2258 converted LA to CLA and that a
significant amount of another, as yet, unidentified isomer was also formed and the data
also, it also indicates that a further biohydrogenation of <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA to C 18:1
isomers, preferably the <i>cis-</i>9-C 18:1 isomer occurs as a result of incubation with <i>B. breve</i>
2258 strain. Since also a small increase of C 18:0 was detected in the chromatogram, it is
possible that additional enzymes are involved, but whether this activity is significant is
unclear. The increase in saturation was obtained in both the supernatant and the bacterial
pellets. Also when the pure CLA isomer was incubated with <i>B. breve</i> 2258 it was further
hydrogenated to more saturated fatty acids, primarily <i>cis-</i>9-C 18:1. This may support the
theory that incorporation of a <i>trans</i> fatty acids instead of <i>cis,</i> and saturation or <i>trans</i>
conversion of <i>cis</i> double bonds is a strategy for the bacterial cell to counteract for the
increased fluidity that occurs when LA and the <i>cis</i>-9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA isomer (which has a
<i>cis</i> bond) is interfering with the membranes which leads to expansion of membrane,
elevation of membrane permeability and impairment of membrane functions (Junker and
Ramos, 1999; Weber <i>et al</i>., 1994).

Interestingly in this study, the differences in fatty acid composition when adding LA and
CLA respectively, to the supernatant and pellets, is not very significant. When adding the
pure <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11 CLA isomer to the supernatant it is converted to a great extent to
other CLA isomer, which is not the case in the LA added supernatant.</p><p num="0023">Because of all the beneficial health effects of CLA, the ability of strains of
bifidobacteria, natural inhabitants of the intestine, to convert free linoleic acid to
CLA can be considered as a novel probiotic trait. Indeed, it is tempting to 
suggest that the anticarcinogenic activity ascribed to some of these probiotic
bacteria could be linked to their ability to produce CLA. Development of
probiotic dairy products with elevated CLA levels also provides an exciting
opportunity. Exploitation of probiotic bifidobacteria harbouring CLA
biosynthetic capabilities offers novel opportunities in the rational design of
improved health-promoting functional foods, with the benefits of enriched CLA
and probiotic bacteria.</p><heading>References</heading><p num="0024"><sl><li><b>Banni S., Angioni E., Casu V., Melis M.P., Carta G., Corongiu F.P., Thompson H.,
Ip C.</b> Decrease in linoleic acid metabolites as a potential mechanism in cancer risk
reduction by conjugated linoleic acid. <i>Carcinogenesis</i> 20(6): 1019-1024 (1999).</li><li><b>Belury M.A.</b> Conjugated dienoic linoleate: A polyunsaturated fatty acid with
unique chemoprotective properties. <i>Nutrition Reviews</i> Vol 53, No 4: 83-93 (1995).</li><li><b>Bergey's Manual of Systematic Bcateriology</b> Vol III (1989).</li><li><b>Brock T.D., Madigan M.T., Martinko J.M., Parker J.</b> Biology of Microorganisms, 7<sup>th</sup>
ed. Prentice-Hall International, London, (1994).</li><li><b>Chin S.F., Liu W., Storkson J.M., Ha Y.L. and Pariza M.W.</b> Dietary sources of
conjugated dienoic isomeres of linoleic acid, a newly recognized class of anticarcinogens.
<i>J. Food Comp. and Anal.</i>5: 185-197 (1992).</li><li><b>Chin Sou F., Storkson Jayne M., Liu W. Albright Karen J., Pariza Michael W.</b>
Conjugated linoleic acid (9,11- and 10,12- octadecadienoic acid) is produced by
conventional but not germ free rats fed linoleic acid. <i>J</i>. <i>Nutr.</i> 124: 694-701 (1993).</li><li><b>Cook Mark E. and Pariza Michael.</b> The role of conjugated linoleic acid (CLA) in health.
<i>Int Dairy journal,</i> 8: 459-462 (1998).</li><li><b>Cook M.E., Jerome D.L., Pariza M.W.</b> Broilers fed conjugated linolec acid had
enhanced bone ash. <i>Poultry Science</i> 76: S41 (1997).</li><li><b>Doyle Ellin.</b> Scientific forum explores CLA knowledge. <i>INFORM</i> 9:69-73 (1998).</li><li><b>Fritsche J., Mossoba M.M., Yurawecz M.P., <i>et al.</i></b> Conjugated linoleic acid (CLA)
isomers in human adipose tissue. <i>Zeitschrift Lebensmittel. Untersuchung Forscung A-Food
Research &amp; Technology</i> 205:415-418 (1997).</li><li><b>Fritsche Jan and Steinhart Hans.</b> Amounts of conjugated linoleic acid (CLA) in 
German foods and evaluation of daily intake. <i>Z Leberism Unters Forsch A</i> 206: 77-82
(1998).</li><li><b>Fritsche Jan and Steinhart Hans.</b> Analysis, occurence and physiological properties of
trans fatty acids (TFA) with particular emphasis on conjugated linoleic acid isomers
(CLA)- a review. <i>Lipid,</i> 6S: 190-210 (1998).</li><li><b>Fujimoto K., Kimoto H., Shishikura M., Endo Y., Ogimoto K.</b> Biohydrogenation of
linoleic acid by anaerobic bacteria isolated from rumen. <i>Biosci. Biotech. Biochem.</i>
57(6):1026-1027 (1993).</li><li><b>Goldin Barry R.</b> Health benefits of probiotics. <i>British Journal of Nutrition,</i> 80: 293-207
(1998).</li><li><b>Ha Y.L., Grimm N.K. and Pariza M.W.</b> Anticarcinogens from fried ground beef: heat
altered derivatives of linoleic acid. <i>Carcinogenesis</i> 8:1881-1887 (1987).</li><li><b>Ha Y.L., Storkson J, Pariza M.W.</b> Inhibition of benzo(a)pyrene- induced neoplasia by
conjugated dienoic derivatives of linoleic acid. <i>Cancer Res.</i> 50:1097-1101 (1990).</li><li><b>Herbel Barbara K., McGuire Michelle K., McGuire Mark A., Schultz Terry D.</b>
Safflower oil consumption does not increase plasma conjugated linoleic acid
concentrations in humans. <i>Am. J. Clin. Nutr.</i> 67: 332-337 (1998).</li><li><b>Huang Y.C., Luedecke L.O., Schultz T.D.</b> Effect of Cheddar-cheese consumption on
the plasma conjugated linoleic acid concentration in men. <i>Nutr. Res.</i> 14:373-386 (1994).</li><li><b>Hughes Peter E., Hunter William J., Tove Samuel B..</b> Biohydrogenation of
unsaturated fatty acids. <i>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</i> Vol.257 No 7: 3643-3649
(1982).</li><li><b>Ip C, Chin S.F, Scimeca J.A, Pariza M.W.</b> Mammary cancer prevention by conjugated
dienoic derivatives of linoleic acid. <i>Cancer Res.</i> 51:6118-6124 (1991).</li><li><b>Ip C., Singh M., Thompson H.J.</b> Cojugated linoleic acid supresses mammary
carcinogenesis and proliferative activity of the mammary gland in the rat. <i>Cancer Res.</i> 54:
1212-1215 (1994).</li><li><b>Ip C, Scimeca J.A., Thompson H.J.</b> Effect of timing and duration of dietary conjugated
linoleic acid on mammary cancer supression. <i>Nutr. Cancer</i> 24:241-247 (1995).</li><li><b>Ip C, Jiang C., Thompson H.J. Scimeca J.A.</b> Retention of conjugated linoleic acid in
the mammary gland is associated with tumour inhibition during the post- initiation phase
of carcinogenesis. <i>Carcinogenesis</i> 18:755-759 (1997).</li><li><b>Jiang Jin, Björk Lennart, Fondén Ragne.</b> Production of conjugated linoleic acid by 
dairy starter cultures. <i>J.Appl. Microbiol.</i> 85:95-102 (1998).</li><li><b>Jiang J., Wolk A., Vessby B.</b> Relation between the intake of milk fat and the occurence
of conjugated linoleic acid in human adipose tissue. <i>Am. J. Clin. Nutr.</i> 70:21-29 (1999).</li><li><b>Kepler C.R., Tove S.B.</b> Linoleate @<sup>12</sup>- <i>cis</i> @<sup>11</sup>- <i>trans-</i> Isomerase. <i>Methods in
enzymology</i> Vol XIV p.105 (1969).</li><li><b>Kepler C.R., Tucker W.P., Tove S.B.</b> Biohydrogenation of unsaturated fatty acids. <i>The
Journal of Biological Chemistry</i> Vol.246 No 14: 3612-3620 (1970).</li><li><b>Kepler C.R., Tucker W.P., Tove S.B.</b> Biohydrogenation of unsaturated fatty acids. <i>The
Journal of Biological Chemistry</i> Vol.246, No 9: 2765-2771 (1971).</li><li><b>Knekt P., Järvinen R., Seppänen R., Pukkala E., Aromaa A.</b> Intake of daily products
and risk of brest acncer. <i>Br. J</i>. <i>Cancer</i> 73:687-691.</li><li><b>Kun Lee Yuan and Salminen Seppo.</b> The coming of age of probiotics. <i>Trends in Food
Science &amp; Technology, 6:</i> 241-245 (1995).</li><li><b>Lal D., Narayanan K.M.</b> Effect of lactation number on the polyunsaturated fatty acids
and and oxidative stbility of milk fats. <i>Indian J. Dairy Sci</i> 37:225-229 (1984).</li><li><b>Lawless F., J.J. Murphy., D Harrington., R.Devery., C. Stanton.</b> Elevation of
conjugated <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans-</i>11<i>-</i> octadecadienoic acid in bovine milk because of dietary
supplementation. <i>J</i>. <i>Dairy Sci.</i> 81:3259-3267 (1998).</li><li><b>Lee K.Y., Salminen S.</b> The coming of age of probiotics.<i>Trends Food Sci. &amp; Tech. &amp;:</i>
241-245 (1995).</li><li><b>Lee K.N., Kritchevsky D., Pariza M.W.</b> Conjugated linoleic acid and atherosclerosis in
rabbits. <i>Atherosclerosis</i> 108:19-25 (1994).</li><li><b>Liew C., Schut H.A.J., Chin S.F., Pariza M.W., Dashwood R.H.</b> Protection of
conjugated linoleic acid against 2-amino3-methylimidazo(4,5-f) quinoline induced colon
carcinogenesis in the F344 rat-- a study of inhibitory mechanisms. <i>Carcinogenesis</i>
16:3037-3043 (1995).</li><li><b>Lin H., Boylston T.D., Chang M.J., Luedecke L.O., Schultz T.D.</b> Survey of the
conjugated linoleic acid contenets of dairy products. <i>J. Dairy Sci.</i> 78:2358-2365 (1995).</li><li><b>Malik A.C., Reinbold G.W., Vedamuthu E.R.</b> An evaluation of the taxonomy of
<i>Propionibacterium. Canadian J. Microbiology</i> 14:1185-1191 (1968).</li><li><b>Miller C.C., Park Y., Pariza M.W., Cook M.E.</b> Feeding conjugated linoleic acid to
animals partially overcomes catabolic responses due to endotoxin injection <i>Biochem</i><i>Biophys. Res. Commun.</i> 198:1107-1112 (1994).</li><li><b>Munday John S., Thompson Keith G., James Kerry A.C.</b> Dietary conjugated linoleic
acids promote fatty streak formation in the C57BL/6 mouse atherosclerosis model. <i>Br. J.
Nutr.</i> 81:251-255 (1999).</li><li><b>Naidu A.S., Bidlack W.R., Clemens R.A.</b> Probiotic spectra of lactic acid bacteria
(LAB). <i>Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr.</i> 39(1):13-126 (1999).</li><li><b>Nicolosi R.J., Rogers E,J., Kritchevsky D., Scimeca J.A.,Huth P.J.</b> Dietary conjugated
linoleic acid reduces plasma lipoproteins and early aortic atherosclerosis in
hypercholesterolemic hamsters. <i>Artery</i> 22:266-277 (1997).</li><li><b>Pariza M.W.</b> Animal studies: summary,gaps and future research. <i>Am. J. Clin. Nutr.</i>
66:S1539-1540 (1997).</li><li><b>Rudel L.L.</b> Invited commentary. Atherosclerosis and conjugated linoleic acid.. <i>Br. J.
Nutr.</i> 81:177-179 (1999).</li><li><b>Salminen Irma, Mutanen Marja, Jauhiainen Matti, Aro Antti.</b> Dietary <i>trans</i> fatty
acids increase conjugated linoleic acid levels in human serum. <i>Nutritional Biochemistry 9:</i>
93-98
(1998).</li><li><b>Sanders M.E.</b> Development of consumer probiotics for the US market. <i>Br. J. Nutr.</i>
80(4):S213-218 (1998).</li><li><b>Schonberg S., Krokan H.E.</b> The inhibitory effect of conjugated dienoic derivatives (cla)
of linoleic acid on the growth of human tumour cell lines is in part due to increased lipid
peroxidation. <i>Anticancer Res.</i> 15:1241-1246 (1995).</li><li><b>Schultz T.D., Chew B.P., Seaman W.R.</b> Differential stimulatorry and inhibitory
responses of human mcf-7 breast cancer cells to linoleic acid and conjugated linoleic acid
in culture. <i>Anticancer Res.</i> 12:2143-2145 (1992).</li><li><b>Sehat Najibullah, Yurawecz Martin P., Roach John A.G., Mossoba Magdi M,
Kramer John K.G. and Ku Youh.</b> Silver ion high performance liquid chromatographic
separation and identification of conjugated dienoic linoleic acid isomeres. <i>Lipids</i> 33: 217-221
(1998).</li><li><b>Shantha N.C., Moody W.G., Tabeidi Z.</b> Conjugated linoleic acid concentrations in dairy
products as affected by processing and storage. <i>J.Food Sci</i> 60(4):695-697 (1995).</li><li><b>Stanton C., Lawless F., Kjellmer G., Harrington D., Devery R., Conolly J.F.,
Murphy J:J.</b> Dietary influences on bovine milk <i>cis-</i>9, <i>trans</i>-11- conjugated linoleic acid 
content. <i>J. Food Sci.</i> 62:1083-1086 (1997).</li><li><b>Tomatori M.</b> Bifidobacteria and their role in human health. <i>J. Industrial Microbiology</i>
6:263-268 (1993).</li><li><b>Van Nostrand R., Douglas M., Considine P.E.</b> Scientific Encyclopedia 7<sup>th</sup> ed. Vol II
(1989).</li><li><b>Visonneau S., Cesano A., Tepper S.A., Scimeca J.A., Santoli D., Kritchevsky D.</b>
Conjugated linoleic acid supresses the growth of human breast adenocarcinoma cells in
scid mice. <i>Anticancer Res.</i> 17:969-973 (1997).</li><li><b>Yang X., Pariza M.W.</b> Conjugated linoleic acid (CLA) -producing bacteria: isolation,
identification and properties of their linoleic acid isomerases. <i>IFT Annual Meeting</i> p.243
(1995). <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><b>Screening of Propionibacterium strains for CLA production from linoleic acid in MRS media.</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Strain</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Remaining

LA (µg/ml)</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>CLA produced</b><b>(µg/ml)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>P.acidi</i></entry><entry align="left">87.5</entry><entry align="left">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>propionici</i> NCFB</entry></row><row><entry align="left">5633</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>P. freudenreichii</i> spp.</entry><entry align="left">73.0</entry><entry align="left">12.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>shermanii LMG 16424</i></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>P. freudenreichii</i> spp.</entry><entry align="left">73.0</entry><entry align="left">13.8</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>shermanii</i> JS (Visby)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1"><b>Strains screened forCLA production</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Species</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Code</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Source</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus</i></entry><entry align="left">NCIMB 11951</entry><entry align="left">Adult intestine</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>reuteri</i></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus reuteri</i></entry><entry align="left">NCIMB 701359</entry><entry align="left">Unknown</entry> </row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus reuteri</i></entry><entry align="left">NCIMB 701089</entry><entry align="left">Unknown</entry> </row> <row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus reuteri</i> </entry><entry align="left">NCIMB 702655</entry><entry align="left">From rat</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus reuteri</i></entry><entry align="left">NCIMB 702656</entry><entry align="left">From rat</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus reuteri</i></entry><entry align="left">DSM 20016</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus helveticus</i></entry><entry align="left">NCDO 257</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus helveticus</i></entry><entry align="left">ATCC 15009</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus helveticus</i></entry><entry align="left">NCDO 1244</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus leichmanii</i></entry><entry align="left">NCDO 299</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus leichmanii</i></entry><entry align="left">NCDO 302</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus fermenticum</i></entry><entry align="left">ATCC 338</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus acidophilus</i></entry><entry align="left">ATCC 4356</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus paracasei</i></entry><entry align="left">UCC 43338</entry><entry align="left">Human GIT</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus paracasei</i></entry><entry align="left">UCC 43364</entry><entry align="left">Human GIT</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus</i></entry><entry align="left">UCC 42319</entry><entry align="left">Human GIT</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>paracasei</i></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus salivarius</i></entry><entry align="left">UCC 43310</entry><entry align="left">Human GIT</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus salivarius</i></entry><entry align="left">UCC 43348</entry><entry align="left">Human GIT</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactobacillus</i></entry><entry align="left">DPC 5336</entry><entry align="left">from cracker</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">Barrel</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Bifidobacterium breve</i></entry><entry align="left">NCTC 11815</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactcoccus lactis</i></entry><entry align="left">DPC 3147</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Lactococcus lactis 290P</i></entry><entry align="left">DPC 152</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Pediococcus pentasescus</i></entry><entry align="left">FBB 63</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1"><b>Table 3 Conversion to CLA by <i>Bifidobacterium</i> strains cultured in MRS broth containing cysteine spiked with 0.5 mg/ml linoleic acid for 48 h.</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Species prod.</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Strain</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Source</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Growth in 0.5mg/ml</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>CLA</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B.</i></entry><entry align="left">NCFB 2204</entry><entry align="left">Adult intestine</entry><entry align="left">+<sup><!--footnotes removed--></sup></entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>adolescent</i></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>is</i></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. adolescentis</i></entry><entry align="left">NCFB 2230</entry><entry align="left">Adult intestine</entry><entry align="left">0<sup><!--footnotes removed--></sup></entry><entry align="left">-<sup><!--footnotes removed--></sup></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. adolescentis</i></entry><entry align="left">NCFB 2231</entry><entry align="left">Adult intestine</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">0<sup><!--footnotes removed--></sup></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. angulatum</i></entry><entry align="left">NCFB 2236</entry><entry align="left">Human faeces</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. bifidum</i></entry><entry align="left">NCFB 795</entry><entry align="left">Human milk</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. breve</i></entry><entry align="left">NCFB 2257</entry><entry align="left">Infant intestine</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">++</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. breve</i></entry><entry align="left">NCFB 2258</entry><entry align="left">Infant intestine</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">+++<sup><!--footnotes removed--></sup></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. breve</i></entry><entry align="left">NCTC 11815</entry><entry align="left">Infant intestine</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">+++</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. breve</i></entry><entry align="left">NCIMB 8815</entry><entry align="left">Nursing stools</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">+++</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. breve</i></entry><entry align="left">NCIMB 8807</entry><entry align="left">Nursing stools</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">+++</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. dentium</i></entry><entry align="left">NCFB 2243</entry><entry align="left">Dental carries</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">+++</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. infantis</i></entry><entry align="left">NCFB 2205</entry><entry align="left">Infant intestine</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. infantis</i></entry><entry align="left">NCFB 2256</entry><entry align="left">Infant intestine</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. lactis</i></entry><entry align="left">Bb12</entry><entry align="left">Chr. Hansens</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. longum</i></entry><entry align="left">BB536</entry><entry align="left">Visby</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Bifidobacterium</i> sp.</entry><entry align="left">UCC 35612</entry><entry align="left">Adult intestine</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">+<sup><!--footnotes removed--></sup></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Bifidobacterium</i> sp.</entry><entry align="left">UCC 35624</entry><entry align="left">Adult intestine</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">+</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Bifidobacterium</i> sp.</entry><entry align="left">UCC 35658</entry><entry align="left">Adult intestine</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">+</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Bifidobacterium</i> sp.</entry><entry align="left">UCC 35675</entry><entry align="left">Adult intestine</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">+</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>Bifidobacterium</i> sp.</entry><entry align="left">UCC 35687</entry><entry align="left">Adult intestine</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">++</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><i>B. pseudocatenulatum</i></entry><entry align="left">NCIMB 8811</entry><entry align="left">Nursling stools</entry><entry align="left">+</entry><entry align="left">+<!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--><!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></li></sl></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>Process for production of CLA by cultivating a microorganism of the genus
bifidobacterium in the presence of linoleic acid and isolating the formed CLA.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>Process according to claim 1 wherein the CLA is cis-9, trans-11 octadecadienoic
acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>Process according to claims 1-2 wherein the microorganism is selected from the
group consisting of bifidobacterium breve, bifidobacterium dentium and
bifidobacterium pseudocatenulatum.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>Process according to claims 1-3 wherein the concentration of linoleic acid in the
culture medium is higher than 1 mg/ml.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The use of a microorganism of the genus bifidobacterium as a probiotics in food
and feed.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The use according to claim 5 in order to prevent or reduce the effects of
diarrhoea, infections, cancer, antibiotic treatment.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>