<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2000078966-A1" country="WO" doc-number="2000078966" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22489483" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20001228"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2000078966-A1" status="new" fvid="77470932"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000078966</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20001228</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-0016915-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>0016915</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20000619</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-14004299-P" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>14004299</doc-number><kind>P</kind><date>19990618</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>C12N  15/30</main-classification><further-classification>A61K  39/02</further-classification><further-classification>C07K  19/00</further-classification><further-classification>C12N  15/62</further-classification><further-classification>G01N  33/569</further-classification><further-classification>C07K  14/20</further-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  39/00        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  39/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  39/02        20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A61K  39/02        20060101C I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  14/195       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07K  14/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N  15/30        20060101A I20060521RMWO        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12N  15/30        20060101C I20060521RMWO        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G01N  33/569       20060101A I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">G01N  33/569       20060101C I20070721RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">A61K  39/02D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07K  14/20</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">G01N  33/569D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">K61K39:00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07K203:00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07K207:00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07K319:00</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">GROUPS OF &lt;i&gt;BORRELIA BURGDORFERI&lt;/i&gt; AND &lt;i&gt;BORRELIA AFZELII&lt;/i&gt; THAT CAUSE LYME DISEASE IN HUMANS</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">GROUPES DE &lt;i&gt;BORRELIA BURGDORFERI&lt;/i&gt; ET DE &lt;i&gt;BORRELIA AFZELII&lt;/i&gt; PROVOQUANT LA MALADIE DE LYME CHEZ L'HOMME</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="WO-1994025596-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1994025596</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1995012676-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1995012676</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>ING-NANG WANG ET AL.:  "Genetic diversity of ospC in a local population of Borrelia burgdorferi sensu stricto" GENETICS, vol. 151, January 1999 (1999-01), pages 15-30, XP002147741</text><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BROOK BIOTECHNOLOGIES INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>UNIV NEW YORK</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BROOK BIOTECHNOLOGIES, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DATTWYLER RAYMOND J</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>DYKHUIZEN DANIEL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GOMES-SOLECKI MARIA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>LUFT BENJAMIN J</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SEINOST GERALD</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DATTWYLER, RAYMOND, J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>DYKHUIZEN, DANIEL</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GOMES-SOLECKI, MARIA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>LUFT, BENJAMIN, J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SEINOST, GERALD</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb"  source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention is drawn to an immunogenic composition comprising OspC polypeptides from Lyme Disease causing &lt;i&gt;Borrelia&lt;/i&gt;. In one embodiment, the immunogenic composition of the present invention comprises at least one OspC polypeptide or immunogenic fragment thereof from each of &lt;i&gt;Borrelia burgdorferi&lt;/i&gt; OspC families A, B, I and K. In another embodiment, the immunogenic composition of the present invention comprises at least one OspC polypeptide or immunogenic fragment thereof from each of &lt;i&gt;Borrelia afzelii&lt;/i&gt; OspC families A and B.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>La présente invention concerne une composition immunogène comprenant des polypeptides OspC provenant de &lt;i&gt;Borrelia&lt;/i&gt; qui provoque la maladie de Lyme. Dans une réalisation, la composition immunogène de la présente invention comprend au moins un polypeptide OspC, ou un des ses fragments immunogènes, provenant de chacune des familles A, B, I et K d'OspC de &lt;i&gt;Borrelia burgdorferi&lt;/i&gt;. Dans une autre réalisation, la composition immunogène de l'invention comprend au moins un polypeptide OspC, ou un de ses fragments immunogènes, provenant de chacune des familles A et B d'OspC de &lt;i&gt;Borrelia afzelii&lt;/i&gt;.</p></abstract><description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="2"/>--><p num="p0001"> GROUPS OF BORRELIA BURGDORFERI AND BORRELIA AFZELII THAT CAUSE LYME DISEASE L HUMANS</p><p num="p0002">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</p><p num="p0003">Lyme disease begins at the site of a tick bite, producing a primary infection with spread of the organism to secondary sites occurring early in the course of infection. Lyme disease is a progressive multi-system disorder and is the most common vector-borne disease in both North America and Europe. This disease was first described as a focus of pediatric arthritis patients in Old Lyme, CT (Steere, A.C., et al, Arth. Rheum. 20:17 (1977)). The association of this syndrome with the bite of the deer tick, Ixodes scapulaήs, led to the identification of the spirochete Borrelia burgdorferi as the causative agent (Burgdorfer, W., et al, Science, 216:1317-1319 (1982)). As culture isolation of the bacterium from clinical and field samples became more efficient, Baranton and colleagues described three pathogenic genospecies, B. Burgdorferi sensu stricto (R. Burgdorferi or B.b.s.s.), B. aβelii, and B. garinii (Baraton, G., et al., Int. J. Syst. Bacteriol. 42:378-383 (1992)). These are members of a species complex, R. burgdorferi sensu lato, which consists of at least 10 different genospecies (Piken, R.N., et al., J. Invest. Dermatoi, 110:211-214 (1998); Postic, D., et al., Int. J. Syst. Bacteriol. 44:143-152 (1994); Valsangiacomo, C.T., et al, Int. J. Syst. Bacteriol. 47:1-10 (1997)). B. Burgdorferi, B. afzelii and R. garinii are thought to be pathogenic and all are found in Europe, but in North</p><p num="p0004">America, R. burgdorferi is the only pathogenic genospecies found. Each of these three genospecies is associated with distinct clinical manifestations (Nan Dam, A. P. et al, Clin. Infect. Dis. 77:708-717 (1993)). This implies that differences in genospecies may play an important role in the wide array of clinical manifestations observed in Lyme Disease.</p><p num="p0005">As an infected tick begins to feed on a mammal, the synthesis of outer surface protein C (OspC) is induced (Schwan, T.G., et al, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2:2909-2913 (1995)). Thus, in early infection, OspC is the major outer membrane 
<!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>-->
protein expressed by the spirochete (Fung, B.P., et al, Infect. Immun. 62:3213-3221 (1994); Padula, S.J., et al, J. Clin. Microbiol, 32:1733-1738 (1994)). Even through OspC has been demonstrated to have limited surface exposure (Cox, D.L., et al, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci., 95:7973-7978 (1996); Mathiesen, M. M., et al, Infect Immun. (5(5:4073-4079 (1998)), OspC is a potent immunogen. Immunization with OspC is protective against tick-transmitted Borrelia infection (Gilmore Jr., R.D., Infect Immun. (54:2234-2239 (1999)). However, because OspC is highly variable in its sequence, the protection is limited to the Borrelia burgdorferi strain expressing the same immunizing OspC encoded by a specific allele. Challenge with heterologous isolates, expressing other ospC alleles results in infection (Probert, W.S., et al, J. Infect. D., 775:400-405 (1997)). OspC is very diverse (Jauris-Heipke, S., et al, Med. Microbiol. Immunol. 182:37-50 (1993)). Livey et al. found thirty- four alleles in seventy-six B. burgdorferi sensu lato isolates (Livey, I., et al, Mol. Microbiol. 18:251-269 (1995)). Currently, Lyme Disease is treated with antibiotics. However, such treatment is not always successful in clearing the infection. Treatment is often delayed due to improper diagnosis with the deleterious effect that the infection proceeds to a chronic condition, where treatment with antibiotics is often not useful. One of the factors contributing to delayed treatment is the lack of effective diagnostic tools. W</p><p num="p0006">Furthermore, while antigens such as OspC are known to be protective, in some cases the existence of multiple alleles of these antigens greatly hinders the development of vaccines based on such antigens that would protect against more than one strain of Borrelia. Two independent trials of first generation vaccines for the prevention of Lyme disease, recently studied the efficacy and safety of a vaccine that is based on recombinant outer surface protein A (OspA) (Sigal, L.H. et al, N. Engl. J. Med 339:216-222, 1998; Steere, NC. et al, N Engl. J. Med. 339:209-215, (1998)). However, a vaccine that consists of recombinant OspA may require frequent booster immunizations. Natural infection with B. burgdorferi does not elicit an antibody response to OspA, as it does against OspC. What is needed is a 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
selection of Borrelia antigens that can be used to either diagnose or vaccinate against all or most forms of Borrelia that cause systemic disease.</p><p num="p0007">Differences in the frequency of R. burgdorferi, B. garinii, and B. afzelii in ticks and human infection has lead to the hypothesis that the different genospecies are differentially pathogenic (Picken, R.N. et al, J. Invest. Dermatol. 770:211-214, 1998; Van Dam, A.P. et al, Clin. Infect. Dis. 7:708-717, 1993). Nevertheless, the number of different strains within a given genospecies and the differences between the strains of a given genospecies as well as between genospecies impose obstacles in the development of immunogenic protein compounds for use as diagnostic and vaccine agents in the detection, prevention and treatment of Lyme disease. A number of investigators have used OspC as a serodiagnostic antigen for early Lyme disease (Fung, B.P. et al, Infect. Immun. (52:3213-3221, 1994; Gerber, M.A. et al, J. Infect. Dis. 171:724-727, 1995; Padula, S.J. et al, J. Clin. Microbiol 32:1733- 1738, (1994)). In these tests, the use of OspC as a diagnostic antigen gave highly specific, but not sensitive results. However, these studies included only one B. burgdorferi strain and therefore only one type of OspC. Routine tests for the diagnosis of Lyme disease also use a single strain protocol and therefore a single OspC allele for detection of antibody to the sprirochete. It is not clear what mixture of OspC proteins must be used to make useful diagnostic and vaccine tools, effective against more than one Lyme disease causing strains of Borrelia, if not against most if not all of the invasive strains within a genospecies. Preferably, such a mixture would be effective against all invasive strains of Lyme disease causing borrelia.</p><p num="p0008">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</p><p num="p0009">The present invention is drawn to a composition comprising OspC polypeptides from Lyme Disease causing Borrelia. In one embodiment, the composition of the present invention comprises an OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from at least two Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families selected from the group consisting of A, B, I and K, excepting the combination consisting of two OspC proteins, wherein one OspC protein is from OspC family A and the second 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
OspC protein is from OspC family I. In another embodiment, the composition of the present invention comprises at least one OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from each of Borrelia afzelii OspC families A and B.</p><p num="p0010">The present invention is also drawn to a method of immunizing an animal against Lyme disease, comprising administering a composition comprising OspC polypeptides from Lyme Disease causing Borrelia. In one embodiment of the present invention, the composition comprises a OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from at least two Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families selected from the group consisting of: A, B, I and K, excepting the combination consisting of two OspC proteins, wherein one OspC protein is from OspC family A and the second OspC protein is from OspC family I. In another embodiment of the present invention, the composition comprises at least one OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from each of Borrelia afzelii OspC families A and B. The composition of the present invention together with suitable excipients and/or adjuvants is administered to an animal such that the animal develops an immune response to at least one OspC polypeptide of the composition.</p><p num="p0011">The present invention is also drawn to a method of detecting an immune response to Lyme Disease causing Borrelia in a host sample. The method comprises contacting a host sample with a composition comprising OspC polypeptides from Lyme disease causing strains of Borrelia, such that anti-OspC antibodies, if present, in said sample bind to said OspC polypeptides. In one embodiment, the composition comprises at least one OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from each of Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families A, B, I and K. The amount of antibodies that have bound said OspC polypeptides or fragments thereof are measured; thereby detecting an immune response to Lyme disease causing Borrelia.</p><p num="p0012">The present invention is also drawn to a diagnostic kit comprising OspC polypeptides from Lyme Disease causing Borrelia. In one embodiment of the present invention, the diagnostic kit comprises at least one OspC polypeptide or diagnostic fragment thereof from each of Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families A, B, I and K. In another embodiment of the present invention, the diagnostic composition 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
comprises at least one OspC polypeptide or diagnostic fragment thereof from each of Borrelia afzelii OspC families A and B.</p><p num="p0013">In other embodiments of the present invention, the composition comprises at least one OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from each of Borrelia afzelii OspC families A and B. In still other embodiments, the composition comprises OspC polypeptides or fragments thereof from Borrelia burgdorferi, Borrelia afzelii, Borrelia garinii and combinations thereof.</p><p num="p0014">The present invention is also drawn to chimeric proteins for use in the methods of the present invention. In one embodiment, the present invention is drawn to a chimeric protein comprising OspC polypeptides from two or more OspC families of Lyme Disease causing Borrelia. In one embodiment, the families comprise Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families A, B, I and K. In other embodiment, the families comprise Borrelia afzelii OspC families A and B. In still other embodiments, the composition comprises chimeric OspC polypeptides or fragments thereof from Borrelia burgdorferi, Borrelia afzelii, Borrelia garinii and combinations thereof.</p><p num="p0015">The chimeric proteins of the present invention comprise at least a first and a second polypeptide of OspC, such that the first polypeptide comprises OspC from about base 26 to about base 630 of a first ospC gene and the second polypeptide comprises about base 28 to about base 570 of a second ospC gene. The chimeric proteins of the present invention can be used in the immunization and detection methods of the present invention.</p><p num="p0016">The present invention provides the minimum number of Borrelia burgdorferi and Borrelia afzelii families that are responsible for systemic disease in humans and is useful for vaccines and diagnostic kits. The present invention provides a combination of proteins that, when used as a vaccine, prevent Lyme disease from becoming systemic. The proteins and chimeric proteins of the present invention can be effective in preventing of Lyme disease as well as having a therapeutic effect on established infection, for example after the tick bite is noticed by the patient. The proteins and chimeric proteins of the present invention are expected to act at the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
level of the tick as well as the level of the host in preventing both infection and disease due to Borrelia burgdorferi, Borrelia afzelii and/or Borrelia garinii. The present invention allows the development of a worldwide vaccine comprising only six proteins necessary to generate a protective immune response against all pathogenic strains of Borrelia burgdorferi and Borrelia afzelii.</p><p num="p0017">The present invention also provides improved diagnostic tools. Because of the present invention, it is now possible to prepare diagnostic tools comprising OspC antigens representing the four pathogenic families of Borrelia burgdorferi and/or the two pathogenic families of Borrelia afzelii, thereby detecting clinically important exposure to pathogenic bacteria while overlooking the remainder of the families which do not cause pathogenic disease.</p><p num="p0018">As demonstrated herein, a significant proportion, if not all, systemic B. burgdorferi sensu stricto infections in humans are associated with four ospC groups and that a significant portion, if not all, systematic R. afzelii infections in humans are associated with two ospC groups. Vaccines against OspC are known to be protective, but have been limited by the diversity of ospC (Probert, W.S. et al, J. Infect. D. 175:400-405, (1997)). The polypeptides of the present invention provide immunogenic proteins, fragments and chimeric proteins thereof for highly protective vaccines and diagnostics. The present invention provides a vaccine that includes one or more of these four forms of OspC. The vaccines of the present invention should be an important second level of protection against disseminated infection of the R. burgdorferi spirochete. Furthermore, single-stranded conformational polymorphism (SSCP) analysis described herein may provide a rapid and powerful tool to monitor vaccine efficacy by detecting rare or new invasive ospC groups. New diagnostic assays of the present invention, based on major ospC groups</p><p num="p0019">A, B, I, and K are useful to identify those at risk for progressive illness. Given that OspC proteins are antigenically variable, individuals infected with one strain may produce an antibody response that is not reactive with an OspC protein from a different major group. Antibody detection using antigen preparations of the present invention, incorporating a proper mix of invasive clones of R. burgdorferi will be 
<!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>-->
much more sensitive than the present, single strain protocols. The compositions of the present invention not only elicit humoral and cell mediated immune responses, the compositions of the present invention are also capable of detecting both humoral and cell mediated immune response when used to test a host sample. The present invention provides both lipidated OspC polypeptides, fragments thereof and chimeric proteins comprising two or more OspC polypeptides, wherein the chimeric protein has a lipidation signal, such as the lipidation signal from outer surface protein B at the 5' terminus of the gene encoding the chimera. Furthermore, the present invention provides unlipidated OspC polypeptides, fragments thereof and chimeric proteins comprising two or more OspC polypeptides, wherein the gene encoding the chimeric protein does not comprise a lipidation signal and the chimeric protein is not lipidated. Unlipidated OspC polypeptides, fragments thereof and chimeric proteins thereof are advantageous due to simpler production methods, improved yields of protein and simpler purification. The unlipidated chimeric proteins of the present invention unexpectedly elicit an immune response against Lyme disease causing strains of Borrelia at least as broadly reactive as lipidated OspC proteins that are used as a positive control. Furthermore, the unlipidated OspC chimeric proteins of the present invention elicit an immune response to more than one genospecies of Lyme disease causing strains of Borrelia, including genospecies and strains that are not used to generate the chimeric OspC immunogen.</p><p num="p0020">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</p><p num="p0021">Figure 1 is a schematic diagram of the frequency distribution of major ospC groups among B. burgdorferi isolates from Eastern Long Island Ixodes scapularis ticks. Figure 2 is a bar graph showing the reactivity of serum from mice immunized with the indicated Borrelia protein or recombinant chimeric Borrelia protein (X-axis) against the indicated OspC antigens (legend) where the serum is from the first bleed. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>-->
 Figure 3 is a bar graph showing the reactivity of serum from mice immunized with the indicated Borrelia protein or recombinant chimeric Borrelia protein (X-axis) against the indicated OspC antigens (legend) where the serum is from the second bleed. Figure 4 is a bar graph showing the reactivity of serum from mice immunized with the indicated Borrelia protein or chimeric recombinant Borrelia protein (X-axis) against the indicated strains of Borrelia burgdorferi sensu stricto (legend).</p><p num="p0022">Figure 5 is a bar graph showing the reactivity of serum from mice immunized with the indicated Borrelia protein or chimeric recombinant Borrelia protein (X-axis) against the indicated strains of Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato (legend).</p><p num="p0023">Figure 6 is bar graph showing the reactivity of serum from mice immunized with the indicated Borrelia protein or chimeric recombinant Borrelia protein (X- axis) against the indicated strains of Borrelia afzelii (legend).</p><p num="p0024">Figure 7 is bar graph showing the reactivity of serum from mice immunized with the indicated Borrelia protein or chimeric recombinant Borrelia protein (X- axis) against the indicated strains of Borrelia garinii (legend).</p><p num="p0025">Figure 8 is a Table comparing the reactivity of lipidated OspC proteins Cl and C2 against sera from patients with the indicated condition with the reactivity of the unlipidated chimeric proteins of the present invention, where the number in parentheses is the total number of sera tested in that category.</p><p num="p0026">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</p><p num="p0027">As described herein, initially nineteen groups of ospC from B. burgdorferi sensu stricto were found within a small tick population (Wang, I-N., et al, Genetics, 757:15-30 (1999)). Major ospC groups were defined using the observation that ospC alleles are either very similar, having less than 2% sequence divergence, or very different, having greater than 8% sequence divergence, with most having greater than 14% sequence divergence. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="10"/>-->
 Based on sequence divergences, alleles of ospC can be grouped into twenty- one major groups (Table II). To assess whether strain differences as defined by a given ospC group are linked to invasiveness and pathogenicity, the frequency distributions of major ospC groups from ticks, from the primary erythema migrans (EM) skin lesion, and from secondary sites, principally from blood and spinal fluid, were compared. As described herein, the frequency distribution oϊospC groups from ticks is significantly different from that of primary site infection which in turn is significantly different from secondary sites. The major ospC groups A, B, I and K increased in frequency from ticks to the primary site and were the only groups found in secondary sites of the infection. Therefore, three categories of major ospC groups are defined herein. One category is common in ticks but very rarely, if ever, causes human disease, a second category that causes only local infection at the tick bite site, and a third category that causes systemic or disseminated disease. While many ospC groups found in ticks were also found in primary skin lesions, the frequency distributions are significantly different between ticks and primary skin lesions</p><p num="p0028">(Table III). All ospC groups were found more or less commonly in ticks. However, only four groups are commonly found in skin lesions or secondary infections (Tables III and IV). As described herein, the primary skin lesions harbored Borrelia having ospC groups other than A, B. I or K rarely or not at all. More importantly, only these four ospC groups were found in secondary sites. The finding that all systemic R. burgdorferi sensu stricto infections are associated with four ospC groups has importance in the diagnosis, treatment and prevention of Lyme disease.</p><p num="p0029">There is evidence that ospC has been transferred between strains and even between genospecies (Wang I-N, et al, Genetics, 757:15-30 (1998)). This is not true of Borrelia chromosomal genes (Dykhuizen, D.E., et al, Proc. Natl Acad. Sci., 50:10163-10167 (1999); Maynard Smith, J. and Smith, N.H., Mol. Biol. Evol, 75:590-599 (1998)). However, ospA and ospC alleles in R. Burgdorferi sensu stricto are almost completely linked (Wang I-N, et al, Genetics, 757:15-30 (1999)). This suggests that once an ospC allele has been transferred into a particular background, there is little or no selection for another similar recombination event. Thus, each 
<!-- EPO <DP n="11"/>-->
major ospC group represents a clonal population descended from a single recombination.</p><p num="p0030">Twenty percent of untreated erythema migrans clear spontaneously without causing any systemic complications (Steere, A.C. et al, Arth. Rheum. 20:7-17, (1977)). As demonstrated herein, this is not significantly different (p = 0.25 for a 2 by 2 contingency test with double dichotomy) from the percent of non- invasive strains found in the skin, suggesting that the erythema migrans that clear spontaneously are caused by non-invasive clones.</p><p num="p0031">There is extensive genetic and antigenic diversity of ospC in all three pathogenic genospecies of R. burgdorferi sensu lato (Livey, I. et al, Mol. Microbiol.</p><p num="p0032">75:257-269, 1995; Masuzawa, T. et al, Clin. Diagn. Lab. Immunol 4:60-63, 1997;</p><p num="p0033">Picken, R.N. et al, J. Invest. Dermatol. 770:211-214, 1998; Theisen, M. et al, J.</p><p num="p0034">Clin. Microbiol 57:2570-2576, 1993; Wang, I-N. et al, Genetics 757:15-30 (1999).</p><p num="p0035">As demonstrated herein, only four groups of ospC alleles are linked to both infectivity and invasiveness, and that invasiveness is confined to a small number of ospC clones. It is clear that the ospA and ospC alleles are tightly linked even though they are on different plasmids (Wang, I-N. et al, Genetics 757:15-30 (1999)). If the invasiveness is caused by allelic variation at another locus, this variation is likely to be tightly linked to the ospC variation. Thus, ospC is a good marker for human pathogenicity and perhaps its determinator. These findings have important implications not only for our understanding of the pathogenesis of this disease but for its diagnosis and prevention.</p><p num="p0036">Spirochetemia is a transient phenomenon, but is presumably key in seeding secondary skin sites, the heart, joints, and nervous system, where these Borrelia cause the secondary and tertiary clinical manifestations of Lyme disease. All four invasive groups of Borrelia burgdorferi were found in isolates from blood and CSF.</p><p num="p0037">The one joint isolate belonged to group A. However, it can be inferred that groups not found in the blood will not be found in the joints since most if not all dissemination of Borrelia to secondary sites is via blood. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="12"/>-->
 Normally, model organisms are used as substitutes for experiments on humans. However, this substitution works only as long as the properties of the model organism and of humans are the same for the studied phenomena. The human immune system plays a critical role which is expected to be different from the immune response in model organisms, particularly the mouse. Humans are accidental and usually dead-end hosts while the mouse is a critical host reservoir. The field of population genetics has developed sound procedures for reaching conclusions from survey data.</p><p num="p0038">The chimeric polypeptides of the present invention elicit specific immune responses to OspC. The chimeric polypeptides also elicit immune response against strains of Lyme disease causing Borrelia of the same genospecies as that represented by the chimeric OspC as well as Lyme disease causing Borrelia of different genospecies than that represented by the chimeric OspC. The immune response includes humoral responses, secretory responses, cell-mediated responses and combinations thereof in an animal treated with the compositions of the present invention. The compositions of the present invention can include additional components suitable for in vitro and in vivo use. These additional components include buffers, carrier proteins, adjuvants, preservatives and combinations thereof. The immunogenic compositions of the present invention can be used to immunize animals including humans. Immunization is understood to elicit specific immunogenic responses as described above. As described herein, an immunogenic response includes responses that result in at least some level of immunity in the treated animal, where the animal was treated with a composition comprising at least one protein or chimeric protein of the present invention. In one embodiment, the treated animal develops immunity against infection by Lyme disease causing Borrelia, wherein the chimeric proteins of the present invention elicit responses against Borrelia burgdorferi, Borrelia afzelii and Borrelia garinii.</p><p num="p0039">Immunity, as described herein, is understood to mean the ability of the treated animal to resist infection, to resist systemic infection, to overcome infection such as systemic infection or to overcome infection such as systemic infection more 
<!-- EPO <DP n="13"/>-->
easily or more quickly when compared to non-immunized or non-treated individuals. Immunity can also include an improved ability of the treated individual to sustain an infection with reduced or no clinical symptoms of systemic infection. The individual may be treated with the chimeric proteins of the present invention either proactively, e.g. once a year or maybe treated after sustaining a tick bite.</p><p num="p0040">For use as a vaccine, the composition of the present invention can include suitable adjuvants, well known in the art, to enhance immunogenicity, potency or half-life of the chimeric proteins in the treated animal. Adjuvants and their use are well known in the art (see for example PCT Publication WO 96/40290, the entire teachings of which are incorporated herein by reference). The composition can be prepared by known methods of preparing vaccines. For example, the OspC proteins or chimeric proteins to be used in the compositions can be isolated and/or purified by known techniques such as by size exclusion chromatography, affinity chromatography, preparative electrophoresis, selective precipation or combinations thereof. The prepared proteins or chimeric proteins can be mixed with suitable other reagents as described above, where the chimeric protein is at a suitable concentration. The dosage of protein or chimeric protein will vary from one μg to 500 μg and depends upon the age, weight and/or physical condition of the animal to be treated. The optimal dosage can be determined by routine optimization techniques, using suitable animal models.</p><p num="p0041">The composition to be used as a vaccine can be administered by any suitable technique. In one embodiment, administration is by injection, e.g. subcutaneous, intramuscular, intravenous, or intra peritoneal injection. In another embodiment, the composition is administered to mucosa, e.g. by exposing nasal mucosa to nose drops containing the proteins of chimeric proteins of the present invention. In another embodiment, the immunogenic composition is administered by oral administration. In another embodiment of the present invention the chimeric proteins are administered by DNA immunization.</p><p num="p0042">Like many outer surface proteins of Borrelia, OspC is produced in the Borrelia spirochete with 5' lipidation. The chimeric polypeptides of the present 
<!-- EPO <DP n="14"/>-->
invention can be produced in both lipidated and non-lipidated form. In one embodiment, the lipidation signal encoded by the wild type ospC is removed from the coding sequence, such that the gene or chimeric gene encodes a non-lipidated OspC or chimeric OspC polypeptide. In another embodiment of the present invention, the lipidation signal of the wild type ospC gene is replaced with the lipidation signal of the ospB gene. In this embodiment, a lipidated OspC or OspC chimeric protein is produced.</p><p num="p0043">The polypeptides of the present invention can be recombinantly expressed in suitable microbial hosts, wherein said hosts include, but are not limited to, bacterial hosts, such as E. coli, fungal hosts S. cerevisiae, or cell culture hosts such as mammalian cell culture or insect cell culture.</p><p num="p0044">While the lack of lipidation signal allows for the production of large amounts of OspC proteins and chimeric OspC proteins, the lack of lipidation signal was previously thought to render outer surface proteins of Borrelia less or non- immunogenic. However, as described herein, the non lipidated chimeric polypeptides of the present invention unexpectedly elicit as broad an immunogenicity as lipidated OspC protein (Figures 2 and 3) and greater immunogenicity against strains of other genospecies (Figure 5-7) compared to the positive controls, which were lipidated OspC from B31 and lipidated OspC from C12.</p><p num="p0045">The proteins and chimeric proteins of the present invention are also antigenic and therefore useful to detect or diagnose the presence of Lyme disease causing Borrelia, especially Borrelia from groups capable of causing disseminated symptoms of Lyme disease. As described herein, disseminated symptoms refers to infection outside of the erythema migrans skin lesion, e.g. infection in blood, CNS or synovia. As described herein, antigenic refers to the ability of a compound to bind products of an immune response, such as antibodies, T-cell receptors or both. Such responses can be measured using standard antibody detection assays, such as ΕLISA or standard T-cell activation assays. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="15"/>-->
 The present invention is drawn to compositions comprising OspC polypeptides from Lyme disease causing Borrelia and chimeric OspC polypeptides. In one embodiment of the present invention, compositions include one or more OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from at least two Borrelia burgdorferi ospC groups, referred also herein as families, selected from the group consisting of A, B, I and K, excepting the combination consisting of two OspC polypeptides from the A and I families. In another embodiment of the present invention, the compositions of the present invention include at least one OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from each of Borrelia burgdorferi ospC families A, B, I and K. In another embodiment, the composition includes at least one OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from each of Borrelia afzelii OspC families A and B. In still another embodiment, the composition includes OspC polypeptides from at least one Borrelia burgdorferi OspC group or family member selected from the group consisting of A, B, I and K and at least one Borrelia afzelii OspC family member selected from the group consisting of A and B .</p> <p num="p0046">As described herein, the ospC families of the present invention share about 98% homology at the nucleic acid level between strains of the same family and share no more than about 92% homology at the nucleic acid level between strains of different families. Determination of homology excludes any non-ospC sequences. Members of the same ospC family have similar antigenic profiles, e.g. elicit immune response against similar strains of Lyme disease causing Borrelia. The chimeric proteins of the present invention unexpectedly elicit immune response to Lyme disease causing Borrelia of different genospecies than the genospecies from which the component polypeptides were derived. In one embodiment of the present invention, Borrelia burgdorferi ospC family A comprises strains B31, CA4, HII, rPI, TP2, LP3, L5, PD7, PKA, TXGW and strains of Borrelia containing ospC allele OC1. In another embodiment of the present invention, Borrelia burgdorferi ospC family B comprises strains 35B808, 61BV3, BUR, DK7, PB3, ZS7 and strains containing ospC alleles OC2 and OC3. In still another embodiment of the present invention, Borrelia burgdorferi ospC family I comprises strains 297, HB 19 and 
<!-- EPO <DP n="16"/>-->
strains containing ospC allele OC10, wherein strain 297 is characterized by ospC of GenBank Accession No. L42893. In still another embodiment of the present invention, Borrelia burgdorferi ospC family K comprises strains 272, 297, 28354, KTPP, MUL and strains containing ospC allele OC12 and OC13, wherein strain 297 is characterized by ospC of GenBank Accession No. U08284.</p><p num="p0047">In another embodiment of the present invention, said compositions comprise an OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from each of Borrelia afzelii OspC families A and B. In one embodiment of the present invention, Borrelia afzelii OspC family A comprises strains Pbo, Pwud, Pko, Pgau, DK2, DK3, DK21, DK8, Bfox and JSB. In another embodiment of the present invention Borrelia afzelii OspC family B comprises strains DK5, ACA1, DK9, XB18h, Pie and 143M. As described above for Borrelia burgdorferi the compositions also include chimeric OspC polypeptides of Borrelia afzelii families A and B.</p><p num="p0048">In one embodiment of the present invention, the OspC polypeptide OspC polypeptide is a chimeric OspC comprising at least one OspC protein variable region or portion thereof from at least one ospC gene. In one embodiment of the present invention, the OspC polypeptide variable region is encoded by a nucleic acid comprising the 3' two thirds of the OspC gene, about nucleotide 150 to about nucleotide 519 of an ospC gene (or about codon 50 to about codon 173). In another embodiment of the present invention, said OspC polypeptide variable region is encoded by a nucleic acid wherein the nucleic acid comprises, for example, nucleotide 244 to about nucleotide 519 (or about codon 81 to about codon 173), nucleic acid from about nucleotide 337 to about nucleotide 519 (or about codon 112 to about codon 173), nucleic acid from about nucleotide 418 to about nucleotide 519 (or about codon 139 to about codon 173), nucleic acid from about nucleotide 244 to about nucleotide 418 (or about codon 81 to about codon 139), nucleic acid from about nucleotide 337 to about nucleotide 418 (or about codon 112 to about codon 139), and nucleic acid from about nucleotide 150 to about nucleotide 243 (or about codon 50 to about codon 81) of an ospC gene. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="17"/>-->
 In still another embodiment, the chimeric OspC polypeptides of the present invention comprises two or more polypeptides wherein a first polypeptide is from a first ospC gene from about nucleotide 26 (or about codon 8) to about nucleotide 630 (or about codon 210). In another embodiment, the first polypeptide is from about nucleotide 28. In another embodiment, the first polypeptide is from about nucleotide 53. In still another embodiment, the first polypeptide is from about nucleotide 55. In another embodiment, the first polypeptide is up to about nucleotide 621 of a first ospC gene. In still another embodiment, the first polypeptide is up to about nucleotide 582 of a first ospC gene. In still another embodiment, the first polypeptide is up to about nucleotide 576 of a first ospC gene. The chimeric OspC of the present invention further comprises a second polypeptide, wherein the second polypeptide is derived from a second ospC gene from about nucleotide 28 (or about codon 9) to about nucleotide 571 (or about codon 190). It is understood that the polypeptides than comprise the chimeric polypeptide can include extra nucleotides or fewer nucleotides from the given ospC gene from which the polypeptide is derived in order to simplify the construction of the gene encoding the chimeric polypeptide, e.g. to allow for the use of convenient restriction endonuclease sites or to allow the ligation of the gene fragments such that a contiguous coding region is created. Based on the guidance provided herein, one of ordinary skill in the art would readily be able to add or remove nucleotides from the termini of the gene fragments encoding the polypeptides of the chimeric OspC protein to generate chimeric proteins of the present invention with no or only routine experimentation. Furthermore, there can be an extra about 1 to about 10 amino acids on the N- and/or C-terminus of the polypeptides and chimeric proteins of the present invention and still retain the properties of the present invention.</p><p num="p0049">The present invention also includes variants or altered versions of the OspC polypeptides and nucleic acids encoding said polypeptides. As used herein, a variant of a polynucleotide or polypeptide refers to a molecule that is substantially similar to either the entire molecule, or a fragment thereof. For example, when the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="18"/>-->
molecule is a polypeptide, variant refers to an amino acid sequence that is altered by one or more amino acids, wherein either a biological function, structure or antigenicity of said sequence or combination thereof is maintained in the variant. The variant may have "conservative" changes, wherein a substituted amino acid has similar structural or chemical properties, e.g., replacement of leucine with isoleucine. Or a variant may have "nonconservative" changes, e.g., replacement of a giycine with a tryptophan. Similar minor variations may also include amino acid deletions or insertions, or both. Similarly, when the molecule is a polynucleotide, variant refers to a sequence that is altered by one or more nucleotides. The variant may have silent variations, wherein the change does not alter the amino acid encoded by the triplet comprising said variation or the variation is not silent, that is, alterations in encoded amino acids are generated.</p><p num="p0050">As used herein, the term "altered version" refers to a polynucleotide sequence or a polypeptide sequence, wherein said sequence has one or more differences with a native or wildtype version of said sequence.</p> <p num="p0051">In another embodiment, the invention includes an isolated nucleic acid molecule comprising a nucleotide sequence which is homologous to one or more of the chimeric sequences of the present invention, or complements thereof. Such a nucleotide sequence exhibits at least about 80% homology, or sequence identity, with one of the chimeric OspC sequences, such that the encoded protein retains the antigenicity and immunogenicity of the unaltered chimeric protein. Preferably, the homologous sequences of the present invention shares at least about 90% homology or sequence identity with the corresponding unaltered chimeric ospC. Particularly preferred sequences have at least about 95% homology or have essentially the same sequence.</p> <p num="p0052">The altered nucleic acids and homologous nucleic acids of the present invention hybridize to the conespondmg chimeric ospC under conditions of high stringency. A general description of stringency for hybridization conditions is provided by Ausubel, F.M., et al, Current Protocols in Molecular Biology, Greene Publishing Assoc. and Wiley-Interscience 1987, &amp; Supp. 49, 2000. Factors such as 
<!-- EPO <DP n="19"/>-->
probe length, base composition, percent mismatch between the hybridizing sequences, temperature and ionic strength influence the stability of nucleic acid hybrids. Thus, stringency conditions, sufficient to allow hybridization of oligonucleotides to the template, can be varied by routine optimization to generate high stringency conditions.</p> <p num="p0053">Alternatively, conditions for stringency are as described in WO 98/40404, the teachings of which are incoφorated herein by reference. In particular, examples of highly stringent, stringent, reduced and least stringent conditions are provided in WO 98/40404 in the Table on page 36. Examples of stringency conditions are shown in Table I below which is from WO98/40404 to Jacobs et al,: highly stringent conditions are those that are at least as stringent as, for example, conditions A-F; stringent conditions are at least as stringent as, for example, conditions G-L; and reduced stringency conditions are at least as stringent as, for example, conditions M-R. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="20"/>--></p><p num="p0054">Table 1</p><p num="p0055"><img id="imgf000020_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="145" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000020_0001.tif" inline="no" he="209"/><!-- EPO <DP n="21"/>--><sup>τ</sup> The hybrid length is that anticipated for the hybridized regιon(s) of the hybndizmg polynucleotides. When hybndizmg a polynucleotide to a target polynucleotide of unknown sequence, the hybnd length is assumed to be that of the hybndizmg polynucleotide. When polynucleotides of known sequence are hybndized, the hybnd length can be determined by aligning the sequences of the polynucleotides and identifying the region or regions of optimal sequence complementanty <sup>t</sup>. SSPE (lxSSPE is 0.15M NaCI, lOmM NaH<sub>2</sub>P0<sub>4</sub>, and 1.25mM EDTA, pH 7.4) can be substituted for SSC (IxSSC is 0.15M NaCI and 15mM sodium citrate) m the hybndization and wash buffers, washes are performed for 15 minutes after hybndizauon is complete</p><p num="p0056">*T<sub>B</sub> - T<sub>R</sub>. The hybndization temperature for hybnds anticipated to be less than 50 base parrs m length should be 5-10°C less than the melting temperature (TJ of the hybnd, where T<sub>m</sub> is determined according to the following equations. For hybnds less than 18 base pans m length, T<sub>m</sub>(°C) = 2(# of A - T bases) * 4(# of G -r C bases). For hybnds between 18 and 49 base pairs in length, T<sub>m</sub>(°C) = 81 5 + 16.6(log<sub>10</sub>[Na<sup>+</sup>]) + 0 41(%G+C) - (600/N), where N is the number of bases in the hybnd, and [Na<sup>+</sup>] is the concentration of sodium ions in the hybndization buffer ([Na<sup>*</sup>] for IxSSC = 0 165 M).</p><p num="p0057">As used herein, "isolated" refers to nucleic acid or polypeptide that has been removed from its original environment (e.g., the natural environment if it is naturally occurring). For example, polynucleotide or DNA or polypeptide, which is separated from some or all of the coexisting materials in the natural system. An isolated polynucleotide can be part of a vector and/or composition, and still be isolated in that the vector or composition is not part of its natural environment. Likewise polypeptides can be part of a composition and still be isolated in that the composition is not part of its natural environment.</p><p num="p0058">The chimeric proteins of the present invention comprise OspC proteins or polypeptides as described above from two or more OspC families of Lyme disease causing Borreha as described in Table II. In one embodiment of the present invention, said families comprise Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families A, B, I and K and Borreha afzelii OspC families A and B. The chimeric proteins of the present invention comprise, for example, a first OspC polypeptide encoded by a nucleic acid comprising a sequence from about codon 18 to about codon 210 of a first ospC gene. In another embodiment, the sequence is from about codon 8. In another embodiment, the sequence is to about codon 207. In another embodiment, the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="22"/>-->
sequence is to about codon 194. In still another embodiment, the sequence is to about codon 192. The chimeric proteins of the present invention further comprise, for example, a second OspC polypeptide comprising an OspC variable polypeptide encoded by nucleic acid fragments as described above. In another embodiment of the present invention, the chimeric protein comprises two or more OspC variable polypeptides as described above.</p><p num="p0059">The chimeric proteins of the present invention further comprise, for example, a second OspC polypeptide encoded by a nucleic acid comprising a sequence from about codon 9 to about codon 190 of a second ospC gene. For the chimeric proteins of the present invention, at least two of said OspC polypeptides or immunogenic fragments thereof are fused together in a single protein, a chimeric protein, encoded by a single nucleic acid, wherein no two adjacent polypeptides in said fusion protein are found in the same configuration in a naturally occurring OspC protein. In still another embodiment, the OspC proteins or chimeric proteins of the present invention from Borrelia burgdorferi and Borrelia afzelii are combined in a composition.</p><p num="p0060">The present invention is drawn to a method of detecting an immune response to Lyme Disease causing Borrelia in a host sample. The method comprises contacting the host sample with a composition comprising OspC polypeptides from Lyme disease causing strains of Borrelia, such that anti-OspC antibodies, if present, in said sample bind to said OspC polypeptides. In one embodiment, the composition comprises one or more OspC polypeptide or diagnostic fragment thereof from two Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families selected from the group consisting of A, B, I and K, excluding the composition consisting of two OspC proteins wherein one OspC protein is from OspC family A and the second OspC protein is from OspC family I. The antibodies that bind the OspC polypeptides of the composition are detected or measured; thereby detecting an immune response to Lyme disease causing Borrelia. In another embodiment, the composition comprises at least two Borrelia OspC polypeptides or diagnostic fragment thereof from two Borrelia afzelii OspC families 
<!-- EPO <DP n="23"/>-->
selected from the group consisting of A and B. In still another embodiment, the composition comprises polypeptides from OspC from Borrelia burgdorferi and Borrelia afzelii. In still another embodiment, the composition comprises one or more polypeptides from each of Borrelia burgdorferi families A, B, I and K and Borrelia afzelii families A and B. The composition can also comprise one or more of the chimeric polypeptides of the present invention.</p><p num="p0061">The present invention is also drawn to kits comprising one or more OspC polypeptides or OspC chimeric polypeptides or combinations thereof together with suitable buffers and antibody detection reagents for the detection or diagnosis of Lyme disease causing strain of Borrelia. In another embodiment, the kits comprise nucleic acid sufficiently homologous to the OspC polypeptides or OspC chimeric polypeptides to detect nucleic acid encoding ospC genes from Lyme disease causing strains of Borrelia together with reagents to detect positive hybridization to target DNA or reagents to specifically DNA, for example. For the puφoses of a detection kit, "homologous" refers to two or more sequences that share substantial similarity but are not identical. Two DNA sequences are "substantially similar" when at least about 95% (preferably at least about 98%) of the nucleotides match over a defined length of the DNA sequences. Sequences that are substantially homologous can be identified by comparing the sequences using standard software available in sequence data banks, or in a Southern hybridization experiment under, for example, stringent conditions as defined for that particular system. Defining appropriate hybridization conditions is within the skill of the art. See, e.g., Ausubel et al, Current Protocols in Molecular Biology, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc., New York; Sambrook et al, Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press. For purposes of the present invention, amino acid sequences having, for example, greater than 90 percent similarity are considered substantially homologous.</p><p num="p0062">The vaccine compositions of the present invention elicit humoral and cell mediated immune responses in a host. Furthermore, the diagnostic compositions of 
<!-- EPO <DP n="24"/>-->
the present invention are capable of detecting both humoral and cell mediated immune response from a host sample using standard immunodiagnostic techniques.</p><p num="p0063">EXEMPLIFICATION EXAMPLE 1: - TECHNIQUES Borrelia strains</p><p num="p0064">One hundred and forty R. burgdorferi strains were isolated from primary erythema migrans (EM) lesions, blood or cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) of patients seen at the Lyme Disease Center at Stony Brook, New York, Lyme Disease Diagnostic Center at New York Medical College, Valhalla, New York or the private practices of the two collaborating physicians on the eastern end of Long Island or were obtained from the Centers for Disease Control (CDC). All patients met the Centers for Disease Control surveillance definition for Lyme Disease (CDC, Morb. Mortal. Wkly. Rep. 46:20-21, (1997)). Isolates from skin, blood and CSF were obtained using standard techniques (Barbour, A.G., Yale J. Biol. Med. 57:521-525, 1984; Berger, B.W. et al, J. Clin. Microbiol. 50:359-361, 1992; Wormser, G.P. et al, J. Clin. Microbiol 5(5:296-298, (1998)). Punch biopsies were taken from the advancing border of the erythema migrans lesion and incubated in BSK-H medium (Sigma, St. Louis, MO) at 34°C to create a culture. There was little culture bias as determined by direct analysis of biopsy tissue compared to culture isolates (Seinost, G. et al, Arch. Derm., 135:1329-1333, (1999)), unlike isolation of R. burgdorferi from unfed ticks (Norris, D.E. et al, J. Clin. Microbiol. 55:2359-2364, (1997)). In addition, twenty-two R. burgdorferi sensu stricto ospC sequences were retrieved from GenBank. The tick data used was either from GenBank or from the study of Wang et al. (Wang, I-N. et al, Genetics 757:15-30 (1999)).</p><p num="p0065">DNA isolation</p><p num="p0066">For isolation of genomic Borrelia DNA, log phase cells were harvested by centrifugation at 10,000 RPM for 30 minutes at 4°C. The bacterial pellet was resuspended in Tris/saline-buffer (10 mM Tris (pH 7.5), 150 mM NaCI). The 
<!-- EPO <DP n="25"/>-->
bacteria were then pelleted and resuspended in TNE (10 mM Tris (pH 7.5) 150 mM NaCI, 1 mM EDTA). Freshly prepared lysozyme (20 mg/ml in TNE), sodium dodecyl sulfate (10%) and proteinase K (20 mg ml) were added and the mixture was incubated at 50°C for one hour, followed by RNAse treatment. DNA was extracted with phenol/chloroform, precipitated with ethanol and resuspended in TE buffer.</p><p num="p0067">Polymerase chain reaction</p><p num="p0068">The ospC gene was amplified using PCR, as described previously (Wang, I- N. et al, Genetics 757:15-30 (1999)). The OspC gene was amplified using two external primers: 5'-AAA GAA TAC ATT AAG TGC GAT ATT-3' (+), SEQ ID NO: 1, beginning at base 6; and 5'-GGG CTT GTA AGC TCT TTA ACT G-3' (-), SEQ ED NO: 4, ending at base 602. The 5' half of ospC was amplified using SEQ ED NO: 1 and the reverse primer, 5'-CAA TCC ACT TAA TTT TTG TGT TAT TAG-3' (-) SEQ ED NO: 2; ending at base 345. The 3' half of ospC was amplified using the primer, 5'-TTG TTA GCA GGA GCT TAT GCA ATA TC-3' (+), SEQ ED NO: 3, beginning at base 289, and SEQ ED NO: 4 as the reverse primer. The external primers amplified a 597 bp fragment. Amplification of the 5' half produced a 340 bp fragment while amplification of the 3' half produced a 314 bp fragment. All the base numbers and amplified fragment sizes are based on ospC sequence of strain B31 (GenBank accession number U01894), with start codon as base 1. Amplification was conducted in 50μl of a solution containing Perkin-Elmer</p><p num="p0069">Cetus lOx PCR buffer (100 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.3), 500 mM KC1), 2.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, deoxynucleoside triphosphates at 0.2 mM per nucleotide, 2.5 U of Taq polymerase (Perkin-Elmer/Cetus) and 0.5 μM of each primer. The amplification reaction was carried out for forty cycles in a DNA thermal-cycler (PTC-100; MJ Research, Inc., Watertown, MA) with an amplification profile of: denaturation at 95°C for 40 seconds, annealing at 54°C for 35 seconds, and extension at 72°C for 1 min, after an initial denaturation step at 96°C for 2 min. Negative controls were included in each experiment to control for contamination. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="26"/>-->
Cold SSCP-analysis.</p><p num="p0070">SSCP analysis was chosen to characterize genetic variation of the isolated ospC gene fragments based on its exquisitely high detection rate of DNA polymoφhisms and point mutations at a variety of positions in DNA fragments (Orita, M. et al, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 5(52766-2770, (1989)). Single point mutations have been detected in fragments up to 800bp long (Michaud, J. et al, Genomics. 75:389-394, (1992)). However, there is evidence that the ability of SSCP analysis to detect mutations begins to decline significantly as PCR fragments approach 400bp in size (Hayashi, K., PCR Methods &amp; Applications 7:34-38, (1991)). Therefore, in order to achieve high efficiency of detection of nucleotide polymorphism, the length of the PCR products used herein was 340bp from the 5' half and 314bp from the 3' half of ospC.</p><p num="p0071">Amplified ospC gene fragments from all one hundred and forty strains were analyzed for genetic variations by the cold SSCP protocol described by Hongyo et al (Hongyo, T. et al, Nucleic. Acids Res. 27:3637-3642, (1993)). Briefly, 5 to 15 μl of the PCR product was added to a mixture containing 4 μl 5x TBE Ficoll sample Buffer (NOVEX, San Diego, CA) and 0.4 μl 1 μM methylmercury hydroxide (Alfa Aesaer, Ward Hill, MA). The amount of the PCR product used for the SSCP analysis was estimated after visualizing the PCR product on an agarose gel with ethidium bromide. The sample mixture was heated to 95°C for 4 min, then chilled on ice prior to loading the entire 20 μl into the gel sample well. The sharpest bands were observed when the sample was applied to a pre-cast 20% TBE gel (NOVEX) electrophoresis system (ThermoFlow ETC Unit, NOVEX) with 1.25x TBE running buffer. Electrophoresis of SSCP products was conducted at a constant temperature of 8°C for 17 h at 240 volts in order to reveal discemable mobility shifts. Gels were stained with 0.5 μl ml ethidium bromide in lx TBE buffer for 25 min and destained in distilled water for 30 min. Stained bands were viewed using a 340nm UV staining box. Samples that showed more than two SSCP bands were reamplified to determine whether the bands found were real alleles or the product of PCR artifacts. Side-by- 
<!-- EPO <DP n="27"/>-->
side SSCP analysis was performed in order to detect even slight shifts in electrophoretic mobility.</p><p num="p0072">DNA sequencing</p><p num="p0073">The ospC gene or representatives of each mobility class were reamplified. Double-stranded PCR fragments were purified by agarose gel electrophoresis and subjected to automated DNA sequencing using fluorescent dideoxy terminator chemistry and the forward and reverse primers originally used for PCR amplification.</p><p num="p0074">Statistical analysis</p><p num="p0075">Chi square analysis of contingency tables was performed. This analysis tests for significant difference in frequency distributions. The tables were 2xN where N is the number of major ospC groups distinguished. The average expected number in each element of the table needs to be about six or greater for an unbiased test (Zar, J.H., Biostatistical Analysis, 3rd ed, p. 206, (1996)). This means that the number of observations should be greater than 6 times 2N. When the expected average number was less than six, the major ospC groups with the lowest number in the sample were combined until the number of observations were about equal to or greater than 12N.</p><p num="p0076">RESULTS ospC mobility classes in human B. burgdorferi isolates.</p><p num="p0077">One hundred and thirty-two isolates of B. burgdorferi sensu stricto from patient samples of skin, blood, and CSF (Table II) were propagated in vitro and used as a source of DNA for analysis. The ospC genotype of each strain was determined by cold SSCP analysis of the 5' end (340bp) of the gene and was confirmed by SSCP analysis of the 3' end (314bp) of ospC. In all R. burgdorferi isolates, the genetic variation at the 5' end of the gene corresponded to the variation at the 3' end. At least two representatives of each SSCP mobility class were subsequently sequenced. The sequences of the same mobility classes were identical in all samples and each mobility class had a unique sequence. Therefore, the sensitivity and specificity of 
<!-- EPO <DP n="28"/>-->
SSCP analysis was 100%. Each SSCP mobility class was designated as an allele. Wang et al. recently described 13 ospC alleles (Wang, I-N. et al, Genetics 757:15- 30). An additional five ospC (OC) mobility classes, OC14-18 are described herein. OC14 has the same ospC sequence as the ospC in strain 2591. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="29"/>--></p><p num="p0078">TABLE El. Alignment of major ospC groups with ospC alleles identified by SSCP analysis</p><p num="p0079">Major ospC ospC allele GenBank Dis¬</p><p num="p0080">Group (SSCP) number<sup>1</sup> Ticks Skin<sup>2</sup> seminated<sup>2</sup></p><p num="p0081">A 1 AF029860 17 23 21</p><p num="p0082">B 2 AF029861 17 19 4</p><p num="p0083">C 3 AF029862 11 3 0</p><p num="p0084">D 4 AF029863 10 1 0</p><p num="p0085">E 5, 7 AF029864 6 1 0</p><p num="p0086">F 6 AF029865 9 0 0</p><p num="p0087">G 8 AF029867 5 7 0</p><p num="p0088">H 9 AF029868 7 6 0</p><p num="p0089">I 10 AF029869 1 9 3</p><p num="p0090">J 11, 18 AF029870 3 7 0</p><p num="p0091">K 12, 13 AF029871 6 32 16</p><p num="p0092">L - L42899 2 0 0</p><p num="p0093">M 14 U01892 1 3 0</p><p num="p0094">N 15 L42899 1 3 0</p><p num="p0095">O - X84778 0 1 0</p><p num="p0096">P - U91796 1 0 0</p><p num="p0097">Q - U91790 1 0 0</p><p num="p0098">R - U91791 2 0 0</p><p num="p0099">S - U91793 1 0 0</p><p num="p0100">T 16 AF065143 0 1 0 u 17 AF065144 0 2 0</p><p num="p0101"><sup>1</sup> A single GenBank sequence of each type is given as an example. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="30"/>--><sup>2</sup> The number of each major ospC group observed in blood, synovial fluid or cerebrospinal fluid. This includes both SSCP data and data from the literature, including GenBank. *R. burgdorferi sensu stricto Groups P through S are only found in Europe. Groups R and S are excluded from the analysis because nearly identical ospC alleles are found in B. afzelii and B. garinii, showing these groups were recently created by cross-species transfer.</p><p num="p0102">Multiple infections Of the one hundred and thirty-two primary isolates from patients with Lyme disease in this study, most contained only a single strain. Seven skin isolates and one CSF isolate contained two different strains as determined by SSCP analysis, thus giving a total of one hundred and forty different strains. The ospC allele pairs found in multiply infected erythema migrans biopsy specimens were (OCl, OCl 2), (OCl, OC14), 2x(OC2, OC3), 2x(OC2, OC12), and (OC8, OC18). CSF isolate</p><p num="p0103">NY940657 contained ospC alleles OCl and OCl 2. For CSF isolate 297, which was isolated in Connecticut, there were two ospC sequences published in GenBank: L42893, which is analogous to OC10 and U08284, which is analogous to OC12. The pair- wise difference of ospC sequences of both strains is 16.4%, suggesting CNS infection with two different strains in this isolate. Overall, 5.5% of all isolates described herein contained two strains. Because as many as 50% of ticks isolated in the wild are infected with multiple strains, exposure to multiple strains in a single tick bite is common, raising the possibility that different strains are differentially pathogenic. To these one hundred forty strains for which the ospC allele was determined herein, twenty-two strains of known ospC sequence from GenBank were added to give a total of one hundred sixty-two. Fifty-one of these strains were obtained either from eastern Long Island; seventy-seven were obtained from Westchester County, New York, and the remainder from other endemic areas in the United States 
<!-- EPO <DP n="31"/>-->
(twenty-two strains) and Europe (twelve strains). The isolates were divided into those from the site of the primary infection, the erythema migrans skin lesion (one hundred eighteen isolates), and those from secondary sites, where the infection had disseminated (forty-four isolates). This later group included, for example, twenty from cerebro-spinal fluid (CSF), twenty-three from blood, and one from synovial fluid.</p><p num="p0104">Major ospC groups in human R. burgdorferi isolates</p><p num="p0105">Surprisingly, as described herein, the differences between ospC sequences among and between the families of R. burgdorferi sensu stricto fell into two groups. Pairs of ospC genes within the same family differed in nucleic acid sequence by less than two percent while pairs of ospC genes from separate families in nucleic acid sequence differed by more than eight percent. Wang et al, defined nineteen major ospC groups, designated A to S (Wang, I-N. et al, Genetics 757:15-30 (1999)). As described herein, two additional ospC groups are provided, designated T and U. OC16 represents major group T and OC17 represents major group U (Table I). The lowest pair-wise differences of group T and U to any other major ospC group are 16.1% and 20.5% respectively.</p><p num="p0106">R. burgdorferi clones are differentially pathogenic</p><p num="p0107">As described herein, clones representing different ospC groups of Borrelia burgdorferi are differentially pathogenic. This is demonstrated by the differing frequencies of the various major ospC groups in ticks, in the initial infection in the skin, and in disseminated infections.</p><p num="p0108">The strains in GenBank and the literature for which the ospC sequences have been determined were widely sampled from the entire geographic range of the species and were chosen irrespective of whether they were from ticks or humans.</p><p num="p0109">These strains gave a small but random sample of the frequencies of the major ospC groups in ticks and humans. As demonstrated herein, the frequency of the major ospC groups from human isolates was found to be significantly different from the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="32"/>-->
frequency found in ticks on Long Island. Table IE shows that the frequency distribution of strains from skin from eastern Long Island differ significantly from tick strains collected in the same area.</p><p num="p0110">TABLE in Major ospC groups A B C D F G H I K Comb.<sup>a</sup></p><p num="p0111">Isolates From</p><p num="p0112">Erythema migrans 13 6 2 0 0 1 0 4 16 4 lesions (N=46)</p><p num="p0113">Ixodes scapularis 12 12 11 9 6 5 7 1 5 6 ticks (N=74)</p><p num="p0114">χ<sup>2</sup> = 36.3 with 9 degrees of freedom pO.OOl <sup>a</sup> Combined major groups are defined by individual frequencies of 0.025 or less and include groups E, J, N, O.</p><p num="p0115">The analysis provided herein of all ospC groups presented in this study showed that most groups are found in both ticks and in humans (Table II). However, major groups A, B, I and K predominated in humans, with A and K groups found most frequently. (Figure 1).</p><p num="p0116">The pattern of pathogenicity of the various clones as demonstrated by frequency in the primary site of infection, the skin, compared to the frequency in secondary sites revealed that only four major groups (A, B, I and K) were found in both the skin and secondary sites (compare Tables III an EV). All other major groups were found only in the skin. When all groups with three or fewer isolates are combined to give the combined group of Table EV, a 2 by 8 contingency test comparing the frequency distribution of skin versus secondary sites gives a significance of p&lt;0.005. When no groups are combined, a 2 by 15 contingency test is still sigmficant (χ<sup>2</sup> = 24.07 with 14 degrees of freedom, p&lt;0.05). The distribution 
<!-- EPO <DP n="33"/>-->
of strains from primary and secondary sites indicated that only a certain of the major groups, A, B, I, and K cause disseminated disease. As described herein, these are referred to as invasive clones whereas other clones are referred to as non- invasive clones.</p><p num="p0117">TABLE EV</p><p num="p0118">Major ospC groups A B G H I J K Comb. Isolates From Erythema migrans 23 19 7 6 9 7 32 16 lesions (N= 118) Disseminated Infections 21 4 0 0 3 0 16 0 (N=44)</p><p num="p0119">χ<sup>2</sup> = 23.6 with 7 degrees of freedom p&lt;0.005 <sup>a</sup> Combined major groups are defined by individual frequencies of 0.025 or less and include groups C, D, E, M, N, O, T and U.</p><p num="p0120">As described herein, the different clones of R. burgdorferi sensu stricto, as defined by ospC groups, are differentially pathogenic. Some groups very rarely, if ever, cause human disease, e.g. ospC groups D, E, F, and L. Some groups cause a local infection at the tick bite site, but not systemic disease, e.g. ospC groups G, H,</p><p num="p0121">J, and T. Finally, there are some groups which are responsible for systemic disease; these are ospC groups A, B, I, and K. Our findings indicate that all systemic R. burgdorferi sensu stricto infections in humans are caused by strains in these four ospC groups.</p><p num="p0122">Figure 1 shows the frequency distribution of major ospC groups among R. burgdorferi isolates from Eastern Long Island Ixodes scapularis ticks, n=72, (A); erythema migrans lesions, n=l 18, (B); and secondary sites of infection, n=44, (C). 
<!-- EPO <DP n="34"/>-->
The percentage of group A plus K increased from 23% in the tick isolates, to 47% in the skin isolates, and to 84% in the secondary sites. The length of the bars in Figure 1 reflect this increase, by holding the length of the combined A and K groups constant. In the skin, groups C, D, E, M, N, O, T and U have been combined since their individual frequencies are 0.025 or less. This combination of groups when combined make up 12.7% of the total number of strains.</p><p num="p0123">A similar analysis was conducted for Borrelia afzelii. The analysis included OspC alleles from 21 strains from GenBank and 12 strains sequenced for this study. These sequences fell into 20 major groups where the definition of a group is less that 1% sequence diversity within a group and at least 7.7% sequence difference between groups. There were two exceptions to this rule which were caused by a deletion in one ospC gene and a cross-species transfer of a small section of DNA in another ospC gene. When these anomalous sections were removed, all ospC alleles fell into 20 groups. Only two groups contained strains from chronic infections - groups A and B. By analogy and the R. burgdorferi study, it appears that only two groups are pathogenic in R. afzelii.</p><p num="p0124">EXAMPLE 2: Protein Expression and Immunoblot</p><p num="p0125">Protein Expression</p><p num="p0126">The Escherichia coli (strain BL21 (pLysS) or strain B834 (DE3)) were transformed with the plasmid encoding the recombinant chimeric Borrelia proteins</p><p num="p0127">(RCBPs), and grown in 10 ml LB media (5 g/1 NaCI, 10 g/1 tryptone, 5 g/1 yeast extract, 25 mg/1 chloramphenicol and 50 mg/1 ampicillin) at 37°C, with shaking.</p><p num="p0128">When the optical density at 600λ reached 0.3-0.4 units, recombinant protein expression was induced by adding IPTG (isopropyl B-D-thiogalactopyranoside) to a final concentration of 0.5 mM and the cells were grown for an additional three hours. The cultures were harvested by centrifugation at 3800xg for five minutes.</p><p num="p0129">The cells were resuspended in 20 mM NaPO<sub>4</sub>, pH7.7 and stored at -20°C overnight.</p><p num="p0130">Once thawed, the crude extracts were incubated with DNase (2 μg/ml) in the presence of 2.5 mM of MgCl<sub>2</sub> at room temperature for thirty minutes, spun at 14000 
<!-- EPO <DP n="35"/>-->
rpm (Eppendorf 5417C) for five minutes and 5 μl of the protein sample was run on a SDS-PAGE which was either stained in Commassie Blue or used for Immunoblot. Protein samples were solubilized, usually with a sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS) containing buffer and in selected cases with reducing agents such as dithiothreitol (DTT) or 2-mercaptoethanol (2-ME). Following solubilization, the material was separated by SDS-PAGE. The proteins were then eletrophoretically transferred to a polyvinylidene difluoride membrane (PVDF, Immobilon-P®, Millipore). The transfer of proteins was monitored by a reversible staining procedure, Ponceau S. The stained membrane was made and the membrane destained by soaking in water for 10 minutes. All non-specific binding sites in the proteins and on the membrane were blocked by immersing the membrane in a solution containing a protein or detergent blocking agent (5 % milk in tris-buffered saline (TBS) Tween-20® 0.1%). The membranes were then incubated with primary antibody (either a monoclonal antibody or Erythema Migrans Lyme disease human serum). The membrane was washed and the antibody-antigen complexes were identified using alkaline phosphatase (AP) enzymes coupled to secondary antibody, either anti- immunoglobulin G (anti-mouse IgG) to detect the monoclonal antibody or anti- human IgA+IgG+IgM to detect the serum antibodies. A chromogenic substrate for alkaline phosphatase was then used to visualize the activity.</p><p num="p0131">EXAMPLE 3: SEROLOGIC CHARACTERIZATION - ELISA (Enzyme-Linked Emmunosorbent Assay)</p><p num="p0132">Immobilization of RCBPs onto ELISA Plates, Determining Optimal RCBP</p><p num="p0133">Binding:</p><p num="p0134">A solution of purified RCBPs in sodium phosphate buffer, pH 9.0 was used to coat commercial microwell plates (MaxiSorp®, Nunc). Recombinant OspC Borrelia proteins are described in Table V. The coating procedure was as follows: 100 μl of a solution containing the appropriate concentration of each RCBP was added to each well and the microwell plate was incubated for either one hour at room temperature or at 4°C overnight. The antigen solution was removed from the 
<!-- EPO <DP n="36"/>-->
wells, the plate washed three times with phosphate buffered saline (PBS) pH 9.0, and 200 μl of blocking solution added (2% BSA fraction V (Sigma) in PBS). Following a thirty minute incubation at 37°C, the plates were washed three times with PBS, wrapped in plastic and stored at 4°C until used. The binding of the individual RCBPs was measured using monoclonal antibodies specific for either OspA or OspC followed (after washing) by an alkaline phosphatase-conjugated goat anti-mouse secondary antibody. The upper limit of protein binding was found to be beyond the working range of the monoclonal antibody used to measure it, and the standard blocking protocol was found to successfully saturate this high protein binding capacity, leaving low background readings in the control wells. The results of these experiments indicated that a protein concentration of 0.5 μg/ml in the coating buffer was optimal for each of the RCBP tested. It was not found to be necessary that the chimeric proteins be immobilized in a specific molar ratio to one another; only that enough of each protein be bound so that epitopes in that chimeric protein do not become limiting in subsequent ELISA assays using patient serum. For practical purposes, it was found that these conditions were met when the monoclonal-capture assay reached an absorbance of about 1.5 units or greater for each mouse monoclonal antibody, with a specific epitope represented in one of the chimeric proteins on the well surface. If necessary, however, the concentrations of individual proteins in the mixture can be adjusted to achieve the desired levels of immobilized protein using routine optimization. Although the amount of each RCBP bound to the surface of the well and the amount of any one epitope exposed to the solution varies somewhat from protein to protein, the amount of bound epitope was not found to be limiting within the useful range of the ELISA.</p><p num="p0135">ELISA Tests:</p><p num="p0136">The standard procedure for the ELISA tests was as follows: human serum samples were diluted 1:100 in specimen diluent (10% fetal bovine serum in PBS pH 9.0) and 100 μl of each sample added to ELISA plate microwells that had been coated with antigen as described above. Following incubation for 1 hour at 37°C, 
<!-- EPO <DP n="37"/>-->
the samples were removed and the plates washed three times in TBS-Tween™ (0.5 M Tris pH 7.2; 1.5 M NaCI; 0.5% Tween ™). Goat anti-human antisera conjugated to alkaline phosphatase specific for either IgM (Fc) or IgG (Fab), (Jackson Immuno Research Laboratories) was diluted 1 : 1000 in PBS, pH 7.4 and 100 μl of the solution added to each well. Following incubation for thirty minutes at 37°C, the plates were washed three times with TBS-Tween ™ and 100 μl of substrate solution (5 mg of p-nitrophenylphosphate tablets dissolved in IX diethanolamine substrate buffer to yield a 2 mg/ml solution - Kirkegaard Perry Laboratory) was added to each well. The plates were incubated for thirty minutes at 37°C and 100 μl of stop solution (5 % EDTA) was added to each well. The absorbance at 410 nm was read on a microplate reader (Dynatech). A sample was considered positive if it produced an average absorbance greater than the mean of the negative controls plus three standard deviations. Cross-reactivity was measured against serum from patients with syphilis, systemic lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis as well as endemic field workers and non-endemic field worker.</p><p num="p0137">Using the above-described ELISA test, serum from various patients was tested. Patients with Erythema Migrans Acute (EMA) had early, localized infections, typified by the presence of well-defined erythemamigvans (EM) in patients from an endemic area. Patients with Early Disseminated (EA), are Acute Disseminated (AcD) infections were typified by EM and one of the following: additional EM lesions, AV block, neurological abnormalities (e.g., seventh nerve pasly), or meningitis. Patients with Acute Convalescent (AcC) were obtained from the same patients as EA and AcD, 2-4 weeks later. Serum was also tested from the CDC from patients with well documented Syphilis (S), serum was also obtained from SUNY at Stony Brook, Division of Rheumatology from patients with well documented systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE) or patients with well documented Rheumatoid Arthritis (RA). Endemic field worker sera (End), were obtained from outdoor workers from Long Island, which is endemic for Lyme disease. Non-endemic sera (Nedn) were obtained from outdoor workers from Arizona, which is not endemic for Lyme disease. In addition, serum was tested from endemic field workers (End) and 
<!-- EPO <DP n="38"/>-->
non-endemic field workers (NEnd). Polypeptides of the present invention were used to test these various sera as summarized in Figure 8. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="39"/>--></p><p num="p0138">Table V</p><p num="p0139"><img id="imgf000039_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="128" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000039_0001.tif" inline="no" he="172"/></p><p num="p0140">C1-C12 are OspC genes/proteins with lipidation signal.</p><p num="p0141">C2C10 and other compound C names refer to chimeric OspC proteins wherein the N-terminal portion of the chimera is derived from a first ospC allele and the C-terminal portion of the chimeric molecule is derived from second ospC allele, as described herein. The polypeptides were not lipidated. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="40"/>-->
EXAMPLE 4: MICE IMMUNIZATION WITH OSPC CHIMERIC PROTEINS AS IMMUNOGEN</p><p num="p0142">Female BALB/c mice, four-five weeks old, were immunized with 5 μg of OspC chimeric proteins in 100 μl of aluminum hydroxide adjuvant by SC (subcutaneous) injection. Five mice were used for each group. For the negative control, five female BALB/c mice were immunized with 100 μl of aluminum hydroxide adjuvant only. Two weeks after immunization, the mice received a boost with the same antigen and two weeks after that an equal boost was administered. One week after each boost, blood was drawn from each mouse (including negative controls) and the serum was tested, using the ELISA method described above, for the presence of the respective anti-OspC chimeric protein antibodies.</p><p num="p0143">Mice were immunized with chimeric proteins as follows in Table VI. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="41"/>--></p><p num="p0144">TABLE VE</p><p num="p0145"><img id="imgf000041_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="144" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000041_0001.tif" inline="no" he="82"/></p><p num="p0146">"Lip" means lipidated N-terminus, Lip CB31 is OspC protein from R. burgdorferi strain B31.</p><p num="p0147">The number immediately after "C" refers to the particular allele of OspC as described herein.</p><p num="p0148">"Unlip" means the unlipidated form of the N-terminus.</p><p num="p0149">Several types of single OspCs from R. burgdorferi sensu stricto, OspCB31, OspC2, OspC5, OspC7, OspCIO, OspC12 and a single OspC from R. afzelii, Ctro, were used as the antigens in an ELISA to test the serum collected from the immunized mice. As shown in Figures 2 and 3, unlipC2C10 and unlipC2C12 elicited an immune response in the form of antibodies, (a humoral response) against a broad range of ospC families, after the first and second bleeds, respectively. The serum from unlipC2C10, unlipC2C12, LipCB31 and LipC12 immunized mice was then used to test against single OspC polypeptides from several strains of the three major Borrelia gene species Borrelia burgdorferi, Borrelia afzelii and Borrelia garinii.</p><p num="p0150">As shown in Figure 4, 13 different strains of R. burgdorferi sensu stricto (B.b.s.s.) were tested for reactivity with the above described sera. Sera from mice immunized with both LipCB31 and LipC12, which were the gold standard of this 
<!-- EPO <DP n="42"/>-->
experiment, detected 12/13 of the B.b.s.s. strains tested. Sera from mice immunized with unlipidated C2C12 detected 8/13 of the strains tested. Use of unlipidated forms of these proteins as vaccine immunogens or diagnostic antigens is desirable because the product yield by the expression vector is much greater and the proteins are much easier to purify. These two reasons alone made the production of these proteins less expensive.</p><p num="p0151">As shown in Figure 5, chimeric proteins unlipC2C10 and unlipC2C12 of the present invention elicited an immune response that detected 5/6, and 6/6 of the strains tested, as compared to the gold standard lipidated proteins LipC12 and LipCBSl, which detected 5/6 and 3/6 of the strains, respectively. When compared to the parental unlipidated OspC2 (rOspC2), the chimeric proteins unlipC2C10 and unlipC2C12 elicited an immune response and detected more strains than the gold standard ((0/6) versus (5/6) and (6/6) respectively). This result was unforeseen and unexpected. In another experiment, as shown in Figures 6 and 7, chimeric proteins of the present invention elicited a significant immune response across all the 18 different strains of R. afzelii (Fig. 6) and all the 21 different strains of R. garinii (Fig. 7). For example, the chimeras unlipC2C10 and unlipC2C12 detected 12 and 18 of the 18 strains of R. afzelii, respectively, as compared to 0/18 detected by the parental unlipidated C2. The same chimeras detected 14 and 20 of the 21 strains of R. garinii, respectively, as compared to 0/21 detected by the parental unlipidated C2. Furthermore, the gold standards LipCB31 and LipC12 detected 2 and 17 of the 18 strains of R. afzelii, respectively, and 2 and 15 of the 21 strains of R. garinii. These results indicate that, unlike the LipOspCB31, LipOspC12 and unlipOspC2, the unlipidated C2C10 and unlipidated C2C12 used as immunogens elicited a significant immune response across all the different strains of R. burgdorferi, B. afzelii and B. garinii tested.</p><p num="p0152">Additional chimeras were constructed and are listed in Table VII. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="43"/>-->
 TABLE Vπ</p><p num="p0153">OspC Polypeptides and Chimeric Polypeptides of the Present Invention</p><p num="p0154">POLYPEPTIDE SEQ ED NO.: (DNA) (POLYPEPTIDES)</p><p num="p0155"><img id="imgf000043_0001" orientation="portrait" wi="143" img-format="tif" img-content="table" file="imgf000043_0001.tif" inline="yes" he="187"/></p><p num="p0156">'Ulip means the polypeptide is unlipidated.</p><p num="p0157"><sup>2</sup>An OspC chimera comprised of 3 OspC polypeptides.</p><p num="p0158"><sup>3</sup>Blip means the polypeptide is lipidated due to the gene having the OspB lipidation signal on the 5' terminus. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="44"/>-->
 While this invention has been particularly shown and described with references to preferred embodiments thereof, it will be understood by those skilled in the art that various changes in form and details may be made therein without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as defined by the appended claims. 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="45"/>--><claim-text/><claim-text>CLAIMS</claim-text><claim-text>What is claimed is:</claim-text><claim-text>1. A composition comprising OspC polypeptides from Lyme Disease causing Borrelia wherein either: a) said composition comprises one or more OspC polypeptides or immunogenic fragments thereof from at least two Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families selected from the group consisting of: A, B, I and K, excepting the combination consisting of two OspC proteins wherein one OspC protein is from family A and the second OspC protein is from family I, or; b) said composition comprises at least one OspC polypeptide or immunogenic fragment thereof from each of Borrelia afzelii OspC families A and B.</claim-text><claim-text>2. The composition of Claim 1 comprising one or more OspC polypeptides or fragments thereof from each of Borrelia burgdorferi families of the group of subpart a).</claim-text><claim-text>3. The composition of Claim 1 , wherein said OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof comprises the OspC protein variable region.</claim-text><claim-text>4. The composition of Claim 3, wherein said OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof is encoded by a nucleic acid comprising nucleotide 26 to about nucleotide 621 of an ospC gene.</claim-text><claim-text>5. The composition of Claim 3, wherein said OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof is encoded by a nucleic acid comprising nucleotide 53 to about nucleotide 570 of an ospC gene. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="46"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>6. The composition of Claim 1 , wherein at least two of said OspC polypeptides or immunogenic fragments thereof are fused together in a single protein, encoded by a single nucleic acid, wherein polypeptides in said fusion protein are not found in the same configuration in a naturally occurring OspC protein.</claim-text><claim-text>7. The composition of Claim 1, wherein the ospC genes encoding the OspC polypeptides within a given OspC family are at least 98% identical at the nucleic acid level.</claim-text><claim-text>8. The composition of Claim 7, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family A comprises strains B31, CA4, HII, EPI, EP2, EP3, L5, PEF, Pka, Txgw and strains containing ospC allele OCl.</claim-text><claim-text>9. The composition of Claim 7, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family B comprises strains 35B808, 61 BV3, BUR, DK7, PB3, Z57 and strains containing ospC genes OC2 and OC3.</claim-text><claim-text>10. The composition of Claim 7, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family I comprises strains 297, HB19 and strains containing ospC gene OC10, wherein strain 297 is characterized by ospC of GenBank accession number L42893.</claim-text><claim-text>11. The composition of Claim 7, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family K comprises strains 272, 297, 28354, KEPP, MUL and strains containing ospC gene OC12 and OC13, wherein strain 297 is characterized by ospC of GenBank accession number U08284. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="47"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>12. The composition of Claim 1, wherein Borrelia afzelii OspC family A comprises strains Pbo, Pwud, PKO, Pgau, DK2, DK3, DK21, DK8, Bfox and JSB.</claim-text><claim-text>13. The composition of Claim 1 , wherein Borrelia afzelii OspC family B comprises strains DK5, ACA1 , DK9, XB 18h, Pie and 134M.</claim-text><claim-text>14. A method of immunizing an animal against Lyme disease, comprising administering a composition comprising at least two OspC polypeptides from Lyme Disease causing Borrelia wherein either: a) said composition comprises one or more OspC polypeptides or fragments thereof from at least two Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families selected from the group consisting of: A, B, I and K, excepting the combination consisting of two OspC proteins wherein one OspC protein is from OspC family A and the second OspC protein is from OspC family I, or; b) said composition comprises at least one OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from each of Borrelia afzelii OspC families A and B.</claim-text><claim-text>15. The method of Claim 14, wherein the composition comprises one or more OspC polypeptides or fragments thereof from each of Borrelia burgdorferi families of the group of subpart a).</claim-text><claim-text>16. The method of Claim 14, wherein said OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof comprises the OspC protein variable region.</claim-text><claim-text>17. The method of Claim 14, wherein said OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof is encoded by a nucleic acid comprising nucleotide 26 to about nucleotide 621 of an ospC gene. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="48"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>18. The method of Claim 14, wherein said OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof is encoded by a nucleic acid comprising nucleotide 53 to about nucleotide 570 of an ospC gene.</claim-text><claim-text>19. The method of Claim 14, wherein at least two of said OspC polypeptides or immunogenic fragments thereof are fused together in a single protein, encoded by a single nucleic acid, wherein polypeptides in said fusion protein are not found in the same configuration in a naturally occurring OspC protein.</claim-text><claim-text>20. The method of Claim 14, wherein the ospC gene encoded the OspC polypeptides within a given OspC family are at least 98% identical at the nucleic acid level.</claim-text><claim-text>21. The method of Claim 14, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family A comprises strains B31, CA4, Hfl, EPI, EP2, EP3, L5, PEF, Pka, Txgw and strains containing ospC allele OCl.</claim-text><claim-text>22. The method of Claim 14, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family B comprises strains 35B808, 61 BV3, BUR, DK7, PB3, Z57 and strains containing ospC genes OC2 and OC3.</claim-text><claim-text>23. The method of Claim 14, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family I comprises strains 297, HB19 and strains containing ospC gene OC10, wherein strain 297 is characterized by ospC of GenBank accession number</claim-text><claim-text>L42893.</claim-text><claim-text>24. The method of Claim 14, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family K comprises strains 272, 297, 28354, KEPP, MUL and strains containing ospC 
<!-- EPO <DP n="49"/>-->
 gene OCl 2 and OC13, wherein strain 297 is characterized by ospC of GenBank accession number U08284.</claim-text><claim-text>25. The method of Claim 14, wherein Borrelia afzelii OspC family A comprises strains Pbo, Pwud, PKO, Pgau, DK2, DK3, DK21, DK8, Bfox and JSB.</claim-text><claim-text>26. The method of Claim 14, wherein Borrelia afzelii OspC family B comprises strains DK5, ACA1, DK9, XB18h, Pie and 134M.</claim-text><claim-text>27. A method of detecting an immune response to Lyme Disease causing Borrelia in a host sample, comprising; a) contacting the host sample with a composition comprising OspC polypeptides from Lyme disease causing strains of Borrelia, such that anti-OspC antibodies, if present in said sample bind to said</claim-text><claim-text>OspC polypeptides; wherein i) said composition comprises one or more OspC polypeptides or fragments thereof from at least two Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families selected from the group consisting of: A, B, I and K, excepting the combination consisting of two OspC proteins wherein one OspC protein is from family A and the second OspC protein is from family I, or; ii) said composition comprises at least one OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof from each of Borrelia afzelii OspC families</claim-text><claim-text>A and B; and b) detecting antibodies that have bound said OspC peptides; thereby detecting an immune response to Lyme disease causing Borrelia.</claim-text><claim-text>28. The method of Claim 27, wherein said OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof comprises the OspC protein variable region. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="50"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>29. The composition of Claim 27, wherein said OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof is encoded by a nucleic acid comprising nucleotide 26 to about nucleotide 621 of an ospC gene.</claim-text><claim-text>30. The composition of Claim 27, wherein said OspC polypeptide or fragment thereof is encoded by a nucleic acid comprising nucleotide 53 to about nucleotide 570 of an ospC gene.</claim-text><claim-text>31. The composition of Claim 27, wherein at least two of said OspC polypeptides or immunogenic fragments thereof are fused together in a single protein, encoded by a single nucleic acid, wherein polypeptides in said fusion protein are not found in the same configuration in a naturally occurring OspC protein.</claim-text><claim-text>32. The method of Claim 27, wherein the ospC genes encoding the OspC polypeptides within a given OspC family are at least 98% identical at the nucleic acid level.</claim-text><claim-text>33. The method of Claim 32, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family A comprises strains B31, CA4, HIE, EPI, EP2, IP3, L5, PEF, Pka, Txgw and strains containing ospC allele OCl.</claim-text><claim-text>34. The method of Claim 32, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family B comprises strains 35B808, 61 BV3, BUR, DK7, PB3, Z57 and strains containing ospC genes OC2 and OC3.</claim-text><claim-text>35. The method of Claim 32, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family I comprises strains 297, HB19 and strains containing ospC gene OC10, wherein strain 297 is characterized by ospC of GenBank accession number L42893. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="51"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>36. The method of Claim 32, wherein Borrelia burgdorferi OspC family K comprises strains 272, 297, 28354, KEPP, MUL and strains containing ospC gene OCl 2 and OCl 3, wherein strain 297 is characterized by ospC of GenBank accession number U08284.</claim-text><claim-text>37. The method of Claim 32, wherein Borrelia afzelii OspC family A comprises strains Pbo, Pwud, PKO, Pgau, DK2, DK3, DK21, DK8, Bfox and JSB.</claim-text><claim-text>38. The method of Claim 32, wherein Borrelia afzelii OspC family B comprises strains DK5, ACA1, DK9, XB18h, Pie and 134M.</claim-text><claim-text>39. A chimeric protein comprising OspC polypeptides from two or more Lyme Disease causing OspC families of Lyme Disease causing Borrelia wherein said chimeric protein comprises: a) a first OspC polypeptide encoded by a nucleic acid comprising a sequence from about nucleotide 26 to about nucleotide 621 of an ospC gene from a first OspC family and b) a second OspC polypeptide encoded by a nucleic acid comprising a sequence from about nucleotide 28 to about nucleotide 570 of an ospC gene from a second OspC family.</claim-text><claim-text>40. The chimeric protein of Claim 39, wherein said OspC families are selected from the group consisting of: Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families A, B, I and K, and Borrelia afzelii OspC families A and B.</claim-text><claim-text>41. A chimeric protein comprising OspC polypeptides from two or more Lyme Disease causing OspC families of Lyme Disease causing Borrelia wherein said chimeric protein comprises: 
<!-- EPO <DP n="52"/>-->
 a) a first OspC polypeptide encoded by a nucleic acid comprising a sequence from about nucleotide 53 to about nucleotide 570 of an ospC gene from a first OspC family and b) a second OspC polypeptide encoded by a nucleic acid comprising a sequence from about nucleotide 28 to about nucleotide 570 of an ospC gene from a second OspC family.</claim-text><claim-text>42. The chimeric protein of Claim 41 , wherein said protein is unlipidated.</claim-text><claim-text>43. A chimeric OspC protein selected from the group consisting of: SEQ Id Nos: 24, 26, 28, 30, 32, 34, 36, 38, 40, 42, 52, 54, 56, 58, 60, 62, 64, 66, 68, 70, 72, 74, 76, 78, 80, 82, 84 and 86.</claim-text><claim-text>44. An isolated nucleic acid encoding a chimeric protein wherein said protein comprises OspC polypeptides from two or more Lyme Disease causing OspC families of Lyme Disease causing Borrelia wherein said chimeric protein comprises: a) a first OspC polypeptide encoded by a nucleic acid comprising a sequence from about nucleotide 26 to about nucleotide 621 of an ospC gene from a first OspC family and b) a second OspC polypeptide encoded by a nucleic acid comprising a sequence from about nucleotide 28 to about nucleotide 570 of an ospC gene from a second OspC family.</claim-text><claim-text>45. The nucleic acid of Claim 44, wherein said OspC families are selected from the group consisting of: Borrelia burgdorferi OspC families A, B, I and K, and Borrelia afzelii OspC families A and B.</claim-text><claim-text>46. The nucleid acid of Claim 44, wherein said protein is unlipidated. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="53"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>7. A isolated nucleic acid comprising OspC polypeptides from two or more Lyme Disease causing OspC families of Lyme Disease causing Borrelia wherein said isolated nucleic acid comprises: a) a first OspC polypeptide encoded by a nucleic acid comprising a sequence from about nucleotide 53 to about nucleotide 570 of an ospC gene from a first OspC family and b) a second OspC polypeptide encoded by a nucleic acid comprising a sequence from about nucleotide 28 to about nucleotide 570 of an ospC gene from a second OspC family.</claim-text><claim-text>48. An isolated nucleic acid selected from the group consisting of : SEQ ID</claim-text><claim-text>Nos: 23, 25, 27, 29, 31, 33, 35, 37, 39, 41, 51, 53, 55, 56, 59, 61, 63, 65, 67, 69, 71, 73, 75, 77, 79, 81, 83 and 85. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>