<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1535984-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1535984" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="34465667" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050601"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1535984-A2" status="new" fvid="24366474"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1535984</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20050601</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04026457-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04026457</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20041108</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-72115603-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>72115603</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031125</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/10        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/12        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/14        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/18        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/182       20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/183       20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/24        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/26        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   1/30        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   9/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L   9/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L  10/00        20060101A I20060722RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L  10/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L  10/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10L  10/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10L   1/14</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10L   1/30</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10L  10/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10L  10/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10L  10/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:18A8</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:18D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:18D7</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:18T</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:24A1</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:24C1</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:26A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:30A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10L1:30B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Katalytisch wirkendes Mischmetalladditiv und Methode zu seiner Verwendung in Verbrennungsanlagen für kohlenwasserstoffhaltige Brennstoffe</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Mixed metal catalyst additive and method for use in hydrocarbonaceous fuel combustion system</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Additif catalytique à base de métaux mixtes et procédé de son utilisation dans des systèmes de combustion pour combustibles hydrocarbonés</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="GB-1189356-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>1189356</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-2248068-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2248068</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-490064-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>490064</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3837820-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3837820</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4047875-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4047875</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1982001375-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1982001375</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2000058422-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000058422</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 200234 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class H09, AN 2002-293064 XP002349084 &amp; CN 1 334 323 A (QU Y) 6 February 2002 (2002-02-06)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>AFTON CHEMICAL CORP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AFTON CHEMICAL CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Afton Chemical Corporation</last-name><address><street>500 Spring Street</street><city>Richmond, VA 23219</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ARADI ALLEN A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>FACTOR STEPHEN A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ROOS JOSEPH W</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ARADI, ALLEN A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>FACTOR, STEPHEN A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ROOS, JOSEPH W.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ARADI, ALLEN A.</last-name><address><street>2935 Vanna Lane</street><city>Richmond Virginia 23233</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>FACTOR, STEPHEN A.</last-name><address><street>11404 Ivy Home Place</street><city>Richmond Virginia 23233</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ROOS, JOSEPH W.</last-name><address><street>10261 Berkeley Manor Drive</street><city>Mechanicsville Virginia 23116</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors> <agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Schwabe - Sandmair - Marx</last-name><address><street>Stuntzstrasse 16</street><city>81677 München</city><country>DE</country></address> </addressbook> </agent> </agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>HU</country><country>IE</country><country>IS</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PL</country><country>PT</country><country>RO</country><country>SE</country><country>SI</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive, fuel composition, and method all
lower both carbon particulate emissions and improve slag properties in combustion
systems including, for instance, utility furnaces and boiler systems.
The mixed metal catalyst includes a transition metal-containing compound,
an alkali metal compound, and a magnesium-containing compound.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention relates to a hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive, fuel composition
and method that both improves the combustion of the fuel and improves
the slag resulting from the combustion of the fuel. Specifically, the
additive, fuel composition and method include the use of the combination of
a manganese-containing compound, at least one alkali metal compound, and
a magnesium-containing compound.</p><heading><u style="single">Background</u></heading><p num="0002">Utility furnaces and industrial boiler systems operating with atmospheric
burners, like all hydrocarbonaceous fuel combustion systems, are
concerned with the amount and quality of the emissions that result from the
combustion of fuel in those systems. Particulate emissions are a byproduct
of incomplete combustion. This carbon-containing particulate is an environmental
issue, and to solve it, fuel compositions are constantly being
modified and combustion methods designed to minimize the amount of particulate
emitted into the environment. Other emission constituents can form
deposits on various parts of the combustion system, for instance, the water
wall pipes, economizer tubes, and/or super heater tubes of utility furnaces
and industrial burner systems. The deposits, typically referred to as slag,
may build up and, over time, significantly reduce the efficiency of the combustion
system. </p><p num="0003">Metal-containing additives have been used in fuel formulations to
catalyze carbon burn out, and thereby reduce particulate emissions, by either
inhibiting particulate agglomeration (alkali metals), enhancing carbon
oxidation at peak combustion temperatures by increasing hydroxyl radical
concentration (alkaline earth metals), or by increasing the rate of catalytic
oxidation by lowering the particulate light-off temperature (transition metals).
It is recognized, however, that use of these specific metal-containing
additives may adversely affect the type and/or quantity of slag that may
build up in a combustion system.</p><p num="0004">In one example, the prior art discloses a method for reducing emissions
which include the use of a mixture of calcium and either alkali metals,
alkaline earth metals other than calcium or mixtures thereof. See U.S. Patent
No. 5,919,276.</p><p num="0005">It is also known that adding magnesium compounds to fuels extends
the time between combustion turbine maintenance when burning ash-containing
fuel. See, e.g., U.S. Patent No. 6,632,257. However, magnesium
does not impact carbon burnout. Magnesium compounds, therefore, positively
affect the type and/or quantity of slag, but do not impact carbon
burnout.</p><heading><u style="single">Detailed Description</u></heading><p num="0006">A hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive, fuel composition, and method lowers
both carbon particulate emissions and improves slag properties in combustion
systems including, for instance, utility furnaces and boiler systems.
The fuel additive package, fuel composition and method of the present invention 
combine the benefit of a mixed metal catalyst that improves carbon
light-off and thereby reduces carbon particulate emissions and the benefit of
magnesium for improving slag formation on, for instance, water wall pipes,
economizer tubes, and super heater tubes of utility furnaces. In one alternative,
the additive package contains the mixed metals transition metal-containing
compound/alkali metal compound/magnesium-containing compound,
in one example having a ratio of about 1/1/3 transition metal alkali
metal/Mg. The additive package herein is made compatible with hydrocarbonaceous
fuels commonly used in connection with various combustion systems.
It is this unique combination of metal catalysts that is able to deliver
the dual benefits of reduced carbon particulate emissions and improved slag
properties resulting from the combustion of the fuel.</p><p num="0007">In one example, a hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive comprises a transition
metal-containing compound, at least one alkali metal compound, and a
magnesium-containing compound. In another example, a fuel composition
comprises a major amount of hydrocarbonaceous fuel and minor amount of
an additive, the additive comprising a transition metal-containing compound,
an alkali metal compound, and a magnesium-containing compound.
In a still further example, a method of improving the combustion of, and the
slag resulting from the combustion of, a hydrocarbonaceous fuel comprises
the steps of providing a hydrocarbonaceous fuel comprising a transition
metal-containing compound, an alkali metal compound, and a magnesium-containing
compound; combusting the fuel in a combustion system, wherein
the combustion of the fuel causes the formation of slag and carbon burnout;
wherein the amount of transition metal, alkali metal and magnesium contained 
in the fuel is in an amount effective to improve the combustion of the
fuel, or reduce particulate emissions, and improve the slag resulting from
combustion of the fuel.</p><p num="0008">The discussion herein is addressed to a hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive,
to a fuel composition, and to a method for improving the combustion of
and the slag resulting from the combustion of a hydrocarbonaceous fuel. In
each instance, a constant is the presence of a mixed metal catalyst combination
comprising at least one transition metal-containing compound/alkali
metal/magnesium-containing compound.</p><p num="0009">In one example, the transition metal-containing compound is an organometallic
compound. Exemplary transition metal-containing organometallic
compounds herein include compounds with stabilizing ligands
containing functional groups such as alcohols, aldehydes, ketones, esters,
anhydrides, sulfonates, phosphonates, chelates, phenates, crown ethers,
naphthenates, carboxylic acids, amides, acetyl acetonates, and mixtures
thereof. The transition metals of this invention include manganese, iron,
cobalt, copper, platinum, palladium, rhodium, ruthenium, osmium, iridium,
molybdenum, scandium, yttrium, lanthanum, cerium, and mixtures thereof.
Manganese-containing organometallic compounds include manganese tricarbonyl
compounds. Such compounds are taught, for example, in US Patent
Nos. 4,568,357; 4,674,447; 5,113,803; 5,599,357; 5,944,858 and European
Patent No. 466 512 B1.</p><p num="0010">Suitable manganese tricarbonyl compounds which can be used include
cyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, methylcyclopentadienyl manganese
tricarbonyl, dimethylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, 
trimethylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, tetramethylcyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyl, pentamethylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl,
ethylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, diethylcyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyl, propylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl,
isopropylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, tert-butylcyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyl, octylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, dodecylcyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyl, ethylmethylcyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyl, indenyl manganese tricarbonyl, and the like, including
mixtures of two or more such compounds. One example is the cyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyls which are liquid at room temperature such
as methylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, ethylcyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyl, liquid mixtures of cyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl
and methylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, mixtures of
methylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl and ethylcyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyl, etc.</p><p num="0011">Preparation of such compounds is described in the literature, for example,
U.S. Pat. No. 2,818,417, the disclosure of which is incorporated
herein in its entirety.</p><p num="0012">Alkali metal compounds useful herein can include the following:
lithium, sodium, potassium, rubidium and mixtures thereof. These metals
may be combined with the fuel as compounds or salts, for instance, of the
following acidic substances or mixtures thereof: (1) sulfonic acids, (2) carboxylic
acids, (3) alkylphenols, (4) sulfurized alkylphenols, and (5) organic
phosphorus acids characterized by at least one direct carbon-to-phosphorus
linkage. The metal salts may be prepared as oil-soluble overbased salts. 
The term "overbase" is used to designate metal salts wherein the metal is
present in stoichiometrically larger amounts than the organic acid radical.</p><p num="0013">In another example, the alkali metal compounds or salts are oil-insoluble
and may be, for example, dispersions, emulsions, mists, sprays,
powdered, or atomized.</p><p num="0014">In one example, the alkali metal is potassium and the compound is
potassium sulfonate, a fuel soluble compound.</p><p num="0015">Examples of magnesium-containing compounds include the following:
neutral or overbased magnesium compounds derived from: (1) sulfonic acids,
(2) carboxylic acids, (3) alkylphenols, (4) sulfurized alkylphenols, and (5) organic
phosphorus acids characterized by at least one direct carbon-to-phosphorus
linkage.</p><p num="0016">In one example, the magnesium-containing compound is magnesium
sulfonate, a fuel soluble compound.</p><p num="0017">Hydrocarbonaceous fuels that benefit from the additive described
herein include those fuels that produce carbon particulate emissions when
combusted and that also form slag in combustion systems once they have
been combusted. These fuels include, for instance, diesel fuel, No. 1, No. 2,
No. 4, No. 5 and No. 6 fuel oils, combinations thereof, and other fuels commonly
used in utility and industrial burner systems. Other examples of fuels
suitable for use in the operation of combustion units described herein
include hydrocarbonaceous fuels such as but not limited to diesel fuel, jet
fuel, alcohols, ethers, kerosene, low sulfur fuels, synthetic fuels, such as
Fischer-Tropsch fuels, liquid petroleum gas, fuels derived from coal, coal,
genetically engineered biofuels and crops and extracts therefrom, natural 
gas, propane, butane, unleaded motor and aviation gasolines, and so-called
reformulated gasolines which typically contain both hydrocarbons of the
gasoline boiling range and fuel-soluble oxygenated blending agents, such as
alcohols, ethers and other suitable oxygen-containing organic compounds.
Other fuels that may be useful include gasoline, bunker fuel, coal (dust or
slurry), crude oil, refinery "bottoms" and by-products, crude oil extracts,
hazardous wastes, yard trimmings and waste, wood chips and saw dust, agricultural
waste, fodder, silage, plastics and other organic waste and/or by-products,
and mixtures thereof, and emulsions, suspensions, and dispersions
thereof in water, alcohol, or other carrier fluids. By "diesel fuel" herein
is meant one or more fuels selected from the group consisting of diesel fuel,
biodiesel, biodiesel-derived fuel, synthetic diesel and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0018">Other components may be included within the additives and/or fuel
compositions described herein provided they do not adversely affect the
amount or formation of slag otherwise obtained herein. Thus, use may be
made of one or more of such components as corrosion inhibitors, antioxidants,
anti-rust agents, detergents and dispersants, fuel lubricity additives,
demulsifiers, dyes, inert diluents, cold flow improvers, conductivity agents,
metal deactivators, stabilizers, antifoam additives, de-icers, biocides, odorants,
drag reducers, combustion improvers, oxygenates and like materials.</p><p num="0019">Combustion systems that may benefit from the additives or fuel compositions
herein include any system that, as a result of the combustion of a
hydrocarbonaceous fuel, has emissions of carbon particulate matter and
that includes components on which slag may build up or form. Water wall
pipes, economizer tubes, and super heater tubes of utility and industrial 
furnaces are common locations where slag may build up. By "combustion
system" herein is meant any and all internal and external combustion devices,
machines, boilers, incinerators, evaporative burners, plasma burner
systems, plasma arc, stationary burners and the like which can combust, or
in which can be combusted, a hydrocarbonaceous fuel. The combustion
units further include any and all burners or combustion devices, including
for example and without limitation herein, stationary burners, waste incinerators,
diesel fuel burners, gasoline fuel burners, power plant generators,
power plant furnaces, and the like. The hydrocarbonaceous fuel combustion
systems include all combustion units, systems, devices, and/or engines that
burn or oxidatively decompose hydrocarbonaceous fuels.</p><p num="0020">Examples of treat rates of the mixed metal compounds described
herein include any treat rates that both improve the particulate emissions
and improve the quality of the slag resulting from the combustion of the fuel.
For purposes herein, the term "improve" or "improving" means that the additive,
fuel composition or method will have lower particulate emissions and
more favorable slag qualities (less build up, more easily cleaned, less dense,
less rigid, less adhesive, more friable, etc.) than additives, fuel compositions,
and methods that do not include the mixed metal catalyst described herein.
In one example, the transition metal-containing compound is included in an
additive package or a fuel composition in an amount sufficient to supply
about 0.1 to 40 ppm manganese metal to the fuel composition. In another
example, the fuel soluble alkali metal is included in an additive or to a fuel
composition in an amount sufficient to supply from 0.1 to 40 ppm alkali
metal to the fuel composition. And in a further example, the amount of slag 
modifying magnesium-containing compound is included in an additive or a
fuel composition in an amount sufficient to supply from about 0.3 to 600
ppm magnesium metal to the fuel composition. In another example, the
magnesium amount is 20 to 60 ppm in the fuel composition. The mass ratio
or proportion of the three metal components is, in one example, approximately
1/1/3, manganese-containing compound/ alkali metal/magnesium-containing
compound. In other examples, the ratio can range from 1/1/1 to
1/2/1 to 1/1/15.5.</p><heading><u style="single">Example</u></heading><p num="0021">The result below illustrates the effectiveness of mixed metal catalysts
in lowering the light-off temperature of carbon, thereby reducing carbon particulate
emissions.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry nameend="3" namest="1">Single-Metal versus Mixed-Metal Catalysts Performance in Carbon-Light-Off.</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Metal Additive Mixture</entry><entry align="left">Carbon Light-Off (°C by TGA)</entry><entry align="left">° C Lowered by Additive</entry></row><row><entry align="left">None</entry><entry align="left">627</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Fe</entry><entry align="left">588</entry><entry align="left">39</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mn</entry><entry align="left">560</entry><entry align="left">67</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cu</entry><entry align="left">426</entry><entry align="left">201</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cu/Mn/K</entry><entry align="left">421</entry><entry align="left">206</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mn/K</entry><entry align="left">412</entry><entry align="left">215</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0022">The carbon light-off tests were conducted by TGA on graphite samples
treated by the respective metal additive or additive combination. The treatment
was by incipient impregnation of the additive from water soluble metal
salts, into the graphite. </p><p num="0023">Graphite was chosen as the surrogate carbon particulate because of
its difficulty to light-off. Therefore it serves as a good carbon substrate on
which to compare different light-off catalysts. In addition, the light-off temperatures
in Table 1 should be considered as very conservative, and the
temperatures that would be seen in the real world with actual carbon-containing
combustion particulate would be even lower.</p><p num="0024">The results in Table 1 show the advantage with respect to carbon particulate
emissions of using mixed metal catalysts over their single metal
components. This is because in the mixed metals, each metal acts on the
carbon in different temperature regimes and the enhanced benefit is due to
the metal that acts in the first temperature regime conditioning the particulate
for a more efficient reaction with the second metal. For example, in the
case of the Mn/K mixed metal catalyst system, the K interacts with the soot
in the high temperature regime as it is forming and keeps it dispersed in the
oxidizing fuel/air charge. As the temperature begins to fall from peak, the
Mn becomes the dominant oxidation catalyst interacting with this high surface
area deposit, and lowering the light-off temperature thus catalyzing oxidation
at lower temperatures. If the K did not interact with the soot before it
aggregated to larger particle sizes, then the surface area exposed to Mn oxidation
would be greatly lowered thus decreasing the efficiency of the Mn
catalyst.</p><p num="0025">The aforementioned mixed metal catalyst systems do not provide improved
slag modification. </p><p num="0026">Some metals such as magnesium do not participate in particulate
burn out chemistries, but are known instead to be efficacious combustion
slag modifiers resulting in a more friable slag that is more easily removed
from a combustion system.</p><p num="0027">When a fuel is formulated such that the two features above are incorporated-reduction
in carbon light-off temperature and slag modification,
then one can have a fuel composition that simultaneously lowers carbon-containing
particulate emissions, and also modifies and improves the slag
resulting from combustion of this fuel in utility and industrial furnaces.</p><p num="0028">Thus, according to an embodiment of the present invention, a mixed,
three-metal combustion catalyst system added to a hydrocarbonaceous fuel
can result in simultaneous (1) combustion improvement such as lower carbon
particulate emissions, and (2) generation of slag which is more friable,
less adhesive, less dense and reduced in total volume or mass, relative to
slag from fuel combustion lacking the present mixed three-metal catalyst
system.</p><p num="0029">A combustion unit plant trial was conducted in which No. 6 fuel oil
containing 1% sulfur and 50 ppm vanadium was combusted in an industrial
boiler system. The combustion and power generation unit was operated at a
330 MW production rate with a maximum capacity of 385 MW. The experiment
lasted for one month during which time slag quality and particulate
emissions were observed. A mixed catalyst system containing manganese
and magnesium in an approximately one to three weight ratio was injected
into the fuel combustion unit of the boiler system. A reduction of 39% in
carbon particulate emissions was achieved during the trial. In addition, visual 
observations of the slag accumulating on the walls of boiler steam tubes
showed a surprisingly different and improved character, texture and volume
when compared to visual observations of boiler steam tubes with slag from
fuel combusted in the absence of the present mixed metal catalyst.</p><p num="0030">Visual observation of the water wall tubes in the utility furnace burning
number 6 fuel oil without the magnesium additive showed heavy glass-like
slag with teardrop ends as a result of gravity induced flow. The spaces
between the tubes through which the combustion gases are supposed to flow
were highly restricted by the slag deposit. When the utility furnace unit was
operated with fuel containing a mixed metal additive package comprising a
manganese-containing compound and a magnesium-containing compound,
the slag appeared dry, more friable, and less glass like. The combustion gas
flow spaces between the water wall tubes were much less restricted. The
magnesium had clearly modified the slag by increasing its melting temperature
above that in the furnace surface environment. As a result, most of the
particulates in the combustion gas solidify before they reach the surfaces.
Some of the particulate reach the surface still molten and serve as a substrate
to hold the non-molten magnesium-modified bulk combustion particulate.
Thus the slag ends up being composed of a major portion of solid
particulate embedded in a minor portion of molten material. This leaves
spaces between the bound solid particulate which gives the resultant slag a
friable property.</p><p num="0031">More specifically, the slag generated appeared softer, like dripping
candle wax, looser and reduced in volume or mass. This change in appearance
and improvement in properties is a result of the inclusion of magnesium 
to a manganese-containing catalyst system previously designed for
combustion improvement and particulate reduction. The invention relates to
the further inclusion of an alkali metal combustion improver to this transition
metal-containing and magnesium-containing catalyst system.</p><p num="0032">It is to be understood that the reactants and components referred to
by chemical name anywhere in the specification or claims hereof, whether
referred to in the singular or plural, are identified as they exist prior to coming
into contact with another substance referred to by chemical name or
chemical type (e.g., base fuel, solvent, etc.). It matters not what chemical
changes, transformations and/or reactions, if any, take place in the resulting
mixture or solution or reaction medium as such changes, transformations
and/or reactions are the natural result of bringing the specified reactants
and/or components together under the conditions called for pursuant
to this disclosure. Thus the reactants and components are identified as ingredients
to be brought together either in performing a desired chemical reaction
(such as formation of the organometallic compound) or in forming a
desired composition (such as an additive concentrate or additized fuel
blend). It will also be recognized that the additive components can be added
or blended into or with the base fuels individually per se and/or as components
used in forming preformed additive combinations and/or subcombinations.
Accordingly, even though the claims hereinafter may refer to
substances, components and/ or ingredients in the present tense ("comprises",
"is", etc.), the reference is to the substance, components or ingredient
as it existed at the time just before it was first blended or mixed with one
or more other substances, components and/or ingredients in accordance 
with the present disclosure. The fact that the substance, components or ingredient
may have lost its original identity through a chemical reaction or
transformation during the course of such blending or mixing operations or
immediately thereafter is thus wholly immaterial for an accurate understanding
and appreciation of this disclosure and the claims thereof.</p><p num="0033">At numerous places throughout this specification, reference has been
made to a number of U.S. Patents, published foreign patent applications and
published technical papers. All such cited documents are expressly incorporated
in full into this disclosure as if fully set forth herein.</p><p num="0034">This invention is susceptible to considerable variation in its practice.
Therefore the foregoing description is not intended to limit, and should not
be construed as limiting, the invention to the particular exemplifications
presented hereinabove. Rather, what is intended to be covered is as set forth
in the ensuing claims and the equivalents thereof permitted as a matter of
law.</p><p num="0035">Patentee does not intend to dedicate any disclosed embodiments to the
public, and to the extent any disclosed modifications or alterations may not
literally fall within the scope of the claims, they are considered to be part of
the invention under the doctrine of equivalents.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive for a fuel composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a transition metal-containing compound;</claim-text><claim-text>an alkali metal compound; and</claim-text><claim-text>a magnesium-containing compound.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive as described in claim 1, wherein
the transition metal-containing compound, alkali metal compound, and
magnesium-containing compound are included in the additive to provide an
atomic ratio of about one part transition metal, one part alkali metal, and
three parts magnesium of the respective metals.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive as described in claim 1,
wherein the transition metal-containing compound is an organometallic
compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive as described in claim 3,
wherein the organometallic compound is a compound with stabilizing
ligands containing a functional group selected from the group consisting of
alcohols, aldehydes, ketones, esters, anhydrides, sulfonates, phosphonates,
chelates, phenates, crown ethers, naphthenates, carboxylic acids, amides,
acetyl acetonates and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive described in claim 3, wherein
the organometallic compound comprises manganese.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive described in claim 5, wherein
the manganese-containing compound is selected from the following group:
cyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, methylcyclopentadienyl manganese
tricarbonyl, dimethylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, trimethylcyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyl, tetramethylcyclopentadienyl manganese
tricarbonyl, pentamethylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl,
ethylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, diethylcyclopentadienyl manganese
tricarbonyl, propylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, isopropylcyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyl, tert-butylcyclopentadienyl manganese
tricarbonyl, octylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl, dodecylcyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyl, ethylmethylcyclopentadienyl manganese
tricarbonyl, indenyl manganese tricarbonyl, and the like, including
mixtures of two or more such compounds, and preferably is methylcyclopentadienyl
manganese tricarbonyl.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive as described in claim 1,
wherein the alkali metal compound contains at least one alkali metal selected
from the group consisting of lithium, sodium, potassium and rubidium.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive as described in claim 1,
wherein the magnesium-containing compound is selected from the group of
compounds derived from sulfonic acids, carboxylic acids, alkylphenols, sulfurized
alkylphenols, and organic phosphorus acids, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive as described in claim 1 or 5,
wherein the amount of transition metal-containing compound is an amount
sufficient to supply about 0.1 to 40 ppm transition material to the fuel composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive as described in claim 1,
wherein the amount of alkali metal compound is an amount sufficient to
supply about 0.1 to 40 ppm alkali metal to the fuel composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>A hydrocarbonaceous fuel additive as described in claim 1,
wherein the amount of magnesium-containing compound is an amount sufficient
to supply about 0.3 to 500 ppm magnesium metal to the fuel composition,
preferably wherein the amount of magnesium-containing compound
is sufficient to supply about 20 to about 60 ppm of magnesium metal to the
fuel composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A fuel composition which comprises a major amount of hydrocarbonaceous
fuel and minor amount of an additive according to one of claims
1 to 11.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A fuel composition as described in claim 12, wherein the
amount of transition metal-containing compound is an amount sufficient to
supply about 0.1 to 20 ppm transition metal to the fuel composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A fuel composition as described in claim 12, wherein the
amount of alkali metal is an amount sufficient to supply about 0.1 to 20
ppm alkali metal to the fuel composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A fuel composition additive as described in claim 12, wherein
the amount of magnesium-containing is an amount sufficient to supply
about 0.3 to 60 ppm magnesium metal to the fuel composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The fuel composition of one of claims 12 to 15, wherein the hydrocarbonaceous
fuel is selected from the group consisting of No. 5 and No.
6 fuel oils, diesel fuel, jet fuel, alcohols, ethers, kerosene, low sulfur fuels,
synthetic fuels, liquid petroleum gas, fuels derived from coal, coal, coal dust,
coal slurry, biofuels, natural gas, propane, butane, unleaded motor and
aviation gasolines, reformulated gasolines, gasolines, bunker fuel, crude oil,
refinery bottoms, crude oil extracts, hazardous wastes, yard trimmings and
waste, wood chips and saw dust, fodder, silage, plastics, organic waste, and
emulsions, suspensions, and dispersions thereof in water, alcohol, or other
carrier fluids, and mixtures of one or more of the foregoing.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>A method of improving the combustion of and the slag resulting
from the combustion of a hydrocarbonaceous fuel composition, the method
comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing a hydrocarbonaceous fuel composition comprising a transition
metal-containing compound, at least one alkali metal compound, and a
magnesium-containing compound;</claim-text><claim-text>combusting the fuel composition in a combustion system, wherein the
combustion of the fuel composition causes the formation of slag;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the amount of transition metal, alkali metal and magnesium
contained in the fuel composition is in an amount effective to improve the
combustion of the fuel composition and improve the slag resulting from
combustion of the fuel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The method of claim 17, wherein a fuel composition of one of
claims 12 to 16 is used.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>A method as described in claim 17 or 18, wherein the slag is improved
by being more easily removed.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>A method as described in claim 17 or 18, wherein the slag is improved
by being less built up.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>A method as described in claim 17 or 18, wherein the slag is improved
by being more friable.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>