<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1211286-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1211286" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="24914479" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020605"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1211286-A1" status="new" fvid="23474586"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1211286</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020605</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01126019-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01126019</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20011031</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-72542000-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>72542000</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001129</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/08        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  23/16        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  25/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  25/04        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  77/00        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  77/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/00        20060101C N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  83/04        20060101A N20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/04+B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/04+B4N</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/04+B4S</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/10+B2</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/10+B4N</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L  23/10+B4S</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L205:08</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L23:08C3A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L23:16</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L25:04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L77:00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M08L83:04</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Polyolefinlegierungen mit besseren Oberflächeneigenschaften</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Improved surface properties in thermopastic olefin alloys</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Amélioration des propriétés de surface d'alliages de polyoléfines</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0262233-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0262233</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0456259-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0456259</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5162422-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5162422</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999025767-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999025767</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; AN 1989-375102 XP002191916 &amp; JP 01 282267 A (ASAHI GLASS), 14 November 1989 (1989-11-14)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VISTEON GLOBAL TECH INC</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VISTEON GLOBAL TECHNOLOGIES, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Visteon Global Technologies, Inc.</last-name><address><street>Suite 728, Parklane Towers East, One Parklane Boulevard</street><city>Dearborn, Michigan 48126</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>RYNTZ ROSE A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>WICHTERMAN BETH M</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>RYNTZ, ROSE A.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WICHTERMAN, BETH M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>RYNTZ, ROSE A.</last-name><address><street>36056 Farmbrook</street><city>Clinton Township, MI 48035</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WICHTERMAN, BETH M.</last-name><address><street>7105 S. Green Hills Drive</street><city>Saline, MI 48176</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Patentanwälte Dr. Solf &amp;amp; Zapf</last-name><address><street>Candidplatz 15</street><city>81543 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A thermoplastic olefin resin composition having improved resistance to
surface impacts, such as scratching, marring and gouging, is provided. The
thermoplastic olefin resin comprises a blend of polyolefin alloy and polyamide
components. The components have relative melt flow rates such that the polyamide
component is selectively segregated toward the front of a melt flow. A
compatibilizing agent is added to overcome the natural incompatibility of the
polyolefin alloy and polyamide components of the resin. The thermoplastic olefin
resin may further include a filler material when increased stiffness or modulus is
desired.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates generally to a thermoplastic resin composition
that demonstrates improved surface durability properties. More specifically, the
invention relates to a polyolefin alloy blended with a polyamide and manipulated in
such a manner as to selectively segregate the polyamide toward the front of a melt
flow of the resin. Also, the invention relates to the addition of a compatibilizing agent
in relatively small amounts to increase the interphase strength between the
polyolefin and polyamide components, thereby overcoming the natural
incompatibility of these two materials. The invention affords improved resistance to
scratching, marring and gouging while maintaining the other well-recognized benefits
of polyolefin alloys, such as superior moldability.</p><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0002">Thermoplastic resins are commonly used in automotive interior components,
such as instrument panels, and exterior components, such as bumpers and/or trim.
Polypropylene resins are often used for these articles due at least in part to their
superior moldability. Polypropylene resins offer a material that can be readily formed
into components of various shapes and sizes by techniques well known in the art,
such as injection and blow molding. Unfortunately, polypropylene demonstrates
poor resistance to various types of surface impacts. Consequently, components 
manufactured from polypropylene resins often exhibit susceptibility to scratching,
marring, and gouging.</p><p num="0003">Various techniques have been proposed for increasing the resistance of
polyolefin resins, such as polypropylene, to surface impacts. For example, some
current components utilize a migratory scratch protection package to bolster
resistance to these defects. For example, work reported by Jack Chu (SPE ANTEC
Proceedings, 1999) indicated that the use of high molecular weight "euracamides",
when added to a thermoplastic olefin material, could increase the scratch propensity
of the material. Work described by Dow Corning (SPE TPO in Automotive
Proceedings, 2000) indicates that the use of high molecular weight siloxane
masterbatches, when used in conjunction with thermoplastic olefins, can also
increase the scratch resistance of the material. Unfortunately, while these add-ins
may confer some protection against damage, they greatly limit other aspects of
components manufactured from the modified polyolefin resin. For example, the
scratch protection add-in may limit the paintability of the component, thereby
reducing the ability to make the component visually appealing. Also, the add-in may
evaporate or whiten over time, thereby causing a displeasing change in the visual
appearance of the component over time. Other approaches include the addition of
filer materials, such as silica, to a polyolefin material. JP 1318051 (Toray Siliconekk)
discloses polyolefins that are modified in this manner. The silica filler may have
been treated with silicone type compounds. The disclosed polyolefins, however, are
not alloys.</p><p num="0004">The use of polyamides as add-ins to improve desirable qualities of
polypropylene has been attempted. However, the natural incompatibility of these
two materials causes a delamination effect and no desired material can be obtained 
by simple melt mixing. Therefore, if a polyamide is to be used to improve the
qualities of polypropylene, the incompatibility of materials must be addressed. One
approach to addressing this incompatibility is presented in Japanese Patent
Publication No. 30945. The approach of this reference involves grafting a
polypropylene with an unsaturated carboxylic acid or a derivative thereof. This
approach makes a polypropylene and a polyamide compatible with each other.
However, the approach of this reference is not satisfactory when an ordinary
polyamide, such as nylon-6, nylon-6,6, and nylon-12, or the like, is used. To
significantly improve the impact resistance of polypropylene by addition of a
polyamide, the physical location of the polyamide in the alloy is critical.</p><p num="0005">U.S. Patent No. 5,206,284 to Fukui, <u style="single">et al.</u> teaches a polypropylene
thermoplastic resin comprising, in part, a modified polypropylene obtained by grafting
an unsaturated carboxylic acid or a derivative thereof, and a modified polyamide
obtained by partially or wholly modifying a polyamide with a clay mineral. In this
reference, the authors overcame the incompatibility of polypropylene and polyamide
by modifying both the polypropylene and the polyamide. While this approach does
overcome the incompatibility of these two materials and does not increase the heat
stability of molded components, resins according to this approach still are prone to
surface damage and have poor paintability.</p><p num="0006">Consequently, there is a need for a thermoplastic resin composition that
retains the desirable attributes of a polyolefin alloy, <i>e</i>.<i>g</i>., superior moldability, while
improving surface durability without imparting adverse properties, such as poor
paintability and whitening, or decreased impact resistance, onto the polyolefin alloy. </p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0007">The current invention provides the desired resin by teaching a resin
comprising a polyolefin alloy, a polyamide, and a compatibilizing agent. The
materials utilized in the resin have a difference between their respective melt flow
rates such that the polyamide is selectively segregated to the surface of the
component during the molding process. In this configuration, the polyamide,
preferably nylon, provides excellent resistance to surface impacts. Compatibility
between the polyolefin alloy and polyamide phases is obtained by the addition in
small amounts of a compatibilizing agent. Also, the stiffness or modulus of molded
parts can be increased by adding inorganic nanocomposite materials, such as clay,
talc, silica, and wollastonite, to the resin.</p><heading><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0008">The present invention provides a thermoplastic resin that comprises a blend
of a polyolefin alloy, a polyamide, and a compatibilizing agent. The polyolefin alloy,
also commonly referred to as a thermoplastic olefin alloy, and polyamide
components of the thermoplastic resin are selected so that the melt flow of each
component is such that the polyamide selectively segregates itself towards the front
of a melt flow of molten resin. This allows the thermoplastic resin of the present
invention to achieve the desired results. That is, this property allows the polyamide
to confer its resistance to surface impacts onto parts molded from the thermoplastic
resin. The compatibilizing agent increases the strength between the polyolefin alloy
and polyamide phases, thereby overcoming the natural incompatibility between
these two phases. The thermoplastic resin of the present invention can also include
a filler material to increase the stiffness or modulus of parts molded from the resin. </p><p num="0009">Polyolefin alloys are frequently used in the art as thermoplastic resins. These
alloys are blends of a polyolefin with an alloy component, such as rubber.
Essentially any polyolefin alloy can be used in the current invention, as long as its
melt flow rate is sufficient as compared to that of the polyamide component. That is,
the polyolefin alloy must have a lower melt flow rate than that of the polyamide.
Having a lower melt flow rate, the alloy is the more viscous component of the blend
and, therefore, is more resistant to flow than the polyamide component. This
ensures that the polyamide component will migrate to the front of the melt flow
during manufacturing of the resin and parts made therefrom. In preferred
compositions, the polyolefin component can be any polyolefin suitable for use as a
thermoplastic resin and able to form a desired alloy, such as polypropylene,
polyethylene, blends of polypropylene with high density polyethylene, polypropylene
blended with ethylene propylene copolymer, and polypropylene blended with
ethylene butene copolymer. In preferred resin compositions according to the present
invention, the alloy component can be rubber, styrene, acrylic, or ionomer. The
alloying component is selected such that it imparts toughness, in particular impact
resistance, to the polypropylene resin, when compounded. Particularly preferred as
the polyolefin alloy is an alloy of polypropylene and rubber. This particular alloy is
preferred because polypropylene has well characterized benefits as a base for
thermoplastic resins, and the use of rubber as an alloy component imparts desired
flexibility onto the alloy.</p><p num="0010">The selection of component types and amounts in the alloy is made such that
the desired impact resistance balance is achieved while maintaining a desired
modulus or stiffness. It has been determined that a ratio of polyolefin to the alloying
material within the range of 70 weight% (wt%)/30 wt% to 90 wt%/10 wt%, inclusively, 
typically provides the desired balance between impact resistance and modulus. In
the resin of the preferred embodiment, which utilizes a polypropylene/rubber alloy as
the polyolefin alloy, a ratio within this range is preferred. A range of
polypropylene/rubber ratios of 75 wt%/25 wt% to 80 wt%/20 wt% is particularly
preferred.</p><p num="0011">The thermoplastic resin of the present invention includes as the second major
component a polyamide. Polyamides are a group of high molecular weight
polymeric materials in which amide linkages (CONH) occur along the molecular
chain. Polyamides typically offer high resistance to surface impacts such as
scratching, marring, and gouging. As indicated above, adding polyamides to
polyolefin alloys is one approach to improving the resistance of these alloys to
surface impacts. However, a natural incompatibility exits between polyamides and
low surface free energy substrates such as a polypropylene/rubber alloy. In order to
successfully create a thermoplastic resin composition of these two elements, this
natural incompatibility must be overcome.</p><p num="0012">Essentially any polyamide can be used as the polyamide component in the
thermoplastic resin of the present invention as long as it has a sufficient melt flow
rate as compared to that of the polyolefin alloy. That is, the melt flow rate of the
polyamide must be such that it imparts the desired difference between melt flow
rates of the polyamide and polyolefin alloy components onto the thermoplastic resin.
Thus, the polyamide component must have a higher melt flow rate than the
polyolefin alloy component. That is, the polyamide component must be less viscous
than the alloy. This relationship between the melt flow rates of the polyamide and
the polyolefin alloy components is developed more fully below. </p><p num="0013">The inventors have found that nylon-6, nylon-6,6, nylon 4,6, nylon-6,10, nylon-9,
nylon-11, nylon-12, nylon-6/6,6, and nylon-12,12 have been found suitable for use
in thermoplastic resins according to the present invention. Nylon-6 is preferred as the
polyamide component due to its acceptable melt flow rate in comparison to the
preferred polyolefin alloy component, a polypropylene/rubber alloy. Also, nylon-6 is
readily available and relatively inexpensive, making it desirable. Furthermore, Nylon-6
possesses relatively low hygroscopic properties in relation to other nylon materials.</p><p num="0014">The thermoplastic resin of the present invention achieves the desired
selective segregation of the polyamide phase at the surface due to the inclusion of
polyolefin alloy and polyamide components having appropriate melt flow rates. That
is, during manufacturing of the thermoplastic resin, the molten resin must be such
that the polyamide component migrates to the front of the melt flow. To achieve this
selective segregation, the polyamide component must be less viscous than the
polyolefin alloy component. The key to this is the difference between the melt flow
rate of the polyolefin alloy component and the polyamide component. It has been
found that a difference of one to twenty (1-20) between the melt flow rates of the
polyolefin alloy and polyamide components is acceptable. A difference in melt flow
rates greater than twenty (20) achieves an extreme localization of the polyamide
component at the surface of the thermoplastic resin, and in fact may result in a
delamination effect, causing separation of the polyamide component from the
polyolefin alloy component. A difference of between one to ten (1-10) is particularly
preferred and a difference of about two (2) is more particularly preferred.</p><p num="0015">In this application, the term 'melt flow rate' refers to the viscosity of a melted
composition at a given temperature with a given weight driving the flow of molten
material. Measurements of melt flow rates are conducted according to an 
international standard procedure, ISO 1133, entitled <i>"Determination of the Melt
Mass-Flow Rate (MFR) and the Melt Volume-Flow Rate (MVR) of Thermoplastics"</i>
(1997), using a weight of 2.16 kg. Measurements for melt flow rates are reported as
grams per ten (10) minutes. For the preferred embodiment, the melt flow ratio of the
selected polyamide to polyolefin alloy components is measured at 260°C (for nylon)
and 230°C (for polypropylene) with 2.16 kg, and reported as g/10min. The ratios of
melt flow rates for nylon-6 to polypropylene/rubber alloy of the preferred embodiment
typically range from 12/10 to 23.3/15, which corresponds to differences between melt
flow rates of between 2 and 8.3. Differences between melt flow rates that lie within
this range have been found to achieve the desired selective segregation, without
leading to any extreme localization and the resulting delamination effect previously
mentioned.</p><p num="0016">Melt flow rate and viscosity are a function of, among other factors, molecular
weight. As the molecular weight of a polymer material increases, the melt flow rate
decreases and viscosity increases. Thus, an appropriate combination of polyolefin
alloy and polyamide components can be determined by first selecting the polyolefin
alloy component, determining its melt flow rate, and subsequently selecting a
polyamide having a suitable molecular weight, thereby ensuring the desired
difference in melt flow rates between the two components.</p><p num="0017">The polyolefin alloy component, particularly with regard to the crystallinity of
the polyolefin component of the blend, may be selected such that the modulus of the
blend is affected. For example, high crystalline polypropylene may be utilized to
achieve a higher modulus blend. The crystallinity of the polypropylene component
can thus affect not only the stiffness of the final alloy but may also affect the 
migration of the nylon to the alloy surface through phase exclusion in the
crystallization processes upon manufacture.</p><p num="0018">The thermoplastic resin of the present invention also includes a
compatibilizing agent to overcome the natural incompatibility of the polyolefin alloy
and polyamide components. The compatibilizing agent is a component that allows
the polyamide to exist at the surface while increasing the cohesive strength between
the polyolefin alloy and polyamide phases of the resin.</p><p num="0019">The thermoplastic resin of present invention utilizes siloxane-modified
derivatives as the compatibilizing agents. These agents are able to increase the
interfacial strength without substantially affecting the desired qualities of the resin,
i.e., resistance to surface impacts, paintability, and low temperature ductility.</p><p num="0020">Essentially any siloxane-modified derivatives can be used as the
compatibilizing agent in the thermoplastic resin according to the present invention.
The following compatibilizing agents have been found to be suitable for use in
thermoplastic resins according to the present invention: monopheryl, monopropyl
siloxane, high molecular weight siloxane gum dispersed in high molecular weight
silicone polyether, methyl-2-phenylpropyl functional polysiloxane, dimethyl,
phenylmethyl silicone, terpolymer fluid, methyl long chain alkyl silicone wax,
polymethyl siloxane fluid, and short chain siloxane.</p><p num="0021">The thermoplastic resin of the present invention can further comprise a filler
material to increase the stiffness or modulus of molded parts created from the
thermoplastic resin. However, the addition of such fillers typically has a negative
effect on resistance to surface impacts. That is, the addition of fillers typically makes
parts manufactured from resins less resistant to surface impacts. Thus, filler
materials should only be used when increased stiffness is desired and necessary, 
such as with automobile bumpers, instrument panels, body panels (e.g., fenders),
and rocker panel moldings. When a filler is used in the thermoplastic resin of the
present invention, a balance must be found between the desire for an increase in
stiffness and the ability to allow the part to have lower resistance to surface impacts
and good low temperature ductility.</p><p num="0022">Various fillers are known in the art and essentially any of these fillers can be
used. The inventors have found that hydrophobe modified wollastonite, clay talc
silica, and wollastonite are acceptable and desirable filler materials due to their ease
of dispersability in the alloy matrix and their particle size range availability.
Particularly preferred as a filler material are calcium metasilicates (Wollastonite) with
loose bulk density of 0.35 to 0.52 g/cm<sup>3</sup> and particle size diameters of 3 to 9 microns.
The filler may be optionally surface treated with aminosilane or 3-methacryloxypropyltrimethoxysilane.</p><p num="0023">The composition of the thermoplastic resin according to the present invention
therefore comprises a polyolefin alloy, a polyamide, and a compatibilizing agent.
The resin may further include a filler material. The inventors have found that a resin
containing ≤ 25 wt% polyamide and 0.25 to 1.5 wt% compatibilizing agent, with the
balance of the weight comprising polyolefin alloy, possesses the desired qualities.
Preferably, the polyamide component constitutes ≤ 10 wt%. Most preferable, the
polyamide component comprises ≤ 5 wt % of the resin. If a filler is used in the resin,
it preferably comprises about 2 to 20 wt %. When a filler is utilized, the wt % of the
compatibilizing agent must be increased by about 1 %. Thus, for example, when a
filler is utilized, the compatibilizing agent preferably comprises between 1.25 and 2.5
wt % of the resin. </p><p num="0024">Thermoplastic resins of the present invention can be prepared using an
extruder capable of maintaining separate and distinct temperature zones between
compartments in which the various components of the resin are added sequentially.
This compartmentalization of temperature zones is necessary because the polyolefin
alloy component may begin to degrade at temperatures at which the polyamide
component is melted. Considering this, the use of a Werner-Pfleiderer twin-screw
extruder has been found to be particularly well suited for manufacturing the
thermoplastic resin of the present invention.</p><p num="0025">First, the polyamide is added into a compartment of the extruder having a
temperature sufficient to melt the polyamide. If nylon-6 is used, 260° C is a suitable
temperature for this first compartment. It is preferred to use pellets of the polyamide
component due to their availability and ease of handling. Next, the molten
polyamide is transported to a downstream compartment of the extruder having a
temperature that is suitable for melting the polyolefin alloy, but not so high as to
degrade the alloy. Thus, if a polypropylene/rubber alloy is used as the polyolefin
alloy, 225° C is a sufficient and appropriate temperature. At this time and in this
compartment, the compatibilizing agent is slowly added. As a siloxane, the
compatibilizing agent is a liquid. Thus, a suitable amount is slowly dripped into the
compartment onto the molten resin. Next, the molten resin is removed from the
extruder and cooled in a water bath. Lastly, the extruded resin is pelletized using
any of various methods known in the art. Following this procedure, the pellets of the
resin according to the present invention are suitable for use in plastic manufacturing
methods known in the art, such as injection and blow molding.</p><p num="0026">The thermoplastic resin of the present invention utilizes polyolefin alloy and
polyamide components that have relative melt flow rates that ensure selective 
segregation of the polyamide component at the front of the melt flow. Thus, when
molten resin is poured, the polyamide selectively segregates itself to the front of the
melt flow. As a result, the polyamide is localized at the surface of a component
being manufactured from the thermoplastic resin of the present invention. Also, the
thermoplastic resin of the present invention includes a compatibilizing agent to
increase the strength between the polyolefin alloy and polyamide components. This
ensures sufficient interphase strength to hold the phases together. The
thermoplastic resin of the present invention may further include a filler material when
increased stiffness is desired. As a result of this composition, thermoplastic resins
according to the present invention have excellent resistance to surface damage,
such as scratching, marring, and gouging, while still retaining desirous features of
the polyolefin alloy, such as superior moldability. Furthermore, the composition is
such that the compatibilizing agent does not impart undesirous characteristics, such
as poor paintability, etc.</p><p num="0027">These characteristics make the resin appropriate and suitable for use in
various plastic components, including interior and exterior automobile components,
industrial parts, and any other molded plastic component that requires the moldability
and other benefits of polyolefin alloys as well as an improved resistance to surface
impacts.</p> <p num="0028">The thermoplastic resin of the present invention is described in more detail
below by way of Examples. However, the following specific examples are merely
illustrative in nature, and are not intended in any way to limit the scope of the present
invention. </p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLES</u></heading><p num="0029">In the Examples, resin pellets produced in the compounding steps were
introduced into a 5" x 5" plaque tool inserted into a 350 ton Cincinnati Milacron
injection molding machine. The pellets were melted at 260°C and introduced into the
tool, which was cooled to 80°C. The total cycle time was 45 seconds. The following
characteristics were measured on the plaques produced previously with the
indicated test methods:</p><heading>1. <u style="single">Resistance to Surface Impact:</u> </heading> <p num="0030">Five Finger Scratch Test, FLTM BN 108-13, indentors with 1.0 mm ± 0.1 mm
diameter, with various loads ranging from 0.6 to 7 Newtons (N). Scratch resistance
testing was performed at room temperature (25°C), relative humidities of 50%, and
scratch velocities of 100 mm/min.</p> <p num="0031">Following the surface impact resistance test, various measurements were
taken, including total material displaced (initial and final microns), percent-displaced
material recovery, volume recovered (cm<sup>3</sup>/m<sup>2</sup>), and percent volume recovery.</p><heading>2. <u style="single">IZOD impact strength (IZOD):</u></heading><p num="0032">Izod impacts (ASTM D256 Method A) were performed at 0°C with a weight of
five-pounds. Impact energies are reported in J/m.</p><p num="0033">All compounds were prepared by adding the desired amount of nylon (10
weight percent) in the first zone of the Werner-Pfeider twin screw extruder set at
260°C equipped with a general compounding screw. The polyolefin alloy component
was added into the second zone of the extruder, with the zone set at 230°C. The
siloxane component (0.1 wt% based on total solids levels), and if desired, the filler 
component, was added directly after the polyolefin alloy component via a sight glass
opening. The siloxane, if in liquid form, was metered into the molten nylon/polyolefin
alloy mixture directly in the compounding screw.

The composition of the Examples are as follows:
<sl><li>Example 1. 3463 TPO (AMTUF 3463, no polyamide); m.p. 170°C, melt flow rate 15
g/10 min at 230°C, 2.16 kg. Note that AMTUF is a trademark of bp polymers, and
3463 is a reactor grade thermoplastic olefin alloy containing polypropylene and
elastomer.</li><li>Example 2. 3463/8202 (polyolefin alloy/nylon-6/no compatibilizing agent); 8202 is
nylon-6, m.p. 235°C, melt flow rate of 10-12 g/10 min at 260°C, 2.16 kg, from
Honeywell.</li><li>Example 3. 3463/BAC (polyolefin alloy/nylon/no compatibilizing agent); BAC is
diterminated nylon-6, with a melt flow rate of 20-25 g/10 min at 260°C, 2.16 kg, from
Honeywell.</li><li>Examples 4-11. Example 3 with various compatibilizer agents added as
indicated in the table.</li><li>Example 12. Example 3 with C18PP (maleated polypropylene, Eastman Chemical)
as compatibilizing agent. </li><li>Example 13. Example 3 with E43PP (maleated polypropylene, Eastman Chemical)
as compatibilizing agent.</li></sl><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Example Number</entry><entry align="left">Polyolefin Alloy/ Polyamide/ Compatibilizing Agent, if present<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">Injection Velocity (in/sec)</entry><entry align="center">Five Finger Scratch (Volume Removed) (cm<sup>3</sup>/m<sup>2</sup>)</entry><entry align="center">Izod (5 lb) (J/m)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1</entry><entry align="left">3464 TPO</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">3.68</entry><entry align="center">317</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">3.61</entry><entry align="center">323</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2</entry><entry align="left">3463/8202</entry><entry align="center">0.3/3</entry><entry align="center">2.37</entry><entry align="center">118</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2.07</entry><entry align="center">125</entry></row><row><entry align="left">3</entry><entry align="left">3463/BAC</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">2.74</entry><entry align="center">209</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2.6</entry><entry align="center">177</entry></row><row><entry align="left">4</entry><entry align="left">3463/BAC/</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">2.33</entry><entry align="center">209</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">DC Z-6018</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.88</entry><entry align="center">270</entry></row><row><entry align="left">5</entry><entry align="left">3463/BAC/</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">2.5</entry><entry align="center">228</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">DC23238</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2.49</entry><entry align="center">186</entry></row><row><entry align="left">6</entry><entry align="left">3463/BAC/</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">1.86</entry><entry align="center">236</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">DC230</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.9</entry><entry align="center">200</entry></row><row><entry align="left">7</entry><entry align="left">3463/BAC/</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">2.14</entry><entry align="center">217</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">DC510</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2.31</entry><entry align="center">206</entry></row><row><entry align="left">8</entry><entry align="left">3463/BAC/</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">1.77</entry><entry align="center">231</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">DC203</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.76</entry><entry align="center">207</entry></row><row><entry align="left">9</entry><entry align="left">3463/BAC/</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">1.74</entry><entry align="center">209</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">DC2503</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.93</entry><entry align="center">218</entry></row><row><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="left">3463/BAC/</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">1.84</entry><entry align="center">150</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">DC200</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.76</entry><entry align="center">161</entry></row><row><entry align="left">11</entry><entry align="left">3463/BAC/</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">1.86</entry><entry align="center">117</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">DC25212</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">1.9</entry><entry align="center">88</entry></row><row><entry align="left">12</entry><entry align="left">3463/BAC</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">1.93</entry><entry align="center">94</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">C18PP</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2.17</entry><entry align="center">77</entry></row><row><entry align="left">13</entry><entry align="left">3463/BAC/E43PP</entry><entry align="center">0.5/3</entry><entry align="center">2.36</entry><entry align="center">94</entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">2.23</entry><entry align="center">77<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0034">All of the Examples were tested for resistance to surface impacts by using the
five-finger scratch test and IZOD tests listed above. The results of these tests for all
Examples, including Comparative Examples, are presented in Table 1.</p><p num="0035">The results of these tests, as Table 1 clearly illustrates, demonstrate the
desired qualities of thermoplastic resins according to the present invention. The
results show that using a polyolefin alloy and polyamide with suitable differences in
their respective flow rates, along with a compatibilizing agent, have positive results
on resistance to surface impacts (i.e., the quantity of damage decreases). Also, as
illustrated by the evaluation of the Examples 12 and 13, which contain E-43PP and
C-18PP maleated polypropylene as compatibilizing agents, it can be seen that the
resin according to the present invention shows demonstrated benefits over polyolefin
alloy and polyamide alone, and over polyolefin alloy and polyamide using maleated
polypropylene as a compatibilizing agent.</p><p num="0036">The foregoing disclosure is the best mode devised by the inventors for
practicing the invention. It is apparent, however, that several variations in
thermoplastic resins in accordance with the present invention may be obvious to one
skilled in the art. Inasmuch as the foregoing disclosure is intended to enable one
skilled in the pertinent art to practice the instant invention, it should not be construed
to be limited thereby but rather should be construed to include such aforementioned
obvious variations and be limited only by the spirit and scope of the following claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A thermoplastic resin, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>75 to 99% by weight of an alloy of a polyolefin and an alloying material, said
alloy having a melt flow rate determined by testing according to ISO 1133 with a
weight of 2.16 kg;</claim-text><claim-text>1 to 25% by weight of a polyamide having a melt flow rate determined by
testing according to ISO 1133 with a weight of 2.16 kg; and</claim-text><claim-text>0.25 to 2.5% by weight of a compatibilizing agent,</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein the difference between said melt flow rate for said alloy and said melt flow
rate for said polyamide is greater than or equal to 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A thermoplastic resin according to claim 1 wherein said difference
between said melt flow rate for said alloy and said melt flow rate for said polyamide
is also less than or equal to 20.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A thermoplastic resin according to claim 1 wherein said polyolefin is a
member selected from the group consisting of polypropylene, polyethylene, a blend
of polypropylene and high density polyethylene, a blend of polypropylene and
ethylene propylene copolymer, and a blend of polypropylene and ethylene butene
copolymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A thermoplastic resin according to claim 1 wherein said alloying
material is a member selected from the group consisting of rubber, styrene, acrylic,
and ionomer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A thermoplastic resin according to claim 1 wherein said polyamide is a
member selected from the group consisting of nylon-6, nylon-6,6, nylon 4,6, nylon-6,10,
nylon-9, nylon-11, nylon-12, nylon-6/6,6, and nylon-12,12.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A thermoplastic resin according to claim 1 wherein said compatibilizing
agent is a member selected from the group consisting of monopheryl, monopropyl
siloxane, high molecular weight siloxane gum dispersed in high molecular weight
silicone polyether, methyl-2-phenylpropyl functional polysiloxane, dimethyl,
phenylmethyl silicone, terpolymer fluid, methyl long chain alkyl silicone wax,
polymethyl siloxane fluid, and short chain siloxane.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A thermoplastic resin according to claim 1 wherein said difference
between said melt flow rate of said alloy and said melt flow rate of said polyamide is
between 1 and 10.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A thermoplastic resin according to claim 1 wherein said difference
between said melt flow rate of said alloy and said melt flow rate of said polyamide is
about 2.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A thermoplastic resin according to claim 1 further comprising 2 to 20%
by weight of a filler material.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A thermoplastic resin according to claim 9 wherein said filler material is
a member selected from the group consisting of hydrophobe-modified wollastonite,
siloxane modified wollastonite, vinyl modified wollastonite, clay, talc silica, and
wollastonite.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>