<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1186577-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1186577" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="24630834" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020313"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1186577-A2" status="new" fvid="23407544"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1186577</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20020313</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01121285-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01121285</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010905</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-65589900-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>65589900</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000906</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C04B  28/14        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C04B  28/14</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Flexible abbindende Fugenzusammensetzung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Flexible setting type joint compound</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Matériau à prise hydraulique pour joints flexibles</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="GB-2228931-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2228931</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3297601-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3297601</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3947398-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3947398</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4238239-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4238239</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5494947-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5494947</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source name="APP"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5746822-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5746822</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5779786-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5779786</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5879825-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5879825</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>AIR PRODUCTS POLYMERS LP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AIR PRODUCTS POLYMERS, L.P.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>AIR PRODUCTS POLYMERS, L.P.</last-name><address><street>7201 Hamilton Boulevard</street><city>Allentown, PA 18195-1501</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HORNAMAN CHRIS E</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HORNAMAN, E. CHRIS</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hornaman, Chris E.</last-name><address><street>2225 Riverbend Road</street><city>Allentown, PA 18103</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Kador &amp;amp; Partner</last-name><address><street>Corneliusstrasse 15</street><city>80469 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A flexible setting type hydraulic joint compound and a method of forming flexible
joints. The flexible joint compound of this invention primarily contains 2 to 20 parts by
weight of an emulsion polymer having a T<sub>g</sub> that is less than about - 40 °C, and 22 to 44
parts by weight of total water, based on 100 parts by weight calcium sulfate hemihydrate
filler. It can be applied to joints between two adjacent sheets of gypsum board to form a
flexible joint that is resistant to cracking.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading><p num="0001">Not applicable.</p><heading>STATEMENT REGARDING FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH OR
DEVELOPMENT</heading><p num="0002">Not applicable.</p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0003">When gypsum board panels (also known as "dry wall" in the industry) or the like
are used as a wall surfacing in the construction of houses and other structures, joint
compounds are typically used in combination with a paper or mesh tape material to close
and fill the joints and corners between adjoining panels.</p><p num="0004">Joint compounds typically are provided and marketed in one of two forms - single
component or ready mix which is a finished formulation ready to apply needing only
stirring before application and two component setting dry mix which is in the form of a dry
free-flowing powder to which water is added and stirred until a workable consistency is
attained.</p><p num="0005">The two main components of joint compounds are a filler and a binder.
Conventional fillers are inert such as calcium carbonate and calcium sulfate dihydrate
(gypsum), and reactive such as calcium sulfate hemihydrate. The type of filler
determines whether the joint compound is a setting or a drying compound.</p><p num="0006">A major portion of the filler in setting joint compounds is calcium sulfate
hemihydrate. Optionally, small portions of inert fillers such as calcium carbonate, talc, 
mica, silica, clays, expanded perlite, calcium sulfate dihydrate, and other mineral fillers
can be added to setting type joint compounds. The calcium sulfate hemihydrate takes
up some of the water in the mix by hydration to form calcium sulfate dihydrate crystals
when the compound sets. The balance of water evaporates or is absorbed into the
substrate.</p><p num="0007">Calcium carbonate is normally the major portion of filler in drying type joint
compounds. Optionally, small portions of inert fillers such as talc, mica, silica, clays,
expanded perlite, and other mineral fillers can also be added to drying type joint
compounds. Hardening occurs as the water is eliminated through evaporation or
absorption into the substrate.</p><p num="0008">A binder serves to provide cohesive strength to the joint compound and to bond
the compound to a surface. Examples of typical binders are poly(vinyl acetate), vinyl
acetate copolymers, and poly(vinyl alcohol).</p><p num="0009">In a widely used technique for filling gypsum board joints, water is added to a dry
mixture containing calcium sulfate hemihydrate to form a high viscosity joint compound
paste which is applied in order to close the joint. A fiberglass, cloth, or paper taping
material is then stretched over the joint and embedded in the soft joint compound. An
overlayer or top dressing of the joint compound is applied over the taping material to
completely fill the joint and provide a smooth surface. After setting, the top dressing can
optionally be sanded to smooth out irregularities prior to painting or applying a wall
covering, or other finishing material.</p><p num="0010">By adjusting the catalysts and retarders present in the joint compound the setting
time can be adjusted to meet the requirements of the applicator. </p><p num="0011">One problem with conventional setting or drying type joint compounds is their
friability. Cracks can develop if the joint is subject to movement either during cure or
drying or after the joint compound has set or dried..</p><p num="0012">An application in which particular problems occur is factory manufactured houses
or manufactured house modules. When components such as ceiling and walls are
moved about during the construction process joint movement can occur and cracking
can occur. Also, as the partially completed structure is moved through the various
manufacturing steps the joints are subject to movement that can cause cracks.
Additionally, as the completed structure is moved from the point of manufacture to
another site the structure is subjected to bending, racking and twisting motion that can
cause joints to flex and crack. The action of transport can result in excessive mechanical
stress that causes cracks to form in the joints of the fabricated gypsum board surfaces.</p><p num="0013">An example of drying type compounds for flexible joints is described in U.S.
5,494,947. They contain an acrylate, a biocide, a reinforcing agent, a latex, surfactants,
a plasticizer, coalescents, a fungicide and a filler. The compounds described in this
patent are deficient in that the time to effect drying is long and unsuitable for the rapid
assembly techniques used in factory assembled structures.</p><p num="0014">Traditional setting type compositions provide the rapid hardening needed for
factory assembled structures but do not have sufficient flexibility and crack if the joint is
subjected to movement.</p><p num="0015">Examples of compositions that combine emulsion polymers with one or more
fillers are described below:
<sl><li>U.S. 3,297,601 (Maynard, et al., 1967) discloses a substantially dry joint
compound containing calcium sulfate hemihydrate, poly(vinyl acetate) and starch which, 
when mixed with water, can be used for finishing joints. Low shrinkage and relatively
fast set times are reported.</li><li>U.S. 3,947,398 (Williams, 1976) discloses a surfacing composition comprising
gypsum plaster and an aqueous emulsion of polymer resin. The polymer resin is usually
a polymer of ethylenically unsaturated monomers such as vinyl resins and polymers of
acrylates and methacrylates. Styrene/acrylic copolymers are preferred. The resins
desirably set to a resin phase which is hard at room temperature (65 °F.) The proportion
of dry resin solids is 10 to 35 wt %, based on the weight of dry plaster solids. Preferred
compositions are reported to be ideally suited for domestic and industrial flooring.</li><li>U.S. 4,238,239 (Brown, 1980) discloses a dry wall joint compound containing a
powdered mixture of 27 to 41 wt % gypsum, 24 to 38 wt % hydrated gypsum, 16 to 26 wt
% calcium carbonate, 5 to 9 wt % plaster of paris, 4 to 6 wt % hydrated amorphous silica,
and 1 to 3 wt % talc. The dry wall joint compound can be mixed with water or an
aqueous mixture of 0.35 to 8 wt % zinc oxide, 0.35 to 1.5 wt % sodium acetate, 0.35 to 3
wt % ammonium alum, and 0.35 to 8 wt % of an acrylic resin. to form a dry wall joint
cement. The joint cement is reported to be resistant to cracking and shrinkage.</li><li>The need remains in the industry for quick setting hydraulic joint setting
compounds that prevents cracking of joints, especially during transport of prefabricated
modules.</li></sl></p><heading>BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0016">This invention is directed to a flexible setting hydraulic joint compound and to a
method of forming flexible joints in adjacent panels of gypsum board. The flexible joint
compound of this invention primarily contains 100 parts by weight calcium sulfate
hemihydrate reactive filler, 2 to 20 parts by weight of an emulsion polymer having a
glass transition temperature (T<sub>g</sub>) of less than about - 40 °C, and additional water for a 
total water content of 26 to 44 parts by weight. Emulsion polymers of this invention are
water based. The emulsion polymer functions as an adhesion promoter and as a binder
for the joint compound. Optionally, one or more other binders, such as a modified
cellulose or poly(vinyl alcohol), can be added. The setting type joint compound can also
optionally contain small portions of inert fillers such as calcium carbonate, talc, mica,
silica, clays, expanded perlite, and other mineral fillers, In addition to the above
components, the joint compound can optionally contain other components such as a
surfactant, an accelerator to reduce the set time, retarders to slow the set time, and
pigments for color. The hydraulic joint compound can be applied to a joint between two
adjacent sheets of gypsum board. Optionally, a layer of tape can be applied to the joint
before the setting type hydraulic joint compound is applied or the hydraulic joint
compound can be used to embed a layer of tape. Additionally, the setting type joint
compound can be used to fill the indentations made when nails or screws are used to
attach the dry wall to the substructure or to fill other imperfections.</p><p num="0017">The setting type hydraulic joint compound of this invention provides the following
advantages:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>setting time can be two hour or less in the absence of an accelerator;</li><li>joint remains flexible during and after setting of the compound;</li><li>cracking at the joint is eliminated; and</li><li>the need for paper tape in the joint can optionally be eliminated.</li></ul></p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0018">Not applicable. </p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0019">Key ingredients of the setting type hydraulic joint compound of this invention are
shown in the table below:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Ingredient</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Amount<!--footnotes removed--></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Preferred Amount<!--footnotes removed--></b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Most Preferred Amount<!--footnotes removed--></b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Calcium sulfate hemihydrate</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Emulsion polymer having a T<sub>g</sub> of less than about - 40 °C (solids).</entry><entry align="center">2 to 20</entry><entry align="center">8 to 16</entry><entry align="center">11 to 14</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Total water (includes water in emulsion polymer).</entry><entry align="center">26 to 44</entry><entry align="center">26 to 44</entry><entry align="center">33 to 41</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Inert fillers, such as calcium carbonate, calcium sulfate dihydrate, clays, expanded perlite, mica, silica, and talc.</entry><entry align="center">0 to 20</entry><entry align="center">1 to 15</entry><entry align="center">1 to 15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Additional surfactant.</entry><entry align="center">0 to 5</entry><entry align="center">0.1 to 1.0</entry><entry align="center">0.1 to 0.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Accelerator.</entry><entry align="center">0 to 5</entry><entry align="center">0 to 5</entry><entry align="center">0 to 5<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0020">Emulsion polymers appropriate for this invention are those that have a T<sub>g</sub> of less
than about - 40 °C; preferably less than about - 45 °C. Examples of appropriate
emulsion polymers are homo- and copolymers of ethylenically unsaturated compounds,
such as vinyl acetate; ethylene; vinyl versatate; C<sub>3</sub>-C<sub>10</sub> alkenoic acids, such as acrylic
acid, methacrylic acid, crotonic acid and isocrotonic acid and their C<sub>1</sub> to C<sub>18</sub> alkyl esters,
such as, methyl, propyl, butyl, and 2-ethylhexyl ester, or esters with C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> alkanols, such
as methanol, ethanol, propanol, butanol, and 2-ethylhexanol; vinyl halides, such as vinyl
chloride; alpha, beta-unsaturated C<sub>4</sub>-C<sub>10</sub> alkenedioic acids such as maleic acid, fumaric
acid, and itaconic acid and their monoesters and diesters with the same C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>18</sub> alkanols;
and nitrogen containing monoolefinically unsaturated monomers, particularly nitriles,
amides, N-methylol amides, C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> alkanoic acid ethers of N-methylol amides and 
allylcarbamates, such as acrylonitrile, acrylamide, methacrylamide, N-methylol
acrylamide, N-methylol methacrylamide, N-methylol allylcarbamate, and C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> alkyl
ethers or C<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> alkanoic acid esters of N-methylol acrylamide, N-methylol
methacrylamide and N-methylol allylcarbamate. Copolymers of 2-ethylhexyl acrylate
and one or more other ethylenically unsaturated compound are preferred.</p><p num="0021">Polymer emulsions typically contain stabilizing agents, such as surfactants and/or
protective colloids. Additional surfactants, such as sodium dodecyl benzene sulfonate
and alkyl naphthalene sulfonate and other alkyl substituted aromatic sulfonates can be
used to assist in the wetting out of the surface to which the joint compound is applied
and to improve the wetting out of the solids in the setting compound during mixing.</p><p num="0022">Conventional accelerating agents or catalysts can be used with the calcium
sulfate hemihydrate if required to adjust the setting time of the mixture. Examples of
appropriate accelerators are ammonium sulfate, calcium sulfate, copper sulfate, ferrous
sulfate, magnesium sulfate, potassium aluminum sulfate (alum), potassium sulfate,
sodium bisulfate, sodium sulfate, and zinc sulfate.</p><p num="0023">The amount of water added is dependent on the viscosity needed for application
by known conventional methods used in the application of joint compounds.</p><p num="0024">The joint composition can be supplied as a two part system in which the dry
components (e.g., calcium sulfate hemihydrate and pigment powder) are in one part and
the liquid components (e.g., polymer emulsion and water) are supplied as a second part.</p><p num="0025">The invention will be further clarified by a consideration of the following examples,
which are intended to be purely exemplary of the invention.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0026">Setting compounds containing several latex polymers were tested for flexibility
and cracking. The compounds consisted of 100 parts of a dry mix containing calcium 
sulfate hemihydrate, about 4 % silica, 2 % alumina, and small amounts of other clay-type
minerals; 28 parts water, and 14.3 parts of a polymer emulsion. The joint between
adjacent panels of gypsum board was filled with the setting compound. No tape was
used in any of the samples.</p><p num="0027">Flexibility was measured by bending the joint until the first sign of cracking failure
occurred and recording the angle at failure.</p><p num="0028">The procedure for determining cracking on drying is a modification of ASTM
Method C-474. A wedge shaped draw down of the mixed joint compound was made on
a piece of gypsum board. The wedge tapered from 1/8" thickness at the thickest side to
0 on the other side. Cracking was measure on an arbitrary scale ranging from 1 (best) to
9 (severe) depending on the thickness of the sample where cracking appeared.</p><p num="0029">Results of the tests are shown in Table 1. <tables><table><tgroup cols="9"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" align="center" namest="1"><b>Latex</b></entry><entry nameend="9" align="center" namest="5"/></row><row><entry align="center"><b>Type (14.3 g)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Tg</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Solids</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>PHR Dry</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Water (g)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Flex Angle, °</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Cracking on drying</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Set Time, Min.</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Observation</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">None</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">28.6</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="right">1.0</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="left">Creamy</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flexbond® 165 2-ethylhexyl acrylate copolymer</entry><entry align="right">-48</entry><entry align="center">69.0</entry><entry align="center">9.9</entry><entry align="center">17.1</entry><entry align="center">90</entry><entry align="right">1.0</entry><entry align="center">94</entry> <entry align="left">Creamy, thick, slightly lumpy</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Valtac® 56 2-ethylhexyl acrylate copolymer</entry><entry align="right">-42</entry><entry align="center">48.0</entry> <entry align="center">6.9</entry> <entry align="center">17.1</entry> <entry align="center">65</entry><entry align="right">1.5</entry><entry align="center">&gt;360</entry><entry align="left">Creamy, thick, slightly lumpy</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Airflex® 600BP VAE/Acrylate copolymer</entry><entry align="right">-40</entry><entry align="center">55.0</entry><entry align="center">7.9</entry><entry align="center">24.6</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="right">1.0</entry><entry align="center">&gt;150</entry><entry align="left">Creamy, Thick and airy</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rhoplex® N-1031 butyl acrylate polymer</entry><entry align="right">&lt;-40</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">37.1</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="right">---</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="left">Coagulated</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rhoplex® N-580 butyl acrylate polymer</entry><entry align="right">&lt;-40</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">32.9</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="right">---</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="left">Coagulated</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rhoplex® N-619 butyl acrylate polymer</entry><entry align="right">&lt;-40</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">34.3</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="right">---</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="left">Coagulated</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flexbond® 149 VAc/dioctyl maleate copolymer</entry><entry align="right">-30</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">7.1</entry><entry align="center">25.7</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="right">2.0</entry><entry align="center">36</entry><entry align="left">Some lumps</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flexbond® 150 VAc/dioctyl maleate copolymer</entry><entry align="right">-28</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">7.1</entry><entry align="center">24.3</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="right">1.5</entry><entry align="center">37</entry><entry align="left">Mix had few lumps</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Airflex® 500 VAE copolymer</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="center">55.0</entry><entry align="center">7.9</entry><entry align="center">18.6</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="right">1.5</entry><entry align="center">54</entry><entry align="left">Creamy, Slightly grainy</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Airflex® 525 VAE copolymer</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="center">55.0</entry><entry align="center">7.9</entry><entry align="center">20.0</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="right">3.0</entry><entry align="center">37</entry><entry align="left">Creamy, Some lumps</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Airflex® 809 VAE copolymer</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="center">55.0</entry><entry align="center">7.9</entry><entry align="center">20.9</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="right">1.5</entry><entry align="center">56</entry><entry align="left">Creamy, Few lumps</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Airflex® 728 VAE/vinyl chloride terpolymer</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="center">55.0</entry><entry align="center">7.9</entry><entry align="center">20.0</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="right">3.0</entry><entry align="center">168</entry><entry align="left">Creamy, Few lumps</entry></row><row><entry>PHR = parts per hundred of dry mix</entry></row><row><entry>VAE = vinyl acetate/ethylene</entry></row><row><entry>VAc = vinyl acetate</entry></row><row><entry>Flexbond, Valtac, and Airflex products supplied by Air Products and Chemicals, Inc. Rhoplex products supplied by Rohm and Haas.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0030">The data in Table 1 show that compositions containing an emulsion polymer with
a T<sub>g</sub> of less than about - 40 °C had a greater flexibility based on the angle at which
failure occurred than other emulsion polymers; however, some emulsion polymers, such
as Valtac 56, retarded the hydration so much that the mix did not cure but rather just 
dried out over a period of several hours. They were flexible but, due to the setting
properties, would have little practical value. For example, a mixture of dry components
of the setting type joint compound and Valtac 56 did not set after 24 hours. All samples
containing an emulsion polymer showed an increase of set time compared to the sample
containing no emulsion polymer.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 2</heading><p num="0031">The procedure of Example 1 was followed using 25.7 g, instead of 14.3 g, of
several emulsion polymers. Results are summarized in Table 2.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="9"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" align="center" namest="1"><b>Latex</b></entry><entry nameend="9" align="center" namest="5"/></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Type</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Tg</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Solids</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>PHR Dry</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Water (g)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Flex Angle, °</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Cracking</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Set Time, Min</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Observation</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flexbond 165</entry><entry align="center">-48</entry><entry align="center">69.0</entry><entry align="center">17.7</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="right">100</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="right">90</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Valtac 56</entry><entry align="center">-42</entry><entry align="center">48.0</entry><entry align="center">12.3</entry><entry align="center">7.1</entry><entry align="right">100</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="right">&gt;120</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flexbond 149</entry><entry align="center">-30</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">12.9</entry><entry align="center">20.0</entry><entry align="right">10</entry><entry align="center">5.5</entry><entry align="right">34</entry><entry align="center">Mix was very lumpy</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flexbond 150</entry><entry align="center">-28</entry><entry align="center">50.0</entry><entry align="center">12.9</entry><entry align="center">18.6</entry><entry align="right">20</entry><entry align="center">5.5</entry><entry align="right">40</entry><entry align="center">Mix was creamy, few lumps</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables>
Data presented in Table 2 show that a higher level of emulsion polymers having a T<sub>g</sub>
lower than about - 40 °C improved joint flexibility. However, for emulsion polymers
having a T<sub>g</sub> higher than about-40 °C (Flexbond 149 and Flexbond 150), joint flexibility
was not improved by using a higher amount of polymer.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 3</heading><p num="0032">The following formulation was used to compare the effect of various additional
surfactants on the workability of the joint compound of this invention. The results are
presented in Table 4. <tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center"><b>Ingredient</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Weight, g</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="center">22.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Additional Surfactant</entry><entry align="center">0.25</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Flexbond 165 emulsion</entry><entry align="center">13.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Calcium sulfate hemihydrate<!--footnotes removed--></entry><entry align="center">100<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="149" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="175"/><img id="img-00120001" orientation="unknown" wi="153" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00120001.tif" inline="no" he="16"/></p><p num="0033">The data of Table 4 show that several surfactants enhanced the workability of the joint
compound. Rhodacal DS-10 gave the best workability.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A setting type flexible joint compound comprising,
for each 100 parts by weight calcium sulfate hemihydrate:
<claim-text><claim-text>2 to 20 parts by weight (solids) of an emulsion polymer having a Tg of
less than about - 40 °C;</claim-text><claim-text>26 to 44 parts by weight total water;</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 20 parts by weight inert filler;</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 5 parts by weight additional surfactant; and</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 5 parts by weight of an accelerator.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The setting type flexible joint compound of claim 1, comprising,
for each 100 parts by weight calcium sulfate hemihydrate:
<claim-text><claim-text>8 to 16 parts by weight of the emulsion polymer solids;</claim-text><claim-text>26 to 44 parts by weight total water;</claim-text><claim-text>2 to 4 parts by weight inert filler;</claim-text><claim-text>0.1 to 1.0 parts by weight additional surfactant; and</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 5 parts by weight accelerator.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The setting type flexible joint compound of claim 1, comprising
for each 100 parts by weight calcium sulfate hemihydrate:
<claim-text><claim-text>11 to 14 parts by weight of the emulsion polymer solids;</claim-text><claim-text>33 to 41 parts by weight total water;</claim-text><claim-text>2 to 4 parts by weight inert filler;</claim-text><claim-text>0.1 to 0.2 parts by weight additional surfactant; and</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 5 parts by weight accelerator.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The setting type flexible joint compound of claim 1, wherein the emulsion
polymer is a hompolymer of an ethylenically unsaturated compound or a copolymer of
one or more ethylenically unsaturated compounds, said ethylenically unsaturated
compounds selected from the group consisting of vinyl acetate; ethylene; vinyl versatate;
a C3-C10 alkenoic acid, a C1 to C18 alkyl ester of a C3 to C10 alkenoic acid, a C1-C18
alkanol ester of a C3-C10 alkenoic acid, a vinyl halide, an alpha, beta-unsaturated C4-C10
alkenedioic acid, a C1 to C18 alkyl ester of an alpha, beta-unsaturated C4-C10 alkenedioic
acid, a C1 to C18 alkanol diester of an alpha, beta-unsaturated C4-C10 alkenedioic acid, a
nitrile, an amide, an N-methylol amide, a C1-C4 alkanoic acid ether of an N-methylol
amide, acrylonitrile, acrylamide, methacrylamide, N-methylol acrylamide, N-methylol
methacrylamide, or N-methylol allylcarbamate, and a C1-C4 alkyl ether or a C1-C4
alkanoic acid ester of N-methylol acrylamide, N-methylol methacrylamide or N-methylol
allylcarbamate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The setting type flexible joint compound of claim 1 wherein the emulsion
polymer is a copolymer of 2-ethylhexyl acrylate and one or more other ethylenically
unsaturated compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The setting type flexible joint compound of claim 1 wherein the inert filler
comprises one or more of calcium carbonate, calcium sulfate dihydrate, clay, expanded
perlite, mica, silica, and talc.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method for producing setting type flexible joints comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a) supplying a first planar substrate having a first edge;</claim-text><claim-text>'b) abutting a second edge of a second planar substrate against said first
edge of the first planar substrate, thereby forming a joint;</claim-text><claim-text>c) applying a setting type hydraulic joint compound to the joint, said joint
compound comprising,
for each 100 parts by weight calcium sulfate hemihydrate:
<claim-text><claim-text>2 to 20 parts by weight (solids) of an emulsion polymer having a Tg
of less than about - 40 °C;</claim-text><claim-text>26 to 44 parts by weight total water;</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 20 parts by weight inert filler;</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 5 parts by weight additional surfactant; and</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 5 parts by weight of an accelerator.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>d) allowing the joint compound to set.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method of claim 7 wherein the joint compound comprises,
for each 100 parts by weight calcium sulfate hemihydrate:
<claim-text><claim-text>8 to 16 parts by weight of the emulsion polymer solids;</claim-text><claim-text>26 to 44 parts by weight total water;</claim-text><claim-text>2 to 4 parts by weight inert filler;</claim-text><claim-text>0.1 to 1.0 parts by weight additional surfactant;</claim-text><claim-text>and 0 to 5 parts by weight accelerator.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method of claim 7 wherein the joint compound comprises,
for each 100 parts by weight calcium sulfate hemihydrate:
<claim-text><claim-text>11 to 14 parts by weight of the emulsion polymer solids;</claim-text><claim-text>33 to 41 parts by weight total water;</claim-text><claim-text>2 to 4 parts by weight inert filler;</claim-text><claim-text>0.1 to 0.2 parts by weight additional surfactant; and</claim-text><claim-text>0 to 5 parts by weight accelerator.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method of claim 7, wherein the emulsion polymer is copolymer of 2-ethylhexyl
acrylate and one or more other ethylenically unsaturated compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The method of claim 7, wherein the inert filler comprises one or more of
calcium carbonate, calcium sulfate dihydrate, clay, expanded perlite, mica, silica, and
talc.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The method of claim 7, wherein paper or mesh tape is embedded in the joint
compound prior to d).</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>