<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1106635-A2" country="EP" doc-number="1106635" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="23822205" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010613"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1106635-A2" status="new" fvid="23141884"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1106635</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20010613</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-00125299-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>00125299</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20001128</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-45881899-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>45881899</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991210</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J   2/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B01J   2/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C05G   3/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C05G   3/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C05G   5/00        20060101A I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C05G   5/00        20060101C I20060521RMUS        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/42        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/48        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08G  18/66        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/16        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 175/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 175/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  18/48T</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08G  18/66P6</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D 175/04</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Polyurethanverkapselte Düngemittel die verbesserte Langsamabgabeeigenschaften aufzeigen</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Polyurethane encapsulated fertilizer having improved slow-release properties</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Engrais encapsulé par polyuréthane ayant des propriétés à libération lente améliorées</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0867422-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0867422</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-10029886-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>10029886</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5538531-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5538531</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BAYER AG</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BAYER CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Bayer Corporation</last-name><address><street>100 Bayer Road</street><city>Pittsburgh, PA 15205</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CLINE ROBERT L</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MARKUSCH PETER H</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SARPESHKAR ASHOK M</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YEATER ROBERT P</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CLINE, ROBERT L.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MARKUSCH, PETER H.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SARPESHKAR, ASHOK M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YEATER, ROBERT P.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CLINE, ROBERT L.</last-name><address><street>302 West Madison</street><city>Paden City, WV 26159</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MARKUSCH, PETER H.</last-name><address><street>111 Lynbrook Drive</street><city>McMurray, PA 15317</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SARPESHKAR, ASHOK M.</last-name><address><street>458 Diablo Drive</street><city>Upper St. Clair, PA 15241</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>YEATER, ROBERT P.</last-name><address><street>RFD 4, Box 78</street><city>Moundsville, WV 26041</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Perchenek, Nils, Dr.</last-name><address><street>Bayer AG KB-RP Patente und Lizenzen</street><city>51368 Leverkusen</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention relates to polyurethane encapsulated fertilizer
particles which exhibit slow-release properties and to a process for their
production. The process comprises applying an isocyanate-reactive
component to fertilizer particles, to form fertilizer particles coated with an
isocyanate-reactive component, applying a polyisocyanate component
onto the coated fertilizer particles to form polyurethane encapsulated
fertilizer particles, and, optionally, repeating these steps as many times as
necessary to form the polyurethane encapsulated fertilizer particles that
contain about 2 to 20% by weight of polyurethane, based on the total
weight of the encapsulated fertilizer particles. Suitable isocyanate-reactive
components include polyesterether polyols that comprise either a blend of
or the reaction product of (i) castor oil having an OH number of about 160
to about 170, a viscosity of about 500 to about 900 mPa·s at 25°C, and a
water content of less than 0.5% by weight; and (ii) a polyether polyol
having an OH number of from 28 to 700, a functionality of from 3 to 8, and
a molecular weight of about 240 to about 6,000, and a viscosity of from
about 50 to 35,000 mPa·s at 25°C. The polyether polyol must be prepared
from a suitable initiator compound and an alkylene oxide comprising at
least 70% by weight of propylene oxide.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to polyurethane encapsulated fertilizers
exhibiting improved slow-release properties and to a process for the
production of these polyurethane encapsulated fertilizers.</p><p num="0002">Commercial particulate fertilizers are produced and marketed in
several different particle types, i.e., granular, pelletized, dusts, pilled, and
prilled fertilizers. Also, they may be formed of inorganic substances,
organic substances, or combinations thereof. The improvements of the
present invention can be applied to any of these types of particulate
fertilizers.</p><p num="0003">In order to be effective in promoting plant growth, fertilizers must
contain some amount of water soluble plant nutrients. These are typically
in the form of water soluble compounds of nitrogen, phosphorus and
potassium, alone or in combination, and often in conjunction with other
elements, such as, for example, calcium, boron, magnesium, zinc,
chlorine, etc. Such particulate fertilizers can be made of a single
component, e.g., urea, ammonium nitrate, potassium chloride, etc., or of
multiple components often mixed with inert water soluble or water
insoluble materials as in common fertilizers designated as 6-6-6, 4-6-4,
10-10-10, 20-20-5, 14-16-0, 5-20-20, and the like. In addition, specialized
fertilizers may contain optional additives such as herbicides, insecticides,
trace elements, iron salts, sulfur, etc. The improvements of the present
invention can be applied to any of these fertilizers.</p><p num="0004">Historically, particulate fertilizers possessed a number of known
defects, the most notable being the too rapid release of soluble plant food,
causing phytotoxicity and the rapid depletion of the plant nutrients by
leaching. Other problems included tendencies to cake and form dust.
These problems are well documented in previous patents that professed 
solutions to one or more of the known defects, including U.S. Patents
3,475,154, 3,259,482, 3,264,088, 3,264,089, 4,711,659, 4,772,490 and
Japanese Patent 52-38361. The present invention provides additional
improvements in the construction of particulate fertilizers which render
them highly attrition resistant and further extended release properties.</p><p num="0005">A number of slow release coatings for particular fertilizers have
previously been proposed. The process of sulfur coating urea particles is
described in U.S. Patent 3,342,577 and was developed in the late 1960's
by the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA) as an economical system for
reducing the rate of dissolution when urea particles are applied to the soil
as fertilizer. This process requires high levels of sulfur, which reduces the
nutrient analysis of the fertilizer particles, and even then, imperfections
remain in the coating, making it necessary to apply a sealant coating,
which is composed of a mixture of 30% polyethylene resin in a 70% bright
stock mineral oil.</p><p num="0006">Attempts to seal the sulfur coating have been described in U.S.
Patent 5,219,465. Topcoats are formed on the sulfur layer using various
polymers which include a polyurethane based on polymethylene
poly(phenyl-isocyanate) and polyester polyols. In this process, the addition
of a catalyst is necessary to promote cure of the polyurethane on the
surface.</p><p num="0007">U.S. Patent 5,599,374 relates to a process for producing sulfur-coated
slow release fertilizers which have improved impact and abrasion
resistance properties. This process applies liquid monomers sequentially
onto the surface of hot sulfur-coated urea granules, and copolymerizes
these to form a firm, tack-free, water insoluble polymer coating sealant.
Suitable liquid monomers are diisocyanates such as diphenylmethane
diisocyanate, and a polyol mixture of diethylene glycol (DEG) and
triethanolamine (TEOA). TEOA serves both as a reactive polyol and as a
catalyst. This patent attempts to overcome the deficiencies of using sulfur
alone to achieve slow release properties. The polyurethane serves to coat 
and cover the areas of the fertilizer particle not covered by the sulfur, and
thus, provide improved time release properties.</p><p num="0008">Coatings in which preformed polymer resins are applied from
solvents have been described in, for example, U.S. Patents 3,475,154 and
3,264,089. The use of solvents creates a vapor hazard as the products are
dried and the solvent evaporation step can result in pinhole imperfections
in the coatings when applied.</p><p num="0009">U.S. Patent 4,369,055 tried to facilitate degradation of coating
materials while maintaining the function for controlling the dissolving-out
rate by dispersing inorganic powders such as sulfur and talc in a low
molecular weight olefin polymer. However, the disclosed coating materials
are difficult to apply in uniform layers because the polymers must be
maintained in the molten state.</p><p num="0010">Polyurethane coatings as disclosed in U.S. Patents 4,711,659,
4,804,403, and 4,969,947 require that the substrate contains a minimum
quantity of reactive -NH<sub>2</sub> groups. Thus, these are not applicable to all
fertilizer compositions for which slow release properties may be desirable.</p><p num="0011">Coating of fertilizer compositions with a biodegradable polymer was
described in U.S. Patent 5,176,734 and 5,206,341 and Japanese Patent
Application No. 146492/1991. These references disclose coating the
fertilizer composition with a biodegradable coating material in a single
layer. The single layer coating has difficulties controlling the dissolving-out
rate of fertilizer nutrients while maintaining biodegradability
simultaneously.</p><p num="0012">Japanese Patent Application No. 97561/1993 discloses a three
layer coating which was prepared by using one type of biodegradable film
and a water soluble resin. This coating also has difficulty in controlling both
the dissolving-out rate and the biodegradability at the same time. The
thickness of the coating material is disclosed as being from 500 to
2,000 µm. Such a coating material requires increased cost, thus making it
questionable for commercial use. </p><p num="0013">Canadian Patent Application No. 2,135,788 relates to coating
fertilizer compositions with at least two types of coating materials wherein
the two coating materials have different dissolving-out rates and moisture
permeability in a multi-layer structure.</p><p num="0014">U.S. Patent 5,538,531 also describes controlled release fertilizers
and a method for their production. These controlled release fertilizers have
a central mass of particulate fertilizer which contains at least one water
soluble plant nutrient surrounded by a plurality of coatings. The inner
coating comprises the reaction product of (A) an aromatic polyisocyanate
or derivatives thereof which contain about 1.5 to 3 NCO groups per
molecule and an NCO group content of 10 to 50% by weight, and (B) a
polyol having from 2 to 6 hydroxyl moieties and at least one alkyl moiety
containing from about 10 to 22 carbon atoms. Suitable polyols include
castor oil and hydrogenated castor oil. An outer coating is also necessary.
The outer coating consists essentially of an organic wax having a drop
melting point of between 50 and 120°C.</p><p num="0015">U.S. Patent 5,645,624 describes an encapsulated fertilizer using
first a layer of rapidly biodegradable aliphatic polyester and polyurethane
compound followed by a slowly biodegradable layer based on cellulose
derivatives and hydrocarbon compound to control the release rate of the
fertilizer.</p><p num="0016">U.S. Patent 5,704,962 describes compositions for treating granular
fertilizers to reduce dust and reduce caking of the fertilizers during storage.
These compositions comprise fatty monoamines, specifically fatty
secondary dialkylamines or mixtures thereof with fatty primary amines.</p><p num="0017">U.S. Patent 5,399,186 describes an apparatus and a process for
coating fertilizer particles with a polymer. This process requires a
multistage fluidized bed apparatus for the continuous coating of fertilizer
substrate particles. This process produces coated fertilizers having a
narrow coating thickness distribution and in which the substrate is
prevented from absorbing moisture prior to being coated. Suitable coating 
materials include, for example, polyvinylidene chloride, polyvinyl chloride,
low density polyethylene, epoxy resins, molten sulfur, wax, polyethylene,
ammonium nitrate, sulfur, liquefied potassium nitrate, and two or more
reactive materials that react to form a water barrier coating such as, for
example, a polyol and an isocyanate.</p><p num="0018">A machine system and a process for the production of attrition
resistant, controlled release fertilizers are described by U.S. Patents
5,374,292 and 5,547,486. This process comprises coating a particular
plant nutrient with a coating material which is chemically bonded to the
nutrient, to provide a uniform coating that can be varied in thickness to
effect various rates of release. In accordance with this process, particulate
plant nutrients are subjected to a pretreatment prior to reaction with a
coupling agent such as an organic diisocyanate. During the pretreatment,
heated plant nutrient granules are subjected to water containing a polyolcatalyst
and a water-soluble low molecular weight polyol, followed by
concurrent or sequential pretreatment with additional low molecular weight
or medium molecular weight polyester polyol. The plant nutrient granules
are pretreated with water in a low molecular weight polyol first, followed by
triethanolamine, and finally the polyisocyanate and the polyethylene
terephthalate polyester polyol. Pretreatment is believed to raise the
reactive functional groups of the particulate water-soluble plant nutrient at
the surface for enhanced molecular contact for rapid and more efficient
subsequent reaction with the coupling agent.</p><p num="0019">U.S. Patent 5,851,261 relates to a process for the production of
polyurea encapsulated fertilizer particles. This process comprises applying
an isocyanate-reactive component containing at least two amine groups to
the fertilizer particles, and applying a polyisocyanate to the amine coated
particles to form polyurea coated particles. The order of applying the
components may also be reversed, such that the polyisocyanate is applied
first, followed by the amine group containing component. </p><p num="0020">Advantages of the present invention include the fact that castor oil
is a natural product that does not present any harm to the environment,
encapsulants based on the combination of castor oil and polyethers result
in superior slow release properties when compared to castor oil alone as
described in, for example, U.S. Patent 5,538,531, or to castor oils which
are chemically modified with methylol groups containing resins which are
commercially available. The polyesterether polyols of the present invention
which comprise (1) blends of castor oil and polyether polyols, or (2)
reaction products of castor oil and polyether polyols can be adjusted in
reactivity using catalysts, and thus, facilitate even film formation on the
fertilizer surface prior to reaction with the isocyanate which results in
encapsulating layers of high homogeneity.</p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0021">This invention relates to a process for the production of
polyurethane encapsulated slow release fertilizer particles, and to the
polyurethane encapsulated slow release fertilizer particles produced by
this process.</p><p num="0022">This process comprises 1) applying a) an isocyanate-reactive
component comprising a polyesterether polyol to fertilizer particles to form
coated fertilizer particles, and 2) applying b) a polyisocyanate component
to the coated fertilizer particles from step 1) to form polyurethane
encapsulated fertilizer particles. These two steps are optionally repeated
(successively) as many times as necessary to form the desired thickness
of the polyurethane coating which encapsulates the fertilizer particles. The
encapsulated fertilizer compositions which are produced by this process
contain from about 2 to 20%, preferably 3 to 15%, most preferably 4 to
10% by weight of polyurethane, based on the total weight of the
encapsulated fertilizer composition, and wherein the polyurethane forming
the encapsulated fertilizer particles is characterized by a water absorption
of less than 1 %, preferably less than 0.5%, based on the total weight of
the polyurethane encapsulant. </p><p num="0023">In a less preferred embodiment of the present invention, this
process comprises 1) applying b) a polyisocyanate component to fertilizer
particles to form isocyanate coated fertilizer particles, and 2) applying a)
an isocyanate-reactive component comprising a polyesterether polyol to
fertilizer particles to the isocyanate coated fertilizer particles from step 1)
to form polyurethane encapsulated fertilizer particles. These two steps are
optionally repeated (successively) as many times as necessary to form the
desired thickness of the polyurethane coating which encapsulates the
fertilizer particles. The encapsulated fertilizer compositions which are
produced by this process contain from about 2 to 20%, preferably 3 to
15%, most preferably 4 to 10% by weight of polyurethane, based on the
total weight of the encapsulated fertilizer composition, and wherein the
polyurethane forming the encapsulated fertilizer particles is characterized
by a water absorption of less than 1 %, preferably less than 0.5%, based
on the total weight of the polyurethane encapsulant.</p><p num="0024">In an alternate embodiment, this process comprises 1) mixing a) an
isocyanate-reactive component comprising a polyesterether polyol and b)
a polyisocyanate either continuously or in a batch process in quantities
such that the ratio of isocyanate groups contained in component b) to
isocyanate-reactive groups contained in component a) is from about 0.8:1
to about 2.0:1, preferably about 0.9:1 to about 1.2:1 and most preferably
about 0.93:1 to about 1.1:1; followed by 2) applying the mixture to the
fertilizer particles; and, optionally, 3) repeating step 2) as often as
necessary to form the desired thickness of polyurethane coating
encapsulating the fertilizer particles. This embodiment is less preferred
due to the possibility of air entrapment during the mixing stage which can
result in bubbles forming in the coating leading to a less-continuous film on
the encapsulated particle. Another problem is that the thickness of the
coating applied on the fertilizer particles may increase correspondingly as
the viscosity of the reacting mixture does. Thus, the particles coated using
the last portion of the mixture have a thicker coating than particles coated 
using the first portion of the mixture. However, some of these problems
can be overcome by continuous mixing and application of the
polyisocyanate and the polyisocyanate-reactive component.</p><p num="0025">The present invention also relates to encapsulated fertilizer
compositions produced by these processes.</p><p num="0026">In accordance with the present invention, suitable polyesterether
polyols comprise (i) 20 to 90% by weight, preferably 40 to 80% by weight,
based on 100% by weight of a)(i) and a)(ii), of castor oil having an OH
number of from 160 to 170, a viscosity of 500 to 900 mPa·s at 25°C, and a
water content of less than 0.5% by weight, based on the total weight of
castor oil, and (ii) 10 to 80% by weight, preferably 20 to 60% by weight,
based on 100% by weight of a)(i) and a)(ii), of a polyether polyol having an
OH number of from 28 to 700, preferably from 112 to 500, a functionality of
from 3 to 8, preferably from 4 to 7, a molecular weight of from about 240 to
about 6,000, preferably from 400 to 2,000, and a viscosity of from 50 to
35,000, preferably from 500 to 25,000 mPa·s at 25°C, and said polyether
polyol being prepared by reacting at least one suitable initiator with one or
more alkylene oxides wherein at least 70%, preferably at least 80%, and
more preferably 100% by weight of the alkylene oxides comprises
propylene oxide, based on 100% by weight of the alkylene oxides. The
polyesterether polyols suitable for the present invention comprise either
blends of castor oil and one or more polyether polyols, or the reaction
products of castor oil and one or more polyether polyols.</p><heading><u style="single">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0027">Suitable polyisocyanates which may be used in forming the
isocyanate compositions in accordance with the present invention include
monomeric diisocyanates, NCO prepolymers, and preferably liquid
polyisocyanates and polyisocyanate adducts. Suitable monomeric
diisocyanates may be represented by the formula R(NCO)<sub>2</sub> in which R
represents an organic group obtained by removing the isocyanate groups
from an organic diisocyanate having a molecular weight of about 56 to 
1,000, preferably about 84 to 400. Diisocyanates preferred for the process
according to the invention are those represented by the above formula in
which R represents a divalent aliphatic, hydrocarbon group having 4 to 12
carbon atoms, a divalent cyclo-aliphatic hydrocarbon group having 6 to 13
carbon atoms, a divalent araliphatic hydrocarbon group having 7 to 20
carbon atoms or a divalent aromatic hydrocarbon group having 6 to 18
carbon atoms. Preferred monomeric diisocyanates are those wherein R
represents an aromatic hydrocarbon group.</p><p num="0028">Examples of the suitable organic diisocyanates include 1,4-tetramethylene
diisocyanate, 1,6-hexamethylene diisocyanate, 2,2,4-trimethyl-1,6-hexamethylene
diisocyanate, 1,12-dodecamethylene
diisocyanate, cyclohexane-1,3- and -1,4-diisocyanate, 1-isocyanato-2-isocyanatomethyl
cyclopentane, 1 -isocyanato-3-isocyanatomethyl-3,5,5-trimethyl-cyclohexane
(isophorone diisocyanate or IPDI), bis(4-isocyanatocyclohexyl)
methane, 2,4'-dicyclohexylmethane diisocyanate, 1,3- and
1,4-bis(isocyanatomethyl) cyclohexane, bis(4-isocyanato-3-methyl-cyclohexyl)
methane, a,a,a',a'-tetramethyl-1,3- and/or -1,4-xylylene
diisocyanate, 1 -isocyanato-1-methyl-4(3)-isocyanatomethyl cyclohexane,
2,4- and/or 2,6-hexahydrotoluene diisocyanate, 1,3- and/or 1,4-phenylene
diisocyanate, 2,4- and/or 2,6-toluene diisocyanate, 2,4'- and/or 4,4'-diphenylmethane
diisocyanate, 1,5-diisocyanato naphthalene and mixtures
thereof. Aromatic polyisocyanates containing 3 or more isocyanate groups
such as 4,4',4"-triphenylmethane triisocyanate and polymethylene
poly(phenylisocyanates) obtained by phosgenating aniline/formaldehyde
condensates may also be used.</p><p num="0029">In accordance with the present invention, at least a portion of the
polyisocyanate component may be present in the form of an NCO
prepolymer or a polyisocyanate adduct, preferably a polyisocyanate
adduct. Suitable polyisocyanate adducts are those containing
isocyanurate, uretdione, biuret, urethane, allophanate, carbodiimide and/or
oxadiazinetrione groups. The polyisocyanate adducts have an average 
functionality of 2.0 to 4 and an NCO content of 5 to 30% by weight.
Suitable adducts/prepolymers include the following type of components:
<sl><li>1) Isocyanurate group-containing polyisocyanates which may
be prepared as set forth in DE-PS 2,616,416, EP-OS 3,765, EP-OS
10,589, EP-OS 47,452, US-PS 4,288,586 and US-PS 4,324,879. The
isocyanato-isocyanurates generally have an average NCO functionality of
3 to 4.0, preferably of from 3.2 to 3.6, and an NCO content of 5 to 30%,
preferably 10 to 25% and most preferably 15 to 25% by weight.</li><li>2) Uretdione diisocyanates which may be prepared by
oligomerizing a portion of the isocyanate groups of a diisocyanate in the
presence of a, i.e., trialkyl phosphine catalyst and which may be used in
admixture with other aromatic, aliphatic and/or cycloaliphatic
polyisocyanates, particularly the isocyanurate group-containing
polyisocyanates set forth under (1) above.</li><li>3) Biuret group-containing polyisocyanates which may be
prepared according to the processes disclosed in U.S. Patents 3,124,605;
3,358,010; 3,644,490; 3,862,973; 3,906,126; 3,903,127; 4,051,165;
4,147,714; or 4,220,749 by using co-reactants such as water, tertiary
alcohols, primary and secondary monoamines, and primary and/or
secondary diamines. These polyisocyanates preferably have an NCO
content of 18 to 22% by weight and an average NCO functionality of 3 to
3.5.</li><li>4) Urethane group-containing polyisocyanates which may be
prepared in accordance with the process disclosed in U.S. Patent
3,183,112 by reacting excess quantities of polyisocyanates, preferably
diisocyanates, with low molecular weight glycols and polyols having
molecular weights of less than 400, such as tripropylene glycol, trimethylol
propane, glycerine, 1,2-dihydroxy propane and mixtures thereof. The
urethane group-containing polyisocyanates have a most preferred NCO
content of 12 to 20% by weight and an (average) NCO functionality of 2.5
to 3. </li><li>5) Allophanate group-containing polyisocyanates which may be
prepared according to the processes disclosed in U.S. Patents 3,769,318,
4,160,080 and 4,177,342. The allophanate group-containing
polyisocyanates have a most preferred NCO content of 12 to 28% by
weight and an (average) NCO functionality of 2 to 4.</li><li>6) Isocyanurate and allophanate group-containing
polyisocyanates which may be prepared in accordance with the processes
set forth in U.S. Patents 5,124,427, 5,208,334 and 5,235,018; the
disclosures of which are herein incorporated by reference.</li><li>7) Carbodiimide group-containing polyisocyanates which may
be prepared by oligomerizing di- or polyisocyanates in the presence of
known carbodiimidization catalysts as described in DE-PS 1,092,007,
US-PS 3,152,162 and DE-OS 2,504,400, 2,537,685 and 2,552,350.</li></sl></p><p num="0030">Preferred polyisocyanate adducts are the polyisocyanates
containing urethane groups, isocyanurate groups, biuret groups or
mixtures of isocyanurate and allophanate groups.</p><p num="0031">The NCO prepolymers, which may also be used as the
polyisocyanate component in accordance with the present invention, are
prepared from the previously described polyisocyanates or polyisocyanate
adducts, preferably monomeric diisocyanates, and organic compounds
containing at least two isocyanate-reactive groups, preferably at least two
hydroxy groups. These organic compounds include high molecular weight
compounds having molecular weights of 500 to about 5,000, preferably
800 to about 3,000, and optionally low molecular weight compounds with
molecular weights below 400. The molecular weights are number average
molecular weights (M<sub>n</sub>) and are determined by end group analysis (OH
number). Products obtained by reacting polyisocyanates exclusively with
low molecular weight compounds are polyisocyanate adducts containing
urethane groups and are not considered to be NCO prepolymers.</p><p num="0032">It is preferred that the polyisocyanates of the present invention are
aromatic polyisocyanates. Some examples of suitable aromatic polyisocyanates 
are 1,3- and/or 1,4-phenylene diisocyanate, 2,4- and/or 2,6-toluene
diisocyanate, 2,4'- and/or 4,4'-diphenylmethane diisocyanate, 1,5-diisocyanato
naphthalene and mixtures thereof.</p><p num="0033">It is more preferred that the polyisocyanates for the presently
claimed invention are polymethylene poly(phenylisocyanate) compositions
having a functionality of from about 2.1 to about 3.5, preferably 2.2 to 3.2
and most preferably of 2.3 to 2.8, and an NCO group content of about 26%
to about 33.4%, preferably about 30.5% to about 33%, and a monomeric
diisocyanate content of from about 20% to about 90% by weight,
preferably from about 40% to about 80%, wherein the content of
monomeric diisocyanate comprises up to about 5% by weight of the 2,2'-isomer,
from about 1 to about 25% by weight of the 2,4'-isomer, and from
about 25 to about 70% by weight of the 4,4'-isomer, based on the entire
weight of the isocyanate composition. The polymeric MDI content of these
isocyanates varies from about 10 to about 80% by weight, preferably from
about 20% to about 60% by weight.</p><p num="0034">"Polymeric MDI" as used herein, refers to polymethylene
poly(phenyl-isocyanate) which in addition to monomeric diisocyanate (i.e.,
two-ring compounds) contains three-ring and higher ring containing
products.</p><p num="0035">Most preferred polyisocyanates include, for example,
polymethylene poly(phenylisocyanate) compositions having an average
functionality of from about 2.2 to about 3.2, preferably about 2.3 to about
2.8, an NCO group content of about 30 to 33% by weight, and a monomer
content of from about 40 to 80% by weight, wherein the content of
monomer comprises no more than about 2% by weight of the 2,2'-isomer,
from about 2 to about 25% by weight of the 2,4'-isomer and from about 35
to about 60% by weight of the 4,4'-isomer, based on the entire weight of
the composition. This isocyanate composition comprises from about 20 to
about 60% by weight of polymeric MDI. </p><p num="0036">Also suitable are mixtures of polyisocyanate compositions as
described above with adducts of MDI including, for example, allophanates
of MDI as described in, for example, U.S. Patents 5,319,053, 5,319,054
and 5,440,003, the disclosures of which are herein incorporated by
reference; urethanes of MDI as described in, for example, U.S. Patents
5,462,766 and 5,558,917, the disclosures of which are herein incorporated
by reference; and carbodiimides of MDI as described in, for example, U.S.
Patents 2,853,473, 2,941,966, 3,152,162, 4,088,665, 4,294,719 and
4,244,855, the disclosures of which are herein incorporated by reference.</p><p num="0037">Isocyanate prepolymers including, for example, those based on
diphenylmethane diisocyanate which may be based on either polyethers or
polyesters are suitable for the present invention. Although these are
typically less preferred isocyanates, these are suitable for fertilizer
encapsulation processes, as long as they are liquid and can be applied
according to the invention. These compounds include, for example, an
isocyanate-terminated prepolymer having an NCO content of about 10%, a
functionality of about 2 and a viscosity of about 2,500 mPa·s at 25°C. Such
prepolymers can be prepared by, for example, reacting 2,4'-isomer rich
MDI with a difunctional polyether (prepared from propylene glycol and
propylene oxide).</p><p num="0038">A most preferred polyisocyanate comprises a polymethylene poly(phenylisocyanate)
having an NCO content of about 32.4%, a functionality
of about 2.5, a viscosity of about 57 mPa·s at 25°C, and having a
monomer content of about 61% by weight. Of the 61% monomer, about
18.0% by weight is the 2,4'-isomer of MDI, about 2% by weight is the 2,2'-isomer
of MDI and about 41% is the 4,4'-isomer of MDI.</p><p num="0039">Another most preferred polyisocyanate component comprises a
polymethylene poly(phenylisocyanate) having an NCO content of about
32.3%, a functionality of about 2.8, a viscosity of about 160 mPa·s at 25°C,
and having a monomer content of about 45% by weight. Of the 45% by 
weight monomer, about 44% is the 4,4'-isomer of MDI and about 1% by
weight is the 2,4'-isomer of MDI.</p><p num="0040">Diphenylmethane diisocyanate which is rich in the 2,4'-isomer is
another most preferred isocyanate for the present invention. Specifically,
diphenylmethane diisocyanate having an isomer distribution comprising
about 44% by weight of the 4,4'-isomer, about 54% by weight of the 2,4'-isomer
and about 2% by weight of the 2,2'-isomer. This diisocyanate has
an NCO content of about 33.6%, a functionality of about 2.0 and a
viscosity of less than about 25 mPa·s at 25°C.</p><p num="0041">Suitable polyesterether polyols to be used in accordance with the
present invention include, for example, those polyesterether polyols which
are either a blend of (i) castor oil and (ii) a polyether polyol, or those
polyesterether polyols which are the reaction product of (i) castor oil and
(ii) a polyether polyol.</p><p num="0042">In accordance with the present invention, suitable polyesterether
polyols comprise (i) 20 to 90% by weight, preferably 40 to 80% by weight,
based on 100% by weight of components (i) and (ii), of castor oil having an
OH number of 160 to 170, a viscosity of 500 to 900 mPa·s at 25°C, and a
water content of less than 0.5% by weight, based on the total weight of
castor oil, and (ii) 10 to 80% by weight, preferably 20 to 60% by weight,
based on 100% by weight of components (i) and (ii), of a polyether polyol
having an OH number of from 28 to 700, preferably from 112 to 500, a
functionality of from 3 to 8, preferably from 4 to 7, a molecular weight of
from about 240 to about 6,000, preferably from about 400 to about 2,000,
and a viscosity of from 50 to 35,000 mPa·s, preferably from 500 to 25,000
mPa·s, at 25°C. These polyesterether polyols can either be blends of (i)
castor oil and (ii) one or more polyether polyols, or the reaction product of
(i) castor oil and (ii) one or more polyether polyols.</p><p num="0043">Some examples of suitable polyether polyols include those started
from initiators such as, for example, glycerol, ethanolamine, ethylene
diamine, trimethylol propane, pentaerythritol, sucrose, L-arabinose, Dribose, 
2-deoxy-D-ribose, D-xylose and various other pentoses, D-glycose,
D-fructose, D-mannose, D-galactose and various other hexoses, Dsedoheptulose
and other heptoses, maltose, lactose, raffinose (a
trisaccharide), etc., and mixtures thereof, such that the above mentioned
functionality requirements are satisfied. Preferred initiators include
compounds such as glycerol, ethylene diamine, trimethylol propane,
pentaerythritol, sucrose, and various other sugars, etc. Particularly
preferred initiators include compounds such as, for example, sucrose,
sorbitol, pentaerythritol, etc. Initiators are reacted with one or more
alkylene oxide to form the desired polyether polyol. It is essential that
propylene oxide be present in an amount such that it is at least about 70%
by weight of the total weight of alkylene oxides. The balance can be, for
example, ethylene oxide, butylene oxide, tetrahydrofuran, styrene oxide,
etc. It is, however, preferred that propylene oxide be present in an amount
such that there is at least 80% by weight of propylene oxide, based on the
total weight of the alkylene oxides. Most preferably 100% by weight of the
alkylene oxides are propylene oxide.</p> <p num="0044">Castor oil by itself has a limited number of OH groups representing
co-reactants for the polyisocyanate. It is therefore preferred to prepare
either blends or reaction products of castor oil with one or more polyether
polyols which are multi-functional in terms of the number of OH groups
available, such as, for example, sugar polyols. Polyols which contain high
amounts of propylene oxide vs. ethylene oxide are preferred.</p><p num="0045">It is also possible to include other additives in either the isocyanate-reactive
component or the polyisocyanate component prior to applying the
component to the fertilizer particles. Possible additives include, for
example, catalysts, preferably ones that are not toxic, flow aids,
surfactants, defoamers and other additives known to those skilled in the
art. Any additive which aids the formation of the polyurethane coating
which encapsulates the fertilizer particles may be included in one or both
of these components. </p><p num="0046">Suitable fertilizer particles for the present encapsulation process
include any of the known chemical fertilizers. Some examples are
ammonium sulfate, ammonium nitrate, urea, guanidine, melamine, sodium
nitrate, ammonia phosphate, potassium phosphate, and combinations
thereof. These fertilizer particles are obviously water soluble.</p><p num="0047">As used herein, the phrase "fertilizer particles" refers to any of the
commercially available particulate fertilizers which are produced and
marketed in various particle types. Some examples include granular,
pelletized, dusts, pilled and prilled fertilizers.</p><p num="0048">An attrition resistant, controlled release particulate fertilizer may be
prepared by applying the isocyanate-reactive component and the
polyisocyanate to fertilizer particles at ambient temperature, preferably,
however, preheated to a temperature of between about 60 and 105°C. The
fertilizer particles are kept in continuous low shear, low impact, motion
relative to each other by a mixing apparatus. Examples of suitable mixing
apparatus include fluid bed, rotating drum, pan pelletizer, and any others
which can provide a continuous, low shear motion of the fertilizer particles.</p> <p num="0049">More specifically, attrition resistant, controlled release fertilizers
may be produced by (i) providing a quantity of fertilizer particles, (ii)
agitating the fertilizer particles such that a gentle mixing thereof is
maintained, (iii) adding to the agitated fertilizer particles an isocyanate-reactive
component comprising one or more polyesterether polyols as
described above, (iv) after the isocyanate-reactive component has spread
uniformly, adding to the agitated fertilizer particles a polyisocyanate
component, in an amount such that the ratio of NCO groups to hydroxyl
groups is from about 2.0 to about 0.8, more preferably 1.2 to 0.9, an most
preferably 1.1 to 0.93, (v) allowing the polyisocyanate and the isocyanate-reactive
materials to react, thus forming a solidified polyurethane coating
on the fertilizer particles, and (vi) cooling the coated fertilizer particles to
about or slightly above room temperature, with continuous agitation. If 
multiple coatings are desired to achieve slower release of the fertilizer,
steps (ii) through (v) can be repeated several times.</p> <p num="0050">In accordance with the present invention, it is preferred that the
fertilizer particles contain less than 10% by weight of reactive functional
groups, and it is particularly preferred that the fertilizer particles are free of
reactive functional groups.</p> <p num="0051">Metering of the streams of the polyisocyanate component and the
isocyanate-reactive component onto the fertilizer particles can be
continuous. It may be, however, advantageously discontinuous, when only
a portion of the total amount of each of the two reactants is added and
allowed to react prior to applying additional portions.</p><p num="0052">Successful application of the coatings of the present invention to
particulate fertilizers depends on factors such as i) correct metering of the
co-reactants, ii) fairly precise temperature control, iii) continuous
movement of fertilizer particles during application of the optionally
successive urethane coatings, and iv) followed by cooling to avoid
agglomeration of the fertilizer particles.</p><p num="0053">In practicing the process of the present invention, the polyesterether
polyol component is preferably applied to the fertilizer particles or granules
prior to the addition of the first isocyanate component.</p><p num="0054">The following examples further illustrate details for the process of
the present invention, and the preparation the compositions of this
invention. The invention, which is set forth in the foregoing disclosure, is
not to be limited either in spirit or scope by these examples. Those skilled
in the art will readily understand that known variations of the conditions
and processes of the following preparative procedures can be used to
prepare these compositions. Unless otherwise noted, all temperatures are
degrees Celsius and all parts and percentages are parts by weight and
percentages by weight, respectively. </p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLES</u></heading><p num="0055">The following components were used in the examples.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="24"><dt><u style="single">Urea Fertilizer Pellets</u>:</dt><dd>urea 98%, pearls, commercially available from
Acros Organies</dd></dl><dl compact="compact" tsize="9"><dt><u style="single">Polyol A</u>:</dt><dd>a blend of two polyether polyols wherein the blend is
characterized by an average functionality of 3.85, an average
OH number of 197.5, an average molecular weight of 1,095,
and a viscosity of 560 mPa·s at 25°C; the blend comprises (i)
75% by weight of a triethanol amine initiated propylene oxide
(100% by wt.) polyether polyol having a functionality of 3, an
OH number of 150, a molecular weight of about 1100, and a
viscosity of about 250 mPa·s at 25°C, and (ii) 25% by weight
of a sucrose/propylene glycol/water initiated propylene oxide
(100% by weight) polyether polyol having a functionality of
about 6.2, an OH number of 340, a molecular weight of
about 1000, and a viscosity of about 9,000 mPa·s at 25°C.
(comparison)</dd><dt><u style="single">Polyol B</u>:</dt><dd>a hydrophobic polyesterether polyol in accordance with the
present invention, being characterized by a functionality of
about 3.36, an OH number of about 199, a molecular weight
of about 945, and a viscosity of about 800 mPa·s at 25°C,
and being prepared by blending (i) 80% by weight of castor
oil with (ii) 20% by weight of a sucrose/propylene
glycol/water initiated propylene oxide (100% by weight)
polyether polyol having a functionality of about 6.2, an OH
number of 340, a molecular weight of about 1000, and a
viscosity of about 9,000 mPa·s at 25°C.</dd><dt><u style="single">Polyol C</u>:</dt><dd>a polyesterether polyol characterized by a functionality of
about 3.4, an OH number of about 165, a molecular weight
of about 1,153, and a viscosity of about 3,500 mPa·s at
25°C, and being prepared by reacting (i) 80% by weight of 
castor oil, with (ii) 20% by weight of a cyclohexanone-formaldehyde
resin having an OH number of between 270
and 330, and a melting point of about 110-120°C,
commercially available from Lawter International as
polyketone aldehyde resin Krumbhaar K-1717 or Creanovn
(formerly Huels America) as ketone aldehyde resin BL1201.
(comparison)</dd><dt><u style="single">Polyol D</u>:</dt><dd>DB castor oil having an OH number of about 164, a
molecular weight of about 928, an equivalent weight of about
342, a functionality of about 2.71 and a viscosity of about
670 mPa·s at 25°C; commercially available from CasChem,
Inc.</dd></dl><dl compact="compact" tsize="13"><dt><u style="single">Isocyanate A</u>:</dt><dd>a polymethylene poly(phenylisocyanate) containing
about 66% diphenylmethane diisocyanate monomers
having a 2,4'-isomer content of about 19% by weight,
based on the total weight of the polymethylene
poly(phenylisocyanate), and 34% of higher
functionality homologs, and having an overall
isocyanate group content of about 32.3% and a
functionality of about 2.3.</dd><dt><u style="single">Catalyst A</u>:</dt><dd>a dibutyltin dilaurate catalyst; commercially available
from Air Products and Chemicals Inc. as Dabco T-12</dd></dl></p><p num="0056">TABLE 1 below sets forth the different polyols used in the examples
in terms of the functionality, OH number, MW and % by weight propylene
oxide.</p><p num="0057"><u style="single">Encapsulation of fertilizer pellets</u>: In each of the examples, the
stated amount of the respective polyol component (see TABLE 2 below)
was added to 100 g of urea fertilizer pellets in an 8 ounce bottle. The bottle
was shaken until the polyol component was coated on the fertilizer pellets
(about 2 to 3 minutes). Isocyanate A in the relevant amount was added to
the polyol coated pellets, and the bottle was shaken until the isocyanate 
coated the polyol-coated fertilizer pellets (about 2-3 minutes). This mixture
was poured into an aluminum pan and placed into a 100°C oven (the
pellets were mixed 2 to 3 times while in the oven to prevent the pellets
from sticking together) until they were dry and no longer stuck together
(about 10 minutes). This procedure of coating and heating the pellets was
repeated two more times using the same amounts of polyol and
isocyanate. After the third coating, the pellets were left in the oven for 1
hour. Theoretically, this would result in about 6.24% polyurethane
encapsulation, based on the total weight of the encapsulated fertilizer
particles. However, the actual amount of polyurethane encapsulation was
about 5.1 to 5.2% due to the loss of coating on the walls of the bottle.</p><heading><u style="single">Test procedure for slow release properties</u>:</heading><p num="0058">After one week, the encapsulated fertilizer granules from each the
examples were compared to unmodified fertilizer pellets using the
following test procedure: 20 g of the fertilizer pellets were combined with
80 g of water, and stored at room temperature in a closed glass jar for 8
hrs. After this time, the solids were filtered off and the amount of solids
dissolved in the aqueous phase was determined after evaporation of the
water for 4 hrs in a 100°C oven. The results are set forth in TABLE 2
below. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Characteristics of Polyols A, B, C and D</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">Polyol A</entry><entry align="left">Polyol B</entry><entry align="left">Polyol C</entry><entry align="left">Polyol D</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Average Functionality</entry><entry align="left">3.85</entry><entry align="left">3.36</entry><entry align="left">3.4</entry><entry align="left">2.71</entry></row><row><entry align="left">OH Number</entry><entry align="left">197.5</entry><entry align="left">199</entry><entry align="left">165</entry><entry align="left">164</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Molecular Weight</entry><entry align="left">1,095</entry><entry align="left">945</entry><entry align="left">1,153</entry><entry align="left">928</entry></row><row><entry align="left">% by Wt. Propylene Oxide</entry><entry align="left">100</entry><entry align="left">100</entry><entry align="left">0</entry><entry align="left">0</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity mPa·s at 25°C</entry><entry align="left">560</entry><entry align="left">800</entry><entry align="left">3,500</entry><entry align="left">670</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><img id="img-00220001" orientation="unknown" wi="86" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00220001.tif" inline="no" he="218"/></p><p num="0059">Additional polyesterether polyols were prepared by blending castor
oil and Polyether Polyol 1 in relative amounts as shown in Table 3 below.
The process used was essentially as described hereinabove with respect
to Polyol B.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="19"><dt><u style="single">Polyether Polyol 1</u>:</dt><dd>a sucrose/propylene glycol/water initiated
polypropylene oxide (100% by wt.) polyether polyol
having a functionality of about 6.2, an OH number of
about 340, a molecular weight of about 1,000 and a
viscosity of about 9,000 mPa·s at 25°C.</dd></dl><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry nameend="4" namest="1">Castor Oil/Polyether Polyol Blends according to the Invention</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Example</entry><entry align="left">Castor Oil (Wt. in grams)</entry><entry align="left">Polyether Polyol 1 (Wt. in grams)</entry><entry align="left">Equivalent Weight of Blend</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyesterether Polyol Blend E</entry><entry align="left">90</entry><entry align="left">10</entry><entry align="center">308.9</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyesterether Polyol Blend F</entry><entry align="left">70</entry><entry align="left">30</entry><entry align="center">258.7</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyesterether Polyol Blend G</entry><entry align="left">60</entry><entry align="left">40</entry><entry align="center">239.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polyesterether Polyol Blend H</entry><entry align="left">50</entry><entry align="left">50</entry><entry align="center">222.6</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0060">The encapsulation of fertilizer pellets was performed as described
in Examples 1-4 above. The test procedure for slow release properties of
the encapsulated fertilizer particles in Examples 7-9 below essentially
corresponded to that described above. <img id="img-00240001" orientation="unknown" wi="88" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00240001.tif" inline="no" he="233"/></p><p num="0061">The following components were used to prepare polyesterether
polyols in accordance with the present invention. In particular, the
resultant polyesterether polyols comprised the reaction products of
castor oil and polyether polyols.
<dl compact="compact" tsize="19"><dt><u style="single">Polyether Polyol 2</u>:</dt><dd>a sorbitol initiated polypropylene oxide (100% by
wt.) polyether polyol having a functionality of about
6, an OH number of about 450, a molecular weight
of about 750 and a viscosity of about 15,000
mPa·s at 25°C.</dd><dt><u style="single">Polyether Polyol 3</u>:</dt><dd>a pentaerythritol initiated polypropylene oxide
(100% by wt.) polyether polyol having a
functionality of about 4, an OH number of about
550, a molecular weight of about 410, and a
viscosity of about 4,460 mPa·s at 25°C.</dd><dt><u style="single">Polyether Polyol 4</u>:</dt><dd>a trimethylolpropane initiated polypropylene oxide
(100% by wt.) polyether polyol having a
functionality of about 3, an OH number of about
370, a molecular weight of about 450 and a
viscosity of about 650 mPa·s at 25°C.</dd></dl></p><p num="0062">Polyesterether polyols comprising the reaction product of a
polyether polyol (i.e. Polyether Polyols 1-4 above) and castor oil were
prepared as follows:</p><p num="0063">To a two (2) liter flask fitted with a stirrer and a heating mantle,
were added 800 grams of Castor Oil, 200 grams of the polyether
polyol, and 0.025 grams of tetrabutyltitanate. The mixture was heated
to 200°C and held at this temperature for 5 hours. Details relative to the
composition and characteristics of the resultant transesterified castor
oil products, i.e. polyesterether polyols, are set forth in Table 5 below. <img id="img-00260001" orientation="unknown" wi="69" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00260001.tif" inline="no" he="222"/></p><p num="0064">A Gel Permeation Chromotography (GPC) was taken of the mixture
of 800 grams of Castor Oil and 200 grams of Polyether Polyol 4 both
before and after thermal treatment. A comparison of these GPC's shows a
broader molecular weight distribution after the thermal treatment which
indicates that transesterification occurred. <img id="img-00280001" orientation="unknown" wi="99" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00280001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/></p><p num="0065">Although the invention has been described in detail in the foregoing
for the purpose of illustration, it is to be understood that such detail is
solely for that purpose and that variations can be made therein by those
skilled in the art without departing from the spirit and scope of the
invention except as it may be limited by the claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process for producing polyurethane encapsulated, slow
release fertilizer particles comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>1) applying
   a) an isocyanate-reactive component comprising a
polyesterether polyol to fertilizer particles to form
coated fertilizer particles, wherein said polyesterether
polyol comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) 20 to 90% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of a)(i) and a)(ii), of castor oil having an OH
number of about 160 to about 170, a viscosity
of about 500 to about 900 mPa·s, and a water
content of less than 0.5% by weight, based on
the total weight of castor oil,
and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) 10 to 80% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of a)(i) and a)(ii), of a polyether polyol having
an OH number of from 28 to 700, a functionality
of from 3 to 8, a molecular weight of from about
240 to about 6,000 and a viscosity of from 50 to
35,000 mPa·s at 25°C, said polyether polyol
being prepared by reacting at least one suitable
initiator compound with one or more alkylene
oxides wherein the alkylene oxide comprise at
least 70% by weight of propylene oxide, based
on the 100% by weight of the alkylene oxides;</claim-text></claim-text>
and</claim-text><claim-text>2) applying
   b) a polyisocyanate component onto the coated fertilizer
particles from step 1) to form polyurethane
encapsulated fertilizer particles,</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein these two steps are optionally repeated (successively) as many
times as necessary, with the polyurethane encapsulated fertilizer particles
from step 2) being substituted for the fertilizer particles in step 1), so as to
form polyurethane encapsulated fertilizer particles containing from about 2
to about 20% by weight of polyurethane, based on the total weight of the
encapsulated fertilizer composition, wherein the polyurethane forming the
encapsulated fertilizer particles is characterized by a water absorption of
less than 1 % by weight, based on the total weight of the polyurethane
encapsulant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
comprises a sugar initiated polyol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has an OH number of from 112 to 500.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has a functionality of from 4 to 7.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has a molecular weight of from 400 to 2,000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has a viscosity of from 500 to 25,000 mPa·s at 25°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol is
prepared by reacting a suitable initiator compound with one or more
alkylene oxides wherein the alkylene oxide comprises at least 80% by
weight of propylene oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The process of Claim 7, wherein the alkylene oxide
comprises at least 90% by weight of propylene oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol is
prepared by reacting a suitable initiator compound with an alkylene oxide,
said initiator compound being selected from the group consisting of
glycerol, trimethylolpropane, ethylenediamine, ethanolamine,
pentaerythritol, sucrose and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein said polyesterether polyol
comprises a)(i) from 40 to 80% by weight of castor oil, and a)(ii) from 20 to
60% by weight of a polyether polyol having an OH number of from 112 to
500, a functionality of from 4 to 7, a molecular weight of from 400 to 2,000,
and a viscosity of from 500 to 25,000 mPa·s at 25°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein a) said polyesterether
polyol comprises the reaction product of (i) said castor oil, and (ii) said
polyether polyol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein a) said polyesterether
polyol comprises a blend of (i) said castor oil, and (ii) said polyether polyol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The process of Claim 10, wherein the formed polyurethane
encapsulated fertilizer particles contain from about 3 to about 15% by
weight of polyurethane, based on the total weight of the encapsulated
fertilizer composition, and wherein the polyurethane forming the
encapsulated fertilizer particles is characterized by a water absorption of
less than 0.5% by weight, based on the total weight of the polyurethane
encapsulant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The process of Claim 13, wherein the formed polyurethane
encapsulated fertilizer particles contain from about 4 to about 10% by
weight of polyurethane, based on the total weight of the encapsulated
fertilizer composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The process of Claim 1, wherein the fertilizer particles
contain less than 10% by weight of reactive functional groups.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A process for producing polyurethane encapsulated, slow
release fertilizer particles comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>1) applying
   a) a polyisocyanate component to fertilizer particles to
form polyisocyanate coated fertilizer particles,
and</claim-text><claim-text>2) applying
   b) an isocyanate-reactive component comprising a
polyesterether polyol onto the polyisocyanate coated
fertilizer particles from step 1) to form polyurethane
encapsulated fertilizer particles, wherein said
polyesterether polyol comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) 20 to 90% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of a)(i) and a)(ii), of castor oil having an OH
number of about 160 to about 170, a viscosity
of about 500 to about 900 mPa·s, and a water
content of less than 0.5% by weight, based on
the total weight of castor oil,
and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) 10 to 80% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of a)(i) and a)(ii), of a polyether polyol having
an OH number of from 28 to 700, a functionality
of from 3 to 8, a molecular weight of from about
240 to about 6,000 and a viscosity of from 50 to
35,000 mPa·s at 25°C, said polyether polyol
being prepared by reacting at least one suitable
initiator compound with one or more alkylene
oxides wherein the alkylene oxide comprise at
least 70% by weight of propylene oxide, based
on the 100% by weight of the alkylene oxides;</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim-text>
wherein these two steps are optionally repeated (successively) as many
times as necessary, with the polyurethane encapsulated fertilizer particles
from step 2) being substituted for the fertilizer particles in step 1), so as to
form polyurethane encapsulated fertilizer particles containing from about 2
to about 20% by weight of polyurethane, based on the total weight of the
encapsulated fertilizer composition, wherein the polyurethane forming the
encapsulated fertilizer particles is characterized by a water absorption of
less than 1% by weight, based on the total weight of the polyurethane
encapsulant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
comprises a sugar initiated polyol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has an OH number of from 112 to 500.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has a functionality of from 4 to 7.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has a molecular weight of from 400 to 2,000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has a viscosity of from 500 to 25,000 mPa·s at 25°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
is prepared by reacting a suitable initiator compound with one or more
alkylene oxides wherein the alkylene oxide comprises at least 80% by
weight of propylene oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>The process of Claim 22, wherein the alkylene oxide
comprises at least 90% by weight of propylene oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
is prepared by reacting a suitable initiator compound with an alkylene
oxide, said initiator compound being selected from the group consisting of
glycerol, trimethylolpropane, ethylenediamine, ethanolamine,
pentaerythritol, sucrose and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="25"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16, wherein said polyesterether polyol
comprises a)(i)I from 40 to 80% by weight of castor oil, and a)(ii) from 20
to 60% by weight of a polyether polyol having an OH number of from 112
to 500, a functionality of from 4 to 7, a molecular weight of from 400 to
2,000, and a viscosity of from 500 to 25,000 mPa·s at 25°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="26"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16, wherein a) said polyesterether
polyol comprises the reaction product of (i) said castor oil, and (ii) said
polyether polyol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="27"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16, wherein a) said polyesterether
polyol comprises a blend of (i) said castor oil, and (ii) said polyether polyol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="28"><claim-text>The process of Claim 25, wherein the formed polyurethane
encapsulated fertilizer particles contain from about 3 to about 15% by
weight of polyurethane, based on the total weight of the encapsulated
fertilizer composition, and wherein the polyurethane forming the
encapsulated fertilizer particles is characterized by a water absorption of
less than 0.5% by weight, based on the total weight of the polyurethane
encapsulant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="29"><claim-text>The process of Claim 28, wherein the formed polyurethane
encapsulated fertilizer particles contain from about 4 to about 10% by
weight of polyurethane, based on the total weight of the encapsulated
fertilizer composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="30"><claim-text>The process of Claim 16, wherein the fertilizer particles
contain less than 10% by weight of reactive functional groups.</claim-text></claim><claim num="31"><claim-text>A process for producing polyurethane encapsulated, slow
release fertilizer particles comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>1) mixing
   a) an isocyanate-reactive component comprising a
polyesterether polyol which comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(i) 20 to 90% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of a)(i) and a)(ii), of castor oil having an OH
number of about 160 to about 170, a viscosity
of about 500 to about 900 mPa·s at 25°C, and
a water content of less than 0.5% by weight,
based on the total weight of castor oil,
and</claim-text><claim-text>(ii) 10 to 80% by weight, based on 100% by weight
of a)(i) and a)(ii), of a polyether polyol having
an OH number of from 28 to 700, a functionality
of from 3 to 8, a molecular weight of from about
240 to about 6,000, and a viscosity of from 50
to 35,000 mPa·s at 25°C, said polyether polyol
being prepared by reacting at least one suitable
initiator compound with one or more alkylene
oxides wherein the alkylene oxides comprise at
least 70% by weight of propylene oxide, based
on 100% by weight of the alkylene oxides;</claim-text></claim-text>
and
and</claim-text><claim-text>b) a polyisocyanate component,
in quantities such that the ratio of isocyanate groups in b) to
isocyanate-reactive groups in a) is from about 0.8:1 to about
2.0:1,</claim-text><claim-text>2) applying the mixture formed in 1) to fertilizer particles, to
form polyurethane encapsulated fertilizer particles,
wherein step 2) is optionally repeated (successively) as many times as
necessary, with the polyurethane encapsulated fertilizer particles formed in
step 2) being substituted for the fertilizer particles, so as to form
polyurethane encapsulated fertilizer particles containing from about 2 to
about 20% by weight of polyurethane, based on the total weight of the
encapsulated fertilizer composition, wherein the polyurethane forming the
encapsulated fertilizer particles is characterized by a water absorption of
less than 1% by weight, based on the total weight of the polyurethane
encapsulant.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="32"><claim-text>The process of Claim 31, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
comprises a sugar initiated polyol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="33"><claim-text>The process of Claim 31, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has an OH number of from 112 to 500.</claim-text></claim><claim num="34"><claim-text>The process of Claim 31, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has a functionality of from 4 to 7.</claim-text></claim><claim num="35"><claim-text>The process of Claim 31, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has a molecular weight of from 400 to 2,000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="36"><claim-text>The process of Claim 31, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
has a viscosity of from 500 to 25,000 mPa·s at 25°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="37"><claim-text>The process of Claim 31, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
is prepared by reacting a suitable initiator compound with one or more
alkylene oxides wherein the alkylene oxide comprises at least 80% by
weight of propylene oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="38"><claim-text>The process of Claim 37, wherein the alkylene oxide
comprises at least 90% by weight of propylene oxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="39"><claim-text>The process of Claim 31, wherein a)(ii) said polyether polyol
is prepared by reacting a suitable initiator compound with an alkylene
oxide, said initiator compound being selected from the group consisting of
glycerol, trimethylolpropane, ethylenediamine, ethanolamine,
pentaerythritol, sucrose and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="40"><claim-text>The process of Claim 31, wherein said polyesterether polyol
comprises a)(i)I from 40 to 80% by weight of castor oil, and a)(ii) from 20
to 60% by weight of a polyether polyol having an OH number of from 112
to 500, a functionality of from 4 to 7, a molecular weight of from 400 to
2,000, and a viscosity of from 500 to 25,000 mPa·s at 25°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="41"><claim-text>The process of Claim 31, wherein a) said polyesterether
polyol comprises the reaction product of (i) said castor oil, and (ii) said
polyether polyol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="42"><claim-text>The process of Claim 31, wherein a) said polyesterether
polyol comprises a blend of (i) said castor oil, and (ii) said polyether polyol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="43"><claim-text>The process of Claim 40, wherein the formed polyurethane
encapsulated fertilizer particles contain from about 3 to about 15% by
weight of polyurethane, based on the total weight of the encapsulated
fertilizer composition, and wherein the polyurethane forming the
encapsulated fertilizer particles is characterized by a water absorption of
less than 0.5% by weight, based on the total weight of the polyurethane
encapsulant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="44"><claim-text>The process of Claim 43, wherein the formed polyurethane
encapsulated fertilizer particles contain from about 4 to about 10% by
weight of polyurethane, based on the total weight of the encapsulated
fertilizer composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="45"><claim-text>The process of Claim 31, wherein the fertilizer particles
contain less than 10% by weight of reactive functional groups.</claim-text></claim><claim num="46"><claim-text>The polyurethane encapsulated, slow release fertilizer
particles produced by the process of Claim 1.</claim-text></claim><claim num="47"><claim-text>The polyurethane encapsulated, slow release fertilizer
particles produced by the process of Claim 16.</claim-text></claim><claim num="48"><claim-text>The polyurethane encapsulated, slow release fertilizer
particles produced by the process of Claim 31.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>