<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1160345-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1160345" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="24306457" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20011205"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1160345-A1" status="new" fvid="23305303"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1160345</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20011205</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01401360-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01401360</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010523</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-57689700-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>57689700</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000523</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  21/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  21/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  21/06        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  21/08        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22C  21/00B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22C  21/08</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Automaten-Aluminium-Legierung sowie Verfahren zur Verwendung</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Free-machining aluminum alloy and method of use</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Alliage d'aluminium de décolletage et procédé d'utilisation</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0793734-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0793734</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-1528182-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>1528182</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-11140575-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>11140575</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-8069792-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>8069792</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-2026457-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>2026457</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="DL" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1996013617-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1996013617</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998023783-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998023783</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 1996, no. 07, 31 July 1996 (1996-07-31) -&amp; JP 08 069792 A (AISIN SEIKI CO LTD), 12 March 1996 (1996-03-12)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 1999, no. 10, 31 August 1999 (1999-08-31) -&amp; JP 11 140575 A (SUMITOMO LIGHT METAL IND LTD), 25 May 1999 (1999-05-25)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>REYNOLDS METALS CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>REYNOLDS METALS COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="original"><addressbook><last-name>REYNOLDS METALS COMPANY</last-name><address><street>6601 West Broad Street</street><city>Richmond, VA 23230</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SUBHASISH SIRCAR</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SUBHASISH, SIRCAR</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SUBHASISH, SIRCAR</last-name><address><street>47F Pleasant Run Drive</street><city>Richmond, Virginia 23233</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Portal, Gérard</last-name><address><street>Cabinet Beau de Loménie 158, rue de l'Université</street><city>75340 Paris Cédex 07</city><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A free-machining alloy is disclosed containing bismuth and indium. The
free-machining constituents act as low melting point compounds for machining
and are specially adapted for use in aluminum alloys such as AA6000 series and
AA2000 series alloys. The bismuth and indium are effective replacements for the
lead and bismuth addition used previously to improve machinability while
providing a high impact energy free machining alloy.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">Field of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention is directed to free-machining alloys
and, in particular, to free-machining aluminum alloys which
contain bismuth and indium.</p><heading><u style="single">Background Art</u></heading><p num="0002">Free-machining aluminum alloys are well known in the art.
These alloys typically include free-machining constituents such
as lead, tin, indium and bismuth for improved machinability.
These constituents form low melting point compounds which readily
melt or soften due to the friction heat created during machining.
Thus, material removal required for the manufacture of complex
parts and components is easily facilitated.</p><p num="0003">During machining, free-machining alloys generate small chips
or curls which are easily collected and do not interfere with the
machining process. It is essential that these free-machining
aluminum alloys form these small chips or curls for proper
machining. Formation of long continuous strips or curls is
totally unacceptable in machining since the curls or strips may
wrap around the work piece or machining tool and disrupt the
operation. Poor machinability also affects other machining
operations since the operator must attend to a single machining
operation and cannot effectively supervise a multiplicity of
operations, as is commonly done in practice. AA6061 alloys are
generally unacceptable for machining since they form these long
continuous curls during machining.</p><p num="0004">United States Patent Nos. 2,026,457 and 2,026,575 to Kempf
et al. disclose free cutting aluminum alloys. Similarly, United
States Patent No. 4,005,243 to Baba et al. discloses a freely
machinable aluminum alloy.</p><p num="0005">Other known machinable alloys include AA6262 and AA2011,
2012 and 2111. </p><p num="0006">While the prior art aluminum alloys provide adequate free
machinability, they are not without drawbacks and/or
disadvantages. For example, AA6262 contains lead and chips from
machining this alloy represent a hazardous waste disposal
problem, in addition to the possibility for exposure to fine lead
particles during machining.</p><p num="0007">Prior art alloys containing bismuth, e.g., AA2011 and
AA2111, can adversely affect the final mechanical properties of
the machined part. Since bismuth has some affinity for
magnesium, the bismuth in these alloys has a tendency to combine
with the magnesium to prevent or reduce Mg<sub>2</sub>Si formation potential
for precipitation strengthening. Bismuth also has a poor
affinity for tin, and alloys having these two components may not
always form the desired low melting point compounds or structures
for free machining.</p><p num="0008">As a solution to the problems identified above, the inventor
has proposed free-machining aluminum alloys containing tin and
indium as a means to eliminate both lead and bismuth as
constituents in free-machining alloys. This alloy system is
disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 5,587,029, titled "Machineable
Aluminum Alloys Containing In and Sn and Process for Producing
the Same", issued December 24, 1996 which is herein incorporated
by reference in its entirety.</p><p num="0009">Although free-machining alloys containing the aforementioned
indium and tin provide excellent machining properties, the levels
of indium when combined with a high price for the source indium
make the alloys somewhat unattractive from an economical
standpoint.</p><p num="0010">Other free machining alloys suffer from inadequate Charpy V-notch
impact strength. For example, AA6020 which has tin and
high levels of silicon, instead of the lead and bismuth in
AA6262, exhibits poor impact properties. Alloys with low impact
properties have a tendency to crack when deep drilled.</p><p num="0011">As such, a need has developed to provide an environmentally
friendly free-machining alloy which does not have its final
mechanical properties compromised by free-machining constituents 
therein, has good impact properties and which is even more
economically attractive.</p><p num="0012">In some applications involving hot automotive brake fluid,
alloys containing Sn have shown to be extremely poor in corrosion
resistance. Hence, this new alloy is also aimed at removing Sn
from alloys that require exposure to hot brake fluid.</p><heading><u style="single">Summary of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0013">Accordingly, it is a first object of the present invention
to provide a free-machining aluminum alloy which eliminates lead
and its adverse effects on the environment during machining chip
disposal.</p><p num="0014">Another object of the present invention is to provide a
free-machining aluminum alloy containing bismuth and indium which
has at least comparable free-machining properties as prior art
alloys.</p><p num="0015">Another object of the present invention is to provide an
economically attractive free-machining alloy.

A still further object of the present invention is to provide a
method of machining using a lead free free-machining alloy which
utilizes bismuth and indium as a low melting point compound for
machinability.</p><p num="0016">A yet another object of the invention is to provide a free-machining
alloy having improved impact properties.</p><p num="0017">A still further object is to provide an alloy having
improved resistance to corrosion when exposed to hot brake fluid.</p><p num="0018">Other objects and advantages of the present invention will
become apparent as a description thereof proceeds.</p><p num="0019">In satisfaction of the foregoing objects and advantages, the
present invention provides an improvement over the prior art
free-machining alloys containing low melting point free-machining
constituents. According to the invention, an effective amount of
bismuth and indium is utilized in these types of alloys as free-machining
constituents, i.e., low melting point compounds
(eutectics). It should be appreciated that the terms "bismuth"
and "tin", as used herein, are not limited to pure elements but 
also include elements having incidental impurities of the types
associated with commercially available alloying elements.</p><p num="0020">The effective amounts of bismuth and indium can be added to
alloy chemistries typical of free-machining alloys such as
aluminum-base alloys, e.g., AA6000 or AA2000 series alloys or
other alloys, ferrous or non-ferrous. The effective amounts are
such that the bismuth and indium form the low melting point
compounds in an amount which, when dispersed throughout the alloy
shape being machined, generate chips rather than curls or
stringers during machining. The free-machining alloying
constituents can range, in vol.%, up to 1.0 and, preferably, up
to 0.5. The lower limit, in some cases, can be as low as 0.01
vol. %. In other cases, the lower limit may be 0.2 or 0.3 vol. %.
While amounts greater than 1.0 vol.% might increase
machinability, the improvement in machinability might have an
unacceptable impact on alloy properties. Similarly, the lower
limit is a function of the desired improvement in machinability.
If the amount is too low, there will be an insufficient number or
dispersion of the low melting point constituents to have any
significant impact on machinability.</p><p num="0021">Preferably, in terms of weight percent, the amounts of Bi
and In are added to a selected alloy so that their respective
weight percentages in the selected alloy range between about 0.10
to 1.5 Bi and about 0.01 to 0.30 In.</p><p num="0022">More preferably, the present invention discloses a free-machining
alloy wherein the bismuth ranges between 0.30-1.0 wt.%,
and the indium ranges between 0.03 and 0.11 wt.%. In one mode,
the bismuth and indium can be provided in a eutectic ratio, i.e.,
33 wt.% In-67 wt.% Bi.</p><p num="0023">In terms of the type of binary alloys, preferred binary
alloys for addition to a given base alloy include, in wt.%, 80
Bi- 20 In, 85 Bi-15 In, 90 Bi-10 In, and 95 Bi-5 In. Binary
alloys with increasing amounts of indium can also be selected but
are not as preferred due to the cost of indium. Indium and
bismuth may be added to the molten base alloy as individual 
elements or as an alloyed constituent (master alloy) in the
desired ratio.</p><p num="0024">The bismuth and indium can be added as substitutes for the
free-machining constituents in AA6262 and AA2111 free machining
aluminum alloys. In addition, they may be added to other alloys
to improve machinability.</p><heading><u style="single">Brief Description of the Drawing</u></heading><p num="0025">Reference is now made to the drawing of the invention
wherein
<sl><li>Figure 1 compares mechanical properties for prior art alloys
and the inventive alloy; and</li><li>Figure 2 compares impact energies for prior art alloys and
the inventive alloy.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">Description of the Preferred Embodiments</u></heading><p num="0026">The present invention is an improvement over prior art free-machining
alloys.</p><p num="0027">According to the invention, an effective amount of bismuth
and indium can be used to provide free machining. Bismuth and
indium are principally substituted for the free-machining or low
melting point constituents in prior art free-machining alloys,
such as lead and bismuth or bismuth and tin.</p><p num="0028">An effective amount of bismuth and indium is a respective
amount of each alloying component that, when combined with the
other component, forms a low melting point compound as part of
the alloy and results in a free-machining alloy that generates
the proper sized machine chips or curls for effective machining.
Indium and bismuth are relatively insoluble in the aluminum
matrix, and, therefore, are dispersed in the matrix as
inclusions, rather than in solid solution.</p><p num="0029">A binary alloy of bismuth and indium has a eutectic
temperature of about 109°C (228°F), i.e., 33 wt.% indium and 67
wt.% bismuth. However, lower amounts of indium will still give a
range of melting point temperatures. For example, an 85 wt.%
bismuth-15 wt.% indium alloy will have some melting between about
109°C and 200°C (228°F and 392°F). Thus, even with off-eutectic 
binary Bi-In alloys, melting of the dispersoids will occur
(starting at 109°C - 228°F) to provide the desired free machining
qualities. It is believed that the inventive alloy can use any
binary bismuth-indium alloy having respective amounts of bismuth
and indium up to the eutectic composition of about 67% bismuth-33%
indium. It also is potentially possible to use even higher
amounts of indium in the binary alloy.</p><p num="0030">Preferably, the ratios between the amounts of bismuth and
indium added, in weight %, fall within the following ranges:
bismuth - 67 to 99 % and indium - 1 to 33 %, more preferably 85
to 95% bismuth and 5 to 15% indium. As stated above, it is
preferred to limit the level of indium so that the binary alloy
and the subsequently modified free machining alloy are
economically attractive.</p><p num="0031">The effective amount of bismuth and indium, when added to a
standard alloy such as a steel or an aluminum alloy, forms a low
melting point compound, or a low melting eutectic in the alloy.
With this low melting point compound present in the alloy, a
local increase in the alloy temperature due to machining of an
article made from the alloy brings the low melting point compound
to a soft or liquid state. In this state, the low melting point
compound loses its strength thereby facilitating the formation of
a chip. The chip can then be easily removed from the machining
area without interfering with the machining process. This
contrasts with prior art alloys which have a tendency to form
long stringers or curls which can interfere with the machining
process.</p><p num="0032">It has been discovered that the use of indium and bismuth as
free-machining constituents for an alloy to be machined offers
significant improvements over prior art systems using lead-bismuth,
bismuth-tin, indium-tin, indium-tin-bismuth and high
silicon and tin low melting point constituents. The well-recognized
problem with lead-bismuth systems is that a large
amount of the lead-bismuth addition is needed to obtain the
necessary volume percent in the alloy for free machining. Since
lead is extremely dense, large additions are needed which 
increase the environmental unacceptability of these types of
alloys. These systems are also disadvantageous in that the
eutectic point of the low melting compound is about 125°C.</p><p num="0033">Bismuth-tin systems, while being lead-free, do not machine
nearly as well as lead-containing systems. These bismuth-tin
systems are also disadvantageous in that the eutectic melting
point is 140°C which is even higher than that of the lead-bismuth
systems discussed above.</p><p num="0034">The invention, in one aspect, is an improvement over the
bismuth-tin systems in that the addition of indium lowers the
melting point. The invention is also an improvement over an
AA6020 alloy when the bismuth-indium binary alloy is used with an
aluminum base alloy in that the inventive alloy exhibits vastly
superior impact properties.</p><p num="0035">Since the inventive free-machining alloys are lead-free,
there is no problem in achieving the necessary volume percent in
the article for acceptable machining properties, while still
being environmentally friendly. It is believed that when using
the bismuth-indium low melting point compound, a volume percent
of up to about 1.0% provides acceptable machining capability,
preferably 0.1 to 0.5% and more preferably about 0.2 to 0.4%. Of
course, the volume percent may vary depending on the alloy system
being used in conjunction with the bismuth-indium addition, the
machining process being used with the article or articles formed
from the alloy, the desired impact on machining properties of the
article, and the acceptable change in properties of the alloy
associated with the addition.</p><p num="0036">If a particular binary alloy, e.g., 85Bi-15In, in wt.%, and
a volume fraction, e.g. 0.3%, are selected for a particular
alloy, one skilled in the art, knowing the density of the
elements to be added and that 0.5% volume fraction of a Pb-Bi
eutectic in AA6262 equals about 1.0 wt.%, can calculate the
amount of bismuth and indium needed to achieve both the binary
composition and volume fraction. For example, targeting a 0.5%
volume fraction and a 90Bi-10In binary alloy, one would add 91
parts of the 90-10 binary rather than 100 parts of a Pb-Bi 
eutectic binary, further split as 82 parts bismuth and 9 parts
indium to maintain the proper Bi-In ratio. This split could then
be reduced proportionately for lower or higher volume fractions,
e.g., 0.4% volume fraction or a 20% reduction in the total amount
of the binary alloy. Since relating volume fraction to the
needed weight percent in a given alloy is within the skill of the
artisan, a further detailed description is not deemed necessary
for understanding of the invention.</p><p num="0037">When adding the bismuth and indium to a particular alloy, it
is preferred that the thus-formed low melting point binary
compound be finely dispersed throughout the alloy article to be
machined. Without a fine dispersion or distribution of the
binary compound, a machining tool may come into contact with
portions of the alloy article being machined that are devoid of
the low melting point compound. Machining these areas may result
in formation of long stringers or the like rather than chips.

The stringers then adversely affect the overall machining
process.</p><p num="0038">When using bismuth and indium free-machining constituents in
an aluminum-based alloy which is heat treatable, the appropriate
controls can be utilized during the various processing steps used
to form the alloys into articles and shapes for machining, e.g.,
working, quenching, annealing, solution heat treating, aging,
etc. Since obtaining a fine distribution or dispersion of free-machining
constituents in aluminum and other alloys is well
known, a further description of these techniques is not deemed
necessary for understanding of the invention.</p><p num="0039">As stated above, it is believed that the use of a bismuth-indium
low melting point compound applies to ferrous and
nonferrous alloys. This system is especially adapted for use in
heat treatable aluminum alloys such as the AA6000, AA5000, AA7000
and AA2000 series and non-heat treatable aluminum alloys such as
AA1000, AA3000 and AA4000 series types</p><p num="0040">Table 1 sets forth, in weight percent, an example of using
the bismuth-indium low melting point compound in an AA6000 series
aluminum alloy. The maximum amount of indium shown in the 
"Broader Limits" portion of Table 1, in one embodiment, is
limited to 0.30 wt. %. Table 2 shows weight percentages for
indium and bismuth in an AA6061 alloy base for different volume
fractions of the binary in the AA6061 material. <img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="101"/><tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Binary Alloy Type</entry><entry align="center">Volume Fraction in Percent</entry><entry align="center">Wt. % Bi in AA6061 Alloy</entry><entry align="center">Wt. % In In AA6061 Alloy</entry></row><row><entry align="center">85Bi - 15In</entry><entry align="center">0.04</entry><entry align="center">0.61</entry><entry align="center">0.11</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.03</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.46</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">0.08</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.02</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.31</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center">90Bi - 10In</entry><entry align="center">0.04</entry><entry align="center">0.66</entry><entry align="center">0.07</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.03</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.49</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.02</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.33</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">0.04</entry></row><row><entry align="center">95Bi - 5In</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry><entry align="center">0.88</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.04</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.70</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">0.04</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.03</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.53</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">0.03</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.02</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.35</entry> <entry align="center" namest="4">0.02</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">0.01</entry><entry align="center" namest="3">0.18</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">0.01</entry> </row> </tbody> </tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0041">Although an AA6000 series aluminum alloy with a low melting
point compound is exemplified in Tables 1 and 2, the weight
percentages for In and Bi set forth are believed useful with
other aluminum alloys and steels.</p><p num="0042">As stated above, systems using just bismuth and tin have not
exhibited improved machinability. It is believed that the
relatively high melting point of a non-eutectic bismuth-tin phase
in these systems, as compared to eutectic lead-bismuth systems or
indium-tin systems, may be related to the lack of good
machinability. It is believed that combining indium with bismuth
improves the machinability of the binary-containing alloy
significantly as compared to these prior art alloys.</p><p num="0043">To demonstrate the effective machining properties of the
inventive alloy, several different types of machining studies
were conducted. Table 3 shows the results of a turning study
wherein various types of free machining alloys were compared in
terms of peak machining temperatures and size and type of
machining pieces. The peak machining temperature is the measured
temperature of the article remote from the machining site, as
distinguished from the local temperature rise in the area being
machined. The alloys tested included AA6061, AA6262, AA6020,
X6030, COMP A, i.e., an In-Sn-Bi-containing AA6061 alloy, and the
inventive alloy (INV B). The X6030 alloy is an indium -tin
containing alloy. The turning study involved rough turning
nominal 1" (25.4 mm) diameter rods at a rate of 2000 RPM and a
feed rate of 0.020 inches (0.51 mm) per revolution (IPR). Metal
removal was 0.400" (10.2 mm) from the diameter with one cut at 4"
(101.6 mm) in length. A finish cut was done at 2000 RPM, an IPR
of 0.005" (0.127 mm) and 0.025" (0.635 mm) metal removal at a 2"
(50.8 mm) cut. Carbide insert tooling was used. As can be seen
from Table 3, the inventive alloy produced small chips, the ideal
machining debris. In addition, the weight of 20 chips for the
inventive alloy was low, thereby substantiating the small size of
the machining debris. The peak temperature for INV B was also
lower than the other free machining alloys, indicating good
machining capability. In contrast, known free machining alloys 
such as AA6262 and AA6020 produced curls. AA6061 was totally
unacceptable as a free machining alloy.</p><p num="0044">In a drilling study wherein a ¼" (6.35 mm) hole was drilled
in a 1" (25.4 m) rod, INV B exhibited slight to no chatter and
small machining chips. In contrast, AA6262 exhibited light
chatter at drilling onset and produced mixed chips and strings
and AA6020 had light chatter and small to medium chips. <tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center">ALLOY DESIGNATION</entry><entry align="center">PEAK TEMP

ºF

(ºC)</entry><entry align="center">COMMENTS</entry><entry align="center">WEIGHT OF 20 CHIPS IN GRAMS</entry></row><row><entry align="center">X6030</entry><entry align="center">113.8</entry><entry align="center">short/med curls</entry><entry align="center">1.30</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">(45ºC)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6020-T8</entry><entry align="center">105.3</entry><entry align="center">long strings</entry><entry align="center">1.16</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">(41ºC)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6262-T9</entry><entry align="center">104.3</entry><entry align="center">small curls</entry><entry align="center">1.34</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">(40ºC)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6061-T6511</entry><entry align="center">142.1</entry><entry align="center">single string</entry><entry align="center">- -</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">(61ºC)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">COMP A</entry><entry align="center">105.4</entry><entry align="center">long chips</entry><entry align="center">1.43</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">(41ºC)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">INV B</entry><entry align="center">110.6</entry><entry align="center">small chips</entry><entry align="center">1.28</entry></row><row><entry align="center" namest="2">(44ºC)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables><tables><table><tgroup cols="13"><tbody><row><entry nameend="13" align="center" namest="1">Compositions of Alloy Designations in Wt. %.</entry></row><row><entry align="center">Alloy</entry><entry align="center">Si</entry><entry align="center">Fe</entry><entry align="center">Cu</entry><entry align="center">Mn</entry><entry align="center">Mg</entry><entry align="center">Cr</entry><entry align="center">Zn</entry><entry align="center">Ti</entry><entry align="center">Sn</entry><entry align="center">Bi</entry><entry align="center">Pb</entry><entry align="center">In</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6020</entry><entry align="center">0.90</entry><entry align="center">0.33</entry><entry align="center">0.65</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry><entry align="center">0.75</entry><entry align="center">0.06</entry><entry align="center">0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">0.97</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">--</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6262-T6511</entry><entry align="center">0.57</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">0.28</entry><entry align="center">0.11</entry><entry align="center">0.89</entry><entry align="center">0.10</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">0.47</entry><entry align="center">0.45</entry><entry align="center">--</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6262-T9</entry><entry align="center">0.55</entry><entry align="center">0.52</entry><entry align="center">0.30</entry><entry align="center">0.13</entry><entry align="center">0.98</entry><entry align="center">0.10</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">0.41</entry><entry align="center">0.46</entry><entry align="center">--</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6061-T6511</entry><entry align="center">0.62</entry><entry align="center">0.32</entry><entry align="center">0.23</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry><entry align="center">0.84</entry><entry align="center">0.13</entry><entry align="center">0.06</entry><entry align="center">0.04</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">--</entry></row><row><entry align="center">COMPA-T5511</entry><entry align="center">0.66</entry><entry align="center">0.22</entry><entry align="center">0.22</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.95</entry><entry align="center">0.10</entry><entry align="center">0.03</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.26</entry><entry align="center">0.27</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">0.08</entry></row><row><entry align="center">INVB-T5511</entry><entry align="center">0.64</entry><entry align="center">0.27</entry><entry align="center">0.20</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.01</entry><entry align="center">0.92</entry><entry align="center">0.10</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.01</entry><entry align="center">&lt;0.01</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">0.68</entry><entry align="center">---</entry><entry align="center">0.10</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0045">The inventive alloy does not sacrifice mechanical properties
at the expense of improved machinability. The levels of ultimate
tensile strength, yield strength, and elongation are equivalent
or better than the prior art alloys noted above. Figure 1
compares the mechanical properties of the alloys listed above and
shows that the inventive alloy is at least as good as the prior
art alloys. More particularly, the INV B-T5511 alloy gives
equivalent mechanical properties as the other free machining
alloys such as COMP A and the X6030 alloy.</p><p num="0046">Quite surprisingly though, the inventive alloy provides
significant improvements in Charpy V-notch impact values.
Referring to the Figure 2, significant improvements are seen for
INV B as compared to the other free machining alloys,
particularly AA6020, and even better than AA6061. Thus, assuming 
that mechanical properties are equivalent between the various
alloys, applications requiring good impact properties are best
served by using INV B rather than other known alloys.</p><p num="0047">In the inventive method, an article or shape is made of an
alloy containing the free-machining constituents, bismuth and
indium. The alloy can be made using any conventional techniques
known to one of ordinary skill in the art, including but not
limited to rolling, extruding, forging and combinations thereof.
Similarly, conventional methodology can be used to form the alloy
into a desired shape for machining. Once the alloy is made into
a shape, e.g., a bar, rod or other work piece with the free-machining
constituents as components thereof, the work piece can
then be machined without interference from the machining debris
since the debris is basically in the form of machining chips
rather than mostly long curls, stringers or other elongated
pieces. The machining can be any type known in the art.</p><p num="0048">As mentioned above, it is believed that the bismuth and
indium alloy constituents can also be used in free-machining
alloy steels. These steels include both austenitic and ferritic
stainless steels as well as low carbon, medium carbon and alloy
grade steels.</p><p num="0049">In summary, the present invention provides for the addition
of a low melting compound to conventional alloys, such as AA 2000
(copper is principal alloying element) and AA6000 (alloys contain
silicon and magnesium in appropriate proportions to form
magnesium silicide) series alloys to improve their machinability.
While using prior art low melting point compounds such as indium
and tin or indium, tin and bismuth improves machinability, as
does the use of a lead and bismuth compound, these compounds are
not without their disadvantages. The addition of lead is
unattractive because of environmental issues. When the cost of
indium is high, its use with the addition of tin or tin and
bismuth becomes economically unattractive.</p><p num="0050">As such, an invention has been disclosed in terms of
preferred embodiments thereof which fulfill each and every one of
the objects of the present invention as set forth above and 
provide a new and improved free-machining alloy and a method of
use.</p><p num="0051">Of course, various changes, modifications and alterations
from the teachings of the present invention may be contemplated
by those skilled in the art without departing from the intended
spirit and scope thereof. Accordingly, it is intended that the
present invention only be limited by the terms of the appended
claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A free-machining lead free aluminum alloy comprising an aluminum alloy
including a low melting point eutectic compound uniformly distributed in the
alloy that consists essentially of indium and bismuth in a volume percent of said
lead free aluminum alloy, said compound softening or melting during machining
to generate small chip-like machining debris.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The alloy according to claim 1, characterized in that the aluminum alloy is
one of an AA6000, AA5000, AA7000, AA1000, AA3000, AA4000, AA8000 or
AA2000 series alloy.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The alloy according to claim 1 or 2, characterized in that the volume
percent is less than 1.0.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The alloy according to any one of claims 1 to 3, characterized in that the
low melting point compound has a melting point ranging between about 109°C
and up to about 270°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The alloy according to any one of claims 1 to 4, characterized in that it has
a composition consisting essentially of, in weight percent:
<claim-text><claim-text>0.4 to 0.8 Si;</claim-text><claim-text>0.15 to 0.4 Cu;</claim-text><claim-text>0.8 to 1.2 Mg;</claim-text><claim-text>0.04 to 0.35 Cr;</claim-text><claim-text>0.01 to 0.4 In;</claim-text><claim-text>0.1 to 1.5 Bi;</claim-text><claim-text>up to 0.7 Fe;</claim-text><claim-text>up to 0.15 Mn;</claim-text><claim-text>up to 0.25 Zn;</claim-text><claim-text>up to 0.15 Ti;</claim-text><claim-text>with the balance aluminum and incidental impurities.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The alloy according to claim 5, characterized in that the Bi ranges between
0.30 and 1.0 and the In ranges between 0.03 and 0.11.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The alloy according to claim 5, characterized in that the Si ranges between
0.55 and 0.65, the Cu ranges between 0.17 and 0.33, and the Cr ranges between
0.06 and 0.12.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The alloy according to claim 7, characterized in that the Bi ranges between
0.30 and 1.0 and the In ranges between 0.03 and 0.11.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The alloy according to any one of claims 1 to 4, characterized in that the In
ranges between 0.01 and 0.30 wt. % and the Bi ranges between 0.10 and 1.5 wt. %
of said lead free aluminum alloy.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A free-machining lead free alloy including a low melting point compound,
wherein the low melting point compound consists essentially of indium and
bismuth in a volume percent of said lead free alloy which during machining of an
article formed from the alloy softens or melts thereby generating chip-like
machining debris.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The alloy according to claim 10, characterized in that the indium ranges
between 0.01 and 0.30 wt. % and the bismuth ranges between 0.10 and 1.50 wt. %
of the free-machining lead free alloy.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The alloy according to claim 11, characterized in that the bismuth ranges
between 0.30 and 1.0 and the indium ranges between 0.03 and 0.11.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A method of machining a work piece and generating fine machining chips
comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>providing a work piece consisting of a lead free alloy including a low
melting point compound consisting essentially of indium and bismuth in volume
percent of said lead free alloy which compound during machining softens or melts
to thereby generate chip-like machining debris; and</claim-text><claim-text>machining said work piece to a desired shape, said machining generating
said fine machining chips.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The method according to claim 13, characterized in that said alloy is a lead
free aluminum alloy.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The method according to claim 13 or 14, characterized in that the lead free
alloy is one of a lead free AA6000 and a lead free AA2000 series alloy.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The method according to any one of claims 13 to 15, characterized in that
the indium ranges between 0.01 and 0.30 wt. % and the bismuth ranges between
0.10 and 1.50.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The method according to any one of claims 13 to 16, characterized in that
the indium ranges between 0.03 and 0.11 and the bismuth ranges between 0.30
and 1.0.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The method according to any one of claims 13 to 15, characterized in that
the alloy has a composition consisting essentially of, in weight percent:
<claim-text><claim-text>0.4 to 0.8 Si;</claim-text><claim-text>0.15 to 0.4 Cu;</claim-text><claim-text>0.8 to 1.2 Mg;</claim-text><claim-text>0.04 to 0.35 Cr;</claim-text><claim-text>0.01 to 0.4 In;</claim-text><claim-text>0.1 to 1.5 Bi;</claim-text><claim-text>up to 0.7 Fe;</claim-text><claim-text>up to 0.15 Mn;</claim-text><claim-text>up to 0.25 Zn;</claim-text><claim-text>up to 0.15 Ti;</claim-text><claim-text>with the balance aluminum and incidental impurities.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The method according to claim 18, characterized in that the bismuth
ranges between 0.30 and 1.00 and the indium ranges between 0.03 and 0.11</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The method according to claim 18, characterized in that the Si ranges
between 0.55 and 0.65, the Cu ranges between 0.17 and 0.33, and the Cr ranges
between 0.06 and 0.12.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>The method according to any one of claims 13 to 20, characterized in that
the work piece is provided as an extruded aluminum article.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>The method according to any one of claims 13 to 20, characterized in that
the work piece is provided as a rolled aluminum article.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>The method according to any one of claims 13 to 20, characterized in that
the work piece is provided as a forged aluminum article.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>