<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1405927-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1405927" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="31993561" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040407"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1405927-A1" status="new" fvid="24002374"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1405927</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040407</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03021784-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03021784</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030926</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-26313502-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>26313502</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021002</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22F   9/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B22F   9/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C   1/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C   1/04        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">B22F   9/04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22C   1/04B1</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22C  21/06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22C  21/10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22C  30/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22F   1/047</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C22F   1/053</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L22F998:10+B22F3/12B+B22F3/15+B22F3/20</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">L22F999:00+B22F1/00A2N+B22F9/04+L22F202/03</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung von kryogen zerkleinerten Legierungen für strangegepressten und geschmiedeten Bauteile</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method for preparing cryomilled aluminum alloys and components extruded and forged therefrom</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé de fabrication d'un alliage broyage cryogénique pour des produits forgés et extrudés</invention-title><citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>AIKIN, B.J.M. (CASE WESTERN RESERVE UNIVERSITY) ET AL:  "Improvements in cryomill processing." ADVANCED PARTICULATE MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSES 1997 (1997), 287-294, GRAPHS, 6 REF. METAL POWDER INDUSTRIES FEDERATION. 105 COLLEGE RD. EAST, PRINCETON, NJ 08540-6692, USA CONFERENCE: 5TH INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON ADVANCED PARTICULATE MATERIALS &amp; PROCE,   XP009021519</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>CHOI, J.H. (HANYANG UNIVERSITY) ET AL: "Consolidation behavior of nanocrystalline Al -5at.%Ti alloys synthesized by cryogenic milling." JOURNAL OF ALLOYS AND COMPOUNDS (9 FEB. 2001) 315, (1-2), 178-186, DIFFRACTION PATTERNS, PHOTOMICROGRAPHS, GRAPHS, 22 REF. ISSN: 0925-8388,   XP001156279</text><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>LEE, Z. (UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA) ET AL:  "Microstructural evolution of cryomilled nanocrystalline Al -Ti-Cu alloy." ULTRAFINE GRAINED MATERIALS II (2002), 653-659, DIFFRACTION PATTERNS, PHOTOMICROGRAPHS, GRAPHS, 10 REF. MINERALS, METALS AND MATERIALS SOCIETY/AIME. 184 THORN HILL ROAD, WARRENDALE, PA 15086-7528, USA CONFERENCE: ULTRAFINE GRAINED MATERIALS II (AS HE,   XP009021523</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>LIAO, X.Z. (LOS ALAMOS NATIONAL LABORATORY) ET AL:  "Deformation mechanisms at different grain sizes in a cryogenically ball- milled Al -Mg alloy." ULTRAFINE GRAINED MATERIALS II (2002), 323-330, PHOTOMICROGRAPHS, DIFFRACTION PATTERNS, 16 REF. MINERALS, METALS AND MATERIALS SOCIETY/AIME. 184 THORN HILL ROAD, WARRENDALE, PA 15086-7528, USA CONFERENCE: ULTRAFINE GRAINED MATERIALS II (AS HELD AT TH,   XP009021521</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>BOEING CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>THE BOEING COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>The Boeing Company</last-name><address><street>100 N. Riverside</street><city>Chicago, IL 60606-1596</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>FRITZEMEIER LESLIE G</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MATEJCZYK DANIEL E</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>VAN DAAM THOMAS J</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>FRITZEMEIER, LESLIE G.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MATEJCZYK, DANIEL E.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>VAN DAAM, THOMAS J.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>FRITZEMEIER, LESLIE G.</last-name><address><street>The Boeing Company P.O. Box 3707 Mail Stop 13-08</street><city>Seattle Washington 98124-2007</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MATEJCZYK, DANIEL E.</last-name><address><street>The Boeing Company P.O. Box 3707 Mail Stop 13-08</street><city>Seattle Washington 98124-2007</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>VAN DAAM, THOMAS J.</last-name><address><street>The Boeing Company P.O. Box 3707 Mail Stop 13-08</street><city>Seattle Washington 98124-2007</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Gahlert, Stefan, Dr.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>Witte, Weller &amp;amp; Partner, Patentanwälte, Postfach 105462</street><city>70047 Stuttgart</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>High strength aluminum alloy powders, extrusions, and
forgings are provided in which the aluminum alloys exhibit high
strength at atmospheric temperatures and maintain high strength
and ductility at extremely low temperatures. The alloy is
produced by blending about 89 atomic% to 99 atomic% aluminum, 1
atomic% to 11 atomic% of a secondary metal selected from the
group consisting of magnesium, lithium, silicon, titanium,
zirconium, and combinations thereof, and up to about 10 atomic%
of a tertiary metal selected from the group consisting of Be,
Ca, Sr, Ba, Ra, Sc, V, Cr, Mn, Fe, Co, Ni, Cu, Zn, Y, Nb, Mo,
Tc, Ru, Rh, Pd, Ag, Cd, W, and combinations thereof. The alloy
is produced by nanostructure material synthesis, such as cryomilling,
in the absence of refractory dispersoids. The synthesized
alloy is then canned, degassed, consolidated, extruded,
and optionally forged into a solid metallic component. Grain
size within the alloy is less than 0.5 µm, and alloys with
grain size less than 0.1 µm may be produced (Fig. 1).
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="38" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="120"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to the production of high strength cryomilled
aluminum alloys, and to the extrusion and forging of cryomilled aluminum alloys.</p><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0002">The aerospace industry requires structural metals and alloys that provide
maximum strength with minimum weight. Traditionally, these roles have been
fulfilled by aluminum, titanium, and alloys thereof. However, as the performance
demands of the industry have increased, previously known aluminum and titanium
alloys have been pushed to the limits of their usefulness.</p><p num="0003">The operation of high performance rocket propulsion systems are particularly
demanding on metallic components. Extruded and forged parts such as fuel
turbopump impellers and other rotational components require high strength and low
density, but also require adequate ductility and toughness. Furthermore, because the
rotational components of liquid-fueled rocket engines are exposed to cryogenic
liquids at very high pressure and low temperature, the rotational components must
retain their high strength and ductility in an extremely cold environment.</p><p num="0004">In the past, high performance aluminum alloy components, such as those used
in rocket propulsion systems, were strengthened through precipitation heat treatment,
resulting in tensile strengths of up to 80 ksi. The heat treated aluminum parts remain
adequate for most modem day propulsion systems but fall short of meeting the
demands of today's high-performance rocket engines and other similarly demanding
propulsion systems. The components formed by precipitation heat treatment are not
particularly suited for use in extremely cold environments such as those temperatures
found in liquid fuel rocket engines. Further, heat treatment introduces residual stress
and distortion in the metallic components, which is particularly troublesome in thin-walled
or high-precision components.</p><p num="0005">The technology of dispersion strengthening has provided aluminum alloys
having strength and durability beyond that provided by precipitation heat treatment.
The dispersion strengthened aluminum alloys are metallic aluminum alloys having a
second phase material of fine particles, dispersed within the metal in a substantially 
homogenous dispersion. The second phase particles are typically oxides of the
aluminum found within the alloy and may also be nitrides, borides, oxy-nitrides, or
carbo-nitrides. The dispersion strengthened aluminum alloys exhibit improved
physical properties over and above those of heat treated aluminum, including
increased mechanical strength and an increase in the temperature at which the
mechanical strength of the alloy begins to fade. Components constructed of
dispersion-strengthened aluminum, sometimes known as sintered aluminum products
(S.A.P.), have high levels of hardness and tensile strength and maintain those
mechanical properties at higher temperatures than comparable aluminum alloys which
are not dispersion-strengthened.</p><p num="0006">The most successful dispersion strengthened alloys have been produced by
dispersing metal oxides within metal alloys through cryogenic milling. The cryogenic
milling, which usually takes place in liquid nitrogen or a similar chilled atmosphere,
provides an ultra-fine dispersion of oxide particles within the alloy and also increases
the strain energy that is stored within the alloy, resulting in reduced grain size upon
reheating of the metal. The ultra-fine dispersion of oxides and reduced grain size
leads to an alloy of relatively high strength, particularly at high temperatures.</p><p num="0007">The use of dispersion strengthened aluminum alloys in propulsion systems is
well studied, and several variations of the dispersion strengthened alloys and methods
of producing the alloys are available. For instance, U.S. Patent 3,740,210 to
Bomford, et al. discloses the milling of aluminum and aluminum oxide powders in a
ball mill with asymmetric organic compounds acting as surfactant agents. The
surfactant acts to retard the welding of aluminum to itself within the ball mill, thus
allowing the comminuted aluminum and aluminum oxide to be mutually
interdispersed in the composite powder. Reduction of the metallic welding also
prevents the ball mill from being frozen by agglomerated metal welded between the
balls and inner walls of the mill. The favorable intermingling of the aluminum and
aluminum oxides provides a composite alloy powder having well dispersed oxides
which leads to a high strength, high temperature alloy product.</p><p num="0008">U.S. Patent 4,818,481 to Luton, et al. discloses the use of cryomilling to
disperse a second phase within an aluminum alloy. Luton '481 explains that the
repeated fracture and cold-welding of metal powder involved in ball milling causes
strain energy to be stored within the milled particles. Recrystallization occurs with
longer milling times, 
resulting in decreased grain size over that of the starting powders. The decreased grain
size corresponds to a better dispersed secondary phase within the alloy which, in turn,
results in improved mechanical properties in the finished product. Although
considerable research has occurred regarding different types of oxide dispersions and
methods by which oxide, nitride, and other precipitates are dispersed within
aluminum alloys, the improvement in the strength of the dispersion strengthened
alloys over the heat treated alloys of the past is fairly modest. Furthermore, the
dispersion-strengthened aluminum alloys are designed for use at high temperatures,
and are not particularly suited for use in extremely low temperature environments.</p><p num="0009">Modern, advanced liquid fuel rocket motors require pump components of
extremely high strength which are capable of maintaining strength and ductility at
extremely low temperatures, due to the use of liquid hydrogen as a rocket fuel. The
aluminum components must be capable of continual high-speed operation, typically
below -300°F. Existing heat treated and dispersion strengthened aluminum alloys are
unable to meet the demands of the next generation of rocket motors and their high
stress, extremely low temperature environments.</p><p num="0010">What are needed are improved aluminum alloys which are not based upon heat
treating techniques or dispersion strengthening techniques of the past, and which are
capable of withstanding the extremely low temperatures and extreme mechanical
stresses inherent in high-performance rocket propulsion systems. What is further
needed is a manner of preparing the improved alloys. What is still further needed is a
manner of extruding and forging components from the improved alloys in order to
obtain products exhibiting extremely high strength and extremely low temperatures.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0011">High strength aluminum alloy powders, extrusions, and forgings are provided
by the instant invention. Methods of producing high strength aluminum alloy
powders, extrusions, and forgings are also provided by the instant invention. The
aluminum alloys exhibit high strength at atmospheric temperatures and maintain high
strength and ductility at extremely low temperatures. The alloys may be formed into
rocket motor components capable of withstanding high stresses. Uses for the alloys
are wide ranging, but the alloys are particularly suited for production of components
for use in liquid fuel rocket motors in the form of pump impellers and ancillary
components which must endure extremely low temperatures during operation. </p><p num="0012">The foundation of the invention is the creation of aluminum alloy powders
having a very fine and stable grain structure. The fine grain structure, small grain
size, and other physical properties inherent to the invented alloy result in metal
components extruded or forged from the alloy powder which have high strength and
which maintain high strength and ductility even at very low temperatures. The alloy
powder is produced by blending aluminum and a secondary metal selected from
magnesium, lithium, silicon, titanium, and zirconium, and synthesizing
nanostructured materials from the powder, preferably by cryomilling. The secondary
metal is either alloyed with the aluminum prior to cryomilling or the magnesium and
aluminum are supplied as a blend and alloyed during the cryogenic milling. In either
situation, it is preferred that refractory material such as oxides, nitrides, carbides, and
borides, are not added to the metallic alloy prior to or during cryomilling.</p><p num="0013">The alloy of the invention is about 89 atomic % to about 99 atomic %
aluminum, and about 1 atomic% to about 11 atomic% of the secondary metal.
Optionally, the alloy contains up to 10 atomic% of a metal selected from Be, Ca, Sr,
Ba, Ra, Sc, V, Cr, Mn, Fe, Co, Ni, Cu, Zn, Y, Nb, Mo, Tc, Ru, Rh, Pd, Ag, Cd, W, or
combinations thereof.</p><p num="0014">Cryomilling the aluminum and secondary metal in accordance with this
invention provides a resultant metallic powder having a very stable grain structure.
The average grain size within the alloy is less than 0.5 µm, and alloys with average
grain size less than 0.1 µm may be produced. The small, stable grains of the alloy
allow components to be extruded or forged from the alloy which exhibit significantly
improved strength over similar alloys produced by other methods. The cryomilled
aluminum alloys also exhibit dramatically improved strength at low temperatures.</p><p num="0015">The method does not rely on the supplemental addition of oxides, nitrides, or
similar refractory substances, as do previously methods of cryomilling metals. The
invented alloy gains its strength from the unique composition of the material and the
unique processing techniques used in the milling of the alloy. Refractory materials
are preferably present within the invented alloy in amounts less than about 0.5
volume%. More preferably, refractory materials are present in amounts of less than
about 0.2%.</p><p num="0016">The aluminum and secondary metal are alloyed together and cryomilled as a
solid solution and, to a small degree, as a precipitate. Since liquid nitrogen is used as
the cooling solution for cryomilling, small amounts of nitrogen may be introduced 
into the alloy as a result of the exposure of the aluminum metal to nitrogen during the
cryomilling. It has been found that this nitrogen does not form refractory-type
nitrides to any appreciable degree. Once again, the alloy relies on unique grain
properties gained during processing, rather than the oxide/nitride dispersion
strengthening used in previous high strength cryomilled aluminum alloys.</p><p num="0017">After cryomilling of the alloy powder, the powder is maintained in a
substantially oxygen free atmosphere. Storage and handling in an argon or a dry
nitrogen atmosphere are the preferred means for maintaining the oxygen free
atmosphere. The oxygen is kept from the milled alloy so that the surface of the metal
particles will not oxidize: prior to being extruded. The argon or nitrogen atmospheres
also prevent the metal powder from absorbing moisture before further processing can
take place. The cryomilling results in an alloy with average grain size of less than 0.5
µm, and preferably less than 0.1 µm.</p><p num="0018">The milled metal powder is packed within a sealed can. The can provides a
form to the metal and also provides evacuation tubing for degassing the powder.
While in the can, the powder is heated to a temperature between about 600°F and
about 850°F and gaseous components within the powder are evacuated by a vacuum
pump connected to the evacuation tubing of the can. Temperature and pressure are
maintained until substantially all of the hydrogen and substantially all of any free
nitrogen are removed. At the conclusion of this degassing operation, the evacuation
tube is sealed by crimping and then welding.</p><p num="0019">After evacuation, the sealed can of powder is placed in a hot isostatic press.
The press is used to maintain the temperature of the metal powder between about
600°F and about 850°F while exerting a pressure upon the metal of between about 15
ksi (kilopounds/in<sup>2</sup>) and about 30 ksi. The pressure and temperature are maintained
until the metal reaches almost 100% of the metal's porosity free density.</p><p num="0020">After the metal powder is compressed, the consolidated metal alloy is extruded
at a temperature, extrusion ratio area, and ram speed appropriate for the particular
alloy. Extrusion is sufficient to form a wide variety of high strength components,
such as those to be used in a liquid fueled rocket engine. Those components that are
not adequately shaped by extrusion may be further forged into the desired shape.
Forging may also be used to provide additional ductility in directions other than the
extrusion axis. </p><p num="0021">The physical properties of the alloy are present within the invented alloy
powder produced in accordance with the invention. The extraordinary strength and
the ability of the alloy to maintain high strength at extremely low temperatures are
believed to be due to the unique grain structure, grain size, and interaction of
constituents of the alloy caused by the cryomilling process. The improved physical
properties of the alloy are exhibited when the alloy powder is compressed and
extruded into a solid metal component. The metal components produced from the
powder have an extremely high yield strength, between about 73 ksi and about 104
ksi, and ultimate tensile strength, between about 78 ksi and about 107 ksi. More
importantly, the metal alloys have the same or higher yield strength at low
temperatures, ranging from about 67 ksi to about 126 ksi at -320°F, and ranging from
about 78 ksi to about 106 ksi at -423°F. Similarly, the ultimate tensile strength of the
alloys ranges from about 78 ksi to about 129 ksi at -320°F and from about 107 ksi to
about 121 ksi at -423°F.</p><p num="0022">The invented alloys produced with the invented method therefore permit the
production of high strength components which have maintained or improved strength
at very low temperatures. The high strength alloys are well suited for use within
liquid fuel rocket motors, particularly as turbopump impellers and propellant ducts for
reusable launch vehicles. Components extruded or forged from the alloys are light
weight, but are able to resist the extreme forces and extremely low temperatures
experienced within the rocket engine. Thus, by utilizing the components formed from
the invented alloy, higher capacity, low weight rocket engines may now be
constructed.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading><p num="0023">Having thus described the invention in general terms, reference will now be
made to the accompanying drawing, which is not necessarily drawn to scale, and
wherein:
<sl><li>Figure 1 is a schematic flow diagram of a process embodiment of this
invention;</li><li>Figure 2 is a side sectional view of an exemplary ball mill and attritor for use
in an embodiment of this invention; </li><li>Figure 3 is a side sectional view of an exemplary extrusion apparatus in
accordance with the invention; and</li><li>Figure 4 is a composite image showing various stages of forging in accordance
with the invention.</li></sl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0024">The present invention now will be described more fully hereinafter with
reference to the accompanying drawings, in which preferred embodiments of the
invention are shown. This invention may, however, be embodied in many different
forms and should not be construed as limited to the embodiments set forth herein;
rather, these embodiments are provided so that this disclosure will be thorough and
complete, and will fully convey the scope of the invention to those skilled in the art.
Like numbers refer to like elements throughout.</p><p num="0025">As used herein, "alloy" describes the solid solution of aluminum and a
"secondary metal" selected from magnesium, lithium, silicon, titanium, and zirconium
which may or may not contain precipitated compounds of aluminum and the
secondary metal. In addition, the alloy may contain metal components such as Be,
Ca, Sr, Ba, Ra, Sc, V, Cr, Mn, Fe, Co, Ni, Cu, Zn, Y, Nb, Mo, Tc, Ru, Rh, Pd, Ag,
Cd, W, or combinations thereof. For convenience, the metals which may be used in
accordance with the invention other than aluminum and the secondary metals are
referred to hereinafter as "tertiary metals". As with any alloys, the invented alloy may
contain very low concentrations of a variety of contaminants or impurities. The
invented alloys do not, however, contain appreciable amounts of refractory materials
such as oxides, nitrides, borides, carbides, oxy-nitrides, or carbo-nitrides.</p><p num="0026">As used herein, "nanostructured material synthesis" or similar terminology
generally refers to methods of metal production which result in a material having
average grain sizes on the order of nanometers. For purposes of the disclosure,
nanostructured materials may include those alloys having an average grain size of 0.5
µm or less. For purposes of this invention, nanostructured material synthesis will also
include the addition of controlled amounts of nitrogen to the metal alloy.</p><p num="0027">Cryomilling in liquid nitrogen is the preferred method to develop the fine
grain size and also to incorporate nitrogen into the alloy. Therefore, cryomilling is
used as the exemplary synthesis method throughout the majority of the disclosure.
However, one skilled in the art could also produce this similar alloys using other 
common methods for formation of nanostructured materials, carried out in a
controlled nitrogen environment. These synthesis methods include, but are not
limited to, gas condensation, chemical vapor condensation, plasma synthesis, rapid
solidification of powder, and severe plastic deformation. Synthesis is always carried
out in a nitrogen environment in order to incorporate a limited, controlled amount of
nitrogen into the metal or alloy.</p><p num="0028">As used herein, "cryomilling" describes the fine milling of metallic
constituents at extremely low temperatures. Cryomilling takes place within a high
energy mill such as an attritor with metallic or ceramic balls. During milling, the mill
temperature is lowered by using liquid nitrogen. In an attritor, energy is supplied in
the form of motion to the balls within the attritor, which impinge portions of the metal
alloy powder within the attritor, causing repeated comminuting and welding of the
metal.</p><p num="0029">The high-strength metal alloy powders, extrusions, and forgings of this
invention begin as a pre-alloyed metal or as a combination of metals in the form of
small particulates or powder. The base metal of the alloy is aluminum, which makes
up about 89 atomic % to about 99 atomic % aluminum. The secondary metal is about
1 atomic% to about 11 atomic% of a secondary metal selected from magnesium,
lithium, silicon, titanium, and zirconium, or combinations thereof. Optionally, the
alloy contains a tertiary metal of up to 10 atomic% selected from Be, Ca, Sr, Ba, Ra,
Sc, V, Cr, Mn, Fe, Co, Ni, Cu, Zn, Y, Nb, Mo, Tc, Ru, Rh, Pd, Ag, Cd, W, or
combinations thereof.</p><p num="0030">By way of comparison, 11 atomic% of the secondary metal in aluminum is
equivalent to about 10 weight% magnesium, 3 weight% lithium, 11 weight%
silicon, 18 weight% titanium, or 30 weight% zirconium.</p><p num="0031">When intimately combined, mixed, and milled, the aluminum and secondary
metal form a solid solution containing small amounts of precipitated aluminum-secondary
metal. When magnesium is used as the secondary metal, the equilibrium
aluminum-magnesium precipitate formed is Al<sub>3</sub>Mg<sub>2</sub>, though other non-equilibrium
phases of the precipitate may also be present. Any other metals, optionally added to
the aluminum and magnesium mixture form a solid solution with the aluminum and
magnesium.</p><p num="0032">If the beginning metal powder is supplied as pre-alloyed powder, then it can
proceed directly to the cryomilling process. Metal powders that have not been 
previously alloyed can also proceed to the cryomilling step, since the cryomilling will
intimately mix the aluminum constituent with the secondary constituent and thereby
alloy the metals.</p><p num="0033">Prior to milling, it is preferred to handle the starting metal powders in a
substantially oxygen free atmosphere. For instance, the aluminum is preferably
supplied by atomizing the aluminum from an aluminum source and collecting and
storing the atomized aluminum in a container under an argon atmosphere. The
aluminum is held in the argon atmosphere, or in a dry nitrogen atmosphere,
throughout all handling, including the operation of mixing the aluminum powder with
the secondary metal prior to milling. Holding the raw aluminum within an argon or
nitrogen atmosphere prevents the surface of the aluminum particles from excessive
oxidation. The inert atmosphere also prevents contaminants such as moisture from
reacting with the raw metal powder. Since magnesium and other metals readily
oxidize, they are treated in the same manner as aluminum prior to milling. Thus, the
aluminum and other metal powders are supplied uncoated, meaning without a coating
of metal oxides.</p><p num="0034">The use of source metal powder having oxide coatings does not completely
destroy the strength and low temperature benefits gained through the invented
process, but alloys produced with a minimum of oxide content are preferred, and
alloys having almost no oxide content may be produced in accordance with this
invention. Further, supplemental refractory materials such as oxides, carbides,
nitrides, borides, oxy-nitrides, carbo-nitrides, and the like are not added to the alloy.
Though supplemental refractory dispersoids usually strengthen metal alloys through
dispersion strengthening, oxides occurring naturally upon the surface of the metal
starting materials are not preferred in the invented alloy, and supplemental refractory
dispersoids cause notable deterioration in the physical properties of the alloy.</p><p num="0035">Referring now to Figure 1, once the constituents of the aluminum alloy are
selected 10, the combined or pre-alloyed metal powder is cryomilled 15. As noted
above, cryomilling is the repeated comminuting and welding of the metal particles in
a very low temperature environment.</p><p num="0036">It is preferred that the cryomilling 15 of the very small particles of metal
powder take place within a ball attritor. As shown in Fig. 2, the ball attritor is
typically a cylindrical vessel 15a filled with a large number of ceramic or metallic
spherical balls 15b, preferably stainless steel. A single fixed-axis shaft 15c is 
disposed within the attritor vessel, and there are several radial arms 15d extending
from the shaft. As the shaft 15c is turned, the arms 15d cause the spherical balls 15b
to move about the attritor. When the attritor contains metal powder and the attritor is
activated, portions of the metal powder are impinged between the metal balls 15b as
they move about the attritor. The force of the metal balls 15b repeatedly impinges the
metal particles and causes the metal particles to be continually comminuted and
welded together. This milling of the metal powder effectively cold-works the metal.</p><p num="0037">Cold working imparts a high degree of plastic strain within the powder
particles. During cold working, the repeated deformation causes a buildup of
dislocation substructure within the particles. After repeated deformation, the
dislocations evolve into cellular networks that become high-angle grain boundaries
separating the very small grains of the metal. Grain diameters as small as
approximately 2.5 x 10<sup>-8</sup> meter have been observed via electron microscopy and
measured by x-ray diffraction at this stage in processing. Structures having
dimensions smaller than 10<sup>-7</sup> meter, such as those found in the metallic produced at
this stage in the invented process, are commonly referred to as nanostructured.</p><p num="0038">Stearic acid may be added as one of the components to be milled with the
metal powder. It promotes the fracturing and re-welding of metal particles during
milling, leading to more rapid milling, and leading to a larger fraction milled powder
produced during a given process cycle.</p><p num="0039">During milling 16, the metal powder is reduced to and held at a temperature of
approximately -320°F by exposure of the metal powder to liquid nitrogen. The liquid
nitrogen is a convenient way to lower the temperature of the entire cryomilling
system. Also, surrounding the metal powder in liquid nitrogen limits exposure of the
metal powder to oxygen or moisture. In operation, the liquid nitrogen is placed inside
the attritor, in contact with the metal particles and the attritor balls.</p><p num="0040">The operating parameters of the cryomilling 16 will depend upon the size of
the attritor. For example, a 150 liter (40 gal) attritor is preferably operated at a speed
of about 100 rpm. The amount of powder added to the attritor is dependent upon the
size and number of balls within the attritor vessel. For a 150 liter attritor filled with
640 kg of 0.25" diameter steel balls, up to approximately 20 kg of metal power may
be milled at any one time.</p><p num="0041">Milling 16 is continued for a time sufficient to reach an equilibrium
nanostructrue grain size within the metal. A milled metal powder having well 
dispersed metal constituents and metallic precipitate was found to be one that had
been cryomilled to an extent to provide a minimum nitrogen content of 0.3%.</p><p num="0042">After milling 16, the metal alloy powder is a homogenous solid solution of
aluminum and the secondary metal, optionally having other added tertiary metal
components and optionally having minor amounts of metallic precipitate interspersed
within the alloy. Grain structure within the alloy is very stable and grain size is less
than 0.5 µm. Depending on the alloy and extent of milling the average grain size is
less than 0.3 µm, and may be lower than 0.1 µm.</p><p num="0043">Not wishing to be bound by theory, a proposed mechanism for the
development of the stable fine grain size in this material is that the nitrogen that is
incorporated into the alloy during processing interacts with aluminum and the
secondary metal to provide the stability against grain growth. Discrete particles such
as nitrides are unobserved at magnifications up to 100,000x (sufficient to resolve
particles as small as 10<sup>-8</sup> m). Nevertheless, the free energy of formation of aluminum
nitride or of magnesium nitride may be characteristic of the effect of nitrogen in the
alloy. Both aluminum nitride and magnesium nitride have large negative free
energies of formation, -287.0 kJ/mole for AIN, and -400.5 kJ/mole for Mg<sub>3</sub>N<sub>2</sub>.
Nitrides of the other secondary metals (lithium, silicon, titanium and zirconium) also
have large negative free energies of formation. Also, magnesium and the other the
secondary metals each have a degree of solid solubility in aluminum.</p><p num="0044">After the metal alloy powder, with the proper composition and grain structure,
is produced, it is transformed into a form that may be shaped into a useful object. The
metal powder is canned 18, degassed 20, and then compacted and welded 25. After
the combined step of compacting and welding 25, also referred to as consolidating 25,
the metal is a solid mass which may be worked and shaped. The consolidated metal is
extruded 30 into a usable metal component, and forged 35 if necessary.</p><p num="0045">At all times from cryomilling 15 through the completion of consolidation 25,
the alloy powder is handled in either a dry nitrogen atmosphere or a vacuum. The
inert atmosphere prevents oxidation of the surface of the alloy powder particles. The
inert atmosphere further prevents the introduction of moisture to the alloy and
prevents other contaminants, which might be problematic in the extruded solid, from
entering the powder.</p><p num="0046">Canning 18 of the alloy powder involves placing the powder within a sealed
airtight container. The container, or can, is equipped with an evacuation port to be 
used in subsequent degassing 20. The alloy powder is degassed 20 while held in the
can. A vacuum pump is operatively attached to the evacuation port of the can and
used to provide a vacuum of approximately 10<sup>-6</sup> torr or better. The temperature of the
metal alloy is raised, concurrently with the vacuum treatment, to a temperature of
between about 600°F and about 850°F, and preferably about 775°F to about 850°F.
The elevated temperature and decreased pressure cause the evacuation of gaseous
components from the metal alloy powder.</p><p num="0047">The degassing 20 removes components of any stearic acid included with the
powder metal blend when cryomilled within the attritor. Hydrogen, which evolves
from the stearic acid, is the main degassed component. Nitrogen found within the
interstices of the powder, as well as nitrogen used to evacuate the can prior to packing
with the metal particles, is also degassed. Small amounts of oxygen or moisture
present within the powder may also be removed from the powder during the
degassing. Degassing 20 is theoretically continued until no free gas species remain in
the alloy powder, but is practically continued until the content of hydrogen is below 5
weight parts per million (wppm).</p><p num="0048">The fine grain size of the metal has the unique and useful property of being
stable on annealing to temperatures of about 850°F. This enables the powder to
endure the relatively high temperatures experienced during degassing 20 and
consolidation 25 while maintaining the fine grain size that contributes to strength.</p><p num="0049">After degassing 20, the can containing the alloy powder is sealed and is
transferred to a hot isostatic press (HIP). The temperature of the powder is either
maintained at between about 600°F to about 850°F after degassing 20 or, if the
temperature of the alloy has been allowed to drop, reheated to between about 600°F to
about 850°F. While maintaining the elevated temperature, the press is pressurized
with argon and the can is compressed within the press at a static pressure of between
about 15 ksi and about 30 ksi. The temperature and pressure exerted upon the metal
alloy powder cause the metal particles to be consolidated into a singular solid billet.
The pressure and temperature are maintained until the mass of consolidated metal is
nearly 100% free of porosity. Though pressing times will vary with the exact alloy
being consolidated, a typical hot isostatic pressing time will be approximately 4 hours.</p><p num="0050">After consolidation 25, the solid metal alloy is extruded 30. Extrusion 30 may
be used to form the solid into a blank for later forging or may be used to form the
solid metal directly into a usable part. The extrusion process typically alters the 
physical properties of the alloy somewhat. For instance, extrusion decreases the
hardness and increases the grain size of the consolidated billet. Also, tensile ductility
is notably improved after extrusion.</p><p num="0051">Referring to Figure 3, the consolidated alloy is typically shaped in the form of
a cylindrical billet 52 having a first diameter 58. The aluminum alloy billet 52 is
forced through a conical die 54 by a ram 56. When the consolidated alloy 52 is
extruded, the diameter of the billet is reduced to a second diameter 60 and the length
of the billet 52 is extended. For extrusion 30, the alloy is heated to a temperature
between about 350°F and 450°F, and preferably about 400°F. Extrusion 30 of the
alloy preferably occurs at greater than a 6 to 1 extrusion area ratio. The speed of the
rain 56 which forces the billet through the die 54 is preferably about 0.02 inches per
second. For a 3 inch diameter extrusion at an extrusion ratio of 7:1, this provides an
average strain rate of 0.025 sec<sup>-1</sup>.</p><p num="0052">Components formed from the metal alloy may be forged 35 if extrusion is not
capable of producing a part of the proper shape or size. It is also desired to forge
those components which need additional ductility in a direction other than the
direction of extrusion.</p><p num="0053">Prior to forging 35, the extruded blank is heated to a temperature of
approximately 600°F. Forging is carried out in a sequence of operations that provide
improved properties in the direction transverse to the extrusion axis. Forging also is
carried out to provide desired shapes. Figure 4 shows the results of each forging
process step. The extruded blank is forged 35 at a low strain rate, sufficient to shape
the component, and to provide isotropic structure and properties to the alloy. In one
embodiment, the first forging operation is an initial upset forging step. Strain rate
during the upset forging should be less than 0.02 per second. The upset forging
results in an alloy component having a form as shown as image 63. After upset
forging, the component next is forged in sequence along three perpendicular axes,
referred to as ABC forging, to thoroughly deform the material, breaking up particle
boundary structures, and providing improved properties in the direction transverse to
the extrusion axis. The result of ABC forging is shown as image 65. After ABC
forging, the alloy component is die forged, referred to as blocker forging, at a strain
rate as high as 0.1 per second, resulting in an alloy component such as shown as
image 67. After blocker forging, the alloy component is rapidly cooled to room
temperature or below in order to limit the growth of an Al-Mg intermetallic phase. </p><p num="0054">After blocker forging and cooling, the component is finish forged. Finish die
forging involves reheating the forged part to about 400°F and forging the part at a
strain rate of less than 0.1 per second, with the result shown as image 69. Overall
forging imparts a total strain to the alloy of from about 0.4 to about 0.8. After final
forging, the part is preferably air cooled. Forging of the metal forms high-strength
aluminum in sizes and shapes beyond those that are producible using extruded
product, provides isotropic mechanical properties, in contrast to extrusions, which
have lower ductility and toughness in directions transverse to the extrusion direction,
and provides a better balance of properties, trading strength to provide beneficial
tensile work hardening behavior that provides enhanced ductility and toughness.</p><p num="0055">The physical properties of the alloy are present within the invented alloy
powder produced in accordance with the invention, and are exhibited by the metal
alloy components formed through consolidation and extrusion of the metal, and
optionally by further forging of the metal. The extraordinary strength and the ability
of the alloy to maintain high strength at extremely low temperatures is believed to be
due to the unique grain structure, grain size, and interaction of constituents of the
alloy caused by the cryomilling process.</p><p num="0056">The high strength of the alloy produced in accordance with the invention is
unrelated to the dispersion of refractory materials such as oxides or nitrides within the
alloy. Samples of the cryomilled and consolidated alloy having a content of 7.5 wt.%
magnesium and the balance aluminum have been examined a number of times via
transmission electron microscopy (TEM) at magnifications up to 100,000x, which is
sufficient to resolve particles as small as 10<sup>-8</sup> m. Nitride particles or other second-base
particles were not observable at this level of resolution. The observed structure
is notably different from that of alloys having nitride or oxide additions that are
readably observable via TEM.</p><p num="0057">The metal components produced from the powder have an extremely high
yield strength, between about 73 ksi and about 104 ksi, and ultimate tensile strength,
between about 78 ksi and about 107 ksi. More importantly, the metal alloys have the
same or higher yield strength at low temperatures, ranging from about 67 ksi to about
126 ksi at -320°F, and ranging from about 78 ksi to about 106 ksi at -423°F.
Similarly, the ultimate tensile strength of the alloys ranges from about 78 ksi to about
129 ksi at -320°F and from about 107 ksi to about 121 ksi at -423°F. </p><p num="0058">Metallic constituents in addition to aluminum and secondary metals may be
combined into the metal alloy in accordance with the invented milling processes. For
instance, any or a combination of the tertiary metals listed above may be combined
with the aluminum and secondary metal. In particular, preferred alloys of
molybdenum, vanadium, tungsten, iron, nickel, cobalt, manganese, copper, niobium,
and chromium can be used in accordance with the processes of this invention to
produce an alloys having greater low temperature strength than corresponding
dispersion strengthened aluminum alloys and other aluminum alloys formed by
methods other than by the invented method.</p><p num="0059">An exemplary embodiment of an alloy which exhibits superior strength
characteristics is the alloy containing 1- 4.6% magnesium, 6 - 9 wt% zinc, 2 wt%
copper, 2 wt% cobalt, 0.2 wt% zirconium, and 0.2 wt% nickel by weight, with the
remainder being aluminum. Cryomilling, consolidating, and extruding the alloy
produces a metal part having room temperature and cryogenic temperature strength
superior to the basic aluminum-magnesium alloys. Table I below provides tensile
data for typical samples of the two materials produced in accordance with the
invention. The measurements were based upon a 0.4" diameter extrusion.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="6"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Alloy</entry><entry align="center">Temperature</entry><entry align="center">yield strength (ksi)</entry><entry align="center">ultimate tensile strength (ksi)</entry><entry align="center">elongation (%)</entry><entry align="center">reduction of area (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2.5 wt% Mg, 8.0 wt% Zn, 1.0 wt% Cu, 1.4 wt% Co, balance Al</entry><entry align="center">-320F</entry><entry align="center">126.8</entry><entry align="center">129.1</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="center">4.7</entry></row><row><entry align="center">7.5 wt% Mg, balance Al</entry><entry align="center">-320F</entry><entry align="center">100.4</entry><entry align="center">119.0</entry><entry align="center">3.6</entry><entry align="center">7.9</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables> </p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><heading><u style="single">Example 1: Production of aluminum / magnesium alloy</u></heading><p num="0060">Aluminum alloy powders of composition 6.7 wt% Mg + Al (balance) were
cryomilled, canned, degassed, consolidated, and extruded into a 3" diameter bar.
Cryomilling was carried out as follows. The attritor was filled with 640 kg grams of
0.25 inch diameter steel balls. Liquid nitrogen was flowed into the attritor. Flow was
maintained for at least about one hour to cool the balls and attritor until the rate of 
boil off was sufficiently low to allow the balls to become completely submerged in
the liquid nitrogen. A transfer hopper was loaded with 17445 grams of aluminum
powder, 2555 grams of 50 wt% aluminum 50 wt% magnesium powder, and 40
grams of stearic acid. Loading of the hopper was carried out in a glove box under dry
nitrogen purge. These components were transferred from the hopper into the attritor
by draining from the hopper into a tube inserted through the lid of the attritor vessel.
The attritor arms were then rotated in brief pulses to gradually move this powder
metal charge down into the liquid nitrogen and steel balls. Next, the attritor speed of
rotation was increased to 100 RPM and maintained at 100 RPM for 8 hours. Liquid
nitrogen level was maintained above the balls throughout this 8 hours. At the end of
the 8 hours, the milled metal powder with liquid nitrogen was drained through a Valve
in the bottom of the attritor into steel bins. These bins were loaded into a glovebox,
where the liquid nitrogen was allowed to boil off, which required approximately 6 to
10 hours. A dry nitrogen purge was maintained during and after boil off to avoid
exposing the powder to air or moisture. Dry powder was weighted and packed into
storage containers.</p> <p num="0061">The dry powder was loaded into a can approximately 11 inch diameter by 7
inch long. A can lid was welded on to close and seal the can. The can was evacuated
by a vacuum pump connected to tube welded to a port in the lid. The can was heated
to approximately 600°F while connected to the vacuum pump, to facilitate degassing
of the can. The can was held at 600°F until the vacuum, measured in the connecting
tube, reached a level that indicated that degassing was nearing completion. The can
was allowed to cool, then the evacuation tube was crimped and welded to seal the can.</p> <p num="0062">Next, the can and powder were hot isostatic pressed at 600°F and 15 ksi for 4
hours, consolidating the powder from about 65% to about 100%. The can was
removed from the compacted powder billet via machining. The billet was then
machined to a cylindrical shape, in preparation for extrusion. The billet was extruded
through conical dies, from a diameter of about 9 inches, to a diameter of about 3
inches, at a temperature of about 400F, at a ram speed of 0.02 inches per second. The
extrusion had the longitudinal tensile properties shown in Table II. The demonstrated
tensile properties of the alloys treated according to the invented method are superior
to corresponding alloys treated according to traditional techniques. <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">σ<sub>y</sub> (ksi)</entry> <entry align="center">σ<sub>u</sub> (ksi)</entry><entry align="center">elong.(%)</entry><entry align="center">Reduction in Area (RA) (%)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">70F</entry><entry align="center">83.0</entry><entry align="center">94</entry><entry align="center">5.7</entry><entry align="center">27.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">- 320F</entry><entry align="center">97.4</entry><entry align="center">109.3</entry><entry align="center">5.7</entry><entry align="center">23.3</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 2: Production of aluminum / magnesium alloy</u></heading><p num="0063">Aluminum alloy powders of composition 8.5 wt% Mg + Al (balance) were
cryomilled, canned, degassed, consolidated and extruded into a 3" diameter tube, wall
thickness 0.25" as described in Example 1. In this case, the extrusion area ratio was
23:1, the ram speed was 0.02 inches per second, and the average strain rate was 0.055
sec<sup>-1</sup>. The extrusion had the tensile properties shown in Table III. The extruded tube
exhibited physical properties that were superior to those of tubes having similar
metallic components produced by traditional methods.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">σ<sub>y</sub> (ksi)</entry><entry align="left">σ<sub>u</sub> (ksi)</entry><entry align="left">elong.(%)</entry><entry align="left">R.A.(%)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">70F - long.</entry><entry align="center">73.4</entry><entry align="center">78.3</entry><entry align="center">14.2</entry><entry align="center">31.5</entry></row><row><entry align="center">70F - trans.</entry><entry align="center">71.4</entry><entry align="center">77.5</entry><entry align="center">6.7</entry><entry align="center">13.6</entry></row><row><entry align="center">- 320F - long.</entry><entry align="center">85.8</entry><entry align="center">91.6</entry><entry align="center">12.2</entry><entry align="center">16.1</entry></row><row><entry align="center">- 320F - trans.</entry><entry align="center">85.6</entry><entry align="center">89.4</entry><entry align="center">7.0</entry><entry align="center">10.9</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 3: Production of Al/Mg/Zn/Cu/Co alloy</u></heading><p num="0064">Aluminum alloy powders of composition 2.5 wt% Mg + 8.0 wt% Zn + 1.0
wt% Cu + 1.4 wt% Co + Al (balance) (composition similar to AA7090) were
cryomilled, canned, degassed, consolidated and extruded into a 0.4" diameter
extrusion according to the method of Example 1. The extrusion had the longitudinal
tensile properties shown in Table IV, which are superior to those corresponding alloys
which were not treated in accordance to the invented method.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">σ<sub>y</sub> (ksi)</entry><entry align="left">σ<sub>u</sub> (ksi)</entry><entry align="left">elong.(%)</entry><entry align="left">R.A.(%)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">70F</entry><entry align="center">104.8</entry><entry align="left">107</entry><entry align="center">6.3</entry><entry align="left">7</entry></row><row><entry align="right">- 320F</entry><entry align="center">126.8</entry><entry align="left">129.</entry><entry align="center">1.8</entry><entry align="left">4.7</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 4: Production of aluminum / magnesium alloy</u></heading><p num="0065">Aluminum alloy powders of composition 6.7 wt% Mg + Al (balance) were
cryomilled, canned, degassed, consolidated and extruded into a 3" diameter bar. A
segment of the bar was subsequently forged into a small block. The block had the 
tensile properties shown in Table V, superior to corresponding alloys milled with
traditional methods.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">σ<sub>y</sub>(ksi)</entry><entry align="left">σ<sub>u</sub>(ksi)</entry><entry align="left">elong.(%)</entry><entry align="left">R.A.(%)</entry></row><row><entry align="right">70F</entry><entry align="center">74.2</entry><entry align="center">83.2</entry><entry align="center">11.7</entry><entry align="center">37.5</entry></row><row><entry align="right">- 320F</entry><entry align="center">85.2</entry><entry align="center">98.3</entry><entry align="center">11.8</entry><entry align="center">22.0</entry></row><row><entry align="right">- 423F</entry><entry align="center">105.9</entry><entry align="center">121.4</entry><entry align="center">7.1</entry><entry align="center">8.7</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 5: Production of aluminum / magnesium alloy</u></heading><p num="0066">Aluminum alloy powders of composition 8.8 wt% Mg + Al (balance) were
cryomilled, canned, degassed, consolidated and extruded into a 3" diameter bar
according to the method of Example 1. The bar was subsequently forged into a
pump-impeller-shaped forging. The forging had the tensile properties in the radial
direction shown in Table VI.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left">σ<sub>y</sub> (ksi)</entry><entry align="left">σ<sub>u</sub>(ksi)</entry><entry align="left">elong.(%)</entry><entry align="left">R.A.(%)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- 320F</entry><entry align="center">67.5</entry><entry align="center">78.5</entry><entry align="center">4.3</entry><entry align="center">4.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left">- 423F</entry><entry align="center">78.5</entry><entry align="center">100.7</entry><entry align="center">4.7</entry><entry align="center">7.4</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0067">As shown in the Examples above, aluminum alloys, extrusions, and forgings
produced in accordance with this invention exhibit high strength at ambient
temperatures and maintain high strength at reduced temperatures such as those
experienced in liquid rocket fuel engines. Thus, components produced in accordance
with the invention are particularly suited for use in low temperature situations.</p><p num="0068">Many modifications and other embodiments of the invention will come to
mind to one skilled in the art to which this invention pertains having the benefit of the
teachings presented in the foregoing descriptions and the associated drawings.
Therefore, it is to be understood that the invention is not to be limited to the specific
embodiments disclosed and that modifications and other embodiments are intended to
be included within the scope of the appended claims. Although specific terms are
employed herein, they are used in a generic and descriptive sense only and not for
purposes of limitation.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An aluminum alloy comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>89 atomic% to 99 atomic% aluminum;</claim-text><claim-text>1 atomic% to 11 atomic% of a secondary metal selected from
the group consisting of magnesium, lithium, silicon, titanium,
zirconium, and combinations thereof; and</claim-text><claim-text>up to about 10 atomic% of a tertiary metal selected from
the group consisting of Be, Ca, Sr, Ba, Ra, Sc, V, Cr, Mn, Fe,
Co, Ni, Cu, Zn, Y, Nb, Mo, Tc, Ru, Rh, Pd, Ag, Cd, W, and combinations
thereof;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein the alloy comprises at least 0.3 % nitrogen by
weight,
   wherein the alloy has an average grain size of less than
0.5 µm, and
   wherein the alloy is substantially free of refractory
materials.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The aluminum alloy of claim 1, wherein the secondary
metal is magnesium.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The aluminum alloy of claim 2, wherein the magnesium
is present in an amount of 4 weight% to 10 weight% of the alloy.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The aluminum alloy of any of claims 1 to 3, wherein
aluminum is present in an amount of 82 weight% to 96 weight%,
and the tertiary metals are selected from the group consisting
of zinc, copper, cobalt, zirconium, and nickel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The aluminum alloy of any of claims 1 to 4, comprising
6 weight% to 9 weight% zinc, less than 2 weight% copper,
less than 2 weight% cobalt, less than about 0.2 weight% zirconium,
and less than about 0.2 weight% nickel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The aluminum alloy of any of claims 1 to 5, wherein
the alloy has a stable grain structure up to at least 454°C
(850°F).</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The aluminum alloy of any of claims 1 to 6, wherein
the alloy is in the form of an extrusion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The aluminum alloy of any of claims 1 to 6, wherein
the alloy is in the form of a forging.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The aluminum alloy of any of claims 1 to 8, wherein
the alloy comprises less than about 0.5 volume% refractory
material.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An aluminum alloy consisting essentially of:
<claim-text><claim-text>89 atomic% to 99 atomic% aluminum;</claim-text><claim-text>1 atomic% to 11 atomic% of a secondary metal selected from
the group consisting of magnesium, lithium, silicon, titanium,
zirconium, and combinations thereof; and</claim-text><claim-text>up to about 10 atomic% of a tertiary metal selected from
the group consisting of Be, Ca, Sr, Ba, Ra, Sc, V, Cr, Mn, Fe,
Co, Ni, Cu, Zn, Y, Nb, Mo, Tc, Ru, Rh, Pd, Ag, Cd, W, and combinations
thereof; and,</claim-text><claim-text>at least 0.3 % nitrogen by weight.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The alloy of claim 10, wherein the alloy has an
average grain size of less than 0.5 µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A method of producing an aluminum alloy comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>providing a metal powder comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>89 atomic% to 99 atomic% aluminum;</claim-text><claim-text>1 atomic% to 11 atomic% of a secondary metal selected
from the group consisting of magnesium, lithium,
silicon, titanium, zirconium, and combinations
thereof; and</claim-text><claim-text>up to about 10 atomic% of a tertiary metal selected
from the group consisting of Be, Ca, Sr, Ba, Ra, Sc,
V, Cr, Mn, Fe, Co, Ni, Cu, Zn, Y, Nb, Mo, Tc, Ru, Rh,
Pd, Ag, Cd, W, and combinations thereof; and,</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text><claim-text>processing the metal powder with a nanostructured material
synthesis technique such that at least 0.3 weight% nitrogen
is added to the metal;</claim-text></claim-text>
   wherein refractory material is not added to the metal
during processing.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The method of claim 12, further comprising the step
of pre-alloying the provided metal powder prior to processing.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 12 or 13, wherein the
synthesis technique is selected from the group consisting of
cryomilling, gas condensation, chemical vapor deposition, plasma
synthesis, rapid solidification, and severe plastic deformation,
whereby a limited and controlled amount of nitrogen may
be introduced into the alloy.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The method of claim 14, wherein the synthesis technique
is cryomilling.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The method of claim 15, wherein the step of cryomilling
comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>supplying the metal powder to a ball mill attritor (15);</claim-text><claim-text>maintaining the supply of metal powder in a liquid nitrogen
medium;</claim-text><claim-text>activating the attritor (15), whereby the metal powder is
repeatedly impinged between metal balls (15b) within the attritor
(15);</claim-text><claim-text>deactivating the attritor (15); and,</claim-text><claim-text>removing the cryomilled metal powder from the attritor
(15).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 15 or 16, wherein the
step of cryomilling is continued until the equilibrium grain
size of the metal is reached.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 15 to 17, wherein the
step of cryomilling is continued for between 6 and 10 hours.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The method of claim 18, wherein the step of cryomilling
is continued for about 8 hours.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 12 to 19, wherein the
step of providing a metallic powder comprises providing a metallic
powder substantially free of oxides.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>The method of claim 20, wherein the metal powder is
provided in a substantially oxygen-free atmosphere.</claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 12 to 21, wherein the
secondary metal is magnesium.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>The method of claim 22, wherein the magnesium is
present in an amount of 4 weight% to 10 weight% of the alloy.</claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 12 to 23, wherein aluminum
is present in an amount of 82 weight% to 96 weight%, and
the tertiary metals are selected from the group consisting of
zinc, copper, cobalt, zirconium, and nickel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="25"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 12 to 24, comprising 6
weight% to 9 weight% zinc, less than 2 weight% copper, less
than 2 weight% cobalt, less than about 0.2 weight% zirconium,
and less than about 0.2 weight% nickel.</claim-text></claim><claim num="26"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 12 to 25, further comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>cryomilling the metallic powder in a liquid nitrogen atmosphere;</claim-text><claim-text>removing gaseous components from the cryomilled powder;</claim-text><claim-text>consolidating the cryomilled powder into a metallic billet
(52); and</claim-text><claim-text>extruding the metallic billet (52).</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="27"><claim-text>The method of claim 26, wherein gaseous components
are removed from the cryomilled powder by packing the cryomilled
powder into a can having an evacuation port and providing
a vacuum to the evacuation port, thereby evacuating gaseous
components from the powder.</claim-text></claim><claim num="28"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 26 to 27, wherein the
removal of gaseous components occurs at a temperature between
about 315°C (600°F) and about 455°C (850°F) for a time suffi-cient
to reduce hydrogen content to a level below about
30 wppm .</claim-text></claim><claim num="29"><claim-text>The method of any of claims 26 to 28, wherein consolidating
the cryomilled powder comprises compressing the
powder within a hot isostatic press.</claim-text></claim><claim num="30"><claim-text>The method of claim 29, wherein the step of extruding
the metal billet comprises preheating the consolidated metal
powder to about 204°C (400°F) and extruding the consolidated
powder with an extrusion area ratio of greater than 6:1 at a
ram speed of about 0.5 centimeters per minute (0.2 inches per
minute).</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>