<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1295969-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1295969" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="8178707" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030326"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1295969-A1" status="new" fvid="23699097"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1295969</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030326</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01122818-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01122818</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010922</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-01122818-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01122818</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010922</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  19/05        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  19/05        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  19/07        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C22C  19/07        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  24/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  24/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  26/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  26/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  26/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  26/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C30B  13/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C30B  13/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  24/10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  26/02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C30B  13/00+29/52</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Züchtung einer MCrAlY-Beschichtung und damit beschichteter Gegenstand</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Method of growing a MCrAIY-coating and an article coated with the MCrAIY-coating</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé pour la croissance d'un revêtement de MCrAlY ainsi qu'un objet revêtu de cet alliage</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-1001055-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1001055</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4743514-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4743514</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5312584-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5312584</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5993980-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5993980</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6024792-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6024792</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>ALSTOM SWITZERLAND LTD</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ALSTOM (SWITZERLAND) LTD</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ALSTOM (Switzerland) Ltd</last-name><address><street>Brown Boveri Strasse 7</street><city>5401 Baden</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>BEZENCON CYRILLE</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HOBEL MATTHIAS</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KHAN ABDUS S</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KONTER MAXIM</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KURZ WILLFRIED</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SCHNELL ALEXANDER</name><address><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>BEZENCON CYRILLE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HOBEL MATTHIAS</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KHAN ABDUS S</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KONTER MAXIM</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KURZ WILLFRIED</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SCHNELL ALEXANDER</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>BEZENCON CYRILLE</last-name><address><street>Combaz 6</street><city>CH-1844Villeneuve</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HOBEL MATTHIAS</last-name><address><street>Dorfstrasse 82</street><city>CH 5210 Windisch</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KHAN ABDUS S</last-name><address><street>Limmatauweg 2</street><city>CH 5408Ennetbaden</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KONTER MAXIM</last-name><address><street>Sommerweg 13</street><city>CH 5313 Klingnau</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KURZ WILLFRIED</last-name><address><street>Creux-de Corsy 9</street><city>CH-1093 La Conversion</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SCHNELL ALEXANDER</last-name><address><street>Sonnenbergstrasse 14</street><city>CH 5408 Ennetbaden</city><country>CH</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties> <international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country> <country>DK</country> <country>ES</country> <country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A gas turbine component consists of a superalloy base material with a single
crystal structure and a protective MCrAIY-coating. The MCrAIY-coating the
MCrAIY has a γ/β-phase and single crystal structure, which is epitaxial with
the base material.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="118"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>FIELD OF INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0001">The invention relates to a method of epitaxially growing a MCrAIY-coating
according to the preamble of claim 1 and to an article coated with the MCrAIY-coating
according to the preamble of claim 4.</p><heading><b>STATE OF THE ART</b></heading><p num="0002">Components designed for the use in the area of high temperature, e.g. blades
or vanes of a gas turbine, are usually coated with resistant coatings. The
coating protects the base material against corrosion and oxidation due to the
thermal effect of the hot environment and consists of an alloy mostly using the
elements Al and Cr. Most turbine components are coated for the protection
from oxidation and/or corrosion with, for example, a MCrAIY coating (base
coat) and some are also coated with a thermal barrier coating (TBC) for thermal
insulation. MCrAIY protective overlay coatings are widely known in the
prior art. They are a family of high temperature coatings, wherein M is selected 
from one or a combination of iron, nickel and cobalt. As an example
US-A-3,528,861 or US-A-4,585,481 are disclosing such kind of oxidation
resistant coatings. US-A-4,152,223 as well discloses such method of coating
and the coating itself. Besides the γ/β-MCrAlY-coating, there is another class
of overlay MCrAIY coatings which are based on a γ/γ'-gamma/gamma prime-structure.
The advantages of γ/γ'-coatings is that they have a negligible thermal
expansion mismatch with alloy of the underlying turbine article. For higher
thermal fatigue resistance the γ/γ'-coating are more convenient compared to
the γ/β-type of MCrAIY-coatings. A higher thermal fatigue resistance in coatings
is most desirable since failure of the most turbine blades and vanes at
elevated temperature is typically thermal fatigue driven.</p><p num="0003">Among γ/γ'-coatings and γ/β-coatings, the field of γ/β-coatings have been an
active area of research and a series of patents has been issued. E.g. a NiCrAlY
coating is described in US-A-3,754,903 and a CoCrAlY coating in US-A-3,676,058.
US-A-4,346,137 discloses an improved high temperature fatigue
resistance NiCoCrAlY coating. US-A-4,419,416, US-A-4,585,481, RE-32,121
and US-A-A-4,743,514 describe MCrAIY coatings containing Si and Hf. US-A-4,313,760
discloses a superalloy coating composition with good oxidation,
corrosion and fatigue resistance.</p><p num="0004">In contrast to the γ/β-coatings, the γ/γ'-type of MCrAIY coatings, known e.g.
from US-A-4,973,445, are relatively new. The unique feature of this type of
γ/γ'-coatings is that their thermal expansion mismatch is close to zero in combination
with a high ductility, what make these coatings more resistant to
thermal fatigue. However the limitations are the low aluminum content and
hence their low reservoir of aluminum.</p><p num="0005">Furthermore, US-A-4,758,480 discloses a class of coatings whose composition
is based on the composition of the underlying substrate. The similarity in
phase structure and in the chemical composition renders the mechanical
properties of the coating similar to those of the substrate thereby reducing
thermomechanically-reduced damage during service. However, when this 
coating is applied by traditional means on the single crystal substrate, the
difference in the E-modulus between &lt;010&gt; oriented surface layer of the
substrate and randomly oriented coating grains produce high TMF damage.</p><p num="0006">US-A- 5,232,789 discloses the further improvement of the TMF properties of
the coating-substrate system. The coating, which has composition and phase
structure similar to the substrate alloy, has at least 1000 times more fine-grained
structure, produced by a special technology. The lowermost interface
portion of the fine-grained coating grows epitaxially, and therefore has the
same crystal orientation as the substrate. Epitaxial growth solves also coating
/ substrate interface adhesion problem.</p><p num="0007">However, the system of a single crystal substrate and the multicrystal coating
still has a large difference in the mechanical behavior between the substrate
and the coating as any equiaxed structure possesses E-modulus much higher
than those for single crystal material in &lt;001&gt; direction. Higher E-modulus
reflects in lower TMF life of the coating compared to the substrate (although
the stresses on substrate-coating interface are significantly reduced compared
to the traditional coating - substrate system). Multiple grain boundaries drastically
reduce the creep resistance of the fine-grain coating, which finally determines
life of the entire blading system.</p><p num="0008">Therefore, in general, US-A-6,024,792 is disclosing a method for producing
monocrystalline structures on substrates with monocrystalline structures by
using an energy beam of high energy from an energy source. The material
which is to be introduced into the monocrystalline structure is supplied to the
melted region of the substrate. The supplied material is completely melted. An
similar method is known from EP-A1-740 977.</p><p num="0009">More special, EP-A1-1 001 055 is disclosing a MCrAIY-coating and a method
of depositing the coating, whereby the coating is epitaxially on the base material
and the coating is grown with a single crystal structure. The coating is
applied by laser cladding. It was found, in fact, that it was difficult to grown a
defect free epitaxial coating with the mentioned γ (gamma) /γ' (gamma prime) 
forming coating material within this document. When using other commercially
available highly oxidation resistant alloys for the laser cladding process, the
single crystal microstructure can not be maintained. Hot tearing cracks and
the breakdown of single crystal solidification occur in the cladded structure,
which results in the formation of undesirable equiaxed grains.</p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0010">It is object of the present invention to find a method of depositing a γ/β-MCrAlY-coating
and to determine in detail the parameter of a defect and crack
free coating material, which is epitaxial with the base material, and, in addition,
the parameter of the method of depositing. The epitaxial coating is grown
on the single crystal substrate, which means that it has the same crystallographic
orientation as the substrate.</p><p num="0011">According to the invention a method of depositing a bond MCrAIY-coating
according to the preamble of claim 1 was found, wherein the MCrAIY-coating
material is melted on the surface of the article and epitaxially solidified and
wherein the MCrAIY is composed in a way that during solidification of the
applied MCrAIY-coating material first a γ (gamma)-phase is solidified and,
subsequently, a β (beta)-phase.</p><p num="0012">According to the invention a bond MCrAIY-coating according to the preamble
of claim 4 was found, wherein the MCrAIY has a γ/β-phase. The composition
of MCrAIY is made in a way that during solidification of the applied MCrAIY-coating
material first a γ (gamma)-phase precipitates and, subsequently, the β
(beta)-phase.</p><p num="0013">Advantageous, the MCrAIY-coating has a solidification interval ΔT<sub>0</sub> of smaller
than 30° C, whereby it has to have a temperature interval ΔT<sub>1</sub> of the last 5%
liquid of smaller than 15° C. Both factors, determine the width of the mushy
zone, the narrower the mushy zone the lower is the susceptibility for hot tearing 
during the cladding process. Narrow mushy zone means that little interdendritic
liquid is subjected to shrinkage stresses during the process.</p><p num="0014">The chemical composition of the new coating should be as close as possible
to the eutectic line of the γ and β-phase, on the γ-phase side of the eutectic
line of the phase diagram nickel - aluminum - chromium ternary. When the
chemical composition of the coating is close to the eutectic line, the change in
the chemical composition of the residual liquid during the solidification process
will be minor resulting in a better SX cladding behavior.</p><p num="0015">As an example, the coating has the following composition (wt.-%) 15 - 30%
Cr, 5.0 - 10% Al, 0.1 - 1.2 % Si, 0.4 - 1.2 Y, 0 - 0.1 Hf, 0.1 - 1.2 Ta, Balance
Ni or Co with Σ (Al + Si) &lt; 11.5 wt.-%, Σ (Si + Ta) &lt; 2.5 wt.-%, Σ (Y+ Hf + Zr
+La) &lt; 1.5 wt.-%, C: max. 0.03 wt.-%, Ca: 0 - 1 wt.-% and Mg: 0-1 wt.-%.</p><p num="0016">According the invention and to obtain a small solidification interval the coating
comprises an addition of (wt.-%) Si &lt; 1.0 %, Hf &lt; 0.5 % , Y &lt; 0.5 %, Ta &lt; 3 %
and Zr &lt; 0.3 % individually or a combination thereof. For increased oxidation
resistance the coating will comprise an addition of Fe, Ga, Mg, Ca individually
or a combination thereof.</p><p num="0017">In an advantages embodiment, the MCrAIY-coating is applied by laser cladding
with a thickness of 100 to 300 µm and the article is a gas turbine component
made a from nickel base super alloy.</p><heading><b>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF DRAWINGS</b></heading><p num="0018">This invention is illustrated in the accompanying drawing, in which
<dl compact="compact" tsize="6"><dt><b>Fig. 1</b></dt><dd>shows a schematic representation of a laser cladding process</dd><dt><b>Fig. 2</b></dt><dd>shows an example of an epitaxially γ/β-MCrAIY-coating according to
the invention and</dd><dt><b>Fig. 3</b></dt><dd>shows an example of a non epitaxially γ/β-MCrAIY-coating.</dd></dl></p><p num="0019">The drawings show only parts important for the invention.</p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0020">This invention is related to a method of epitaxially growing a MCrAIY-coating 6
having a γ/β-microstructure onto a surface 5 of an article 4 such as blades or
vanes of gas turbines or any other part which is exposed to a hot temperature
environment. The article 4 has a single crystal (SX) structure and can be
made, as an example, from a nickel base super-alloy. Nickel base superalloys
are known in the state of the art, e.g. from the document US-A-5,888,451, US-A-5,759,301
or from US-A-4,643,782, which is known as "CMSX-4". In general,
figure 1 shows a laser cladding process which is characterized by impinging
particles of the MCrAIY-coating material with a powder jet 1 onto a
molten pool 2 formed by controlled laser heating by scanning the laser beam
3 successively over the surface 5 of the single crystal article 4. The arrow 7
shows the direction of the movement over the article 4.</p><p num="0021">The laser cladding technology has been used to apply an epitaxial MCrAIY-coating
6 with 100 - 300 µm thickness on the single crystal superalloy article
4. The coating 6 has a γ/β-structure and is epitaxially grown on the article 4,
which means that it has the same crystal orientation as the article 4.</p><p num="0022">According to the invention during solidification of the melted MCrAIY-coating 6
onto a surface 5 of an article 4 due to the composition of the MCrAIY-coating
first a γ (gamma)-phase is solidified and, subsequently, a β (beta)-phase. The
γ or γ'-phases within MCrAIY coatings and in superalloy base materials are
face-cubic centered (fcc) structured. A β phase is, in contradiction, base-cubic
centered (bcc) structured, i.e. there is a lattice mismatch between the γ and
the β phase. When the β phase is growing onto the γ substrate this lattice
mismatch leads immediately to internal stresses, which always results in
cracking. When the β phase is the second phase to solidify, which means the
β-phase is solidifying in the interdendritc areas, hot tearing can easily be
avoided because the bcc structured β-phase. The β-phase shrinks less during 
solidification compared to the γ-phase and has a larger volume than the γ
phase, which means minor shrinkage during solidification, and is therefore
stabilizing the γ dendrites as they grow. Due to facts mentioned above the
coating has a very low susceptibility for hot tearing and cracking during stress
relief heat treatments. Thus, the coating is crack free. Subsequently, the cladding
of the γ/β-coating gives a higher flexibility in the laser process parameters
such as cladding speed and laser power, which leads in an increased process
window.</p><p num="0023">Therefore the chemical composition of the new coating 6 should be close to
the eutectic line of the γ and β-phase, on the γ-phase side of the eutectic line
of the phase diagram nickel - aluminum - chromium ternary. When the
chemical composition of the coating is close to the eutectic line, the change in
the chemical composition of the residual liquid during the solidification process
will be minor resulting in a better SX cladding behavior.</p><p num="0024">Furthermore, it has be found that the following factors are critical for the successful
epitaxial growth of the MCrAIY-coating 6 having the γ/β-structure. The
solidification interval ΔT<sub>0</sub> of the coating 6 must be narrow, e.g. smaller than
30°C.</p><p num="0025">A γ/β-MCrAIY-coating 6 according to the invention has the following preferred
range of (wt.-%): 15 - 30% Cr, 5.0 - 10 % Al, 0.1 -1.2 % Si, 0.4 - 1.2 Y, 0 -
0.1 Hf, 0.1 - 1.2 Ta, balance Ni or Co and unavoidable impurities with Σ (Al +
Si) &lt; 11.5 %, Σ (Si + Ta) &lt; 2.5 %, Σ (Y+ Hf + Zr +La) &lt; 1.5 %, C max. 0.03 %,
Ca: 0 - 1 % and Mg: 0-1 %.</p><p num="0026">In an advantageous embodiment the concentration of minor elements in the
coating, i.e. Y, Hf, Si, Zr and Ta must be adjusted to design the solidification
behavior of the coating alloy. Some of those elements widen the solidification
interval e.g. Si. This results in the formation of interdentric liquid with low solidus
temperature phases with hot tearing phenomena (solidification cracking).
The concentration of the minor elements such as Y, Zr and Ta must be adjusted 
to avoid formation of brittle phases containing these elements and
sensitive to cracking under residual stresses produced during cooling after
solidification. Thus, according to the invention and to obtain a small solidification
interval, the following conditions have to be fulfilled (wt.-%) Si &lt; 1.0 %, Hf
&lt; 0.5 %, Y &lt; 0.5 %, Ta &lt; 3 % and Zr &lt; 0.3 %.</p><p num="0027">Another important factor is that the last 5% liquid must be smaller than 15°C.
Both factors, the small solidification interval and the temperature interval ΔT<sub>1</sub>
of the last 5% liquid determine the width of the mushy zone, the narrower the
mushy zone the lower is the susceptibility for hot tearing during the cladding
process. Narrow mushy zone means that little interdendritic liquid is subjected
to shrinkage stresses during the process.</p><p num="0028">The coating 6 may contain the elements Si, Hf and Zr and a small addition of
Ta, Fe, Ga, Mg, Ca individually or a combination thereof as well for increased
oxidation resistance.</p><p num="0029">Examples for the coating according to the invention is shown in table 1 (wt.-%)
<tables><table><tgroup cols="11"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Example</entry><entry align="center">Ni</entry><entry align="center">Co</entry><entry align="center">Cr</entry><entry align="center">Al</entry><entry align="center">Re</entry><entry align="center">Ta</entry><entry align="center">Si</entry><entry align="center">Y</entry><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">ΔT<sub>0</sub> [°C]</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I</entry><entry align="center">Bal.</entry><entry align="center">24</entry><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="center">11.5</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">1.2</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="center">II</entry><entry align="center">Bal.</entry><entry align="center">36</entry><entry align="center">22</entry><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">80</entry></row><row><entry align="center">III</entry><entry align="center">Bal.</entry><entry align="center">40</entry><entry align="center">23</entry><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="center">--</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">25</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0030">The ΔT<sub>0</sub> of Coating I, II and III respectively are 100°C, 80°C and 25°C, The
coating I could not be grown epitaxially due to the fact the here beta phase
appears first and, thus, an equiaxed structure is formed. The coating II also
behaved similarly. In according to the invention the coating III could be grown
defect free and epitaxially.</p><p num="0031">On the other hand, when the laser parameters e.g. such as laser power,
scanning speed, protection gas are optimized and balanced against each
other for the deposition of the single crystal MCrAIY coating 6 onto a single 
crystal base material. The alloys design of the newly MCrAIY coatings enables
the maintenance and growth of the SX coating.</p><p num="0032">The Example of Fig. 2 shows a workpiece as a result of a coating from this
invention with a fully SX-structure and no cracks. The conditions of the annexed
claims have been fulfilled. The very even and parallel dendrite structure
indicate the SX structure of the clad, this has been also proven with the Electron
Back Scattering Diffraction (EBSD) Kikuchi technique.</p><p num="0033">In contradiction, Fig. 3 shows an example of a non-epitaxially nucleation at the
CMSX-4 substrate with a coating according example I in table 1. It shows an
alloy, where β phase is the first phase to solidify. The bright dendrites which
are visible is the re-melted base material. Although cladded with optimized
laser parameters the coating material was very difficult to apply. Outside of
the rage of the conditions of the claims it is very susceptible to hot tearing and
breakdown of single crystal structure.</p><heading><b>REFERENCE NUMBERS</b></heading><p num="0034"><dl compact="compact" tsize="1"><dt>1</dt><dd>powder jet</dd><dt>2</dt><dd>molten pool</dd><dt>3</dt><dd>laser beam</dd><dt>4</dt><dd>article</dd><dt>5</dt><dd>surface of article 4</dd><dt>6</dt><dd>coating</dd><dt>7</dt><dd>direction of movement</dd></dl><dl compact="compact" tsize="3"><dt>ΔT<sub>0</sub></dt><dd>Solidification interval of coating 6</dd><dt>ΔT<sub>1</sub></dt><dd>Solidification interval of the last 5% of liquid of the coating 6</dd></dl></p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method of epitaxially growing a MCrAIY-coating (6) onto a surface (5) of
an article (4), the article (4) having a single crystal structure, wherein the
MCrAIY-coating (6) has a γ/β - structure and the coating material is melted
on the surface (5) of the article (4) and epitaxially solidified and wherein
the MCrAIY is composed in a way that during solidification of the applied
MCrAIY-coating material first a γ (gamma)-phase is solidified and, subsequently,
a β (beta)-phase.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method according to claim 1, wherein the MCrAIY-coating (6) solidifies
in a solidification interval (ΔT0) of smaller than 30° C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method according to claim 1, wherein the last 5% of the MCrAIY-coating
(6) liquid solidifies in a temperature interval smaller than 15°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method according to claim 1, wherein the MCrAIY-coating (6) is applied
by laser cladding.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An article (4) having a surface (5) and a single crystal structure, the article
(4) coated with protective MCrAIY-coating (6), which MCrAIY (6) is epitaxially
grown on the surface (5) of the article (4), wherein the MCrAIY has a
γ/β-phase.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The article (4) according to claim 4, wherein the composition of MCrAIY is
made in a way that during solidification of the applied MCrAIY-coating
material first a γ (gamma)-phase precipitates and, subsequently, the β
(beta)-phase.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The article (4) according to claim 5 or 6, wherein the MCrAIY-coating (6)
has a solidification interval (ΔT0) of smaller than 30° C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The article (4) according to claim 5 or 6, wherein the MCrAIY-coating (6)
has a temperature interval (ΔT1) of the last 5% liquid of smaller than 15° C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The article (4) according to claim 5 or 6, wherein the chemical composition
of the new coating 6 is be close to the eutectic line of the γ and β-phase,
on the γ-phase side of the eutectic line of the phase diagram nickel - aluminum
- chromium ternary.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The article (4) according to claim 5 or 6, wherein the MCrAIY-coating (6)
has a thickness of 100 to 300 µm.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The article (4) according to claim 5 or 6, wherein the MCrAIY-coating (6) is
applied by laser cladding.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The article (4) according to claim 5 or 6, wherein the MCrAIY-coating (6) is
crack free.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The article (4) according to claim 5 or 6, wherein the coating (6) has the
following composition (wt.-%) 15 - 30% Cr, 5.0 - 10 % Al, 0.1 -1.2 % Si,
0.4 - 1.2 Y, 0 - 0.1 Hf, 0.1 - 1.2 Ta, balance Ni or Co and unavoidable impurities
with Σ (Al + Si) &lt; 11.5 %, Σ (Si + Ta) &lt; 2.5 %, Σ (Y+ Hf + Zr +La) &lt;
1.5 %, C max. 0.03 %, Ca: 0 - 1 % and Mg: 0-1 %.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The article (4) according to claim 5 or 6, wherein the coating (6) comprises
an addition of (wt.-%) Si &lt; 1.0 %, Hf &lt; 0.5 %, Y &lt; 0.5 %, Ta &lt; 3 % and Zr
&lt; 0.3 % individually or a combination thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The article (4) according to claim 5 or 6, wherein the coating (6) comprises
an addition of Fe, Ga, Mg, Ca individually or a combination thereof</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The article (4) according to any of the claims 5 to 15, wherein it is a gas
turbine component made from nickel base super alloy.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>