<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-0995803-A2" country="EP" doc-number="0995803" kind="A2" lang="EN" family-id="26476631" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20000426"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-0995803-A2" status="new" fvid="22823340"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0995803</doc-number><kind>A2</kind><date>20000426</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-99120056-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>99120056</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19991019</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-14554899-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>14554899</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990525</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-29889698-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>29889698</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19981020</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C12Q   1/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C12Q   1/00B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Kit zum Probebehandeln und Verfahren zum Probebehandeln für Analyse mit einem Biosensor</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Sample treating kit and sample treating method using the same for analysis with a biosensor</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Kit pour traiter un échantillon et procédé pour traiter un échantillon en l'utilisant pour analyse avec un biocapteur</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0537761-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0537761</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0732406-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0732406</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-5240828-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>5240828</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-59006897-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>59006897</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-7083871-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>7083871</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 008, no. 085 (C-219), 18 April 1984 (1984-04-18) &amp; JP 59 006897 A (SEKISUI KAGAKU KOGYO KK), 13 January 1984 (1984-01-13)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 017, no. 699 (P-1665), 21 December 1993 (1993-12-21) &amp; JP 05 240828 A (KANZAKI PAPER MFG CO LTD), 21 September 1993 (1993-09-21)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 1995, no. 06, 31 July 1995 (1995-07-31) &amp; JP 07 083871 A (MATSUSHITA ELECTRIC IND CO LTD), 31 March 1995 (1995-03-31)</text><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MATSUSHITA ELECTRIC IND CO LTD</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MATSUSHITA ELECTRIC INDUSTRIAL CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MATSUSHITA ELECTRIC INDUSTRIAL CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>1006, Ohaza Kadoma</street><city>Kadoma-shi, Osaka 571-8501</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>MIYASHITA MARIKO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>NANKAI SHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>YOSHIOKA TOSHIHIKO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MIYASHITA, MARIKO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NANKAI, SHIRO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YOSHIOKA, TOSHIHIKO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MIYASHITA, MARIKO</last-name><address><street>16-2 Takaginishimachi</street><city>Nishinomiya-shi, Hyogo 663-8032</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NANKAI, SHIRO</last-name><address><street>4-50-12 Nasuzukuri</street><city>Hirakata-shi, Osaka 573-0071</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>YOSHIOKA, TOSHIHIKO</last-name><address><street>15-15-307 Takatsuka-cho</street><city>Hirakata-shi, Osaka 573-0035</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Dr. Elisabeth Jung Dr. Jürgen Schirdewahn Dipl.-Ing. Claus Gernhardt</last-name><address><street>Clemensstrasse 30</street><city>80803 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties> <international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country> </ep-contracting-states> </designated-states> </international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention provides a sample solution
treating instrument facilitating rapid and simplified
adjustment of the condition of a sample solution proper
for analysis with a biosensor before supply to the
biosensor. The sample solution treating instrument in
accordance with the present invention comprises control
means, such as a catalyst or an adsorbent, for example,
which can remove any interfering substance for adjusting
the sample solution proper for measurement with a
biosensor.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="63" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="58"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to an instrument
for treating a sample solution to be supplied to a
biosensor for analysis and a method for treating a sample
solution using the same. More specifically, the present
invention relates to a sample treating kit and a sample
treating method using the same for analysis with a
biosensor.</p><p num="0002">One method for simple quantitative measurement
of a specific component contained in a sample solution is
to determine oxidation current by reacting, in the
presence of an electron acceptor, the specific component
with an oxidoreductase corresponding to the substrate of
the specific component and electrochemically oxidizing the
reduced electron acceptor.</p><p num="0003">Biosensors using this measurement principle
enable measurement of various substances if a proper
oxidoreductase corresponding to the substrate of an
analyte is selected.</p><p num="0004">However, since such biosensor makes analysis
with the aid of enzyme reaction and electrode reaction,
smooth progress of the enzyme reaction and electrode 
reaction is mandatory in order to improve measurement
accuracy of the biosensor.</p><p num="0005">Therefore, there are several studies to enhance
enzyme activity by adjusting temperature and pH of the
sample solution or remove any interfering substance with
the enzyme or electrode reaction.</p><p num="0006">Moreover, sample solutions may sometimes include
oxidizable substances which may produce oxidation current
due to their concurrent oxidation with the electron
acceptor and generate a positive error in the measured
oxidation current. This can result in impaired
measurement accuracy of the biosensor. Therefore,
reduction of adverse effects of such oxidizable substance
to a minimum becomes a requisite.</p><p num="0007">Conventional biosensors are installed with means
for solving the above-mentioned problems inside their
measurement system.</p><p num="0008">Here, the operation of measurement of a flow
injection analyzer (YSI MODEL 2700 SELECT, made by Yellow
Spring Instrument Co., Inc.) as a biosensor using an
immobilized enzyme membrane and electrode reaction will be
described as one example.</p><p num="0009">The measurement system of this analyzer
comprises an electrode system including at least a working
electrode and a counter electrode, an immobilized enzyme
membrane attached to the electrode system, a sample 
chamber to which a sample solution is supplied to make
measurement there, and an electric circuitry connected to
the electrode system.</p><p num="0010">First, one end of an aspiration tube for
aspirating a sample whose other end communicates with the
sample chamber is immersed in a sample solution and the
solution is aspirated by the tube and supplied to the
sample chamber through the communicating other end. At
that time, a certain amount of buffer solution is
aspirated by another aspiration tube and supplied to the
sample chamber.</p><p num="0011">Subsequently, the sample solution and the buffer
solution thus supplied are mixed by agitation using a
stirrer installed in the sample chamber. When a certain
time has passed after supply of the sample solution and
buffer solution, electrochemical measurement is performed
to quantitate the analyte in the sample solution.</p><p num="0012">Any analyzer having such structure adjusts pH of
the sample solution to a suited pH for enzyme reaction and
dilutes the sample solution to an appropriate
concentration by supplying the buffer solution to the
sample chamber.</p><p num="0013">Concurrent agitation of the sample solution and
buffer solution facilitates their rapid mixing on one hand
and promotes dissolution of the enzyme in the mixed
solution on the other hand. This in turn enables supply 
of sufficient oxygen to proceed enzyme reaction.</p><p num="0014">Despite the above advantages, such analyzer
requires exchange of the immobilized enzyme membrane with
a proper one depending on the analyte. Moreover, since
the pH range proper for enzyme reaction varies by enzyme,
the buffer solution must be exchanged concurrently. This
renders manipulation of the analyzer inconvenient.</p><p num="0015">Although dilution of the sample solution reduces
adverse effects of the interfering substances hindering
enzyme and electrode reactions and the oxidizable
substance, complete elimination of these effects is much
difficult. This limits the extent of improvement of the
measurement accuracy.</p><heading>BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0016">A primary object of the present invention is,
therefore, to provide a sample solution treating
instrument that facilitates simple adjustment of a sample
solution to be supplied to a biosensor for analysis to a
condition facilitating rapid analysis with high accuracy.</p><p num="0017">Another object of the present invention is to
provide a method for treating a sample solution to be
supplied to a biosensor for analysis, using the above
sample solution treating instrument.</p><p num="0018">The present invention provides a sample solution
treating instrument for formulating a sample solution to 
be supplied to a biosensor for analysis, comprising
control means for placing the sample solution in a proper
condition for analysis with the biosensor.</p><p num="0019">The method for treating a sample solution in
accordance with the present invention comprises the steps
of introducing a sample solution, which will be supplied
to a biosensor for analysis, into the above sample
solution treating instrument, and adjusting the sample
solution closest to a proper condition for analysis with
the biosensor.</p><p num="0020">In a preferred mode of the present invention,
the control means has a catalyst located inside the
instrument for converting an interfering substance in the
sample solution to a harmless substance having no adverse
effect on the measurement results.</p><p num="0021">In another preferred mode of the present
invention, the control means has an adsorbent located
inside the instrument for adsorbing and removing an
interfering substance in the sample solution.</p><p num="0022">In a further preferred mode of the present
invention, the control means has a buffer agent located
inside the instrument for adjusting pH of the sample
solution to a proper pH for the activity of an enzyme in
the biosensor.</p><p num="0023">While the novel features of the invention are
set forth particularly in the appended claims, the 
invention, both as to organization and content, will be
better understood and appreciated, along with other
objects and features thereof, from the following detailed
description taken in conjunction with the drawings.</p><heading>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWING</heading><p num="0024"><sl><li>FIG. 1 is a perspective view illustrating an
appearance of a sample solution treating instrument in
accordance with one example of the present invention.</li><li>FIG. 2 is a longitudinal cross-sectional view of
the treating instrument of FIG. 1.</li><li>FIG. 3 is a longitudinal cross-sectional view
illustrating a sample solution treating instrument in
accordance with another example of the present invention.</li><li>FIG. 4 is a perspective view illustrating a
sample solution treating instrument in accordance with a
further example of the present invention.</li><li>FIG. 5 is a longitudinal cross-sectional view of
a sample solution treating instrument in accordance with a
further example of the present invention.</li><li>FIG. 6 is a plan view sketch illustrating a
biosensor used in one example of the present invention
from which a reaction layer has been omitted.</li><li>FIG. 7 is a longitudinal cross-sectional view
illustrating the biosensor of FIG. 6.</li></sl></p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0025">As discussed above, the sample solution treating
instrument in accordance with the present invention
comprises control means which places a sample solution in
a proper condition for analysis with a biosensor, namely,
controls the condition of the sample solution by
eliminating adverse influences of the above-mentioned
interfering substances on the measurement results or
controls the sample solution to have an adequate pH range
or temperature range for the activity of an enzyme to be
used. Pretreatment of the sample solution with this
treating instrument facilitates rapid and high accuracy
analysis of any specific component contained in the sample
solution.</p><p num="0026">When the control means has a substance which
catalyzes conversion of the above-mentioned interfering
substance to a harmless substance having no effect on the
measurement results, then it is possible to remove the
effect of such interfering substance.</p><p num="0027">For example, when a sample solution containing
an oxidizable interfering substance is used, if the
treating instrument is provided with a catalyst layer
containing an enzyme which catalyzes oxidation of this
interfering substance or a metal oxide such as manganese
dioxide, etc., the interfering substance is oxidized upon
supply of the sample solution to the treating instrument 
and is converted to a harmless substance at no risk of
producing oxidation current. This results in improved
measurement accuracy of the biosensor.</p><p num="0028">Exemplary oxidizable substances include a
variety of vitamin, such as vitamin B<sub>2</sub>, vitamin C, etc.,
dyes such as anthocyanin, tannic acid, etc., and organic
acids such as uric acid, etc. When the sample solution
contains, for instance, ascorbic acid, namely vitamin C,
inclusion of ascorbate oxidase in the catalyst layer may
result in successful conversion of ascorbic acid to
dehydroascorbic acid which is much refractory to
oxidation.</p><p num="0029">Alternatively, the catalyst layer may contain a
catalyst which converts such substance to which the
enzyme contained in the biosensor mistakenly reacts by
taking it as an analyte, into a substance to which the
enzyme is least likely to react.</p><p num="0030">The catalyst layer may contain a single enzyme.
However, inclusion of two or more enzymes in the catalyst
layer proves particularly convenient when the sample
solution contains two or more interfering substances,
because this facilitates treatment of the sample solution
by only one operation.</p><p num="0031">When the control means has an adsorbent having a
physically adsorbing ability, it is possible to remove the
interfering substance from the sample solution. </p><p num="0032">For example, organic acids such as lactic acid
generating during brewing foods impair accuracy of the
measurement of glucose concentration for quality control
of brewed foods, because they have adverse effects on the
enzyme reaction and electrode reaction.</p><p num="0033">The measurement accuracy, however, can be
improved by treating the sample solution to remove such
organic acids, using a treating instrument formed with an
adsorbent layer containing activated carbon.</p><p num="0034">Alternatively, when the control means has a
buffer agent which can be dissolved in the sample solution
upon supply of the sample solution to the treating
instrument and places the sample solution in a proper pH
range for the activity of the enzyme used, the enzyme
activity in the biosensor can be enhanced and rapid
measurement can be performed with high accuracy.</p><p num="0035">For example, when lactate oxidase is the enzyme
to be used, the use of a buffer agent such as phosphate
buffer is better in order to place the sample solution in
a pH range between 6 and 7 which is adequate pH range for
the activity of lactate oxidase. Any arbitrary buffer
agent, such as McIlvaine buffer or Tris-HCl buffer, may be
used depending on the enzyme to be used.</p><p num="0036">Resins are suitable for constituting the
treating instrument in accordance with the present
invention. However, the present invention is not limited 
to the resin and any material that permits formation of
the above-mentioned control means can be used.</p><p num="0037">As to the shape, the treating instrument in
accordance with the present invention is not limited to a
specific shape and any shape that can accommodate the
above-mentioned control means and retain the sample
solution may be used.</p><p num="0038">As to the location of the control means, it can
be located at an arbitrary site which can make contact
with the sample solution when the sample solution is
supplied to the treating instrument.</p><p num="0039">A provision of heating means to the treating
instrument enables direct supply of a sample solution
shortly after being taken out from a low temperature
reservoir, such as refrigerator, to a biosensor for
measurement. Furthermore, not limited to enzyme, normal
catalysts have a temperature at which they can exert their
best activity. Therefore, controllability of the
temperature of the sample solution at such temperature is
considered much convenient, because this enables rapid
completion of treatment and analysis of the sample
solution.</p><p num="0040">As the heating means, it is recommended to cover
the treating instrument with an electric heating sheet
such as a textile incorporated with heating wires.</p><p num="0041">It is also recommended to include stirring means 
in the treating instrument, because it helps to mix the
sample solution with the catalyst layer or a layer of
buffer agent homogeneously.</p><p num="0042">The method for treating a sample solution in
accordance with the present invention comprises the steps
of introducing a sample solution to be supplied to a
biosensor for analysis into the sample solution treating
instrument as explained above, and adjusting the sample
solution closest to a proper condition for the measurement
with the biosensor.</p><p num="0043">This structure eliminates laborious
manipulations, such as dilution of sample solution, for
reducing adverse effects of any interfering substance
contained in the sample solution after its introduction
into a biosensor.</p><p num="0044">The biosensor has a tendency of losing its
measurement accuracy with increases of analyte
concentrations in the sample solution. Therefore,
diluting the sample solution to an adequate magnification
by supplying water, buffer solution and so on enhances
measurement accuracy of the biosensor.</p><p num="0045">In doing so, it is recommended to use a buffer
solution that can place the sample solution in a proper pH
range for the activity of the enzyme in the biosensor.</p><p num="0046">Supplementary agitation and/or heating of the
sample solution would accelerate the treatment of sample 
solution.</p><p num="0047">As the biosensor used here, disposable
biosensors as described below are convenient. Although
the sensors used in the following examples have no cover
member, the use of commercially available sensors having a
cover member for covering the base plate and forming,
between the base plate and the cover member, a sample
supply pathway for introducing a sample solution into the
reaction layer is recommended. U.S. Pat. No. 5,120,420
which discloses details of such sensor with a cover member
is incorporated herein by reference.</p><p num="0048">In the following, the present invention will be
described more specifically by way of concrete examples.</p><p num="0049">FIG. 1 is a perspective view illustrating a
sample solution treating instrument in accordance with one
example of the present invention and FIG. 2 is a
longitudinal cross-sectional view of FIG. 1.</p><p num="0050">A control membrane 11 is formed by either
directly pressing a substance serving as means for placing
a sample solution in a predetermined condition against a
bottom of a resin vessel 10, or dropping a solution
dissolving the substance in a proper solvent or a
dispersion of the substance in a proper dispersion medium
on the bottom, followed by drying and volatilizing the
solvent or the dispersion medium.</p><p num="0051">FIG. 3 is a longitudinal cross-sectional view 
illustrating a sample solution treating instrument in
accordance with another example of the present invention.
A control membrane 21 is formed on an inner wall of a
resin vessel 20 in the same manner as in FIG. 2.</p><p num="0052">FIG. 4 is a perspective view illustrating a
sample solution treating instrument in accordance with a
further example of the present invention.</p><p num="0053">The treating instrument is composed of a sample
treating unit 30 comprising a porous carrier, such as
nonwoven glass fiber cloth or filter paper, and a sample
supply unit 31. The sample treating unit 30 retains a
substance for placing the sample solution in a desired
condition. The sample treating unit 30 can be formed by
dissolving the substance in an appropriate solvent in
which the porous carrier is immersed and dried to
volatilize the solvent or, alternatively, by dropping a
solution dissolving the substance or a dispersion of the
substance in a dispersion medium on the porous carrier and
drying it to volatilize the solvent or dispersion medium.
The sample supply unit 31 is made of an elastic material
capable of retaining the sample solution insides, such as
sponge. After passing through the sample treating unit
30, the sample solution reaches the sample supply unit 31
communicating with the sample treating unit 30 to be
supplied to a biosensor therefrom.</p><p num="0054">FIG. 5 is a longitudinal cross-sectional view of 
a sample solution treating instrument in accordance with a
further example of the present invention. Treating layers
41 and 42 are formed inside a resin vessel 40 equipped
with a sample solution supply nozzle 43 on its bottom.
The treating layers are made of the substance for placing
the sample solution in a desired condition or a liquid
permeable material retaining the substance. The sample
solution to be treated is introduced into the vessel 40
through an opening of the vessel 40, treated during its
passage through the treating layers 41 and 42, and
supplied to a biosensor through the nozzle 43.</p><p num="0055">FIG. 6 is a plan view sketch illustrating a
biosensor used in one example of the present invention
from which a reaction layer has been omitted.</p><p num="0056">A silver paste is printed on an electrically
insulating base plate 1 made of polyethylene terephthalate
by known screen printing to form leads 2 and 3.
Subsequently, a conductive carbon paste containing a resin
binder is printed on the base plate 1 to form a working
electrode 4. The working electrode 4 is so made to
contact the lead 2. An insulating paste is further
printed on the base plate 1 to form an insulating layer 6.
The insulating layer 6 covers the periphery of the working
electrode 4 to hold an exposed area of the working
electrode 4 constant. Finally, the same conductive carbon
paste containing a resin binder is printed on the base 
plate 1 to contact the lead 3 thereby forming a ring-like
counter electrode 5.</p><p num="0057">FIG. 7 is a longitudinal cross-sectional view
illustrating the biosensor of FIG. 6. A reaction layer 7
containing an enzyme and an electron acceptor is formed on
the electrode system comprising the working electrode 4
and the counter electrode 5 on the base plate 1.</p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0058">After preparation of a fruit juice as a sample
solution, the glucose concentration in the fruit juice was
measured using the biosensor illustrated in FIG. 6. The
reaction layer 7 of the biosensor contained glucose
oxidase (hereinafter abbreviated to "GOx") as the enzyme
and potassium hexacyanoferrate (III) as the electron
acceptor.</p><p num="0059">Fruit juices normally contain much ascorbic acid
which is an oxidizable substance. Therefore, the use of
fruit juices as they are can produce a positive error in
the measured oxidation current and the obtained value will
be higher than the actual value.</p><p num="0060">Therefore, prior to introduction into the
biosensor, a fruit juice to be measured was adjusted using
a treating instrument produced as follows.</p><p num="0061">An aqueous solution of ascorbate oxidase
(hereinafter abbreviated to "AsOx") which is a catalyst of 
selective oxidation reaction of ascorbic acid was dropped
on the bottom of the resin vessel 10 in FIG. 2 and dried
in a dry atmosphere to form a layer 11 of AsOx, which gave
a treating instrument to be used in this example.</p><p num="0062">A fruit juice was supplied to the treating
instrument. As a result, the ascorbic acid contained in
the fruit juice was converted to a harmless substance,
dehydroascorbic acid, having no adverse influence on the
measurement of oxidation current by the catalytic action
of AsOx.</p><p num="0063">The fruit juice thus formulated was introduced
into the biosensor as a sample solution. When dropped on
the reaction layer 7 of the biosensor, the sample solution
dissolved the reaction layer 7 and the GOx present in the
reaction layer 7 selectively oxidized the glucose
contained in the fruit juice. This enzyme reaction
accompanied reduction reaction of the potassium
hexacyanoferrate (III) to potassium hexacyanoferrate (II).</p><p num="0064">When a predetermined time has passed after the
fruit juice was dropped, a voltage was applied, with
reference to the counter electrode 5, onto the working
electrode 4 to reoxidize the potassium hexacyanoferrate
(II) to potassium hexacyanoferrate (III) and the oxidation
current flowing during reoxidation reaction was measured.</p><p num="0065">The result showed successful measurement of the
glucose concentration in the fruit juice with the same 
accuracy as the measurement of a glucose standard solution
containing no ascorbic acid.</p><p num="0066">In measuring a fruit juice which was considered
to contain much glucose, the fruit juice was diluted by
concurrently supplying water to the treating instrument.
The result showed that glucose quantitation was more
accurate for the diluted sample solution than for the
original sample solution.</p><p num="0067">When the fruit juice was adjusted to come in a
proper pH range for the activity of AsOx using, as a
diluent, a buffer solution with an adjusted pH between 4
and 8 in place of water, the measurement accuracy was
further increased.</p><p num="0068">After being supplied to the treating instrument,
the sample solution was stirred. This accelerated
dissolution of the AsOx layer and facilitated supply of
sufficient oxygen to the sample solution. Promoted
catalytic reaction of the AsOx enabled rapid treatment of
the sample solution.</p><p num="0069">Next, a fruit juice shortly after being taken
out from a refrigerator was supplied to the treating
instrument whose resin vessel as shown in FIG. 2 was
covered with an electric heating sheet in order to warm up
the fruit juice. As a result, since the fruit juice was
successfully heated to a proper temperature for the
activity of AsOx, the treatment was rapid. This fruit 
juice was supplied as it was to the biosensor for analysis
in the same manner as described above which resulted in
rapid and high accuracy analysis.</p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0070">First, fruit fermentation mash generating in the
course of fermentation of wine (hereinafter referred to as
"must") was prepared as a sample solution and the glucose
concentration in the must was measured using an identical
biosensor to that of Example 1. Measurement and control
of the glucose concentration in the must during
fermentation is key to management of the quality of wine.</p><p num="0071">However, must normally contains much polyphenol
such as tannic acid, for example, which is an oxidizable
substance. Therefore, the use of such must as it is can
produce a positive error in the measured oxidation current
and the obtained value will be higher than the actual
value.</p><p num="0072">Therefore, prior to introduction into the
biosensor, a must to be measured was treated using a
treating instrument produced as follows.</p><p num="0073">An aqueous solution of polyphenol oxidase
(another name is laccase) which is a catalyst of selective
oxidation reaction of polyphenol was dropped on the bottom
of the resin vessel 10 in FIG. 2 and dried in a dry
atmosphere to form an enzyme layer 11, which gave a 
treating instrument to be used in this example.</p><p num="0074">A must was supplied to the treating instrument.
As a result, the polyphenol contained in the must was
converted to a harmless substance, polyquinone, having no
adverse influence on the measurement of oxidation current
by the catalytic action of laccase.</p><p num="0075">The must thus formulated was introduced into the
biosensor as a sample solution to measure the glucose
concentration in the must in the same manner as in Example
1.</p><p num="0076">The result showed successful measurement of the
glucose concentration in the must with the same accuracy
as the measurement of a glucose standard solution
containing no polyphenol.</p><p num="0077">In measuring a must which was considered to
contain much glucose, dilution of the must by concurrently
supplying water or a buffer solution at an adjusted pH
between 4 and 8 similar to Example 1 enabled to increase
the measurement accuracy.</p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="0078">A nutritional drink was prepared as a sample
solution (RIPOVITAN D, manufactured by Taisho
Pharmaceutical, Co., Ltd.) and fructose and glucose
concentrations in the drink were measured in the same 
manner as in Example 1. At measurement of fructose
concentration, fructose dehydrogenase was contained in the
reaction layer 7 in place of GOx.</p><p num="0079">Luxury drinks like nutritional drink normally
contain additives such as vitamin C (ascorbic acid)
functioning as an antioxidant, vitamin B<sub>2</sub> (riboflavin)
functioning as a dye. All of them are oxidizable
substances and can produce a positive error in the
measured oxidation current if used as they are, resulting
in a higher value than the actual value.</p><p num="0080">Therefore, prior to introduction into the
biosensor, a nutritional drink to be measured was treated
using a treating instrument produced as follows.</p><p num="0081">An aqueous mixture of an aqueous AsOx solution
and another aqueous solution of riboflavinase which is a
catalyst of selective degradation of riboflavin at a
volumetric ratio of 1:1 was dropped on the sample treating
unit 30 in FIG. 4 and dried in a dry atmosphere to carry
AsOx and riboflavin on the sample treating unit 30, which
gave a treating instrument to be used in this example.</p><p num="0082">A nutritional drink was supplied to the sample
treating unit 30 of the treating instrument. As a result,
the vitamin C in the nutritional drink was converted, via
the action of AsOx, to a harmless substance,
dehydroascorbic acid, having no adverse influence on the
measurement of oxidation current. Similarly, the vitamin 
B<sub>2</sub> was converted, via the action of riboflavinase, to a
harmless substance, ribitol, having no adverse influence
on the measurement of oxidation current.</p><p num="0083">The nutritional drink thus formulated during its
passage through the sample treating unit 30 is introduced
into the biosensor through the sample supply unit 31.
Since the sample supply unit 31 is a sponge, the
nutritional drink can be introduced into the biosensor by
simply pressing the biosensor against the unit 31 and
measurement can be initiated.</p><p num="0084">The nutritional drink thus formulated was
introduced into the biosensor in the same manner as
described above to measure the fructose and glucose
concentrations in the drink.</p><p num="0085">The result showed successful measurement of the
fructose and glucose concentrations in the drink with the
same accuracy as the measurement of fructose and glucose
standard solutions.</p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0086">Glucose concentration was managed in the same
manner as in Example 1 in the course of brewing Japanese
rice wine (hereinafter referred to as "sake").</p><p num="0087">Fermentation of sake generates a variety of
organic acids such as lactic acid, malic acid, etc., in
addition to ethanol. Some of those organic acids may have 
adverse effects on the enzyme reaction and electrode
reaction of the biosensor.</p><p num="0088">Therefore, prior to introduction into the
biosensor, sake as a sample solution was treated using a
treating instrument as described below.</p><p num="0089">The treating instrument used here has the
structure as shown in FIG. 5. More specifically, it has a
laminate of (1) a treating layer 41 formed by pressing a
mixture of an activated carbon powder with a powder of
polytetrafluoroethylene at an appropriate ratio into a
pellet and (2) a treating layer 42 formed by dropping a
solution of a buffer agent on a glass filter and drying it
to carry the buffer agent on the glass filter. The buffer
solution is in a pH range between 4 and 7 at which GOx
exhibits its best activity.</p><p num="0090">A sake moromi was supplied to the treating
instrument in order to adjust its low pH between 3 and 4
to a proper pH at the treating layer 42 by means of the
buffer agent and removing all organic acids contained in
the moromi at the treating layer 41 by means of physical
adsorption of activated carbon.</p><p num="0091">Measurement of the glucose concentration in the
sample solution thus formulated in the same manner as in
Example 1 was accurate.</p><p num="0092">In the foregoing example, although sake moromi
was used as the sample to be treated with the treating 
instrument of the present invention, the instrument was
similarly effective for removing ethanol and organic acids
in the must of wine.</p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="0093">Using a medium under fermentation of lactic acid
bacteria as a sample solution, the concentration of L-lactic
acid in the medium was measured using the biosensor
shown in FIG. 6. In this example, the enzyme was L-lactate
oxidase (hereinafter abbreviated to "LOx") and the
electron acceptor was potassium hexacyanoferrate (III).</p><p num="0094">Fermentation of lactic acid bacteria generates
L-lactic acid with the progress of fermentation, which in
turn changes the medium to acidic medium. The enzyme LOx
in the biosensor decreases its activity rapidly when it
has a pH value of 7 or less. Therefore, the use of a
medium at advanced stages of fermentation for measurement
with the biosensor can result in marked impairment of the
measurement accuracy.</p><p num="0095">Therefore, the following treating instrument was
produced for treating the medium as a sample solution in
order to adjust pH of the sample solution.</p><p num="0096">The treating instrument was produced by
spreading a dispersion of dipotassium hydrogenphosphate in
toluene on the lateral wall of the vessel 10 in FIG. 3 and
volatilizing toluene to form a control membrane 21. </p><p num="0097">The medium under fermentation of lactic acid
bacteria was introduced into the treating instrument thus
produced to adjust the pH of the medium to 7.</p><p num="0098">The medium thus formulated was introduced into
the biosensor. A drop of the medium on the reaction layer
7 of the biosensor dissolved the reaction layer 7 and LOx
in the reaction layer 7 selectively oxidized L-lactic acid
in the medium. This enzyme reaction accompanied reduction
reaction of the potassium hexacyanoferrate (III) to
potassium hexacyanoferrate (II). Then, the reduced
potassium hexacyanoferrate (II) was electrochemically
reoxidized to potassium hexacyanoferrate (III) in the same
manner as in Example 1 to measure oxidation current during
the reoxidation reaction in order to determine the
concentration of L-lactic acid in the medium. The result
showed successful measurement with high accuracy.</p><p num="0099">As discussed above, the present invention
enables rapid and simplified adjustment of the condition
of a sample solution proper for analysis with a biosensor
prior to its supply to the biosensor, thereby enhancing
the measurement accuracy of the biosensor.</p><p num="0100">Although the present invention has been
described in terms of the presently preferred embodiments,
it is to be understood that such disclosure is not to be
interpreted as limiting. Various alterations and 
modifications will no doubt become apparent to those
skilled in the art to which the present invention
pertains, after having read the above disclosure.
Accordingly, it is intended that the appended claims be
interpreted as covering all alterations and modifications
as fall within the true spirit and scope of the invention.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A sample solution treating instrument for
formulating a sample solution to be supplied to a
biosensor for analysis, comprising control means for
placing said sample solution in a proper condition for
analysis with said biosensor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The sample solution treating instrument in
accordance with claim 1, wherein said control means has a
catalyst located inside said instrument, said catalyst
being a catalyst converting an interfering substance in
said sample solution to a harmless substance having no
adverse effect on the measurement results.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The sample solution treating instrument in
accordance with claim 2, wherein said catalyst is at least
one enzyme.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The sample solution treating instrument in
accordance with claim 1, wherein said control means has an
adsorbent located inside said instrument, said adsorbent
being an adsorbent adsorbing and removing an interfering
substance in said sample solution.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The sample solution treating instrument in
accordance with claim 1, wherein said control means has a
buffer agent located inside said instrument, said buffer
agent being capable of adjusting pH of said sample
solution to a proper pH for the activity of an enzyme in
the biosensor.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The sample solution treating instrument in
accordance with claim 1, further comprising heating means
of said sample solution.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method for treating a sample solution
comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>introducing a sample solution, which will be
supplied to a biosensor for analysis, into the sample
solution treating instrument as claimed in claim 1, and</claim-text><claim-text>adjusting said sample solution closest to a
proper condition for analysis with said biosensor.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><drawings status="new"><figure num="1"><img id="img-00280001" orientation="unknown" wi="106" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00280001.tif" inline="no" he="240"/></figure><figure num="2"><img id="img-00290001" orientation="unknown" wi="103" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00290001.tif" inline="no" he="198"/></figure><figure num="3"><img id="img-00300001" orientation="unknown" wi="91" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00300001.tif" inline="no" he="162"/></figure><figure num="4"><img id="img-00310001" orientation="unknown" wi="83" img-format="tif" img-content="dr" file="00310001.tif" inline="no" he="209"/></figure></drawings><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>