<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="WO-2001019944-A1" country="WO" doc-number="2001019944" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="23563779" status="new" date-produced="20090508" date="20010322"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="WO-2001019944-A1" status="new" fvid="77506199"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2001019944</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010322</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="US-0025167-W" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>0025167</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20000914</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-39561899-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>39561899</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>19990914</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classification-ipc status="new"><edition>7</edition><main-classification>C11D   1/00</main-classification><further-classification>A61L   2/18</further-classification></classification-ipc><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B08B   3/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B08B   3/08        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/83        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/83        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/835       20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/835       20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/86        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   1/86        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/48        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D   3/48        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C11D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">E03D   9/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">E03D   9/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   1/83</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   1/835</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   1/86</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D  11/00B2D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C11D   3/00B13</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="EN">TOILET BOWL CLEANING METHOD</invention-title><invention-title load-source="docdb" status="new" lang="FR">PROCEDE DE NETTOYAGE DE CUVETTE DE TOILETTES ET D'URINOIRS</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="CA-2201406-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>CA</country><doc-number>2201406</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0832964-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0832964</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997006237-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997006237</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1998057544-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1998057544</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999019432-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999019432</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999066017-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999066017</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit> <patcit ucid="WO-2000012662-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2000012662</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="XP" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources> </patcit> </patent-citations> <non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>See also references of EP     1214388A1</text><sources><source name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>JOHNSON &amp; SON INC S C</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>S.C. JOHNSON &amp; SON, INC.</name></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HEMPEL VIRGINIA M</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KLINKHAMMER MICHAEL E</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MOODYCLIFFE TIMOTHY I</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HEMPEL, VIRGINIA, M.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KLINKHAMMER, MICHAEL, E.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MOODYCLIFFE, TIMOTHY, I.</name></addressbook></inventor></inventors></parties></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Disclosed herein are methods of cleaning toilet basins and urinals. Cleaning components are applied to the interior surfaces of these basins other than through the flush water, without scrubbing. They are allowed to be in contact with the surface of the basin for at least one-half hour before normal use of the toilet/urinal. Preferred methods for applying the cleaning compositions are with a spray bottle or an aerosol can, with application occuring on a daily, overnight basis.</p></abstract><abstract load-source="docdb" source="national office" status="new" lang="FR"><p>L'invention concerne des procédés de nettoyage de cuvettes de toilettes et d'urinoirs. Des composants de nettoyage sont appliqués sur les surfaces internes des cuvettes autrement que par l'eau de la chasse, sans récurage. On peut mettre en contact ces composants avec la surface de la cuvette pendant au moins une demi heure avant l'utilisation normale des toilettes ou de l'urinoir. On réalise des procédés d'application préférés des compositions de nettoyage en utilisant une bouteille de pulvérisation ou une bombe aérosol, sur la base d'une journée ou d'une nuit.</p></abstract><description load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><!-- EPO <DP n="2"/>--><p num="p0001"> TOILET BOWL CLEANING METHOD CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS Not applicable. STATEMENT REGARDING- FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH</p><p num="p0002">Not applicable.</p><p num="p0003">BACKGROUND OF INVENTION The present invention relates to a method of cleaning plumbing fixtures. More particularly it relates to a method of cleaning toilet bowls and urinals which alleviates the need for scrubbing or manually wiping the basin to work in the cleaner.</p><p num="p0004">A variety of toilet bowl cleaners are known which are intended to be used by scrubbing them against a toilet basin. In some cases the cleaners are liquids that are squirted from a bottle against the basin (e.g. "Liquid Toilet Duck" sold by S.C. Johnson &amp; Son, Inc.). In other cases the cleaners are aerosol sprays that are sprayed against the side of the basin (e.g. "Vanish" toilet bowl cleaner sold by S.C. Johnson &amp; Son, Inc.) .</p><p num="p0005">It is also known in the art to provide a product that is sprayed against a shower or bathtub wall immediately after the use of the shower or bathtub which keeps the tub or shower cleaner without the need for wiping. This is described in U.S. patent 5,587,022 (see also the related U.S. patents 5,536,452 and 5,587,664, and the related PCT publications WO 96/22346 and WO 98/02511) .</p><p num="p0006">However, toilet and urinal basins are designed to receive contaminated waste. Even after flushing^ the basins often sit partially filled with hard water that contains minerals that can stain a bowl (e.g. leave a ring) . Existing cleaning formulations that are designed to keep showers or bathtubs relatively clean without scrubbing are ineffective for toilet basins and urinals. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="3"/>-->
 A variety of techniques have been developed for delivering cleaning compounds via the flush water that sits in a toilet bowl. However, delivering the cleaning solution to the water of the bowl in this way dilutes the cleaning material. Moreover, such- systems are less effective for the portion of the bowl above the water line.</p><p num="p0007">With respect to urinals, blocks of disinfecting materials have been positioned near the outlet of the basin, sometimes in or on top of ice. However, such materials are not designed to clean the side walls of the basin.</p><p num="p0008">In that the prior art has not to date provided a satisfactory way of cleaning the side walls of a toilet or urinal basin which alleviates the need for scrubbing or wiping a cleaner against the basin, sponges, brushes and the like that have been contaminated with toilet bowl water and cleaner still need to be stored between uses.</p><p num="p0009">Thus, a need exists for improved methods of cleaning toilet bowls and urinals.</p><p num="p0010">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION In one aspect the invention provides a method of cleaning a basin of a plumbing fixture selected from the group consisting of toilet bowl and urinal basins. Such basins have a drain opening and a side wall portion extending upwardly therefrom. One applies a cleaning composition containing at least water and a surfactant to the side wall portion other than via flush water. One then allows the cleaning composition to remain on the side wall portion for at least one half hour (preferably at least an hour, even more preferably at least six hours) after it is applied. The method is completed without the cleaning composition being scrubbed against or manually wiped against the wall, and without the composition being completely rinsed off the wall during the period.</p><p num="p0011">The surfactant can be any of the known anionic, nonionic, cationic or zwitterionic surfactants that are 
<!-- EPO <DP n="4"/>-->
suitable for use in a toilet bowl environment, albeit a mixture of either nonionic and anionic, or nonionic and cationic, surfactants is preferred for this purpose.</p><p num="p0012">In a further aspect, the basin is a toilet bowl basin having a top portion, and the cleaning composition is applied at least between the top portion and a normal "water line" of the basin (the normal fill level of the basin) .</p><p num="p0013">The cleaning composition is preferably delivered via a spray so that the cleaning composition will in large part adhere to the bowl sides above the water (rather than primarily running down into the bowl water) . A pump sprayer can be used to deliver the material, or the material can be combined with an aerosol gas propellant (such as propane, butane, isobutane, and mixtures thereof) and then delivered from an aerosol can.</p><p num="p0014">These and still other features of the present invention will be apparent from the description which follows. The following description is of the preferred embodiments. However, the claims should be looked to in order to better understand the full scope of the invention.</p><p num="p0015">DETAILED DESCRIPTION Example 1 - nonionic mixed with cationic - pump spray One preferred liquid spray type cleaner has the following formula: ingredient preferred source weight % water 97.522 ethoxylated alcohol Lutensol A08 1.00 sodium lauryl ether Steol 4N 0.500 sulfate sulphamic acid 0.500 fragrance 0.250 cellulosic thickener Rheozan 0.220 dye Pigmosol blue 6900 0.008 
<!-- EPO <DP n="5"/>-->
 Example 1 was applied to a toilet bowl by spraying it from a pump trigger bottle in which it was contained. The product was sprayed in a manner to cover the entire inside wall of the bowl above the water line and below the rim. About 10 g of spray was required to achieve desired coverage. The applied product was allowed to remain in contact with the bowl for a minimum of one-half hour (preferably at least six hours - over night) , after which the toilet could be used in the usual manner. This procedure was repeated once a day for four weeks.</p><p num="p0016">This resulted in the removal of all visible stains and deposits, and prevented further stains from forming on the bowl sides above the water line.</p><p num="p0017">Example 2 - nonionic and cationic - aerosol An aerosol form of the invention has the following formula : ingredient preferred source weight % deionized water 76.692720 tetrasodium salt EDTA 10.152000 ethylenediamine 0.122200 tetraacetic acid diethelene glycol 5.64000 butyl ether nonylphenol ethoxylated Union Carbide 0.188000 alcohol</p><p num="p0018">Tergitol NP-10 nonionic surfactant Sandoxylate SX-424 0.188000</p><p num="p0019">-Clariant Corporation fragrance 0.094000 isobutane 6.000000 miristalammonium Stepan 0.406080 chloride and quaternium 14- disinfectant/surfactant 
<!-- EPO <DP n="6"/>-->
 Example 2 was sprayed into a toilet bowl in essentially the same manner as described in Example 1 for the spray bottle, albeit from an aerosol can. It was applied at the same intervals and with similar results. Example 3 - pump spray</p><p num="p0020">The following formulation is also suitable for use with a trigger nozzle delivery system: ingredient preferred source weight % water 92.787 Ammonyx DO CIO Stepan 1.67 amine oxide</p><p num="p0021">Glucopon 325 NK Henkel 1.5 bacteriocide Stepan 0.27500</p><p num="p0022">BTC 2125M, 80% fragrance 0.150 propylene glycol 3.0 monobutylether tetrasodium salt of 0.4</p><p num="p0023">EDTA 40% caustic soda, 50% 0.218</p><p num="p0024">Other Variations While certain specific ingredients have been described as being useful for formulations of the present invention, these can be varied. For example, the anionic surfactant is preferably 0 to 10% of the formulation, the cationic surfactant is preferably 0 to 10% of the formulation, the nonionic surfactant is preferably .2 to 10% of the formulation, and there is preferably up to 5% sulphamic acid or up to 15% tetrasodium salt of EDTA, and up to 3% fragrance. There is also preferably more than 75% water. There can also be other additives and dyes as are conventional with toilet bowl cleaners. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="7"/>-->
 While this invention has been described above in connection with cleaning a toilet bowl, it can also be effectively employed in conjunction with a urinal. The cleaner composition would be applied along the inner side walls of the urinal. As in conjunction with a toilet bowl, the cleaner could be applied on a daily basis and preferably at the end of the day. It should be allowed to remain in contact with the inner surface of the urinal for at least one half hour, and preferably six hours, before rinsing. Industrial Applicability</p><p num="p0025">The invention provides a method of cleaning urinals and toilets which receive flushable waste. 
</p></description><claims load-source="pctxml" status="new" lang="EN"><claim id="clm-0001" num="0001"><!-- EPO <DP n="8"/>--><claim-text/><claim-text>CLAIMS</claim-text><claim-text>We claim:</claim-text><claim-text>1. A method of cleaning a basin of a plumbing fixture selected from the group consisting of toilet bowl basins and urinal basins, the basin having a drain opening and a side wall portion extending upwardly therefrom, the method comprising: applying a cleaning composition containing water and a surfactant to the side wall portion other than via flush water; and allowing the cleaning composition to remain on the wall portion for at least one half hour after it is applied on the wall portion; wherein the method is completed without the cleaning composition being scrubbed against or manually wiped against the wall.</claim-text><claim-text>2. The method of claim 1, wherein as part of the method the cleaning composition is allowed to contact the side wall portion for at least one hour after application of the cleaning composition against the wall.</claim-text><claim-text>3. The method of claim 1, wherein as part of the method the cleaning composition is allowed to contact the side wall portion for at least six hours after application of the cleaning composition against the wall.</claim-text><claim-text>4. The method of claim 1, wherein the plumbing fixture is a toilet bowl having a top portion and the cleaning composition is applied along the side wall at least between the top portion and a normal water level line of the toilet bowl.</claim-text><claim-text>5. The method of claim 1, wherein the plumbing fixture is a urinal. 
<!-- EPO <DP n="9"/>--></claim-text><claim-text>6. The method of claim 1, wherein the cleaning composition further comprises an aerosol propellant gas.</claim-text><claim-text>7. The method of claim 1, wherein the cleaning composition comprises both a nonionic and an anionic surfactant .</claim-text><claim-text>8. The method of claim 1, wherein the cleaning composition comprises both a nonionic and a cationic surfactant .</claim-text><claim-text>9. The method of claim 1, wherein the cleaning composition comprises a disinfectant.</claim-text><claim-text>10. The method of claim 1, wherein the cleaning composition comprises anionic surfactant present in a range of 0.00% to 10.00% by weight or cationic surfactant present in a range of 0.00% to 10.00% by weight, there being one but not both of cationic surfactant and anionic surfactant in the composition, nonionic surfactant being present in a range of 0.20% to 10.00% by weight, sulphamic acid being present in a range of 0.00% to 5.00% by weight or sodium salt of EDTA being present in a range of 0.00% to 15% by weight, and fragrance being present in a range of 0.00% to 3.00% by weight. 
</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>