<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1418201-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1418201" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="32105494" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040512"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1418201-A1" status="new" fvid="24056685"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1418201</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040512</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03024523-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03024523</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031027</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002325201-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002325201</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021108</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   5/00        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08J   5/00        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/00        20060101CFI20061208BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/16        20060101AFI20061208BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/17        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/29        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   5/3467      20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/00        20060101ALI20061208BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  67/00        20060101CLI20061208BHEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L 101/16        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/16</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08K   5/29</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08L 101/16</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Biologisch abbaubare Plastikzusammensetzung, die damit hergestellten Gegenstände und eine Methode zur Kontrolle der biologischen Abbaurate</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">A biodegradable plastic composition, a molded article thereof and a method for controlling biodegradation rate using the same composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composition de matière plastique biodégradable, article moulé à partir de cette composition et méthode pour contrôler la vitesse de décomposition biologique</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-19630599-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>19630599</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0890604-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0890604</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1193050-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1193050</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5484881-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5484881</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE  CA [Online] CHEMICAL ABSTRACTS SERVICE, COLUMBUS, OHIO, US; NAGANO, HIROTA ET AL: "Fire-, heat-, and hydrolysis-resistant polyester elastomer compositions" retrieved from STN Database accession no. 130:140381 XP002266309 &amp; JP 11 021436 A (TOYOBO CO., LTD., JAPAN) 26 January 1999 (1999-01-26)</text><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NISSHIN SPINNING</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NISSHINBO INDUSTRIES INC.</last-name><address><street>31-11, Ningyocho 2-chome, Nihonbashi</street><city>Chuo-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>IIDA HIROTAKA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NAKAMURA NORIMASA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TAKAHASHI IKUO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TAKEUCHI TSUYOSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YAMAZAKI YOSHIHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>IIDA, HIROTAKA</last-name><address><street>R&amp;amp;D Center Nisshinbo Industries, Inc 1-2-3 Ohnodai</street><city>Midori-ku Chiba-shi Chiba</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NAKAMURA, NORIMASA</last-name><address><street>R&amp;amp;D Center Nisshinbo Industries, Inc 1-2-3 Ohnodai</street><city>Midori-ku Chiba-shi Chiba</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TAKAHASHI, IKUO</last-name><address><street>R&amp;amp;D Center Nisshinbo Industries, Inc 1-2-3 Ohnodai</street><city>Midori-ku Chiba-shi Chiba</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TAKEUCHI, TSUYOSHI</last-name><address><street>R&amp;amp;D Center Nisshinbo Industries, Inc 1-2-3 Ohnodai</street><city>Midori-ku Chiba-shi Chiba</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>YAMAZAKI, YOSHIHIRO</last-name><address><street>R&amp;amp;D Center Nisshinbo Industries, Inc 1-2-3 Ohnodai</street><city>Midori-ku Chiba-shi Chiba</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Müller-Boré &amp;amp; Partner Patentanwälte</last-name><address><street>Grafinger Strasse 2</street><city>81671 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A biodegradable plastic composition which can be
stably adjusted in biodegradation rate, and has greatly
improved resistance to hydrolysis and weather, in
particular the former, and durability resulting from the
improved resistances; a molded article thereof; and a method
for controlling biodegradation rate using the same
composition. The biodegradable plastic composition
comprising (A) 100 parts by weight of biodegradable plastic,
(B) 0.01 to 10 parts by weight of a carbodiimide compound
and (C) 0.01 to 10 parts by weight of at least one compound
selected from the group consisting of benzotriazole-,
triazine- and hydroxylamine-based one; the molded article
thereof; and the method for controlling biodegradation rate
using the same composition.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a biodegradable
plastic composition, a molded article thereof and a method
for controlling biodegradation rate using the same
composition, in more detail, the present invention relates
to a biodegradable plastic composition which exhibits
greatly improved resistance to hydrolysis and weather, in
particular the former, by compounding specified agents
therein and excellent durability resulting from the
improved resistances, applications of the composition such
as a biodegradable molded article, and a method for
controlling biodegradation rate of the biodegradable
plastic.</p><p num="0002">Recently, researches and developments of the
biodegradable plastic have been promoted on the background
of increasing attention to a need and a significance of the
environmental preservation, while problems such as
environmental contamination caused by plastic wastes have
been closed up. </p><p num="0003">The biodegradable plastics are roughly classified
into aliphatic polyesters having polyester groups in a
molecular backbone thereof (including those produced by
microorganisms), natural macromolecule type polymers such
as cellulose, polysaccharides produced by microorganisms,
polyvinyl alcohol (PVA) and polyethers such as polyethylene
glycol (PEG).</p><p num="0004">Among them, aliphatic polyesters have not been
utilized as the biodegradable plastic because they have,
in general, low melting points and poor heat stabilities
in their production stages, and a sufficiently large
molecular weight has not been obtained to provide physical
properties suitable for practical molded articles. However,
with technological developments to solve these problems,
a high molecular weight of aliphatic polyester has come out,
and started to be used in such fields as materials for
agriculture, forestry and fishery (mulch film, plantation
pot, fishing line, fishing net, and the like), materials
for civil engineering work (water holding sheet, net for
plants, sandbag, and the like) and packaging and containers
field (those difficult to be recycled due to adhered soil,
foods, and the like).</p><p num="0005">The biodegradable plastics including the above-described
aliphatic type polyesters, however, should not
only have the same level of functions to the conventional
plastics (in characteristics such as strength, water
resistance, formability and heat resistance) in use, but
also be rapidly degradable by microorganisms generally 
present in the nature in disposal thereof.</p><p num="0006">Based on these situations, several methods for
controlling the degradation rate of the biodegradable
plastic have been proposed, for example, a method aiming
at shortening of degradation period by an addition of
hydrolase (disclosed by, e.g., JP-A-4-168149 (refer to
claims or the like)), and another method contrary aiming
at an extension of the degradation period by reducing
unreacted monomers and impurities in a polymer and low
molecular weight compounds such as linear or cyclic
oligomers (disclosed by, e.g., JP-A-9-12688 (refer to
claims or the like)), are known.</p><p num="0007">Notwithstanding these proposals, however, the
biodegradable plastic consisting of the aliphatic polyester
according to the conventional arts has currently such
problems as a hydrolysis reaction progressing in the
aliphatic polyester induced by exposure to moisture in an
ambient atmosphere or by being heated during a production
process of pellets thereof, which are raw materials of
plastic products, or in a production process of products
from said pellets, leading to lowering or dispersion of
initial properties of molded articles as well as an unstable
biodegradability of products thereof, and thus adjustment
of the biodegradability, that is, biodegradation rate, is
not yet sufficient.</p><p num="0008">The present inventors proposed, as disclosed by,
e.g., JP-A-11-80522 (refer to claims or the like), a 
biodegradable plastic composition with an adjusted
biodegradation rate by compounding a carbodiimide compound
into the biodegradable plastic. Although this proposal
improved a hydrolysis resistance or a function for adjusting
biodegradability, although not to a sufficient extent. The
proposal also had another problem of loosing transparency
of product, in particular, in a polylactic acid based
biodegradable plastic product with an increased compounding
amount of the carbodiimide compound to enhance the
hydrolysis resistance.</p><p num="0009">JP-A-2001-525473 (refer to claims or the like), for
example, also proposes a method aiming at an extension of
the degradation period by compounding an aromatic
carbodiimide as a hydrolysis stabilizer to the
biodegradable polymer. This method, however, involve
problems, because the biodegradable polymer it gives shows
hydrolysis resistance still insufficient, although
improved, decreased transparency irrespective of addition
amount of the stabilizer, and insufficient weather
resistance.</p><p num="0010">Moreover, JP-A-6-184417 (refer to claims or the
like), for example, proposes a lactic-based composition

characterized by a lactic-based polymer as a biodegradable
polymer compounded with at least one type of additive
selected from the group consisting of ultraviolet absorber
and light stabilizer at 0.001 to 5 parts by weight per 100
parts by weight of the polymer. However, this invention is
aimed at controlling decomposition of the polymer by solar 
rays but not at controlling hydrolysis.</p><p num="0011">Still more, JP-A-2002-114893 (refer to claims or
the like), for example, proposes a thermoplastic polyester
resin composition, although not biodegradable,
characterized by a thermoplastic polyester resin compounded
with a resin-based ultraviolet absorber and aliphatic-based
polycarbodiimide compound to improve resistances of the
resin, which has relatively high heat resistance, to weather,
alkali and hydrolysis. However, the resin-based ultraviolet
absorber disclosed by the document involves a problem of
being not compatible with a biodegradable plastic.</p><p num="0012">Therefore, it is an object of the present invention
to solve the problems of the conventional arts and to provide
a biodegradable plastic composition capable of adjusting
its biodegradation rate, greatly improved in resistance to
hydrolysis and weather, in particular the former, and
excellent in durability resulting from the improved
resistances. It is another object of the present invention
to provide a molded article of the composition. It is still
another object of the present invention to provide a method
for controlling biodegradation rate of the biodegradable
plastic.</p><p num="0013">The present inventors, after an extensive study to
solve the above-described problems of the conventional arts,
found that compounding specified amounts of a carbodiimide
compound (including a polycarbodiimide compound) having at 
least one carbodiimide group in the molecule and a specified
compound in a biodegradable plastic, in particular, an
aliphatic polyester, could improve the resulting
biodegradable plastic composition in resistance to
hydrolysis and weather, in particular in hydrolysis
resistance resulting from the synergistic effect by the
carbodiimide compound and specified compound, and thereby
could adjust biodegradation rate of the biodegradable
plastic. The present invention was thus accomplished based
on these findings.</p><p num="0014">The first aspect of the present invention provides
a biodegradable plastic composition comprising (A) 100
parts by weight of biodegradable plastic, (B) 0.01 to 10
parts by weight of a carbodiimide compound, and (C) 0.01
to 10 parts by weight of at least one compound selected from
the group consisting of benzotriazole-, triazine- and
hydroxylamine-based one.</p><p num="0015">The second aspect of the present invention provides
the biodegradable plastic composition of the first aspect,
characterized in that the benzotriazole-based compound is
a benzotriazole-based ultraviolet absorber.</p><p num="0016">The third aspect of the present invention provides
the biodegradable plastic composition of the first aspect,
characterized in that the triazine-based compound is a
triazine-based ultraviolet absorber or triazine derivative
having at least one amino group in the molecule.</p><p num="0017">The fourth aspect of the present invention provides
the biodegradable plastic composition of the first aspect, 
characterized in that the hydroxylamine-based compound is
N-hydroxybenzotriazole, N-hydroxysuccinimide or a
derivative thereof.</p><p num="0018">The fifth aspect of the present invention provides
the biodegradable plastic composition of the first aspect,
characterized in that the biodegradable plastic (A) is an
aliphatic-based polyester.</p><p num="0019">The sixth aspect of the present invention provides
the biodegradable plastic composition of the first aspect,
characterized in that the carbodiimide compound (B) is
aliphatic polycarbodiimide.</p><p num="0020">The seventh aspect of the present invention
provides the biodegradable plastic composition of the sixth
aspect, characterized in that the aliphatic
polycarbodiimide compound has an isocyanate terminal.</p><p num="0021">The eighth aspect of the present invention provides
a molded article of a biodegradable plastic obtained by
molding the biodegradable plastic composition of any one
of the first to seventh aspects.</p><p num="0022">The ninth aspect of the present invention provides
the molded article of the biodegradable plastic of the
eighth aspect, which is in the form of molded article,
extrudate, blow-molded article, thermally molded article,
fiber, non-woven fabric, film or sheet.</p><p num="0023">The tenth aspect of the present invention provides
a method for controlling biodegradation rate of a
biodegradable plastic, characterized in that a 
biodegradable plastic (A) is compounded with a carbodiimide
compound (B) and at least one compound (C) selected from
the group consisting of benzotriazole-, triazine- and
hydroxylamine-based one in such a way to adjust its
biodegradability.</p><p num="0024">As described above, the present invention relates
to a biodegradable plastic composition and the like,
characterized in that a biodegradable plastic (A) is
compounded with specified amounts of a carbodiimide
compound (B) and specified compound (C), and the preferred
embodiments thereof include the followings:
<sl><li>(1) The biodegradable plastic composition of the first
aspect, characterized in that it comprises 100 parts by
weight of the biodegradable plastic (A) ; 0. 1 to 5 parts by
weight of the carbodiimide compound (B); and 0.1 to 5 parts
by weight of the compound (C).</li><li>(2) The biodegradable plastic composition of the third
aspect, characterized in that the triazine-based compound
is a triazine-based ultraviolet absorber.</li><li>(3) The biodegradable plastic composition of the fourth
aspect, characterized in that the hydroxylamine-based
compound is N-hydroxybenzotriazole.</li><li>(4) The biodegradable plastic composition of the fifth
aspect, characterized in that the aliphatic-based polyester
is a polylactic acid-based polyester.</li></sl></p><p num="0025">Hereinbelow, the present invention will be 
described in detail for each element.

   The biodegradable plastic composition of the
present invention comprises (A) a biodegradable plastic
compounded with (B) a carbodiimide compound and (C) at least
one compound selected from the group consisting of
benzotriazole-, triazine- and hydroxylamine-based one.</p><heading>1. Biodegradable plastic (A)</heading><p num="0026">The examples of the biodegradable plastic as a main
component used in the biodegradable plastic compound of the
present invention include those derived from polyesters
metabolized by microorganisms, of which aliphatic-polyesters
are more preferable because they are easily
metabolized by microorganisms.</p><p num="0027">In general, the biodegradable plastic is believed
to undergo biodegradation through the following processes.</p><p num="0028">Namely, in a decomposition of a polymer material
(biodegradable plastic) discharged into an environment, (i)
a polymer degrading enzyme is adsorbed on the surface of
the polymer material. This enzyme is a substance secreted
extracellularly by a certain kind of microorganism. (ii)
The enzyme, then, breaks such chemical bonds of polymer
chains as ester, glycosidic and peptide linkages by a
hydrolysis reaction. (iii) As a result, the polymermaterial
is reduced in molecular weight and decomposed even to a
monomer unit by a degrading enzyme. (iv) Finally, decomposed
products are further metabolized and utilized by various
microorganisms and converted into carbon dioxide, water and 
bacterial cell components.</p><p num="0029">On the other hand, poly (α-oxyacid) represented by
polylactic acid, is believed to undergo biodegradation in
2 stages.</p><p num="0030">In the primary stage, a high-molecular-weight
polylactic acid is decomposed mainly by simple hydrolysis
involving no microorganisms, because it is difficult to
decompose by microorganisms. When decomposed to have a
number-average molecular weight (Mn) of the order of 10,000
to 20, 000, it will undergo the secondary decomposition stage
proceeding in the presence of a microbial polymer degrading
enzyme, in addition to the simple hydrolysis. The second
stage decomposes the polylactic acid even to a monomer unit.
The decomposed products are further metabolized and
utilized by various microorganisms and converted into
carbon dioxide, water and bacterial cell components.</p><p num="0031">The aliphatic polyesters which are easily
metabolized and hydrolyzed by microorganisms include:
<sl><li>(1) polylactic acid (polylactide) type aliphatic polyester;</li><li>(2) aliphatic polyester as a product of condensation
reaction of polyvalent alcohol and polybasic acid;</li><li>(3) aliphatic polyester produced by microorganisms such as
polyhydroxybutylate (PHB); and</li><li>(4) polycaprolactone (PCL) type aliphatic polyester. Any of
the above aliphatic polyesters can be preferably used as
the biodegradable plastic for the present invention.</li></sl></p><p num="0032">Further, in the present invention, the
biodegradable plastic is not limited to the above-described 
aliphatic polyesters but any types thereof can be used as
long as they have such chemical bonds as ester, glycosidic
and peptide linkages which facilitate a scission of polymer
chain in the biodegradable plastic by the hydrolysis
reaction. Such type of polymers include, for example, a
carbonate copolymer of the aliphatic polyester produced by
randomly introducing a carbonate structure into a molecular
chain backbone of the aliphatic polyester, and a copolymer
of the aliphatic polyester having amide bonds and a
polyamide produced by introducing nylon into a molecular
chain backbone of the aliphatic polyester.</p><p num="0033">Next, the aliphatic polyesters will be further
described in more detail.</p><heading>(1) Polylactic acid (polylactide) type aliphatic polyester</heading><p num="0034">The polylactic acid (polylactide) type aliphatic
polyesters include polylactides, and specifically polymers
of oxyacids such as lactic acid, malic acid and glycolic
acid and copolymers thereof including, for example,
polylactic acid, poly(α- malic acid), polyglycolic acid and
a copolymer of glycolic acid and lactic acid, in particular,
a hydroxycarboxylic acid type aliphatic polyesters,
typically represented by polylactic acid.</p><p num="0035">The above-described polylactic acid type aliphatic
polyester can be obtained, in general, by a ring-opening
polymerization method of lactide, as a cyclic diester, and
corresponding lactone (so to speak a lactide method), as 
well as a direct dehydration condensation method of lactic
acid and a polycondensation method of formalin and carbon
dioxide, as a method other than the lactide method.</p><p num="0036">Further, examples of the catalyst for producing the
above-described polylactic acid type aliphatic polyester
include tin, antimony, zinc, titanium, iron and aluminum
compounds. Among them, a tin-based or aluminum-based
catalyst is more preferable, and tin octoate and aluminum
acetylacetonato are particularly preferable.</p> <p num="0037">Among the above-described polylactic acid type
aliphatic polyesters, poly(L-lactic acid) obtained by the
ring-opening polymerization of the lactide is preferable,
because poly (L-lactic acid) is hydrolyzed to L-lactic acid,
whose safety has already been confirmed. However, the
polylactic acid type aliphatic polyesters useful for the
present invention are not limited to the above type
polyesters, and therefore the lactide used for producing
the polylactic acid is also not limited to L-type.</p><heading>(2) Aliphatic polyester as a product of condensation
reaction of polyvalent alcohol and polybasic acid.</heading><p num="0038">Examples of the aliphatic polyester as a product
of condensation reaction of polyvalent alcohol and
polybasic acid include an aliphatic glycol/polybasic acid
type polyester obtained by reacting an aliphatic glycol with
aliphatic polybasic acid (or anhydride thereof) in the
presence of a catalyst, or a high-molecular-weight 
aliphatic glycol/polybasic acid type polyester obtained in
the presence of a small amount of coupling agent, if
necessary.</p><p num="0039">The aliphatic glycols for producing the aliphatic
glycol/polybasic acid type polyesters useful for the
present invention include, for example, ethylene glycol,
1,4-butandiol, 1,6-hexanediol, decamethylene glycol,
neopentyl glycol and 1,4-cyclohexanedimethanol. Ethylene
oxide can be also used. These glycols may be used in
combination.</p><p num="0040">Examples of the aliphatic polybasic acid or
anhydride thereof to form the aliphatic glycol/polybasic
acid type polyester by the reaction with the above-described
aliphatic glycol include succinic acid, adipic acid,
suberic acid, sebacic acid, dodecanic acid, and succinic
anhydride and adipic anhydride, which are generally
available in the market, and can be used for the present
invention. These polybasic acids and anhydrides thereof may
be used in combination.</p> <p num="0041">The above-described glycols and polybasic acids
are of aliphatic type. They may be compounded with a small
amount of another component, such as aromatic glycol or
aromatic polybasic acid (terephthalic acid, trimellitic
anhydride, pyromellitic anhydride or the like).</p> <p num="0042">In addition, examples of the catalyst to produce 
the above-described aliphatic glycol/polybasic acid type
polyester are salts of organic acids, alkoxides and oxides
of such metals as titanium, tin, antimony, cerium, zinc,
cobalt, iron, lead, manganese, aluminum, magnesium and
germanium, and among them, a tin-based or aluminum-based
compound is more preferable.</p> <p num="0043">The above-described aliphatic glycol/polybasic
acid type polyester may be produced by reacting an
equivalent amount of the aliphatic glycol and aliphatic
polybasic acid together with the catalyst by heating, using
a solvent appropriately selected depending on raw material
.compounds, if necessary, and a prepolymer with a low degree
of polymerization can be produced by controlling progress
of the reaction.</p><p num="0044">In the production of the above-described aliphatic
glycol/polybasic acid type polyester, a coupling agent can
be used, in particular, for the prepolymer with low degree
of polymerization, to further increase its number-average
molecular weight. Examples of the coupling agent include
diisocyanate, oxazoline, diepoxy compounds and acid
anhydrides, and particularly diisocyanate is preferably
used.</p><p num="0045">The diisocyanate as the above-described coupling
agent is not specifically limited in type. They include
2,4-tolylene diisocyanate, a mixture of 2,4-tolylene
diisocyanate and 2,6-tolylene diisocyanate, 
diphenylmethane diisocyanate, 1,5-naphthalene
diisocyanate, xylylene diisocyanate, hydrogenated
xylylene diisocyanate, hexamethylene diisocyanate,
isophorone diisocyanate and 4,4'-dicyclohexylmethane
diisocyanate. Hexamethylene diisocyanate is particularly
preferable in view of a hue of the aliphatic
glycol/polybasic acid type polyester obtained and
reactivity while being compounded into the above-described
prepolymer.</p><p num="0046">Amount of the above-described coupling agent is 0. 1
to 5 parts by weight, preferably 0.5 to 3 parts by weight
based on 100 parts by weight of the above-described
prepolymer. An amount less than 0.1 parts by weight results
in an insufficient extent of the coupling reaction, whereas
an amount above 5 parts by weight tends to cause gelation.</p><p num="0047">Moreover, the above-described aliphatic
glycol/polybasic acid type polyester may have a terminal
hydroxyl group capped by another compound via a double bond,
urethane bond or urea bond, or a modified one.</p><p num="0048">Typical examples of the aliphatic polyester on the
markets, as a condensation product of polyvalent alcohol
and polybasic acid, are polybutylene succinate (PBS) and
polyethylene succinate (PES).

   Examples of the polybutylene succinate (PBS) type
aliphatic polyester are, for example, polybutylene
succinate (PBS) made from butanediol and succinic acid, an 
adipate copolymer (PBSA) obtained by copolymerizing adipic
acid to accelerate biodegradability, and
adipate/terephthalate copolymer obtained by
copolymerizing terephthalic acid. The commercial products
include "Bionolle®, "EnPol®", "Ecoflex®" and "BioMax®"
supplied by Showa Highpolymer, Ire Chemical, BASF and Du
Pont, respectively.

   In addition, poly(ethylene succinate) (PES) is also
commercially available, and a commercial product such as
"Lunarle SE®" is supplied by Nippon Shokubai.</p><heading>(3) Aliphatic polyester produced by microorganisms</heading><p num="0049">Certain kind of microorganisms accumulates a
polyester in their cells. The polyester produced by
microorganisms is a thermoplastic polymer with a melting
point derived from the organisms. Such a polyester is
decomposed by an enzyme secreted extracellularly by a
microorganism in natural environment and completely
disappears because decomposition products are consumed by
the microorganism.

   Such (aliphatic) polyesters produced by
microorganisms include polyhydroxybutyrate (PHB),
poly(hydroxybutyric acid - hydroxypropionic
acid)copolymer and poly(hydroxybutyric acid
hydroxyvaleric acid) copolymer.</p><heading>(4) Polycaprolactone (PCL) type aliphatic polyester</heading><p num="0050">Polycaprolactone, a kind of aliphatic polyester,
is obtained by a ring-opening polymerization of ε-caprolactone, 
and can be decomposed by various bacteria,
although it is a water-insoluble polymer.</p><p num="0051">Polycaprolactone is an aliphatic polyester
expressed by a general formula: -(O(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>CO)<sub>n</sub>-, and as a
commercial product of the polycaprolactone type aliphatic
polyester, for example, "Tone®" supplied from Nippon Unicar
is known.</p><heading>2. Carbodiimide compound (B)</heading><p num="0052">As the carbodiimide compounds (including
polycarbodiimide compounds) having at least one
carbodiimide group in the molecule, useful for the present
invention, those synthesized by commonly well known methods
may be used. The compound can be obtained, for example, by
conducting a decarboxylation condensation reaction of
various polyisocyanates in the presence of an
organophosphorus or organometallic compound as a catalyst
at a temperature not lower than about 70°C, without using
any solvent or using an inert solvent.</p><p num="0053">Examples of the monocarbodiimide compound included
in the above-described carbodiimide compounds are
dicyclohexylcarbodiimide, diisopropylcarbodiimide,
dimethylcarbodiimide, diisobutylcarbodiimide,
dioctylcarbodiimide, t-butylisopropylcarbodiimide,
diphenylcarbodiimide, di-t-butylcarbodiimide and di-β-naphthylcarbodiimide,
and among them,
dicyclohexylcarbodiimide and diisopropylcarbodiimide are
particularly preferable because of their industrial 
availability.</p><p num="0054">Further, as the polycarbodiimide compound included
in the above-described carbodiimide compounds, those
produced by various methods may be used, but basically those
produced by conventional production methods for
polycarbodiimide [for example, the methods disclosed in USP
No. 2941956, JP-B-47-33279, J. Org. Chem. 28, 2069-2075
(1963) and Chemical Review 1981, Vol. 81, No.4, p619-621]
can be used.</p><p num="0055">Examples of organic diisocyanate, as a raw material
for producing a polycarbodiimide compound include, for
example, aromatic diisocyanate, aliphatic diisocyanate,
alicyclic diisocyanate and a mixture thereof, and
specifically include 1,5-naphthalene diisocyanate,
4,4'-diphenylmethane diisocyanate, 4,4'-diphenyldimethylmethane
diisocyanate, 1,3-phenylene
diisocyanate, 1,4-phenylene diisocyanate, 2,4-tolylene
diisocyanate, 2,6-tolylene diisocyanate, a mixture of
2,4-tolylene diisocyanate and 2,6-tolylene diisocyanate,
hexamethylene diisocyanate, cyclohexane-1,4-diisocyanate,
xylylene diisocyanate, isophorone diisocyanate,
dicyclohexylmethane-4,4'- diisocyanate,
methylcyclohexane diisocyanate, tetramethylxylylene
diisocyanate, 2,6-diisopropylphenyl isocyanate and
1,3,5-triisopropylbenzene-2,4-diisocyanate.</p><p num="0056">In addition, in the case of the above-described 
polycarbodiimide compound, its degree of polymerization can
be controlled to an appropriate level by terminating the
polymerization reaction before it is completed by cooling
or the like. In such a case, it has isocyanate at the terminal.
Moreover, the remaining isocyanate at the terminal may be
capped totally or partly by use of a compound such as
monoisocyanate capable of reacting with the terminal
isocyanate group of the polycarbodiimide compound, in order
to control its degree of polymerization at an appropriate
level. Controlling its degree of polymerization is
preferable for improved quality, resulting from improved
compatibility with the polymer and storage stability.</p><p num="0057">Examples of the monoisocyanate for controlling
degree of polymerization of the polycarbodiimide compound
by capping its terminal group include phenyl isocyanate,
tolyl isocyanate, dimethylphenyl isocyanate, cyclohexyl
isocyanate, butyl isocyanate and naphthyl isocyanate.</p><p num="0058">Further, the terminal capping agents for
controlling degree of polymerization of the
polycarbodiimide compound by capping its terminal group are
not limited to the above-described monoisocyanates, and
include compounds having active hydrogen capable of
reacting with isocyanate. These compounds include (i)
aliphatic, aromatic or alicyclic compounds having -OH group,
such as methanol, ethanol, phenol, cyclohexanol, N-methylethanolamine,
polyethylene glycol monomethyl ether
and polypropylene glycol monomethyl ether; (ii) compounds 
having a =NH group, such as diethylamine and
dicyclohexylamine; (iii) compounds having a -NH<sub>2</sub> group, such
as butylamine and cyclohexylamine; (iv) compounds having
a -COOH group, such as succinic acid, benzoic acid and
cyclohexanoic acid; (v) compounds having a -SH group, such
as ethylmercaptan, allylmercaptan and thiophenol; (vi)
compounds having an epoxy group; and (vii) acid anhydrides,
such as acetic anhydride, methyltetrahydrophthalate
anhydride, and methylhexahydrophthalic anhydride.</p><p num="0059">The decarboxylation condensation reaction of the
above-described organic diisocyanate is performed in the
presence of a suitable carbodiimidation catalyst. The
carbodiimidation catalysts preferable for the present
invention include an organophosphorus compound, and
organometallic compound [expressed by the general formula
M- (OR)<sub>4</sub>, wherein M is titanium (Ti) , sodium (Na) , potassium
(K), vanadium (V), tungsten (W), hafnium (Hf), zirconium
(Zr), lead (Pb), manganese (Mn) , nickel (Ni), calcium (Ca),
barium (Ba) or the like, and R is an alkyl or aryl group
having carbon atoms of 1 to 20], of which phospholeneoxide
as the organophosphorus compound and alkoxide of titanium,
hafnium or zirconium as the organometallic compound are
particularly preferable from the viewpoint of activity.</p><p num="0060">The above-described phospholeneoxides include
specifically 3-methyl-1-phenyl-2-phospholene-1-oxide,
3-methyl-1-ethyl-2-phospholene-1-oxide, 1,3-dimethyl-2-phospholene-1-oxide,
1-phenyl-2-phospholene-1-oxide, 1-ethyl-2-phospholene-1-oxide, 
1-methyl-2-phospholene-1-oxide
and double bond isomers thereof, of which 3-methyl-1-phenyl-2-phospholene-1-oxide
is particularly
preferable because of its industrial availability.</p><p num="0061">The inventors of the present invention consider
that the carbodiimide compound (B) in the biodegradable
plastic composition of the present invention has the
following functions: first, it reacts with the residual
hydroxyl or carboxyl group in the biodegradable compound,
which is considered to accelerate the hydrolysis, during
the initial stage after it is compounded, to control the
hydrolysis, and then it is added to the bonds in the
biodegradable plastic cleaved by the hydrolysis to
recombine them.</p><p num="0062">The carbodiimide compound useful for the present
invention is not limited so long as it has at least one
carbodiimide group to realize the above functions. However,
an aliphatic polycarbodiimide compound is preferable
because of its safety, stability and compatibility with the
biodegradable plastic.</p><p num="0063">An aliphatic carbodiimide compound having
isocyanate group at the terminal is particularly preferable
because of its hydrolysis resistance.</p><p num="0064">Moreover, an aliphatic carbodiimide compound is
more preferable than an aromatic carbodiimide compound
viewed from its resistance to hydrolysis and weather, and
compatibility with the biodegradable plastic. </p><p num="0065">Amount of the carbodiimide compound (B) is
preferably 0.01 to 10 parts by weight, more preferably 0.1
to 5 parts by weight, particularly preferably 0.1 to 3 parts
by weight based on 100 parts by weight of the biodegradable
plastic. An amount less than 0.01 parts by weight may give
no effect on adjustment or control of the biodegradation
rate of the biodegradable plastic composition, whereas the
amount over 10 parts by weight may reduce the
biodegradability of the biodegradable plastic, and
furthermore may deteriorate its transparency, which may
cause problems for those purposes in which transparency is
required.</p><heading>3. Compound (C)</heading><p num="0066">The biodegradable plastic composition of the
present invention includes at least one compound (Compound
(C)) selected from the group consisting of benzotriazole-,
triazine- and hydroxylamine-based one.</p><p num="0067">The compound (C) imparts a notable effect of
hydrolysis resistance to the biodegradable plastic
composition by preventing hydrolysis of the biodegradable
plastic, when used in combination with the carbodiimide
compound (B).</p><heading>(1) Benzotriazole-based compound</heading><p num="0068">Examples of the benzotriazole-based compound as
one of those for the compound (C) to be compounded in the
biodegradable plastic composition of the present invention
include those normally used as organic ultraviolet 
absorbers and for peptide condensation. It may be merely
benzotriazole or its derivative.</p><p num="0069">The benzotriazole-based compound used as an
ultraviolet absorber (UVA) is not limited, so long as it
is normally used as an ultraviolet absorber. They include
2-(2'-hydroxy-5'-methylphenyl)benzotriazole, 2-(2'-hydroxy-5'-t-butylphenyl)benzotriazole,
2-(2'-hydroxy-3'-t-butyl-5'-methylphenyl)-5-chlorobenzotriazole,
2-(3,5-di-t-butyl-2-hydroxyphenyl)-5-chlorobenzotriazole,
2-[2'-hydroxy-3',5'-bis (α, α-dimethylbenzyl)phenyl]benzotriazole
and 2-(2'-hydroxy-3',5'-di-t-butylphenyl)benzotriazole.</p><p num="0070">More specifically, the commercial products include
"TINUVIN 234®," "TINUVIN 320®," "TINUVIN 326®," "TINUVIN
327®," "TINUVIN 328®" and "TINUVIN P®" supplied by Ciba
Specialty Chemicals, and "Sumisorb 340®" supplied by
Sumitomo Chemical.</p><p num="0071">Examples of the benzotriazole-based compound for
peptide condensation include N-hydroxybenzotriazole (or
1-hydroxybenzotriazole) and its derivative.</p><heading>(2) Triazine-based compound</heading><p num="0072">Examples of the triazine-based compound as one of
those for the compound (C) to be compounded in the
biodegradable plastic composition of the present invention
include those normally used as organic ultraviolet
absorbers and those having at least one amino group in the 
molecule.</p><p num="0073">The triazine-based compound used as an ultraviolet
absorber (UVA) is not limited, so long as it is normally
used as an ultraviolet absorber. They include 2-(4,6-diphenyl-1,3,5-triazin-2-yl)-5-[(hexyl)oxy]phenol
and
2-[4,6-bis(2,4-dimethylphenyl)-1,3,5-triazin-2-yl]-5-[(octyl)oxy]phenol.
More specifically, the commercial
products include "TINUVIN 1577®" supplied by Ciba Specialty
Chemicals, and "Cyasorb UV-1164®" supplied by Cytec
Industries.</p><p num="0074">The triazine derivatives having at least one amino
group in the molecule include 2,4,6-triamino-1,3,5-triazine
(or melamine), 2,4-diamino-6-phenyl-1,3,5-triazine
(or benzoguanamine), 2,4-diamino-6-methyl-1,3,5-triazine,
2,4-diamino-6-(2-(dodecasylamino)ethyl)-1,3,5-triazine,
2,4-diamino-6-(o-methoxyphenyl)-1,3,5-triazine,
4,6-diamino-1,2-dihydro-2,2-dimethyl-1-(2,6-xylyl)-1,3,5-triazine,
2,4-diamino-6-(2-methoxyethyl)-1,3,5-triazine,
2-amino-4-ethyl-1,3,5-triazine,
2-amino-4-phenyl-1,3,5-triazine,
2-amino-4-ethyl-6-methyl-1,3,5-triazine, 2-amino-4-ethyl-6-phenyl-1,3,5-triazine,
2-amino-4-methyl-6-phenyl-1,3,5-triazine
and 2,4-bis-(n-octylthio)-6-(4-hydroxy-3,5-di-t-butylanilino)-1,3,5-triazine.
More
specifically, the commercial products include
"IRGANOX565®" and "CHIMASSORB119 FL®, supplied by Ciba
Specialty Chemicals. The triazine derivative useful for the 
present invention is not limited to the above, and any
triazine derivative may be used so long as it has at least
one amino group in the molecule.</p><heading>(3) Hydroxylamine-based compound</heading><p num="0075">Examples of the hydroxylamine-based compound as
one of those for the compound (C) to be compounded in the
biodegradable plastic composition of the present invention
include those used for peptide condensation. They include
N-hydroxybenzotriazole (1-hydroxybenzotriazole), N-hydroxysuccinimide
and a derivative thereof. N-hydroxybenzotriazole
is also cited as one of the
benzotriazole-based compounds described above.</p><p num="0076">The compound (C) is compounded in the biodegradable
plastic composition of the present invention at a content
at which it can exhibit, when used in combination with the
carbodiimide compound (B), an effect of improving
resistance to hydrolysis and weather, in particular a
synergistic effect of improving hydrolysis resistance.</p><p num="0077">Amount of the compound (C) is preferably 0.01 to
10 parts by weight, more preferably 0.1 to 5 parts by weight,
particularly preferably 0.1 to 3 parts by weight based on
100 parts by weight of the biodegradable plastic. An amount
less than 0.01 parts by weight may neither give an effect
on adjustment or control of the biodegradation rate of the
biodegradable plastic composition nor a synergistic effect
with the carbodiimide compound (B), whereas an amount over
10 parts by weight may reduce the biodegradability of the 
biodegradable plastic, and furthermore may not produce the
effect which reflects the amount.</p><p num="0078">In the present invention, the biodegradable
plastic (A) may be incorporated with the carbodiimide
compound (B) and compound (C) by dissolving these compounds
in an organic solvent and then distilling off the solvent.
It is preferable that the organic solvent can dissolve the
biodegradable plastic, needless to say, and is free of
nonpolymerizable, active hydrogen. More specifically, the
organic solvents useful for the present invention include
chloroform and tetrahydrofuran (THF).</p><p num="0079">In the present invention, mixing of the above-described
carbodiimide compound (B) and compound (C) with
the biodegradable plastic (A) can be performed by melt
mixing using an extruder, or adding the carbodiimide
compound (B) and compound (C) after the termination of
synthesis of the biodegradable plastic.</p><p num="0080">The melt mixing may be performed by one of the
following methods:
<sl><li>(1) Mix the carbodiimide compound (B) and compound (C) , into
which the biodegradable plastic (A) is mixed.</li><li>(2) Mix the biodegradable plastic (A) and any one of the
carbodiimide compound (B) and compound (C), into which the
remainder is mixed.</li><li>(3) Mix the biodegradable plastic (A) and carbodiimide
compound (B), into which a mixture of the biodegradable
plastic (A) and compound (C) is mixed. </li><li>(4) Simultaneously mix the biodegradable plastic (A),
carbodiimide compound (B) and compound (C).</li></sl></p><p num="0081">Biodegradation rate of the biodegradable plastic
of the present invention can be adjusted by type and amount
of the carbodiimide compound (B) and the compound (C) to
be compounded, and the type and the amount of the above to
be compounded may be determined depending on a specific
purpose of the biodegradable plastic composition.</p><heading>4. Other additives and the like</heading><p num="0082">The biodegradable plastic composition of the
present invention may be further compounded with one or more
additives within a range not to impair the effects of the
present invention. These additives include reinforcing
agent, clay, inorganic or organic filler, amine-, phenol-or
phosphorus-based antioxidant, heat stabilizer, hindered
amine type light stabilizer and UV absorber, as well as flame
retardant, lubricant, wax, colorant, crystallization
promoter and degradable organic substances such as starch,
if necessary.</p><p num="0083">The biodegradable plastic composition of the
present invention can be stably adjusted in biodegradation
rate, and has greatly improved resistance to hydrolysis and
weather, in particular the former, and durability resulting
from the improved resistances. Therefore it can be suitably
used in such fields as materials for agriculture, forestry
and fishery (mulch film, mulch sheet, plantation pot, 
fishing line, fishing net, and the like); materials for
civil engineering works (water-holding sheet, net for
plants, sandbag, and the like); and molded article,
extrudate, blow-molded article, thermally molded article,
fiber, non-woven fabric, film for packing/container fields,
in particular, molded articles of the biodegradable plastic
such as film, sheet, fiber, bottle and tray.</p><heading>EXAMPLES</heading><p num="0084">Hereinbelow, the present invention will be
explained in more detail using Examples, which by no means
limit the present invention. Physical properties in
Examples and Comparative Examples were measured and
evaluated by the following methods.</p><heading>[Hydrolysis resistance]</heading><p num="0085">Each test sample piece was left in an air-conditioned
chamber maintained at 80°C and 90%RH for a fixed
period (200, 150 or 100 hours), and ratios (%) of tensile
strength and elongation after the test to the values before
the test were calculated. Hydrolysis resistance was ranked
as "good" for the sample with high ratios (%) of tensile
strength and elongation.</p><heading>[Weather resistance]</heading><p num="0086">Each test sample piece was exposed to light from
a xenon lamp under the conditions of BPT 50C°×60% for 2000
hours, and ratios (%) of tensile strength and elongation
after the test to the values before the test were calculated. 
Weather resistance was ranked as "good" for the sample with
high ratios (%) of tensile strength and elongation.</p><p num="0087">Before describing Examples and Comparative
Examples, synthesis methods for carbodiimide compounds will
be described first.</p><heading>[Synthesis Example 1 for a carbodiimide compound]</heading><p num="0088">4,4'-dicyclohexylmethane diisocyanate was
treated for carbodiimidation at 185°C for 24 hours in the
presence of 3-methyl-1-phenyl-2-phospholene-1-oxide as a
carbodiimidation catalyst, incorporated at 0.5 parts by
weight based on 100 parts by weight of the diisocyanate.
The resulting carbodiimide compound with isocyanate group
at the terminal had an NCO% of 2.4 and average polymerization
degree of 15.</p><heading>[Examples 1 to 3]</heading><p num="0089">An aliphatic polyester resin as the biodegradable
plastic (A), mainly composed of polybutylene
succinate/adipate, carbodiimide compound (B) and compound
(C) were dry blended, followed by mixing in a twin screw
extruder to prepare a film with a thickness of 200 µm through
T-die, where the compounds (B) for Examples 1 to 3 were 1
part of "Carbodilite HMV-10B®" as an aliphatic carbodiimide
compound supplied by Nisshinbo Industries, Inc.,
"Carbodilite HMV-8CA®" supplied by Nisshinbo Industries,
Inc. and "Stabaxol P" supplied by Bayer AG, respectively,
and the compound (C) for Examples 1 to 3 was 0.5 parts of 
2-[2'-hydroxy-3',5'-bis(α,α-dimethylbenzyl)phenyl]benzotriazole
as a benzotriazole-based
compound ("TINUVIN 234®" supplied by Ciba Specialty
Chemicals), all part(s) by weight based on 100 parts by
weight of the component (A) . Each film was punched by a JIS
No. 4 dumbbell to prepare the test piece, which was evaluated
for its resistance to weather and hydrolysis (test period:
200 hours). Table 1 gives the compositions and evaluation
results.</p><heading>[Comparative Examples 1 to 3]</heading><p num="0090">A film was prepared in each of Comparative Examples
1 to 3 in the same manner as in each of Examples 1 to 3,
except that the compound (C) was not compounded, to evaluate
its resistance to weather and hydrolysis (test period: 200
hours). Table 1 gives the compositions and evaluation
results. <tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Example 1</entry><entry align="center">Example 2</entry><entry align="center">Example 3</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Example 1</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Example 2</entry><entry align="center">Comparative Example 3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">1. Composition (parts by weight)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(A) Biodegradable plastic</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Polybutylene succinate/adipate</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry><entry align="center">100</entry></row><row><entry align="left">· Polylactic acid</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(B) Carbodiimide compound</entry></row><row><entry align="left">· Carbodilite HMV-10B</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">· Carbodilite HMV-8CA</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">· Stabaxol P</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(C) Specified compound</entry></row><row><entry align="left">· TINUVIN 234 (ultraviolet absorber)</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">0.5</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry><entry align="center">-</entry></row><row><entry align="left">2. Evaluation results</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(1) Weather resistance Strength ratio (%)</entry><entry align="center">93</entry><entry align="center">91</entry><entry align="center">73</entry><entry align="center">48</entry><entry align="center">42</entry><entry align="center">17</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Weather resistance Elongation ratio (%)</entry><entry align="center">91</entry><entry align="center">92</entry><entry align="center">81</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">30</entry><entry align="center">5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">(2) Hydrolysis resistance<!--footnotes removed-->1 Strength ratio (%)</entry><entry align="center">93</entry><entry align="center">91</entry><entry align="center">91</entry><entry align="center">43 43</entry><entry align="center">31</entry><entry align="center">27</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Hydrolysis resistance<!--footnotes removed-->1 Elongation ratio (%)</entry><entry align="center">91</entry><entry align="center">92</entry><entry align="center">88</entry><entry align="center">35</entry><entry align="center">20</entry><entry align="center">24<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0091">As shown in Table 1, which compares the results of
Examples 1 to 3 with those of Comparative Examples 1 to 3,
it is apparent that the carbodiimide compound (B) and
compound (C) produce a synergistic effect for improving
resistance to hydrolysis and weather.</p><heading>[Examples 4 to 11]</heading><p num="0092">A film was prepared in Example 4 in the same manner
as in Example 1, except that an aliphatic polyester resin
as the biodegradable plastic (A), mainly composed of
polylactic acid, the carbodiimide compound prepared in
Synthesis Example 1 to have isocyanate group at the terminal 
as the compound (B) and benzotriazole-based compound (C)
(2-(2'-hydroxy-3'-t-butyl-5'-methylphenyl)-5-chlorobenzotriazole,
"TINUVIN 326®" supplied by Ciba
Specialty Chemicals) were compounded, to evaluate its
resistance to weather and hydrolysis (test period: 150
hours). Table 2 gives the composition and evaluation
results.</p><p num="0093">A film was prepared in each of Examples 5 to 11 in
the same manner as in Example 1, except that a different
composition was used, to evaluate its resistance to weather
and hydrolysis (test period: 150 hours) . Table 2 gives the
compositions and evaluation results.</p><p num="0094">The compound (C) used in Examples 10 and 11 was
2-[4,6-bis(2,4-dimethylphenyl)-1,3,5-triazin-2-yl]-5-[(octyl)oxy]phenol
as a triazine-based compound ("Cyasorb
UV-1164®" supplied by Cytec Industries).</p><heading>[Comparative Examples 4 to 8]</heading><p num="0095">A film was prepared in each of Comparative Examples
4 to 8 in the same manner as in Example 1, except that a
different composition was used, to evaluate its resistance
to weather and hydrolysis (test period: 150 hours) . Table
2 gives the composition and evaluation results.

   A film was prepared in the absence of specified
compound (C) in each of Comparative Examples 4 to 6, and
in the absence of carbodiimide compound in Comparative
Example 8. Comparative Example 7 used an oxazoline-based
compound in place of specified compound (C) and carbodiimide 
compound (B). <img id="img-00340001" orientation="unknown" wi="121" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00340001.tif" inline="no" he="231"/></p><heading>[Examples 12 and 13]</heading><p num="0096">A film was prepared in Example 12 in the same manner
as in Example 1, except that a polyester resin mainly
composed of polybutylene succinate/adipate/terephthalate
("EnPol G 8002®" supplied by Ire Chemical), aliphatic
carbodiimide compound ("Carbodilite HMV-8CA®" supplied by
Nisshinbo Industries) and benzotriazole were used as the
biodegradable plastic (A), carbodiimide compound (B) and
compound (C), respectively, to evaluate its hydrolysis
resistance (test period: 100 hours). Table 3 gives the
composition and evaluation results.</p><p num="0097">A film was prepared in Example 13 in the same manner
as in Example 1, except that a polyester resin mainly
composed of polybutylene succinate/adipate/terephthalate,
aliphatic carbodiimide compound ("Carbodilite HMV-8CA®"
supplied by Nisshinbo Industries) and benzotriazole (2-(3,5-di-t-butyl-2-hydroxyphenyl)-5-
chlorobenzotriazole,
"TINUVIN 327®" supplied by Ciba Specialty Chemicals) were
used as the biodegradable plastic (A), carbodiimide
compound (B) and compound (C), respectively, to evaluate
its hydrolysis resistance (test period: 100 hours). Table
3 gives the composition and evaluation results.</p><heading>[Comparative Examples 9 to 12]</heading><p num="0098">A film was prepared in each of Comparative Examples
9 to 12 in the same manner as in Example 1, except that a
different composition was used, to evaluate its hydrolysis
resistance (test period: 100 hours). Table 3 gives the 
composition and evaluation results.</p><p num="0099">Comparative Example 9 used an epoxy compound in
place of a specified compound (C) and carbodiimide compound
(B) . Comparative Example 10 used an epoxy compound in place
of a carbodiimide compound (C) . Comparative Example 11 used
2,2'-dihydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone ("Cyasorb UV-24®"
supplied by Cytec Industries) as a benzophenone-based
ultraviolet absorber in place of a specified compound (C) .
Comparative Example 12 used 2-(3,5-di-t-butyl-2-hydroxyphenyl)-5-
chlorobenzotriazole ("TINUVIN 327®"
supplied by Ciba Specialty Chemicals) as a
benzotriazole-based compound (C), but no carbodiimide
compound (B) as was the case with Comparative Example 8. <img id="img-00370001" orientation="unknown" wi="140" img-format="tif" img-content="tb" file="00370001.tif" inline="no" he="230"/></p><p num="0100">As obvious from the results of Examples and
Comparative Examples shown in Table 1 - 3, it was found that
the biodegradable plastic composition of the present
invention comprising a biodegradable plastic (A) compounded
with a carbodiimide compound (B) and specified compound (C)
exhibited much higher resistance to hydrolysis and weather,
in particular resistance to biodegradation induced by
hydrolysis, than the composition free of compound (B) or
(C), e.g., those prepared in Comparative Examples 1 to 6,
8 and 12.</p><p num="0101">It was also found that the biodegradable plastic
composition of the present invention compounded with a
varying content of carbodiimide compound had hydrolysis
resistance improving roughly in proportion to carbodiimide
content (Examples 5 to 8), by which is meant that
biodegradation rate can be stably controlled by its content.</p><p num="0102">On the other hand, the compositions prepared in
Comparative Examples to contain a compound similar to a
carbodiimide compound (B) or specified compound (C) was
found to show no improvement in hydrolysis resistance, where
an oxazoline compound was used in Comparative Example 7,
epoxy compound in Comparative Examples 9 and 10, and
benzophenone-based ultraviolet absorber in Comparative
Example 11. It is particularly noted that the composition
prepared in Example 13 to contain a specified
benzotriazole-based ultraviolet absorber as the compound
(C) is much more resistant to hydrolysis than the one
prepared in Comparative Example 11 to contain a
benzophenone-based ultraviolet absorber. </p><p num="0103">The biodegradable plastic composition of the
present invention, characterized in that it comprises a
biodegradable plastic (A) compounded with specified amounts
of a carbodiimide compound (B) and compound (C), shows
notable advantages because it can be stably adjusted in
biodegradation rate, and has greatly improved resistance
to hydrolysis and weather, in particular the former, and
durability resulting from the improved resistances.</p><p num="0104">Therefore it can be suitably used in such fields
as materials for agriculture, forestry and fishery (mulch
film, mulch sheet, plantation pot, fishing line, fishing
net, and the like); materials for civil engineering works
(water-holding sheet, net for plants, sandbag, and the
like); and molded article, extrudate, blow-molded article,
thermally molded article, fiber, non-woven fabric, film for
packing/container fields, in particular, molded articles
of the biodegradable plastic such as film, sheet, fiber,
bottle and tray.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A biodegradable plastic composition comprising (A) 100
parts by weight of biodegradable plastic, (B) 0.01 to 10
parts by weight of a carbodiimide compound, and (C) 0.01
to 10 parts by weight of at least one compound selected from
the group consisting of benzotriazole-, triazine- and
hydroxylamine-based one.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The biodegradable plastic composition according to
claim 1, characterized in that said benzotriazole-based
compound is a benzotriazole-based ultraviolet absorber.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The biodegradable plastic composition according to
claim 1, characterized in that said triazine-based compound
is a triazine-based ultraviolet absorber or triazine
derivative having at least one amino group in the molecule.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The biodegradable plastic composition according to
claim 1, characterized in that said hydroxylamine-based
compound is N-hydroxybenzotriazole, N-hydroxysuccinimide
or a derivative thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The biodegradable plastic composition according to
anyone of claims 1 to 4, characterized in that said biodegradable plastic
(A) is an aliphatic-based polyester.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The biodegradable plastic composition according to
anyone of claims 1 to 5, chracterized in that said carbodiimide compound
(B) is aliphatic polycarbodiimide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The biodegradable plastic composition according to
claim 6, characterized in that said aliphatic
polycarbodiimide compound has an isocyanate terminal.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A molded article of a biodegradable plastic obtained
by molding the biodegradable plastic composition according
to any one of claims 1 to 7.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The molded article of the biodegradable plastic
according to claim 8, which is in the form of molded article,
extrudate, blow-molded article, thermally molded article,
fiber, non-woven fabric, film or sheet.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A method for controlling biodegradation rate of a
biodegradable plastic, characterized in that a
biodegradable plastic (A) is compounded with a carbodiimide
compound (B) and at least one compound (C) selected from
the group consisting of benzotriazole-, triazine- and
hydroxylamine-based one in such a way to adjust its
biodegradability.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>