<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1486538-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1486538" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="33296896" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20041215"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1486538-A1" status="new" fvid="24211573"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1486538</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20041215</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-04253517-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>04253517</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20040611</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2003168807-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2003168807</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030613</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  67/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  67/12        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  67/20        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09B  67/50        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   7/12        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D   7/12        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/02        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/02        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 201/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D 201/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09B  67/00B5D</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09B  67/00C2</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Verfahren zur Herstellung von einem Kupferphthalocyaninpgiment der beta Form</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Process for the production of beta type copper phthalocyanine pigment</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Procédé de fabrication d'un pigment de phtalocyanine de cuivre de la forme bèta</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0803545-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0803545</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-3084067-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>3084067</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-7310024-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>7310024</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-2999862-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>2999862</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3954795-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3954795</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5175282-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5175282</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5281268-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5281268</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6306938-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6306938</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6379450-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6379450</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 0152, no. 56 (C-0845), 28 June 1991 (1991-06-28) &amp; JP 3 084067 A (TOYO INK MFG CO LTD), 9 April 1991 (1991-04-09)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 1996, no. 03, 29 March 1996 (1996-03-29) &amp; JP 7 310024 A (DAINIPPON INK &amp; CHEM INC), 28 November 1995 (1995-11-28)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TOYO INK MFG CO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TOYO INK MFG. CO., LTD.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TOYO INK MFG. CO., LTD.</last-name><address><street>3-13, Kyobashi 2-chome, Chuo-ku</street><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>IDE YUUSAKU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KOTANI TAKUYA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OSHIBA TOSHIO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SHIROMARU OSAMU</name><address><country>JP</country></address> </addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>IDE, YUUSAKU</name></addressbook></inventor> <inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KOTANI, TAKUYA</name> </addressbook> </inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OSHIBA, TOSHIO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SHIROMARU, OSAMU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>IDE, YUUSAKU</last-name><address><street>Toyo Ink Mfg. Co. Ltd. 3-13 Kyobashi 2-chome</street><city>Chuo-ku Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KOTANI, TAKUYA</last-name><address><street>Toyo Ink Mfg. Co. Ltd. 3-13 Kyobashi 2-chome</street><city>Chuo-ku Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OSHIBA, TOSHIO</last-name><address><street>Toyo Ink Mfg. Co. Ltd. 3-13 Kyobashi 2-chome</street><city>Chuo-ku Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SHIROMARU, OSAMU</last-name><address><street>Toyo Ink Mfg. Co. Ltd. 3-13 Kyobashi 2-chome</street><city>Chuo-ku Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Srinivasan, Ravi Chandran</last-name><address><street>J.A. KEMP &amp;amp; CO. 14 South Square Gray's Inn</street><city>LONDON WC1R 5JJ</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A process for the production of a β type copper
phthalocyanine pigment having an average primary crystal
diameter of 80 ± 40 nm and a primary crystal aspect ratio
of 2.0 ± 1.0 and having a crystallite diameter of 22 ± 5
nm in the direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200)
plane, a crystallite diameter of 27 ± 5 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (001) plane and a crystallite diameter
of 15 ± 5 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (010)
plane,

   which process comprises,

   dry-milling a crude copper phthalocyanine having
a purity of 97 to 100 % and a primary crystal diameter of
0. 5 to 100 µm at 180 to 50 °C, to prepare an α/β mixed crystal
type copper phthalocyanine having an α ratio of 5 to 35 %,
and

   treating the dry-milled product in a water-miscible
organic solvent.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a process for the
production of a β type copper phthalocyanine pigment according
to a dry-milling method.</p><heading>Prior Arts of the Invention</heading><p num="0002">Generally, a copper phthalocyanine after synthesis
is called a crude copper phthalocyanine, and it is formed of
large particles having a primary crystal diameter of 0.5 to
100 µm. For this reason, it is impossible to directly use the
above crude copper phthalocyanine as a pigment for a printing
ink. The step of decreasing the size of primary crystals of
the above crude copper phthalocyanine to about 100 ± 50 nm,
which is a size usable as a printing ink, is called pigmentation.
There are a variety of methods for the pigmentation.</p><p num="0003">Most general is a method which is called a solvent
salt milling method. In this method, a milling assistant such
as a common salt and an organic solvent, which promotes the
conversion of crystals to β type, are added to the crude copper
phthalocyanine and the mixture is milled. A β type copper
phthalocyanine pigment obtained according to the above method
has an average primary crystal diameter of 80 ± 40 nm and a
primary crystal aspect ratio of 2.0 ± 0.5, that is, the size
and shape of primary crystals are uniform. The above
characteristics in physical properties advantageously reflect
on its aptitude, so that the β type copper phthalocyanine pigment
is suitable for a printing ink in terms of fluidity and tinting
strength and is thus widely used. However, the above method 
uses a milling assistant in an amount several times as large
as that of the pigment and it uses a high boiling solvent which
is a high environmental loading substance, so that numerous
amounts of time and energy are required for the step of recovering
the milling assistant or the organic solvent. In addition, the
above method has a significant problem in that inorganic salts
as a milling assistant corrode equipment, i.e., the load on
the equipment is high.</p><p num="0004">In contrast, there is known a method in which the crude
copper phthalocyanine is dry-milled and then the dry-milled
phthalocyanine is treated with an organic solvent or the like.
Since the steps of this method are simplified when compared
with those of the above-mentioned solvent salt milling method,
this method is very effective means for providing a low-price
β type copper phthalocyanine pigment.</p><p num="0005">Crystals of a β type copper phthalocyanine converts
into α type crystals, which is thermodynamically unstable, by
means of a mechanical impact force such as that in dry-milling.
It is known that, when a β type crude copper phthalocyanine
is dry-milled at a milling temperature of 80 to 90 °C, generally,
the α ratio in the dry-milled copper phthalocyanine becomes
60 % or more (JP-A-7-310024).</p><p num="0006">On the other hand, when the milling is carried out
by a small impact force, naturally, the ratio of α type crystals
can be controlled to be small. For example, JP-A-2-294365
discloses that, when the milling is carried out at a milling
temperature of 100 °C, the content of α type crystals in the
dry-milled product is 21 %. However, the milling by such a degree
of impact force cannot achieve the size distribution of pigment
particles obtained by the solvent salt milling method.</p><p num="0007">The solvent salt milling method is characterized by
applying a powerful frictional force to a dough composed of 
a crude copper phthalocyanine of huge primary crystals, an
organic solvent and a milling assistant.</p><p num="0008">On the other hand, the method in which the dry-milled
product is treated with an organic solvent or the like is
characterized in that α type crystals are converted into β type
crystals and, simultaneously, a strong aggregation of fine
primary crystals is deflocculated to obtain an intended
dispersed particle diameter. However, it is known that primary
crystals grow into a needle form in the step of converting the
α type crystals in the dry-milled product into β type crystals
and the aspect ratio becomes large when compared with that of
the solvent salt milling method.</p><p num="0009">The method, in which the crude copper phthalocyanine
is dry-milled and then treated with an organic solvent or the
like, is advantageous in that the step of recovering the milling
assistant required in the solvent salt milling method is
unnecessary, and it is also advantageous in view of a powder
treatment amount since the dry-milling is effectively carried
out. On the other hand, the above method has a defect in that
β type crystals are converted into α type crystals at the time
of applying a mechanical force. In addition, when α type crystals
are made to convert into β type crystals by the function of
the organic solvent, pigment primary crystals grow into a needle
form and the aspect ratio becomes larger as compared with that
of the solvent salt milling method. Therefore, there arise a
problem of reddening in hue based on the orientation of dispersed
particles and a problem of a decrease in fluidity based on the
structural viscosity. Further, there is a method in which the
crude copper phthalocyanine is dry-milled in the presence of
a small amount of an organic solvent for preventing the formation
of α type crystals. However, this method has a quality problem
of difficulty in controlling the α ratio based on an 
inhomogeneous treatment and a cost problem of investment in
equipment such as an explosion-proof apparatus suitable for
the solvent treatment.</p><p num="0010">The present inventors have focused attention on that
the α ratio in the above α/β mixed crystal type copper
phthalocyanine obtainedby dry-milling exerts an influence upon
the aspect ratio of a pigment as an end product, and found that
the aspect ratio of pigment particles obtained by treatment
with an organic solvent or the like decreases with a decrease
in the α ratio in the milled product.</p><p num="0011">Further, the present inventors have found that the
deflocculation properties of the dry-milled product, which is
a strong aggregate, depend on the α ratio and that when the
α ratio is smaller than 5 %, the deflocculation properties
decrease extremely.</p><p num="0012">As the mechanical impact force or the milling time
increases, the α ratio in the dry-milled product obtained by
dry-milling increases. This phenomenon can be explained as
follows. The bonding of a copper atom, which is a β type
phthalocyanine center metal, to a nitrogen atom at a
meso-position in an adjacent phthalocyanine molecule oriented
in a longitudinal direction by the Jahn-Teller effect, is cut
by mechanical stress, so that the internal energy increases.
As a result thereof, the crystals convert into
thermodynamically-unstable α type crystals. It is thus supposed
that the crystals are again converted from α type into β type
by a function which aims at thermodynamical stabilization, such
as a function of heat or a nonacidic organic solvent, with
releasing an enthalpy of Δβ ← α = -10.8 kJ/mol, i.e., releasing
10.8kJ/mol.</p><p num="0013">In the dry-milling step, it is sufficient, for
increasing the α ratio by decreasing the re-conversion of α 
type crystals into β type crystals, to jointly use a substance
which suppresses a lattice contraction in the c axis direction
of α type crystal. Conversely, it is inferred on the basis of
crystal structure analysis, that it is sufficient for obtaining
a dry-milled product having a low α ratio to use a crude copper
phthalocyanine having a less amount of the substance which
suppresses a lattice contraction in the c axis direction.</p><p num="0014">From the above inference, it is deduced that a
dry-milled product having a low α ratio can be more easily
obtained by dry-milling a high-purity crude copper
phthalocyanine. This point has been verified by an experiment.</p><p num="0015">From the above theoretical backgrounds, so long as
the crude copper phthalocyanine is high-purity, crystals are
not easily converted into α type crystals even when a mechanical
impact force is applied. Therefore, the degree of heating during
the dry-milling can be decreased.</p><p num="0016">The dry-milling conditions for obtaining an α/β mixed
crystal type copper phthalocyanine having an α ratio of 5 to
35 % are clarified as follows. The α/β mixed crystal type copper
phthalocyanine having an α ratio of 5 to 35 % is obtained by
dry-milling a crude copper phthalocyanine having a purity of
97 to 100 % at a dry-milling temperature of 180 to 50 °C, preferably
160 to 80 °C.</p><heading>Summary of the Invention</heading><p num="0017">It is an object of the present invention to provide
a process for the production of a β type copper phthalocyanine
pigment of which the aspect ratio of primary crystals is small.</p><p num="0018">It is another object of the present invention to
provide a process for the production of a β type copper
phthalocyanine pigment which retains quality, in terms of
tinting strength, gloss and fluidity, equivalent to that of 
a pigment obtained by the solvent salt milling method and is
free from defects of the solvent-salt-milling method, i.e.,
use of a large amount of a milling assistant and use of a high
boiling solvent having a high COD value.</p><p num="0019">According to the present invention, there is provided
a process for the production of a β type copper phthalocyanine
pigment having an average primary crystal diameter of 80 ± 40
nm and a primary crystal aspect ratio of 2.0 ± 1.0 and having
a crystallite diameter of 22 ± 5 nm in the direction perpendicular
to a monoclinic β (200) plane, a crystallite diameter of 27
± 5 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (001) plane and
a crystallite diameter of 15 ± 5 nm in the direction perpendicular
to a β (010) plane,

   which process comprises the step (A) of dry-milling
a crude copper phthalocyanine having a purity, based on a
sulfuric acid dissolution method, of 97 to 100 % and a primary
crystal diameter of 0.5 to 100 µm at a temperature of 180 to
50°C, to prepare an α/β mixed crystal type copper phthalocyanine
having an α ratio of 5 to 35 % and the step (B) of treating
the dry-milled product obtained in the step (A) in a
water-miscible organic solvent.</p><p num="0020">According to the present invention, there is further
provided a process according to the above, wherein the
water-miscible organic solvent is a liquid mixed with water.</p><heading>Detailed Description of the Invention</heading><p num="0021">The present invention will be explained in detail
hereinafter. The dry-milling of the present invention
pulverizes a crude copper phthalocyanine with a milling
apparatus containing milling media, such as beads,
substantially without a liquid substance . Themilling is carried
out by utilizing a milling force or destructive force due to 
a collision between the milling media. The dry-milling apparatus
can be selected from known milling apparatuses such as a dry-type
attritor, a ball mill, a vibrating mill, etc. Further, the
dry-milling may be carried out in a deoxidation atmosphere after
the atmosphere in the dry-milling apparatus is replaced with
the deoxidation atmosphere by supplying a nitrogen gas, etc.,
as required.</p><p num="0022">The dry-milling apparatus can be selected from known
dry-type milling apparatuses heatable with steam, oil or the
like, such as a dry-type attritor, a ball mill, a vibrating
mill, etc. The milling time can be freely set depending upon
the milling apparatus used or depending upon a desired
milled-particle diameter. In a general dry-milling, the inside
of the milling apparatus heats up, so that, in most cases, the
dry-milling is carried out with cooling the temperature down
to 80 to 100 °C. In the present invention, a milled product
having an intended α ratio is obtained by adjusting the inside
temperature to 180 to 50 °C, preferably 160 to 80 °C. When the
temperature exceeds 180 °C, undesirably, an influence is exerted
upon the quality of the pigment.</p><p num="0023">As the crude copper phthalocyanine, there is used a
crude copper phthalocyanine having a purity, based on a sulfuric
acid dissolution method, of 97 to 100 %. When the above purity
is smaller than 97 %, a milled product having a high α ratio
is obtained.</p><p num="0024">In the present invention, the purity of the crude
copper phthalocyanine based on the sulfuric acid dissolution
method is measured as follows.</p><p num="0025">5 g of a sample is little by little added to 100 g
of 98 % sulfuric acid at room temperature with stirring. After
the completion of the addition, the mixture is stirred for 2
hours, and then it is poured into 500 ml of distilled water 
with stirring. The resultant mixture is stirred under heat at
90 °C and, 0.5 hour later, it is dried at 100 °C to a constant
weight. Then, it is filtered under suction with a 17G4 glass
filter, which have been weighed, and washed with water until
the filtrate becomes free from acid. Then, the washed product
remaining on the glass filter is dried at 100 °C to a constant
weight, and then weighed. The purity can be obtained by the
following expression.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Purity/% = weight after treatment × 100 / weight before<st32:break type="required"/>
treatment</st32:df></p><p num="0026">The α ratio of the milled product is 5 to 35%, preferably
10 to 30 %. A limitation is imposed upon the upper limit of
the α ratio by an increase in the aspect ratio of pigment primary
crystals. Further, a limitation is imposed upon the lower limit
by deflocculation properties of a strong aggregate.</p><p num="0027">The solvent treatment of the milled product obtained
is carried out with an organic solvent alone or a mixture of
the organic solvent with water.</p><p num="0028">The kind of the solvent is a water-miscible organic
solvent. Examples thereof include alcohol compounds such as
isopropanol, butanol, isobutanol, ethyl cellosolve, butyl
cellosolve and cyclohexanol and ketone compounds such as acetone
or methyl ethyl ketone. These solvents may be used alone or
in combination.</p><p num="0029">In the solvent treatment step, there may be used a
bead mill such as an Eiger mill, a sand mill, a ball mill, a
pearl mill ("DCP mill" supplied by EIRICH, etc.), a cosmo mill,
a Z mill, a dispermat or a basket mill.</p><p num="0030">In the solvent treatment step, there may be used a
medialess disperser such as a wet type jet mill ("GENUS PY"
supplied by Genus, "Nanomizer" supplied by Nanomizer) or a
homomixer. </p><p num="0031">In the present invention, the pigment may be treated
with a resin for giving an aptitude suitable to an application
thereof. This treatment can be carried out during the step (A)
or the step (B). The resin may be added during the dry-milling
or during the solvent treatment. The resin can be freely selected
from resins suitable for a printing ink, such as rosins typified
by polymerized rosin, hydrogenated rosin or disproportionated
rosin, or a rosin-modified phenol resin.</p><p num="0032">In the present invention, the pigment may be treated
with a surfactant for giving an aptitude suitable to an
application thereof. This treatment can be carried out during
the step (A) or during the step (B). The surfactant can be
freely selected from nonionic surfactants, anionic surfactants
and cationic surfactants so long as it is suitable for a printing
ink.</p><p num="0033">When a gravure ink, an offset ink or a coating
composition is produced from the copper phthalocyanine pigment
produced by the process of the present invention, the vehicle
therefor is not specially limited. The vehicle may contain an
adjuvant or an extender pigment.</p><p num="0034">The vehicle for the gravure ink is composed of a resin
and a solvent. Examples of the resin include gum rosin, wood
rosin, tall oil rosin, lime rosin, rosin ester, a maleic resin,
a polyamide resin, a vinyl resin, cellulose nitrate, cellulose
acetate, ethyl cellulose, chlorinated rubber, cyclized rubber,
an ethylene- vinyl acetate copolymer resin, a polyurethane resin,
a polyester resin, an alkyd resin, an acrylic resin, gilsonite,
dammar, shellac, etc., a mixture of at least two of these, and
a water-soluble res in or emulsion res in prepared by solubili zing
any one of the above resins or the mixture in water. Examples
of the solvent include a hydrocarbon, an alcohol, a ketone,
an ether alcohol, an ether, an ester and water. </p><p num="0035">The vehicle for the offset ink is composed of a resin,
a plant oil and a solvent. Examples of the resin include a
rosin-modified phenol resin, a petroleum resin, an alkyd resin
and a resin obtainedby modifying any one of these resins with
a drying oil. Examples of the plant oil include linseed oil,
tung oil and soybean oil. Examples of the solvent include
n-paraffin, I-paraffin, aromatic, naphthene, α-olefin and
water.</p><p num="0036">The vehicle for the coating composition is composed
of a resin and a solvent. Examples of the resin include an acrylic
resin, an alkyd resin, an epoxy resin, chlorinated rubber, vinyl
chloride, a synthetic resin emulsion, a silicon resin, a
polyurethane resin, a polyester resin, a melamine resin, a urea
resin, a mixture of at least two of these, or a water-soluble
resin or emulsion resin prepared by solubilizing any one of
the above resins in water. Examples of the solvent include
a hydrocarbon, an alcohol, a ketone, an ether alcohol, an ether,
an ester and water.</p><p num="0037">The gravure ink composition, the offset ink
composition or the coating composition, provided by the present
invention, can be produced by mixing or dispersing the above
copper phthalocyanine pigment or a mixture of the copper
phthalocyanine pigment with a phthalocyanine derivative
with/in the corresponding vehicle with a dispersing apparatus.
The dispersing apparatus includes a dissolver, a high-speed
mixer, a homomixer, a kneader, a flusher, a roll mill, a sand
mill and an attritor.</p><heading>Examples</heading><p num="0038">The present invention will be explained concretely
with reference to Examples and Comparative Examples hereinafter.
In the Examples, there was used, as a standard pigment, a β 
type copper phthalocyanine pigment prepared from a crude copper
phthalocyanine by a solvent salt milling method (a common salt
in five times amount). The aspect ratio of particles of the
pigment was about 2.0. The aspect ratio of primary crystal was
calculated from a photograph taken with a transmission electron
microscope.</p><p num="0039">The α ratio and the diameter of a crystallite were
obtained from an X-ray diffraction profile.</p><p num="0040">The α ratio was calculated by the following expression.
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">α ratio/% = { (integrated intensity at a diffraction<st32:break type="required"/>
angle of 14.3° - 16.0°) - (integrated intensity at a diffraction<st32:break type="required"/>
angle of 13.8°)} × 100 / {(total of integrated intensities at<st32:break type="required"/>
diffraction angles of 12.2°, 14.3° - 16.0°, and 18.0°) -<st32:break type="required"/>
(integrated intensity at a diffraction angle of 13.8°)}</st32:df></p><p num="0041">The diameter of a crystallite was calculated by the
Scherrer expression from an integral width value based on
diffraction planes of β (001), β (200) and β (010) at diffraction
angles of 7.0°, 10.5° and 18.5°.</p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0042">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 99 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 115°C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 15 % of α type crystals. 50 parts
by weight of the milled product was added to 100 parts by weight
of isobutanol and 50 parts by weight of water, and the mixture
was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour. It
was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less by the
above pre-mixing procedure. The confirmation of the α ratio
was carried out using a sample obtained by adding the slurry 
after the pre-mixing treatment to an equal amount of methanol,
filtering the resultant mixture with a filter paper No.5C
supplied by TOYO ROSHI KAISHA, LTD., further dashing 3 times
amount of isobutanol over a material remaining on the filter
paper to wash the material, and air-drying the washed material.
Then, 200 parts by weight of isobutanol and 100 parts by weight
of water were further added, and the resultant mixture was
circulatively dispersed with an Eiger mill having a mill volume
of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal beads at 50 °C for 1 hour. Then,
200 parts by weight of water was added, and the resultant mixture
was distilled and then spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The
aspect ratio of particles of the pigment was 2.3, and the α
ratio was 1 % or less. The crystallite diameter was 23 nm in
the direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it
was 26 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (001) plane
and it was 15 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (010)
plane. The pigment was compared with a standard pigment. An
ink of the pigment of the present Example had quality equivalent
to the quality of an ink of the standard pigment in terms of
tinting strength, gloss, fluidity, etc., and the hue thereof
was greenish.</p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0043">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 97 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 90 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a milled
product containing 27 % of α type crystals. 50 parts by weight
of the milled product was added to 150 parts by weight of
isobutanol, 50 parts by weight of water and 0.7 part by weight
of PELEX OT-P (anionic surfactant supplied by KAO Corporation) 
and the mixture was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C
for 1.5 hours. It was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to
1 % or less. Then, 225 parts by weight of isobutanol and 75
parts by weight of water were further added, and the resultant
mixture was circulatively dispersed with an Eiger mill having
a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal beads at 60 °C
for 1 hour. Then, 260 parts by weight of water was added, and
the resultant mixture was distilled and then spray-dried, to
obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles of the pigment
was 2.7, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The crystallite diameter
was 23 nm in the direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200)
plane, it was 25 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (001)
plane and it was 14 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β
(010) plane. The pigment was compared with a standard pigment.
An ink of the pigment of the present Example had quality
equivalent to the quality of an ink of the standard pigment
in terms of tinting strength, gloss, fluidity, etc., and the
hue thereof was greenish.</p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="0044">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 98 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 140 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 8 % of α type crystals. 50 parts by
weight of the milled product was added to 75 parts by weight
of isobutanol, 175 parts by weight of water and 0.5 part by
weight of ESTER GUMAT (rosin ester type resin supplied by Arakawa
Chemical Industries, Ltd.), and the mixture was stirred with
a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour. It was confirmed that
the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less. Then, 175 parts by weight 
of isobutanol and 75 parts by weight of water were further added,
and the resultant mixture was circulatively dispersed with an
Eiger mill having a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal
beads at 60 °C for 1.5 hours. Then, 75 parts by weight of water
was added and the resultant mixture was distilled and then
spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of particles
of the pigment was 2.1, and the α ratio was 1 % or less. The
crystallite diameter was 22 nm in the direction perpendicular
to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it was 26 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (001) plane and it was 16 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (010) plane. The pigment was compared with
a standard pigment. An ink of the pigment of the present Example
had quality equivalent to the quality of an ink of the standard
pigment in terms of tinting strength, gloss, fluidity, etc.,
and the hue thereof was greenish.</p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0045">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 99 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 115 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 15 % of α type crystals. 50 parts
by weight of the milled product was added to 75 parts by weight
of ethyl cellosolve and 75 parts by weight of water, and the
mixture was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour.
It was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less.
Then, 150 parts by weight of ethyl cellosolve and 150 parts
by weight of water were further added, and the resultant mixture
was circulatively dispersed with an Eiger mill having a mill
volume of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal beads at 50 °C for 1 hour.
Then, 70 parts by weight of water was added and the resultant 
mixture was distilled and then spray-dried, to obtain a pigment.
The aspect ratio of particles of the pigment was 2.3, and the
α ratio was 1 % or less. The crystallite diameter was 19 nm
in the direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200) plane,
it was 24 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (001) plane
and it was 18 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (010)
plane. The pigment was compared with a standard pigment. An
ink of the pigment of the present Example had quality equivalent
to the quality of an ink of the standard pigment in terms of
tinting strength, gloss, fluidity, etc., and the hue thereof
was greenish.</p><heading>Comparative Example 1</heading><p num="0046">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 93%, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled at 130 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a
milled product containing 45 % of α type crystals. 50 parts
by weight of the milled product was added to 100 parts by weight
of isobutanol and 50 parts by weight of water, and the mixture
was stirred with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 2 hours. It
was confirmed that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less. Then,
200 parts by weight of isobutanol and 100 parts by weight of
water were further added, and the resultant mixture was
circulatively dispersed with an Eiger mill having a mill volume
of 200 ml using 0.8 mm  steal beads at 50 °C for 1 hour. Then,
200 parts by weight of water was added and the resultant mixture
was distilled and then spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The
aspect ratio of particles of the pigment was 4.0, and the α
ratio was 1 % or less. The crystallite diameter was 22 nm in
the direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it 
was 26 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (001) plane
and it was 16 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (010)
plane. The pigment was compared with a standard pigment. An
ink of the pigment of the present Comparative Example was poor
in terms of tinting strength, clarity and fluidity when compared
with an ink of the standard pigment of the solvent salt milling
method.</p><heading>Comparative Example 2</heading><p num="0047">500 parts by weight of a crude copper phthalocyanine
having a purity of 98 %, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution
method, and a primary crystal diameter of 1 to 10 µm was charged
into a 5-liter dry-type attritor, and the crude copper
phthalocyanine was milled in the presence of 15 parts by weight
of xylene at 120 °C for 1 hour, to obtain a milled product
containing 3 % of α type crystals. 50 parts by weight of the
milled product was added to 75 parts by weight of isobutanol
and 175 parts by weight of water, and the mixture was stirred
with a high-speed mixer at 80 °C for 1 hour. It was confirmed
that the α ratio decreased to 1 % or less. Then, 175 parts by
weight of isobutanol and 75 parts by weight of water were further
added, and the resultant mixture was circulatively dispersed
with an Eiger mill having a mill volume of 200 ml using 0.8
mm  steal beads at 60 °C for 1.5 hours. Then, 75 parts by weight
of water was added and the resultant mixture was distilled and
then spray-dried, to obtain a pigment. The aspect ratio of
particles of the pigment was 2.0, and the α ratio was 1 % or
less. The crystallite diameter was 22 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200) plane, it was 27 nm in
the direction perpendicular to a β (001) plane and it was 16
nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (010) plane. The pigment
was compared with a standard pigment. An ink of the pigment 
of the present Comparative Example was poor in terms of tinting
strength, clarity and gloss when compared with an ink of the
standard pigment of the solvent salt milling method.</p><heading>Effect of the Invention</heading><p num="0048">The present invention can produce the β type copper
phthalocyanine pigment of which the primary crystal aspect
ratio is small. Further, the above β type copper phthalocyanine
pigment has quality, in terms of tinting strength, gloss,
fluidity, etc., equivalent to the quality of a pigment of
the generally-used solvent salt milling method, but gives
less loading to equipment and environment since salts as a
milling assistant and a high-boiling solvent having a high
COD value are not used.

Typically, in the β-type pigment prepared by the process
of the present invention, substantially all of the primary
pigment particles have the average primary crystal diameter,
primary crystal aspect ratio and crystallite diameters set
out above.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A process for the production of a β type copper
phthalocyanine pigment having an average primary crystal
diameter of 80 ± 40 nm and a primary crystal aspect ratio
of 2.0 ± 1.0 and having a crystallite diameter of 22 ± 5
nm in the direction perpendicular to a monoclinic β (200)
plane, a crystallite diameter of 27 ± 5 nm in the direction
perpendicular to a β (001) plane and a crystallite diameter
of 15 ± 5 nm in the direction perpendicular to a β (010)
plane,
   which process comprises,
<claim-text><claim-text>(A) dry-milling a crude copper phthalocyanine having
a purity, based on a sulfuric acid dissolution method, of 97
to 100 % and a primary crystal diameter of 0.5 to 100 µm at
a temperature of 180 to 50 °C, to prepare an α/β mixed crystal
type copper phthalocyanine having an α ratio of 5 to 35 %,
and</claim-text><claim-text>(B) treating the thus obtained dry-milled product
in a water-miscible organic solvent.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A process according to claim 1, wherein the
water-miscible organic solvent is a liquid mixed with water.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A process according to claim 1 or 2, wherein, in step
(B), the dry-milled product is treated with a bead mill.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>A printing ink or coating composition comprising
a β type copper phthalocyanine pigment produced by a process
according to any one of claims 1 to 3, and a vehicle.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A process for preparing a printing ink or a coating
composition, which process comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) preparing a phthalocyanine pigment by a process according
to any one of claims 1 to 3; and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) dispersing the thus obtained pigment in a vehicle.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>