<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1304368-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1304368" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="8182310" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030423"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1304368-A1" status="new" fvid="23721168"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1304368</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030423</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01308365-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01308365</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010928</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-01308365-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01308365</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010928</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 125/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 125/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 129/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 129/54        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 135/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 135/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 141/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 141/10        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 159/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 159/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 159/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 159/24        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 171/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 171/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 125/10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 129/54</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 135/10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 141/10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 159/20</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 159/22</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 159/24</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 171/00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M207:027</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M207:028</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M207:10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M207:26</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M207:262</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M215:064</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M219:044</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M219:046</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M223:045</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N210:01</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N210:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N230:04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N240:00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N240:12</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Schmierstoffzusammensetzung für Gasmotoren</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">A gas engine lubricating oil composition</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Une composition d'huile lubrifiante pour moteurs à gaz</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0354621-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0354621</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0486893-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0486893</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0779355-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0779355</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5380508-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5380508</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5739088-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5739088</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6140281-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6140281</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999035218-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999035218</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>INFINEUM INT LTD</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>INFINEUM INTERNATIONAL LIMITED</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Infineum International Limited</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 1, Milton Hill</street><city>Abingdon, Oxfordshire OX13 6BB</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CHAMBARD LAURENT</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>OWEN YOLANDA</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CHAMBARD, LAURENT</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OWEN, YOLANDA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CHAMBARD, LAURENT</last-name><address><street>27b Huntersfield, Stanford in the Vale</street><city>Oxfordshire SN7 8NQ</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OWEN, YOLANDA</last-name><address><street>3 Whitehorn Farm Cottages, Charlton Village Road</street><city>Charlton, Wantage, Oxfordshire OX12 7HW</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Lewis, Pauline Therese</last-name><address><street>Infineum UK Limited, P.O. Box 1, Milton Hill</street><city>Abingdon, Oxfordshire OX13 6BB</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A gas engine lubricating oil composition that is substantially free from dispersant.</p><p>The gas engine lubricating oil composition has a TBN in the range of 3.5 to 20.</p><p>The gas engine lubricating oil composition comprises an oil of lubricating viscosity
and at least one metal detergent.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention concerns a gas engine lubricating oil composition.</p><p num="0002">Gas engines, which are also called gas-fuelled or gas-fired engines, are used to
drive pumping stations of natural-gas pipelines, blowers and generators in, for
example, purification plants and on gas tankers. Gas engines may be two- or
four-stroke, spark-ignited or compression-ignited. Gas Otto engines ignite a
mixture of gas and air using spark plugs. Gas diesel engines use a continuous
injection of a small amount, such as, for example, 5-10%, of diesel fuel.</p><p num="0003">Gas engines operate at high temperatures such as greater than 200ºC in a piston
environment. These high temperatures cause oxidation of the gas engine
lubricating oil composition, which produces undesirable acids. These acids cause
corrosion of the gas engine, in particular, corrosion of bearings in crankshaft
journals and crankpins. Acids are also produced if the gas engine uses a fuel that
is rich in sulfur.</p><p num="0004">It is important that a gas engine lubricating oil composition does not produce
piston deposits or in the case of two-stroke engines cause plugging of exhaust
slots. The gas engine lubricating oil composition should therefore preferably have
either a low ash content such as, for example, below 0.6 wt% ash, or a medium
ash content such as, for example, between 0.6 and 1.5 wt% ash, as determined
by ASTM D874. If a lubricating oil composition has an ash level that is too low, it
will shorten the working life of valves and cylinder heads. If, on the other hand, a
lubricating oil composition has an ash level that is too high, excessive deposits will
be produced in upper combustion chambers and upper piston areas.</p><p num="0005">Gas engine lubricating oil compositions usually include a major amount of base oil
of lubricating viscosity and the following additives: up to 10 wt% of detergents, 0.5
to 8 wt% of dispersants, 0.05 to 2.0 wt% of antioxidants, 0.01 to 0.2 wt% of metal
deactivators, 0.05 to 1.5 wt% of anti-wear additives, 0.05 to 0.6 wt% of pour point 
depressants, 0.001 to 0.2 wt% of anti-foam agents and 0.1 to 3.0 wt% of viscosity
index improvers.

The present invention is concerned with the problem of providing an improved gas
engine lubricating oil composition. In particular, the present invention is
concerned with the problem of providing a gas engine lubricating oil composition
that exhibits reduced corrosion of the gas engine. The present invention is also
concerned with the problem of providing a gas engine lubricating oil composition
that exhibits reduced deposits at high temperatures.</p><p num="0006">In accordance with the present invention there is provided a gas engine lubricating
oil composition having a TBN in the range of 3.5 to 20, the gas engine lubricating
oil composition comprising:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>an oil of lubricating viscosity; and</li><li>at least one metal detergent;</li></ul>
characterised in that the gas engine lubricating oil composition is substantially free
from dispersant.</p><p num="0007">In accordance with the present invention there is also provided a method of
lubricating a gas engine, the method comprising the step of operating the gas
engine while lubricating it with a gas engine lubricating oil composition that is
substantially free from dispersant, the gas engine lubricating oil composition
comprising at least one metal detergent.</p><p num="0008">In accordance with the present invention there is also provided a gas engine
lubricating oil concentrate that is substantially free from dispersant, the
concentrate comprising at least one metal detergent.</p><p num="0009">By 'substantially free' we include the gas engine lubricating oil composition being
totally free from dispersant and the gas engine lubricating oil composition
comprising only negligible amounts of dispersant which are insufficient to provide
a dispersant effect, such amounts being, for example, less than 0.5 wt%
dispersant, preferably less than 0.1 wt% dispersant, or, in terms of nitrogen 
content, less than 0.01 wt% nitrogen, preferably less than 0.001 wt% nitrogen and
most preferably around 0.000 wt% nitrogen.</p><p num="0010">The gas engine lubricating oil composition preferably includes less than 0.5 wt%
dispersant, even more preferably less than 0.1 wt% dispersant. Most preferably,
the gas engine lubricating oil composition is completely free from dispersant.</p><p num="0011">The inventors have surprisingly found that removing dispersant from gas engine
lubricating oil compositions reduces corrosion of the gas engine (as shown, for
example, using the Ball Rust test). The inventors have also found that removing
dispersant from gas engine lubricating oil compositions reduces the build-up of
deposits (as shown, for example, using the Panel Coker Test).</p><heading><u style="single">Lubricating Oil Composition</u></heading><p num="0012">The lubricating oil composition preferably has a TBN in the range of from 4 to 20,
more preferably from 6 to 20, even more preferably 6 to 15.</p><heading><u style="single">Oil of Lubricating Viscosity</u></heading><p num="0013">The oil of lubricating viscosity (also referred to as lubricating oil) may be any oil
suitable for the lubrication of a gas engine. The lubricating oil may suitably be an
animal, a vegetable or a mineral oil. Suitably the lubricating oil is a petroleum-derived
lubricating oil, such as a naphthenic base, paraffinic base or mixed base
oil. Alternatively, the lubricating oil may be a synthetic lubricating oil. Suitable
synthetic lubricating oils include synthetic ester lubricating oils, which oils include
diesters such as di-octyl adipate, di-octyl sebacate and tridecyl adipate, or
polymeric hydrocarbon lubricating oils such as, for example, liquid polyisobutene
and poly-alpha olefins. Commonly, a mineral oil is employed. The lubricating oil
generally comprises greater than 60, typically greater than 70, wt% of the
lubricant. The lubricating oil typically has a kinematic viscosity at 100ºC of from 2
to 40, for example from 3 to 15, mm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> and a viscosity index of from 80 to 100, for
example, from 90 to 95. </p><p num="0014">Another class of lubricating oils is hydrocracked oils, where the refining process
further breaks down the middle and heavy distillate fractions in the presence of
hydrogen at high temperatures and moderate pressures. Hydrocracked oils
typically have a kinematic viscosity at 100ºC of from 2 to 40, for example from 3 to
15, mm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> and a viscosity index typically in the range of from 100 to 110, for
example from 105 to 108.</p><p num="0015">The oil may include 'brightstock' which refers to base oils that are solvent-extracted,
de-asphalted products from vacuum residuum generally having a
kinematic viscosity at 100ºC of from 28 to 36 mm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> and are typically used in a
proportion of less than 30, preferably less than 20, more preferably less than 15,
most preferably less than 10, such as less than 5, wt%, based on the weight of the
composition.</p><heading><u style="single">Metal Detergent</u></heading> <p num="0016">A detergent is an additive that reduces formation of piston deposits, for example
high-temperature varnish and lacquer deposits, in engines; it has acid-neutralising
properties and is capable of keeping finely divided solids in suspension. It is
based on metal "soaps", that is metal salts of acidic organic compounds,
sometimes referred to as surfactants.</p><p num="0017">The detergent comprises a polar head with a long hydrophobic tail. The polar
head comprises a metal salt of a surfactant. Large amounts of a metal base are
included by reacting an excess of a metal compound, such as an oxide or
hydroxide, with an acidic gas such as carbon dioxide to give an overbased
detergent which comprises neutralised detergent as the outer layer of a metal
base (e.g. carbonate) micelle.</p><p num="0018">The metal may be an alkali or alkaline earth metal such as, for example, sodium,
potassium, lithium, calcium, barium and magnesium. Calcium is preferred. </p><p num="0019">The surfactant may be a salicylate, a sulfonate, a carboxylate, a phenate, a
thiophosphate or a naphthenate. Metal salicylate is the preferred metal salt.</p><p num="0020">The detergent may be a complex/hybrid detergent prepared from a mixture of
more than one metal surfactant, such as a calcium alkyl phenate and a calcium
alkyl salicylate. Such a complex detergent is a hybrid material in which the
surfactant groups, for example phenate and salicylate, are incorporated during the
overbasing process. Examples of complex detergents are described in the art.
Surfactants for the surfactant system of the metal detergents contain at least one
hydrocarbyl group, for example, as a substituent on an aromatic ring. The term
"hydrocarbyl" as used herein means that the group concerned is primarily
composed of hydrogen and carbon atoms and is bonded to the remainder of the
molecule via a carbon atom, but does not exclude the presence of other atoms or
groups in a proportion insufficient to detract from the substantially hydrocarbon
characteristics of the group. Advantageously, hydrocarbyl groups in surfactants
for use in accordance with the invention are aliphatic groups, preferably alkyl or
alkylene groups, especially alkyl groups, which may be linear or branched. The
total number of carbon atoms in the surfactants should be at least sufficient to
impact the desired oil-solubility. Advantageously the alkyl groups include from 5 to
100, preferably from 9 to 30, more preferably 14 to 20, carbon atoms. Where
there is more than one alkyl group, the average number of carbon atoms in all of
the alkyl groups is preferably at least 9 to ensure adequate oil-solubility.</p> <p num="0021">The detergents may be non-sulfurized or sulfurized, and may be chemically
modified and/or contain additional substitutents. Suitable sulfurizing processes
are well known to those skilled in the art.</p> <p num="0022">The detergent preferably has a TBN less than 250, more preferably less than 100.</p> <p num="0023">The detergents may be used in a proportion in the range of 0.5 to 30, preferably 2
to 20, or more preferably 2 to 15, wt% based on the weight of the lubricating oil
composition. </p><heading><u style="single">Other Additives</u></heading><p num="0024">Antiwear additives may be present in the gas engine lubricating oil composition.
The antiwear additives may be metallic or non-metallic, preferably the former.</p><p num="0025">Dihydrocarbyl dithiophosphate metal salts are examples of anti-wear additives that
may be used in the present invention. The metal in the dihydrocarbyl
dithiophosphate metal salts may be an alkali or alkaline earth metal, or aluminium,
lead, tin, molybdenum, manganese, nickel or copper. Zinc salts are preferred,
preferably in the range of 0.1 to 1.5, preferably 0.5 to 1.3, wt%, based upon the
total weight of the gas engine lubricating oil composition. They may be prepared
in accordance with known techniques by firstly forming a dihydrocarbyl
dithiophosphoric acid (DDPA), usually by reaction of one or more alcohols or a
phenol with P<sub>2</sub>S<sub>5</sub> and then neutralizing the formed DDPA with a zinc compound.
For example, a dithiophosphoric acid may be made by reacting mixtures of
primary and secondary alcohols. Alternatively, multiple dithiophosphoric acids can
be prepared comprising both hydrocarbyl groups that are entirely secondary and
hydrocarbyl groups that are entirely primary. To make the zinc salt, any basic or
neutral zinc compound may be used but the oxides, hydroxides and carbonates
are most generally employed. Commercial additives frequently contain an excess
of zinc due to use of an excess of the basic zinc compound in the neutralisation
reaction.</p><p num="0026">The preferred zinc dihydrocarbyl dithiophosphates are oil-soluble salts of
dihydrocarbyl dithiophosphoric acids and may be represented by the following
formula:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">[(RO) (R<sup>1</sup>O) P(S)S]<sub>2</sub> Zn</st32:che>
where R and R<sup>1</sup> may be the same or different hydrocarbyl radicals containing from
1 to 18, preferably 2 to 12, carbon atoms and including radicals such as alkyl,
alkenyl, aryl, arylalkyl, alkaryl and cycloaliphatic radicals. Particularly preferred as
R and R<sup>1</sup> groups are alkyl groups of 2 to 8 carbon atoms. Thus, the radicals may, 
for example, be ethyl, n-propyl, I-propyl, n-butyl, I-butyl, sec-butyl, amyl, n-hexyl, I-hexyl,
n-octyl, decyl, dodecyl, octadecyl, 2-ethylehexyl, phenyl, butylphenyl,
cyclohexyl, methylcyclopentyl, propenyl, butenyl. In order to obtain oil-solubility,
the total number of carbon atoms (i.e. in R and R<sup>1</sup>) in the dithiophoshoric acid will
generally be 5 or greater. The zinc dihydrocarbyl dithiophosphate can therefore
comprise zinc dialkyl dithiophosphates.</p><p num="0027">Antioxidants may also be added to the gas engine lubricating oil composition.
These may be aminic or phenolic. Examples of aminic include secondary
aromatic amines.such as diarylamines, for example diphenylamines wherein each
phenyl group is alkyl-substituted with an alkyl group having 4 to 9 carbon atoms.
Examples of phenolics include hindered phenols, including mono-phenols and bisphenols.
The anti-oxidant may be present in an amount of up to 3 wt%.</p><p num="0028">One or more of the following additives may also be present in the gas engine
lubricating oil composition: pour point depressants such as poly(meth)acrylates or
alkyl aromatic polymers; anti-foaming agents such as silicone anti-foaming agents;
viscosity index improvers such as olefin copolymers; dyes; metal deactivators
such as aryl thiazines, triazoles or alkyl substituted dimercapto thiadiazoles; and
demulsifiers.</p><p num="0029">It may be desirable to prepare an additive package or concentrate of the gas
engine lubricating oil composition. The additive package may be added
simultaneously to the base oil to form the gas engine lubricating oil composition.
Dissolution of the additive package into the lubricating oil may be facilitated by
solvents and by mixing accompanied with mild heating. The additive package will
typically be formulated to contain the detergent in proper amounts to provide the
desired concentration, and/or to carry out the intended function in the final
formulation when the additive package is combined with a predetermined amount
of base lubricant. The additive package may contain active ingredients in an
amount, based on the additive package, of, for example, from 2.5 to 90, preferably
from 5 to 75, most preferably from 8 to 60, wt% of additives in the appropriate
proportions, the remainder being base oil. </p><p num="0030">The final formulations may typically contain about 5 to 40 wt% of the additive
package, the remainder being base oil.</p><p num="0031">The term 'active ingredient' (a.i.) as used herein refers to the additive material that
is not diluent.</p><heading><u style="single">Examples</u></heading><p num="0032">The present invention is illustrated by, but in no way limited to, the following
examples.</p><heading><u style="single">Examples</u></heading><p num="0033">Gas engine lubricating oil compositions identified in Table 1 were prepared by:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>blending the detergents at room temperature for approximately 10
minutes;</li><li>adding all of the other components; and</li><li>heating the mixture to 60ºC for 30 minutes while stirring.</li></ul><tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>Example 1</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Comparative</b><b>Example 1</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Comparative</b><b>Example 2</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Comparative</b><b>Example 3</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>64BN</b><b>Salicylate</b><b>(available from</b><b>Infineum UK Ltd)</b></entry><entry align="left">5.20</entry><entry align="left">5.20</entry><entry align="left">5.20</entry><entry align="left">5.20</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Dispersant</b><b>C 9231</b><b>(available from</b><b>Infineum UK Ltd)</b></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">3.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Dispersant</b><b>C 9265</b><b>(available from</b><b>Infineum UK Ltd)</b></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">3.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Dispersant</b><b>C 9260</b><b>(available from</b><b>Infineum UK Ltd)</b></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">2.00</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Nitrogen</b><b>Content (%w)</b></entry><entry align="left">0.00</entry><entry align="left">0.018</entry><entry align="left">0.047</entry><entry align="left">0.021 </entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>ZDDP</b><b>C 9415</b><b>(available from</b><b>Infineum UK Ltd)</b></entry><entry align="left">0.26</entry><entry align="left">0.26</entry><entry align="left">0.26</entry><entry align="left">0.26</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Aminic Anti- oxidant</b><b>C 9452</b><b>(available from</b><b>Infineum UK Ltd)</b></entry><entry align="left">1.35</entry><entry align="left">1.35</entry><entry align="left">1.35</entry><entry align="left">1.35</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Antifoam</b><b>C 9496</b><b>(available from</b><b>Infineum UK Ltd)</b></entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">0.10</entry><entry align="left">0.10</entry><entry align="left">0.10</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Base Oil</b><b>Group I</b></entry><entry align="left">Esso</entry><entry align="left">Esso</entry><entry align="left">Esso</entry><entry align="left">Esso</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">TESTS</u></heading><p num="0034">The gas engine lubricating oil compositions in Table 1 were subjected to the
following tests:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>Base Number, ASTM D 2896-98;</li><li>Ash content, ASTM D 874-00;</li><li>Ball Rust Test, ASTM D 6557-00; and</li><li>Panel Coker Test (see below).</li></ul></p><heading><u style="single">The Panel Coker Test</u></heading><p num="0035">This test involves splashing a gas engine lubricating oil composition on to a
heated test panel to see if the oil degrades and leaves any deposits that might
affect engine performance. The test uses a panel coker tester (model PK-S)
supplied by Yoshida Kagaku Kikai Co, Osaka, Japan. The test starts by heating
the gas engine lubricating oil composition to a temperature of 100ºC through an oil
bath. A test panel made of aluminium alloy, which has been cleaned using
acetone and heptane and weighed, is placed above the gas engine lubricating oil
composition and heated to 320ºC using an electric heating element. When both
temperatures have stabilised, a splasher splashes the gas engine lubricating oil
composition on to the heated test panel in a discontinuous mode: the splasher
splashes the oil for 15 seconds and then stops for 45 seconds. The discontinuous
splashing takes place over 1 hour, after which the test is stopped, everything is 
allowed to cool down, and then the aluminium test panel is weighed and rated
visually. The difference in weight of the aluminium test panel before and after the
test, expressed in mg, is the weight of deposits. The visual rating is made from 0
to 10, with 0 being for a completely black panel and 10 being for a completely
clean panel.</p><heading><u style="single">RESULTS</u></heading><p num="0036">The results of the tests are summarised in Table 2 below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="left"><b>Example</b><b>1</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Comparative</b><b>Example 1</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Comparative</b><b>Example 2</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Comparative</b><b>Example 3</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Base Number</b></entry><entry align="center">5.2</entry><entry align="center">5.2</entry><entry align="center">5.2</entry><entry align="center">5.2</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Ash Content (%)</b></entry><entry align="center">0.44</entry><entry align="center">0.44</entry><entry align="center">0.44</entry><entry align="center">0.44</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Ball Rust, Merit</b><b>P/F:100</b></entry><entry align="center">105</entry><entry align="center">81</entry><entry align="center">87</entry><entry align="center">76</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Panel Coker</b><b>(300ºC)</b><b>Plate Rating (Merit)</b></entry><entry align="center">7.1</entry><entry align="center">3.9</entry><entry align="center">5.2</entry><entry align="center">4.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left"><b>Panel</b><b>Coker</b><b>(300ºC)</b><b>Deposits

(grams)</b></entry><entry align="center">8.9</entry><entry align="center">10.9</entry><entry align="center">10.0</entry><entry align="center">12.9</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0037">As shown in the Table above, Example 1 in accordance with the invention exhibits
an unexpectedly high result in the Ball Rust test, which means that it exhibits
reduced corrosion. Example 1 also exhibits an unexpectedly low deposit and a
high Plate Rating in the Panel Coker test at high temperature. Example 1 is
therefore an improved gas engine lubricating oil composition.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A gas engine lubricating oil composition having a TBN in the range of 3.5 to
20, the gas engine lubricating oil composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>an oil of lubricating viscosity; and</claim-text><claim-text>at least one metal detergent;</claim-text></claim-text>characterised in that the gas engine lubricating oil composition is
substantially free from dispersant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the gas engine lubricating oil
composition comprises less than 0.5 wt% dispersant, more preferably less
than 0.1 wt% dispersant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The composition as claimed in claim 1, wherein the gas engine lubricating oil
is completely free from dispersant.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The composition as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein the
gas engine lubricating oil composition has a nitrogen content of less than
0.01 wt%, preferably less than 0.001 wt%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The composition as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein the
metal detergent is selected from: a metal salicylate detergent, a metal
phenate detergent, a metal sulfonate detergent, a metal carboxylate
detergent, a metal thiophosphate detergent, a complex/hybrid metal
detergent, or a mixture thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The composition as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein the
metal detergent is selected from alkali or alkaline earth metals.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The composition as claimed in claim 6, wherein the metal in the metal
detergent is selected from: calcium, barium, sodium, lithium, potassium or
magnesium.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The composition as claimed in any one of the preceding claims, wherein the
metal detergent is calcium salicylate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method of lubricating a gas engine, the method comprising the step of
operating the gas engine while lubricating it with the gas engine lubricating
oil composition claimed in any one of claims 1-8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A gas engine lubricating oil concentrate that is substantially free from
dispersant, the concentrate comprising at least one metal detergent.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>