<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1281701-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1281701" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="22717510" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20030205"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1281701-A1" status="new" fvid="23685498"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1281701</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20030205</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-02025590-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>02025590</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021115</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-19441302-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>19441302</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020712</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   5/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K   5/04        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 105/00        20060101CFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 105/38        20060101AFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 129/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 129/74        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 171/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 171/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 177/00        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 177/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  20/02        20060101ALN20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  40/30        20060101ALN20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  70/00        20060101ALN20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K   5/04B4B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 129/74</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 171/00R</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M211:022B</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N220:302</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N230:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N240:30</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Grundschmieröl aus synthetischen Estern hoher Viskosität</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">High viscosity synthetic ester lubricant base stock</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Huile de base lubrifiant à base d'esters synthétiques à viscosité élevée</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0518567-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0518567</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0653479-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0653479</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1199300-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1199300</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3670013-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3670013</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5964581-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5964581</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1996002489-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1996002489</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999010455-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999010455</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HATCO CORP</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HATCO CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HATCO CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>1020 King George post Road</street><city>Fords, New Jersey 08863</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>CARR DALE D</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MCHENRY MICHAEL A</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>STYER JEREMY P</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>CARR, DALE D.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MCHENRY, MICHAEL A</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>STYER, JEREMY P.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>CARR, DALE D.</last-name><address><street>54 Wetmore Avenue</street><city>Morristown, NJ 07960</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MCHENRY, MICHAEL A</last-name><address><street>10 Pebble Beach Way</street><city>Washington, NJ 07882</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>STYER, JEREMY P.</last-name><address><street>61-6B Winding Wood Drive</street><city>Sayreville, NJ 08872</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Maiwald Patentanwalts GmbH</last-name><address><street>Elisenhof Elisenstrasse 3</street><city>80335 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>BG</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>CZ</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>EE</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>SK</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A high viscosity synthetic ester base stock of about ISO 68 to 400 is formed
from a neopentylpolyol condensed with at least one monocarboxylic acid selected from
the group consisting of linear acids having between 4 to 10 carbon atoms and branched
chain acids having from 5 to 10 carbon atoms in an excess of hydroxyl to carboxylic acid
groups to form a partial polyneopentylpolyol ester that is further reacted with the same or
similar acid to form a high viscosity polyneopentylpolyol ester.. Lubricants formed from
the base stocks have satisfactory miscibility with standard highly or fully fluorinated
refrigeration fluids.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u> </heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to synthetic ester lubricant base stocks, and more
particularly to high molecular weight synthetic ester lubricant base stocks formed from
neopentylpolyols and monocarboxylic acids or mixtures of monocarboxylic acids suitable
for use in industrial refrigeration systems.</p><p num="0002">It is well known that chlorofluorocarbons previously utilized as propellants in
aerosols and as refrigeration fluids are no longer used due to the adverse impact on the
earth's ozone layer. Efforts to eliminate the use of chlorofluorocarbons has led to the
development of alternative fluids that are highly or fully fluorinated hydrocarbons.</p><p num="0003">Working refrigeration fluids generally include a minor amount of lubricant.
Typically, the refrigeration fluids include between about 5 to 15 or 20 parts by weight of
lubricant with the balance being the fluorocarbon. In chlorofluorocarbon systems,
lubricants have been mineral oils which are fully miscible with the chlorofluorocarbons.
However, such lubricants are not miscible with the highly or fully fluorinated
hydrocarbons such as 1,1,1,2-tetrafluoroethane, commonly known as HFC-134a. Other
chlorine-free fluorocarbons include a hydrofluorocarbon (HFC) having 1 to 3 carbon
atoms and preferably 1 to 2 carbon atoms, for example, difluoromethane (HFC-32),
trifluoromethane (HFC-23), pentafluoroethane (HFC-125), 1,1,2,2-tetrafluoroethane
(HFC-134), 1,1,1-trifluoroethane (HFC-143a), 1,1-difluoroethane (HFC-152a) or a
mixture of two or more kinds of these HFCs.</p><p num="0004">It has been found that certain carboxylic esters of polyhydroxy compounds are
fully miscible with the highly or fully fluorinated fluids. An early publication describing
such lubricants is European Patent EP 0 422 185 B1. Lubricants of the type disclosed are
low viscosity fluids of the type utilized in home window air conditioning units and
automotive air conditioning units. The lubricants are prepared by the condensation of
pentaerythritol and monocarboxylic acids containing between about 6 to 8 carbon atoms. 
This generally produces an ester having a viscosity at 40°C of between about 17.5 to
about 52.0 cSt. Such lubricants are also disclosed in U.S. Patent No. 5,964,581.</p> <p num="0005">Larger industrial refrigeration units of the type utilized in building and factory
cooling units call for refrigeration fluids including lubricants having significantly higher
viscosity in the ISO 100 to 350 range (100 to 350 centistokes at 40°C). Typically such
higher viscosity lubricants would be formed from dipentaerythritol and higher molecular
weight carboxylic acids. This would include lubricant base stocks having a viscosity
between about 68 to 400 cSt at 40°C. Alternatively, dicarboxylic acids can be utilized
along with the monocarboxylic acids to form complex esters when reacted with a polyol,
however these esters tend to be less stable than polyol esters of monocarboxylic acid
alone. Production of higher viscosity lubricants is generally not possible from a
monopentaerythritol starting material. It is preferable to use monopentaerythritol,
however, because the cost of monopentaerythritol is much lower than the cost of
dipentaerythritol.</p> <p num="0006">Accordingly, it is desirable to provide a synthetic ester lubricant base stock
having a viscosity between about ISO 68 to 400 based on condensation of
monopentaerythritol and monocarboxylic acids.</p> <heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0007">Generally speaking, in accordance with the invention, high viscosity synthetic
ester lubricant base stocks based on polyneopentylpolyol esters suitable for use with high-fluorine
containing refrigeration fluids are provided. The polyneopentylpolyol esters are
formed by reacting a neopentylpolyol having less than 10 carbon atoms with at least one
monocarboxylic acid selected from the group of linear acids having from 4 to 10 carbon
atoms, and branched chain acids having from 5 to 10 carbon atoms. The
neopentylpolyols include pentaerythritol, trimethylolpropane, trimethylolethane,
neopentyl glycol and the like. A preferred acid is a mixture of a linear acid and a 
branched acid in a mole ratio of between 5:1 to 1:5, preferably between about 1:1 to 1:3
and most preferably between 1:3 to 1:4.</p><p num="0008">The polyol and acid are first reacted in the presence of an excess of hydroxyl
groups to form a partial polyneopentylpolyol ester of desired viscosity. Then an excess of
monocarboxylic acid or acid mixture is added to the reaction mixture and the
esterification reaction is continued to yield an ester having a viscosity in the range of 68
to 400 cSt at 40°C.</p><p num="0009">Optionally, finished esters can be prepared to a higher viscosity than desired.
These can then be blended with a lower viscosity neopentylpolyol ester to achieve the
desired target viscosity. Significant economic benefits are realized by this approach to
building viscosity in the ISO range of between about 68 to 400. The base stocks are then
blended with a refrigerant lubricant additive package to form the lubricant. The additive
packages are well known in the art and include antioxidants, anti-wear agents, metal
pacifiers, friction modifiers and the like.</p><p num="0010">In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the starting polyol is
pentaerythritol and the acid is a mixture of valeric acid (C<sub>5</sub> acid) and 3,5,5-trimethylhexanoic
acid (isoC<sub>9</sub> acid). It has been found that these esters are particularly
suitable for use in synthetic refrigeration fluids as they provide good miscibility with
highly or fully fluorinated refrigeration fluids over a broad temperature range.</p><p num="0011">Accordingly, it is an object of the invention to provide a high viscosity
synthetic ester base stock having satisfactory miscibility with refrigeration fluids.</p><p num="0012">Another object of the invention is to provide an improved high viscosity
synthetic ester base stock formed from a neopentylpolyol at reduced costs.</p><p num="0013">A further object of the invention is to provide a high molecular weight
synthetic ester base stock having a high ISO grade in the range of about 68 to 400 based
on a neopentylpolyol.</p><p num="0014">Yet another object of the invention is to provide a method for preparing a high
viscosity synthetic ester base stock from a neopentylpolyol and an acid or acid mixture
consisting of monocarboxylic acids. </p><p num="0015">Yet a further object of the invention is to provide a high viscosity synthetic
ester base stock formed from monopentaerythritol and an acid mixture of valeric acid and
isoC<sub>9</sub> acid.</p><p num="0016">Still other objects and advantages of the invention will in part be obvious and
will in part be apparent from the specification. The invention accordingly comprises a
composition of matter possessing the characteristics, properties and the relation of
components which will be exemplified in the compositions hereinafter described, and the
scope of the invention will be indicated in the claims.</p><heading><u style="single">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</u></heading><p num="0017">The high viscosity synthetic ester lubricant base stocks prepared in accordance
with the invention are esters or blends of esters of certain polyneopentylpolyols. These
esters provide good miscibility with highly or fully fluorinated refrigeration working
fluids and are obtained at significant economic benefit.</p><p num="0018">In the preferred embodiments of the invention, the base stock is a blend of
esters which form the reaction product of a two step process. In the initial step a
neopentylpolyol having less than 10 carbon atoms and preferably from 5 to 8 carbon
atoms is reacted with an acid or acid mixture of linear C<sub>4</sub> - C<sub>10</sub> acid and/or branched C<sub>5</sub> -
C<sub>10</sub> acid in the presence of an excess of hydroxyl groups to carboxyl groups in the
presence of an acid catalyst to form a partial polyneopentylpolyol ester mixture. When
the anticipated water of reaction has been removed from the reaction vessel to yield a
product of desired viscosity, the resulting partial polyneopentylpolyol ester is then reacted
with an excess of an acid or acid mixture that can vary or be the same acid or acid
mixture used in the initial step to yield the high viscosity ester product.</p><p num="0019">The neopentylpolyol utilized to prepare compositions in accordance with the
invention preferably is at least one neopentylpolyol represented by the structural formula:
<img id="img-00040001" orientation="unknown" wi="33" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00040001.tif" inline="no" he="29"/> 
wherein each R is independently selected from the group consisting of CH<sub>3</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub> and
CH<sub>2</sub>OH. Examples of such a neopentylpolyol include pentaerythritol,
trimethylolpropane, trimethylolethane, neopentyl glycol and the like. In some
embodiments of this invention, the neopentylpolyol comprises only one such
neopentylpolyol. In other embodiments it comprises two or more such neopentylpolyols.
When the neopentylpolyol is pentaerythritol, the polypentaerythritol moiety of the
reaction product includes pentaerythritol, dipentaerythritol, tripentaerythritol,
tetrapentaerythritol, etc.</p><p num="0020">The acid or acid mixture includes a linear monocarboxylic acid and/or a
branched chain monocarboxylic acid. The linear acid is one having from 4 to 10 carbon
atoms and the branched acid has from 5 to 10 carbon atoms. Preferably, the acid is
valeric acid (C<sub>5</sub> acid) or a mixture of acids of valeric acid and 3, 5, 5-trimethylhexanoic
acid (isoC<sub>9</sub> acid).</p><p num="0021">When an acid mixture is used, preferably the linear acid is valeric acid present
in amounts between about 15 to 35 mole percent and the branched acid is isoC<sub>9</sub> acid
present between about 65 to 85 mole percent. In a most preferred embodiment of the
invention the valeric acid is present between about 20 to 25 mole percent and the iso-C<sub>9</sub>
acid between about 75 to 80 mole percent.</p><p num="0022">The initial stage of the reaction to form the polyneopentylpolyol esters is
conducted in the manner described by Leibfried in U.S. patent No. 3,670,013 and in
commonly assigned U.S. Patent No. 5,895,778. The descriptions of both patents are
incorporated herein by reference. Here, when pentaerythritol is the neopentylpolyol, a
reaction mixture of pentaerythritol (272 w) and valeric acid (217 v) is placed into a
reactor with extra valeric acid (38 v) in a receiver to assure a constant level of valeric acid
in the reaction mixture. The mixture is heated to a temperature of 171°C and
concentrated sulfuric acid (1.0 w) diluted with water (2 v) is added. The reaction mixture
is heated to 192°C and maintained until 50.5 v of water is removed after about 1.4 hours.
The Leibfried analysis of the product shows pentaerythritol, dipentaerythritol,
tripentaerythritol and tetrapentaerythritol moieties at weight ratios of 34:38:19:8. </p><p num="0023">The initial concentration of monocarboxylic acid material in the reaction
mixture is such as to provide an initial mole ratio of carboxyl groups to hydroxyl groups
in a range from about 1:4 to about 1:2.</p><p num="0024">In the present case, when the polyol is pentaerythritol, the polyol and
carboxylic acid or acid mixture are charged in a mole ratio of about 1:1 to 1:3 with a
preferred starting ratio of about 1:2. This mixture is reacted using an effective amount of
an acid catalyst material as described in the Leibfried patent.</p><p num="0025">The reaction is continued until the desired quantity of water is removed from
the reaction mixture. This is determined by experimentation and may be estimated by
calculating the expected amounts of water of reaction. At this point when the starting
neopentylpolyol is pentaerythritol, the mixture includes partial esters of pentaerythritol,
dipentaerythritol, tripentaerythritol, tetrapentaerythritol and the like. Optionally, the acid
catalyst may be neutralized with alkali. In order to complete the esterification of the
partial esters, an excess of an acid or acid mixture and optionally an esterification catalyst
as is well known in the art is added to the reaction mixture which is then heated, water of
reaction removed and acid returned to the reactor. Optionally, the product can be isolated
without completing the esterification of the remaining hydroxyl groups, or the
esterification can be carried out to some desired extent other than to completion.</p><p num="0026">The acid catalyst is at least one acid esterification catalyst. Examples of acid
esterification catalysts include mineral acids, preferably, sulfuric acid, hydrochloric acid,
and the like, acid salts such as, for example, sodium bisulfate, sodium bisulfite, and the
like, sulfonic acids such as, for example, benzenesulfonic acid, toluenesulfonic acid,
polystyrene sulfonic acid, methylsulfonic acid, ethylsulfonic acid, and the like. The
reaction mixture is heated to between about 150° and 250°C while withdrawing acid
vapor and water vapor to yield the polypentaerythritol partial ester product.</p><p num="0027">Prior to esterifying the partial esters, the intermediate product will include a
variety of condensation products of the neopentylpolyol. When pentaerythritol is the
neopentylpolyol, the reaction mixture will include significantly more pentaerythritol than
the 10 to 15 weight percent generally present in commercially available dipentaerythritol. 
Depending on the initial ratio of carboxyl groups to hydroxyl groups and selection of
reaction conditions, the partial ester product may include the following components in the
weight ranges specified in the following table.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="left">Pentaerythritol Moiety</entry><entry align="left">Weight Percent</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pentaerythritol</entry><entry align="left">30 to 45</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dipentaerythritol</entry><entry align="left">30 to 45</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Tri/tetrapentaerythritol</entry><entry align="left">20 to 35</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Others</entry><entry align="left">3 to 15</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0028">In the initial step of the reaction an excess of hydroxyl groups to
monocarboxylic acid groups is present to form the partial esters of the neopentylpolyol,
such as partial esters of pentaerythritol, dipentaerythritol, tripentaerythritol,
tetrapentaerythritol, etc. The excess of hydroxyl groups is necessary to promote the
polymerization of the partial esters. The molar ratio of acid or acid mixture to the polyol
can be varied depending on the desired rate of reaction, degree of condensation and the
ultimate desired viscosity of the lubricant. After formation of the partial esters, generally,
a 10 to 25 percent excess, with respect to hydroxyl groups, of an acid or acid mixture is
added to the reactor and heated. Water of reaction is collected during the reaction while
the acids are returned to the reactor. The use of vacuum will facilitate the reaction.
When the hydroxyl value is reduced to a sufficiently low level, the bulk of the excess acid
is removed by vacuum distillation. Any residual acidity is neutralized with an alkali. The
resulting polyneopentylpolyol ester is dried and filtered as described in Example 1 below.</p><p num="0029">The invention will be better understood with references to the following
examples. These examples are presented for purposes of illustration only, and are not
intended to be construed in a limiting sense.</p><p num="0030">The reactor in each preparatory example is equipped with a mechanical stirrer,
thermocouple, thermoregulator, Dean Stark trap, condenser, nitrogen sparger, and
vacuum source. The esterification may or may not be carried out in the presence of
esterification catalysts, which are well known in the art. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0031">To a reactor as described above was charged 392 grams pentaerythritol
(2.88 moles), 122 grams valeric acid (1.20 moles), 686 grams isoC<sub>9</sub> acid (4.34 moles) and
a strong acid catalyst as described in Leibfried. The expected water of esterification from
the initial charge is 5.54 moles or about 100 grams.</p><p num="0032">The mixture was heated to a temperature of about 170°C and water of reaction
was removed and collected in the trap. Vacuum was applied at temperature to obtain a
reflux thereby removing the water and returning the acid collected in the trap to the
reactor.</p><p num="0033">The temperature was maintained at 170°C with vacuum until 125 ml of water
was collected. At this point the reaction mixture consisted of partial esters of
pentaerythritol, dipentaerythritol, tripentaerythritol, tetrapentaerythritol, etc. After
cooling to about 134°C, 85 grams C<sub>5</sub> acid and 480 grams isoC<sub>9</sub> acid were added, along
with an amount of alkali sufficient to neutralize the acid catalyst.</p><p num="0034">Heat was applied to raise the temperature of the reaction mixture to 240°C,
which was maintained for about 8 hours. At this time a total of 173 ml water was
collected and the hydroxyl value was 6.4 mgKOH/g.</p><p num="0035">The reaction was then held at 240°C for about 3 additional hours. Vacuum
was applied to remove excess acid overhead. When the acid value was less than 1.0
mgKOH/g, the mixture was cooled to 80°C. Residual acidity was neutralized with alkali.
The viscosity at 40°C was 261 cSt and at 100°C was 21.0 cSt. Approximately 75 grams
of a technical pentaerythritol ester of valeric and isononanoic acids was added and the
product was dried and filtered.</p><p num="0036">A complete analysis of the product after filtering was as follows:
<sl><li>Acid value = &lt;0.01 mg KOH/g</li><li>Blue Soap = 0.0 ppm</li><li>Viscosity @ 100°C = 19.2 cSt</li><li>Viscosity @ 40°C = 223 cSt</li><li>Viscosity Index = 97 </li><li>Pour Point = -25°F (-32°C)</li><li>Flash Point = 515°F (268°C)</li><li>Moisture = 367 ppm</li><li>Density @ 60°F = 8.178 lbs./gal.</li><li>APHA Color = 300</li></sl></p><p num="0037">The resulting product showed satisfactory miscibility with R-134a refrigeration
fluid.</p><heading><u style="single">Examples 2 - 5</u></heading><p num="0038">The procedure of Example 1 was followed to prepare a high viscosity ester
base stock of ISO 220 grade from monopentaerythritol and an acid mixture of the
following amounts of valeric acid and isoC<sub>9</sub> acid.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Example</entry><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Acid Mixture (mole %)</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">% C<sub>5</sub></entry><entry align="center">% isoC<sub>9</sub></entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="right">100</entry><entry align="right">0</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="right">75</entry><entry align="right">25</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right">50</entry></row><row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="right">100</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Example 6</u></heading><p num="0039">The resulting ester base stocks of Examples 1 to 5 were mixed at 15 weight
percent with R-134a refrigeration fluid. All were fully miscible at room temperature.
The miscible ranges were as follows:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Example</entry><entry nameend="3" align="center" namest="2">Acid Mixture

(mole %)</entry><entry align="center" namest="4">Miscible Range</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">C<sub>5</sub></entry><entry align="center">isoC<sub>9</sub></entry><entry align="center">°C</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="right">100</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="right">-23 to 53</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="right">75</entry><entry align="right">25</entry><entry align="right">-3 to 53</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right">-8 to &gt;60</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="right">22</entry><entry align="right">78</entry><entry align="right">-8 to &gt;60</entry></row><row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="right">0</entry><entry align="right">100</entry><entry align="right">+3 to &gt;60</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0040">It will thus be seen that the objects set forth above, among those made apparent
from the preceding description, are efficiently attained and, since certain changes may be
made in the above compositions of matter without departing from the spirit and scope of
the invention, it is intended that all matter contained in the above description shall be
interpreted as illustrative and not in a limiting sense.</p><p num="0041">It is also to be understood that the following claims are intended to cover all of
the generic and specific features of the invention herein described and all statements of
the scope of the invention which, as a matter of language, might be said to fall
therebetween.</p><p num="0042">Particularly it is to be understood that in said claims, ingredients or compounds
recited in the singular are intended to include compatible mixtures of such ingredients
wherever the sense permits.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A high viscosity synthetic polyneopentylpolyol ester lubricant base stock,
comprising the reaction mixture formed by
   reacting a neopentylpolyol having less than 10 carbon atoms with at least
one monocarboxylic acid selected from the group consisting of linear monocarboxylic
acids having from 4 to 10 carbon atoms and branched chain acids having from 5 to 10
carbon atoms, in the presence of an excess of hydroxyl groups, and an acid catalyst to
form polyneopentylpolyol partial esters,
   neutralizing the acid catalyst; and
   reacting the partial polyneopentylpolyol esters with at least one
monocarboxylic acid selected from the group consisting of linear acids having
from 4 to 10 carbon atoms, and branched chain acids having from 5 to 10 carbon
atoms,
   the resulting polyneopentylpolyol ester having a viscosity from about 68 to
400 cSt at 40°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 1, wherein the polyneopentylpolyol partial ester is
formed in the presence of an excess of hydroxyl groups in a mole ratio of carboxyl groups
to hydroxyl groups in the reaction mixture in a range from about 0.25:1 to about 0.50:1;
and the partial polyneopentylpolyol esters are reacted with an excess of about 15 weight
percent of acid to yield with the final ester base stock.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 1, wherein the polyneopentylpolyol ester is formed
from a polyneopentylpolyol partial ester which is formed from a neopentylpolyol
represented by the following structural formula:
wherein each R is selected from the group consisting of-CH3, -C2H5, and -CH2OH.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 3, wherein the neopentylpolyol is a polyol selected
from the group consisting of pentaerythritol, trimethylolpropane, trimethylolethane,
neopentyl glycol, and mixtures thereof.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 3, wherein the neopentylpolyol is pentaerythritol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 1, wherein the linear acid reacted with the
neopentylpolyol is valeric acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 1, wherein the branched chain acid reacted with the
neopentylpolyol is a nine carbon atom acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 7, wherein the branched chain acid is 3,5,5-trimethylhexanoic
acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 1, wherein the linear acid reacted with the
polyneopentylpolyol partial ester is valeric acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 1, wherein the branched chain acid reacted with the
polyneopentylpolyol partial ester is a nine carbon atom acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 10, wherein the branched chain acid is 3,5,5-trimethylhexanoic
acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A method of preparation of high viscosity synthetic polyneopentylpolyol
ester lubricant base stocks, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>reacting a neopentylpolyol having less than 10 carbon atoms with at least
one monocarboxylic acid selected from the group consisting of linear monocarboxylic
acids having from 4 to 10 carbon atoms and branched chain acids having from 5 to 10
carbon atoms, in the presence of an excess of hydroxyl groups, and an acid catalyst to
form partial polyneopentylpolyol esters,</claim-text><claim-text>neutralizing the acid catalyst; and</claim-text><claim-text>reacting the partial polyneopentylpolyol esters with at least one
monocarboxylic acid selected from the group consisting of linear acids having from 4 to
10 carbon atoms, and branched chain acids having from 5 to 10 carbon atoms, and</claim-text><claim-text>the resulting polyneopentylpolyol ester having a viscosity from about 68 to
400 cSt at 40°C.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A method of preparation of high viscosity synthetic polyneopentylpolyol
ester lubricant base stocks, comprising
   reacting a neopentylpolyol having less than 10 carbon atoms with a
monocarboxylic acid mixture of (i) at least one linear monocarboxylic acid having from 4
to 10 carbon atoms, and (ii) at least one branched chain monocarboxylic acid having from
5 to 10 carbon atoms, in the presence of an excess of hydroxyl groups and an acid catalyst
to form polyneopentylpolyol partial esters,
   neutralizing the acid catalyst; and
   reacting the partial polyneopentylpolyol partial esters with a
monocarboxylic acid mixture of (i) at least one linear monocarboxylic acid having from 4
to 7 carbon atoms, and (ii) at least one branched chain monocarboxylic acid having from
6 to 10 carbon atoms,
   the resulting polyneopentylpolyol ester having a viscosity from about 68 to
400 cSt at 40°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A refrigeration compressor fluid comprising, a highly or fully fluorinated
refrigerant and between about 5 to 20 weight percent of a high viscosity synthetic
polyneopentylpolyol ester lubricant including a polyneopentylpolyol ester reaction mixture
formed by
   reacting a neopentylpolyol having less than 10 carbon atoms with at least
one monocarboxylic acid selected from the group consisting of linear monocarboxylic
acids having from 4 to 10 carbon atoms and branched chain acids having from 5 to 10
carbon atoms, in the presence of an excess of hydroxyl groups, and an acid catalyst to
form partial polyneopentylpolyol esters,
   neutralizing the acid catalyst; and
   reacting the partial polyneopentylpolyol esters with at least one
monocarboxylic acid selected from the group consisting of linear acids having from 4 to
10 carbon atoms, and branched chain acids having from 5 to 10 carbon atoms,
   the resulting polyneopentylpolyol ester having a viscosity from about 68 to 400
cSt at 40°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A high viscosity synthetic polyneopentylpolyol ester lubricant base stock,
comprising the reaction mixture formed by
   reacting a neopentylpolyol having less than 10 carbon atoms with (1) at
least one linear monocarboxylic acid having from 4 to 10 carbon atoms and (2) at least
one branched chain monocarboxylic acids acid having from 5 to 10 carbon atoms, in the
presence of an excess of hydroxyl groups, and an acid catalyst to form
polyneopentylpolyol partial esters,
   neutralizing the acid catalyst; and
   reacting the polyneopentylpolyol partial esters with at least one
monocarboxylic acid selected from the group consisting of linear acids having from 4 to
10 carbon atoms, and branched chain acids having from 5 to 10 carbon atoms,
   the resulting polyneopentylpolyol ester having a viscosity from about 68 to
400 cSt at 40°C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 1, wherein the acid reacted with the
neopentylpolyol is a mixture of a linear acid a branched chain acid in a mole ratio
between about 5:1 to 1:5.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 16, wherein the mole ratio is between about 1:1 to
1:4.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 16, wherein the mole ratio is between about 1:3 to
1:4.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 17, wherein the linear acid is valeric acid and the
branched acid is 3,5,5-trimethylhexanoic acid.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The base stock of claim 18, wherein the linear acid is valeric acid and the
branched acid is 3,5,5-trimethylhexanoic acid.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>