<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1233052-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1233052" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="8181718" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20020821"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1233052-A1" status="new" fvid="23547311"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1233052</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20020821</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01301407-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01301407</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010216</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="EP-01301407-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01301407</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010216</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  51/41        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  51/41        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  65/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07C  65/05        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 159/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 159/20        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10M 159/22        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  10/04        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  20/00        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  20/02        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  30/04        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C10N  40/25        20060101ALN20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C  51/41C+65/05</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C  51/41C+65/10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07C  65/05</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 159/20</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C10M 159/22</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M207:262</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10M290:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N240:102</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M10N240:103</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="IDT">M10N210:02</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="IDT">M10N230:04</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="IDT">M10N230:041</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="IDT">M10N240:10</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="IDT">M10N240:101</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="IDT">M10N240:104</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="IDT">M10N270:00</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="IDT">M10N270:02</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Überbasische Detergenz-Additive</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Overbased detergent additives</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Des additifs détergents surbasiques</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0267658-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0267658</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0657523-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0657523</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4824585-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4824585</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997046643-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997046643</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997046644-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997046644</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997046645-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997046645</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1997046646-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1997046646</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>INFINEUM INT LTD</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>INFINEUM INTERNATIONAL LIMITED</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Infineum International Limited</last-name><address><street>P.O. Box 1, Milton Hill Business &amp;amp; Technology Centre</street><city>Milton Hill, Abingdon, Oxfordshire OX13 6BB</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HAMMOND STEPHEN</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>PRICE MARK ANDREW</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SKINNER PHILIP DR</name><address><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HAMMOND, STEPHEN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>PRICE, MARK ANDREW</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SKINNER, PHILIP DR.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HAMMOND, STEPHEN</last-name><address><street>Rosemead Cottage Chester Road Kesall</street><city>Taporley Cheshire CW6 OSE</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>PRICE, MARK ANDREW</last-name><address><street>32 Blewbury Road, East Hagbourne</street><city>Didcot, Oxfordshire OX11 9LF</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SKINNER, PHILIP DR.</last-name><address><street>4 The Cleave, Harwell</street><city>Didcot Oxfordshire OX11 OEW</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Mansell, Keith Rodney</last-name><address><street>Infineum UK Ltd, Law Department, P.O. Box 1, Milton Hill</street><city>Abingdon, Oxfordshire OX13 6BB</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>AT</country><country>BE</country><country>CH</country><country>CY</country><country>DE</country><country>DK</country><country>ES</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>GR</country><country>IE</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country><country>LU</country><country>MC</country><country>NL</country><country>PT</country><country>SE</country><country>TR</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>Overbased detergent additives for lubricating oils comprise an organic
carboxylate, such as an alkylsalicylate, as a surfactant and have a TBN of 200 or
greater, an active ingredient content of 65 mass % or greater, and a kinematic
viscosity at 100°C of less than 1000 mm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">The present invention relates to overbased alkaline earth metal detergent
lubricant additives.</p><p num="0002">The use of alkaline earth metal salts of organic carboxylic acids as detergent
additives for lubricating oil compositions (or lubricants) is known in the art. When
applied in lubricating oil compositions, they ensure that the inside of engine cylinders
remains clean and that the deposition of carbonaceous products on pistons and in
piston grooves is counteracted, so that piston ring sticking is prevented. They are also
known in basic (or overbased) form. Overbasing provides an alkaline reserve which,
when applied in lubricating oil compositions, reacts with and neutralizes acidic
compounds formed during the operation of the engine in which the composition is
applied. Thus, sludge which may arise is maintained in dispersion while acids which
would enhance sludge formation are neutralized.</p><p num="0003">EP-A- 248 465 and -267 658 describe such overbased materials and processes
for making them comprising the neutralization of an organic carboxylic acid with
alkaline earth metal hydroxides or oxides in the presence of a hydrocarbon solvent
and an alcohol promoter and water to provide such overbased lubricating oil detergent
additives, including the neutralization of alkyl salicylic acids to produce overbased
calcium salts of such acids.</p><p num="0004">Such overbased additives are in the form of concentrates comprising colloidal
particles of basic material stabilised in a liquid medium (or diluent or base oil) by ions
of the acidic material, sometimes referred to as surfactant or soap. Desirable
properties of such an additive include a high total base number (TBN), good
handleability to enable it to be readily admixed to make a final lubricant, and a high
active ingredient content to maximise the efficiency of the additive. Unfortunately,
these desirable properties may conflict with one another: a high active ingredient
content may generate handleability problems by causing the viscosity to become
unacceptably high. EP-A-0 267 658, for example, describes overbased additives, 
wherein the surfactant is a salicylate, which, although having good basic and
handleability properties, have active ingredient contents that do not exceed 60 mass
%. Overbased detergents, wherein the surfactant is an organic carboxylate, having a
high TBN and a handleable viscosity, that also have a high active matter content, have
now surprisingly been provided.

Thus, a first aspect of the present invention is an overbased alkaline earth metal, such
as Ca or Mg, detergent lubricant additive comprising, as a surfactant for the additive,

   a major proportion of an organic carboxylate, the additive having
<sl><li>(a) a TBN of 200 or greater, or 250 or greater, or 300 or greater such as 300
to 500, for example 300 to 400;</li><li>(b) an active ingredient content of 65 mass % or greater, such as up to 95, 90,
85 or 80, mass %, active ingredient being all matter other than base oil;
and</li><li>(c) a kinematic viscosity at 100°C of less than 1000, such as from 50 to less
than 1000, for example from 100 to 500, mm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup>.</li></sl></p><p num="0005">A second aspect of the invention is a lubricating oil composition comprising an
admixture of an oil of lubricating viscosity, in a major amount, and an additive
according to the first aspect of the invention, in a minor amount.</p><p num="0006">A third aspect of the invention is a method of lubricating a marine diesel engine,
such as a trunk piston engine, comprising supplying to the engine a lubricating oil
composition according to the second aspect of the invention.</p><p num="0007">A fourth aspect of the invention is a combination comprising
<sl><li>(a) mechanical parts to be lubricated of a marine diesel engine, such as a trunk
piston engine; and</li><li>(b) a lubricating oil composition according to the second aspect of the
invention.</li></sl></p><p num="0008">In this specification: <sl><li>"Major amount" means in excess of 50 mass % of the composition.</li><li>"Minor amount" means less than 50 mass % of the composition, both in
respect of the stated additive and in respect of the total mass % of all of the additives
present in the composition, reckoned as active ingredient of the additive or additives.</li><li>"Comprises or comprising" or cognate words are taken to specify the presence
of stated features, steps, integers, or components, but does not preclude the presence
or addition of one or more other features, steps, integers, components or groups
thereof.</li><li>"TBN" is Total Base Number as measured by ASTM D2896.</li><li>"Oil-soluble" or "oil-dispersible" do not necessarily indicate that the
additive(s) are soluble, dissolvable, miscible or capable of being suspended in oil, in
all proportions. They do mean, however, that they are, for example, soluble or stably
dispersible in oil to an extent sufficient to exert their intended effect in the
environment in which the oil is employed. Moreover, the additional incorporation of
other additives may also permit incorporation of higher levels of a particular additive,
if desired.</li></sl></p><p num="0009">It should be noted that the lubricating oil compositions of this invention
comprise defined individual, i.e. separate, components that may or may not remain the
same chemically before and after mixing.</p> <p num="0010">The features of the invention will now be discussed in further detail as
follows:-</p><heading><u style="single">OVERBASED DETERGENT</u></heading><p num="0011">In the detergents of the first aspect of the invention, suitable organic
carboxylate detergents are those derived from acids containing a benzene or
naphthalene ring and an oil-solubilising group or group having a total of at least 8, in
particular at least 12, carbon atoms. Preferred are hydrocarbyl-, particularly
alkylsalicylic acids having at least 10 carbon atoms in the alkyl group or groups, in
particular 12 to 26, such as 14 to 18 carbon atoms. Preferably, a salicylate constitutes
the sole surfactant for the additive. </p><p num="0012">"Hydrocarbyl" means a group composed primarily of carbon and hydrogen
atoms, connected via a carbon atom, and that may contain other atom(s) provided they
do not substantially alter the hydrocarbon nature of the group.</p> <p num="0013">Other suitable acids that may be used include substituted or unsubstituted
aliphatic or cycloaliphatic acids. As examples, there may be mentioned naphthenic
acids; and aliphatic acids having more than 8 carbon atoms such as stearic, isostearic,
palmitic, myristic, oleic and hydroxystearic acids, and tertiary carboxylic acids.</p> <p num="0014">The detergents may, for example, be prepared by a batch process comprising
the following steps:
<sl><li>(a) neutralising an organic acid, such as an oil-soluble alkylsalicylic acid, with
excess calcium hydroxide in the presence of an organic diluent oil, a liquid
monohydric alcohol and water:</li> <li>(b) in a first carbonation step, carbonating the mixture with carbon dioxide;</li><li>(c) raising and then lowering the temperature of the mixture;</li><li>(d) providing more calcium hydroxide and, in a second carbonation step,
carbonating the mixture with carbon dioxide;</li><li>(e) raising the temperature of the mixture and providing more diluent oil; and</li><li>(f) removing solvents and water and, optionally filtering.</li></sl>
Alternatively, the detergents may be prepared, in some embodiments, by a process
analogous to the above, but involving a single carbonation step.</p><p num="0015">The overbased detergents are useful as additives for oil-based compositions,
for example, lubricants or greases. The amount of overbased detergent to be included
in the oil-based composition depends on the type of composition and its proposed
application: lubricants for marine applications typically contain 0.5 to 18 mass % of
overbased detergent, on an active ingredient basis based on the final lubricant, while
automotive crankcase lubricating oils typically contain 0.01 to 6 mass % of overbased
detergent, on an active ingredient basis based on the final lubricant. </p><heading><u style="single">LUBRICATING OIL COMPOSITIONS</u></heading><p num="0016">To provide the second aspect of the invention, the overbased detergents may
be incorporated into an oil of lubricating viscosity (or base stock) in any convenient
way. Thus, they may be added directly to the oil by dispersing or dissolving them in
the oil at the desired concentration optimally with the aid of a suitable solvent such as
toluene or cyclohexane, and at ambient or elevated temperature.</p><p num="0017">Because the detergents of the invention possess both high TBN and high
active matter content, it is possible to blend lubricating oil compositions that have
both relatively high TBN and high organic carboxylate surfactant concentrations, at
lower detergent treat rates than hitherto.</p><p num="0018">A particular problem associated with marine engine lubrication occurs when
the engine is a trunk piston marine diesel engine (ie a medium-speed, four-stroke
engine. Their manufacturers commonly design them to use a variety of diesel fuels,
ranging from good quality high distillate fuel with low sulfur and low asphaltene
content to poorer quality intermediate of heavy fuel such as "Bunker C" or residual
fuel oil with generally higher sulfur and asphaltene content. Lubricants used in such
engines often become contaminated with asphaltene components from the fuel,
leading to cleanliness problems in service, sometimes referred to as "black paint".</p><p num="0019">The lubricating oil compositions of this invention have been found to be
particularly efficacious in mitigating the "black paint" problem.</p><p num="0020">The base stock for the composition may be synthetic or natural.</p><p num="0021">Synthetic base stocks include alkyl esters of dicarboxylic acids, polyglycols
and alcohols; poly-α-olefins, including polybutenes; alkyl benzenes; organic esters of
phosphoric acids; and polysilicone oils. </p><p num="0022">Natural base stocks include mineral lubricating oils which may vary widely as
to their crude source, for example, as to whether they are paraffinic, naphthenic,
mixed, or paraffinic-naphthenic, as well as to the method used in their production, for
example, their distillation range and whether they are straight run or cracked,
hydrofined, or solvent extracted.</p><p num="0023">Lubricating oil base stocks suitable for use in crankcase lubricants
conveniently have a viscosity of 2.5 to 12 mm<sup>2</sup>/s, at 100°C, although base stocks with
other viscosities may be used, for example, bright stock.</p><p num="0024">Lubricating oil base stocks suitable for use in marine lubricants conveniently
have a viscosity of typically 3 to 15 mm<sup>2</sup>/s, at 100°C, although base stocks with other
viscosities may also be used. Thus, for example, bright stocks, which typically have a
viscosity of 30 to 35 mm<sup>2</sup>/s, at 100°C may be used.</p><p num="0025">Additional additives may be incorporated in the composition to enable it to
meet particular requirements. Examples of additional additives which may be
included in lubricating oil compositions containing an overbased detergent in
accordance with the invention are viscosity index improvers, corrosion inhibitors,
oxidation inhibitors or antioxidants, friction modifiers, dispersants, other detergents,
metal rust inhibitors, anti-wear agents, pour point depressants, and anti-foaming
agents. Lubricating oils suitable for use in marine engines advantageously include a
dispersant and an antiwear agent as additional additives and may also contain other
additives, for example, additional antioxidants, antifoaming agents and/or rust
inhibitors. Certain of the additional additives specified below are more appropriate
for use in lubricants for automobile engines than for use in lubricants for marine
engines.</p><p num="0026">Viscosity index improvers (or viscosity modifiers) impart high and low
temperature operability to a lubricating oil and permit it to remain shear stable at
elevated temperatures and also exhibit acceptable viscosity or fluidity at low
temperatures. Suitable compounds for use as viscosity modifiers are generally high 
molecular weight hydrocarbon polymers, including polyesters, and viscosity index
improver dispersants, which function as dispersants as well as viscosity index
improvers. Oil-soluble viscosity modifying polymers generally have weight average
molecular weights of from about 10,000 to 1,000,000, preferably 20,000 to 500,000,
as determined by gel permeation chromatography or light scattering methods.</p><p num="0027">Corrosion inhibitors reduce the degradation of metallic parts contacted by the
lubricating oil composition. Thiadiazoles, for example those disclosed in US-A-2 719
125, 2 719 126 and 3 087 932, are examples of corrosion inhibitors for lubricating
oils.</p><p num="0028">Oxidation inhibitors, or antioxidants, reduce the tendency of mineral oils to
deteriorate in service, evidence of such deterioration being, for example, the
production of varnish-like deposits on metal surfaces and of sludge, and viscosity
increase. Suitable oxidation inhibitors include sulphurized alkyl phenols and alkali or
alkaline earth metal salts thereof; diphenylamines; phenyl-naphthylamines; and
phosphosulphurized or sulphurized hydrocarbons.</p><p num="0029">Other oxidation inhibitors or antioxidants which may be used in lubricating oil
compositions comprise oil-soluble copper compounds. The copper may be blended
into the oil as any suitable oil-soluble copper compound. By oil-soluble it is meant
that the compound is oil-soluble under normal blending conditions in the oil or
additive package. The copper may, for example, be in the form of a copper
dihydrocarbyl thio- or dithio-phosphate. Alternatively, the copper may be added as
the copper salt of a synthetic or natural carboxylic acid, for example, a C<sub>8</sub> to C<sub>18</sub>
fatty acid, an unsaturated acid, or a branched carboxylic acid. Also useful are oil-soluble
copper dithiocarbamates, sulphonates, phenates, and acetylacetonates.
Examples of particularly useful copper compounds are basic, neutral or acidic copper
Cu<sup>I</sup> and/or Cu<sup>II</sup> salts derived from alkenyl succinic acids or anhydrides.</p><p num="0030">Copper antioxidants will generally be employed in an amount of from about 5
to 500 ppm by weight of the copper, in the final lubricating composition. </p><p num="0031">Friction modifiers and fuel economy agents which are compatible with the
other ingredients of the final oil may also be included. Examples of such materials
are glyceryl monoesters of higher fatty acids, esters of long chain polycarboxylic
acids with diols, oxazoline compounds, and oil-soluble molybdenum compounds.</p><p num="0032">Dispersants maintain oil-insoluble substances, resulting from oxidation during
use, in suspension in the fluid, thus preventing sludge flocculation and precipitation or
deposition on metal parts. So-called ashless dispersants are organic materials which
form substantially no ash on combustion, in contrast to metal-containing (and thus
ash-forming) detergents. Borated metal-free dispersants are also regarded herein as
ashless dispersants. Suitable dispersants include, for example, derivatives of long
chain hydrocarbon-substituted carboxylic acids in which the hydrocarbon groups
contain 50 to 400 carbon atoms, examples of such derivatives being derivatives of
high molecular weight hydrocarbyl-substituted succinic acid. Such hydrocarbyl-substituted
carboxylic acids may be reacted with, for example, a nitrogen-containing
compound, advantageously a polyalkylene polyamine, or with an ester. Particularly
preferred dispersants are the reaction products of polyalkylene amines with alkenyl
succinic anhydrides.</p><p num="0033">A viscosity index improver dispersant functions both as a viscosity index
improver and as a dispersant. Examples of viscosity index improver dispersants
suitable for use in lubricating compositions include reaction products of amines, for
example polyamines, with a hydrocarbyl-substituted mono- or dicarboxylic acid in
which the hydrocarbyl substituent comprises a chain of sufficient length to impart
viscosity index improving properties to the compounds.</p><p num="0034">Examples of dispersants and viscosity index improver dispersants may be
found in EP-A-24146.</p><p num="0035">Additional detergents and metal rust inhibitors include the metal salts, which
may be overbased, of sulphonic acids, alkyl phenols, sulphurized alkyl phenols, alkyl
salicylic acids, thiophosphonic acids, naphthenic acids, and other oil-soluble mono-and 
dicarboxylic acids. Representative examples of detergents/rust inhibitors, and
their methods of preparation, are given in EP-A-208 560.</p><p num="0036">Antiwear agents, as their name implies, reduce wear of metal parts. Zinc
dihydrocarbyl dithiophosphates (ZDDPs) are very widely used as antiwear agents.
Especially preferred ZDDPs for use in oil-based compositions are those of the
formula Zn[SP(S)(OR<sup>1</sup>)(OR<sup>2</sup>)]<sub>2</sub> wherein R<sup>1</sup> and R<sup>2</sup> contain from 1 to 18, and
preferably 2 to 12, carbon atoms.</p><p num="0037">Pour point depressants, otherwise known as lube oil flow improvers, lower the
minimum temperature at which the fluid will flow or can be poured. Such additives
are well known. Foam control may be provided by an antifoamant of the
polysiloxane type, for example, silicone oil or polydimethyl siloxane.</p><p num="0038">Some of the above-mentioned additives may provide a multiplicity of effects;
thus for example, a single additive may act as a dispersant-oxidation inhibitor. This
approach is well known and need not be further elaborated herein.</p><p num="0039">When lubricating compositions contain one or more of the above-mentioned
additives, each additive is typically blended into the base oil in an amount which
enables the additive to provide its desired function. Representative effective amounts
of such additives, when used in crankcase lubricants, are as follows: <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Additive</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Mass % a.i.<!--footnotes removed--> (Broad)</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Mass % a.i.<!--footnotes removed--> (Preferred)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Viscosity Modifier</entry><entry align="left">0.01-6</entry><entry align="left">0.01-4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Corrosion Inhibitor</entry><entry align="left">0.01-5</entry><entry align="left">0.01-1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oxidation Inhibitor</entry><entry align="left">0.01-5</entry><entry align="left">0.01-1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Friction Modifier</entry><entry align="left">0.01-5</entry><entry align="left">0.01-1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dispersant</entry><entry align="left">0.1-20</entry><entry align="left">0.1-8</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Detergents/rust inhibitors</entry><entry align="left">0.01-6</entry><entry align="left">0.01-3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Anti-wear Agent</entry><entry align="left">0.01-6</entry><entry align="left">0.01-4</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pour Point Depressant</entry><entry align="left">0.01-5</entry><entry align="left">0.01-1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Anti-Foaming Agent</entry><entry align="left">0.001-3</entry><entry align="left">0.001-0.15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mineral or Synthetic Base Oil</entry><entry align="left">Balance</entry><entry align="left">Balance<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0040">Typical proportions for additives for a TPEO (a trunk piston engine oil) are as
follows:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Additive</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Mass % a.i.<!--footnotes removed--> (Broad)</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Mass % a.i.<!--footnotes removed--> (Preferred)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Detergent(s)</entry><entry align="left">0.5-15</entry><entry align="left">2-12</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dispersant(s)</entry><entry align="left">0.5-5</entry><entry align="left">1-3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Anti-wear agent(s)</entry><entry align="left">0.1-1.5</entry><entry align="left">0.5-1.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Oxidation inhibitor</entry><entry align="left">0.2-2</entry><entry align="left">0.5-1.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Rust inhibitor</entry><entry align="left">0.03-0.15</entry><entry align="left">0.05-0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pour point depressant</entry><entry align="left">0.03-0.15</entry><entry align="left">0.05-0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mineral or synthetic base oil</entry><entry align="left">Balance</entry><entry align="left">Balance<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0041">Typical proportions for additives for a MDCL (a marine diesel cylinder
lubricant) are as follows: <tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="left"><b>Additive</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Mass % a.i.<!--footnotes removed--> (Broad)</b></entry><entry align="left"><b>Mass % a.i.<!--footnotes removed--> (Preferred)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Detergent(s)</entry><entry align="left">1-18</entry><entry align="left">3-15</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dispersant(s)</entry><entry align="left">0.5-5</entry><entry align="left">1-3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Anti-wear agent(s)</entry><entry align="left">0.1-1.5</entry><entry align="left">0.5-1.3</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Pour point depressant</entry><entry align="left">0.03-0.15</entry><entry align="left">0.05-0.1</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Mineral or synthetic base oil</entry><entry align="left">Balance</entry><entry align="left">Balance<!--footnotes removed--></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0042">When a plurality of additives are employed it may be desirable, although not
essential, to prepare one or more additive packages comprising the additives, whereby
several additives can be added simultaneously to the base oil to form the lubricating
oil composition. Dissolution of the additive package(s) into the lubricating oil may be
facilitated by solvents and by mixing accompanied with mild heating, but this is not
essential. The additive package(s) will typically be formulated to contain the
additive(s) in proper amounts to provide the desired concentration in the final
formulation when the additive package(s) is/are combined with a predetermined
amount of base lubricant. Thus, one or more overbased detergents in accordance with
the present invention may be added to small amounts of base oil or other compatible
solvents together with other desirable additives to form additive packages containing
active ingredients in an amount, based on the additive package, of, for example, from
about 2.5 to about 90 mass %, and preferably from about 5 to about 75 mass %, and
most preferably from about 8 to about 60 mass % by weight, additives in the
appropriate proportions with the remainder being base oil.</p><p num="0043">The final formulations may typically contain about 5 to 40 mass % of the
additive package(s) with the remainder being base oil.</p><heading><u style="single">EXAMPLES</u></heading><p num="0044">The following Examples illustrate, but in no way limit, the invention. </p><heading><u style="single">Example 1 Preparation of Overbased Calcium Salicylate Detergent Additive</u></heading><p num="0045">Toluene (453g), methanol (296g), water (27g), and diluent oil (19g; SN150)
were introduced into a reactor and mixed while maintaining the temperature at
approximately 20°C. Calcium hydroxide (Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>) (142g) was added, and the
mixture was heated to 40°C, with stirring. To the slurry obtained in this way was
added alkylsalicylic acid (495g) and toluene (100g) followed by a further quantity
(20g) of toluene.</p><p num="0046">After neutralization of the alkylsalicylic acid by the calcium hydroxide, the
temperature of the mixture was reduced to approximately 28°C, and was maintained at
approximately 28°C while carbon dioxide (50g) was injected into the mixture over a
period of 90 to 120 minutes. The temperature was then raised to 60°C over 60
minutes, following which the mixture was cooled to a temperature of approximately
28°C over 30 minutes. At 28°C, a further quantity of calcium hydroxide (98g) was
added and then the temperature was maintained at approximately 28°C while carbon
dioxide (50g) was again injected into the mixture over a period of 90 to 120 minutes.
After this second carbonation step, the temperature was raised to 60°C over 90
minutes. During this heat treatment period, when the temperature reached 45°C, a
further charge of diluent oil (167g) was added.</p><p num="0047">To complete the synthesis, the produce was heated from 60 to 160°C in about
six hours to remove the solvents and water. This solvent stripping process was
performed in three stages:
<sl><li>1. under atmospheric pressure to 114°C, at which point a final charge of diluent
oil (50g) was added.</li><li>2. under a pressure of 500mbar between 114°C and 125°C</li><li>3. under a pressure of 250mbar between 125°C and 160°C.</li></sl>
   Finally, the product was filtered to remove sediment.</p><p num="0048">Characteristics of the overbased calcium salicylate detergent additive made by
this process were as follows:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>TBN = 364mgKOH/g (measured by ASTM D2896) </li><li>Kv100 = 217 mm<sup>2</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> (measured by ASTM D445)</li><li>Active ingredient content = 76 mass % (calculated as, [mass of final
product - mass of base oil]/[mass of final product])</li></ul></p><heading><u style="single">Example 2 Single Carbonation</u></heading><p num="0049">453g toluene, 296g methanol, 27g water, and 19g of diluent oil (SN150) were
introduced into a reactor and mixed while maintaining the temperature at
approximately 20°C. Calcium hydroxide (Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>) (206g) was added, and the
mixture was heated to 40°C, with stirring. To the slurry obtained in this way was
added 588g of alkylsalicylic acid and 100g of toluene followed by a further quantity
(20g) of toluene.</p><p num="0050">After neutralization of the alkylsalicylic acid by the calcium hydroxide, the
temperature of the mixture was reduced to approximately 28°C, and was maintained
at approximately 28°C while carbon dioxide (81g) was injected into the mixture over
a period of 210 minutes. The temperature was then raised to 60°C over 90 minutes.
During this heat treatment period, when the temperature reached 45°C, a further
charge of diluent oil (84g) was added.</p><p num="0051">To complete the synthesis, the product was heated from 60 to 160°C in about six
hours to remove the solvents and water. This solvent stripping process was performed
in three stages:
<sl><li>1. under atmospheric pressure to 114°C, at which point a final charge of diluent oil
(84g) was added</li><li>2. under a pressure of 500mbar between 114°C and 125°C</li><li>3. under a pressure of 250mbar between 125°C and 160°C.</li></sl></p><p num="0052">Finally, the product was filtered to remove sediment.</p><p num="0053">Characteristics of the overbased detergent made by this process are as follows:
<ul list-style="bullet"><li>TBN = 309mgKOH/g (measured by ASTM D2896)</li><li>Kv100 = 299cSt (measured by ASTM D445) </li><li>Active ingredient content = 81% (calculated as, [mass of final product - mass of
base oil] / [mass of final product] )</li></ul></p><heading><u style="single">Example 3 Preparation of Lubricating Oil Composition</u></heading><p num="0054">An overbased calcium salicylate detergent such as prepared in Example 1 was
blended with an oil of lubricating viscosity at a treat rate of only 8.3% to give a
composition of 30 TBN and a salicylate (surfactant) content of 43 mmol/kg.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An overbased alkaline earth metal, such as Ca or Mg, detergent lubricant
additive comprising, as a surfactant for the additive, a major proportion of an
organic carboxylate, the additive having
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) a TBN of 200 or greater, or 250 or greater, or 300 or greater such as 300 to 500,
for example 300 to 400;</claim-text><claim-text>(b) an active ingredient content of 65 mass % or greater, such as up to 95, 90, 85
or 80, mass %, active ingredient being all matter other than base oil; and</claim-text><claim-text>(c) a kinematic viscosity at 100°C of less than 1000, such as from 50 to less than
1000, for example from 100 to 500, mm2s-1.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>An additive as claimed in claim 1 wherein the organic carboxylate is a
salicylate.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>An additive as claimed in claim 2 wherein the salicylate is an alkylsalicylate in
which the alkyl group has, for example, at least 10 such as from 14 to 18 carbon
atoms.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>An additive as claimed in claim 2 or claim 3 wherein the salicylate constitutes
the sole surfactant for the additive.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>A lubricating oil composition comprising an admixture of an oil of lubricating
viscosity, in a major amount, and an additive as claimed in any of claims 1 to 4,
in a minor amount.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A composition as claimed in claim 5 in the form of a marine lubricant such as a
trunk piston marine engine oil or a marine cylinder oil.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>A method of lubricating a marine diesel engine comprising supplying to the
engine a lubricating oil composition as claimed in claim 6.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A combination comprising
<claim-text><claim-text>(a) mechanical parts to be lubricated of a marine diesel engine; and</claim-text><claim-text>(b) a lubricating oil composition as claimed in claim 6</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>