<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1413610-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1413610" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="31993332" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040428"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1413610-A1" status="new" fvid="24027092"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1413610</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040428</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03255717-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03255717</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030912</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-25431502-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>25431502</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20020924</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C20</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C8</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Nichtionische Zusätze zur Kontrolle der Pfützenbildung von Tintenstrahldruckertinten</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Nonionic additives to control puddling in inkjet inks</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Additifs non ioniques pour controler la formation de flaques de l'encre pour jet d'encre</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="DE-19848843-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>DE</country><doc-number>19848843</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0602551-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0602551</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1236778-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1236778</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="JP-2000038533-A" status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000038533</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4166044-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4166044</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5837044-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5837044</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5837046-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5837046</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5891232-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5891232</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-5935309-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>5935309</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN vol. 2000, no. 05, 14 September 2000 (2000-09-14) -&amp; JP 2000 038533 A (FUJI SHIKISO KK), 8 February 2000 (2000-02-08)</text><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HEWLETT PACKARD DEVELOPMENT CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HEWLETT-PACKARD DEVELOPMENT COMPANY, L.P.</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Hewlett-Packard Development Company, L.P.</last-name><address><street>20555 S.H. 249</street><city>Houston, Texas 77070</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MOFFATT JOHN R</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>UHLIR-TSANG LINDA C</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MOFFATT, JOHN R.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>UHLIR-TSANG, LINDA C.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MOFFATT, JOHN R.</last-name><address><street>2675 NE Lancaster No. 123</street><city>Corvallis, OR 97330</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>UHLIR-TSANG, LINDA C.</last-name><address><street>515 NW Elizabeth Drive</street><city>Corvallis, OR 97330</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Jackson, Richard Eric</last-name><address><street>Carpmaels &amp;amp; Ransford, 43-45 Bloomsbury Square</street><city>London WC1A 2RA</city><country>GB</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A puddling additive comprising a nonionic, polar group and a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon 
tail for use in reducing puddling in an inkjet ink. The nonionic, polar group is an alcohol, 
alkene, or zwitterionic group and the C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail is a saturated or unsaturated 
C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon chain. The inkjet ink also comprises a dye and an ink vehicle. A 
method of reducing puddling in an inkjet ink is also disclosed. The method comprises 
adding a puddling additive to the inkjet ink, wherein the puddling additive comprises a 
nonionic, polar group and a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail. </p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0001">Field of the Invention: The present invention relates to an additive used to 
control puddling in inkjet inks. More specifically, the invention relates to a 
puddling additive having a nonionic, polar group and a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail. </p><p num="0002">State of the Art: Inkjet printing is a popular alternative for home and office 
printing due to the low cost of inkjet printers, advances in quality of the printed 
images, and the relatively noise-free operation. Notwithstanding these 
advantages, research and development continue in order to improve inkjet print 
quality while maintaining a reasonable cost for the inkjet printer and the printing 
process. </p><p num="0003">A conventional color inkjet printer comprises a plurality of resistor 
elements arranged in a particular pattern in a printhead. The resistor elements 
are located in a chamber that is provided with an opening for inkjet ink to enter 
from a reservoir. Together, the printhead and the reservoir comprise an inkjet 
pen. The printhead also includes an orifice plate having a plurality of orifices 
through which inkjet ink is expelled toward a print medium. Each resistor 
element is connected by a conductive trace to a microprocessor, where current-carrying 
signals cause one or more selected resistor elements to heat up. The 
heat creates a bubble of vapor ink in the chamber, which is expelled through 
the orifices toward the print medium. The properly sequenced ejection of inkjet 
ink from each orifice causes characters or other images to be printed on the  
 
print medium as the printhead is moved across the print medium. The inkjet 
printers produce high quality printing and are both compact and affordable. In 
addition, since only the ink strikes the paper, the inkjet printer is fast and quiet. </p><p num="0004">To print color images, inkjet printing uses a combination of cyan, 
magenta, yellow, and, optionally, black inkjet inks to produce all the colors of a 
color spectrum. The cyan, magenta, yellow, and, optionally, black inkjet inks 
are referred to collectively as a "set" of inkjet inks. A color inkjet printer typically 
has four inkjet pens, one pen for each of the inkjet inks. Color inkjet inks are 
typically aqueous-based and are formulated by dissolving or dispersing a 
colorant, such as a dye or pigment, in an aqueous ink vehicle. For example, a 
yellow inkjet ink uses a yellow dye or pigment dissolved or dispersed in the ink 
vehicle, while a blue inkjet ink uses a cyan dye or pigment dissolved or 
dispersed in the ink vehicle. If the colorant is a dye, the dye is typically present 
in a salt form. The ink vehicle comprises additional components depending on 
the application and desired properties of the color inkjet ink, as known in the art. </p><p num="0005">To produce high quality images, the inkjet ink must be compatible with 
the inkjet pen and the print medium. The properties of an optimal inkjet ink 
include, among others, good crusting resistance, good stability, low color-to-color 
bleed, and rapid dry time. In addition, the inkjet ink must be capable of 
passing through the inkjet orifice without clogging the orifice or puddling on the 
orifice plate. The inkjet ink should also permit rapid cleanup of the machine 
components with minimal effort. Although inkjet inks are known to possess one 
or more of the foregoing properties, few inkjet inks possess all of these 
properties because an improvement in one property often negatively impacts 
another property. </p><p num="0006">While the overall print quality of currently produced inkjet inks is generally 
high, puddling of these inks still occurs on the orifice plate of the printhead. 
Magenta inkjet inks typically exhibit worse puddling than cyan and yellow inkjet 
inks. Puddling occurs when the ink that is ejected through the orifices does not 
reach the print medium. Instead, the inkjet ink collects on an outer surface of 
the orifice plate or puddles adjacent to the edge of the orifice. This occurs when  
 
ink drops exiting the orifices leave behind minute amounts of ink on the orifice 
plate around each orifice. The extent of the puddling varies from a few, small 
drops of ink to the formation of large puddles on large portions of the orifice 
plate. Large puddles partially or completely block the orifices and cause 
missing nozzles, false low decap values, or changes in the trajectory of the ink 
drops. The change in trajectory results in the ink drop not hitting its targeted 
pixel center, which creates printing errors on the media and reduces the quality 
of the printed image. </p><p num="0007">Various solutions to address the problem of puddling have been 
proposed. Some solutions propose modifying the printhead or pen to reduce 
puddling, while other solutions modify the inkjet ink composition. For example, 
a coating of hydrophobic material is applied to the printhead to reduce its 
wettability and, thereby, reduce puddling. However, this modification to the 
printhead is costly. A combination of pen architecture and modifications to the 
inkjet ink composition have also been suggested to improve puddling. </p><p num="0008">Proposed modifications to the inkjet inks include adding anionic and 
nonionic surfactants to the inkjet ink. Similarly, adding a first surfactant and a 
second surfactant to improve puddling has been proposed. The first surfactant 
has a hydrophilic-lipophilic balance ("HLB") value of 1.5 units lower than the 
second surfactant. Additional modifications include adding salts to the inkjet 
inks. However, adding salts or surfactants causes reliability and materials 
interaction issues because these additives cannot be used with all dyes or ink 
vehicles. In addition, adding surfactants or salts negatively affects desirable 
properties of the inkjet inks. </p><p num="0009">It would be desirable to improve puddling of inkjet inks by using additives 
that are effective in low amounts and do not negatively affect other properties of 
the inkjet inks. In addition, it would be desirable to use additives that are 
effective in many types of ink vehicles.  </p><heading>BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0010">A puddling additive used in an inkjet ink is disclosed. The puddling 
additive comprises a nonionic, polar group and a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail. 
Preferably, the nonionic, polar group is an alcohol, alkene, or zwitterionic group 
and is attached to a saturated or unsaturated C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail. 
Preferably, the C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail has between 8 and 18 carbons. </p><p num="0011">A method of reducing puddling in inkjet inks is also disclosed. The 
method comprises adding a puddling additive to the inkjet ink. The puddling 
additive has a nonionic, polar group and a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail. </p><p num="0012">A set of inkjet inks is also disclosed. Each inkjet ink comprises a dye, an 
aqueous ink vehicle, and a puddling additive, which comprises a nonionic, polar 
group and a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail. </p><heading>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading> <p num="0013">A nonionic additive used to control puddling in an inkjet ink is disclosed. 
The inkjet ink comprises a dye, an ink vehicle, and a puddling additive, which 
includes a nonionic, polar group and a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail. A set of inkjet 
inks, each comprising the puddling additive, is used in a color printer. A method 
of reducing puddling in inkjet inks is also disclosed. The method comprises 
adding a puddling additive to the inkjet ink, where the puddling additive 
comprises a nonionic, polar group and a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail. A set of inkjet 
inks is also disclosed. </p><p num="0014">The amounts of the components in the inkjet ink are expressed in weight 
percent ("wt %") of the total weight of the ink composition. The purity of all 
components is that used in normal commercial practice for inkjet inks. </p><p num="0015">An inkjet ink of the present invention may comprise a colorant, such as a 
dye or pigment, an ink vehicle, and a puddling additive. If the colorant is a dye, 
the dye may be nonionic, cationic, anionic, or a mixture of nonionic, cationic, 
and/or anionic dyes. Dyes are well known in the art and are commercially 
available from numerous sources including, but not limited to, Avecia  
 
(Wilmington, DE), Mitsubishi Chemical Corp. (Tokyo, Japan), and Ilford AG 
(Fribourg, Switzerland). The dyes included may be Acid dyes, Direct dyes, 
Food dyes, Mordant dyes, or Reactive dyes and may be water-soluble or water-insoluble. 
Examples of dyes include, but are not limited to, sulfonate and 
carboxylate dyes, such as those dyes that are commonly employed in inkjet 
printing. Specific examples of dyes that may be used in the inkjet ink include, 
but are not limited to, Sulforhodamine B (sulfonate), Acid Blue 113 (sulfonate), 
Acid Blue 29 (sulfonate), Acid Red 4(sulfonate), Rose Bengal (carboxylate), 
Acid Yellow 17 (sulfonate), Acid Yellow 29 (sulfonate), Acid Yellow 42 
(sulfonate), Acridine Yellow G (sulfonate), Acid Yellow 23, Acid Blue 9, Nitro 
Blue Tetrazolium Chloride Monohydrate or Nitro BT, Rhodamine 6G, 
Rhodamine 123, Rhodamine B, Rhodamine B Isosyanate, Safranine O, Azure 
B, and Azure B Eosinate, all of which are available from Sigma-Aldrich 
Chemical Company (St. Louis, MO). Examples of anionic, water-soluble dyes 
include, but are not limited to, Direct Yellow 132, Direct Blue 199, Magenta 377 
(available from Ilford AG, Switzerland), alone or together with Acid Red 52. 
Examples of water-insoluble dyes include azo, xanthene, methine, polymethine, 
and anthroquinone dyes. Specific examples of water-insoluble dyes include 
Ciba-Geigy Orasol Blue GN, Ciba-Geigy Orasol Pink, and Ciba-Geigy Orasol 
Yellow. The dye is not critical to the operability of the present invention and, 
therefore, the selection of dye is not discussed in detail. Rather, it is understood 
that one of ordinary skill in the art could select any suitable dye for use in the 
present invention. </p><p num="0016">In addition to color dyes or pigments, black dyes or pigments may be 
used in the inkjet ink. For example, Direct Black 154, Direct Black 168, Fast 
Black 2, Direct Black 171, Direct Black 19, Acid Black 1, Acid Black 191, Mobay 
Black SP, or Acid Black 2 may be used. </p><p num="0017">The dye may be present in the inkjet ink in a range from approximately 
0.1 to approximately 15 wt % of the total weight of the inkjet ink, with 
approximately 0.5 to approximately 5 wt % being preferred. The amount of dye 
necessary in the inkjet ink is largely dependent on the solubility of the dye in the  
 
ink vehicle, the desired color to be achieved with the inkjet ink, and the purity 
and strength of the dye. </p> <p num="0018">The ink vehicle may comprise an aqueous-based ink vehicle that 
includes water or a mixture of water and at least one water-soluble organic 
solvent. The water-soluble organic solvent may include, but is not limited to, an 
aliphatic alcohol, an aromatic alcohol, a diol, a glycol ether, a poly(glycol) ether, 
a caprolactam, a formamide, an acetamide, and a long chain alcohol, or 
mixtures thereof. Examples of organic solvents employed in the practice of this 
invention include, but are not limited to, primary alcohols of 30 carbons or less, 
primary aromatic alcohols of 30 carbons or less, secondary aliphatic alcohols of 
30 carbons or less, secondary aliphatic alcohols of 30 carbons or less, 1,3-alkyldiols 
of 30 carbons or less, alkyltriols of 30 carbons or less, 1, □-alcohols of 
30 carbons or less, ethylene glycol alkyl ethers, propylene glycol alkyl ethers, 
poly(ethylene glycol) alkyl ethers, higher homologs of poly(ethylene glycol) alkyl 
ethers, poly(propylene glycol) alkyl ethers, higher homologs of poly(propylene 
glycol) alkyl ethers, N-alkyl caprolactams, unsubstituted caprolactams, 
substituted formamides, unsubstituted formamides, substituted acetamides, and 
unsubstituted acetamides. Specific organic solvents that are preferably 
employed in the practice of this invention include, but are not limited to, N-methyl 
pyrrolidone, 1,5-pentanediol, 2-pyrrolidone, diethylene glycol, 1,3-(2-methyl)-propanediol, 
1,3,5-(2-methyl)-pentanetriol, tetramethylene sulfone, 3-methoxy-3-methylbutanol, 
glycerol, 3-pyridylcarbinol, pentaerythritol, 1,2-alkyldiols, 
and mixtures thereof. For instance, the water-soluble organic solvent 
in the ink vehicle may include a mixture of a diol, a polyglycol, and a glycol. The 
water-soluble organic solvent(s) is present in a range from approximately 0.01 
to approximately 50 wt % of the total weight of the inkjet ink, with approximately 
0.1 to approximately 20 wt % being preferred. </p> <p num="0019">The ink vehicle may optionally include surfactants, humectants, buffers, 
preservatives, biocides, and/or viscosity modifiers, depending on the desired 
properties of the inkjet ink. For instance, at least one surfactant may be used in 
the ink vehicle. The surfactant may be a nonionic, amphoteric, or ionic 
surfactant. Nonionic and amphoteric surfactants include TERGITOL®  
 
compounds, which are alkyl polyethylene oxides available from Dow Chemical 
(Midland, Michigan); TRITON® compounds, which are alkyl phenyl polyethylene 
oxide surfactants available from Rohm &amp; Haas Co. (Philadelphia, PA); BRIJ® 
compounds available from ICI Americas (Wilmington, DE); PLURONIC® 
compounds, which are polyethylene oxide block copolymers available from 
BASF (Mount Olive, NJ); SURFYNOL® compounds, which are acetylenic 
polyethylene oxides available from Air Products (Allentown, PA); polyethylene 
oxide ("POE") esters; POE diesters; POE amines; POE amides; and 
dimethicone copolyols. The concentration of surfactant employed in the present 
invention may range from approximately 0 to approximately 40 wt % of the total 
weight of the inkjet ink. Preferably, the surfactant is present at approximately 
0.01 % to 5wt %. </p> <p num="0020">Buffers may be used to maintain the inkjet ink at a desired pH. The 
buffer may be an organic-based biological buffer or an inorganic buffer. The 
buffers employed may provide a pH ranging from approximately 3 to 
approximately 9, preferably from approximately 6 to approximately 9, and most 
preferably from approximately 8 to approximately 8.5. Examples of buffers 
include Trizma Base, available from Sigma-Aldrich Corp. (Milwaukee, 
Wisconsin); 4-morpholine ethane sulfonic acid ("MES"); 4-morpholinepropanesulfonic 
acid ("MOPS"); and beta-hydroxy-4-morpholinepropane-sulfonic 
acid ("MOPSO"). </p><p num="0021">The puddling additive may comprise a nonionic, polar group and a C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> 
hydrocarbon tail. The nonionic, polar group and C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail may be 
directly attached to one another or indirectly attached by a spacer. The term 
"nonionic, polar group" refers to a polar group having a neutral charge or a polar 
group having both a positive charge and a negative charge (a zwitterion), 
thereby effectively having an overall, neutral charge. The nonionic, polar group 
may include, but is not limited to, an alkane, an alkene, a polyethylene oxide, an 
ether, an alcohol, or a zwitterionic group. </p><p num="0022">The C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail of the puddling additive may be a saturated 
or unsaturated hydrocarbon chain comprising between 6 and 30 carbons. If the 
C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail is unsaturated, it may have at least one site of  
 
unsaturation (carbon-carbon double bond), with each site of unsaturation having 
either a cis or trans stereochemistry. The hydrocarbon chain may also be either 
a straight or branched chain. </p><p num="0023">An alcohol, alkene, or zwitterionic group may be used as the nonionic, 
polar group of the puddling additive. For instance, oleyl alcohol, which is 
available from Sigma-Aldrich Corp. (St. Louis, MO), has an alcohol group as the 
nonionic, polar group. <i>trans</i>-5-decene and <i>trans</i>-4-octene both have an alkene 
group as the nonionic, polar group and are also available from Sigma-Aldrich 
Corp. (St. Louis, MO). Oleyl dimethylamine oxide has a zwitterionic group as 
the nonionic, polar group and is available from Henkel Corp. (Düsseldorf, 
Germany). Hydrocarbon chains having between 8 and 18 carbons may be used 
as the C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail. Preferably, the hydrocarbon chains are straight 
chains and have between 0 and 1 site of unsaturation. </p><p num="0024">The puddling additive may be present in the inkjet ink in an amount 
effective to control puddling and may be soluble in the inkjet ink in the amount 
used. It is known in the art that longer chain hydrocarbons are less soluble in 
the ink vehicle than shorter chain hydrocarbons. Therefore, the length of the 
C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail of the puddling additive may be selected so that the 
puddling additive is soluble in the ink vehicle. The puddling additive may be 
present in an amount ranging from approximately 0.1 wt % to approximately 2.0 
wt % of the total weight of the inkjet ink. The amount of puddling additive used 
in the inkjet ink is a minimal amount that is sufficient to control puddling without 
negatively impacting other properties of the inkjet inks. Since the amount of 
puddling additive is minimal and does not negatively impact other properties, the 
puddling additive may be used in a wide variety of ink vehicles. In addition, 
more than one puddling additive may be used in the inkjet ink to achieve the 
desired decrease in puddling. </p><p num="0025">The puddling additive may be commercially available in reagent grade 
purity (99<sup>+</sup>% purity). In addition, the puddling additive may be synthesized by 
techniques known in the art. For example, a puddling additive having an odd 
number of carbons in the hydrocarbon chain, a branched hydrocarbon chain,  
 
more than one site of unsaturation, or a stereochemistry that is not commercially 
available may be synthesized by techniques known in the art. </p><p num="0026">In one embodiment, the puddling additive has an alcohol as the nonionic, 
polar group and a hydrocarbon chain comprising 18 carbons as the C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> 
hydrocarbon tail. </p><p num="0027">In another embodiment, the puddling additive has an alkene as the 
nonionic polar group and a hydrocarbon chain comprising between 8 and 10 
carbons as the C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail. </p><p num="0028">In yet another embodiment, the puddling additive has a zwitterionic group 
as the nonionic, polar group and a hydrocarbon chain comprising 18 carbons as 
the C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail. </p><p num="0029">The components of an exemplary inkjet ink are shown in Table 1, along 
with ranges of the amount of each component. The inkjet ink may be cyan, 
magenta, yellow, or black, depending on the dye that is used. 
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" namest="1">Components Of The Inkjet Ink Composition </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Component </entry><entry align="left">Wt % </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Dye</entry><entry align="left">Approximately 0.5 to 5 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Diol/polyglycol ether/glycol ether</entry><entry align="left">Approximately 10 to 15 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Buffer</entry><entry align="left">Approximately 0.2 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Preservative/biocide</entry><entry align="left">Approximately 0.05 to 0.5 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Surfactant</entry><entry align="left">Approximately 0.02 to 4 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Puddling additive</entry><entry align="left">Approximately 0.1 to 2.0 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Water</entry><entry align="left">Remainder </entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0030">The inkjet inks are formulated by combining these components, using 
methods known in the art. The puddling additives described herein may be 
easily incorporated into existing formulation processes because the puddling 
additives are present in low amounts. Therefore, the puddling additive does not 
create solubility issues that require modifying existing formulation processes.  
 
Rather, the puddling additive is added to the inkjet ink along with other 
components of the inkjet ink. Since the puddling additives are easily 
incorporated into existing processes, the cost of reducing puddling is low. </p><p num="0031">Cyan, yellow, magenta, and black inks having the puddling additives 
described herein may be used in a set of inkjet inks in a color printer. The set of 
inkjet inks may be used to print high quality images on normal or specialty print 
media. While each of the inkjet inks in the ink set may comprise the puddling 
additive, it is also contemplated that the puddling additive may be present in at 
least one of the inkjet inks. For example, if puddling only occurs in the magenta 
ink of a particular set of inkjet inks, only that ink may include the puddling 
additive. In addition, each of the inkjet inks in the set may include the same 
puddling additive or may include a different, puddling additive. </p><heading>Example 1</heading><heading>Inkjet Ink Compositions</heading><p num="0032">Magenta inkjet inks including the components listed in Table 1 were 
produced. The dye used in these inkjet inks was a magenta dye available from 
Mitsubishi Chemical Corp. (Tokyo, Japan). The puddling additives that were 
used in the magenta inkjet inks are listed in Table 2, along with the amount of 
the puddling additive that was tested.  <tables><table><tgroup cols="5"><tbody><row><entry nameend="5" namest="1">Puddling Results for Magenta Inkjet Inks </entry></row><row><entry align="center"><b>General Chemical Category</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Puddling additive</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Amount of Puddling additive (wt %)</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Chemical Formula</b></entry><entry align="center"><b>Puddling score (lower scores preferred)</b></entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alcohol</entry><entry align="left">Oleyl alcohol</entry><entry align="center">0.6</entry><entry align="left">C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>36</sub>O</entry><entry align="left">0 </entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">Oleyl alcohol</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="left">C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>36</sub>O</entry><entry align="left">0 </entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">Polyethylene (10) oleyl ether</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="left">C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>35</sub>(OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub>OH, n is approximately 10</entry><entry align="left">1.6 </entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">Polyethylene (20) oleyl ether</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="left">C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>35</sub>(OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub>OH, n is approximately 20</entry><entry align="left">2.2 </entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left">Polyethylene (2) oleyl ether</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="left">C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>35</sub>(OCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub>OH, n is approximately 2</entry><entry align="left">4.0 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Alkenes</entry><entry align="left"><i>trans</i>-5- decene</entry><entry align="center">0.6</entry><entry align="left">C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>20</sub></entry><entry align="left">0.3 </entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left"><i>trans</i>-5-decene</entry><entry align="center">1.0</entry><entry align="left">C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>20</sub></entry><entry align="left">0.2 </entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left"><i>trans</i>-4-octene</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="left">C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>16</sub></entry><entry align="left">1.1 </entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left"><i>trans</i>-7- tetradecene</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="left">C<sub>14</sub>H<sub>28</sub></entry><entry align="left">4.3 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Zwitterionic surfactants</entry><entry align="left"><i>cis</i>-oleyl dimethylami ne oxide</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="left">R(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>N<sup>+</sup>O<sup>-</sup>, R is oleyl</entry><entry align="left">0.4 </entry></row><row><entry align="left"/><entry align="left"><i>cis</i>-oleyl betaine</entry><entry align="center">0.4</entry><entry align="left">CH<sub>3</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>7</sub>CHCH(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>7</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>N<sup>+</sup>(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> CH<sub>2</sub>COO<sup>-</sup></entry><entry align="left">1.4 </entry></row><row><entry align="left">Control Ink</entry><entry align="left">None</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">3.2 </entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0033">To act as a control, magenta inkjet inks lacking the puddling additive 
were also produced. </p><p num="0034">The inkjet inks were formulated by direct mixing of the components. The 
pH of the inkjet inks was adjusted to between approximately 8.0 and 8.5 by the 
addition of sodium hydroxide. At this pH range, the puddling additives were 
present as a sodium salt.  </p><heading>Example 2</heading><heading>Puddling Results</heading><p num="0035">The inkjet inks described in Example 1 were tested to determine their 
puddling characteristics. The inkjet ink was printed continuously over a full 
sheet of print medium. To determine the extent of puddling, the inkjet pen was 
removed before it was serviced and the amount of puddling on the printhead 
was visually observed. </p><p num="0036">Puddling was measured by visually observing the printhead after printing 
and assigning a "puddling score" to reflect the extent of puddling of each inkjet 
ink. A low puddling score indicated a low amount of puddling. Inkjet inks 
having a puddling score less than approximately 1.0 exhibited the greatest 
decrease in puddling. Puddling in each inkjet ink having the puddling additive 
was compared to puddling of a control inkjet ink. A ratio of the puddling score of 
each inkjet ink having the puddling additive to the puddling score of the control 
inkjet ink is reported in Table 2 as the "% of no additive." </p><p num="0037">As shown in Table 2, the inkjet inks comprising oleyl alcohol, <i>trans</i>-5-decene, 
<i>trans</i>-4-octene, and oleyl dimethylamine oxide exhibited the greatest 
reduction in puddling. Oleyl alcohol was tested at 0.6 and 1.0 wt % and showed 
improved puddling at both amounts. </p><p num="0038">The inkjet inks comprising <i>trans</i>-5-decene and <i>trans</i>-4-octene also 
showed improved puddling. Both of these puddling additives have an alkene 
group as the nonionic, polar group, while <i>trans</i>-5-decene has a C<sub>10</sub> hydrocarbon 
tail and <i>trans</i>-4-octene has a C<sub>8</sub> hydrocarbon tail. </p><p num="0039">Using oleyl dimethylamine oxide as the puddling additive also showed 
improved puddling in the inkjet inks. Oleyl dimethylamine oxide has a 
zwitterionic group as the nonionic, polar group and a C<sub>18</sub> hydrocarbon tail.  </p><heading>Example 3</heading><heading>Additional Puddling Additives</heading><p num="0040">Puddling additives having an alkane, a polyethylene oxide, or an ether as 
the nonionic, polar group are synthesized or purchased. In addition, puddling 
additives having a hydrocarbon chain comprising 6, 7, 9, or 11-17 carbons in 
the C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> hydrocarbon tail are synthesized or purchased. Puddling additives 
having a hydrocarbon chain comprising between 19 and 30 carbons in the C<sub>6</sub>-C<sub>30</sub> 
hydrocarbon tail are also synthesized or purchased </p><p num="0041">The puddling additives are formulated into inkjet inks and printed as 
previously described. Inkjet inks comprising these puddling additives exhibit 
reduced puddling. </p><p num="0042">While the invention may be susceptible to various modifications and 
alternative forms, specific embodiments have been described in detail herein. 
However, it should be understood that the invention is not intended to be limited 
to the particular forms disclosed. Rather, the invention is to cover all 
modifications, equivalents, and alternatives falling within the spirit and scope of 
the invention as defined by the following appended claims. </p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An inkjet ink with improved puddling, comprising: 
<claim-text><claim-text>a dye; </claim-text><claim-text>an inkjet vehicle; and </claim-text><claim-text>a puddling additive comprising a nonionic, polar group and a C6-C30 
hydrocarbon tail. </claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>An inkjet ink composition, comprising: 
<claim-text><claim-text>a set of cyan, yellow, magenta, and black inkjet inks, each inkjet ink comprising a 
dye, an aqueous ink vehicle, and a puddling additive, wherein the puddling additive 
comprises an nonionic, polar group and a C6-C30 hydrocarbon tail. </claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>A method of improving puddling in an inkjet ink, comprising: 
<claim-text><claim-text>adding a puddling additive comprising a nonionic, polar group and a C6-C30 
hydrocarbon tail to the inkjet ink, wherein the inkjet ink comprises a dye and an inkjet 
vehicle. </claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The inkjet ink, the inkjet ink composition, and the method of claims 1-3, 
wherein the nonionic, polar group comprises an alcohol group, an alkene group, or a 
zwitterionic group. </claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The inkjet ink, the inkjet ink composition, and the method of claims 1-4, 
wherein the C6-C30 hydrocarbon tail is saturated. </claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The inkjet ink, the inkjet ink composition, and the method of claims 1-4, 
wherein the C6-C30 hydrocarbon tail is unsaturated. </claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The inkjet ink, the inkjet ink composition, and the method of claims 1-6, 
wherein the C6-C30 hydrocarbon tail has between 8 and 18 carbon atoms. </claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The inkjet ink, the inkjet ink composition, and the method of claims 1-7, 
wherein the puddling additive is selected from the group consisting of trans-5-decene, 
trans-4-octene, oleyl alcohol, and oleyl dimethylamine oxide. </claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The inkjet ink composition of claim 2, wherein each inkjet ink comprises a 
different puddling additive having a nonionic, polar group and a 
C6-C30 hydrocarbon tail. </claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The inkjet ink, the inkjet ink composition, and the method of 
claims 1-9, wherein the puddling additive is present in the inkjet 
ink between approximately 0.4 to 1.0 percent by weight of the total 
weight of the inkjet ink. </claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>