<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1550741-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1550741" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="32096707" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20050706"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1550741-A1" status="new" fvid="24381878"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1550741</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20050706</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03751401-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03751401</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031009</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-0312945-W" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>0312945</doc-number><kind>W</kind><date>20031009</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002295964-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002295964</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021009</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002295966-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002295966</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021009</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2003167075-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2003167075</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030611</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  26/02        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C23C  26/02        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C23C  26/02</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">ROTOR UND BESCHICHTUNGSVERFAHREN DAFÜR</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">ROTOR AND COATING METHOD THEREFOR</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">ROTOR ET PROCEDE DE REVETEMENT DESTINE A CELUI-CI</invention-title><citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>See references of WO  2004033755A1</text><sources><source name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ISHIKAWAJIMA HARIMA HEAVY IND</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI ELECTRIC CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ISHIKAWAJIMA-HARIMA JUKOGYO KABUSHIKI KAISHA</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MITSUBISHI DENKI KABUSHIKI KAISHA</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Ishikawajima-Harima Jukogyo Kabushiki Kaisha</last-name><address><street>2-1, Ote-machi 2-chome, Chiyoda-ku</street><city>Tokyo 100-8182</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MITSUBISHI DENKI KABUSHIKI KAISHA</last-name><address><street>2-3, Marunouchi 2-chome, Chiyoda-ku</street><city>Tokyo 100-8310</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>AKIYOSHI MASAO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>ARAI MIKIYA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>GOTO AKIHIRO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>OCHIAI HIROYUKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SABURI SHIGERU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SAKAI JUN</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TEZUKA TSUNAO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TSUGUMI SHOGO</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>WATANABE MITSUTOSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="epo"><addressbook><name>YAMAKAWA TSUYOSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new"  format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>AKIYOSHI, MASAO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>ARAI, MIKIYA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>GOTO, AKIHIRO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>OCHIAI, HIROYUKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SABURI, SHIGERU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SAKAI, JUN</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TEZUKA, TSUNAO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TSUGUMI, SHOGO</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>WATANABE, MITSUTOSHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YAMAKAWA, TSUYOSHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>AKIYOSHI, MASAO</last-name><address><street>2-3, Marunouchi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8310</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>ARAI, MIKIYA</last-name><address><street>2-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8182</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>GOTO, AKIHIRO</last-name><address><street>2-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8182</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>OCHIAI, HIROYUKI</last-name><address><street>2-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8182</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SABURI, SHIGERU</last-name><address><street>2-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8182</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SAKAI, JUN</last-name><address><street>2-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8182</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TEZUKA, TSUNAO</last-name><address><street>2-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8182</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TSUGUMI, SHOGO</last-name><address><street>2-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8182</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>WATANABE, MITSUTOSHI</last-name><address><street>2-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8182</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>YAMAKAWA, TSUYOSHI</last-name><address><street>2-1, Ohtemachi 2-chome</street><city>Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8182</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Grünecker, August, Dipl.-Ing.</last-name><address><street>Patentanwälte Grünecker, Kinkeldey, Stockmair &amp;amp; Partner Maximilianstrasse 58</street><city>80538 München</city><country>DE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><pct-or-regional-filing-data ucid="JP-0312945-W" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>JP</country><doc-number>0312945</doc-number><kind>W</kind></document-id></pct-or-regional-filing-data><pct-or-regional-publishing-data ucid="WO-2004033755-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2004033755</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040422</date></document-id></pct-or-regional-publishing-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>CH</country><country>DE</country><country>ES</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>IT</country><country>LI</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>A pulsed discharge is generated between tip ends of
a rotating member such as a blade and a discharge electrode
including a hard material such as cBN in dielectric liquid or
gas by a power supply for discharge to melt the discharge
electrode, and a part of the discharge electrode is attached
to the tip end of the rotating member to form an abrasive
coating film including the hard materials such as cBN.
<img id="img-00000001" orientation="unknown" wi="91" img-format="tif" img-content="ad" file="00000001.tif" inline="no" he="70"/></p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><u style="single">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><heading><u style="single">Technical Field of the Invention</u></heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a rotating member
such as a blade or labyrinth seal for use in a gas turbine,
steam turbine, compressor or the like, and a method for
coating the rotating member. More particularly, it relates
to a rotating member on a part of which a coating film
including a hard material is formed, and a method for coating
the rotating member.</p><heading><u style="single">Description of the Related Art</u></heading><p num="0002">For a rotating member such as a blade or a labyrinth
seal, a clearance between a rotating section and a stationary
section such as a chip clearance between the blade and a
casing or a shroud, or a seal clearance between the labyrinth
seal and a honeycomb seal needs to be kept/set to be
appropriate during operation of a gas turbine. When the
clearance is set to be excessively large fearing for contact,
an efficiency of the gas turbine drops. Conversely, when the
clearance is set to be excessively small, a tip end of the
rotating member breaks and causes a trouble of the gas
turbine.</p><p num="0003">Therefore, in consideration of the contact with
surrounding members (casing, shroud, honeycomb seal, and the
like) of the rotating member, a tip end of a blade or a 
labyrinth seal is coated with an abrasive coating of a
relatively hard material for chipping off the material of a
contact surface of the surrounding member. The surrounding
member is coated with an abradable coating of a material
which is relatively easily chipped. Accordingly, the chip
clearance or the seal clearance is adjusted to be minimized,
when the side of the surrounding member is chipped off by the
tip end of the rotating member by taking advantage of a
hardness difference of the coating at the time of driving of
the gas turbine.</p><p num="0004">Here, FIG. 1A is a perspective view of a usual
turbine blade, FIG. 1B is a perspective view of the turbine
blade with a chip shroud, and FIG. 1C is a perspective view
of a compressor blade. It is to be noted that a platform or
a dovetail on a turbine disk side is omitted from these
figures. In a turbine blade 1 shown in FIG. 1A, the whole
surface of a blade tip end is coated with an abrasive coating
5a. In a turbine blade 2 with a chip shroud shown in FIG. 1B,
the whole surfaces of the tip ends of chip fins 4 disposed on
a chip shroud 3 (i.e., the tip ends of the turbine blade) are
coated with abrasive coatings 5b. Furthermore, for the blade
1 of the compressor shown in FIG. 1C, an abrasive coating 5c
is applied over the region of the blade tip end (including
the backside of the figure).</p><p num="0005">Moreover, FIG. 2 is a sectional view showing one
example of a labyrinth seal tip end. The labyrinth seal is
disposed in the clearance between a rotating section and a 
stationary section to prevent leakage of air or combustion
gas, and is a seal structure frequently used in a gas turbine
and compressor. In general, an annular labyrinth seal 6
including concave/convex portion is disposed on a rotating
section side, and a honeycomb seal (not shown) including a
structure easy to be chipped off is disposed on a stationary
section side. FIG. 2 is a sectional view cut in a plane
including a center axis of the labyrinth seal 6, and an
abrasive coating 5d is applied to the tip end of the convex
portion of the labyrinth seal 6.</p><p num="0006">These abrasive coatings have heretofore been applied
by methods such as welding, thermal spraying, and plating
(e.g., see References 1 and 2). With the coating by the
welding, a welding rod or a powder body is used to coat
predetermined portions such as the tip end of the turbine
blade or the labyrinth seal. With the coating by the thermal
spraying, zirconia is thermally sprayed which has a small
difference of thermal expansion from a mother material and
whose hardness is relatively high (Vickers hardness of 1300
HV). With the coating by the plating, abrasive grains
(Vickers hardness of 4500 HV) of cubic boron nitride (cBN)
high in hardness is electrically attached by nickel plating.</p><p num="0007">It is to be noted that other prior arts related to
the present invention are described in References 3, 4.

[Reference 1]

   Japanese Laid-Open Patent Publication No. 11-286768

[Reference 2]
 
   Japanese Laid-Open Patent Publication No. 2000-345809

[Reference 3]

   Japanese Laid-Open Patent Publication No. 7-301103

[Reference 4]

   Japanese Laid-Open Patent Publication No. 8-319804</p><p num="0008">However, in the above-described methods, a portion
which does not have to be coated is masked in order to
closely attach the abrasive coating, the surface to be coated
needs to be blast-treated in order to enhance adhesion, and
there are problems that there are many pretreatments and
costs are high. In either conventional thermal spraying or
plating method, there have been problems that the adhesion of
the coating is bad, peel occurs at the time of the driving,
an engine trouble is caused, and additionally the chip
clearance or the seal clearance is not kept to be appropriate.
Furthermore, there has been a problem that with the coating
by the welding, only a metal much lower in hardness can be
coated as compared with a ceramic, and therefore abrasive
properties (properties for chipping off a material to be
ground) are inferior. Moreover, there has been a problem
that a quality level fluctuates by an operator's expertise,
and a welding crack easily occurs with respect to a material
bad in thermal conductivity and small in elongation.
Furthermore, there has been a problem that post-treatments
such as grinding for processing to a required dimension after
the welding are required, and a lot of trouble is required.</p><p num="0009">Moreover, according to References 3 and 4, in the 
coating method, discharge is performed between the rotating
member and an electrode on first discharge conditions such
that the electrode is consumed, and the electrode is formed
in accordance with a shape of a coating film forming portion.
Thereafter, the coating film is formed by discharge between
the electrode and the rotating member on second discharge
conditions. Then, even when the electrode is not processed
beforehand for a product shape, a coating object portion can
appropriately be coated. On the first discharge conditions
for consuming the electrode, the electrode is set to have a
minus polarity, a pulse width is set to 1 µs or less, and a
current value is set to 10 A or less. On the second
discharge conditions for forming the coating film, the
electrode is preferably set to have the minus polarity, the
pulse width is set to 2 to 10 µs, and the current value is
set to 5 to 20 A.</p><p num="0010">Moreover, in the conventional abrasive coating,
since the whole area of the tip end of the blade is coated,
there has been a problem that a coating range is broad and
yield of products is bad.</p> <p num="0011">Furthermore, heretofore, the coating has been
performed by the plating or the thermal spraying. Therefore,
in the production (manufacturing) of the labyrinth seal,
coating pretreatments such as a blast process and a process
of attaching a masking tape are required before the coating,
and coating post-treatments such as a process of removing the 
masking tape are required after the coating. Therefore, an
operation time required for the production (manufacturing) of
the labyrinth seal lengthens, and it is not easy to enhance
productivity of the labyrinth seal.</p><p num="0012">Additionally, for the same reason, the abrasive coat
cannot firmly be attached to the tip edge of a seal fin.
Therefore, there has been a problem that the abrasive coat
easily peels off the tip edge of the seal fin and the quality
level of the labyrinth seal is not stable.</p><heading><u style="single">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</u></heading><p num="0013">The present invention has been developed to solve
the above-described various problems. That is, a first
object of the present invention is to provide a rotating
member which does not require any pretreatment or post-treatment
and which has good adhesion and which is coated
with a precise and abrasive coating of a relatively hard
material (hereinafter referred to as a hard material in the
present specification for the sake of convenience) compared
to a material of an opponent component that contacts with the
rotating member during rotation, and a method for coating the
rotating member.</p> <p num="0014">Moreover, the first object is also to provide a
method for forming a long-service-life coating in tests of
high cycle fatigue (HCF) or low cycle fatigue (LCF) in an
abrasive coated component.</p> <p num="0015">Furthermore, a second object of the present 
invention is to provide a rotating member in which an area of
coating of a hard material can be optimized to enhance a
yield and a method for coating the rotating member.</p> <p num="0016">Additionally, a third object of the present
invention is to provide a rotating member in which an
operation time required for production of a labyrinth seal is
reduced and productivity of labyrinth components can be
enhanced and a method for coating the rotating member.</p><p num="0017">To achieve the first object, according to a first
invention, there is provided a method for coating a rotating
member, comprising the steps of: generating a pulsed
discharge between a rotating member formed into a
predetermined shape and a discharge electrode of a green
compact in dielectric liquid or gas to transfer a hard
material of the discharge electrode or a hard material
changed from a material of the discharge electrode onto the
rotating member by each discharge pulse so that a hard
concavity and convexity is formed on the rotating member,
wherein the green compact includes the hard material or the
material changing into the hard material by the discharge;
and repeatedly generating the discharge pulse to form on the
rotating member a hard coating film having the concavity and
convexity.</p><p num="0018">Moreover, according to a second invention, in the
method for coating the rotating member, the hard coating film
is an abrasive coating film that is formed on a part of the 
rotating member and rubs against and shaves an opponent
component.</p><p num="0019">According to the first and second inventions, since
the so-called discharge coating method is used, pretreatments
such as masking and blast treatment or post-treatments such
as the grinding are not necessary, the coating film or a
layer having good adhesion can be formed, further the coating
film containing remarkably hard materials such as a cubic
boron nitride (cBN) can be coated, and the hard coating film
and the coating film having good abrasive properties can be
formed.</p><p num="0020">Abrasive properties are enhanced by the treatment on
a condition for a coating having coarse surface.</p><p num="0021">Moreover, according to a third invention, the method
comprises the steps of: generating discharge between the
rotating member and the discharge electrode on a first
discharge condition on which the discharge electrode is
consumed so that a shape of the discharge electrode is made
to conform to a shape of a coating film forming portion on
the rotating member; and thereafter generating discharge
between the discharge electrode and the rotating member on a
second discharge condition to form the coating film on the
rotating member.</p><p num="0022">Furthermore, according to a fourth invention,
preferably, on the first discharge condition, the discharge
electrode has a minus polarity, a pulse width is 1 µs or less,
and a current value is 10 A or less, and on the second 
discharge condition, the discharge electrode has a minus
polarity, the pulse width is 2 to 10 µs, and a current value
is 5 to 20 A.</p><p num="0023">Additionally, the coating film is preferably formed
on the tip end of the rotating member. Furthermore, for the
hard member, as in an eighth invention, the discharge
electrode of a green compact containing one of or a mixture
of cBN, TiC, TiN, TiAlN, TiB<sub>2</sub>, WC, Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>, SiC, ZrC, VC, B<sub>4</sub>C,
Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>, ZrO<sub>2</sub>-Y, and Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.</p><p num="0024">Moreover, the material forming the hard member by
the discharge is preferably one of or a mixture of Ti, Cr, W,
V, Zr, Si, Mo, and Nb or a mixture of these, and these are
formed into carbide by the discharge in an oil to form a hard
coating film.</p><p num="0025">Since a so-called discharge coating method is used
according to this method, the tip end of the rotating member
can easily be coated with the hard material. From the
viewpoint of resistance to oxidation, a coating film
containing TiC, WC, or cBN is preferably formed on the
rotating member that is driven at a low temperature, a
coating film containing cBN or Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> is used in the rotating
member that is driven at a high temperature, and a coating
film containing ZrO<sub>2</sub>-Y or Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is formed on the rotating
member that is driven at a further high temperature.</p><p num="0026">Accordingly, a fifth, sixth, seventh, and ninth
invention, there is provided a method of enhancing a fatigue
strength of a coated surface. </p><p num="0027">A coating film which does not easily stretch as
compared with a mother material is formed on the surface.
Then, since a thin coating film bears a tensile load, the
coating film on the surface easily cracks. In the coating by
a discharge surface treatment, since a hard layer is firmly
welded to the mother material, the crack of the coating film
is developed into that of the mother material. To avoid this,
it is necessary to form a coating film having a ductility, a
layer for preventing the development of the crack between the
mother material and the coating film, or a coating layer
strong against pull.</p><p num="0028">In a fifth invention, in the coating film, a ratio
of a coated area coated with the hard material in a coating
film forming portion, that is, coverage is suppressed, a
portion not coated with the hard material, that is, the
portion having the ductility is scattered and left, and the
ductility is left.</p><p num="0029">In a sixth invention, the discharge electrode is
made to contain a metal which does not easily form carbide,
accordingly the portion of a metal having the ductility is
scattered and formed between the hard materials, and the
ductility is left.</p><p num="0030">In a seventh invention, a porous coating film mainly
formed of a metal is formed as a base. Thereafter, since the
coating film containing the hard material is formed on the
porous coating film, the crack of the coating layer is
prevented from being developed into the mother material. </p><p num="0031">In a ninth invention, the surface of the coating
layer is peened, and residual stress of compression is left.
Even when the mother material stretches, a tensile stress is
reduced.</p><p num="0032">These fifth to seventh, and ninth inventions are
effective not only for the coating with the hard material but
also for the discharge surface treatment for forming the
coating film on the surface such as wear-resistant coating.</p><p num="0033">Moreover, according to the eighth invention, since a
remarkably hard ceramic usable in the coating of the hard
material is provided, it is possible to provide the coating
of an effective hard material.</p><p num="0034">Furthermore, according to a tenth invention, there
is provided a rotating member having an abrasive coating film
on a part thereof that is formed by a pulsed discharge
between the rotating member and a discharge electrode of a
green compact in dielectric liquid or gas, wherein the green
compact includes a hard material or a material that changes
into a hard material by the discharge, and the abrasive
coating film includes the hard material of the green compact
or the hard material that is changed from the material of the
green compact by the discharge. The rotating member is
characterized in that the pretreatments such as a masking or
blast process or the post-treatments such as grinding are not
unnecessary and the coating film or the layer having good
adhesion is formed. Furthermore, the coating film is
preferably formed on the tip end of the rotating member. </p><p num="0035">For the rotating member, the discharge is caused
between the rotating member and the discharge electrode in
the dielectric liquid or gas to form an abrasive coating film
including the hard material on a part of the rotating member,
so that the rotating member superior in abrasive properties
can be formed.</p><p num="0036">According to the eleventh to fourteenth inventions,
since the coating film having the ductility is formed, the
layer for preventing the development of the crack is formed
between the mother material and the coating film, and the
coating layer strong against the pull is formed, the rotating
member high in fatigue strength is provided.</p><p num="0037">Moreover, according to a fifteenth invention, a
remarkably hard ceramic usable in the coating of the hard
material is provided, and accordingly the rotating member
having good abrasive properties is provided.</p><p num="0038">To achieve the second object, according to a 16th
invention, there is provided a rotating member in which only
the vicinity of a portion of the rotating member having a
possibility of contact with a component disposed opposite to
the rotating member is coated with a hard material.
Accordingly, a rotating member little in labor of operation,
small in electrode use amount, good in yield of products and
low in cost is obtained.</p><p num="0039">In a 17th invention, there is a further inexpensive
rotating member in which a range to be coated is locally 
limited.</p><p num="0040">In an 18th invention, there is provided a rotating
member coated in a method for enhancing the abrasive
properties of the tenth to 17th inventions. The rotating
member is coated on the conditions for a coarse surface
roughness to enhance the abrasive properties.</p><p num="0041">A 19th invention is a concrete example of the 16th
invention, and there is provided a blade whose tip end is
coated with a hard material. Only a corner of the blade in a
rotation advance direction and the vicinity of the corner are
coated with the hard material.</p><p num="0042">Since the range of the coating of the hard material
is optimized, the yield can be enhanced, the operation time
is shortened, and the coating material can be saved.</p><p num="0043">A 20th invention is a concrete example of the 17th
invention, and there is provided a rotating member in which
the coating film is formed on not all, but some of blades of
a rotor or a blisk. The number of coated blades is minimized,
and accordingly the operation time is reduced and the coating
material can further be saved.</p><p num="0044">To achieve a third object, in a 21st invention, the
rotating member is a rotating labyrinth seal component which
is one of structure elements of a labyrinth seal structure
which suppresses leak of a gas or liquid between a stationary
component and a rotating component.</p><p num="0045">The rotating member comprises an annular seal 
component main body, and an annular seal fin integrally
formed on an outer peripheral surface of the seal component
main body, and a tip edge of the seal fin is coated with a
hard material. For the coat of the hard material, an
electrode for coating having consumability is used, a pulsed
discharge is caused between the electrode for coating and the
tip edge of the seal fin in dielectric liquid or gas, and the
coat includes the hard material formed of a constituting
material of the electrode for coating formed on the tip edge
of the seal fin by a discharge energy or a reactant of the
constituting material.</p><p num="0046">Here, in general, the "electrode for coating having
the consumability" means a green compact electrode (including
a thermally treated green compact electrode) obtained by
compression molding of a powdered metal (including a metal
compound), a mixed material of the powdered metal and a
powdered ceramic, or the powdered ceramic having conductivity.
Further, "electrode for coating having the consumability"
also means a silicon electrode formed of solid silicon. It
is to be noted that the ceramic having conductivity is
appropriately subjected to a surface treatment.</p><p num="0047">According to a 21st invention, the coat of the hard
material is a coating film including a hard material
constituted of a constituting material of the electrode for
coating or a reactant of the constituting material formed on
the tip edge of the seal fin by a discharge energy generated
between the electrode for coating and the tip edge of the 
seal fin without performing plating or thermal spraying.
Therefore, in the production of the rotating labyrinth seal
component, coating pretreatments such as a blast treatment
and a process of attaching a masking tape and coating post-treatments
such as a process of removing the masking tape are
unnecessary.</p><p num="0048">Moreover, since a boundary portion between the coat
of the hard material coated by the discharge energy and a
mother body of the seal fin has alloy composition changing
properties (alloy composition changes depending on the
position), the coat of the hard material can firmly be
connected to the tip edge of the seal fin.</p><p num="0049">Furthermore, in the 21st invention, preferably as in
the 22nd invention, the coat of the hard material includes a
plurality of local coating films locally formed on a
plurality of portions in a peripheral direction in the tip
edge of the seal fin.</p><p num="0050">By this constitution, the coat of the hard material
includes a plurality of local coats. Therefore, in other
words, the coating film including the hard material
constituted of the constituting material of the electrode for
coating or the reactant of the constituting material is
locally formed on a plurality of portions of the peripheral
direction in the tip edge of the seal fin, not in the whole
periphery of the tip edge of the seal fin. Therefore, the
electrode for coating can be formed in a small and simple
shape in accordance with the size or the shape of the portion 
to be treated in the tip edge of the seal fin. Moreover, the
amount of an electrode material for use in the electrode for
coating can be reduced.</p><p num="0051">It is to be noted that as described above, since the
coat of the hard material (local coat of the hard material)
can firmly be connected to the tip edge of the seal fin, the
entire rotating labyrinth seal component can have sufficient
abrasive properties by the local coat of the plurality of
hard materials without coating the whole periphery of the tip
edge of the seal fin with the hard material.</p><p num="0052">Further in the tenth invention, preferably as in the
15th invention, the electrode for coating is the green
compact electrode obtained by compression molding of the
powdered metal, the mixed material of the powdered metal and
the powdered ceramic, or the powdered ceramic having the
conductivity, or the solid silicon electrode. Furthermore,
the ceramic is one of or a mixture of cBN, Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>, TiC, TiN,
TiAlN, TiB<sub>2</sub>, ZrO<sub>2</sub>-Y, ZrC, VC, B<sub>4</sub>C, WC, SiC, Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>, and Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.</p><p num="0053">Here, the "powdered metal" also includes a powdered
metal compound. It is to be noted that a ceramic that does
not have conductivity is appropriately subjected to the
surface treatment so as to secure the conductivity.</p><p num="0054">Moreover, in a 23rd invention, there is provided a
labyrinth seal structure which suppresses a leakage of a gas
or liquid between a stationary component and a rotating
component, comprising: a stationary-side seal component
integrally disposed on the stationary component; an annular 
seal component main body which is disposed inside the
stationary-side seal component and which is capable of
rotating integrally with the rotating component and which is
integrally disposed on the rotating component; an annular
seal fin integrally formed on an outer peripheral surface of
the seal component main body; and a hard coat formed on the
tip edge of the seal fin, wherein the hard coat is a coating
film including a hard material constituted of a constituting
material or a reactant of the constituting material of an
electrode for coating formed on the tip edge of the seal fin
by a discharge energy of a pulsed discharge between the
electrode for coating and the tip edge of the seal fin, and
the electrode for coating has consumability.</p><p num="0055">Here, the "stationary-side seal component" includes
a honeycomb-shaped stationary honeycomb seal component, or a
stationary abradable seal component whose inside is coated
with an abradable coat.</p><p num="0056">Moreover, in general, the "electrode for coating
having the consumability" means a green compact electrode
(including a thermally treated green compact electrode)
obtained by compression molding of a powdered metal
(including a metal compound), a mixed material of the
powdered metal and a powdered ceramic, or the powdered
ceramic having conductivity. Further, the "electrode for
coating having the consumability" also means a silicon
electrode formed of solid silicon. It is to be noted that
for the ceramic which does not have the conductivity, the 
surface of the ceramic powder which does not have the
conductivity is subjected to a treatment for forming a
conductive coating film so as to appropriately secure the
conductivity.</p><p num="0057">According to the 23rd invention, the rotating
labyrinth seal component includes the coat of the hard
material. Therefore, to integrally rotate the rotating
labyrinth seal component with the rotating component, even
when the stationary-side seal component is deformed, and the
rotating labyrinth seal component contacts with the
stationary-side seal component, the stationary-side seal
component is simply shaved by the coat of the hard material
in the rotating labyrinth seal component, and the rotating
labyrinth seal component is hardly shaved.</p><p num="0058">Accordingly, a clearance between the stationary-side
seal and the rotating labyrinth seal component is inhibited
from being enlarged during the rotation of the rotating
component, and a seal effect of the labyrinth seal structure
can be kept in an appropriate state. Moreover, the rotating
labyrinth seal component is set so as to slightly contact
with the stationary-side seal component during initial
rotation of the rotating component. Accordingly, during or
after the initial rotation, the clearance between the
stationary-side seal component and the rotating labyrinth
seal component can be reduced as much as possible, and the
seal effect of the labyrinth seal structure can further be
enhanced. </p><p num="0059">Moreover, the coat of the hard material is the
coating film including the hard material constituted of the
constituting material of the electrode for coating or the
reactant of the constituting material formed on the tip edge
of the seal fin by the discharge energy generated between the
electrode for coating and the tip edge of the seal fin
without performing the plating or thermal spraying.
Therefore, in the production of the rotating labyrinth seal
component, the coating pretreatments such as the blast
treatment and the process of attaching the masking tape and
the coating post-treatments such as the process of removing
the masking tape are unnecessary.</p><p num="0060">Furthermore, since the boundary portion between the
coat of the hard material coated by the discharge energy and
the mother material of the seal fin has alloy composition
changing properties, the coat of the hard material can firmly
be connected to the tip edge of the seal fin.</p><p num="0061">Furthermore, in a 24th invention, preferably the
coat of the hard material includes a plurality of local
coating films locally formed on a plurality of portions in
the peripheral direction in the tip edge of the seal fin.</p><p num="0062">By this constitution, the coat of the hard material
includes a plurality of local coats of the hard material.
Therefore, in other words, the coating film including the
hard material constituted of the constituting material of the
electrode for coating or the reactant of the constituting
material is locally formed on a plurality of portions to be 
treated of the peripheral direction in the tip edge of the
seal fin, not in the whole periphery of the tip edge of the
seal fin. Therefore, the electrode for coating can be formed
into the small and simple shape in accordance with the size
or the shape of the portion to be treated in the tip edge of
the seal fin. Moreover, the amount of the electrode material
for use in the electrode for coating can be reduced.</p><p num="0063">It is to be noted that as described above, since the
coat of the hard material (local coat of the hard material)
can firmly be connected to the tip edge of the seal fin, the
entire rotating labyrinth seal components can have sufficient
abrasive properties by the local coats of the plurality of
hard materials without coating the whole periphery of the tip
edge of the seal fin with the hard material.</p><p num="0064">In a 25th invention, there is provided a method for
manufacturing a rotating member of a blade or a labyrinth
member, comprising: a first step of forming a forging
material or a casting material into a predetermined shape by
mechanical processing; and a second step of generating a
pulsed discharge between a rotating member formed into a
predetermined shape and a discharge electrode of a green
compact or solid silicon in dielectric liquid or gas to
transfer a hard material of the discharge electrode or the
hard material changed from a material of the discharge
electrode onto the rotating member by each discharge pulse so
that a hard concavity and convexity is formed on the rotating
member, wherein the green compact includes the hard material 
or the material changing into the hard material by the
discharge, and repeatedly generating the discharge pulse to
form on the rotating member a hard coating film having the
concavity and convexity.</p><p num="0065">In a 26th invention, in the above-described
manufacturing method, in the second step, an abrasive coating
film that rubs against and shaves an opponent component is
formed as the hard coating film on a part of the rotating
member.</p><p num="0066">In a 27th invention, there is provided the method
for manufacturing the rotating member, wherein the second
step comprises the steps of forming a discharge electrode
into a shape in accordance with a shape of a predetermined
portion of the rotating member.</p><p num="0067">In a 28th invention, there is provided a method for
providing discharge conditions that the shape of the
discharge electrode conform to that of the coating film
forming portion of the rotating member to form the electrode
without any trouble.</p><p num="0068">In a 29th invention, there is provided the method
for manufacturing the rotating member which does not easily
collapse from fatigue, wherein during the forming of the
coating film in the second step, a discharge condition is
controlled to set a coverage to be 95% or less in the coating
film forming portion, the coverage being a ratio of an area
at which the coating film including the hard material is
formed. </p><p num="0069">In a 30th invention, there is provided the method of
manufacturing the rotating member, wherein the ratio of the
coverage is controlled to provide the rotating member which
does not easily collapse from fatigue.</p><p num="0070">In a 31st invention, there is provided the method
for manufacturing the rotating member which does not easily
collapse from fatigue, wherein in the second step, the green
compact electrode containing 5% or more by volume of a metal
which does not easily react into carbide is used to perform
the discharge.</p><p num="0071">In a 32nd invention, there is provided the method
for manufacturing the rotating member which does not easily
collapse from fatigue, wherein the second step comprises the
steps of: forming a porous coating film on a coating film
forming portion of the rotating member; and thereafter
forming the coating film including the hard material on the
porous coating film. In a 33rd invention, there is
provided the method for manufacturing the rotating member
superior in abrasive properties by using the appropriate
discharge electrode material of the green compact in the
second step.</p><p num="0072">In a 34th invention, there is provided the method of
manufacturing the rotating member which does not easily
collapse from fatigue, further comprising: a third step of
subjecting the coating film formed in the second step to a
peening treatment.</p><p num="0073">Other objects and advantageous characteristics of 
the present invention will be apparent from the following
description with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p><heading><u style="single">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</u></heading><p num="0074"><sl><li>FIG. 1A is a perspective view of a usual turbine
blade, FIG. 1B is a perspective view of the turbine blade
with a chip shroud, and FIG. 1C is a perspective view of a
compressor blade;</li><li>FIG. 2 is a perspective view showing one example of
a conventional labyrinth seal tip end;</li><li>FIG. 3 is a diagram showing a first embodiment of a
rotating member and coating method of the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 4 is a diagram showing a second embodiment of
the rotating member and coating method of the present
invention;</li><li>FIG. 5 is a diagram showing a third embodiment of
the rotating member and coating method of the present
invention;</li><li>FIG. 6 is a diagram showing a fourth embodiment of
the rotating member and coating method of the present
invention;</li><li>FIGS. 7A, 7B, and 7C are perspective views of the
usual turbine blade according to a fifth embodiment of the
rotating member of the present invention;</li><li>FIGS. 8A, 8B, and 8C are perspective views of the
turbine blade with a chip shroud according to a sixth
embodiment of the rotating member of the present invention; </li><li>FIGS. 9A, and 9B are perspective views of the
compressor blade according to a seventh embodiment of the
rotating member of the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 10 is a diagram showing the fifth embodiment of
the coating method according to the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 11 is a schematic diagram of a labyrinth seal
structure according to an eighth embodiment of the rotating
member of the present invention;</li><li>FIG. 12 is a front view of a labyrinth seal of FIG.
11; and</li><li>FIG. 13 is a schematic diagram of a discharge
processing machine according to the eighth embodiment of the
coating method according to the present invention.</li></sl></p><heading><u style="single">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</u></heading><p num="0075">Preferable embodiments of the present invention will
hereinafter be described with reference to the drawings. It
is to be noted that components common to the respective
drawings are denoted with the same reference numerals, and
redundant description is omitted.</p><p num="0076">FIG. 3 is a diagram showing a first embodiment of a
rotating member and coating method of the present invention.
This figure shows that a tip end of a blade 1 for use in a
gas turbine or a compressor is coated with a hard material.</p><p num="0077">In the method of the present invention, as shown in
FIG. 3, the blade 1 and a discharge electrode 11 including
cubic boron nitride (cBN) is submerged in a processing tank 
12 filled with dielectric liquid (oil). A pulsed discharge
is caused between the tip end of the blade 1 and the
discharge electrode 11 by a power supply for discharge 14 to
melt the discharge electrode 11. A part of the electrode is
welded to the tip end of the blade 1 to form a cBN-containing
coating film 10. Here, only sections of the blade 1 and
discharge electrode 11 are shown, the blade 1 is fixed by a
blade fixing jig, and the discharge electrode 11 is fixed by
an electrode fixing jig (not shown). It is to be noted that
FIG. 3 shows an example of the blade, but a labyrinth seal
which is the same rotating member can also be coated with the
hard material in a similar method. It is to be noted that in
the figure, reference numeral 13 denotes the blade fixing jig.</p><p num="0078">In the above description, cBN is used as the hard
material, and cBN is a coating material optimum for the
turbine blade exposed at a high temperature, in that Vickers
hardness is 4500 HV at room temperature, and Vickers hardness
close to 2000 HV can be maintained even at high temperature
of 900°C or more. Additionally, from the viewpoint of
resistance to oxidation, a hard material of TiC, WC can be
used in the rotating member for use at a low temperature,
Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> can be used in the rotating member for use at a high
temperature, and ZrO<sub>2</sub>-Y or Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> can be used in the rotating
member for use at a further high temperature. Therefore,
according to the present invention, a coating film containing
TiC, WC, or cBN is formed on the rotating member for use at
the low temperature, a coating film containing cBN or Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub> 
is used in the rotating member for use at the high
temperature, and a coating film containing ZrO<sub>2</sub>-Y or Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> is
formed on the rotating member for use at the further high
temperature. Needless to say, these hard materials may also
be mixed to form an optimum coating film. It is to be noted
that a discharge coating technique is disclosed, for example,
in "Surface Treatment Method of Metal Material by In-liquid
Discharge" of Japanese Laid-Open Patent Publication No. 7-197275,
and the description is omitted.</p><p num="0079">Here, since ceramics such as cBN are hard insulating
materials, a single ceramic such as cBN cannot be formed into
the discharge electrode, but the discharge electrode
containing the ceramics such as cBN can be formed by use of a
conductive binder. For example, Co-based alloy powder can be
used as a binder, and ceramic powder such as cBN may be mixed
with a Co-based alloy powder, charged in a press mold, and
compressed/molded. It is to be noted that an amount of
binder is preferably about 50% or more by a volume ratio.</p><p num="0080">Furthermore, the powder of ceramics such as cBN may
be coated with titanium (Ti), nickel (Ni), or cobalt (Co)
which is a binder to form the discharge electrode. A
particle diameter of the whole powder needs to be smaller
than a pole distance between the electrode and a work during
a discharge surface treatment, and is therefore preferably
about 10 µm or less. The powder of ceramics such as cBN can
easily be coated with a thin coating film of a Ti, Ni, or Co
metal by vapor deposition. </p><p num="0081">When the conductive binder is mixed, and the
discharge electrode containing the ceramics such as cBN is
formed in this manner, the discharge can be caused in the
portion of the binder, the discharge electrode is brought
into a molten state by heat energy, and a part of the
discharge electrode can be welded/attached to the tip end of
the rotating member such as the blade. As a result, the tip
end of the rotating member can be coated with a hard coating
film containing the ceramics such as cBN.</p><p num="0082">Here, Table 1 shows results of a wear test in which
two test pieces (upper and lower test pieces) coated by the
coating method of the present invention are ground (rubbed)
with each other at the high temperature.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="3"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Coating material</entry><entry align="center">Wear amount (µm)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Upper test piece</entry><entry align="center">Ni alloy</entry><entry align="center">600 or more</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Lower test piece</entry><entry align="center">cBN coating</entry><entry align="center">0</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0083">The upper test piece is RENE77 which is a nickel-based
alloy, and the lower test piece is cBN which is the
coating film of the present invention. For test conditions,
temperature: 800 degrees centigrade, surface pressure: 7 MPa,
cycle number: 10<sup>7</sup> cycles, and amplitude: 0.35 mm. As seen
from Table 1, a wear amount of 600 µm or more is measured on
an Ni alloy, but no wear is detected on the coating film of
cBN. From this result, it is seen that cBN is superior in
abrasive properties. It is to be noted that this Ni alloy is
an alloy constituted of a component ratio of Ni: 57%, Cr: 15%,
Co: 15%, Mo: 5%, Ti: 3.5%, Al: 4.4, C: 0.1%. </p><p num="0084">When a so-called discharge coating method is used to
coat the tip end of the rotating member such as the blade
with the coating film containing the ceramics such as cBN,
the hard coat can easily be applied by use of characteristics
of the ceramics such as cBN, and a coating film having good
adhesion and quality level can be coated as compared with
conventional methods such as welding and thermal spraying.
According to the present invention, since a thin coating film
(or a layer) that has a thickness of several microns to 30 µm
can be formed, the coating film is not easily cracked, and
precision can be controlled by a unit of several µm.
Therefore, it is possible to provide a coating method optimum
for precision components such as the blade and labyrinth seal.</p><p num="0085">Coarser surface roughness for abrasive properties of
shaving the opponent component to be ground is preferable.
In the example, the surface roughness is coarser than 1.2
µmRa.</p><p num="0086">As described above, since the so-called discharge
coating method is used in the present invention, the
pretreatments such as the masking and blast process are
unnecessary, the coating film having good adhesion can easily
and inexpensively be formed, and further a coating film
containing ceramics such as cubic boron nitride (cBN) can be
coated. Therefore, a portion of the rotating member
requiring the abrasive properties can be coated with a hard
coating film superior in abrasive properties.</p><p num="0087">A coating layer of the hard material is hard, and 
small in ductility. Therefore, a tensile stress applied to
the component is not borne by a mother material in a
component having a large ductility, and is borne only by the
coating layer of the surface. Therefore, the surface cracks,
and there is a possibility that the crack is developed into
the mother material. To avoid this, a method of imparting
the ductility to the coating layer is used.</p><p num="0088">Table 2 shows the number of cycles reaching
destruction in a high cycle fatigue (HCF) test in which an
outer diameter of a round rod is coated with the hard
material and a tensile load is going to be repeated in an
axial direction.</p><p num="0089">Without any coating of the hard material, the
material does not break up to one million cycles. However,
in the coating in which a ratio of a coated area in a coating
surface with the hard material, that is, a coverage (see FIG.
4) of coating is 98%, the material breaks at 20 thousand
cycles. When the coverage is suppressed at about 95%, the
material does not break up to one million cycles.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="4"><tbody><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">Coating state</entry><entry align="center">Cycle number of break</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">No coating</entry><entry align="center">One million cycles</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">98% coverage of TiC</entry><entry align="center">20 thousand cycles</entry></row><row><entry align="right"/><entry align="left">95% coverage of TiC</entry><entry align="center">One million cycles</entry></row><row><entry>HFC test conditions: 500°C, 650 MPa, pull of round rod having a diameter of 5 mm in axial direction at 30 Hz</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0090">When the coverage of the coating is lowered to 95%
or less, the abrasive properties of the whole coating surface 
are slightly sacrificed to increase the ductility. When the
coverage is raised, the ductility decreases, and fatigue
strength drops. However, at 95%, the fatigue strength does
not largely drop, and the abrasive properties little drop.
In one method of lowering the coverage, a discharge time is
reduced, a range in which the discharge does not occur is
left, and the coverage can be reduced. The treatment is
usually performed for a time of five minutes/square
centimeter, but the time may be reduced to about 3.8
minutes/square centimeter.</p><p num="0091">A calculation equation is as follows:
<st32:df xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/" align="center">Time for obtaining a coverage of 95%<st32:break type="required"/>
= time for obtaining a coverage of 98%*LOG(1-0.95)/LOG(1-<st32:break type="required"/>
0.98).</st32:df>
The coverage of 98% is regarded as a coverage of 100%. To
calculate the time from a time for obtaining a coverage of
50%, 0.98 in LOG(1-0.98) is changed to 0.5.</p><p num="0092">In another method, as shown in FIG. 5, with the use
of the electrode to which a metal powder that is not easily
carbonized is added, ductile properties of the metal is
imparted to the coating layer. When the electrode contains
5% or more of a metal that is not easily carbonized, 5% or
more of a portion having the ductility remains, and an effect
similar to that of Table 2 can be expected. Also in this
method, the abrasive properties of the whole coating surface
are slightly sacrificed. Examples of the metal which is not
easily carbonized include cobalt, nickel, and iron. For the 
coverage, one blade has been described. However, there are a
large number of blades. Therefore, even if the coverage is
low, or the abrasive properties are not seen in a certain
portion of a certain blade, the other blades can cover the
properties. This also applies to an annular seal because if
one portion on the circumference of the annular seal has the
abrasive properties, it is possible to obtain the abrasive
properties.</p><p num="0093">Moreover, as still another method, as shown in FIG.
6, a porous layer is formed as a base for the coating layer
of the hard material in order to prevent the crack of the
coating layer from being developed into the mother material.
The porous layer is formed under the coating layer. This
base is also formed by discharge coating. The porous layer
having a thickness of 0.05 mm or more can be formed by using
the electrode obtained by compression molding of a powder of
metals such as Stellite. Thereafter, the porous layer is
coated with the hard material.</p><p num="0094">Moreover, the surface of the coating of the hard
material is peened, the surface is accordingly stretched, a
compression stress is left, and a tensile stress is reduced
even when the mother material is elongated. The fatigue
strength can be enhanced by the effect.</p><p num="0095">FIGS. 7A to 7C, 8A to 8C, 9A and 9B are perspective
views showing fifth to seventh embodiments of the rotating
member of the present invention. It is to be noted that in 
these figures, a platform or a dovetail on a disk side is
omitted.</p><p num="0096">In the turbine blade 1 of FIG. 7A, the corner of the
blade in a rotation advance direction, that is, the blade tip
end of a blade surface on the back side and a tip end surface
are coated with a coating 20 of the hard material.</p><p num="0097">In a thin turbine blade of FIG. 7B, the blade tip
end of a blade surface on the back side and the entire tip
end surface are coated, and the opposite surface may not be
coated.</p><p num="0098">In the turbine blade of FIG. 7C, the blade tip end
of a blade surface on the back side is coated, and the entire
tip end surface is not coated.</p><p num="0099">In the turbine blade 2 with the chip shroud of FIG.
8A, the corner of the tip end of a chip fin 4 in the rotation
advance direction, or the surface of the chip fin 4 in the
rotation advance direction, that is, the backside surface of
the tip end of the chip fin 4 on are coated with a coating 21
of the hard material. It is to be noted that the chip shroud
3 is disposed to prevent resonance of the blades 2 at the
time of a high-speed rotation of the gas turbine and to
prevent a high-temperature gas from leaking to the outside of
the blades 2.</p><p num="0100">In a small blade of FIG. 8B, the entire surface of
the tip end and the surface of the rotation advance direction
(i.e., on the backside surface of the tip end of the chip fin
4) are coated, and the opposite surface may not be coated. </p><p num="0101">In the turbine blade of FIG. 8C, the surface of the
rotation advance direction (i.e., the backside surface of the
tip end) is coated, and the whole surface of the tip end is
not coated.</p><p num="0102">In the compressor blade 1 of FIG. 9A, the corner of
the blade in the rotation advance direction, that is, the
blade tip end of a blade surface on the front side and the
tip end surface are coated with a coating 22 of the hard
material.</p><p num="0103">In the compressor blade of FIG. 9B, the surface of
the rotation advance direction, that is, the blade tip end of
a blade surface on the front side is coated, and the entire
surface of the tip end is not coated.</p><p num="0104">In the blades of FIGS. 9A and 9B, an abrasive
property test was carried out by simulation of an actual
device, a difference was not recognized in the property.</p><p num="0105">As described above, the coating of the hard material
is applied so as to shave the abradable coating by the tip
ends of the blades 1, 2 by taking advantage of the hardness
difference, at the time of driving the blades 1, 2 to keep a
minimum chip clearance. The abradable coating is applied on
the casing or the shroud. Moreover, this phenomenon starts
by the contact between the casing or the shroud and the
corners of the blades 1, 2 in the rotation advance direction,
and ends when the casing or the shroud is shaved. That is,
after the contact of the corner, another portion of the same
blade hardly contacts with the casing or the shroud. In 
consideration of this fact, the coating of the hard material
does not have to be applied over the entire region of the
blade tip end as in the related art. As described in the
present invention, it is sufficient that only the range of
the contact with the abradable coating, that is, only the
corner of the rotation advance direction, or only the surface
of the rotation advance direction is coated with the coatings
20, 21, 22 of the hard material. When the range to be coated
is optimized in this manner, the range to be coated is
narrowed, the yield of products is enhanced, the operation
time can be shortened, the expensive coating material can be
saved, and the cost can be reduced.</p><p num="0106">FIG. 10 is a diagram showing a fifth embodiment of
the coating method according to the present invention, and is
a diagram showing the coating method of the blades shown in
FIGS. 7A to 7C. In the coating method of the present
invention, the blade 1 and a discharge electrode 23 is
submerged in the processing tank 12 filled with the
dielectric liquid (oil), the discharge electrode 23 is
disposed in the vicinity of the corner in the rotation
advance direction of the blade 1, the discharge is caused
between them, and only the corner of the blade 1 in the
rotation advance direction is coated with the coating 20 of
the hard material.</p><p num="0107">The coating 20 of the hard material is formed to
have a very thin thickness of 10 to 20 µm (exaggerated for
ease of seeing in the figure). Therefore, after molding the 
blade 1 as usual, it is sufficient to apply the coating 20 of
the hard material only to a range of contact with the
opposite member, that is, only the corner of the rotation
advance direction or the surface of the rotation advance
direction. Needless to say, the corner of the blade 1 is
shaved by the thickness of the coating 20 of the hard
material by machine processing, and a casting mold in
consideration of the thickness beforehand may be used to mold
the blade 1.</p><p num="0108">Moreover, in a case of a thin blade, the coating of
the hard material may be formed entirely on the rotation
advance direction surface and the tip end surface. However,
the surface disposed opposite to the rotation advance
direction surface does not have to be coated.</p><p num="0109">It is to be noted that only the sections of the
blade 1 and discharge electrode 23 are shown in FIG. 10.</p><p num="0110">In this coating method, the discharge electrode 23
shaped so as to coat only the blade tip end of the blade
surface on the back side and the tip end surface is
preferably used so that only the corner of the blade 1 in the
rotation advance direction can be subjected to the discharge
coating. For example, the discharge electrode 23 has a
substantially L-shaped section, and a shape curved along the
back side of the blade.</p><p num="0111">The electrode may be processed beforehand into a
product shape. However, alternatively, the electrode may be
formed in accordance with the product shape by the discharge 
on the discharge condition on which the electrode is easily
consumed. As this condition, the electrode is set to have a
minus polarity, and the discharge is caused on comparatively
small energy condition on which the pulse width is set to 1
µs or less, and the current value is 10 A or less. Then, the
damage onto the product is suppressed, and the electrode can
accord with the product shape.</p><p num="0112">When the coating film is formed, the electrode is
assumed to have the minus polarity, and the discharge is
caused on comparatively large energy condition on which the
pulse width is about 2 to 10 µs, and the current value is
about 5 to 20 A.</p><p num="0113">It is to be noted that although not shown, with the
turbine blade with the chip shroud 2 shown in FIGS. 8A to 8C,
such an electrode to coat the corner of the chip fin 4 in the
rotation advance direction may be used.</p><p num="0114">In the discharge coating, the discharge is caused on
the surfaces disposed opposite to each other by application
of a voltage between the blade 1 and the discharge electrode
23 submerged in the dielectric liquid, the surface of the
discharge electrode 23 is molten by the discharge, and the
molten element is attached on the surface of the blade 1 to
form the alloy on the surface. A solidified coating material
is used for the discharge electrode 23.</p><p num="0115">Since the thickness of the coating can be controlled
by the degree of several micrometers, the discharge coating
is a coating method optimum for the precision components such 
as the blade 1. Moreover, a place where the discharge does
not occur is not coated. Therefore, since the portion to be
coated can locally be coated, the pretreatments such as the
masking are unnecessary. Since heat generation is small, the
blade is not thermally deformed, and the post-treatment is
also unnecessary.</p><p num="0116">As described above, in the present invention, since
the coating range of the hard material is optimized, the
yield of products can be enhanced. Since the operation time
can be shortened, and the coating material can be saved, the
cost can be reduced. Furthermore, since the so-called
discharge coating is used, only the corner of the rotation
advance direction of the blade or the surface of the rotation
advance direction can easily and inexpensively can be coated
with the hard material.</p><p num="0117">Moreover, even when all the blades assembled onto a
rotor are not coated with the hard material, some of the
blades are coated with the hard material, and it is then
possible to obtain the effect. This also applies to the
annular seal, as long as one or more portions on the
circumference may have the abrasive properties.</p><p num="0118">FIG. 11 is a schematic diagram of a labyrinth seal
structure according to an eighth embodiment of the rotating
member of the present invention, and FIG. 12 is a front view
of a labyrinth seal of FIG. 11. FIG. 13 is a schematic 
diagram of a discharge processing machine according to the
eighth embodiment of the coating method according to the
present invention.</p><p num="0119">As shown in FIGS. 11 and 12, a labyrinth seal
structure 31 according to the embodiment of the present
invention is used in the gas turbine of a jet engine, and
inhibits a leak of a combustion gas between an engine
stationary component 33 and an engine rotating component 35.
The labyrinth seal structure 31 includes, as constituting
elements, a honeycomb-shaped stationary-side honeycomb seal
component 37 integrally disposed on the engine stationary
component 33, and a rotating labyrinth seal component 39
disposed inside the stationary-side honeycomb seal component
37 and capable of rotating integrally with the engine
rotating component 35. It is to be noted that a stationary-side
abradable seal component whose inside is coated with the
abradable coat may also be used instead of the stationary-side
honeycomb seal component 37.</p><p num="0120">A concrete constitution of the rotating labyrinth
seal component 39 which is an important part of the
embodiment of the present invention is as follows.</p><p num="0121">That is, an annular seal component main body 41
which is a main body of the rotating labyrinth seal component
39 is integrally disposed on the engine rotating component 35,
and a plurality of annular seal fins 43 are integrally formed
on the outer peripheral surface of the seal component main
body 41. Tip edges of the respective seal fins 43 are coated 
with coats 45 of the hard material. Furthermore, for each
coat 45 of the hard material, an electrode 47 for coating
having consumability (see FIG. 13) is used, and a pulsed
discharge is caused between the electrode 47 for coating and
the tip edge of the seal fin 43. The constituting material
of the electrode 47 for coating or the reactant of the
constituting material forms into the coating film containing
the hard material on a plurality of treated portions in the
tip edges of the seal fins 43 by the discharge energy, and
accordingly a plurality of (four in the embodiment of the
present invention) local coats 45a of the hard material are
applied at equal intervals.</p><p num="0122">Here, in the embodiment of the present invention, in
general, "the electrode for coating having the consumability"
means a green compact electrode (including a thermally
treated green compact electrode) obtained by compression
molding of a powdered metal (including a metal compound), a
mixed material of the powdered metal and a powdered ceramic,
or the powdered ceramic having conductivity. "The electrode
for coating having the consumability" may also mean a silicon
electrode formed of solid silicon. It is to be noted that
the ceramic having conductivity is subjected to the surface
treatment for forming a conductive coating film on the
ceramic powder, and molded by compression, so that the
conductivity is secured. Especially, examples of the
"powdered metal" include Ti, Co, and the like, and the
examples of the "powdered ceramic" include cBN, TiC, TiN, 
TiAlN, AlN, TiB<sub>2</sub>, WC, Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub>, SiC, ZrC, VC, B<sub>4</sub>C, Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>, ZrO<sub>2</sub>-Y,
Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, and the like.</p><p num="0123">The examples of the material which reacts by the
discharge energy to form the coating film containing the hard
material include Ti, W, Cr, Zr, Si, V, Mo, Nb.</p><p num="0124">Furthermore, the electrode 47 for coating has a
shape approximate to that of the portion to be treated in the
tip edges of the seal fins 43.</p><p num="0125">Next, a concrete constitution of a discharge
processing machine 49 for use in coating the coat 45 of the
hard material, and a coating method for coating the coat 45
of the hard material will be described with reference to FIG.
13.</p><p num="0126">That is, in the discharge processing machine 49
according to the embodiment of the present invention, a bed
51 is used as a processing machine base, and a table 53 is
disposed on the bed 51. The table 53 can be moved in X-axis
directions (left and right directions in FIG. 13) by driving
an X-axis servo motor (not shown), and can be moved in Y-axis
directions (front and back directions of a sheet surface of
FIG. 13) by driving a Y-axis servo motor (not shown).</p><p num="0127">A processing tank 55 in which dielectric liquid L
such as dielectric oil is disposed on the table 53, and a
support plate 57 is disposed in the processing tank 55. A
support tool 59 to which the seal component main body 41 is
fixed is disposed on the support plate 57.</p><p num="0128">A processing head 61 is disposed via a column (not 
shown) above the bed 51 (above in FIG. 13), and this
processing head 61 can move in Z-axis directions (upward and
downward directions in FIG. 13) by driving a Z-axis servo
motor. Moreover, an electrode hold member 63 for holding the
electrode 47 for coating is disposed on the processing head
61.</p><p num="0129">It is to be noted that the electrode hold member 63
and the support tool 59 are electrically connected to a power
supply 65.</p><p num="0130">Therefore, the seal component main body 41 is fixed
by the support tool 59 in a state in which a portion of the
tip edge of the seal fin 43 to be treated in the peripheral
direction is directed right upwards in the processing tank 55.
Next, the table 53 is moved in the X-axis and Y-axis
directions (at least either one direction) by driving the X-axis
and Y-axis servo motors. Thereby, the position of the
seal fin 43 is determined such that the portion of the tip
end of the seal fin 43 to be treated faces the electrode 47
for coating.</p><p num="0131">Moreover, the electrode 47 for coating is moved
integrally with the processing head 61 in the Z-axis
direction by driving the Z-axis servo motor, while a pulsed
voltage is generated between the electrode 47 for coating and
the portion of the tip end of the tip fin 43 to be treated in
the dielectric liquid L. Accordingly, the electrode material
of the electrode 47 for coating is locally diffused in and/or
welded to the portion of the tip edge of the seal fin 43 to 
be treated by the discharge energy, and the portion of the
tip edge of one seal fin 43 to be treated can locally be
coated with a local coat 45a of the hard material.</p><p num="0132">Furthermore, when the table 53 is moved in the Y-axis
directions by driving the Y-axis servo motor, the
position of another seal fin 43 is determined such that the
portion of the tip fin of the seal fin 43 to be treated faces
the electrode 47 for coating. Then, as described above, the
electrode material of the electrode for coating 47 is locally
diffused in and/or welded to the portion of the tip edge of
this seal fin 43 to be treated by the discharge energy, and
the portion of the tip edge of the seal fin 43 to be treated
is locally coated with the local coat 45a of the hard
material.</p><p num="0133">After locally coating the portion of the tip edge of
a plurality of the seal fins 43 to be treated with the local
coat 45a of the hard material, the similar operation is
repeated. Thereby, also the other portions of the tip edges
of a plurality of the seal fins 43 to be treated are also
locally coated with the local coats 45a of the hard material.</p><p num="0134">Next, the function of the embodiment of the present
invention will be described.</p><p num="0135">The rotating labyrinth seal component 39 includes
the coat 45 of the hard material. Therefore, to integrally
rotate the rotating labyrinth seal component 39 and the
engine rotating component 35, even when the engine stationary
component is deformed and the rotating labyrinth seal 
component 39 contacts with the stationary-side honeycomb seal
component 37, the stationary-side honeycomb seal component 37
is only shaved by the coat 45 of the hard material in the
rotating labyrinth seal component 39. The rotating labyrinth
seal component 39 is substantially hardly shaved.</p><p num="0136">Accordingly, the clearance between the stationary-side
honeycomb seal component 37 and the rotating labyrinth
seal component 39 is inhibited from increasing during the
rotation of the engine rotating component 35, and the seal
effect of the labyrinth seal structure 31 can be kept in an
appropriate state. The rotating labyrinth seal component 39
is set beforehand so as to slightly contact with the
stationary-side honeycomb seal component 37 at the time of
the initial rotation of the engine rotating component 35.
Accordingly, the clearance between the stationary-side
honeycomb seal component 37 and the rotating labyrinth seal
component 39 can be set to be as small as possible during and
after the initial rotation, and the seal effect of the
labyrinth seal structure 31 can further be enhanced.</p><p num="0137">Moreover, coating of the coats 45 of the hard
material is performed on the portions of the tip edges of the
seal fins 43 by diffusing and/or welding of the electrode
material of the electrode 47 for coating by the discharge
energy generated between the electrode for coating 47 and the
portion of the tip edge of the seal fin 43 without performing
the plating or thermal spraying. Therefore, in the
production of the rotating labyrinth seal component 39, the 
coating post-treatments such as the blast treatment and the
process of removing the masking tape are unnecessary.</p><p num="0138">Furthermore, the boundary portion between the coat
45 of the hard material formed by the discharge energy and
the mother body of the seal fin 43 has alloy composition
changing properties, and the coat of the hard material can
firmly be connected to the tip edge of the seal fin 43.</p><p num="0139">Moreover, the coat 45 of the hard material includes
a plurality of local coats 45a of the hard material. In
other words, the electrode material 47 of the electrode for
coating is locally diffused in and/or welded to a plurality
of portions to be treated of the peripheral direction in the
tip edge of the seal fin 43, not in the whole periphery of
the tip edge of the seal fin 43. Therefore, the electrode 47
for coating can be formed to have a small and simple shape in
accordance with the size and/or the shape of the portion of
the tip edge of the seal fin 43 to be treated. Accordingly,
the amount of the electrode material used to form the
electrode 47 for coating can be reduced.</p><p num="0140">It is to be noted that as described above, the coat
45 of the hard material (local coat 45a of the hard material)
can firmly be connected to the tip edge of the seal fin 43.
Therefore, even when the entire tip edge periphery of the
seal fin 43 is not coated with the coat 45 of the hard
material, the sufficient abrasive properties of the entire
rotating labyrinth seal component 39 can be achieved by a
plurality of local coats 45a of the hard material. </p><p num="0141">As described above, according to the embodiment of
the present invention, in the production of the rotating
labyrinth seal component 39, the coating pretreatments such
as the blast process and the process of attaching the masking
tape, and the coating post-treatments such as the process of
removing the masking tape are not required. Therefore, the
operation time required for the production of the rotating
labyrinth seal component 39 is reduced, and it is easy to
enhance the productivity of the rotating labyrinth seal
components 39.</p><p num="0142">Moreover, since the coat 45 of the hard material can
firmly be connected to the tip edge of the seal fin 43, the
coat 45 of the hard material does not easily peel off from
the tip edge of the seal fin 43, and the quality level of the
rotating labyrinth seal component 39 is stabilized.</p><p num="0143">Furthermore, the entire rotating labyrinth seal
component 39 has sufficient abrasive properties, and the
electrode 47 for coating can be formed to have the small and
simple shape in accordance with the size/shape of the portion
to be treated of the tip edge in the seal fin 43. Moreover,
the amount of the electrode material used to form the
electrode for coating 47 can be reduced. Therefore, the
production cost of the rotating labyrinth seal component 39
can be reduced.</p><p num="0144">It is to be noted that the present invention is not
limited to the description of the embodiment of the present
invention. For example, instead of the discharge in the 
dielectric liquid L, the discharge in the electrically
insulating gas can be performed. Thus, various modifications
can be carried out.</p><p num="0145">As described above, according to the present
invention, in the production of the rotating labyrinth seal
component, the coating pretreatments such as the blast
process and the process of attaching the masking tape, and
the coating post-treatments such as the process of removing
the masking tape are not required. Therefore, the operation
time required for the production of the rotating labyrinth
seal component is reduced, and it is easy to enhance the
productivity of the rotating labyrinth seal components.</p><p num="0146">Moreover, since the coat of the hard material can
firmly be connected to the tip edge of the seal fin, the coat
of the hard material does not easily peel off from the tip
edge of the seal fin, and the quality level of the labyrinth
seal is stabilized.</p><p num="0147">Furthermore, in addition to the above-described
effect, the entire rotating labyrinth seal component has
sufficient abrasive properties, and the electrode for coating
can be formed to have the small and simple shape in
accordance with the size/shape of the portion to be treated
of the tip edge in the seal fin. Moreover, the amount of the
electrode material used to form the electrode for coating can
be reduced. Therefore, the production cost of the rotating
labyrinth seal component can be reduced.</p><p num="0148">It is to be noted that some preferable embodiments 
of the present invention have been described, but it would be
understood that the scope of the present invention is not
limited to these embodiments. Conversely, the scope of the
present invention includes all improvements, modifications,
and equivalents included in the appended claims.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A method for coating a rotating member,
comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>generating a pulsed discharge between a rotating
member formed into a predetermined shape and a discharge
electrode of a green compact in dielectric liquid or gas to
transfer a hard material of the discharge electrode or a hard
material changed from a material of the discharge electrode
onto the rotating member by each discharge pulse so that a
hard concavity and convexity is formed on the rotating member,
wherein the green compact includes the hard material or the
material changing into the hard material by the discharge;
and</claim-text><claim-text>repeatedly generating the discharge pulse to form on
the rotating member a hard coating film having the concavity
and convexity.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The method for coating the rotating member
according to claim 1, wherein the hard coating film is an
abrasive coating film that is formed on a part of the
rotating member and rubs against and shaves an opponent
component.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The method for coating the rotating member
according to claim 1 or 2, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>generating discharge between the rotating member and
the discharge electrode on a first discharge condition on
which the discharge electrode is consumed so that a shape of
the discharge electrode is made to conform to a shape of a
coating film forming portion on the rotating member; and</claim-text><claim-text>thereafter generating discharge between the
discharge electrode and the rotating member on a second
discharge condition to form the coating film on the rotating
member.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The method for coating the rotating member
according to claim 3, wherein on the first discharge
condition, the discharge electrode has a minus polarity, a
pulse width is 1 µs or less, and a current value is 10 A or
less, and
   on the second discharge condition, the discharge
electrode has a minus polarity, the pulse width is 2 to 10 µs,
and a current value is 5 to 20 A.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The method for coating the rotating member
according to any one of claims 1 to 4, wherein for the
coating film, a coverage which is a ratio of a coated area in
a coating film forming portion is 95% or less.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The method for coating the rotating member
according to any one of claims 1 to 4, wherein the coating
film is formed by using the discharge electrode that contains
5% or more by volume of a metal which does not easily react
into carbide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The method for coating the rotating member
according to any one of claims 1 to 4, wherein at the time of
forming the coating film, a porous coating film is formed as
a base, and then, the coating film including the hard
material is formed on the porous coating film.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>The method for coating the rotating member
according to any one of claims 1 to 7, wherein the coating
film is formed by using the discharge electrode of the green
compact including one of or a mixture of cBN, TiC, TiN, TiAlN,
TiB2, WC, Cr3C2, SiC, ZrC, VC, B4C, Si3N4, ZrO2-Y, and Al2O3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method for coating the rotating member
according to any one of claims 1 to 8, further comprising the
step of peening the coating film.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>A rotating member having an abrasive coating
film on a part thereof that is formed by a pulsed discharge
between the rotating member and a discharge electrode of a
green compact or solid silicon in dielectric liquid or gas,
   wherein the green compact includes a hard material
or a material that changes into a hard material by the
discharge, and
   the abrasive coating film includes the hard material
of the green compact or the hard material that is changed
from the material of the green compact or solid silicon by
the discharge.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>The rotating member according to claim 10,
wherein a coverage of coating is 95% or less in a coating
film forming portion.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The rotating member according to claim 10,
wherein the discharge electrode of the green compact includes
the hard material or the material that changes into the hard
material by the discharge and includes 5% or more by volume
of a metal which does not easily react into carbide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>The rotating member according to claim 10,
wherein the coating film includes:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first porous layer that is formed on the part of
the rotating member by a pulsed discharge between the
rotating member and a discharge electrode of a green compact
or solid silicon in dielectric liquid or gas, wherein the
first porous layer includes a hard material of the green
compact or a hard material that is changed from a material of
the green compact or solid silicon by the discharge; and</claim-text><claim-text>a second layer that is formed on the first porous
layer by a pulsed discharge between the first porous layer
and a discharge electrode of a green compact or solid silicon
in dielectric liquid or gas, wherein the second layer
includes a hard material of the green compact or a hard
material that is changed from a material of the green compact
or solid silicon by the discharge.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>The rotating member according to any one of
claims 10 to 13, wherein the coating film includes a peened
layer that is formed by penning the formed coating film.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>The rotating member according to any one of
claims 10 to 14, wherein the discharge electrode includes the
green compact, the thermally treated green compact or solid
silicon,
   the green compact is obtained by compression molding
of a powdered metal, a powder of a compound of the metal, a
powder of a ceramic or a mixture thereof, and
   the ceramic is one of or a mixture of cBN, Cr3C2, TiC,
TiN, TiAlN, TiB2, ZrO2-Y, ZrC, VC, B4C, WC, SiC, Si3N4, and
Al2O3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>The rotating member according to any one of
claims 10 to 15, wherein the coating film is formed on the
part on the rotating member that faces or contacts with an
opponent component.</claim-text></claim><claim num="17"><claim-text>The rotating member according to any one of
claims 10 to 16, wherein the coating film is formed on a
portion of the part on the rotating member that faces or
contacts with an opponent component.</claim-text></claim><claim num="18"><claim-text>The rotating member according to any one of
claims 10 to 17, comprising a rotating member body and a
casing component that covers the rotating member body,
   wherein the coating film having hard concavity and
convexity is formed on a part of the rotating member body by
repeatedly generating discharge pulse between the rotating
member body and the discharge electrode to transfer the hard
material of the discharge electrode or the hard material
changed from the material of the discharge electrode onto the
part of the rotating member body, and
   the casing component is made of a material of which
hardness is smaller than that of the hard material of the
coating film.</claim-text></claim><claim num="19"><claim-text>The rotating member according to any one of
claims 10 to 15, wherein the rotating member is a blade, the
blade and a discharge electrode are submerged in dielectric
liquid or gas to dispose the discharge electrode in the
vicinity of a corner of a blade tip end in a rotation advance
direction and/or the vicinity of a surface of the blade tip
end in the rotation advance direction and/or the vicinity of
the blade tip end surface, the discharge is generated between
the blade and the discharge electrode so that the coating
including the hard material is formed on the corner of the
blade tip end in the rotation advance direction, or the
adjacent surface to the blade tip in the rotation advance
direction, or the end surface of the blade tip, or both of
the adjacent surface to the blade tip in the rotation advance
direction and the end surface of the blade tip.</claim-text></claim><claim num="20"><claim-text>The rotating member according to any one of
claims 10 to 16, wherein the abrasive coating film including
the hard material is formed on not all, but some of blades of
a rotor or a blisk.</claim-text></claim><claim num="21"><claim-text>The rotating member according to any one of
claims 10 to 15, wherein the rotating member is a rotating
labyrinth seal component which is one of structure elements
of a labyrinth seal structure to suppress a leak of a gas or
liquid between a stationary component and a rotating
component,
   the rotating member comprises:
<claim-text><claim-text>an annular seal component main body; and</claim-text><claim-text>an annular seal fin integrally formed on an outer
peripheral surface of the seal component main body,</claim-text><claim-text>a tip edge of the seal fin is coated with the
abrasive coating film including the hard material,</claim-text><claim-text>the discharge electrode having consumability is used,
a pulsed discharge is generated between the discharge
electrode and the tip edge of the seal fin in dielectric
liquid or gas so that the abrasive coating film is formed to
include the hard material of the discharge electrode or the
hard material changed from the material of the discharge
electrode by the discharge.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="22"><claim-text>The rotating member according to claim 21,
wherein the abrasive coating film including the hard material
comprises a plurality of local coating films locally formed
on a plurality of portions in a peripheral direction in the
tip edge of the seal fin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="23"><claim-text>A labyrinth seal structure which suppresses a
leakage of a gas or liquid between a stationary component and
a rotating component, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a stationary-side seal component integrally disposed
on the stationary component;</claim-text><claim-text>an annular seal component main body which is
disposed inside the stationary-side seal component and which
is capable of rotating integrally with the rotating component
and which is integrally disposed on the rotating component;</claim-text><claim-text>an annular seal fin integrally formed on an outer
peripheral surface of the seal component main body; and</claim-text><claim-text>a hard coat formed on the tip edge of the seal fin,</claim-text><claim-text>wherein the hard coat is a coating film including a
hard material constituted of a constituting material or a
reactant of the constituting material of an electrode for
coating formed on the tip edge of the seal fin by a discharge
energy of a pulsed discharge between the electrode for
coating and the tip edge of the seal fin, and the electrode
for coating has consumability.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="24"><claim-text>The labyrinth seal structure according to claim
23, wherein the coat including the hard material comprises a
plurality of local coating films locally formed on a
plurality of portions in a peripheral direction in the tip
edge of the seal fin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="25"><claim-text>A method for manufacturing a rotating member of
a blade or a labyrinth member, comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>a first step of forming a forging material or a
casting material into a predetermined shape by mechanical
processing; and</claim-text><claim-text>a second step of generating a pulsed discharge
between a rotating member formed into a predetermined shape
and a discharge electrode of a green compact or solid silicon
in dielectric liquid or gas to transfer a hard material of
the discharge electrode or the hard material changed from a
material of the discharge electrode onto the rotating member
by each discharge pulse so that a hard concavity and
convexity is formed on the rotating member, wherein the green
compact includes the hard material or the material changing
into the hard material by the discharge, and repeatedly
generating the discharge pulse to form on the rotating member
a hard coating film having the concavity and convexity.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="26"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing the rotating
member according to claim 25, wherein in the second step, an
abrasive coating film that rubs against and shaves an
opponent component is formed as the hard coating film on a
part of the rotating member.</claim-text></claim><claim num="27"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing the rotating
member according to claim 25 or 26, wherein the second step
comprises the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>generating discharge between the rotating member and
the discharge electrode on a first discharge condition on
which the discharge electrode is consumed so that a shape of
the discharge electrode is made to conform to a shape of a
coating film forming portion on the rotating member; and</claim-text><claim-text>thereafter generating discharge between the
discharge electrode and the rotating member on a second
discharge condition to form the coating film on the rotating
member.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="28"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing the rotating
member according to claim 27, wherein on the first discharge
condition, the discharge electrode has a minus polarity, a
pulse width is 1 µs or less, and a current value is 10 A or
less, and
   on the second discharge condition, the discharge
electrode has a minus polarity, the pulse width is 2 to 10 µs,
and a current value is 5 to 20 A.</claim-text></claim><claim num="29"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing the rotating
member according to any one of claims 25 to 28, wherein
during the forming of the coating film in the second step, a
discharge condition is controlled to set a coverage to be 95%
or less in the coating film forming portion, the coverage
being a ratio of an area at which the coating film including
the hard material is formed.</claim-text></claim><claim num="30"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing the rotating
member according to claim 29, wherein the ratio of the
coverage is controlled by reducing a discharge treatment time
to 76% or less of a discharge treatment time for a coverage
of 100%.</claim-text></claim><claim num="31"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing the rotating
member according to any one of claims 25 to 28, wherein in
the second step, the green compact electrode containing 5% or
more by volume of a metal which does not easily change into
carbide is used to perform the discharge.</claim-text></claim><claim num="32"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing the rotating
member according to any one of claims 25 to 28, wherein the
second step comprises the steps of: forming a porous coating
film on a coating film forming portion of the rotating
member; and thereafter forming the coating film including the
hard material on the porous coating film.</claim-text></claim><claim num="33"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing the rotating
member according to any one of claims 25 to 29, wherein the
discharge electrode of the green compact used in the second
step is a green compact discharge electrode formed by
compression molding of one of or a mixture of cBN, TiC, TiN,
TiAlN, TiB2, WC, Cr3C2, SiC, ZrC, VC, B4C, Si3N4, ZrO2-Y, and
Al2O3.</claim-text></claim><claim num="34"><claim-text>The method for manufacturing the rotating
member according to any one of claims 25 to 33, further
comprising: a third step of subjecting the coating film
formed in the second step to a peening treatment.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>