<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1132412-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1132412" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="18590905" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20010912"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1132412-A1" status="new" fvid="23245220"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1132412</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20010912</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-01400618-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>01400618</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20010309</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2000072514-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2000072514</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20000310</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A01N  59/00        20060101ALI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A01N  59/00        20060101CLI20060101BMKR        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A01N  59/16        20060101AFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A01N  59/16        20060101CFI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A01N  59/20        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A01N  61/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">A01N  61/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   8/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   8/36        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F   8/44        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 212/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 212/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 220/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 220/44        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 236/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08F 236/04        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08K   3/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  25/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  25/08        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  33/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  33/20        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  47/00        20060101ALI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C08L  47/00        20060101CLI20051220RMJP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C08F   8/44</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Antimikrobielles Mittel und Verfahren zur Herstellung davon</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Antimicrobial agent and production process thereof</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Agent antimicrobien ainsi que son procédé de fabrication</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0220612-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0220612</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0286243-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0286243</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0575882-A2" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0575882</doc-number><kind>A2</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-0641805-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0641805</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="FR-2033922-A5" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>FR</country><doc-number>2033922</doc-number><kind>A5</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="GB-2300368-A"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>GB</country><doc-number>2300368</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-3553160-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>3553160</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4143203-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4143203</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-4604420-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>4604420</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-1999051651-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>1999051651</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="Y" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Section Ch, Week 9406 Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB; Class A82, AN 1994-045581 XP002170248 &amp; JP 06 001932 A (MITSUBISHI HEAVY IND. CO., LTD.), 11 January 1994 (1994-01-11)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>SONY CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>SONY CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>SONY CORPORATION</last-name><address><street>7-35, Kitashinagawa 6-chome Shinagawa-ku</street><city>Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>HARUO WATANABE</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>TSUTOMU NOGUCHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YASUHITO INAGAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>HARUO, WATANABE</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>TSUTOMU, NOGUCHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YASUHITO, INAGAKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>HARUO, WATANABE</last-name><address><street>c/o Sony Corporation, 7-35, Kitashinagawa 6-chome</street><city>Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook> </inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>TSUTOMU, NOGUCHI</last-name><address><street>c/o Sony Corporation, 7-35, Kitashinagawa 6-chome</street><city>Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country> </address> </addressbook> </inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>YASUHITO, INAGAKI</last-name><address><street>c/o Sony Corporation, 7-35, Kitashinagawa 6-chome</street><city>Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Gillard, Marie-Louise</last-name><address><street>Cabinet Beau de Loménie 158, rue de l'Université</street><city>75340 Paris Cédex 07</city><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An antimicrobial agent utilizes a resin having acrylonitrile and styrene
and/or a conjugated diene as units. The antimicrobial agent includes a metal salt-containing
copolymer, and the metal salt-containing copolymer is obtained by
treating a copolymer containing acrylonitrile and at least one of styrene and a
conjugated diene as units with an acid to thereby introduce acid radicals into the
copolymer, and converting at least part of the acid radicals into a metal salt, in
particular a salt of at least one metal selected from among Ag, Cu, and Zn.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading><heading>1. Field of the Invention</heading><p num="0001">The present invention relates to a novel antimicrobial agent which is
prepared by using a copolymer derived from, for example, a spent resin, and to a
production process of the antimicrobial agent.</p><heading>2. Description of the Related Art</heading><p num="0002">Antimicrobial agents for suppressing the growth of bacteria and/or fungi
include inorganic antimicrobial agents, organic antimicrobial agents extracted
from natural products, organic antimicrobial agents composed of aliphatic
compounds, and organic antimicrobial agents composed of aromatic compounds.</p><p num="0003">Such inorganic antimicrobial agents include, for example, sodium
hypochlorite, and other chlorine compounds; hydrogen peroxide, and other
peroxides; boric acid, sodium borate, and other borate compounds; copper sulfate,
and other copper compounds; zinc sulfate, zinc chloride, and other zinc
compounds; sulfur, calcium polysulfate, sulfur hydrate, and other sulfur
substances; calcium oxide, and other calcium compounds; silver thiosulfite
complex, silver nitrate, and other silver compounds; as well as iodine and sodium
silicofluoride.</p><p num="0004">The organic antimicrobial agents extracted from natural products include,
but are not limited to, hinokitiol, Phyllostachys pubescens extract, and creosote
oil.</p><p num="0005">The organic antimicrobial agents composed of aliphatic compounds
include, but are not limited to, tributyltin oxide, and other organotin compounds;
copper naphthenate, and other cyclopentane derivatives; methyl bromide, and
other halides; ethyl alcohol, isopropyl alcohol, and other monohydric alcohols; 2-bromo-2-nitro-1,3-propanediol,
and other dihydric alcohols; formaldehyde,
glutaraldehyde, and other saturated aldehydes; sorbic acid, potassium sorbate, and
other carboxylate compounds; ethylene oxide, propylene oxide, and other ether
compounds; beta-oxypropiolactone, and other lactone compounds; 3-trimethoxysilylpropyldimethyloctadecylammonium
chloride, and other quaternary 
ammonium salt compounds; di(octylaminoethyl)glycine hydrochloride, and other
amino acid derivatives; sodium lauryl sulfate, and other sulfonic acid compounds;
bisdequalinium acetate, and other hydroxamic acid compounds; isocyanuric
chloride, and other cyanuric acid compounds; methyl isocyanate, and other cyanic
acid compounds; bis(trichloromethyl)sulfone, and other sulfone compounds;
polyhexamethylenebiguanidine hydrochloride, and other guanidine compounds;
1,3-dichloro-5,5-dimethylhydantoin, and other hydantoin compounds; 5-oxy-3,4-dichloro-1,2-dithiol,
and other dithiol compounds; iron methylarsinate, and other
arsine compounds; tris(ethylphosphate)aluminium, and other phosphate
compounds; and thiocarbamide compounds.</p><p num="0006">The organic antimicrobial agents composed of aromatic compounds
include, but are not limited to, bis(4-nitrophenyl)carbonate, and other carbonate
compounds; benzalkonium chloride, benzethonium chloride, and other quaternary
ammonium salt compounds; 2,6-dichloro-4-nitroaniline, and other monoamine
compounds; potassium nitroethylbenzylethylenediamine, and other diamine
compounds; aluminium N-nitroso-N-cyclohexylhydroxylamine, and other
hydroxylamine compounds; dihydromethyloxathiinecarboxanilide dioxide, and
other anilide compounds; 2-(4-thiazolyl)benzimidazole, and other imidazole
compounds; 5-methyl-1,2,4-triazol-3,4-benzothiazole, and other benzothiazole
compounds; 2,4-dichloro-6-chloroanilino-1,3,5-triazine, and other triazine
compounds; chlorhexidine hydrochloride, chlorhexidine gluconate, and other
guanidine compounds; cetylpyridinium chloride, and other pyridine compounds;
dimethylpyrazolylhydroxyphenylpyrimidine, and other pyrimidine compounds;
2,2'-methylenebis-3,4,6-trichlorophenol, and other halogenobenzene compounds;
copper hydroxynonylbenzenesulfonate, and other benzenesulfonate compounds;
benzoic acid, and other benzenecarboxylic acid compounds; thimerosal, and other
mercaptocarboxylic acid compounds; ethyl hydroxybenzoate, and other
hydroxycarboxylic acid compounds; phenol, cresol, and other monohydric phenol
compounds; resorcinol, and other dihydric phenol compounds; phenoxyethanol,
and other phenoxy ether compounds; pentachlorophenyl laurate, and other phenol
ester compounds; triphenyltin oxide, and other phenyl compounds; diphenyl, and
other biphenyl compounds; beta-naphthol, and other monohydric naphthols; 
monochloronaphthalene, and other naphthalene compounds;
dodecylisoquinolinium bromide, and other isoquinoline compounds; as well as
nitrile compounds, isothiazole compounds, thiadiazole compounds,
halogenophenol compounds, pyrrole compounds, quinone compounds, quinoline
compounds, and organic phosphoric ester compounds.</p><p num="0007">However, there has been no antimicrobial agent using an ABS resin, or
another resin, whereas the above types of antimicrobial agents are typically used.
Resins each containing acrylonitrile and styrene and/or a conjugated diene are
classified as polystyrenic resins such as ABS resins, SAN resins, and ASA resins,
and as synthetic rubbers such as NBR rubbers. These resins are relatively low in
cost. Particularly, the former polystyrenic resins are excellent in rigidity,
dimensional stability, workability, and other properties and are widely used as
materials for covers and casings for various applications, housings, and other parts
of electric equipment and automobiles, and as other resinous materials. The latter
synthetic rubbers are widely used as tubes, hoses, and various cushioning
materials.</p><p num="0008">Under these circumstances, these materials are expected to be used in
further broader applications and demands are made to improve these materials to
those having higher added values. In other words, these materials are now used in
the aforementioned applications alone and are not used as antimicrobial agents.</p><p num="0009">Additionally, products obtained by using the above resins yield a large
quantity of spent resins as discarded materials with an increasing production. The
amount of discarded materials composed of these materials tends to increase in
recent years, and there are increasing demands to make effective use of such
discarded materials from the viewpoint of global environmental conservation.</p><heading>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading><p num="0010">Accordingly, it is a first object of the present invention to provide a novel
antimicrobial agent using a resin containing acrylonitrile and styrene and/or a
conjugated diene as units and to provide a production process thereof.</p><p num="0011">An antimicrobial agent according to the present invention includes a metal
salt-containing copolymer, the metal salt-containing copolymer being obtained by 
treating a copolymer with an acid to thereby introduce acid radicals into the
copolymer, which copolymer includes acrylonitrile and at least one of styrene and
a conjugated diene as units, and converting at least part of the acid radicals into a
metal salt. In the copolymer, at least part of the acid radicals are preferably
converted into a salt of at least one metal selected from Ag, Cu, and Zn.</p><p num="0012">The invention antimicrobial agent having the above configuration includes
a metal salt as at least part of acid radicals introduced into a copolymer and is
rendered antimicrobial. In other words, the present invention can impart
antimicrobial property to the resulting copolymer by the introduction of a metal
salt into the copolymer and can provide a novel antimicrobial agent.</p><p num="0013">A second object of the present invention is to make effective use of
resources by reusing spent resins. Specifically, the invention antimicrobial agent
may include the copolymer composed of a spent resin.</p><p num="0014">In a third aspect, the present invention provides a process for producing an
antimicrobial agent. The process includes the steps of treating a copolymer
containing acrylonitrile and at least one of styrene and a conjugated diene as units
with an acid to thereby introduce acid radicals into the copolymer; and converting
at least part of the acid radicals into a metal salt, in particular a salt of at least one
metal selected from among Ag, Cu, and Zn.</p><p num="0015">The invention process for producing an antimicrobial agent having the
above configuration can impart antimicrobial property to the copolymer by
subjecting the copolymer to an acid treatment step and then to a conversion step
into a metal salt (hereinafter briefly referred to as "conversion step").</p><p num="0016">The invention process for producing an antimicrobial agent as the third
object of the invention may prepare the copolymer using a spent resin. In this
embodiment, the present invention can make effective use of resources by reusing
spent resins.</p><heading>DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading><p num="0017">The present invention will now be illustrated in further detail with
reference to embodiments of the invention antimicrobial agents and production
process thereof. </p><p num="0018">The antimicrobial agent according to the present invention is composed of
a copolymer containing acrylonitrile and styrene and/or a conjugated diene (e.g.,
butadiene or isoprene) as units. Specifically, the copolymer in the antimicrobial
agent comprises acrylonitrile and styrene as units, comprises acrylonitrile and a
conjugated diene as units, or comprises acrylonitrile, styrene and a conjugated
diene as units.</p><p num="0019">In the production of the antimicrobial agent, the copolymer is initially
subjected to an acid treatment step in which the copolymer is treated with an acid
to thereby introduce acid radicals into the copolymer. The acid radicals are
introduced into the styrene and/or conjugated diene moiety of the copolymer.
Additionally, the acrylonitrile moiety of the copolymer is hydrolyzed in the acid
treatment step. The acrylonitrile moiety is amidated through hydrolysis to thereby
impart hydrophilicity to the copolymer.</p><p num="0020">Subsequent to the acid treatment step, the copolymer having introduced
acid radicals and being hydrolyzed is subjected to the conversion step to thereby
convert part or overall of the acid radicals into a metal salt, in particular a salt of a
metal selected from among Ag, Cu, and Zn. The copolymer is converted into a
metal salt-containing copolymer having antimicrobial property by the introduction
of a metal salt through the conversion step. The metal salt-containing copolymer
after the conversion step is in a gel state and is subjected to a drying step to
thereby yield an antimicrobial agent. Such drying operations include, for
example, solar drying, baking, drying under reduced pressure, centrifugal drying,
and press drying.</p><p num="0021">The antimicrobial agent preferably comprises the units, acrylonitrile and
styrene and/or a conjugated diene, in a predetermined proportion from the
viewpoints of antimicrobial activities and easiness to handle. Specifically, the
copolymer comprises the acrylonitrile unit in a proportion of preferably 5 to 80%
by mole, more preferably 10 to 60% by mole, and most preferably 20 to 50% by
mole.</p><p num="0022">If the content of acrylonitrile is less than 5% by mole, the copolymer after
acid treatment step may become soluble in water and such a water-soluble
copolymer is difficult to handle in subsequent steps. In contrast, if the 
acrylonitrile content exceeds 80% by mole, the resulting copolymer may become
rigid and cannot be crushed into pieces and is difficult to handle. Additionally,
the content of styrene and/or a conjugated diene is relatively decreased, and sites
to which acid radicals are introduced are decreased to thereby decrease
antimicrobial activities in some cases.</p><p num="0023">The copolymer comprises the styrene and/or conjugated diene unit in a
proportion of preferably 20 to 95% by mole, more preferably 45 to 85% by mole,
and most preferably 50 to 80% by mole.</p><p num="0024">If the content of the styrene and/or conjugated diene unit is less than 20%
by mole, sites to which acid radicals are introduced are decreased to thereby
decrease antimicrobial activities in some cases. Additionally, the resulting
copolymer becomes rigid and cannot be crushed into pieces and is difficult to
handle. In contrast, if the content of the styrene and/or conjugated diene unit
exceeds 95% by mole, the copolymer after acid treatment step may become
soluble in water and such a water-soluble copolymer is difficult to handle in
subsequent steps.</p><p num="0025">The copolymer for use in the invention may further comprise additional
units in addition to the acrylonitrile unit, styrene unit, and conjugated diene unit.
Such additional units include, but are not limited to, maleic anhydride, itaconic
anhydride, (-methylstyrene, acrylamide, methacrylamide, acrylic acid and acrylic
esters (e.g., saturated or unsaturated hydrocarbons each having 1 to 10 carbon
atoms), methacrylic acid and methacrylic esters (e.g., saturated or unsaturated
hydrocarbons each having 1 to 10 carbon atoms), vinyl acetate, vinyl chloride,
ethylene, propylene, butylene, vinylpyrrolidone, and vinylpyridine.</p><p num="0026">The copolymer has a weight average molecular weight (Mw) of preferably
1000 to 20000000, and more preferably 10000 to 1000000. If Mw is less than
1000, the resulting copolymer may become soluble in water in the acid treatment
step and the subsequent conversion step, and desired antimicrobial activities may
not be obtained. In contrast, if Mw exceeds 20000000, reaction rates in the acid
treatment step and the subsequent conversion step are decreased and the process is
not practically desirable. </p><p num="0027">As the copolymer, use can be made of resinous materials such as an
acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene resin (hereinafter referred to as "ABS resin"), a
styrene-acrylonitrile resin (hereinafter referred to as "SAN resin"), an acrylatestyrene-acrylonitrile
resin (hereinafter referred to as "ASA resin"), a polyethylene
chloride-acrylonitrile-styrene resin (hereinafter referred to as "ACS resin"), and an
acrylonitrile-butadiene rubber (hereinafter referred to as "NBR rubber"). These
resinous materials may be any of "virgin pellets" newly produced, discharged
articles (odd products) discharged in production procedures of resin materials or
molded articles, and spent resinous materials. Such spent resinous materials have
been molded for a specific application and are derived from housings and various
parts materials used in, for example, electric products and automobiles or from
tubes, hoses, and various cushioning materials.</p><p num="0028">Spent resinous materials as above are particularly preferably used as the
copolymer. Such spent resinous materials can be obtained from discharging sites
such as plants, shops, and consumers. Especially, most of spent resinous
materials recovered from plants and shops are more uniform in composition than
spent resinous materials discharged from consumers as general waste and are
preferably used as the copolymer.</p><p num="0029">The copolymer for use in the invention may be alloys with other resinous
materials and may be copolymers further including additives such as pigments,
dyes, stabilizers, flame-retardants, plasticizers, fillers, and auxiliaries.
Alternatively, the copolymer may be a mixture of a spent resinous material and a
virgin pellet.</p><p num="0030">Additional resins which can be mixed with the copolymer for use herein
are preferably resins that do not adversely affect individual reactions in the acid
treatment step and the conversion step. Such resins include, for example,
poly(phenylene ether), polycarbonates, poly(phenylene sulfide), poly(ethylene
terephthalate), poly(butylene terephthalate), polyamides, and polyesters. The
content of the additional resin in the antimicrobial agent is preferably 60% by
weight or less relative to the copolymer. A content of the additional resin
exceeding 60% by weight may inhibit individual reactions in the acid treatment
step and the conversion step. </p><p num="0031">The copolymer is preferably processed into pieces as a pretreatment of the
acid treatment step. Techniques for processing the copolymer into pieces are as
follows.</p><heading>(1) Grinding with a grinder and then sieving</heading><p num="0032">It is advantageous to grind after freezing when the copolymer comprises a
rubber component.</p><heading>(2) Heating and melting the copolymer to thereby pelletize the same into
fine beads</heading><p num="0033">The pieces of the copolymer preferably have a size of 3.5 mesh or less. If
the copolymer has a size exceeding 3.5 mesh, the copolymer has a small surface
area and is resistant to acid treatment, resulting in an increasing reaction time.
Accordingly, if the copolymer has a size exceeding 3.5 mesh, the amount of
introduced acid radicals is decreased and the property of carrying a metal salt may
be substantially decreased.</p><p num="0034">Additionally, the copolymer should preferably further comprise an
inorganic pigment such as carbon black and titanium dioxide. When the
copolymer comprises an inorganic pigment, the inorganic pigment is detached
from the copolymer during the acid treatment step, and the acid is facilitated to
permeate to a surface of the copolymer and the periphery of portions where the
inorganic pigment is detached becomes sensitive to acid treatment. By this
configuration, the acid treatment of the copolymer is enhanced.</p><p num="0035">The content of the inorganic pigment is preferably 0.01 to 20% by weight,
and more preferably 0.05 to 10% by weight relative to the dry weight of the
copolymer. If the content of the inorganic pigment is less than 0.01% by weight,
the effect of enhancing the acid treatment as mentioned above may not be
exhibited. In contrast, if the content of the inorganic pigment exceeds 20% by
weight, the proportion of the copolymer component having antimicrobial
activities is relatively decreased and desired antimicrobial activities may not be
exhibited.</p><p num="0036">The inorganic pigment such as carbon black and titanium dioxide may be
originally contained in the copolymer or may be independently added to and
mixed with the copolymer. Particularly from the viewpoint of improving 
properties of the antimicrobial agent, the inorganic pigment should be preferably
originally contained in the copolymer. Such inorganic pigments such as carbon
black and titanium dioxide for use in the invention may be those generally used in
plastics as coloring agents, reinforcing agents, and materials for imparting electric
conductivity.</p><p num="0037">For example, the carbon black may be any of carbon black produced by
channel technique, furnace technique, and thermal technique. Each of these
carbon black products can be used alone or in combination. The carbon black has
a mean particle size of preferably 5 to 500 nm, and more preferably 10 to 50 nm.</p><p num="0038">The titanium dioxide may be any of rutile type titanium dioxide, anatase
type titanium oxide, and ultrafine titanium dioxide. Each of these types of
titanium dioxide can be used alone or in combination. The titanium dioxide has a
mean particle size of preferably 0.01 to 50 nm, and more preferably 0.05 to 10
nm.</p><p num="0039">Inorganic acids are advantageously used as acids for use in the acid
treatment step. The amount of the inorganic acid is preferably 1 to 500 times by
weight and more preferably 10 to 200 times by weight that of the copolymer to be
treated with the acid. If the amount of the inorganic acid is less than once that of
the copolymer, the amount of the acid radical introduced into styrene and/or
conjugated diene unit and the rate of hydrolyzed acrylonitrile group are decreased,
and the amount of the metal salt contained in the copolymer may be insufficient
from the viewpoint of antimicrobial activities. In contrast, if it exceeds 500 times,
an excessive amount of the inorganic acid is used to thereby increase cost, and is
not desirable in practice.</p><p num="0040">Such inorganic acids include a concentrated sulfuric acid, sulfuric
anhydride, fuming sulfuric acid, chlorosulfonic acid, and other sulfonating agents,
as well as nitric acid, fuming nitric acid, phosphoric acid, phosphorus chloride,
and phosphorus oxide. Among them, concentrated sulfuric acid, sulfuric
anhydride, fuming sulfuric acid and chlorosulfonic acid are preferred, of which a
concentrated sulfuric acid of 70% by weight or more is specifically preferred.</p><p num="0041">Each of these inorganic acids can be used alone or in combination. When
they are used in combination, a plurality of inorganic acids may be previously 
mixed or a plurality of inorganic acids may be added in turn. For example, the
copolymer is initially treated with a concentrated sulfuric and sulfuric anhydride
is added to the treated copolymer to thereby yield an antimicrobial agent which is
stable in shape in an aqueous system. This is because the treatment with
concentrated sulfuric acid mainly hydrolyzes a nitrile moiety of the copolymer,
and the subsequent treatment with sulfuric anhydride forcefully subjects a styrene
or conjugated diene moiety to sulfone-crosslinking to thereby yield a copolymer
as a highly crosslinked gel.</p><p num="0042">The acid treatment step may be performed in an inorganic acid as well as
in a system with an organic solvent. Such organic solvents for use herein include
aliphatic halogenated hydrocarbons having one or two carbon atoms such as 1,2-dichloroethane,
chloroform, dichloromethane, and 1,1-dichloroethane; alicyclic
hydrocarbons such as cyclohexane, methylcyclohexane, and cyclopentane;
nitromethane, nitrobenzene, sulfur dioxide, paraffin-series hydrocarbons (e.g.,
those having one to seven carbon atoms), acetonitrile, carbon disulfide,
tetrahydrofuran, 1,2-dimethoxyethane, acetone, methyl ethyl ketone, and
thiophene. Of these organic solvents, preferred are aliphatic halogenated
hydrocarbons having one or two carbon atoms, alicyclic hydrocarbons,
nitromethane, nitrobenzene, and sulfur dioxide. Each of these solvents can be
used alone or in combination. These organic solvents can be mixed in any
proportion.</p><p num="0043">The proportion of the organic solvent is preferably less than 200 times by
weight that of the copolymer. An amount of the organic solvent exceeding 200
times by weight may decrease the reaction rate of acid treatment and may
deteriorate economical efficiency.</p><p num="0044">Where necessary, a Lewis acid can be used in acid treatment of the
copolymer. Such Lewis acids include triethyl phosphate, trimethyl phosphate,
and other alkyl phosphates, dioxane, acetic anhydride, ethyl acetate, ethyl
palmitate, diethyl ether, and thioxane. An inorganic acid or organic solvent used
in the acid treatment step can be supplied again to a reaction by recovering after
the completion of the reaction and recycling to the reaction as intact, or by
recovering through extraction or distillation. </p><p num="0045">The above acid treatment of the copolymer can introduce acid radicals into
the styrene and/or conjugated diene moiety of the copolymer and can amidate
acrylonitrile moiety through hydrolysis to thereby modify the copolymer to a
hydrophilic resin. Such acid radicals introduced into the styrene and/or
conjugated diene moiety include, for example, sulfonic acid group, -PO(OH)<sub>2</sub>, and
-CH<sub>2</sub>PO(OH)<sub>2</sub>.</p><p num="0046">Specifically, to introduce sulfonic acid group as the acid radical, the
copolymer is allowed to react with the sulfonating agent such as concentrated
sulfuric acid, sulfuric anhydride, fuming sulfuric acid, or chlorosulfonic acid
directly or in a solvent. To introduce -PO(OH)<sub>2</sub> group, phosphorus trioxide is
added to the solvent to thereby further enhance hydrolysis. Of these acid radicals,
sulfonic acid group is specifically preferred. Each of these acid radicals can be
introduced alone or in combination into the copolymer.</p><p num="0047">The amount of the acid radical in the copolymer is preferably 5 to 95% by
mole, and more preferably 10 to 70% by mole, relative to the total units. If the
amount of the acid radical exceeds 95% by mole relative to the total units, the
acid-treated copolymer may become soluble in water, resulting in deteriorated
dimensional stability of the product antimicrobial agent. In contrast, the amount
less than 5% by mole relative to the total units may deteriorate water permeability
and water absorbing property (especially to aqueous electrolyte solutions) of the
copolymer and may inhibit treatment with a metal salt in the metal salt treatment
step, resulting in deteriorated antimicrobial activities.</p><p num="0048">Depending greatly on the presence or absence of the organic solvent, a
reaction temperature in the acid treatment step should preferably fall in a range
from 0°C to 200°C and more preferably in a range from 30°C to 120°C. If the
reaction temperature is lower than 0°C, the reaction rate is impracticably
decreased and the resulting antimicrobial agent may not exhibit satisfactory
performances. If it exceeds 200°C, molecular chains of the copolymer are liable
to be cleaved through thermal decomposition and the resulting copolymer may
become soluble in water.</p><p num="0049">The reaction in the acid treatment step should be preferably performed for
1 minute to 40 hours, and more preferably for 5 minutes to 2 hours, while 
depending greatly on the reaction temperature. If the reaction time is less than 1
minute, the reaction may not sufficiently proceed. If it exceeds 40 hours, the
production efficiency may be deteriorated.</p><p num="0050">In the conversion step, the acid radical moiety of the copolymer having
acid radicals introduced in the acid treatment step is converted into a metal salt, in
particular a metal salt of at least one metal selected from Ag, Cu, and Zn. The
acid radical can be converted into a metal salt, for example, by filtrating the
reaction product obtained in the acid treatment step through a filter, washing the
filtered product with a large quantity of water, and then adding a metal salt to the
product, or by directly adding the product obtained in the acid treatment step to an
aqueous solution of the metal salt. By these techniques, part or overall of the acid
radicals introduced in the acid treatment step can be converted into a metal salt.</p><p num="0051">Organic salts, inorganic salts, organic hydroxides, and inorganic
hydroxides can be used in combination with these metal salts in the conversion
step. Such organic salts, inorganic salts, organic hydroxides, and inorganic
hydroxides include, but are not limited to, hydroxides, carbonates, acetates,
sulfates, phosphates, salts of organic acids, and other compounds of ammonium,
alkali metals (e.g., sodium, lithium, and potassium), alkaline earth metals (e.g.,
magnesium and calcium), and other metals (e.g., aluminium, titanium,
germanium, tin, and iron).</p><p num="0052">The above antimicrobial agent, in which part or overall of the acid radicals
introduced into the copolymer are converted into a specific metal salt, can
effectively inhibit growth and reproduction of bacteria, fungi, and other
microorganisms. The antimicrobial agent can be produced by using a spent
resinous material as described above. Accordingly, the present invention can add
values to waste materials which have been conventionally discarded, can
effectively utilize the wasted materials to thereby make effective use of resources.</p><p num="0053">The invention antimicrobial agent can be used in combination with a
conventionally known antimicrobial agent. Such conventional antimicrobial
agents include inorganic antimicrobial agents, organic antimicrobial agents
extracted from natural products, organic antimicrobial agents composed of 
aliphatic compounds, and organic antimicrobial agents composed of aromatic
compounds.</p><p num="0054">Such inorganic antimicrobial agents include, but are not limited to, sodium
hypochlorite, and other chlorine compounds; hydrogen peroxide, and other
peroxides; boric acid, sodium borate, and other borate compounds; copper sulfate,
and other copper compounds; zinc sulfate, zinc chloride, and other zinc
compounds; sulfur, calcium polysulfate, sulfur hydrate, and other sulfur
substances; calcium oxide, and other calcium compounds; silver thiosulfite
complex, silver nitrate, and other silver compounds; as well as iodine and sodium
silicofluoride.</p><p num="0055">The organic antimicrobial agents extracted from natural products include,
for example, hinokitiol, Phyllostachys pubescens extract, and creosote oils.</p><p num="0056">The organic antimicrobial agents composed of aliphatic compounds
include, but are not limited to, tributyltin oxide, and other organotin compounds;
copper naphthenate, and other cyclopentane derivatives; methyl bromide, and
other halogen compounds; ethyl alcohol, isopropyl alcohol, and other monohydric
alcohols; 2-bromo-2-nitro-1,3-propanediol, and other dihydric alcohols;
formaldehydes, glutaraldehyde, and other saturated aldehydes; sorbic acid,
potassium sorbate, and other carboxylic acid compounds; ethylene oxide,
propylene oxide, and other ether compounds; beta-oxypropiolactone, and other
lactone compounds; 3 trimethoxysilylpropyldimethyloctadecylammonium
chloride, and other quaternary ammonium salt compounds;
di(octylaminoethyl)glycine hydrochloride, and other amino acid derivatives;
sodium lauryl sulfate, and other sulfonic acid compounds; bisdequalinium acetate,
and other hydroxamic acid compounds; isocyanuric chloride, and other cyanuric
acid compounds; methyl isocyanate, and other cyanate compounds;
bis(trichloromethyl)sulfone, and other sulfone compounds;
polyhexamethylenebiguanidine hydrochloride, and other guanidine compounds;
1,3-dichloro-5,5-dimethylhydantoin, and other hydantoin compounds; 5-oxy-3,4-dichloro-1,2-dithiol,
and other dithiol compounds; iron dimethylarsinate, and
other arsine compounds; tris(ethylphosphate)aluminium, and other phosphate
compounds; and thiocarbamide compounds. </p><p num="0057">The organic antimicrobial agents composed of aromatic compounds
include, but are not limited to, bis(4-nitrophenyl)carbonate, and other carbonate
compounds; benzalkonium chloride Abenzethonium chloride, and other
quaternary ammonium salt compounds; 2,6-dichloro-4-nitroaniline, and other
monoamine compounds; potassium nitroethylbenzylethylenediamine, and other
diamine compounds; aluminium N-nitroso-N-cyclohexylhydroxylamine, and
other hydroxylamine compounds; dihydromethyloxathiinecarboxanilide dioxide,
and other anilide compounds; 2-(4-thiazolyl)benzimidazole, and other imidazole
compounds; 5-methyl-1,2,4-triazol-3,4-benzothiazole, and other benzothiazole
compounds; 2,4-dichloro-6-chloroanilino-1,3,5-triazine, and other triazine
compounds; chlorhexidine hydrochloride, chlorhexidine gluconate, and other
guanidine compounds; cetylpyridinium chloride, and other pyridine compounds;
dimethylpyrazolylhydroxyphenylpyrimidine, and other pyrimidine compounds;
2,2'-methylenebis-3,4,6-trichlorophenol, and other halogenobenzene compounds;
copper hydroxynonylbenzenesulfonate, and other benzenesulfonic acid
compounds; benzoic acid, and other benzenecarboxylic acid compounds;
thimerosal, and other mercaptocarboxylic acid compounds; ethyl
hydroxybenzoate, and other hydroxycarboxylic acid compounds; phenol, cresol,
and other monohydric phenol compounds; resorcinol, and other dihydric phenol
compounds; phenoxyethanol, and other phenoxy ether compounds;
pentachlorophenyl laurate, and other phenol ester compounds; triphenyltin oxide,
and other phenyl compounds; diphenyl, and other biphenyl compounds; betanaphthol,
and other monohydric naphthols; monochloronaphthalene, and other
naphthalene compounds; dodecylisoquinolinium bromide, and other isoquinoline
compounds; as well as nitrile compounds, isothiazole compounds, thiadiazole
compounds, halogenophenol compounds, pyrrole compounds, quinone
compounds, quinoline compounds, and organic phosphate compounds.</p><p num="0058">The present invention will be illustrated in further detail with reference to
the following Examples 1 to 4, which are not intended to limit the scope of the
present invention. In these examples, the invention antimicrobial agents were
prepared and were evaluated. </p><heading>EXAMPLE 1</heading><p num="0059">A waste ABS (acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene) resin was crushed and
classified to 16 to 32 mesh with a refrigerating shredder. To 30 parts by weight of
a 96% by weight concentrated sulfuric acid, 1 part by weight of the classified
waste resin was added, and the resulting mixture was allowed to react at 80°C for
20 minutes. This waste ABS resin was a black part of a 8-mm cassette tape guard
panel and was composed of 52% by mole of styrene, 28% by mole of
acrylonitrile, and 20% by mole of butadiene, and further was composed of 2% by
weight of carbon black.</p><p num="0060">After the completion of reaction, a solid matter in the reaction system was
filtrated through glass filter, was rinsed, and was neutralized with 50 parts by
weight of a 1 N sodium hydroxide solution, and was then washed with sufficient
amounts of water. The resulting product was ultimately separated into filtrate and
filter cake by filtration. At this stage, silver nitrate was added to the resulting
filtrate to find that the filtrate did not become whitish to thereby verify that
concentrated hydrochloric acid component was completely removed by
neutralization and rinsing.</p><p num="0061">Next, the filter cake was dispersed in 1000 parts by weight of pure water,
and 10 parts by weight of a 1.0 M silver nitrate solution was added to the
dispersion and was mixed thoroughly, and the resulting mixture was rinsed and
was then filtrated. The resulting solid matter was then dried in a circulation drier
at 105°C for 2 hours to thereby yield an antimicrobial agent composed of a black
solid matter.</p><p num="0062">The resulting antimicrobial agent was subjected to elementary analysis to
find that the antimicrobial agent comprised sulfonic acid group in a proportion of
33% by mole relative to total monomeric units and that it comprised silver in a
molar ratio of 0.82 relative to the sulfonic acid group.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 2</heading><p num="0063">An antimicrobial agent was prepared in the same manner as in Example 1,
except that a waste SAN (styrene-acrylonitrile) resin and 10 parts by weight of a
1.0 M copper sulfate pentahydrate instead of the waste ABS resin and 10 parts by
weight of 1.0 M silver nitrate solution. The resulting antimicrobial agent was 
found to contain sulfonic acid group in a proportion of 36% by mole relative to
the total monomeric units and to contain copper in a molar ratio of 0.91 relative to
the sulfonic acid group.</p><p num="0064">The waste SAN resin was a transparent guard panel part of a 8-mm
cassette tape and was composed of 60% by mole of styrene and 40% by mole of
acrylonitrile.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 3</heading><p num="0065">A waste ABS resin was crushed and classified to 16 to 32 mesh with a
refrigerating shredder. To 90 parts by weight of a 96% by weight concentrated
sulfuric acid, 3.5 parts by weight of the classified resin were added, and allowed
to react at 60°C for 60 minutes. Then, 0.5 part by weight of fuming sulfuric acid
(SO3 content: 60% by weight) was added to the mixture and the reaction was
continued for further 30 minutes. The resulting reaction mixture was subjected to
neutralization and rinsing in the same manner as in Example 1. To the resulting
dispersion in the present example, 50 parts by weight of a 1.0 M zinc sulfate
heptahydrate were added and the resulting mixture was stirred thoroughly, was
rinsed, and was then filtrated. An antimicrobial agent was thus prepared in a
similar manner as in Example 1 except the above procedures. The resulting
antimicrobial agent according to Example 3 was found to contain sulfonic acid
group in a proportion of 42% by mole relative to the total monomeric units and to
contain zinc in a molar ratio of 0.85 relative to the sulfonic acid group.</p><p num="0066">The waste ABS resin was a white housing of a computer and was
composed of 48% by mole of styrene, 39% by mole of acrylonitrile, and 13% by
mole of butadiene, and was further composed of 1% by weight of titanium
dioxide. According to this example, a white antimicrobial agent was obtained.</p><heading>EXAMPLE 4</heading><p num="0067">Initially, 3 parts by weight of the waste ABS resin used in Example 1 were
added to 70 parts by weight of cyclohexane, and 4.2 parts by weight of sulfuric
anhydride were added dropwise to the resulting mixture held at 30°C. The
mixture was held at a temperature of 30±2°C and was allowed to react for 2 hours.
The resulting solid matter was filtrated and was then rinsed. </p><p num="0068">The rinsed solid matter was then filtrated and was dispersed in 2000 parts
by weight of pure water. To the dispersion, 50 parts by weight of a 1.0 M zinc
sulfate heptahydrate and 30 parts by weight of a 1.0 M copper sulfate
pentahydrate were added, and the mixture was stirred thoroughly and was rinsed.
An antimicrobial agent according to Example 4 was prepared in a similar manner
as in Example 1, except for the above procedures. The resulting antimicrobial
agent was found to contain sulfonic acid group in a proportion of 25% by mole
relative to the total monomeric units and to contain zinc and copper in molar
ratios of 0.42 and 0.36, respectively, relative to the sulfonic acid group.</p><p num="0069">The antimicrobial activities of the above-prepared antimicrobial agents
according to Examples 1 to 4 were evaluated in the following manner.</p><p num="0070">Initially, a test antimicrobial agent was spread on a sterilized Petri dish,
and pure water was added dropwise on the antimicrobial agent, and the
antimicrobial agent which was in swelling state in equilibrium was allowed to
stand for 15 minutes. Excess water was then removed by absorption by a filter
paper.</p><p num="0071">Next, a 0.001% meat extract containing 5x10<sup>5</sup>/ml Escherichia coli IFO
3972 was prepared, and 2 ml of the meat extract were added dropwise into the
Petri dish, and the Petri dish was covered with a lid and was cultured at 35°C at
relative humidity of 90% or more for 24 hours.</p><p num="0072">After the completion of cultivation, the culture solution was taken out from
the Petri dish, cells of Escherichia coli were separated by rinsing and were
inoculated on a standard agar plate medium and were cultured at 35°C for 2 days.
On the agar plate medium, living Escherichia coli after culture in the Petri dish
alone forms colonies, and Escherichia coli which was died or suppressed in
growth does not form colonies. The number of colonies formed on the agar plate
medium after the completion of cultivation was counted and was converted to
thereby evaluate the antimicrobial activity of the antimicrobial agent spread in the
Petri dish.</p><p num="0073">Escherichia coli which was cultured in a Petri dish without addition of an
antimicrobial agent was used as a comparative example (control) in the evaluation
of antimicrobial activity. </p><p num="0074">The results in evaluation are as follows.</p><p num="0075">The numbers of living colonies of Escherichia coli in the Petri dish are
shown below.
<sl><li>Comparative Example: 8x10<sup>5</sup></li><li>Example 1: 150</li><li>Example 2: 40</li><li>Example 3: 90</li><li>Example 4: 110</li></sl></p><p num="0076">These results show that the antimicrobial agents according to Examples 1
to 4 certainly inhibit growth and reproduction of Escherichia coli and sterilize
almost all of the microbe in the Petri dish. Accordingly, by converting part or
overall of acid radicals in the copolymer into a specific metal salt, antimicrobial
activity can be imparted to the copolymer to thereby yield an antimicrobial agent
having satisfactory antimicrobial activities.</p><p num="0077">As is described in detail above, the invention antimicrobial agents, in
which at least part of acid radicals formed in the copolymer is converted into a
metal salt, in particular a salt of at least one metal selected from Ag, Cu, and Zn,
can exhibit satisfactory antimicrobial activities. The present invention can
therefore provide completely novel antimicrobial agents using specific
copolymers. According to the present invention, such antimicrobial agents can be
produced from spent resinous materials, and resources can be effectively utilized,
contributing to global environmental conservation.</p><p num="0078">According to the invention process for producing an antimicrobial agent,
acid radicals are introduced into a copolymer and at least part of the acid radicals
is converted into a metal salt, in particular a salt of at least one metal selected
from Ag, Cu, and Zn. The invention process can therefore produce completely
novel antimicrobial agents using specific copolymers. Additionally, spent
resinous materials can be used in the invention process, and resources can be
effectively utilized, contributing to global environmental conservation.</p><p num="0079">Other embodiments and variations will be obvious to those skilled in the
art, and this invention is not to be limited to the specific matters stated above.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An antimicrobial agent comprising a metal salt-containing copolymer,
said metal salt-containing copolymer being obtained by treating a copolymer with
an acid to thereby introduce acid radicals into said copolymer, said copolymer
comprising acrylonitrile and at least one of styrene and a conjugated diene as
units; and converting at least part of said acid radicals into a metal salt.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>An antimicrobial agent according to claim 1, wherein said metal salt-containing
copolymer is obtained by converting at least part of said acid radicals
into a salt of at least one metal selected from the group consisting of Ag, Cu, and
Zn.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>An antimicrobial agent according to one of claims 1 or 2, wherein said
metal salt-containing copolymer comprises 5 to 80% by mole of acrylonitrile.</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>An antimicrobial agent according to anyone of claims 1 to 3, wherein
said metal salt-containing copolymer comprises 20 to 95% by mole of at least one
of styrene and a conjugated diene.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>An antimicrobial agent according to anyone of claims 1 to 4, wherein
said copolymer comprises at least one selected from the group consisting of
acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene resins, styrene-acrylonitrile resins, and
acrylonitrile-butadiene rubbers.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>An antimicrobial agent according to anyone of claims 1 to 5, wherein
said copolymer further comprises an inorganic pigment.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>An antimicrobial agent according to claim 6, wherein said inorganic
pigment is at least one of carbon black and titanium dioxide.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>An antimicrobial agent according to one of claims 6 or 7, wherein said
copolymer comprises 0.01 to 20% by weight of said inorganic pigment.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>An antimicrobial agent according to anyone of claims 1 to 8, wherein
said copolymer comprises a spent resin.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>An antimicrobial agent according to anyone of claims 1 to 9, wherein
said acid radicals are sulfonic acid groups.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>An antimicrobial agent according to anyone of claims 1 to 10, wherein
said copolymer comprises 5 to 95% by weight of said acid radicals relative to the
overall units of said copolymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>A process for producing an antimicrobial agent comprising a metal
salt-containing copolymer, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>treating a copolymer with an acid to thereby introduce acid radicals into
said copolymer, said copolymer containing acrylonitrile and at least one of styrene
and a conjugated diene as units; and</claim-text><claim-text>converting at least part of said acid radicals into a metal salt.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="13"><claim-text>A process according to claim 12, wherein said at least part of the
radical acids are converted into a salt of at least one metal selected from the group
consisting of Ag, Cu, and Zn.</claim-text></claim><claim num="14"><claim-text>A process according to one of claims 12 or 13, wherein a spent resin is
used for the preparation of said copolymer.</claim-text></claim><claim num="15"><claim-text>A process according to anyone of claims 12 to 14, wherein at least one
inorganic acid selected from the group consisting of a concentrated sulfuric acid,
sulfuric anhydride, fuming sulfuric acid, chlorosulfonic acid, phosphoric acid,
phosphorus chloride, and phosphorus oxide is used in said treating step.</claim-text></claim><claim num="16"><claim-text>A process according to anyone of claims 12 to 15, wherein said
copolymer is processed to a size of 3.5 mesh or less prior to said acid treatment.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>