<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1405850-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1405850" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="31996238" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040407"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1405850-A1" status="new" fvid="24003211"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1405850</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040407</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03103578-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03103578</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20030926</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002289226-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002289226</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021001</date></document-id></priority-claim><priority-claim ucid="JP-2002289227-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002289227</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021001</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 305/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C07D 305/06        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K  19/34        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09K  19/34        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C07D 305/06</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09K  19/34A</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="ICO">M07D305:06</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">(Meth)acrylverbindung mit einer Oxetanylgruppe und damit hergestellter Flüssigkristallfilm</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">(Meth)acrylic compound having an oxetanyl group and liquid crystal film produced by using the same</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Composé (méth)acrylique contenant un groupe oxétanyl et film à cristaux liquides produit en utilisant le même</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="JP-2002250805-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>JP</country><doc-number>2002250805</doc-number><kind>A</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="Y"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="WO-2002028985-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>WO</country><doc-number>2002028985</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations><non-patent-citations><nplcit status="new"><text>DATABASE WPI Derwent Publications Ltd., London, GB;  AN 2001-075363 XP002265550 &amp; JP 2000 319527 A (NITTO DENKO CORP.), 21 November 2000 (2000-11-21)</text><sources><source category="AD" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit><nplcit status="new"><text>PATENT ABSTRACTS OF JAPAN &amp; JP 2002 250805 A (TOPPAN PRINTING CO LTD.), 6 September 2002 (2002-09-06)</text><sources><source category="A" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></nplcit></non-patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NIPPON OIL CORP</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NIPPON OIL CORPORATION</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Nippon Oil Corporation</last-name><address><street>3-12, Nishi-shimbashi 1-chome, Minato-ku</street><city>Tokyo 105-8412</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KOBAYASHI MASAAKI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MATSUMOTO TAKUYA</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>MAZAKI HITOSHI</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>NAKAMURA TORU</name><address><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KOBAYASHI, MASAAKI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MATSUMOTO, TAKUYA</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>MAZAKI, HITOSHI</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>NAKAMURA, TORU</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KOBAYASHI, MASAAKI</last-name><address><street>c/o Nippon Oil Corporation, 8 Chidori-cho, Naka-ku</street><city>Yokohama-shi, 231-0815, Kanagawa</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MATSUMOTO, TAKUYA</last-name><address><street>c/o Nippon Oil Corporation, 8 Chidori-cho, Naka-ku</street><city>Yokohama-shi, 231-0815, Kanagawa</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>MAZAKI, HITOSHI</last-name><address><street>c/o Nippon Oil Corporation, 8 Chidori-cho, Naka-ku</street><city>Yokohama-shi, 231-0815, Kanagawa</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>NAKAMURA, TORU</last-name><address><street>c/o Nippon Oil Corporation, 8 Chidori-cho, Naka-ku</street><city>Yokohama-shi, 231-0815, Kanagawa</city><country>JP</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Janson, Ronny</last-name><address><street>Ehrner &amp;amp; Delmar Patentbyra AB, Box 10316</street><city>100 55 Stockholm</city><country>SE</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FI</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country><country>NL</country><country>SE</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>The present invention provides a novel compound
which is suitable as the starting material of a
side-chain type liquid crystalline polymeric substance
having a reactive group which is excellent in
reactivity upon fixation of the liquid crystal
orientation structure. The novel compound is a
(meth)acrylic compound having an oxetanyl group
represented by the formula
<img id="img-80000001" orientation="unknown" wi="160" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="80000001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
wherein R<sup>1</sup> is hydrogen or methyl, R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen, methyl,
or ethyl, "-L<sub>1</sub>-M-L<sub>2</sub>-" represents a mesogen portion, and
n and m are each an integer of 0 to 10. The present
invention also provides a liquid crystal film
containing the side-chain type liquid crystalline
polymeric substance and a liquid crystal display
mounted with such a liquid crystal film.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p num="0001">This invention relates to a novel (meth)acrylic
compound having a polymerizable oxetanyl group and a
novel side-chain type liquid crystalline polymeric
substance derived from the (meth)acrylic compound.
This invention also relates to a liquid crystal film
containing such a polymeric substance and a liquid
crystal display mounted with such a liquid crystal
film.</p><p num="0002">In recent years, as a result of the researches and
developments which have been actively conducted to
apply liquid crystal materials to optical purposes, a
liquid crystal film produced by aligning a liquid
crystal material has practically used for the purposes
of providing a liquid crystal display with color
compensation and wide viewing angle properties.</p><p num="0003">Various methods of forming a liquid crystal
material into a film are known. For example, there is
a method in which a liquid crystal film is produced by
forming a liquid crystalline polymeric substance film
over a substrate which can align the substance and then
heating the film to a temperature equal to or higher
than the glass transition temperature "Tg", followed
by rapid cooling of the film so as to fix the orientation 
of the liquid crystal, as disclosed in Japanese Patent
Laid-Open Publication No. 3-9321. However, although
this method is applicable to both main chain- and side
chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric substances, it
has problems that the process would be increased in load
and eligible alignment substrates are limited when
using a main-chain type liquid crystalline polymeric
substance with a high Tg. Furthermore, when using a
side-chain type liquid crystalline polymeric substance,
this method has a problem in the heat resistance of the
resulting liquid crystal film and a drawback that the
orientation of the liquid crystal would be disordered
at a temperature in the vicinity of the Tg.</p><p num="0004">Alternatively, as disclosed in Japanese Patent
Laid-Open Publication No. 8-21915, there is a method
in which a liquid crystal film is produced by pouring
a liquid crystalline low molecular weight substance
having a reactive group into a liquid crystal cell
provided with an alignment substrate and heating the
cell to a temperature at which the substance exhibits
a liquid crystal phase so as to be oriented in a liquid
crystal orientation state, followed by fixing the
orientation by polymerizing the substance with an
external force such as light or heat. However, in this
method, it is difficult to control the parameters of
the resulting liquid crystal film because the liquid
crystal to be oriented is a low molecular weight 
substance and thus the physical properties such as
fluidity and birefringence are heavily dependent on
temperature. Further, this method may often have a
problem with the heat resistance of the resulting
liquid crystalline film because the structure of the
liquid crystal after polymerization becomes similar to
that of a side chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric
substance and thus the sufficiently high Tg can not be
obtained.</p><p num="0005">As an alternative for polymerizing and fixing a
liquid crystal orientation by an external force, there
is a method in which a mixture of a liquid crystalline
polymeric substance and a reactive low molecular weight
substance is allowed to be oriented to a liquid crystal
phase and subjected to an external force so as to be
reacted and cured, as reported in Japanese Patent
Laid-Open Publication No. 10-120640. However,
because the reaction between the liquid crystalline
polymeric substance and the reactive low molecular
weight substance does not progress sufficiently, the
Tg is not sufficiently raised, leading to a problem with
the heat resistance of the resulting liquid crystal
film.</p><p num="0006">In view of these problems, a method as disclosed
in Japanese Patent Laid-Open Publication No.
2000-319527 is now considered to be the most effective
in which method a reactive group is directly introduced 
into a liquid crystalline polymeric substance with a
relatively low Tg, such as a side chain-type and then
subjected to an external force such as light or heat
to be cross-linked after orienting the reactive group
to a liquid crystal state, thereby raising the Tg.
However, this method has a problem that it is difficult
to synthesize such a side chain-type liquid crystalline
polymeric substance with a reactive group. For example,
when the polymeric structure is constructed prior to
the introduction of a reactive group, the amount
thereof may be insufficient. On the other hand, in a
method in which from a monomer having two reactive
groups, a side chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric
substance having a reactive group is synthesized by
polymerizing one of the reactive group, it is necessary
that the reactivity of the other reactive group must
be maintained lower than that of the reactive group to
be reacted, leading to a problem that the reactive group
of the polymeric substance after being oriented to a
liquid crystal phase tends to be insufficient.</p><p num="0007">The present invention was made in view of the
foregoing problems and provides a novel compound which
is suitable as the starting material of a side
chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric substance
having a reactive group with an excellent reactivity
upon fixation of a liquid crystal orientation and a side
chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric substance 
derived from such a compound. Furthermore, the present
invention also provides a liquid crystal film with an
excellent heat resistance which is produced from a
liquid crystal material containing such a side chain-type
liquid crystalline polymeric substance by fixing
the orientation state of the liquid crystal material
and a liquid crystal display mounted with the liquid
crystal film.</p><p num="0008">After an extensive research and study made by the
present inventors, they found a novel polymerizable
compound having an oxetanyl group which can be used as
the starting material of a side chain-type liquid
crystalline polymeric substance which can be easily
synthesized and is excellent in orientability and
fixation of the orientation structure.</p><p num="0009">That is, according to a first aspect of the present
invention, there is provided a (meth)acrylic compound
having an oxetanyl group represented by the formula
<img id="img-00050001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00050001.tif" inline="no" he="24"/>
wherein R<sup>1</sup> is hydrogen or methyl, R<sup>2</sup> is hydrogen, methyl,
or ethyl, L<sub>1</sub> and L<sub>2</sub> each are selected from a single bond,
-O-, -O-CO- and -CO-O-, M represents a formula
selected from formulas (2), (3) and (4) below, and n
and m are each independently an integer from 0 to 10: <st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">- P<sub>1</sub>-L<sub>3</sub>-P<sub>2</sub>-L<sub>4</sub>-P<sub>3</sub>-</st32:che><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">- P<sub>1</sub>-L<sub>3</sub>-P<sub>3</sub>-</st32:che><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">- P<sub>3</sub>-</st32:che>
wherein P<sub>1</sub> and P<sub>2</sub> are each independently a group selected
from formulas (5) below, P<sub>3</sub> is a group selected from
formulas (6) below, and L<sub>3</sub> and L<sub>4</sub> are each independently
selected from a single bond, -CH=CH-, -C≡C-, -O-,
-O-CO- and -CO-O-:
<img id="img-00060001" orientation="unknown" wi="151" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060001.tif" inline="no" he="74"/>
and
<img id="img-00060002" orientation="unknown" wi="159" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00060002.tif" inline="no" he="54"/></p><p num="0010">According to a second aspect of the present
invention, there is provided a side chain-type liquid
crystalline polymeric substance obtained by
homopolymerizing the (meth)acrylic portion of the 
(meth)acrylic compound having an oxetanyl group
represented by formula (1) or copolymerizing same with
another (meth)acrylic compound.</p><p num="0011">According to a third aspect of the present
invention, there is provided the side chain-type liquid
crystalline polymeric substance having a unit
represented by formula (7) below derived from a
(meth)acrylic compound having an oxetanyl group of
formula (1) above:
<img id="img-00070001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00070001.tif" inline="no" he="47"/></p><p num="0012">According to a fourth aspect of the present
invention, there is provided the side chain-type liquid
crystalline polymeric substance containing a unit of
formula (7) above in an amount of 5 to 100 percent by
mol.</p><p num="0013">According to a fifth aspect of the present
invention, there is provided the side chain-type liquid
crystalline polymeric substance of whose
weight-average molecular weight is from 2,000 to
100, 000.</p><p num="0014">According to a sixth aspect of the present
invention, there is provided a liquid crystal material 
containing the side-chain type liquid crystalline
polymeric substance in an amount of 10 percent by mass
or more.</p><p num="0015">According to a seventh aspect of the present
invention, there is provided the liquid crystal
material which further contains a photo cationic
initiator and/or a thermal cationic initiator.</p><p num="0016">According to an eighth aspect of the present
invention, there is provided a liquid crystal film
formed by fixing the orientation state of the liquid
crystal material</p><p num="0017">According to a ninth aspect of the present
invention, there is provided a method of producing a
liquid crystal film wherein the liquid crystal material
is developed over an alignment substrate so as to align
the liquid crystal material in a liquid crystal
orientation state, followed by fixing the orientation
by light irradiation and/or a heat treatment.</p><p num="0018">According to a tenth aspect of the present
invention, there is provided the method of producing
a liquid crystal film wherein the orientation state is
one obtained by fixing a orientation state selected
from the group consisting of nematic, twisted nematic,
cholesteric, and nematic hybrid orientations.</p><p num="0019">According to an eleventh aspect of the present
invention, there is provided an optical film comprising
the liquid crystal film. </p><p num="0020">According to a twelfth aspect, there is provided
the optical film is one selected from the group
consisting of a retardation film, a color compensation
film, a viewing angle improving film, a circular
polarizing film, and an optical rotatory film.
<sl><li>FIG. 1 shows the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 1 obtained in Example 1.</li><li>FIG. 2 shows the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 2 obtained in Example 2.</li><li>FIG. 3 shows the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 3 obtained in Example 3.</li><li>FIG. 4 shows the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 4 obtained in Example 4.</li><li>FIG. 5 shows the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 5 obtained in Example 5.</li><li>FIG. 6 shows the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 6 obtained in Example 6.</li><li>FIG. 7 shows the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 7 obtained in Reference Example 1.</li><li>FIG. 8 shows the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 8 obtained in Reference Example 1.</li><li>FIG. 9 shows the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the side-chain
type liquid crystalline polyacrylate 4 obtained in
Example 7.</li><li>FIG. 10 shows the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the side
chain-type liquid crystalline polyacrylate 13 obtained
in Reference Example 2. </li><li>FIG. 11 shows the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the
difunctional oxetane monomer in Reference Example 3.</li><li>FIG. 12 is a schematic view showing the axial
arrangement of each of the components constituting the
liquid crystal display used in Example 10.</li><li>FIG. 13 is a schematic view showing the axial
arrangement of each of the components constituting the
liquid crystal display used in Example 11.</li></sl></p><p num="0021">The present invention will be described in more
detail below.</p><p num="0022">The (meth)acrylic compound having an oxetanyl
group of the present invention is represented by the
formula
<img id="img-00100001" orientation="unknown" wi="165" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00100001.tif" inline="no" he="27"/></p><p num="0023">In formula (1), R<sup>1</sup> is hydrogen or methyl, R<sup>2</sup> is
hydrogen, methyl, or ethyl, L<sub>1</sub> and L<sub>2</sub> each are selected
from a single bond, -O-, -O-CO-, and -CO-O-, M
represents a formula selected from formulas (2), (3)
and (4) below, and n and m are each independently an
integer from 0 to 10:
<st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">-P<sub>1</sub>-L<sub>3</sub>-P<sub>2</sub>-L<sub>4</sub>-P<sub>3</sub>-</st32:che><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">- P<sub>1</sub>-L<sub>3</sub>-P<sub>3</sub>-</st32:che><st32:che xmlns:st32="http://www.matrixware.com/ns/st32/">-P<sub>3</sub>-</st32:che>
wherein P<sub>1</sub> and P<sub>2</sub> are each independently a group selected 
from formulas (5) below, P<sub>3</sub> is a group selected from
formulas (6) below, and L<sub>3</sub> and L<sub>4</sub> are each independently
selected from a single bond, -CH=CH-, -C≡C-, -O-,
-O-CO- and -CO-O-:
<img id="img-00110001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110001.tif" inline="no" he="70"/>
and
<img id="img-00110002"  orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00110002.tif"  inline="no"  he="50"/></p><p num="0024">That is, the (meth)acrylic compound having an
oxetanyl group of the present invention is
characterized in that it contains a mesogen portion
comprising an aromatic ester, spacer portions bonding
thereto and comprising a hydrocarbon chain, a reactive
oxetanyl group at one terminal end, and a (meth) acrylic
group at the other terminal end as constituting units 
and a polymeric substance obtained by homopolymerizing
the (meth)acrylic group of this compound or
copolymerizing same with another (meth)acrylic
compound exhibits liquid crystallinity.</p><p num="0025">First of all, each of the constituting units will
be described.</p><p num="0026">The mesogen portion of the (meth) acrylic compound
having an oxetanyl group of the present invention is
represented by "-L<sub>1</sub>-M-L<sub>2</sub>-" in formula (1) wherein M is
represented by "-P<sub>1</sub>-L<sub>3</sub>-P<sub>2</sub>-L<sub>4</sub>-P<sub>3</sub>-", "-P<sub>1</sub>-L<sub>3</sub>-P<sub>3</sub>-", or
"-P<sub>3</sub>-". The mesogen portion has such a structure that
1 to 3 aromatic- or cyclohexane-rings are bonded
directly (single bond) or via an ether bond (-O-) or
an ester bond (-CO-O-) to the spacer portion, oxetanyl
group or (meth)acrylic group.</p><p num="0027">In formula (1) , L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2</sub>, L<sub>3</sub>, and L<sub>4</sub> are each
independently a single bond (this means that the groups
of the both sides bond directly without via the group
represented by "L") or represents -CH=CH-, -C≡C-, -O-,
-O-CO- or -CO-O-. P<sub>1</sub> and P<sub>2</sub> are each independently a
group selected from formulas (5), while P<sub>3</sub> is a group
selected from formulas (6).</p><p num="0028">Although the mesogen portion may be selected
arbitrary from the above-described combinations,
preferred examples are those represented by the
following formulas: <img id="img-00130001"  orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130001.tif" inline="no" he="28"/><img id="img-00130002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130002.tif" inline="no" he="21"/><img id="img-00130003" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00130003.tif" inline="no" he="22"/></p><p num="0029">The spacer portions represented by "- (CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub>-" and
"-(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>m</sub>-" in formula (1) each represent a single bond
which means that "n" or "m" is 0 or a divalent
straight-chain hydrocarbon having 1 to 10 carbon atoms,
i. e. , "n" or "m" is an integer of 1 to 10. As long as
the intended compound exhibits liquid crystallinity,
the mesogen portion may bond directly without via the
spacer portions or bond via an ether bond (-O-) or an
ester bond (-CO-O-), to the oxetanyl group portion and
the (meth)acrylic portion. In general, too short
spacers between the mesogen portion and the
(meth)acrylic group portion would narrow the
temperature range at which the liquid crystallinity is
exhibited, while too long spacers would adversely
affect the heat resistance of the resulting liquid
crystal film. In view of these, the spacer portions
between the mesogen portion and the (meth) acrylic group
portion has usually 1 to 8, preferably 2 to 6 carbon 
atoms. Too long spacers between the mesogen portion
and the oxetanyl group portion would adversely affect
the heat resistance of the resulting liquid crystal
film. Therefore, the spacer portions between the
mesogen portion and the oxetanyl group portion have
usually 0 to 6, preferably 0 to 4 carbon atoms (0 carbon
atoms denotes herein that the mesogen portion bonds
directly to the oxetanyl group portion).</p><p num="0030">One of the terminal ends of the (meth)acrylic
compound having an oxetanyl group of the present
invention is a reactive oxetanyl group, while the other
terminal end is a (meth)acrylic group. Since the
compound is a difunctional monomer having both an
oxetanyl group which is a cationic polymerizable group
and a (meth)acrylic group which is radical- or
anionic-polymerizable group, the (meth)acrylic group
can be polymerized only by radical- or
anionic-polymerization, thereby obtaining a side chain
type-liquid crystalline polymeric substance having an
oxetanyl group which is a cationic polymerizable group.
That is, a side chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric
substance is synthesized by anionic-or
radical-polymerization of the (meth)acrylic group in
the presence of the cationic polymerizable oxetanyl
group whose reactivity is low under the conditions
except those for cationic polymerization. A side
chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric substance is 
lower in Tg than a main chain-type liquid crystalline
polymeric substance and thus can be easily oriented at
a low temperature. After orienting the side-chain type
liquid crystalline polymeric substance thus obtained,
the oxetanyl group is polymerized, i.e., cured and
cross-linked in the presence of cations, resulting in
the rise of Tg. Therefore, a liquid crystal film with
improved heat resistance and mechanical strength can
be produced from the resulting side chain-type liquid
crystalline polymeric substance.</p><p num="0031">No particular limitation is imposed on the method
of synthesizing the (meth)acrylic compound having an
oxetanyl group which can, therefore, be synthesized
using any of conventional organic chemistry synthesis
methods.</p><p num="0032">For example, a portion having an oxetanyl group
is coupled to a portion having a (meth)acrylic group
by means of the Williamson's ether synthesis or an ester
synthesis using a condensing agent thereby
synthesizing a (meth)acrylic compound having two
reactive functional groups, i.e., an oxetanyl group and
a (meth)acrylic group. More specifically, the
(meth) acrylic compound having an oxetanyl group of the
present invention can be synthesized by the following
processes: <img id="img-00160001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00160001.tif" inline="no" he="139"/></p><p num="0033">The abbreviations in the above formulas indicate
the following compounds:
<sl><li>DCC : 1,3-dicyclohexylcarbodiimide</li><li>DMAP : 4-dimethylaminopyridine</li><li>DCM : dichloromethane</li><li>PPTS : pyridinium-p-toluene sulfonate</li><li>THF : tetrahydrofuran</li><li>DMF : dimethylformamide</li><li>BHT : 2,6-di-t-butyl-4-methylphenol</li></sl></p><p num="0034">The side chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric
substance of the present invention is one containing 
a unit represented by formula (7) below derived from
a (meth)acrylic compound having an oxetanyl group
represented by formula (1):
<img id="img-00170001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00170001.tif" inline="no" he="49"/></p><p num="0035">The side chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric
substance containing a unit represented by formula (7)
can be easily synthesized by homopolymerizing the
(meth)acrylic group portion of the (meth)acrylic
compound having an oxetanyl group of formula (1) or
copolymerizing the same with another (meth)acrylic
compound by way of radical or anionic polymerization.
No particular limitation is imposed on the
polymerization conditions. Therefore, the
polymerization may be carried out under normal
conditions.</p><p num="0036">As an example of the radical polymerization, a
method may be used in which a (meth)acrylic compound
is solved in a solvent such as dimethylformamide (DMF)
and reacted at a temperature of 80 to 90 °C for several
hours using 2,2'-azobisisobutylonitrile (AIBN) or
benzoyl peroxide (BPO) as an initiator. Alternatively,
a method is effective in which in order to allow the 
liquid crystal phase to be stably exhibited, a living
radical polymerization is conducted using a copper (I)
bromide/2,2'-bipyridyl-based or TEMPO-based initiator
so as to control the molecular weight distribution.
These radical polymerizations are needed to be
conducted strictly under deoxidation conditions.</p><p num="0037">As an example of the anionic polymerization, a
method may be used in which a (meth)acrylic compound
is solved in a solvent such as tetrahydrofuran (THF)
and reacted using a strong base such as organic lithium
compounds, organic sodium compounds or a Grignard
reagent. Alternatively, this polymerization can be
converted to a living anionic polymerization by
optimizing the initiator or reaction temperature
thereby controlling the molecular weight distribution.
These anionic polymerizations are needed to be
conducted strictly under dehydration and deoxidation
conditions.</p><p num="0038">No particular limitation is imposed on the type
of a (meth) acrylic compound to be copolymerized as long
as the compound exhibits a liquid crystallinity.
However, preferred are (meth)acrylic compounds having
a mesogen group because it can enhance the liquid
crystallinity of the resulting polymeric substance.
More specifically, particularly preferred are those as
represented by the following formulas: <img id="img-00190001" orientation="unknown" wi="162" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00190001.tif" inline="no" he="61"/></p><p num="0039">The side chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric
substance of the present invention contains a unit of
formula (7) in an amount of preferably 5 to 100 percent
by mol and particularly preferably 10 to 100 percent
by mol. The side chain-type liquid crystalline
polymeric substance of the present invention has a
weight average molecular weight of preferably 2, 000 to
100,000 and particularly preferably 5,000 to 50,000.</p><p num="0040">Next, the polymeric liquid crystal material
containing the side chain-type liquid crystalline
polymeric substance of the present invention will be
described herein below.</p><p num="0041">The polymeric liquid crystal material of the
present invention contains the side chain-type liquid
crystalline polymeric substance of the present
invention in an amount of at least 10 percent by mass
or more, preferably 30 percent by mass or more, and more
preferably 50 percent by mass or more. A composition
containing less than 10 percent by mass of the side
chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric substance is 
not preferred because the concentration of the
polymeric group in the composition will be reduced and
thus the mechanical strength after the polymerization
will be insufficient.</p><p num="0042">The polymeric liquid crystalline composition of
the present invention may contain various compounds
which can be mixed without disturbing the liquid
crystallinity, other than the side chain-type liquid
crystalline polymeric substance. Examples of such
compounds are compounds having cationic polymerizable
functional group such as oxetanyl, epoxy and vinylether
groups, various polymeric substances having a film
forming capability, and various low molecular- or
polymeric-compounds exhibiting a nematic-,
cholesteric-, or discotic liquid crystallinity.
Furthermore, various optically active substances
regardless of whether it exhibits a liquid
crystallinity or not may be blended so as to allow the
polymeric liquid crystalline composition to exhibit a
cholesteric liquid crystallinity.</p><p num="0043">After the polymeric liquid crystal material of the
present invention is subjected to an orientation
treatment, the oxetanyl group is cross-linked by
cationic polymerization thereby improving the heat
resistance of the resulting liquid crystal film.
Therefore, in order to allow the cationic
polymerization to progress easily and rapidly, the 
polymeric liquid crystalline composition preferably
contains a photo- or thermal-cation generator which
generates cations by an external force such as light
or heat. If necessary, various sensitizers may be used
in combination.</p><p num="0044">The term "photo cation generator" used herein
denotes a compound which can generate cations by
irradiation of a light with a specific wavelength and
may be organic sulfonium salt-, iodonium salt-, or
phosphonium salt-based compounds. Counter ions of
these compounds are preferably antimonate, phosphate,
and borate. Specific examples are Ar<sub>3</sub>S<sup>+</sup>SbF<sub>6</sub><sup>-</sup>, Ar<sub>3</sub>P<sup>+</sup>BF<sub>4</sub><sup>-</sup>,
and Ar<sub>2</sub>I<sup>+</sup>PF<sub>6</sub><sup>-</sup> wherein Ar indicates a phenyl or
substituted phenyl group. Sulfonic acid esters,
triazines, diazomethanes, β-ketosulfone,
iminosulfonato, and benzoinsulfonate are also
eligible.</p><p num="0045">The term "thermal cation generator" used herein
denotes a compound which can generate cations by being
heated to a certain temperature and may be
benzylsulfonium salts, benzylammonium salts,
benzylpyridinium salts, benzylphosphonium salts,
hydradinium salts, carbonic acid esters, sulfonic acid
esters, amineimides, antimony pentachloride-acetyl
chloride complexes, diaryliodonium salt-dibenzyloxy
copper, and halogenated boron-tertiary amine adducts.</p><p num="0046">Since the amount of the cation generators to be 
added in the polymeric liquid crystalline composition
varies depending on the structure of the mesogen
portion or spacer portions constituting the side
chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric substance to
be used, the equivalent weight of the oxetanyl group,
and the conditions for liquid crystal orientation, it
can not be determined with certainty. However, it is
within the range of usually 100 ppm by mass to 20 percent
by mass, preferably 100 ppm by mass to 10 percent by
mass, more preferably 0.2 percent by mass to 7 percent
by mass, and most preferably 0.5 percent by mass to 5
percent by mass. The amount of less than 100 ppm by
mass is not preferred because the polymerization may
not progress due to the insufficient amount of cation
to be generated. The amount of more than 20 percent
by mass is not also preferred because the cation
generator remains in a large amount in the resulting
liquid crystal film and thus the light resistance
thereof would be deteriorated.</p><p num="0047">Next, the method of producing a liquid crystal
film using a liquid crystal material containing the
above-described polymeric liquid crystalline
composition will be described hereinafter. Although
not restricted, the liquid crystal film may be produced
by developing the liquid crystal material over an
alignment substrate to be oriented and fixing the
orientation by subjecting the material to light 
irradiation and/or a heat treatment.</p><p num="0048">First of all, the liquid crystalline material of
the present invention is developed over an alignment
substrate thereby aligning the material. Examples of
the alignment substrate are films of such as polyimide,
polyphenylene sulfide, polyphenylene oxide, polyether
ether ketone, polyethylene naphthalate, polyethylene
terephthalate, polyarylate, and triacetyl cellulose.
Although some of these films exhibit a sufficient
capability to align the liquid crystalline material and
thus can be used as aligning substrates as they are,
most of them are used after being subjected to a
treatment such as rubbing, stretching, polarization
irradiation, or skew ray irradiation such that the
films exhibit or are enhanced in alignment capability.
Alternatively, a conventional alignment film such as
polyimide, polyvinyl ether, or polyvinyl cinnamate may
be laminated over the substrate film and subjected to
a treatment such as rubbing, stretching, polarization
irradiation, or skew ray irradiation so as to impart
the aligning capability.</p> <p num="0049">In the case where there are problems that the
alignment substrate to be used is not optically
isotropic, the resulting liquid crystal film is opaque
at a wavelength region where it is intended to be used,
or the alignment substrate is so thick that it causes
a problem in practical use, the alignment substrate may 
be used temporarily until the liquid crystal film is
laminated over and transferred to an optically
isotropic film or a transparent film with which the
liquid crystal film is transparent at a wavelength
region where it is intended to be used or attached to
a liquid crystal cell. The transferring method may
be any conventional method. For example, as disclosed
in Japanese Patent Laid-Open Publication Nos. 4-57017
and 5-333313, there may be used a method in which after
a liquid crystal layer with an alignment substrate is
laminated via a pressure sensitive adhesive or adhesive
over a substrate on which the liquid crystal layer is
to be transferred and the surface is cured using an
pressure-sensitive adhesive or adhesive, only the
liquid crystal film is transferred on the substrate by
peeling off the alignment substrate.</p><p num="0050">Examples of the substrate onto which the liquid
crystal layer is transferred are a triacetyl cellulose
film such as Fujitack (manufactured by Fuji Photo Film
Co., Ltd.) and Konicatack (manufactured by Konica
Corp.); a transparent film such as TPX film
(manufactured by Mitsui Chemical Inc.), Arton film
(manufactured by JSR), Zeonex film (manufactured by
Nippon Zeon Co., Ltd) and Acryprene film (manufactured
by Mitsubishi Rayon Co., Ltd.); and a polyethylene
terephthalate film treated with silicone or provide on
its surface with a peelable layer. If necessary, the 
liquid crystal film may be transferred directly to a
polarizing film.</p><p num="0051">No particular limitation is imposed on the
pressure sensitive adhesive or adhesive to be used for
transferring the liquid crystal film as long as it is
of optical grade. Therefore, there may be used
conventional acrylic-, epoxy-, or urethane-based ones.</p><p num="0052">The liquid crystal material is developed on an
alignment substrate and formed into a liquid crystal
material layer by a method in which the liquid crystal
material in a molten state is coated directly over an
alignment substrate or a method in which a solution of
the liquid crystal material is coated over an alignment
substrate and dried to remove the solvent.</p><p num="0053">No particular limitation is imposed on the solvent
used for preparing the solution as long as it can
dissolve the liquid crystal material of the present
invention and be evaporated under appropriate
conditions. Preferred examples of the solvent are
ketones such as acetone, methyl ethyl ketone, and
isophorone; ether alcohols such as butoxyethyl alcohol,
hexyloxyethyl alcohol, and methoxy-2-propanol; glycol
ethers such as ethylene glycol dimethyl ether and
diethylene glycol dimethyl ether; esters such as ethyl
acetate and ethyl lactate; phenols such as phenol and
chlorophenol; amides such as N,N-dimethylformamide,
N,N-dimethylacetoamide, and N-methylpyrrolidone; 
halogen-based solvents such as chloroform,
tetrachloroethane, and dichlorobenzene; and mixtures
thereof. A surfactant, a defoaming agent, or a
leveling agent may be added to the solution so as to
form a uniform film layer on an alignment substrate.</p> <p num="0054">No particular limitation is imposed on the methods
of coating the liquid crystalline material directly or
the solution thereof as long as they can ensure the
uniformity of the film layer. Therefore, there may be
used any conventional method. Examples of the method
are spin coating, die coating, curtain coating, dip
coating, and roll coating methods.</p> <p num="0055">In the method of coating the liquid crystal
material solution, it is preferred to add a drying
process for removing the solvent after coating. No
particular limitation is imposed on the drying method
as long as it can maintain the uniformity of the film
layer. Therefore, there may be used any conventional
method and thus the solvent may be removed in a heater
(furnace) or blowing hot air.</p> <p num="0056">The liquid crystal material layer formed on an
alignment substrate is subjected to a heat treatment
or the like so as to form a liquid crystal orientation
and further subjected to light irradiation and/or a
heat treatment to fix the orientation. In the first
heat treatment, the liquid crystal material is heated
to a temperature at which it exhibits a liquid crystal 
phase so as to allow the material to be oriented with
a self-orientability which the material naturally has.
Since the conditions for the heat treatment vary in the
optimum conditions and limits depending on the liquid
crystal phase behavior temperature (transition
temperature) of the liquid crystal material to be used,
it can not be determined with certainty. However, it
is within the range of usually 10 to 250 °C and
preferably 30 to 160 °C. The liquid crystal material
layer is heated at preferably a temperature equal to
the glass transition temperature or higher and more
preferably a temperature which is 10°C higher than the
glass transition temperature. A too low temperature
is not preferred because there is a possibility that
the orientation to the liquid crystal phase does not
progress sufficiently, while a too high temperature is
not also preferred because the cationic polymerizable
reactive group in the liquid crystal material and the
alignment substrate are adversely affected. The heat
treatment is conducted for usually 3 seconds to 30
minutes and preferably 10 seconds to 10 minutes. The
heat treatment for less than 3 seconds is not preferred,
because there is a possibility that the orientation may
not be achieved sufficiently. Whereas the heat
treatment for longer than 30 minutes is not also
preferred, because the productivity is deteriorated.</p><p num="0057">After forming the liquid crystal orientation by 
subjecting the liquid crystal material layer to the
heat treatment or the like, the liquid crystal material
is cured with the polymerization reaction of the
cationic polymerizable reactive group in the
composition while maintaining the liquid crystal
orientation state. This curing process is conducted
to fix the liquid crystal orientation thus formed by
a curing (cross-linking) reaction thereby modifying
the film layer to be harder.</p><p num="0058">As described above, since the liquid crystal
material of the present invention has a cationic
polymerizable reactive group, it is preferred to use
a cationic polymerization initiator (cation generator)
for polymerizing (cross-linking) the reactive group.
As such a polymerization initiator, a photo cation
generator is preferred to a thermal cation generator.</p><p num="0059">In the case of using a photo cation generator,
after addition thereof, the processes prior the thermal
treatment for the liquid crystal orientation are
conducted under dark conditions (conditions where
light is shielded to an extent that the photo cation
generator does not dissociate) whereby the liquid
crystalline material does not cure until being
subjected to the orientation process and thus can be
oriented to a liquid crystal phase while maintaining
sufficient flowability. Thereafter, a light from a
light source capable of emitting an appropriate 
wavelength of light is irradiated so as to generate
cations thereby curing the liquid crystal material.</p><p num="0060">The light irradiation is conducted by irradiating
a light from a light source having a spectrum in an
absorption wavelength of the photo cation generator to
be used such as a metal halide lamp, a high-pressure
mercury lamp, a low-pressure mercury lamp, a xenon lamp,
an arc discharge lamp, and a laser thereby decomposing
the photo cation generator. The irradiation dose per
cm<sup>2</sup> is within the range of generally 1 to 2000 mJ and
preferably 10 to 1000 mJ in the integrated irradiation
dose. However, when the absorption region of the photo
cation generator is extremely different from the
spectrum of the light source or the liquid crystal
material itself can absorb a light in the wavelength
of the light source, the irradiation dose is not limited
to the above range. In these cases, a method may be
employed in which a suitable photo sensitizer or two
or more kinds of photo cation generators having
different absorption wavelengths are used.</p><p num="0061">The temperature at the time of the light
irradiation needs to be within the range wherein the
liquid crystal material exhibits a liquid crystal
orientation. Furthermore, the light irradiation is
preferably conducted at a temperature which is the Tg
of the liquid crystalline material, or higher in order
to conduct the curing effectively. </p><p num="0062">The liquid crystal material layer produced
through the above-described processes becomes a
sufficiently solid and strong film. More specifically,
since the three-dimensional bond of the mesogen portion
is archived by the curing reaction, the liquid crystal
material layer (film) of the present invention is
improved not only in heat-resistance (rise of the
temperature at which the liquid crystal orientation is
maintained) but also in mechanical strength such as
resistance to scratch, wear and cracking. The present
invention is of great significance in the industrial
sense because it can achieve the directly-opposed
purposes, i.e., the control of a liquid crystal
orientation at ease and the improvements of the
thermal/mechanical strength, at the same time.</p><p num="0063">The liquid crystal material layer wherein the
liquid crystal orientation is fixed can be used as an
optical film in the form in which the film remains
supported on the alignment substrate (alignment
substrate/(alignment layer)/liquid crystal film), in
the form in which the film is transferred to a
transparent substrate film or the like other than the
alignment substrate (transparent substrate
film/liquid crystal film), or in the form of a single
layer of the liquid crystal film.</p><p num="0064">The liquid crystal orientation state which the
liquid crystal material layer of the present invention 
will be able to assume can be controlled by properly
selecting the side chain-type liquid crystalline
polymeric substance and the structures of the other
compounds constituting the liquid crystal material.
The liquid crystal material layer of the present
invention can assume a nematic orientation, a twisted
nematic orientation, a cholesteric orientation, a
nematic hybrid orientation, a smectic orientation, or
a smectic C<sup>*</sup> orientation and an optical film wherein
the orientation is fixed can be produced.</p><p num="0065">The liquid crystal film of the present invention
can be used particularly as an optical film and mounted
in a liquid crystal display. Optical films have
various uses and are preferably used as optical
retardation films, color compensation films, viewing
angle improving films, circular polarizer films, and
optical rotatory films.</p><p num="0066">For example, an optical film wherein a nematic or
twisted nematic orientation is fixed functions as an
optical retardation film and a compensation plate for
an STN-, TN-, OCB-, or HAN-transmission or reflection
type liquid crystal display. An optical film wherein
a cholesteric or smectic C<sup>*</sup> orientation is fixed can
be used as a polarizing reflective film for luminance
enhancement, a reflection color filter, and various
decoration films utilizing color variations of
reflection light depending on viewing angles due to the 
selective reflection. An optical film wherein a
smectic orientation is fixed can be used as a
diffraction film. An optical film wherein a nematic
hybrid orientation is fixed can be used as an optical
retardation film or wave plate utilizing a retardation
upon viewing from the front and a viewing angle
improving film for a TN-type liquid crystal display
utilizing the asymmetric nature of viewing angle
dependency of retardation.</p><p num="0067">A side chain-type liquid crystalline polymeric
substance can be easily produced by radical or anionic
polymerization of the (meth) acrylic compound having an
oxetanyl group of the present invention. The
side-chain type liquid crystalline polymeric substance
can be easily oriented at a low temperature and is
cation-polymerized so as to polymerize and cross-link
the oxetanyl group thereby obtaining a liquid crystal
film with fixed orientation. The resulting liquid
crystal film is enhanced in heat resistance and
hardness and excellent in mechanical strength.</p><p num="0068">The present invention will be further described
in the following examples, but the present invention
should not be construed as being limited thereto.</p><p num="0069">The analyzing methods used in the examples are as
follows.</p><heading>(1) <sup>1</sup>H-NMR measurement</heading><p num="0070">A compound was dissolved in deuterated chloroform 
and the composition was determined by means of <sup>1</sup>H-NMR
at 400 MHz (JNM-GX400 manufactured by Nippon
Electronics Co., Ltd.).</p><heading>(2) GPC measurement</heading><p num="0071">The GPC measurement was carried out by dissolving
a compound in tetrahydrofuran and using 8020 GPC system
manufactured by Tosoh corporation equipped with
TSK-GEL, Super H1000, Super H2000, Super H3000, and
Super H4000 which are connected in series and
tetrahydrofuran as an eluent solvent. Polystyrene was
used as a standard for calibration of molecular weight.</p><heading>(3) Observation of phase behavior</heading><p num="0072">The liquid crystal phase behavior was observed
using an Olympus BH2 polarizing microscope while
heating a sample on a Metler hot stage.</p><p num="0073">The phase transition temperature was measured
using a differential scanning calorimeter DSC7
manufactured by Perkin Elmer Co.</p><heading>(4) Parameter measurement of liquid crystal film</heading><p num="0074">The retardation of a nematic orientation was
measured using KOBRA manufactured by Otsuka
Electronics Co., Ltd.</p><heading>Example 1</heading><p num="0075">In accordance with Scheme 1 below, an acrylic
compound having an oxetanyl group (acrylic compound 1)
was synthesized using 3-ethyl-3-hydroxymethyloxetane
(OXT-101, manufactured by Toagosei Co., Ltd.). </p><p num="0076">The <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic compound 1 is
shown in Fig. 1. "x" in the figures indicates the peak
of the impurities.
<img id="img-00340001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00340001.tif" inline="no" he="147"/></p><heading>Example 2</heading><p num="0077">In accordance with Scheme 2 below, an acrylic
compound having an oxetanyl group (acrylic compound 2)
was synthesized using 3-ethyl-3-hydroxymethyloxetane
(OXT-101, manufactured by Toagosei Co., Ltd).</p><p num="0078">The <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic compound 2 is 
shown in Fig. 2.
<img id="img-00350001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350001.tif" inline="no" he="79"/></p><heading>Example 3</heading><p num="0079">In accordance with Scheme 3 below, an acrylic
compound 3 having an oxetanyl group (acrylic compound
3) was synthesized. The <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 3 is shown in Fig. 3.
<img id="img-00350002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00350002.tif" inline="no" he="54"/></p><heading>Example 4</heading><p num="0080">In accordance with Scheme 4 below, an acrylic 
compound 4 having an oxetanyl group (acrylic compound
4)was synthesized. The <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 4 is shown in Fig. 4.
<img id="img-00360001" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00360001.tif" inline="no" he="41"/></p><heading>Example 5</heading><p num="0081">In accordance with Scheme 5 below, an acrylic
compound 5 having an oxetanyl group (acrylic compound
5)was synthesized. The <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 5 is shown in Fig. 5.
<img id="img-00360002" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00360002.tif" inline="no" he="55"/></p><heading>Example 6</heading><p num="0082">In accordance with Scheme 6 below, an acrylic
compound 6 having an oxetanyl group (acrylic compound
6) was synthesized. The <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of the acrylic
compound 6 is shown in Fig. 6. <img id="img-00370001" orientation="unknown" wi="163" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00370001.tif" inline="no" he="61"/></p><heading>Reference Example 1</heading><p num="0083">In accordance with Scheme 7 below, acrylic
compounds (wherein m = 1) and (wherein m = 3) having
no oxetanyl group (acrylic compounds 7 and 8)were
synthesized. The <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum of each the acrylic
compounds 7 and 8 is shown in Fig. 7 and 8.
<img id="img-00370002" orientation="unknown" wi="161" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00370002.tif" inline="no" he="34"/></p><heading>Example 7</heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of side chain-type liquid crystalline
polyacrylates having an oxetanyl group</u></heading><p num="0084">The acrylic compounds 1 to 8 were subjected to a
radical-polymerization using
2,2' -azobisisobutylonitrile as an initiator and DMF as
a solvent under a nitrogen atmosphere at a temperature
of 90°C for 6 hours and reprecipitated with methanol
for purification thereby obtaining side chain-type 
liquid crystalline polyacrylates having an oxetanyl
group (Polyacrylates 1 to 12).</p><heading>Reference Example 2</heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of side chain-type liquid crystalline
polyacrylates having no oxetanyl group</u></heading><p num="0085">With the same procedures of Example 7, side
chain-type liquid crystalline polyacrylates having no
oxetanyl group (Polyacrylates 13 and 14) were
synthesized.</p><p num="0086">Table 1 below shows the formulations, molecular
weight, Tg and phase behavior of each of Polyacrylates
1 to 14. In Table 1, "Sm", "Nm" and "Iso" indicate
smectic phase, nematic phase, and isotropic phase,
respectively. A phase behavior indicated by "phase
(Sm)-temperature-phase (Nm) also indicates that the
polyacrylate exhibited a isotropic phase at a
temperature of 250 °C or higher.</p><p num="0087">Figs. 9 and 10 show the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrums of
Polyacrylates 4 and 13. <tables><table><tgroup cols="12"><tbody><row><entry align="center" namest="1">Polymer No.</entry><entry nameend="9" align="center" namest="2">Monomer Unit (molar ratio, percentage)</entry><entry align="center" namest="10">Weight Average Molecular Weight</entry><entry align="center" namest="11">Tg (°C)</entry><entry align="center" namest="12">phase Behavior</entry></row><row><entry align="center"/><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="center">8</entry></row><row><entry align="center">1</entry><entry align="right">100</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">39,600</entry><entry align="center">81</entry><entry align="left">Sm-170°C-Nm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">2</entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">21,500</entry><entry align="center">78</entry><entry align="left">Sm-152°C-Nm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">3</entry><entry align="right">20</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">80</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">9,700</entry><entry align="center">81</entry><entry align="left">Sm-138°C-Nm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">4</entry><entry align="right">10</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">90</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">9,500</entry><entry align="center">79</entry><entry align="left">Sm-109°C-Nm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">5</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">20</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">80</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">21,400</entry><entry align="center">71</entry><entry align="left">Sm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">6</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">20</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">80</entry><entry align="center">6,100</entry><entry align="center">61</entry><entry align="left">Sm-213°C-Nm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">7</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">20</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">80</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5,500</entry><entry align="center">56</entry><entry align="left">Sm-140°C-Nm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">8</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">20</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">40</entry><entry align="right">40</entry><entry align="center">5,500</entry><entry align="center">60</entry><entry align="left">Sm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">9</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">20</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">80</entry><entry align="center">5,600</entry><entry align="center">63</entry><entry align="left">Sm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">10</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">4,900</entry><entry align="center">66</entry><entry align="left">Sm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">11</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">5,200</entry><entry align="center">66</entry><entry align="left">Sm-123°C-Nm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">12</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">9,500</entry><entry align="center">74</entry><entry align="left">Sm-144°C-Iso</entry></row><row><entry align="center">13</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">100</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="center">6,600</entry><entry align="center">74</entry><entry align="left">Nm</entry></row><row><entry align="center">14</entry><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right"/><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="right">50</entry><entry align="center">7,900</entry><entry align="center">59</entry><entry align="left">Sm-128°C-Nm</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading>Reference Example 3</heading><heading><u style="single">Synthesis of a difunctional oxetane monomer</u></heading><p num="0088">In accordance with Scheme 8, a difunctional
oxetane monomer was synthesized. The <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum
of the monomer is shown in Fig. 11.</p><p num="0089">From the DSC measurement and Metler observation,
it was found that the monomer exhibited the phase
behavior represented by "crystal-69°C-nematic
phase-95°C-isotropic phase".
<img id="img-00390001" orientation="unknown" wi="164" img-format="tif" img-content="cf" file="00390001.tif" inline="no" he="65"/></p><heading>Example 8</heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of a liquid crystal film using a side
chain-type liquid crystalline polyacrylate
(Polyacrylate 4)</u></heading><p num="0090">1.0 g of Polyacrylate 4 obtained in Example 7 was
dissolved in 9 ml of cyclohexane and to the solution
was added in a dark place 0.05 g of a propylene carbonate
solution with 50%
triaryllsulfoniumhexafluoroantimonate (a reagent
manufactured by Aldrich Co.), followed by filtration
of the insolubles with a polytetrafluoroethylene
filter with a pore size of 0. 45 µm thereby preparing
a solution of a liquid crystal material.</p><p num="0091">The solution was spin-coated over a 50 µm
thickness polyethylene naphthalate film "Teonex Q-51"
manufactured by TEIJIN Limited whose surface had been
subjected to a rubbing treatment with a rayon cloth and
then dried at a temperature of 60°C on a hot plate. The
resulting liquid crystal material layer on the film was
irradiated with an ultraviolet light of the integrated
irradiation dose of 450 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> from a high-pressure
mercury lamp under an air atmosphere while heating at
a temperature of 150°C and then cooled thereby
obtaining a cured liquid crystal material layer.</p><p num="0092">Since the polyethylene naphthalate film used as
a substrate is large in birefringence and thus not
preferred as an optical film, the resulting film (the 
liquid crystal material layer) was transferred via an
ultraviolet curing-type adhesive "UV-1394"
manufactured by Toagosei Co., Ltd. onto a
triacetylcellulose film (TAG) thereby obtaining an
optical film. More specifically, UV-1394 with a
thickness of 5 µm was coated over the cured liquid
crystal material layer on the film and laminated with
a TAC film. After the laminate was subjected to an
irradiation of ultraviolet light of 400 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> from the
TAC film side so as to cure the adhesive, the
polyethylene naphthalate film (substrate) was peeled
off.</p><p num="0093">As a result of observations of the resulting
optical film using a polarizing microscope, it was
confirmed that it exhibited a monodomain uniform
nematic liquid crystal orientation without the
occurrence of disclination and the retardation was 115
nm. Only the liquid crystal material portion was
scrapped off and the glass transition temperature
thereof was measured using a DSC. As a result, it was
found to be 95°C. The pencil hardness of the liquid
crystal material surface of the film was on the order
of 2H and thus it was confirmed that the film had a
sufficient hardness.</p><p num="0094">The optical film was laminated via a non-carrier
pressure sensitive adhesive onto a 2mm thickness glass
plate and over the film was laminated a polarizer 
(SQW-862 manufactured by Sumitomo Chemical Co., Ltd. )
such that the rubbing axis of the liquid crystal layer
is aligned with the absorption axis of the polarizer.
This sample was observed through the polarizer on a
backlight and found to be a uniform film. After the
sample was kept in a thermostat whose temperature was
set at 80°C, for 24 hours, it was removed therefrom and
similarly observed. As a result, neither change nor
disorder in the liquid crystal orientation was
observed.</p><p num="0095">As described above, it was found that the use of
Polyacrylate 4 made it possible to produce a film which
exhibits an excellent liquid crystal orientability and
is improved in thermal stability and strength after
fixation of the liquid crystal orientation.</p><heading>Reference Example 4</heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of a liquid crystal film using a side
chain-type liquid crystalline polyacrylate
(Polyacrylate 13)</u></heading><p num="0096">1.0 g of Polyacrylate 13 obtained in Reference
Example 2 was dissolved in 9 ml of cyclohexane, followed
by filtration of the insolubles with a
polytetrafluoroethylene filter with a pore size of 0.45
µm thereby preparing a solution of a liquid crystal
material.</p><p num="0097">The solution was spin-coated over a 50 µm
thickness polyethylene naphthalate film "Teonex Q-51" 
manufactured by TEIJIN Limited whose surface had been
subjected to a rubbing treatment with a rayon cloth and
then dried at a temperature of 60°C on a hot plate. The
resulting liquid crystal material layer on the film was
heated at a temperature of 150°C for 5 minutes and then
quenched to room temperature thereby obtaining a liquid
crystal material layer.</p><p num="0098">Since the polyethylene naphthalate film used as
a substrate is large in birefringence and thus not
preferred as an optical film, the resulting film
(liquid crystal material layer) was transferred via an
ultraviolet curing-type adhesive "UV-1394"
manufactured by Toagosei Co., Ltd. onto a
triacetylcellulose film (TAC) thereby obtaining an
optical film. More specifically, UV-1394 with a
thickness of 5 µm was coated over the cured liquid
crystal material layer on the film and laminated with
a TAC film. After the laminate was subjected to an
irradiation of ultraviolet light of 400 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> from the
TAC film side so as to cure the adhesive, the
polyethylene naphthalate film (substrate) was peeled
off.</p><p num="0099">As a result of observations of the resulting
optical film using a polarizing microscope, it was
confirmed that it exhibited a monodomain uniform
nematic liquid crystal orientation without the
occurrence of disclination and the retardation was 100 
nm. However, after only the liquid crystal material
portion was scrapped off and the glass transition
temperature thereof was measured using a DSC, it was
found to be 80°C which is low. The pencil hardness of
the liquid crystal material surface of the film was on
the order of B and thus it was confirmed that the film
was too soft to be used as an optical film.</p><p num="0100">The film was laminated via a non-carrier pressure
sensitive adhesive onto a 2mm thickness glass plate and
over the film was laminated a polarizer (SQW-862
manufactured by Sumitomo Chemical Co., Ltd.) such that
the rubbing axis of the liquid crystal layer is aligned
with the absorption axis of the polarizer. This sample
was observed through the polarizer on a backlight and
found to be a uniform film. After the sample was kept
in a thermostat whose temperature was set at 80°C, for
24 hours, it was removed therefrom and similarly
observed. It was found that the film had voids at
peripheries due to the disordered liquid crystal
orientation.</p><heading>Example 9</heading><heading><u style="single">Preparation of a liquid crystal film using a side
chain-type liquid crystalline polyacrylate
(Polyacrylate 4)</u></heading><p num="0101">0.8 g of Polyacrylate 4 obtained in Example 7 and
0.2 g of the difunctional oxetane monomer obtained in
Reference Example 3 were dissolved in 9 ml of 
cyclohexane and to the solution was added in a dark place
0.05 g of a propylene carbonate solution with 50%
triallylsulfoniumhexafluoroantimonate (a reagent
manufactured by Aldrich Co.), followed by filtration
of the insolubles with a polytetrafluoroethylene
filter with a pore size of 0.45 µm thereby preparing
a solution of a liquid crystalline material.</p><p num="0102">The solution was spin-coated over a 100 µm
thickness polyimide film "KAPTON" manufactured by Du
Pont Co . whose surface had been subjected to a rubbing
treatment with a rayon cloth and then dried at a
temperature of 60°C on a hot plate. The resulting
liquid crystal material layer on the film was
irradiated with an ultraviolet light of the integrated
irradiation dose of 450 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> from a high-pressure
mercury lamp under an air atmosphere while heating at
a temperature of 150°C and then cooled thereby
obtaining a cured liquid crystal material layer.</p><p num="0103">Since the polyimide film used as a substrate was
brown and thus not preferred as an optical film, the
resulting film (liquid crystal material layer) was
transferred via an ultraviolet curing-type adhesive
"UV-1394" manufactured by Toagosei Co., Ltd. onto a
triacetylcellulose film (TAC) thereby obtaining an
optical film. More specifically, UV-1394 with a
thickness of 5 µm was coated over the cured liquid
crystal material layer on the film and laminated with 
a TAC film. After the laminate was subjected to an
irradiation of ultraviolet light of 400 mJ/cm<sup>2</sup> from the
TAG film side so as to cure the adhesive, the polyimide
film (substrate) was peeled off.</p><p num="0104">As a result of observations of the resulting
optical film using a polarizing microscope, it was
confirmed that it exhibited a monodomain uniform
nematic hybrid liquid crystal orientation without the
occurrence of disclination and the retardation viewed
from the front was 115 nm. The retardation viewed from
a direction obliquely at an angle of 40° from the
vertical along the rubbing axis was 141 nm, while that
from the opposite angle, i.e., -40° was 53 nm and
asymmetric to the 40° retardation. Furthermore,
there was no point wherein the retardation was 0nm at
any angle. From these observations, it was found that
the film exhibited a nematic hybrid orientation
structure.</p><p num="0105">Furthermore, only the liquid crystal material
portion was scrapped off and the glass transition
temperature thereof was measured using a DSC. As a
result, the Tg was not observed.</p><p num="0106">The optical film was laminated via a non-carrier
pressure sensitive adhesive onto a 2mm thickness glass
plate and over the film was laminated a polarizer
(SQW-862 manufactured by Sumitomo Chemical Co., Ltd.)
such that the rubbing axis of the liquid crystal layer 
is aligned with the absorption axis of the polarizer.
This sample was observed through the polarizer on a
backlight and found to be a uniform film. After the
sample was kept in a thermostat whose temperature was
set at 80°C, for 24 hours, it was removed therefrom and
similarly observed. As a result, neither change nor
disorder in the liquid crystal orientation was
observed.</p><p num="0107">The pencil hardness of the liquid crystal material
surface of the film was on the order of 2H and thus it
was confirmed that the film had a sufficient hardness.
As described above, it was found that the use of
Polyacrylate 4 made it possible to produce a film which
exhibits an excellent liquid crystal orientability and
is improved in thermal stability and strength after
fixation of the liquid crystal orientation.</p><heading>Example 10</heading><p num="0108">The optical film with a retardation of 115 nm
obtained in Example 8 (hereinafter referred to "optical
film A") and an optical film with a retardation of 265
nm obtained by the same procedure of Example 8 except
that thickness of the liquid crystal material layer
(hereinafter referred to "optical film B") was changed
were used in combination as a wide bandwidth λ /4 plate
and assembled with a transflective TFT-TNECB-type
liquid crystal cell with a reflector thereby producing
a liquid crystal display with the arrangement shown in 
Fig. 12. The liquid crystal cell contained ZLI-1695
manufactured by Merck Ltd as a liquid crystal material
which had been formed into a homogenously-oriented
liquid crystal layer with a thickness of 5 µm. The
pretilt angle at the cell interface was 2° , while the
Δnd of the liquid crystal cell was 310 nm. As a
polarizer, SQW-862 manufactured by Sumitomo Chemical
Co., Ltd. was used.</p><p num="0109">As a result, it was confirmed that CR = 8, i.e.,
an excellent white and black was achieved.</p><heading>Example 11</heading><p num="0110">Wide bandwidth λ/4 plates were formed with the
optical film A, the optical film with a front
retardation of 115nm and obtained in Example 9
(hereinafter referred to as "optical film C") , and the
optical film 12 obtained in Example 10 and assembled
with a TFT-transflective ECB-type liquid crystal cell
with a reflector thereby producing a liquid crystal
display with the arrangement shown in Fig. 13. The
liquid crystal cell contained ZLI-1695 manufactured by
Merck Ltd as a liquid crystalline material which had
been formed into a homogenously-oriented liquid
crystal layer with a thickness of 5 µm. The pretilt
angle at the cell interface was 2° , while the Δnd of
the liquid crystal cell was 310 nm. As a polarizer,
SQW-862 manufactured by Sumitomo Chemical Co. , Ltd. was
used. </p><p num="0111">As a result, it was confirmed that CR = 8, i.e.,
an excellent white and black was achieved. Furthermore,
it was also confirmed that a wider viewing angle can
be obtained with this display than that of Example 10.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>A (meth)acrylic compound having an oxetanyl
group represented by the formula

wherein R1 is hydrogen or methyl, R2 is hydrogen, methyl,
or ethyl, L1 and L2 each are selected from a single bond,
- O-, -O-CO-, and -CO-O-, M represents a formula
selected from formulas (2), (3) and (4) below, and n
and m are each independently an integer from 0 to 10:
- P1-L3-P2-L4-P3--P1-L3-P3-- P3-
wherein P1 and P2 are each independently a group selected
from formulas (5) below, P3 is a group selected from
formulas (6) below, and L3 and L4 are each independently
selected from a single bond, -CH=CH-, -C≡C-, -O-,
-O-CO- and -CO-O-
</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>A side chain-type liquid crystalline
polymeric substance obtained by homopolymerizing the
(meth)acrylic portion of the (meth)acrylic compound
having an oxetanyl group as defined in claim 1 or
copolymerizing same with another (meth)acrylic
compound.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The side chain-type liquid crystalline
polymeric substance according to claim 2 which has a
unit represented by formula (7) below derived from a
(meth)acrylic compound having an oxetanyl group as
defined in claim 1:
</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The side chain-type liquid crystalline
polymeric substance according to claim 3 which contains
a unit of said formula (7) in an amount of 5 to 100
percent by mol.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The side chain-type liquid crystalline
polymeric substance according to claim 2 wherein the
weight-average molecular weight is from 2,000 to
100,000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>A liquid crystal material which contains the
side-chain type liquid crystalline polymeric substance
as defined in claim 2 in an amount of 10 percent by mass
or more.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The liquid crystal material which further
contains a photo cationic initiator and/or a thermal
cationic initiator.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>A liquid crystal film which is formed by fixing
the orientation state of the liquid crystal material
as defined in claim 6 or 7.</claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>A method of producing a liquid crystal film
wherein the liquid crystal material as defined in claim
6 or 7 is developed over an alignment substrate so as
to align the liquid crystal material in a liquid crystal
orientation state, followed by fixing the orientation
by light irradiation and/or a heat treatment.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method of producing a liquid crystal film
according to claim 9 wherein said orientation state
is one obtained by fixing an orientation state selected
from the group consisting of nematic, twisted nematic,
cholesteric, and nematic hybrid orientations.</claim-text></claim><claim num="11"><claim-text>An optical film which comprises the liquid
crystal film as defined in claim 8.</claim-text></claim><claim num="12"><claim-text>The optical film according to claim 11 which
is selected from the group consisting of a retardation
film, a color compensation film, a viewing angle
improving film, a circular polarizing film, and an
optical rotatory film.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>