<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE patent-document
  PUBLIC "-//MXW//DTD patent-document XML//EN" "http://www.matrixware.com/dtds/patents/v1.2/patent-document.dtd"><patent-document ucid="EP-1416021-A1" country="EP" doc-number="1416021" kind="A1" lang="EN" family-id="32093543" status="new" date-produced="20090516" date="20040506"><bibliographic-data><publication-reference ucid="EP-1416021-A1" status="new" fvid="24023264"><document-id status="new" format="original"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1416021</doc-number><kind>A1</kind><date>20040506</date></document-id></publication-reference><application-reference ucid="EP-03078344-A" status="new" is-representative="NO"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>03078344</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20031022</date></document-id></application-reference><priority-claims status="new"><priority-claim ucid="US-28495702-A" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>28495702</doc-number><kind>A</kind><date>20021031</date></document-id></priority-claim></priority-claims><technical-data status="new"><classifications-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101AFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41J   2/01        20060101CFI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101ALI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">B41M   5/00        20060101CLI20060310RMJP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101A I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr><classification-ipcr status="new">C09D  11/00        20060101C I20051008RMEP        </classification-ipcr></classifications-ipcr><classification-ecla status="new"><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C</classification-symbol><classification-symbol scheme="EC">C09D  11/00C2B</classification-symbol></classification-ecla><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="DE">Bevorzugte Materialien für pigmentierte Tintenstrahldrucktinten</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN">Preferred materials for pigmented ink jet ink</invention-title><invention-title load-source="ep" status="new" lang="FR">Matériaux préférés pour encres pigmentées pour l'impression par jet d'encre</invention-title><citations><patent-citations><patcit ucid="EP-0732382-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>0732382</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA"  created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1167466-A1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1167466</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="EP-1193301-A1"  status="new"><document-id status="new"  format="epo"><country>EP</country><doc-number>1193301</doc-number><kind>A1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X"  name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit><patcit ucid="US-6245832-B1" status="new"><document-id status="new" format="epo"><country>US</country><doc-number>6245832</doc-number><kind>B1</kind></document-id><sources><source category="X" name="SEA" created-by-npl="N"/></sources></patcit></patent-citations></citations></technical-data><parties><applicants><applicant status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>EASTMAN KODAK CO</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>EASTMAN KODAK COMPANY</name></addressbook></applicant><applicant status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>EASTMAN KODAK COMPANY</last-name><address><street>343 State Street</street><city>Rochester, New York 14650</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></applicant></applicants><inventors><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>FLOOD ELMER C</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>KRZEMIEN WENDY S</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="epo"><addressbook><name>YAU HWEI-LING</name><address><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>FLOOD, ELMER C.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>KRZEMIEN, WENDY S.</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="intermediate"><addressbook><name>YAU, HWEI-LING</name></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>FLOOD, ELMER C.</last-name><address><street>c/o EASTMAN KODAK COMPANY 343 State Street</street><city>Rochester New York 14650-2201</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>KRZEMIEN, WENDY S.</last-name><address><street>c/o EASTMAN KODAK COMPANY 343 State Street</street><city>Rochester New York 14650-2201</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor><inventor status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>YAU, HWEI-LING</last-name><address><street>c/o EASTMAN KODAK COMPANY 343 State Street</street><city>Rochester New York 14650-2201</city><country>US</country></address></addressbook></inventor></inventors><agents><agent status="new" format="original"><addressbook><last-name>Weber, Etienne Nicolas</last-name><address><street>Kodak Industrie, Département Brevets, CRT, Zone Industrielle</street><city>71102 Chalon sur Saône Cedex</city><country>FR</country></address></addressbook></agent></agents></parties><international-convention-data><designated-states><ep-contracting-states><country>DE</country><country>FR</country><country>GB</country></ep-contracting-states></designated-states></international-convention-data></bibliographic-data><abstract load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><p>An ink jet ink composition comprising: from 40.0 to 99.0% by
weight of water; from 0.1 to 20.0% by weight of a pigment; from 0 to 70.0% by
weight of a water miscible co-solvent; and from 0.1 to 20.0 % by weight of a
water-reducible addition polymer; wherein the weight average molecular weight
of the polymer is from 2,000 to 100,000; the acid number is from 50 to 400; and
the acid group on the polymer is neutralized by an alkaline metal hydroxide such
as lithium hydroxide, sodium hydroxide potassium hydroxide, or a mixture
thereof; and wherein all weight percentages are based on the total weight of the
ink composition. An ink jet printing method is also disclosed.</p></abstract><description load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><heading><b>FIELD OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0001">This invention relates to pigmented inks for ink jet printing
employing water-reducible addition polymers of preferred composition.</p><heading><b>BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0002">Ink jet printing is a non-impact method for producing images by
the deposition of ink droplets on a substrate (paper, transparent film, fabric, etc.)
in response to digital signals. Ink jet printers have found broad applications
across markets ranging from industrial labeling to short run printing to desktop
document and pictorial imaging.</p><p num="0003">In ink jet recording processes, it is necessary that the inks being
used meet various performance requirements. Such performance requirements
are generally more stringent than those for other liquid ink applications, such as
for writing instruments (e.g., a fountain pen, felt pen, etc.). In particular, the
following conditions are generally required for inks utilized in ink j et printing
processes:
<sl><li>(1) The ink should possess physical properties such as viscosity, surface
tension, and electric conductivity matching the discharging conditions of the
printing apparatus, such as the driving voltage and driving frequency of a
piezoelectric electric oscillator, the form and material of printhead orifices, the
diameter of orifices, etc;</li><li>(2) The ink should be capable of being stored for a long period of time without
causing clogging of printhead orifices during use;</li><li>(3) The ink should be quickly fixable onto recording media, such as paper,
film, etc., such that the outlines of the resulting ink dots are smooth and there is
minimal blotting of the dotted ink;</li><li>(4) The printed image should be of high quality, such as having a clear color
tone and high density, have high gloss and high color gamut; </li><li>(5) The printed image should exhibit excellent waterfastness (water resistance)
and lightfastness (light resistance);</li><li>(6) The printed (ink) images should have good adhesion to the surface of
image receiving elements and should be durable and highly resistant to physical
and mechanical scratches or damages</li><li>(7) The ink should not chemically attack, corrode or erode surrounding
materials such as the ink storage container, printhead components, orifices, etc;</li><li>(8) The ink should not have an unpleasant odor and should not be toxic or
inflammable; and</li><li>(9) The ink should exhibit low foaming and high pH stability characteristics.</li></sl></p><p num="0004">The inks used in various ink jet printers can be classified as either
dye-based or pigment-based. A dye is a colorant that is molecularly dispersed or
solvated by a carrier medium. The carrier medium can be a liquid or a solid at
room temperature. A commonly used carrier medium is water or a mixture of
water and organic cosolvents. Each individual dye molecule is surrounded by
molecules of the carrier medium. In dye-based inks, no particles are observable
under the microscope. Although there have been many recent advances in the art
of dye-based ink jet inks, such inks still suffer from deficiencies such as low
optical densities on plain paper and poor lightfastness. When water is used as the
carrier medium, such inks also generally suffer from poor waterfastness.</p><p num="0005">Pigment-based inks have been gaining in popularity as a means of
addressing these limitations. In pigment-based inks, the colorant exists as
discrete particles. These pigment particles are usually treated with addenda
known as dispersants or stabilizers that serve to keep the pigment particles from
agglomerating and/or settling out.</p><p num="0006">Pigment-based inks suffer from a different set of deficiencies than
dye-based inks. One deficiency is that pigment-based inks interact differently
with specially coated papers and films, such as transparent films used for 
overhead projection and glossy papers and opaque white films used for high
quality graphics and pictorial output. In particular, it has been observed that
pigment-based inks produce imaged areas that are entirely on the surface of
coated papers and films, which result in images that have poor dry and wet
adhesion properties and can be easily smudged. In recent years, inkjet receivers
have been developed to have both high gloss and high porosity to give fast drying
capabilities. However, scratch mark smudges are more visible on high gloss
receivers. In order to provide a pigmented ink composition that can be used in
printing images on an ink jet porous glossy, receiving element having acceptable
durability and smudging resistance, polymers are often used as additive in
pigmented inks.</p><p num="0007">U.S. Patent 6,533,408, discloses classes of water-dispersible
polymers used in pigmented ink for both durability and ozone stability
improvement, including aqueous polyurethane dispersion. However, not all
polymers can be jetted from inkjet printhead easily and reliably.</p><p num="0008">Addition type polymers have been commonly used in pigment-based
inks, as an additive to pigment dispersions to improve print durability. The
polymer is usually not ionically or physically associated with pigment dispersion
in ink till printed on an ink jet receiver. U.S. Patent 4,597,794 teaches the use of
a polymer in pigment based inkjet ink, the polymer has both ethylenically
unsaturated carboxylic acid substituent as a hydrophilic portion and an aromatic
ring substituent as a hydrophobic portion, and wherein the said hydrophilic
portion constitutes from 2 to 40 weight percent of said polymer, and the
molecular weight of the polymer prefers to be 1,000 to 100,000. U.S. Patent
5,106,417 claims the use of polyacrylic resins containing carboxylic acid group in
pigmented ink to improve image quality and water resistance. Preferred acrylic
resins consist of ethyl acrylate, methyl methacrylate and acrylic or methacrylic
acid, having acid number of 50-300, and weight average molecular weight (Mw)
of 30,000 to 70,000. U.S. Patent 5,172,133 teaches the use acrylic acid-ethyl
acrylate-styrene copolymers in pigmented ink jet ink to improve storage stability 
and clogging resistance. U.S. Patent 5,883,157 teaches the use of styrene-maleic
anhydride copolymer in ink jet ink to improve image quality and dry time on
plain paper, and resistance to printhead clogging. The mean molecular weight of
styrene-maleic anhydride copolymer is from 1000 to 10,000. U.S. Patent
5,913,971 claims the use of a terpolymer obtained from acrylic acid, styrene and
α-methyl styrene and has an average molecular weight of 2,000 to 8,000 and an
acid number of 90 to 130 in pigment based ink jet ink to improve print durability
while maintaining good storage stability. WO 9,516,002 also teaches the use of
styrene-acrylic acid copolymer ammonium salt in black ink to improve jettability
from an inkjet printhead and high print density.</p><p num="0009">A general phenomenon has been noticed by the inventors that as
acid number of the polymer is increased and molecular weight of the polymer is
decreased in order to get satisfactory and uniform jettability from an ink jet
printhead, the print durability is compromised, especially if the printed image has
been wet with aqueous fluids. The deficiency is due to the fact that polymer has
increased water solubility. However, when a polymer having increased molecular
weight and decreased acid number is used, image defects due to lack of reliable
jettability is noticed, resulting in density decrease in printing direction across the
page.</p><p num="0010">Due to the low cost of materials made from addition
polymerization, it is desirable to find an optimum polymer composition to be used
in an ink jet ink so that printed images on an ink jet receiving element have
improved physical durability such as scratch and smudging resistance while
maintaining reliable jettability from ink jet printheads to produce quality images
at all time.</p><heading><b>SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0011">These and other objects are achieved in accordance with this
invention which relates to an ink jet ink composition comprising from 40.0 to
99.0% by weight of water; from 0.1 to 20.0%, usually 0.1 to 20.0%, and
preferably 0.2 to 15.0% by weight of a pigment; from 0 to 70.0%, usually from 
1.0 to 50%, and preferably 5.0 to 40.0% by weight of one or more water miscible
co-solvent; and from 0.1 to 20.0 %, preferably from 0.2 to 15.0% by weight of a
water-reducible addition polymer; wherein the addition polymer may comprise
the monomers of allyl compounds, ally esters, vinyl ethers, vinyl esters, vinyl
heterocyclic compounds, styrene or a styrene derivative, olefins and halogenated
olefins, itconic acid and esters, crotonic acid and esters, unsaturated nitriles,
acrylic acid or methacrylic acid and esters, vinyl alcohols, acrylamides and
methacrylamides, vinyl ketones, or multifunctional monomers; and wherein the
weight average molecular weight of the polymer is from 2,000 to 100,000,
preferably 4,000 to 40,000; the acid number is from 50 to 400, preferably 100 to
300; and the acid group on polymer is neutralized by alkaline metal hydroxide,
such as potassium hydroxide, sodium hydroxide or lithium hydroxide.</p><heading><b>DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</b></heading><p num="0012">The support for the ink-receiving element employed in the
invention can be paper or resin-coated paper, plastics such as a polyolefin type
resin or a polyester-type resin such as poly(ethylene terephthalate), polycarbonate
resins, polysulfone resins, methacrylic resins, cellophane, acetate plastics,
cellulose diacetate, cellulose triacetate, vinyl chloride resins, poly(ethylene
naphthalate), polyester diacetate, various glass materials, etc. or comprising an
open pore structure such as those made from polyolefins or polyesters. The
thickness of the support employed in the invention can be, for example, from 12
to 500 µm, preferably from 75 to 300 µm.</p><p num="0013">In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the continuous,
coextensive, porous ink-receiving layer contains organic or inorganic particles.
Examples of organic particles which may be used include core/shell particles such
as those disclosed in U.S. Patent 6,422,697, and homogeneous particles such as
those disclosed in U.S. Patent 6,475,602. Examples of organic particles that may
be used include acrylic resins, styrenic resins, cellulose derivatives, polyvinyl
resins, ethylene-allyl copolymers and polycondensation polymers such as 
polyesters. Examples of inorganic particles that may be used in the invention
include silica, alumina, titanium dioxide, clay, calcium carbonate, barium sulfate,
or zinc oxide.</p><p num="0014">In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the porous ink-receiving
layer comprises from 20% to 100% of particles and from 0% to 80% of
a polymeric binder, preferably from 80% to 95% of particles and from 20% to 5%
of a polymeric binder. The polymeric binder may be a hydrophilic polymer such
as poly(vinyl alcohol), poly(vinyl pyrrolidone), gelatin, cellulose ethers,
poly(oxazolines), poly(vinylacetamides), partially hydrolyzed poly(vinyl
acetate/vinyl alcohol), poly(acrylic acid), poly(acrylamide), poly(alkylene oxide),
sulfonated or phosphated polyesters and polystyrenes, casein, zein, albumin,
chitin, chitosan, dextran, pectin, collagen derivatives, collodian, agar-agar,
arrowroot, guar, carrageenan, tragacanth, xanthan, rhamsan and the like.
Preferably, the hydrophilic polymer is poly(vinyl alcohol), hydroxypropyl
cellulose, hydroxypropyl methyl cellulose, a poly(alkylene oxide), poly(vinyl
pyrrolidinone), poly(vinyl acetate) or copolymers thereof or gelatin.</p><p num="0015">In order to impart mechanical durability to an ink jet recording
element, crosslinkers which act upon the binder discussed above may be added in
small quantities. Such an additive improves the cohesive strength of the layer.
Crosslinkers such as carbodiimides, polyfunctional aziridines, aldehydes,
isocyanates, epoxides, polyvalent metal cations, vinyl sulfones, pyridinium,
pyridylium dication ether, methoxyalkyl melamines, triazines, dioxane
derivatives, chrom alum, zirconium sulfate and the like may be used. Preferably,
the crosslinker is an aldehyde, an acetal or a ketal, such as 2,3-dihydroxy-1,4-dioxane.</p><p num="0016">As used herein, a porous ink jet receiving layer is one that is
usually composed of inorganic or organic particles bonded together by a binder.
The amount of particles in this type of coating is often far above the critical
particle volume concentration, which results in high porosity in the coating.
During the ink jet printing process, ink droplets are rapidly absorbed into the 
coating through capillary action and the image is dry-to-touch right after it comes
out of the printer. Therefore, porous coatings allow a fast "drying" of the ink and
produce a smear-resistant image.</p><p num="0017">The porous ink-receiving layer can also comprise an open-pore
polyolefin, an open-pore polyester or an open pore membrane. An open pore
membrane can be formed in accordance with the known technique of phase
inversion. Examples of porous ink-receiving layer comprising an open-pore
membrane are disclosed in U.S. Patent 6,497,941 and U.S. Patent 6,503,607.</p><p num="0018">Pigments which may be used in the invention include organic and
inorganic pigments, alone or in combination, such as those as disclosed, for
example in U.S. Patents 5,026,427; 5,086,698; 5,141,556; 5,160,370; and
5,169,436. The exact choice of pigments will depend upon the specific
application and performance requirements such as color reproduction and image
stability. Pigments suitable for use in the present invention include, for example,
azo pigments, monoazo pigments, disazo pigments, azo pigment lakes, β-Naphthol
pigments, Naphthol AS pigments, benzimidazolone pigments, disazo
condensation pigments, metal complex pigments, isoindolinone and isoindoline
pigments, polycyclic pigments, phthalocyanine pigments, quinacridone pigments,
perylene and perinone pigments, thioindigo pigments, anthrapyrimidone
pigments, flavanthrone pigments, anthanthrone pigments, dioxazine pigments,
triarylcarbonium pigments, quinophthalone pigments, diketopyrrolo pyrrole
pigments, titanium oxide, iron oxide, and carbon black. Typical examples of
pigments which may be used include Color Index (C. I.) Pigment Yellow 1, 2, 3,
5, 6, 10, 12, 13, 14, 16, 17, 62, 65, 73, 74, 75, 81, 83, 87, 90, 93, 94, 95, 97, 98,
99, 100, 101, 104, 106, 108, 109, 110, 111, 113, 114, 116, 117, 120, 121, 123,
124, 126, 127, 128, 129, 130, 133, 136, 138, 139, 147, 148, 150, 151, 152, 153,
154, 155, 165, 166, 167, 168, 169, 170, 171, 172, 173, 174, 175, 176, 177, 179,
180, 181, 182, 183, 184, 185, 187, 188, 190, 191, 192, 193, 194; C. I. Pigment
Orange 1, 2, 5, 6, 13, 15, 16, 17, 17:1, 19, 22, 24, 31, 34, 36, 38, 40, 43, 44, 46,
48, 49, 51, 59, 60, 61, 62, 64, 65, 66, 67, 68, 69; C. I. Pigment Red 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 21, 22, 23, 31, 32, 38, 48:1, 48:2,
48:3, 48:4, 49:1, 49:2, 49:3, 50:1, 51, 52:1, 52:2, 53:1, 57:1, 60:1, 63:1, 66, 67,
68, 81, 95, 112, 114, 119, 122, 136, 144, 146, 147, 148, 149, 150, 151, 164, 166,
168, 169, 170, 171, 172, 175, 176, 177, 178, 179, 181, 184, 185, 187, 188, 190,
192, 194, 200, 202, 204, 206, 207, 210, 211, 212, 213, 214, 216, 220, 222, 237,
238,239,240,242,243,245,247,248,251,252,253,254,255,256,258,261,
264; C.I. Pigment Violet 1, 2, 3, 5:1, 13, 19, 23, 25, 27, 29, 31, 32, 37, 39, 42, 44,
50; C.I. Pigment Blue 1, 2, 9, 10, 14, 15:1, 15:2, 15:3, 15:4, 15:6, 15, 16, 18, 19,
24:1, 25, 56, 60, 61, 62, 63, 64, 66; C.I. Pigment Green 1, 2, 4, 7, 8, 10, 36, 45;
C.I. Pigment Black 1, 7, 20, 31, 32, and C.I. Pigment Brown 1, 5, 22, 23, 25, 38,
41, 42. In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the pigment employed is C.I.
Pigment Blue 15:3, C.I. Pigment Red 122, C.I. Pigment Yellow 155, C.I. Pigment
Yellow 74, bis(phthalocyanylalumino)tetraphenyldisiloxane or C.I. Pigment
Black 7.</p><p num="0019">The aqueous carrier medium for the ink composition employed in
the invention is water or a mixture of water and at least one water miscible co-solvent.
Selection of a suitable mixture depends on the requirements of the
specific application, such as desired surface tension and viscosity, the selected
pigment, drying time of the pigmented ink jet ink, and the type of paper onto
which the ink will be printed. Representative examples of water-miscible cosolvents
that may be selected include (1) alcohols, such as methyl alcohol, ethyl
alcohol, n-propyl alcohol, isopropyl alcohol, n-butyl alcohol, sec-butyl alcohol, t-butyl
alcohol, iso-butyl alcohol, furfuryl alcohol, and tetrahydrofurfuryl alcohol;
(2) ketones or ketoalcohols such as acetone, methyl ethyl ketone and diacetone
alcohol; (3) ethers, such as tetrahydrofuran and dioxane; (4) esters, such as ethyl
acetate, ethyl lactate, ethylene carbonate and propylene carbonate; (5) polyhydric
alcohols, such as ethylene glycol, diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol,
tetraethylene glycol, propylene glycol, polyethylene glycol, glycerol, 2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol
1,2,6-hexanetriol and thioglycol; (6) lower alkyl mono- or diethers
derived from alkylene glycols, such as ethylene glycol mono-methyl 
(or -ethyl) ether, diethylene glycol mono-methyl (or -ethyl) ether, diethylene
glycol mono-butyl (or -ethyl) ether, propylene glycol mono-methyl (or -ethyl)
ether, poly(ethylene glycol) butyl ether, triethylene glycol mono-methyl (or
-ethyl) ether and diethylene glycol di-methyl (or -ethyl) ether; (7) nitrogen
containing cyclic compounds, such as pyrrolidone, N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone, and
1,3-dimethyl-2-imidazolidinone; and (8) sulfur-containing compounds such as
dimethyl sulfoxide, 2,2'-thiodiethanol, and tetramethylene sulfone.</p><p num="0020">The amount of water-miscible co-solvent is in the range of 0 to
70%, usually 1.0 to 50.0 weight %, and preferably approximately 5 to 40
weight %, based on the total weight of the ink.</p><p num="0021">In general it is desirable to make a pigmented ink jet ink in the
form of a concentrated mill grind, which is subsequently diluted to the appropriate
concentration for use in the ink jet printing system. This technique permits
preparation of a greater quantity of pigmented ink from the equipment. If the mill
grind was made in a solvent, it is diluted with water and optionally other solvents
to the appropriate concentration. If it was made in water, it is diluted with either
additional water or water miscible solvents to the desired concentration. By
dilution, the ink is adjusted to the desired viscosity, color, hue, saturation density,
and print area coverage for the particular application. The method for the
preparation of the mill grind is disclosed in U.S. Patents 5,679,138; 5,670,139 and
6,152,999. In a preferred embodiment of the invention, a dispersant is also added
to the ink jet ink composition and is used to break down the pigment to submicron
size during the milling process and keeps the colloidal dispersion stable
and free from flocculation for a long period of time.</p><p num="0022">In the case of organic pigments, the ink may contain from 0.1 to
20.0%, preferably from 0.2 to 15.0% pigment by weight of the total ink
composition for most ink jet printing applications. If an inorganic pigment is
selected, the ink will tend to contain higher weight percentages of pigment than
with comparable inks employing organic pigments, and may be as high as 
approximately 75% in some cases, since inorganic pigments generally have higher
specific gravities than organic pigments.</p><p num="0023">The polymers used in this invention are commonly known as
water-reducible resins, which are polymers having hydrophilic groups in some
monomers. Polymer is not water soluble till neutralized by base. Acid number is
a common term used to indicate the amount of acid group in a polymer, it is
defined as mg of KOH required to neutralize 1 g of resin slids. The monomers
for the addition polymer of this invention can be selected from methyl
methacrylate, ethyl methacrylate, butyl methacrylate, ethyl acrylate, butyl
acrylate, hexyl acrylate, n-octyl acrylate, lauryl methacrylate, 2-ethylhexyl
methacrylate, nonyl acrylate, benzyl methacrylate, 2-hydroxypropyl methacrylate,
acrylonitrile, methacrylonitrile, vinyl acetate, vinyl propionate, vinylidene
chloride, vinyl chloride, styrene, α-methyl styrene, t-butyl styrene, vinyl toluene,
butadiene, isoprene, N,N-dimethyl acrylamide, acrylic acid, methacrylic acid,
chloromethacrylic acid, maleic acid and derivatives thereof.
Examples of suitable monomers include allyl compounds such as allyl
esters (e.g., allyl acetate, allyl caproate, etc.); vinyl ethers (e.g.,
methyl vinyl ether, butyl vinyl ether, methoxyethyl vinyl ether,
ethoxyethyl vinyl ether, chloroethyl vinyl ether, 1-methyl-2,2-dimethylpropyl
vinyl ether, hydroxyethyl vinyl ether, diethylene glycol
vinyl ether, dimethylaminoethyl vinyl ether, butylaminoethyl vinyl ether,
benzyl vinyl ether, tetrahydrofurfuryl vinyl ether, etc.); vinyl esters
(such as vinyl acetate, vinyl propionate, vinyl butyrate, vinyl
isobutyrate, vinyl dimethyl propionate, vinyl ethyl butyrate, vinyl
chloroacetate, vinyl dichloroacetate, vinyl methoxyacetate, vinyl phenyl
acetate, vinyl acetoacetate, etc.); vinyl heterocyclic compounds (such as
N-vinyl oxazolidone, N-vinylimidazole, N-vinylpyrrolidone, N-vinylcarbazole,
vinyl thiophene, N-vinylethyl acetamide, etc.); styrenes
(e.g, styrene, divinylbenzene, methylstyrene, dimethylstyrene,
ethylstyrene, isopropylstyrene, sodium styrenesulfonate, potassium 
styrenesulfinate, butylstyrene, hexylstyrene, cyclohexylstyrene,
benzylstyrene, chloromethylstyrene, trifluoromethylstyrene,
acetoxymethylstyrene, acetoxystyrene, vinylphenol, (t-butoxycarbonyloxy)
styrene, methoxystyrene, 4-methoxy-3-methylstyrene, dimethoxystyrene,
chlorostyrene, dichlorostyrene, trichlorostyrene, bromostyrene,
iodostyrene, fluorostyrene, methyl vinylbenzoate ester, vinylbenzoic acid,
etc.); crotonic acids (such as crotonic acid, crotonic acid amide,
crotonate esters (e.g., butyl crotonate, etc.)); vinyl ketones (e.g.,
methyl vinyl ketone, etc ); olefins (e.g., dicyclopentadiene, ethylene,
propylene, 1-butene, 5,5-dimethyl-1-octene, etc.); itaconic acids and
esters (e.g., itaconic acid, methyl itaconate, etc.), other acids such as
sorbic acid, cinnamic acid, methyl sorbate, citraconic acid, chloroacrylic
acid mesaconic acid, maleic acid, fumaric acid, and ethacrylic acid;
halogenated olefins (e.g., vinyl chloride, vinylidene chloride, etc.);
unsaturated nitriles (e.g., acrylonitrile, etc.); acrylic or methacrylic
acids and esters (such as acrylic acid, methyl acrylate, methacrylic acid,
methyl methacrylate, ethyl acrylate, butyl acrylate, butyl methacrylate,
2-hydroxyethyl methacrylate, 2- acetoacetoxyethyl methacrylate,
sodium-2-sulfoethyl acrylate, 2aminoethylmethacrylate hydrochloride,
glycidyl methacrylate, ethylene glycol dimethacrylate, etc.); and
acrylamides and methacrylamides (such as acrylamide, methacrylamide,
N-methylacrylamide, N,N- dimethylacrylamide, N-isopropylacrylamide,
N-s-butylacrylamide, N-t- butylacrylamide, N-cyclohexylacrylamide,
N-(3-aminopropyl)methacrylamide hydrochloride,
N-(3-dimethylaminopropyl)methacrylamide hydrochloride, N,
N-dipropylacrylamide, N-(1,1-dimethyl-3-oxobutyl)acrylamide, N-(1,1,2-trimethylpropyl)acrylamide,
N-(1,1,3,3-tetramethylbutyl)acrylamide, N-(1-phthalamidomethyl)acrylamide,
sodium N-(1,1-dimethyl-2-sulfoethyl)acrylamide,
N-butylacrylamide, N-(1,1-dimethyl-3-oxobutyl)acrylamide,
N-(2-carboxyethyl)acrylamide, 3-acrylamido-3-methylbutanoic 
acid, methylene bisacrylamide, etc.). The polymer of this
invention can be prepared by emulsion polymerization, solution polymerization or
bulk polymerization technique well known in the art. Furthermore, the addition
polymer of this invention has a weight average molecular weight of 2,000 to
100,000, preferably 4,000 to 40,000; an acid number of 50 to 400, preferably 100
to 300; and the acid group, preferably 75% to 100%, is neutralized by alkaline
metal hydroxide, such as potassium hydroxide, sodium hydroxide or lithium
hydroxide.</p><p num="0024">The addition polymer used in the invention is present in the ink jet
ink generally from 0.1% to 20% by weight, preferably from 0.2% to 15% by
weight based on the total weight of the ink.</p><p num="0025">Jet velocity, separation length of the droplets, drop size and stream
stability are greatly affected by the surface tension and the viscosity of the ink.
Pigmented ink jet inks suitable for use with ink jet printing systems should have a
surface tension in the range of 20 dynes/cm to 60 dynes/cm and, more preferably,
in the range 30 dynes/cm to 50 dynes/cm. Control of surface tensions in aqueous
inks is accomplished by additions of small amounts of surfactants. The level of
surfactants to be used can be determined through simple trial and error
experiments. Anionic and cationic surfactants may be selected from those
disclosed in U. S. Patents 5,324,349; 4,156,616 and 5,279,654 as well as many
other surfactants known in the ink jet ink art. Commercial surfactants include the
Surfynols® from Air Products; the Zonyls® from DuPont and the Fluorads®
from 3M.</p><p num="0026">A humectant is added to the composition employed in the process
of the invention to help prevent the ink from drying out or crusting in the orifices
of the ink jet printhead. Polyhydric alcohol humectants useful in the composition
employed in the invention for this purpose include, for example, ethylene glycol,
diethylene glycol, triethylene glycol, propylene glycol, tetraethylene glycol,
polyethylene glycol, glycerol, 2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol, 1,2,6-hexanetriol and
thioglycol. The humectant may be employed in a concentration of from 10 to 
50% by weight. In a preferred embodiment, diethylene glycol or a mixture of
glycerol and diethylene glycol is employed at a concentration of between 10 and
20% by weight.</p><p num="0027">The ink has physical properties compatible with a wide range of
ejecting conditions, i.e., driving voltages and pulse widths for thermal ink jet
printing devices, driving frequencies of the piezo element for either a drop-on-demand
device or a continuous device, and the shape and size of the nozzle.</p><p num="0028">A penetrant (0-10% by weight) may also be added to the ink
composition employed in the process of the invention to help the ink penetrate the
receiving substrate, especially when the substrate is a highly sized paper. A
preferred penetrant for the inks employed in the present invention is n-propanol at
a final concentration of 1-6% by weight.</p><p num="0029">A biocide (0.01-1.0% by weight) may also be added to the ink
composition employed in the process of the invention to prevent unwanted
microbial growth which may occur in the ink over time. A preferred biocide for
the inks employed in the present invention is Proxel® GXL (Zeneca Colours Co.)
at a concentration of 0.05-0.5% by weight. Additional additives that may
optionally be present in ink jet inks include thickeners, conductivity enhancing
agents, anti-kogation agents, drying agents, and defoamers.</p><p num="0030">Ink jet inks made using water-dispersible polymers employed in
this invention are employed in ink jet printing wherein liquid ink drops are
applied in a controlled fashion to an ink receiving substrate, by ejecting ink
droplets from plurality of nozzles, or orifices, in a print head of ink jet printers.</p><p num="0031">Commercially available ink jet printers use several different
methods to control the deposition of the ink droplets. Such methods are generally
of two types: continuous stream and drop-on-demand.</p><p num="0032">In drop-on-demand systems, a droplet of ink is ejected from an
orifice directly to a position on the ink receiving layer by pressure created by, for
example, a piezoelectric device, an acoustic device, or a thermal process
controlled in accordance digital data signals. An ink droplet is not generated and 
ejected through the orifices of the print head unless it is needed. Ink jet printing
methods, and related printers, are commercially available and need not be
described in detail.</p><p num="0033">The following examples illustrate the utility of the present
invention.</p><heading><b>EXAMPLES</b></heading><heading><u style="single">Example 1</u></heading><p num="0034">Magenta pigment dispersion was prepared as described below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry nameend="2" align="left" namest="1">Magenta Pigment Dispersion 1 (MD-1)</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   Polymeric beads, mean diameter of 50 micron (milling media)</entry><entry align="center">325 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   Quinacridone magenta (Pigment Red 122) from Sun Chemical Co.</entry><entry align="center">30 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   Oleoyl methyl taurine, (OMT) potassium salt</entry><entry align="center">9 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   Deionized water</entry><entry align="center">210.8 g</entry></row><row><entry align="left">   Proxel GXL ® (biocide from Zeneca)</entry><entry align="center">0.2 g</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0035">The above components were milled in a 2 liter double walled
vessel obtained from BYK-Gardner using a high energy media mill manufactured
by Morehouse-Cowles Hochmeyer. The mill was run for approximately 8 hours
at room temperature. The dispersion was separated from the milling media by
filtering the millgrind through a 4-8 µm KIMAX® Buchner Funnel obtained from
VWR Scientific Products.</p><heading><u style="single">Preparation of addition polymer solutions</u></heading><heading><u style="single">P1</u></heading><p num="0036">Jonrez IJ-4655, a styrene-acrylic resin material was obtained from
Westvaco in un-neutralized solid form. The weight average molecular weight is 
5,600, glass transition temperature is 80°C and acid number is 230, quoted from
Westvaco.</p><heading><u style="single">P1-KOH</u></heading><p num="0037">40 grams of P-1, 87.4 g of 10% KOH solution, and 32.6 g of water
were mixed in a sealed glass container. The mixture was stirred in 60°C for 16
hours to obtain a clear solution of 25% P-1 in which 95% of acid was neutralized
with KOH.</p><heading><u style="single">P1-NaOH</u></heading><p num="0038">40 grams of P-1, 62.4 g of 10% NaOH solution, and 57.6 g of
water were mixed in a sealed glass container. The mixture was stirred in 60°C for
16 hours to obtain a clear solution of 25% P-1 in which 95% of acid was
neutralized with NaOH.</p><heading><u style="single">P1-LiOH</u></heading><p num="0039">40 grams of P-1, 6.56 g of LiOH monohydrate, and 113.44 g of
water were mixed in a sealed glass container. The mixture was stirred in 60°C for
16 hours to obtain a clear solution of 25% P-1 in which 95% of acid was
neutralized with LiOH.</p><heading><u style="single">P1-DMEA</u></heading><p num="0040">40 grams of P-1, 6.56 g of LiOH monohydrate, and 113.44 g of
water were mixed in a sealed glass container. The mixture was stirred in 60°C for
16 hours to obtain a clear solution of 25% P-1 in which 95% of acid was
neutralized with NH<sub>4</sub>OH.</p><heading><u style="single">P1-DMEA</u></heading><p num="0041">40 grams of P-1, 13.90 g of N,N-dimethylethanol amine, and
106.10 g of water were mixed in a sealed glass container. The mixture was stirred 
in 60°C for 16 hours to obtain a clear solution of 25% P-1 in which 95% of acid
was neutralized with N,N-dimethylethanol amine.</p><heading><u style="single">P1-TEA</u></heading><p num="0042">40 grams of P-1, 16.00 g of triethylamine, and 104.00 g of water
were mixed in a sealed glass container. The mixture was stirred in 60°C for 16
hours to obtain a clear solution of 25% P-1 in which 95% of acid was neutralized
with triethylamine.</p><heading><u style="single">P1-TELA</u></heading><p num="0043">40 grams of P-1, 23.30 g of triethanolamine, and 96.80 g of water
were mixed in a sealed glass container. The mixture was stirred in 60°C for 16
hours to obtain a clear solution of 25% P-1 in which 95% of acid was neutralized
with triethanolamine.</p><heading><u style="single">P1-DELA</u></heading><p num="0044">40 grams of P-1, 16.40 g of diethanolamine, and 103.60 g of water
were mixed in a sealed glass container. The mixture was stirred in 60°C for 16
hours to obtain a clear solution of 25% P-1 in which 95% of acid was neutralized
with diethanolamine.</p><heading><u style="single">P1-EM</u></heading><p num="0045">40 grams of P-1, 17.90 g of 4-ethylmorpholine, and 102.10 g of
water were mixed in a sealed glass container. The mixture was stirred in 60°C for
16 hours to obtain a clear solution of 25% P-1 in which 95% of acid was
neutralized with 4-ethylmorpholine. </p><heading><u style="single">P2</u></heading><p num="0046">P-2 was TruDot IJ-4680 available from Westvaco Corporation,
supplied in solution form of 26% solids. It is a styrene-acrylic polymer having
acid number of 170 and Tg of 50C. Organic amine was used as the base to
solubilize the polymer.</p><heading><u style="single">P2-KOH</u></heading><p num="0047">P2-KOH was prepared by mixing 1000 grams of P2 solution
(TruDot IJ-4680, available from Westvaco Corporation) with 400 gram of 10%
KOH solution, and then followed by heating to 80C under vacuum to remove
volatile organic amine. The final solution was 25.84% in solids. The amine
counter ion for the acid on polymer was expected to be replaced by potassium ion
after the reaction.</p><heading><u style="single">Ink Preparation</u></heading><p num="0048">An ink formulation employed in this invention was prepared by
mixing all ingredients with mild stirring at room temperature. In addition to
magenta pigment PR122 from MD-1 at 2.2% and addition polymer at 2.0%, the
ink also contained glycerol at 6%, diethylene glycol at 20%, Dowanol EB ® at
2.5%, and Surfynol 465 ® at 0.2%, all by weight.</p><p num="0049">The pigment and addition polymers used in the inks employed in
this invention and the comparison inks are given in the following Table 1:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Ink</entry><entry align="center">Polymer Dispersion</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-1 (Control)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-2 (Control)</entry><entry align="center">P1-DMEA</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-3 (Control)</entry><entry align="center">P1-TEA</entry></row> <row><entry align="center">C-4 (Control)</entry><entry align="center">P1-TELA</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-5 (Control)</entry><entry align="center">P1-DELA</entry> </row> <row><entry align="center">C-6 (Control)</entry> <entry align="center">P1-EM</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-7 (Control)</entry><entry align="center">P1-NH4OH</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-1</entry><entry align="center">P1-KOH</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-2</entry><entry align="center">P1-NaOH</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-3</entry><entry align="center">P1-LiOH </entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-8 (Control)</entry><entry align="center">P2</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-4</entry><entry align="center">P2-KOH</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><heading><u style="single">Ink Jet Recording Elements</u></heading><p num="0050">Epson Premium Glossy Photo Paper@ SO41286, (Epson
Corporation), which is a porous glossy receiver, was used for inkjet printing.</p><heading><u style="single">Ink Jet Printing</u></heading><p num="0051">A series of inks having the ingredients shown in Table 1 were
added to empty Hewlett-Packard HP 692C ink cartridges and loaded into an HP
692C printer to print on Epson Ink jet receiver. A digital image of 4 inches wide
by 0.75 inches long area was printed across the page at 100% ink coverage.</p><heading><u style="single">Jetting non-uniformity</u></heading><p num="0052">Jetting non-uniformity is defined as the density difference between
the left side and right side of the image printed above. Status A reflectance
densities as measured by an X-Rite® densitometer on the two ends of imaged area
4 inches apart were recorded. The less difference in density between the two
sides of the printed image indicates the better jetting uniformity. It is most
desirable to get identical density (or zero density difference) from both sides of
the image.</p><heading><u style="single">Wet and Dry Rub Resistance</u></heading><p num="0053">The ink jet printed sample with 100% ink coverage prepared above
was subjected to wet and dry rub resistance tests. A wet rub resistance test was
carried out by placing an approximately 2.54 cm diameter water droplet on the
ink-coated sample surface for 2 minutes, after which the excess water was gently
wiped off using a paper towel. The above treated area was then rubbed with a dry
paper towel for 8 passes under a pressure of 200 grams over a 3.5 cm diameter
area. Status A reflectance density as measured by an X-Rite® densitometer on 
the tested area was recorded and compared to the optical density before testing.
Wet rub resistance is defined as the percentage of optical density (OD) retained
after testing. 100% density retained indicates no damage or loss or optical density
on the imaged area.</p><p num="0054">A dry rub resistance test was carried out by rubbing the samples
with a dry paper towel for 8 passes under a pressure of 200 grams over a 3.5 cm
diameter area. Status A reflectance density as measured by an X-Rite®
densitometer on the tested area was recorded and compared to the optical density
before testing. Dry rub resistance is defined as the percentage of optical density
(OD) retained after testing. 100% density retained indicates no damage or loss or
optical density on the imaged area. The results are listed in Table 3 below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Ink No.</entry><entry align="center">Polymer in Ink</entry><entry align="center">Optical density at the right side of printed image</entry><entry align="center">Optical density at the left side of printed image</entry><entry align="center">Jetting non-uniformity</entry><entry align="center">Dry Durabilit y (% density retained)</entry><entry align="center">Wet Durability (% density retained)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-1</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">2.23</entry><entry align="center">2.25</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">67.7%</entry><entry align="center">58.4%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-2</entry><entry align="center">P1-DMEA</entry><entry align="center">1.83</entry><entry align="center">0.07</entry><entry align="center">1.76</entry><entry align="center">98.4%</entry><entry align="center">102.4%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-3</entry><entry align="center">P1-TEA</entry><entry align="center">1.66</entry><entry align="center">0.06</entry><entry align="center">1.60</entry><entry align="center">88.5%</entry><entry align="center">101.8%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-4</entry><entry align="center">P1-TELA</entry><entry align="center">1.64</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry><entry align="center">1.59</entry><entry align="center">103.5%</entry><entry align="center">106.9%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-5</entry><entry align="center">P1-DELA</entry><entry align="center">1.48</entry><entry align="center">0.06</entry><entry align="center">1.42</entry><entry align="center">99.5%</entry><entry align="center">106.7%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-6</entry><entry align="center">P1-EM</entry><entry align="center">1.54</entry><entry align="center">0.05</entry><entry align="center">1.49</entry><entry align="center">99.0%</entry><entry align="center">95.5%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-7</entry><entry align="center">P1-NH4OH</entry><entry align="center">2.04</entry><entry align="center">1.71</entry><entry align="center">0.33</entry><entry align="center">97.2%</entry><entry align="center">99.1%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-1</entry><entry align="center">P1-KOH</entry><entry align="center">1.98</entry><entry align="center">2.00</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">98.0%</entry><entry align="center">102.5%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-2</entry><entry align="center">P1-NaOH</entry><entry align="center">1.88</entry><entry align="center">1.92</entry><entry align="center">0.04</entry><entry align="center">100.0%</entry><entry align="center">99.5%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-3</entry><entry align="center">P1-LiOH</entry><entry align="center">1.93</entry><entry align="center">1.95</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">94.9%</entry><entry align="center">100.0%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-8</entry><entry align="center">P2</entry><entry align="center">1.72</entry><entry align="center">0.07</entry><entry align="center">1.65</entry><entry align="center">98.9%</entry><entry align="center">98.6%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-4</entry><entry align="center">P2-KOH</entry><entry align="center">1.89</entry><entry align="center">1.74</entry><entry align="center">0.15</entry><entry align="center">99.0%</entry><entry align="center">102.1%</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0055">In Table 2, a pigmented ink formulated without any polymer, such
as C-1, had very good jetting uniformity, as shown by the very small difference in
optical density when printing across a page. However, the image does not possess
durability to common handling, as indicated by the low % density retained after
durability test.</p><p num="0056">The durability of a print can be easily improved by the addition of
polymer in ink, also shown in Table 2. However, jetting (non)uniformity varied
depending on the base used to neutralize the addition polymer. The above results
show that ink j et inks containing addition polymer that is neutralized with KOH,
NaOH or LiOH in accordance with the invention printed on porous glossy
receiver not only had good jetting uniformity (or low jetting non-uniformity), but
also had improved dry and wet rub resistance.</p><heading><u style="single">Example 2</u></heading><heading>Magenta Pigment Dispersion 2 (MD-2)</heading><p num="0057">A self-dispersed pigment red 122 dispersion prepared by surface
modification technology through diazonium reaction was obtained from Cabot
Corporation. The sample identification by Cabot was IJX-266, at 10.2% solids.</p><heading><u style="single">Ink Preparation</u></heading><p num="0058">Inks were prepared as described in Example 1, except using
surface modified pigment dispersion MD-2.</p><p num="0059">The pigment and addition polymers used in the inks employed in
this invention and the comparison inks are given in the following Table 4:
<tables><table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Ink</entry><entry align="center">Polymer Dispersion</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-9 (Control)</entry><entry align="center">None</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-10 (Control)</entry><entry align="center">P1-DMEA</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-11 (Control)</entry><entry align="center">P1-TEA</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-5</entry><entry align="center">P1-KOH</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-6</entry><entry align="center">P1-NaOH</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0060">These inks were printed and images were evaluated identical to
those described in Example 1. The results are listed in Table 5 below.
<tables><table><tgroup cols="7"><tbody><row><entry align="center">Ink No.</entry><entry align="center">Polymer in Ink</entry><entry align="center">Optical density at the right side of printed image</entry><entry align="center">Optical density at the left side of printed image</entry><entry align="center">Jetting non-uniformity</entry><entry align="center">Dry Durabilit y (% density retained)</entry><entry align="center">Wet Durability (% density retained)</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-9</entry><entry align="center">None</entry><entry align="center">1.36</entry><entry align="center">1.59</entry><entry align="center">0.23</entry><entry align="center">59.6%</entry><entry align="center">33.8%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-10</entry><entry align="center">P1-DMEA</entry><entry align="center">1.21</entry><entry align="center">0.07</entry><entry align="center">-1.14</entry><entry align="center">70.4%</entry><entry align="center">52.0%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">C-11</entry><entry align="center">P1-TEA</entry><entry align="center">1.08</entry><entry align="center">0.12</entry><entry align="center">-0.96</entry><entry align="center">102.6%</entry><entry align="center">79.3%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-5</entry><entry align="center">P1-KOH</entry><entry align="center">1.66</entry><entry align="center">1.72</entry><entry align="center">0.06</entry><entry align="center">103.6%</entry><entry align="center">68.7%</entry></row><row><entry align="center">I-6</entry><entry align="center">P1-NaOH</entry><entry align="center">1.63</entry><entry align="center">1.65</entry><entry align="center">0.02</entry><entry align="center">68.9%</entry><entry align="center">45.7%</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></tables></p><p num="0061">In Table 5, a pigmented ink formulated without polymer, such as
C-9, had good jetting uniformity, as shown by the small difference in optical
density when printing across a page. However, the image does not possess
durability to common handling, as indicated by the low % density retained after
the durability test.</p><p num="0062">The durability of a print can be easily improved by the addition of
polymer in the ink. However, jetting (non)uniformity varied depending on the
base used to neutralize the addition polymer. The above results show that ink jet
inks I-5 and I-6, containing addition polymer that is neutralized with KOH and
NaOH in accordance with the invention, when printed on a porous glossy
receiver, not only had good jetting uniformity (or low jetting non-uniformity), but
also had improved dry and wet rub resistance.</p><p num="0063">The invention has been described in detail with particular reference
to certain preferred embodiments thereof, but it will be understood that variations
and modifications can be effected within the spirit and scope of the invention.</p></description><claims load-source="ep" status="new" lang="EN"><claim num="1"><claim-text>An ink jet ink composition comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>from 40.0 to 99.0% by weight of water;</claim-text><claim-text>from 0.1 to 20.0% by weight of a pigment;</claim-text><claim-text>from 0 to 70.0% by weight of a water miscible co-solvent; and</claim-text><claim-text>from 0.1 to 20.0 % by weight of a water-reducible addition polymer;</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein the weight average molecular weight of the polymer is from 2,000 to
100,000; the acid number is from 50 to 400; and the acid group on the polymer is
neutralized by alkaline metal hydroxide; and
wherein all weight percentages are based on the total weight of the ink
composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="2"><claim-text>The ink jet ink composition of claim 1 wherein the addition
polymer comprises monomers selected from the group consisting of allyl
compounds, allyl esters, vinyl ethers, vinyl esters, vinyl heterocyclic compounds,
styrene or a styrene derivative, olefins and halogenated olefins, itconic acid and
esters, crotonic acid and esters, unsaturated nitriles, acrylic acid or methacrylic
acid and esters, vinyl alcohols, acrylamides and methacrylamides, vinyl ketones,
and multifunctional monomers.</claim-text></claim><claim num="3"><claim-text>The ink jet ink composition of claim 1 wherein 75 to 100% of
the acid groups on the polymer is neutralized by alkaline metal hydroxide,</claim-text></claim><claim num="4"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1 wherein the water miscible
co-solvent is from 1.0 to 50.0% by weight of the entire ink composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="5"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1 wherein the pigment is from 0.2 to
15.0% by weight of the entire ink composition.</claim-text></claim><claim num="6"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1 wherein the addition polymer has a
Tg of -40 to 200 degrees C.</claim-text></claim><claim num="7"><claim-text>The composition of claim 1 wherein the addition polymer
has a molecular weight of 4,000 to 40,000.</claim-text></claim><claim num="8"><claim-text>An ink jet printing method, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text><claim-text>A) providing an ink jet printer that is responsive to digital data signals;</claim-text><claim-text>B) loading said printer with an ink comprising:
<claim-text><claim-text>from 40.0 to 99.0% by weight of water;</claim-text><claim-text>from 0.1 to 20.0% by weight of a pigment;</claim-text><claim-text>from 0 to 70.0% by weight of a water miscible co-solvent; and</claim-text><claim-text>from 0.1 to 20.0 % by weight of a water-reducible addition polymer;</claim-text></claim-text>
wherein the weight average molecular weight of the polymer is from 2,000 to
100,000; the acid number is from 50 to 400; and the acid group on the polymer is
neutralized by alkaline metal hydroxide; and wherein all weight percentages are
based on the total weight of the ink composition;</claim-text><claim-text>C) loading said printer with an ink-receiving element comprising a
support having thereon an ink-receiving layer; and</claim-text><claim-text>D) printing on said ink-receiving layer using said ink jet ink in
response to said digital data signals.</claim-text></claim-text></claim-text></claim><claim num="9"><claim-text>The method of claim 19 wherein the ink-receiving element
comprises a support having thereon a continuous, coextensive, porous ink-receiving
layer having interconnecting voids.</claim-text></claim><claim num="10"><claim-text>The method of claim 20 wherein the porous ink-receiving
layer comprises from 20% to 100% of water-dispersible polymer particles and
from 0% to 80% of a polymeric binder.</claim-text></claim></claims><copyright>User acknowledges that Matrixware and its third party providers retain all right, title and interest in and to this xml under applicable copyright laws.  User acquires no ownership rights to this xml including but not limited to its format.  User hereby accepts the terms and conditions of the Licence Agreement set forth at http://www.matrixware.com/legal/marec/data_licence.html</copyright></patent-document>